<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335553">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/05/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/06/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000446066</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Short-term efficacy of neural mobilisation for patients with nerve-related neck and arm pain</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Short-term efficacy of standardised neural mobilisation for patients with nerve-related neck and unilateral arm pain</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1115-1797</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cervical radicular pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants assigned to neural mobilisation will receive one-on-one treatments with a physiotherapist (4 treatments over 2 weeks). The physiotherapist will apply 2 manual therapy techniques and prescribe 2 nerve gliding exercises for a home program at each treatment session. The manual therapy techniques include a cervical lateral glide away from the symptomatic arm and a shoulder girdle oscillation technique. Each manual therapy technique will be applied for a total of 4 minutes at each treatment session. The nerve gliding exercises for the home program include a 'sliding' technique and a 'tensioning' technique biased toward the median nerve and cervical nerve roots. In a 'sliding' technique, a movement that lengthens the median nerve bed (e.g., elbow and wrist extension) is counterbalanced by another movement that shortens the nerve bed (e.g., neck side-bending toward the symptomatic arm). A 'tensioning' technique involves simultaneous movements that lengthen the median nerve bed (e.g., elbow and wrist extension combined with neck side-bending away from the symptomatic arm). Participants will perform 10-15 repetitions of the 'sliding' and 'tensioning' techniques 3 times daily on days they do not attend treatment. On days that participants attend treatment, 10-15 repetitions of the 'sliding' and 'tensioning' techniques will be performed under the guidance of the physiotherapist. This will enable the physiotherapist to check that nerve gliding exercises are performed correctly and to progress exercises as necessary. All manual therapy techniques and nerve gliding exercises will not provoke participants' symptoms. The maximum sensory response allowed during each technique is a gentle stretching or pulling sensation that settles immediately upon completion of the technique.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants assigned to the wait-and-see approach will not receive any physiotherapy treatment. They will continue their daily activities as tolerated during the 4 weeks of the trial. It is expected that the level of daily activity will vary on a case-by-case basis for participants assigned to the wait-and-see approach.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient-reported improvement on a global rating of change scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Four weeks after baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neck pain (mean of patient's current, greatest, and least pain over previous 24 hours on 0 - 10 numeric pain rating scale)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Four weeks after baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Arm pain (mean of patient's current, greatest, and least pain over previous 24 hours on 0 - 10 numeric pain rating scale)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Four weeks after baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neck Disability Index (0 - 50 points)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Four weeks after baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient-Specific Functional Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Four weeks after baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Neck pain that spreads into one arm below the level of the deltoid tuberosity

2. Non-traumatic onset of symptoms

3. Symptoms present for at least four weeks

4. Composite pain rating of at least 3/10 (mean of patient's ratings of the average level of neck pain and arm pain during the previous week; pain ratings will be measured with separate 0 - 10 numeric pain rating scales)

5. Symptoms reproduced by a median nerve biased neurodynamic test

6. Ability to speak and read English for self-report items measured at baseline and four weeks after baseline</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Bilateral arm symptoms

2. Traumatic onset of symptoms

3. Two or more abnormal neurologic findings at the same nerve root level (C5 - T1) (i.e., decreased strength, decreased deep tendon reflex, decreased sensation)

4. Evidence of central nervous system involvement

5. Medical "red flags" that suggest non-musculoskeletal pathology

6. Physiotherapy treatment for neck and arm pain in the previous six months

7. Previous surgery on the neck or upper limb</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Volunteers will be screened by phone for age, symptom onset and duration, symptom location, composite pain rating, previous physiotherapy treatment, surgical history, and English fluency. Volunteers who pass the phone screen will come to the research lab to provide informed consent and undergo an examination to determine if they meet all enrollment criteria. The examination will confirm enrollment criteria screened by phone and will include assessment of medical "red flags", the median nerve biased neurodynamic test, and neurologic status. Consecutive volunteers who meet all enrollment criteria will be admitted into the study.

Treatment allocation will be concealed. Group assignments have been placed in sealed opaque envelopes by a research not involved in data collection. Another research assistant not involved in data collection will reveal the group assignment to each patient after baseline measurements have been completed.</concealment>
    <sequence>An independent body, The Queensland Clinical Trials Centre, prepared the randomisation list with a computerised random number generator. Block randomisation without stratification has been used to assign participants to the neural mobilisation and wait-and-see groups.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>21/07/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>84</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Robert Nee</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Neuropathic Pain Research Group,
Clinical Centre for Research Excellence in Spinal Pain, Injury and Health,
School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences,
The University of Queensland,
Brisbane, QLD 4072</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Neuropathic Pain Research Group, Clinical Centre for Research Excellence in Spinal Pain, Injury and Health, School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences, The University of Queensland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Neuropathic Pain Research Group,
Clinical Centre for Research Excellence in Spinal Pain, Injury and Health,
School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences,
The University of Queensland,
Brisbane, QLD 4072</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Bill Vicenzino</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Clinical Centre for Research Excellence in Spinal Pain, Injury and Health,
School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences,
The University of Queensland,
Brisbane, QLD 4072</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Gwen Jull</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Clinical Centre for Research Excellence in Spinal Pain, Injury and Health,
School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences,
The University of Queensland,
Brisbane, QLD 4072</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Joshua Cleland</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of Physical Therapy,
College of Graduate and Professional Studies,
Franklin Pierce University,
Rindge, NH 03461</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>United States of America</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Michel Coppieters</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Neuropathic Pain Research Group,
Clinical Centre for Research Excellence in Spinal Pain, Injury and Health,
School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences,
The University of Queensland,
Brisbane, QLD 4072</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Some patients with neck and arm pain have symptoms because nerves in the neck and arm have become overly sensitive to movement. There is some evidence that this type of neck and arm pain can be well managed with specific treatment to the nerves in the neck and arm (nerve mobilisation). However, the evidence is limited and we cannot predict which patients respond best to nerve mobilisation. The primary aim of this trial is to determine whether nerve mobilisation leads to clinically important improvements in pain and function for patients with nerve-related neck and arm pain. The secondary aim is to determine if a set of clinical findings can accurately predict which patients with nerve-related neck and arm pain will respond best to nerve mobilisation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Medical Research Ethics Committee, The University of Queensland</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The University of Queensland,
Brisbane, QLD 4072</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/03/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2009000194</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Michel Coppieters</name>
      <address>Neuropathic Pain Research Group,
Clinical Centre for Research Excellence in Spinal Pain, Injury and Health,
School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences,
The University of Queensland
Brisbane, QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 1644</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3365 1622</fax>
      <email>m.coppieters@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Michel Coppieters</name>
      <address>Neuropathic Pain Research Group,
Clinical Centre for Research Excellence in Spinal Pain, Injury and Health,
School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences,
The University of Queensland
Brisbane, QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 1644</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3365 1622</fax>
      <email>m.coppieters@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Robert Nee</name>
      <address>Neuropathic Pain Research Group,
Clinical Centre for Research Excellence in Spinal Pain, Injury and Health,
School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences,
The University of Queensland
Brisbane, QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 4 2118 1498</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.nee@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>