<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370879">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/06/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000962437</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>MS1819-SD phase IIa clinical trial for patients with exocrine pancreatic insufficiency (EPI) caused by chronic pancreatitis (CP) and/or distal pancreatectomy.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A multicentre open-label phase IIa study with escalating dose of MS1819-SD, to investigate the efficacy and safety of a Yarrowia lipolytica lipase preparation for the compensation of exocrine pancreatic insufficiency caused by chronic pancreatitis and/or distal pancreatectomy.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>MS1819SD</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>AZUR RX Number MS1819/16/01 </secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Exocrine pancreatic insufficiency (EPI) caused by chronic pancreatitis (CP) </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Exocrine pancreatic insufficiency (EPI) caused by distal pancreatectomy.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other endocrine disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is an open-label study meaning that all eligible participants will receive the study drug MS1819-SD. 
The study is divided into four main phases:
Phase A: Screening (less than 3 months)
Phase B: Washout for Porcine Pancreatic Extracts (PPEs) (12-15 days)
Phase C: Open label escalating dose of MS1819 (12-15 days each step)
Phase D: Follow-up (12-15 days)
After providing informed consent, eligible patients will be required to washout from porcine pancreatic extracts (PPEs) for 12-15 days; there are no other specific requirements or refrains during the washout period. Before commencing on the lowest of four daily doses of MS1819-SD (study drug) for four days (study drug taken orally as capsules, 5 times a day and taken with food). 
Patients will complete four treatment periods, with the daily dose of MS1819-SD increasing in ascending order for each participant in each treatment period. Patients will receive standardized high-fat diet containing 100 g of fat per day (3 meals and 2 snacks) for the first three days of each dosing period. Any remaining food will be asked to be returned, to allow the assessment of the fat intake. Stool samples will be collected during the dosing period to measure the amount of fat absorbed. Capsules of non-absorbable dye markers will be given together with the first fat meal and at the end of the 72-hour fat diet phase. Blood samples, vital signs and general well being of the patients will also be recorded during this period. Patients will be required to enter dose administration details (i.e. time of administration of study medication each day) on the dosing diary provided by the site. The study staff will review the dosing diary to ensure that patients are administering the study medication correctly,
The planned MS1819-SD doses are 280 mg/day, 560 mg/day, 1120 mg/day and 2240 mg/day.
The last study visit/follow-up visit will include assessment of vital signs, collection of blood samples and recording of general well-being of patients.
The total duration of the MS1819-SD treatment phase is of 48-60 days,
The total duration of patient participation in the study is of 74-93 days.

</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary objective of this Phase IIa study is to investigate the safety of escalating doses of MS1819SD, a spraydried yarrowia lipolytica lipase preparation in people with chronic pancreatitis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Safety will be assessed at the end of each treatment period by physical examination, with particular attention paid to immunoallergic effects and digestive symptoms.

In addition, the following clinical laboratory tests will be conduct to assess the outcome:
1. Circulating level of LIP2 gene product
2. Circulating antibodies against LIP2 gene product
3. Faecal calprotectin,
4. Haematology (Complete Blood Count),
5. Biochemistry (creatinine, urea, ASpartate amino-Transferase, ALanine amino-Transferase, Alkaline phosphatase, Gamma-glutamyl transpeptidase, bilirubin, Creatine Kinase).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary objective for this study is to investigate the efficacy of MS1819SD
in patients with chronic pancreatitis by analysis of coefficient of fat absorption (CFA)and change from baseline. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants will be required to complete five day stool collections following high fat
meals at the end of the washout period and at the end of each treatment phase.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients with established Exocrine Pancreatic Insufficiency (EPI) associated to Chronic Pancreatitis (CP) and/or pancreatectomy that fulfill the following criteria will be included:

1. Signed and dated informed consent form
2. Age 18 years and older,
3. Male or female,
4. Body weight within the range [50-100 Kg] for males or [40-90 Kg] for females,
5. Distal pancreatectomy for any disorder (e.g. acute pancreatitis or its complications, CP or its complications, pancreatic endocrine or exocrine cancer, or others) and/or CP of any etiology (e.g. alcohol, genetics, hypercalcemia, or others) of grade 2 or higher (Cambridge classification),
6. Faecal pancreatic elastase-1 less than 100 micro g/g of stools at screening,
7. Coefficient of Fat Absorption (CFA) measurement less than or equal to 75% at washout of phase B,
8. Female patients must be post-menopausal (defined as at least 12 months post cessation of menses), surgically sterile or, if of childbearing potential, using a reliable method of contraception during the study.
9. Being considered as reliable and capable of adhering to the protocol, according to the judgment of the investigator.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Cystic fibrosis,
2. Total or partial gastrectomy,
3. Cephalic or total duodenopancreatectomy,
4. Documented fibrosing colonopathy,
5. Any small bowel disease possibly responsible for malabsorption, including small intestinal bacterial overgrowth, celiac disease, small bowel resection for more than or equal to 1 meter length, etc.,
6. Acute pancreatitis or exacerbation of CP for less than or equal to 3 months,
7. Pancreatectomy for exocrine or endocrine cancer for less than or equal to 1 year,
8. Metastatic or locally recurrent exocrine pancreatic cancer,
9. Known hypersensitivity or other severe reaction to any ingredient of the investigational medicinal product,
10. Bilirubin greater than3 times ULN (upper limit normal),
11. ALT or AST greater than 3 times ULN,
12. Alkaline phosphatase greater than 3 times ULN,
13. Gamma glutamyl transferase greater than 5 times ULN,
14. Patients with a known allergy to the stool marker,
15. Lactation or known pregnancy or positive pregnancy test at both screening and baseline for women of childbearing potential,
16. Drug addiction that would preclude participation and compliance with study procedures,
17. Chronic alcoholic intoxication that would preclude compliance with study procedures and/or intoxication greater than 50 grams alcohol/day,
18. Participation in another clinical study involving an Investigational Medicinal Product (IMP) within 30 days prior to inclusion or concomitantly with this study.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>This study is a phase IIa trial, aiming to primarily investigate the safety and to provide exploratory information on the efficacy of different MS1819 doses.
Twelve patients are considered sufficient to assess the safety of doses administered during the escalating dose Phase C within the range of doses evaluated. To account for an anticipated 20% withdrawal rate, approximately 15 patients are planned to be enrolled. 

No power calculation has been performed. The sets used for safety and efficacy analyses will include the following:
Safety Set:
A. The safety set is defined as all patients who receive at least one dose of MS1819-SD. Patients will be analysed according to the treatment actually received.
Efficacy Analysis Sets:
A. Full analysis set (FAS): is defined as all patients receiving at least one dose of treatment and with some efficacy assessment available on treatment. The FAS is considered as the primary set for the efficacy analysis.
B. Per-Protocol set (PP): is a subset of the FAS comprising all patients who do not violate the terms of the protocol in a way that would affect the study outcome significantly, as determined by the study clinician.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>28/11/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>27/01/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>12</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>6</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>Linear Clinical Research - Nedlands</hospital>
    <hospital>Mackay Base Hospital - Mackay</hospital>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
    <postcode>4740 - Mackay</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Wellington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Christchurch</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>INC Research Australia Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>159 Port Road Hindmarsh
South Australia 5007
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>AzurRx</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Jardin des Entreprises
290, chemin de St-Dionisy
30980 Langlade
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>France</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a Phase IIa study, testing a new medication for chronic pancreatitis. The new medication is called MS1819-SD which is a modified version of a naturally occurring enzyme made in the pancreas.

The primary purpose of this study is to investigate the safety of escalating doses of study drug MS1819-SD in people with chronic pancreatitis. This enzyme has demonstrated an appropriate profile to compensate the pancreatic lipase (enzyme) deficiency that is common with CP patients. The deficiency in this enzyme can be responsible of greasy diarrhea, fecal urge and weight loss.

The design of the study is open-label, meaning that all eligible participants will receive the study drug MS1819-SD. The MS1819-SD dose will increase throughout the study during dose escalation visits in each treatment period; study includes a total of four treatment periods. The planned MS1819-SD doses in these treatment periods are 280 mg/day, 560 mg/day, 1120 mg/day and 2240 mg/day.

The total duration of the MS1819-SD treatment phase is of 48-60 days, The total duration of patient participation in the study is of 74-93 days.

Approximately twelve patients will be enrolled in this study.

The eligible patients will be required to washout from porcine pancreatic extracts before commencing on the lowest of four daily doses of MS1819SD for four days (drug taken orally, five times a day). Participants will complete four treatment periods, with the daily dose of MS1819SD increasing in each treatment period.

Safety will be assessed at the end of each treatment period with particular attention paid to immunoallergic effects, digestive symptoms and clinical laboratory tests.

The secondary purpose of this study is to investigate the efficacy of MS1819SD
in patients with chronic pancreatitis by analysis of coefficient of fat absorption (CFA) and change from baseline. 

Participants will be required to complete five day stool collections following high fat
meals at the end of the washout period and at the end of each treatment phase.

This study is being sponsored by AzurRx (the Sponsor). The Sponsor will fund researchers who conduct this research for the use of their facilities and to conduct this study.

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee (The Queen Elizabeth Hospital) </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Basil Hetzel Institute DX465101
The Queen Elizabeth Hospital
28 Woodville Road
Woodville South SA 5011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/07/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>17/05/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Central Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
 Ethics Department
 Freyberg Building
 Reception  Ground Floor
 20 Aitken Street
 Wellington</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/09/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/07/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>129 Glen Osmond Road Eastwood South Australia 5063</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/09/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/07/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Quoc Nam Nguyen</name>
      <address>Department of Gastroenterology
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 7088 7900</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>QuocNamNguyen@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Pavina Pavina</name>
      <address>INC Research Australia Pty Ltd Suite 1, Level 2, 924 Pacific Highway Gordon NSW 2072 </address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 8437 9249 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Pavina.pavina@incresearch.com </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Quoc Nam Nguyen</name>
      <address>Department of Gastroenterology
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 7088 7900</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>QuocNamNguyen@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Pavina Pavina</name>
      <address>INC Research Australia Pty Ltd
Suite 1, Level 2, 924 Pacific Highway
Gordon NSW 2072 </address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 8437 9249 </phone>
      <fax>+61 2 8437 9299</fax>
      <email>Pavina.pavina@incresearch.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>