<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365714">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/01/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/02/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000131651</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Prospective Randomized Trial of the Direct Anterior Approach versus the Posterior Approach in Primary Total Hip Arthroplasty </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomized trial comparing the anterior and posterior approaches in hip replacement surgery for patients having unilateral hip arthritis using a series of questionnaires to measure pre and post operative outcomes and differences.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Osteoarthritis of the hip - outcomes following hip replacement surgery using the anterior and posterior approaches</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be randomized into two groups to undergo hip replacement surgery via the anterior or posterior approach. Surgery will be performed by 2 senior orthopaedic surgeons at a single institution. Participants will be assessed pre and post-operatively up to 3 months post operatively using a series of questionnaires. 

The anterior approach used utilizes a modified varient of the Hueter anterior approach. This surgery is expected to take between 1-2 hours to peform depending on complexity.
The incision is made 2cm posterior and 1cm distal to the anterior superior iliac spine (ASIS) and extended in a straight line distally and slightly posterior ending approximately 2cm anterior to the greater trochanter (GT)

The interval between Sartorius and tensor fascia lata (TFL) is palpated and then incised. The lateral femoral cutaneous nerve is identified and protected. TFL is then retracted laterally while Sartorius is retracted medially. The interval is then further developed through the interval between rectus femoris and gluteus medius until the lateral hip capsule can be palpated.  Iliopsoas and rectus femoris are gently elevated and retracted medially to complete the exposure of the hip capsule. 

The lateral circumflex vessels are then identified and ligated. Capsulotomy is then performed and the edges tagged, reflected and protected to allow for subsequent reconstruction.

The femoral neck is then cut and femoral head delivered. The femur is now externally rotated approximately 45 degrees to facilitate acetabular exposure Precautions are taken during external rotation to prevent fractures. Preparation of the acetabulum can now occur. The anterior musculature is retracted carefully to minimize soft tissue damage. Labral excision is completed and the inferior capsule band incised to facilitate liner placement. Reaming is done under direct vision and acetabular component trialling is done under radiographic guidance. 

On completion of acetabular preparation, the femur is externally rotated to 90 degrees and the hip adducted and hyperextended. If there is inadequate exposure of the femur, release of obturator internus with piriformis can be performed.  

Once exposure is adequate, the femur is then breached with a box cut and broached. Broaching is undertaken carefully to prevent proximal femur fractures, cortical perforation and excessive anteversion. Broaching is completed when the size matches that of the preoperative template. This is guided by feel and depth. The femoral components are then trialled guided by the pre-operative template and final broach size.

The hip reduced with internal rotation. Leg length, offset and stability are checked clinically and with the aid of the image intensifier. On meeting the parameters, the hip is then dislocated, trial components removed, prosthesis inserted and hip reduced. The capsular incision is now repaired. Haemostasis with diathermy or ligation is achieved prior to closure of the soft tissue and skin.
</interventions>
    <comparator>We will be comparing the anterior approach (intervention) with the posterior approach for primary hip replacement surgery (standard approach/comparator). The surgery is expected to take between 1-2 hours depending on complexity.

A 8-12 cm incision is made posterior to the greater trochanter. The gluteal fascia is split and the fibres of gluteus maximus are dissected to expose the short external rotators of the hip. The piriformis muscle is identified and the sciatic nerve palpated and protected. The hip joint capsule is then exposed through the incision and reflection of these muscles.

The femoral neck is cut at the templated level whilst the hip is in its anatomical position. The femoral head is removed. Acetabular preparation commences. The operative leg is flexed and externally rotated away from the operator. The labrum and soft tissue is removed from the acetabulum prior to reaming. Reaming is done under direct vision and considered complete when reaching good bone stock. Acetabular components are trialled and fitted.

Upon completion of acetabular fitting, femoral preparation can begin. Breaching and broaching of the femur is done under direct vision. Broaching again is considered complete when parameters are met. The femoral components are trialled and the hip reduced. Leg length, offset and stability are checked. Once satisfactory, trial components are removed and the prosthesis proper inserted. The posterior capsule and short rotators are repaired using non-absorbable sutures to reduce the risk of post-operative dislocation.  Haemostasis is obtained prior to closure of the fascia, subcutaneous tissue and skin.  
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>WOMAC
</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-operatively
2 weeks post operatively
6 weeks post operatively
12 weeks post operatively
1 year post operatively</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Oxford Hip Score</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-operatively
2 weeks post operatively
6 weeks post operatively
12 weeks post operatively
1 year post operatively</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional performance assessment pre and post total hip arthroplasty will be conducted with a 10 metre walk test. </outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-operatively
2 weeks post operatively
6 weeks post operatively
12 weeks post operatively
1 year post operatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient completed quality of life assessment questionnaire pre and post total hip arthroplasty will be assessed using the EuroQol/EQ5D patient completed questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-operatively
2 weeks post operatively
6 weeks post operatively
12 weeks post operatively
1 year post operatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Radiographic prosthesis placement
</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks post operatively
1 year post operatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical data - eg: Peri-operative data, Length of hospital stay and recovery, compilcations, analgesic use.

Complications - observed would potentially include common complications associated with hip replacement surgery such as superficial wound infection, Deep vein thrombosis, peri-prosthetic fracture, prosthesis dislocation rates, palsy/damage to the lateral cutaneous nerve of the thigh 

Late presenting complications such peri prosthetic joint infection will also be observed if possible</outcome>
      <timepoint>from surgery to 12 weeks post operatively. Serious complications outside follow-up period but before publication will be included.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Symptomatic unilateral hip arthritis
ASA 2-3</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Symptomatic bilateral hip arthritis
ASA&gt;3</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/02/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>18/02/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>13/01/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>70</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>73</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>3/03/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Box Hill Hospital - Box Hill</hospital>
    <hospital>Maroondah Hospital - Ringwood East</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Eastern Health Orthopaedic Unit</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Orthopaedic Unit
Box Hill Hospital
Nelson Road
Box Hill VIC 3128</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Eastern Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>5 Arnold Street 
Box Hill
VIC 3128</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Box Hill Golf Club</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>202 Station St, Box Hill South VIC 3128</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The research is aimed at investigating and comparing two surgical techniques practised for hip replacement surgery. The standard approach used across many health institutions is the posterior approach.  This study compares the outcomes between the posterior and the anterior approach.
The anterior approach is a well established technique that is widely used in Europe and the USA. There is reportedly a reduced rate of dislocation and quicker recovery time. However it is a technique that requires a higher level of skill and specialized equipment. The study aims to determine if the anterior approach for hip replacement surgery is equal if not better when compared to the standard posterior approach. Participants will be randomly allotted into one of two groups. One group will have surgery via the anterior approach and the other via the posterior approach. Participants will only know which group they are allotted to post operatively. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Awaiting publication in Journal of Arthroplasty</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Eastern Health Office of Research and Ethics</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>5 Arnold Street
Box Hill
VIC 3128</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/12/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>E11-1314</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/10/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tze Ern Cheng</name>
      <address>Eastern Health
5 Arnold Street
Box Hill
VIC 3128</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9895 3333</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>TzeErn.Cheng2@easternhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tze Ern Cheng</name>
      <address>Eastern Health
5 Arnold Street
Box Hill
VIC 3128</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9895 3333</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>TzeErn.Cheng2@easternhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tze Ern Cheng</name>
      <address>Eastern Health
5 Arnold Street
Box Hill
VIC 3128</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9895 3333</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>TzeErn.Cheng2@easternhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tze Ern Cheng</name>
      <address>Eastern Health
5 Arnold Street
Box Hill
VIC 3128</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9895 3333</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>TzeErn.Cheng2@easternhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>