<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364229">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/05/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/05/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000534785</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Preventing early and unintended pregnancy in Vanuatu: a community-based intervention targeting adolescents.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Cluster randomised controlled trial of a peer-led, community-based health promotion intervention to improve knowledge, attitudes and use of contraception among adolescents (15-19 years) in Vanuatu</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Contraception</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Contraception</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study will assess a participatory health promotion intervention developed by Wan Smolbag Theatre in conjunction with Burnet Institute. The intervention will build on existing peer education models used by Wan Smolbag adapted to incorporate reproduction and family planning. The intervention will be conducted in communities by trained peer educators and will include at least one participatory group workshop (lasting at least 1-2 hours) for adolescents aged 15-19 years, followed by at least two individual sessions (each lasting approximately 1 hour) with a peer educator to provide personalised information, counselling and referral to youth-friendly health services. The workshops and individual sessions will focus on improving knowledge and fostering supportive attitudes towards pregnancy prevention, addressing misconceptions, promotion of voluntary contraception, identification of risk and protective factors, and building interpersonal and negotiation skills. Participants will also be provided with printed resources about sexual and reproductive health and offered condoms and referral to youth-friendly health services. The intervention will be conducted over 2 months, commencing with the community-based workshop, followed by individual sessions at approximately 3-week intervals. There is no maximum number of session that a participant may attend. Details will be recorded by peer educators regarding the length and number of sessions attended by each participant.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will receive printed resources about sexual and reproductive health (including family planning, sexually transmitted infections, HIV) and offered condoms and referral to youth-friendly health services.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Knowledge of reproduction and contraception assessed by 18 knowledge questions. Questions are adapted from the World Health Organisation Survey Questionnaire for Young People and the Demographic and Health Survey Young Adult Reproductive Health Survey.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 2 months post-intervention. Questionnaire administered by interview.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Attitudes towards contraception assessed by 10 attitude questions. Questions are adapted from the World Health Organisation Survey Questionnaire for Young People and the Demographic and Health Survey Young Adult Reproductive Health Survey.   </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 2 months post-intervention. Questionnaire administered by interview.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported use of any modern method of contraception at last sex (within the last 6 months). Modern contraceptive methods include: condom (male or female); oral contraceptive pill; injectable; implant; intrauterine device; emergency contraception; other vaginal barrier method; and male and female sterilisation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 2 months post-intervention. Questionnaire administered by interview.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Contraceptive Self-Efficacy Scale score. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 2 months post-intervention. Questionnaire administered by interview.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Aged 15-19 years
Residing in study communities</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>15</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>19</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Nil</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Twenty-eight participating communities (rural and urban) on two islands of Vanuatu will be recruited by the study team following community consultation and consent from the community leader to participate. These 28 communities were identified during formative research.  Trained peer educators will approach all young people residing in the community to ascertain eligibility. All eligible adolescents will be invited to participate, with a target of 14 participants (7 male, 7 female) per community (cluster). Following enrollment of all individual participants, communities will be randomly assigned to the intervention or control groups.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer-generated series of random numbers will be used to allocate communities (clusters) to the intervention or control group. This will be conducted by a member of the team not involved in the recruitment of communities or individual participants.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>13/08/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>13/08/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>19/10/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>370</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Vanuatu</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Burnet Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>85 Commercial Road
Melbourne VIC 3004</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Australian Agency for International Development (AusAID)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>255 London Circuit
Canberra ACT 2601 
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Wan Smolbag Theatre</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>PO Box 1024
Port Vila
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Vanuatu</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Sexual activity during adolescence is common in many Pacific countries, however many young people lack adequate knowledge about reproduction and contraception to help protect themselves from unintended pregnancy. Up to a quarter of girls aged 15-19 in this region have already commenced childbearing. Many of these pregnancies are unintended and often have significant consequences for the health and wellbeing of girls and their families.

There are a number of peer education programs in the Pacific that aim to improve young peoples knowledge about sexual and reproductive health, howver there are limited examples of programs that focus on preventing unintended pregnancy. In addition, very little research has looked at the effectivess of peer education in this region.

This study will trial a peer education program that focuses on prevention of pregnancy, targeting adolescents aged 15-19 years in rural and urban communities of Vanuatu. The program will adapt other successful peer education activities and will include community-based workshops, one-on-one education and counselling, and printed materials. These activities will provide accurate and comprehensive information about reproduction and contraception and also help young people develop interpersonal and negotiation skills. The program aims to improve adolescents knowledge and attitudes about contraception with the overall goal of reducing early and unintended pregnancy. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>55 Commercial Rd
Melbourne VIC 3004</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/05/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>185/12</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Elissa Kennedy</name>
      <address>Centre for International Health
Burnet Institute
85 Commercial Road
Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9282 2119</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>elissa@burnet.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Elissa Kennedy</name>
      <address>Centre for International Health
Burnet Institute
85 Commercial Road
Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9282 2119</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>elissa@burnet.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Elissa Kennedy</name>
      <address>Centre for International Health
Burnet Institute
85 Commercial Road
Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9282 2119</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>elissa@burnet.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>