<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82702">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/03/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/04/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000158369</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Phase Ib/II Study of CYT997 in Combination with Carboplatin in Relapsed Glioblastoma Multiforme</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase Ib/II Study of CYT997 in Combination with Carboplatin in Relapsed Glioblastoma Multiforme: Assessing Safety and Tolerability.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>CCL08001</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Glioblastoma multiforme</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Brain</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Carboplatin (Area under curve (AUC) =5 intravenous administration) on day 1; and CYT997 (intravenous administration at dose selected during Phase Ib component) on day 2 of a 21 day cycle</interventions>
    <comparator>Historical control information from patients with relapsed glioblastoma multiforme</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the safety and tolerability of escalating doses of CYT997 when given in combination with standard carboplatin therapy (Phase Ib component).  Dose escalation will cease once the Maximum Tolerated Dose has been identified and 6 patients have been treated at the Recommended Dose for Phase II.  Safety and tolerability outcomes will be measured using the NCI CTCAE (v3) grading of adverse events.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Ongoing throughout therapy up until 30 days after last dose of CYT997</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To estimate the progression-free survival at 6 months (PFS-6) utilising the dose of
CYT997 identified in the Phase Ib component of this study (Phase II component</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after initiation of therapy</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Objective response rate (ORR)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Response is measured every second cycle of therapy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall survival</outcome>
      <timepoint>Continuous.  No finite follow-up period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and tolerability</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured continuously from study commencement through to 30 days after last dose of CYT997</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Effects on pharmacodynamic markers of vascular disruption and tumour apoptosis</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured during first cycle of therapy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetic analysis of carboplatin and CYT997 in combination will be determined from blood samples taken at specified timepoints in cycles 1 and 2.  Plasma samples will be analysed to establish blood concentrations of CYT997 and Carboplatin.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed during first cycle of therapy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria> Patients must have histologically-confirmed glioblastoma multiforme that has
progressed after initial surgery, radiation therapy and temozolomide chemotherapy.
 Measurable tumour must be present on gadolinium-enhanced magnetic resonance imaging (MRI)
 At least 3 months must have elapsed from completing radiation to minimize the
possibility of pseudo-progression.
 At least 4 weeks since prior chemotherapy (6 weeks if the last regimen included carmustine (BCNU) or lomustine (CCNU)).
 Age = 18 years.
 If patients are taking steroids, the dose must be stable for = 7 days.
 Eastern Co-operative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status = 2.
 Life expectancy of greater than 2 months.
 Patients must have adequate organ and marrow function as defined below:
o Absolute neutrophil count = 1.5 × 109/L
o Platelet count = 100 × 109/L
o Total bilirubin within normal limits
o Liver enzymes (Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) or alanine aminotransferase (ALT)) &lt; 5 × upper limit of normal (ULN)
o Creatinine within normal limits OR creatinine clearance = 60 mL/min/1.73 m2 for
patients with creatinine levels above normal
o Normal left ventricular ejection fraction on a gated blood pool scan or
echocardiogram
 Must agree to use adequate contraceptive measures if indicated
 Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients who have received any other investigational agent in the preceding four weeks prior to commencing therapy in this study.
Patients who have been previously treated with carboplatin.
Patients who have been previously treated with bevacizumab or other anti-angiogenesis or vascular-disrupting agents.
Patients who are receiving enzyme-inducing anticonvulsant drugs (EIACD) such as phenytoin or carbamazepine.
Patients with a history of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical composition to CYT997 or other agents used in the study.
Patients with uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, cardiac arrhythmia or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with study requirements.
Pregnant or lactating women.
Patients with immune deficiency, including Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) -positive patients.
Patients with uncontrolled diarrhoea despite optimal medication and those with any history of acute gastrointestinal bleeding.
Patients who are unable or unwilling to undergo MRI scanning.
Patients with the following conditions/treatments will be excluded:
Myocardial infarction within 6 months;
History of stroke or transient ischemic attacks (TIAs);
Unstable angina pectoris or acute ischemic changes on ECG;		
History of diabetic retinopathy;
Symptomatic peripheral arterial disease;
Major surgery in the last 4 weeks;
Evidence of intra-tumoural haemorrhage on imaging, except for stable grade-1 post-operative haemorrhage;
Current therapeutic anti-coagulation with warfarin or a heparin (excludes low-dose prophylactic heparin);
Uncontrolled hypertension;
The need for any anti-arrhythmic drugs.
Presence of luminal stenosis of 50% or more in any of the extracranial or intracranial arteries supplying the brain, as measured by magnetic resonance angiography (MRA) at baseline. 
Patients with a baseline prolongation of the QTc interval of Common Toxicity Criteria (CTC) grade 1 (QTc &gt; 0.45-0.47 sec) or greater.
Patients with impaired cardiac function or clinically significant cardiac diseases, including any one of the following:
Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction (LVEF) &lt; 45% as determined by Multigated Acquisition (MUGA) scan or echocardiogram;
complete left bundle branch block;
obligate use of a cardiac pacemaker;
congenital long QT syndrome;
history or presence of ventricular tachyarrhythmia;	
presence of unstable atrial fibrillation (ventricular response &gt; 100 bpm).  Patients with stable atrial fibrillation are eligible, provided they do not meet any of the other cardiac exclusion criteria;
clinically significant resting bradycardia (&lt; 50 bpm);
right bundle branch block + left anterior hemiblock (bifasicular block);
angina pectoris = 3 months prior to starting study drug;
acute MI = 3 months prior to starting study drug; or
other clinically significant heart disease (e.g., congestive heart failure, uncontrolled hypertension, history of labile hypertension, or history of poor compliance with an antihypertensive regimen).
Patients currently receiving treatment with medications known to prolong the QTc interval and/or to induce Torsades de Pointes arrhythmia</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1 / Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>22/09/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>35</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>YM BioSciences Australia Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 2, 499 St Kilda Road, Melbourne, VIC 3004</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>YM BioSciences Australia Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 2, 499 St Kilda Road, Melbourne, VIC 3004</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a study of an experimental anti-cancer drug called CYT997, which targets the blood supply of the tumour. In this study, CYT997 is given as a 24 hour intravenous (IV) infusion on day 2 of a 21 day treatment cycle over 3 cycles. In this study, CYT997 is given in combination with another commonly used standard chemotherapy drug called Carboplatin. 

You may be eligible to join this study if you have Relapsed Glioblastoma Multiforme and a life expectancy of more than two months. 

Most advanced cancers will eventually stop responding to cancer treatments. In this situation, for people who may be eligible for this drug trial, there may not be any alternative standard treatments. Participants will receive supportive care and symptomatic treatments during the trial, in addition to receiving CYT997 and Carboplatin. The major focus of this trial is to test the safety, tolerability and effectiveness of CYT997 when given in combination with Carboplatin in patients with Relapsed Glioblastoma Multiforme. This involves finding out the highest dose of CYT997 that can be given without causing severe side effects. The trial also aims to assess the effects (good and bad) that CYT997 may have on you and your cancer.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Support Unit
Level 4 Main Block
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Rd
Clayton Victoria 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/09/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>08045A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>17/03/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Sydney and Central Coast Health Services Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Office, Level 4 Vindin House
Royal North Shore Hospital
Pacific Highway St Leonards NSW 2065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/12/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>0810-219M(CTN)</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Flinders Clinical Recearch Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Room 2A 221, Flinders Medical Centre
Flinders Drive 
Bedford Park South Australia 5042</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/03/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>13/09</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Gold Coast Health Services District Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Gold Coast Hospital, 108 Nerang Street, Southport, Queensland 4215</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>HREC/09/QGC/54</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Gregg Smith</name>
      <address>Level 2, 499 St Kilda Road, Melbourne, VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9926 0406</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9926 0499</fax>
      <email>gsmith@ymbiosciences.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Juliana Tasevska</name>
      <address>Level 2, 499 St Kilda Road, Melbourne, VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9926 0404</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jtasevska@ymbiosciences.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Juliana Tasevska</name>
      <address>Level 2, 499 St Kilda Road, Melbourne, VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9926 0404</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9926 0499</fax>
      <email>jtasevska@ymbiosciences.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>