<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369471">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/10/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/01/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000057482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Clinical trial of Sailuotong (SLT) for Vascular Dementia or Alzheimer's Disease with evidence of cerebrovascular disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Multicentre, Randomised, Double-Blind, Placebo Controlled Trial to Evaluate the Effectiveness and Safety of Sailuotong (SLT), a Standardised Herbal Medicine Formula in Patients with Vascular Dementia and Alzheimer's Disease with Cerebrovascular Disease</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1175-5097 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Vascular Dementia </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Alzheimer's Disease with Cerebrovascular Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Herbal remedies</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dementias</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Alzheimer's disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>STL active compounds: Ginsenosides powder  27.27 mg  per capsule; ginkgo flavone glycosides27.27 mg  per capsule; 	crocins  5.46 mg per capsule. Participants randomised to the active group will take 2 SLT capsules (60 mg/capsule) orally, twice daily for 52 weeks. Adherence to the protocol will be monitored by drug tablet return.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo, virtually identical starch capsule containing inactive ingredients</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The difference between SLT and the placebo groups in the changes between the Vascular Dementia Assessment Scale-cognitive Subscale (VaDAS-cog) scores from baseline</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 26 and 52 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The difference between SLT and the placebo groups in the changes between the Alzheimer's Disease Cooperative Study-activities of daily living (ADCS-ADL) scores from baseline</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 26 and 52 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The difference between SLT and the placebo group in the changes between the Clinicians Interview Based Impression of Change-plus (CIBIC-plus) scores from baseline </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 26 and 52 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The differences between the SLT and placebo group in the changes between the additional executive function tests including CLOX and EXIT-25 scores from baseline
 </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 26 and 52 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The difference between SLT and the placebo group in the changes between the Cornell Scale of Depression in Dementia scores from Baseline </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 26 and 52 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The difference between SLT and the placebo group in the changes in the dementia quality of life (DEMQOL) scores from baseline</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 26 and 52 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The difference between SLT and the placebo groups in the changes in neuropsychiatric symptoms (comprising delusions, hallucinations, depression/dysphoria, anxiety, agitation/aggression, euphoria, dis-inhibition, irritability/lability, apathy, aberrant motor activity and, night-time behaviour disturbances) in the changes in the Neuropsychiatric Inventory-Clinician rating scale (NPI-C) scores from Baseline. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 26 and 52 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The difference between SLT and the placebo groups in the changes between changes in cerebral blood flow and volumes as determined by MRI from Baseline </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 26 and 52 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety - 'Liver and renal function and routine haematological tests (FBC, coagulation, platelet function) will be conducted at each visit and any AEs will be reported. Although serious adverse events (SAEs) are not anticipated for this trial, SAE procedures will be followed in these circumstances.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, week 4, 13, 26,30, 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. &gt;=40 years old;
2. Outpatients diagnosed with either probable VaD as defined by the National Institute of 3. Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINCDS) and the Association Internationale pour la Recherche et l'Enseignement en Neurosciences (AIREN)  or possible Alzheimers Disease as defined by the National Institute of Neurological and Communication Disorders and Stroke (NINCDS)-Alzheimer's Disease and Related Disorders Association (ADRDA) with significant neuroimaging (CT or MRI) evidence of cerebrovascular disease, at least 3 months prior to screening;
3.. An MMSE score between 10 - 24 for the diagnosis of mild to moderate dementia;
4. Absence of severe depression (Geriatric Depression Scale 15-item version, total score &lt;=11);
5. Stable or controlled by optimal medication over  at least 3 months for, (if present) hypertension, diabetes, cardiac disease or stroke, or if on hypnotics and sedatives for more than 3 months prior to inclusion in the study ;
6. Agreement to take part in the study as evidenced by a personally signed and dated informed consent document indicating that the subject (or a legally acceptable representative if the subject is unable to provide consent), has been informed of all pertinent aspects of the study;
7. For patients who have a Study Partner/Carer, this Carer must be able to assist the subject comply with the study protocol. This requires the Study Partner/Carer to be in contact with the subject at least 2 days per week; 
8. If female, has no intention to become pregnant during the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Have other types of dementia, and/or severe form of delirium, depression, schizophrenia, acute illness or poorly controlled chronic diseases;
2. Receive administration of the following drugs/herbs including donepezil, rivastigmine, galantamine, memantine,, huperzine, and any ingredients in the SLT formula including ginseng, ginkgo and saffron.;
3. Have a history of severe forms of peptic ulcers, diabetes with complications, pulmonary disorders, renal and/or hepatic disorders;
4. Abnormal pathology test results: Cr &gt; 1.5 times upper limit of normal (ULN); Alt, AST or ALP &gt; 2 times ULN;  PT &gt; 3 second more than ULN; APTT &gt; 10 seconds more than ULN; Plt &lt; 100,000/mcL
5. Have severe dysphasia, mental retardation and/or life expectancy &lt; 6 months;
6. Are allergic to more than 2 medications or at least 1 ingredient of SLT;
7. Are pregnant or lactating women.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A statistician external to the research team generated the randomisation treatment sequence using block randomisation to evenly allocate participants into either the active or placebo treatment group. Allocation concealment - the principal investigator will determine the eligibility of each subject who will then, if eligible, be allocated to the next numbered box of product by the clinical research nurse or research associate.  </concealment>
    <sequence>The method of sequence generation was done using a freely available online computer application randomization.com by a statistician external to the research team</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Based on the magnitude of ADAS-cog improvement in previous trials using ginkgo for dementia, an improvement of ADAS-cog of at least 2 points (with a standard deviation of 3.9 units) was used to calculate sample size. As a result, a total of 162 patients are required to detect this difference with 90% power at the 0.05 significance level. A sample of 170 will be needed to give 90% power to detect a 4-point change in ADCS-ADL with an estimated standard deviation of 8.0. Allowing for a total non-compliance/withdrawal rate of 25%, 226 participants will be recruited into the trial across all centres to ensure 170 patients in the final analyses.

Data will be analysed using linear mixed models through which we will test for differences between treatment group on each outcome over time, with adjustment for random variation between treatment centres, with and without adjustment for other potentially important predicts (e.g. compliance, age, gender, severity of VaD). Non-linear changes over time by a) fitting time as categorical variable and b) testing for quadratic and cubic effects will be tested for.  Results will be reported as regression coefficients (or odds ratios if categorical) and associated 95% confidence intervals. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/08/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/08/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>226</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/11/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Liverpool Hospital - Liverpool</hospital>
    <hospital>Bankstown-Lidcombe Hospital - Bankstown</hospital>
    <hospital>Hornsby Ku-ring-gai Hospital - Hornsby</hospital>
    <hospital>Wollongong Hospital - Wollongong</hospital>
    <hospital>War Memorial Hospital - Waverley</hospital>
    <hospital>The Prince Charles Hospital - Chermside</hospital>
    <hospital>Norwest Private Hospital - Bella Vista</hospital>
    <postcode>2170 - Liverpool</postcode>
    <postcode>2200 - Bankstown</postcode>
    <postcode>2077 - Hornsby</postcode>
    <postcode>2500 - Wollongong</postcode>
    <postcode>2024 - Waverley</postcode>
    <postcode>4064 - Milton</postcode>
    <postcode>2153 - Bella Vista</postcode>
    <postcode>4032 - Chermside</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australia Shineway Technology Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Unit 2806, 591-597 George St, 
Sydney NSW 2000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australia Shineway Technology Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Unit 2806, 591-597 George St, 
Sydney NSW 2000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Dementia is the leading cause of mental and physical disability in the elderly. Vascular dementia (VaD) that accounts for 15-20% of all dementia cases is a syndrome of acquired cognitive functional impairment with a complex pathophysiological basis. Viable pharmaceutical options are currently lacking.

Herbal medicine has been used for the treatment of ageing-related disorders for more than 2000 years ago in ancient China. Combination therapies are complex mixtures are believed to be able to enhance therapeutic efficacy through synergistic and multi-target mechanisms and are ideal and may be relevant for disorders such as VaD that has multifactorial / multisystem pathophysiology components. Conventional pharmaceutical techniques have been used to develop a novel, standardised herbal formulation, Sailuotong (SLT) targeting VaD. Data from pre-clinical studies have shown significant improvements in memory functions and in pathogenic biochemical parameters in various animal models. Appropriate safety of SLT has also been shown in acute and chronic toxicity and herb-drug interactions studies. 

We propose to undertake a rigorous phase III clinical trial of SLT in 226 patients with mild to moderate probable VaD or Alzheimers disease with cerebrovascular disease (AD+CVD). The aim of this 52-week randomised, multicentre, double-blind, placebo controlled trial is to: 
1. Determine the efficacy of SLT on cognitive function and activities of daily living, and
2. Monitor the safety of SLT as a treatment for VaD or AD+CVD during a 52-week treatment period.

The primary outcome measures include Vascular Dementia Assessment Scale cognitive subscale (VaDAS-cog) and Alzheimers Disease Co-operative Study Activities of Daily Living Inventory (ADCS-ADL). In addition, there are six secondary outcome measures including: The Clinicians Interview Based Impression of Change-plus (CIBIC-plus), 

Additional executive function tests using CLOX and EXIT-25, Assessment of depression using the Cornell Scale of Depression in Dementia (CSDD), Quality of life assessment using the SF-36, Functional MRI Assessment in a subset group, and The Neuropsychiatric Inventory-Clinician rating scale (NPI-C). Liver and renal function and routine haematological tests will be conducted regularly during the trial. All adverse events will be recorded at each visit, including those suspected to be related to the treatment and any worsening of symptoms will be closely monitored. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.nicm.edu.au/nicm/clinical_trials/slt_for_vascular_dementia </trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Western Sydney Local Health District Human Research Ethics Comittee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Locked Bag 7103
Liverpool BC NSW 2170  
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/11/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/LPOOL/81 </hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/02/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Western Sydney University Human Research Ethics Comittee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Engagement, Development and Innovation (REDI)
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith NSW 2751</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/09/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H11554</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/09/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Specialist Services Medical Group Research and Ethics Comittee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 505
Westmead NSW 2145</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/09/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>NA</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/09/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Dennis Chang</name>
      <address>National Institute of Complementary Medicine (NICM)  
Bldg 22, Western Sydney University, Campbelltown Campus
Narellan Rd, Campbelltown
Postal Address: Locked Bag 1797  PENRITH   NSW   2751
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4620 3310</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4620 3722</fax>
      <email>D.Chang@westernsydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kellie Bilinski</name>
      <address>National Institute of Complementary Medicine (NICM)  
Bldg 22, Western Sydney University, Campbelltown Campus
Narellan Rd, Campbelltown
Postal Address: Locked Bag 1797  PENRITH   NSW   2751</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4620 3578</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4620 3291 </fax>
      <email>K.Bilinski@westernsydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Dennis Chang</name>
      <address>National Institute of Complementary Medicine (NICM)  
Bldg 22, Western Sydney University, Campbelltown Campus
Narellan Rd, Campbelltown
Postal Address: Locked Bag 1797  PENRITH   NSW   2751</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4620 33100</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4620 3722</fax>
      <email>D.Chang@westernsydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kellie Bilinski</name>
      <address>National Institute of Complementary Medicine (NICM)  
Bldg 22, Western Sydney University, Campbelltown Campus
Narellan Rd, Campbelltown
Postal Address: Locked Bag 1797  PENRITH   NSW   2751</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4620 3578</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4620 3291 </fax>
      <email>K.Bilinski@westernsydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>