<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365834">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/02/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/03/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000222640</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Cognition and Type 2 Diabetes  A pilot randomised controlled trial (RCT) of exercise</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In people with type 2 diabetes, does structured exercise improve or preserve brain health?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1153-6018</utrn>
    <trialacronym>CDOT-X</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>cognitive impairment</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>dementia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>type 2 diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dementias</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention group will receive a 6 month structured exercise program by fully trained exercise physiologists. Two one-hour supervised sessions per week will occur at the Menzies Research Institute gymnasium on non-consecutive days, plus a further one-hour per week unsupervised session at the participants home with prescribed exercises (e.g. walking). Each supervised session will consist of a warm-up and cool-down, moderate- to high-intensity progressive resistance training exercises using body weight, simple machine or free weights of 8-15 repetitions (e.g. free weights: bicep curls, shoulder press, chest press; body weight: step ups or sit to stand +/- weight vest; machine weights: quadriceps press, shoulder press, chest press, knee extension), and an aerobic component involving stationary cycling, cross trainer or treadmill walking at 40-84% of VO2R. The program will be tailored to participants abilities and progressive intensity applied with increasing fitness. Adherence will be assessed by attendance at the supervised exercise sessions and completion of personal exercise diaries. </interventions>
    <comparator>The control arm will also receive a 6 month light stretching/gentle movements program. Two one-hour supervised sessions per week will occur at the Menzies Research Institute, and the participants will be asked to carry out one unsupervised session at home.  Each session will consist of gentle stretches and movements of the upper and lower limb muscles.  Adherence will be assessed by attendance at the supervised exercise sessions and completion of personal exercise diaries.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Brain MRI - grey matter volume</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Brain MRI  Measures of interest are brain volumes (white, white matter lesion, hippocampus), regional cerebral perfusion (CBF using arterial spin labeling ASL), white matter integrity (fractional anisotropy FA, mean diffusivity MD using diffusion tensor imaging DTI).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive measures: assessments of selective attention, executive function, processing speed and memory will be made using standard neurological tests:Hopkins Verbal Learning Test  R, Form 1; Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale  Third Edition (WAIS-III) Subsets of Digit Span, Digit Symbol Coding and Symbol Search; Controlled Oral Word Association Test (COWAT); Category Fluency Test; Rey Complex Figure copying and delayed recall task; Stroop Test (Victoria Form);Trails A &amp; B.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Central haemodynamics: These will be measured non-invasively at rest, during exercise VO2 test and over 24 hours</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Retinal photography using a Canon CR-DGi non-mydriatic retinal camera retinal vascular measures (length/diameter, optimality ratio)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Short Physical Performance Battery </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Skin microvessel function measured by Laser Doppler Flowmetry</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Echocardiogram to measure left heart function</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasting bloods  for fasting glucose, insulin, lipids, HbA1C  and stored at -80 for future assays of, neurotrophins, serum AGEs plasma cytokine and oxidative stress markers </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Usual physical activity measured with accelerometers worn over 7 days (measured at baseline, 3months and in the last week of the intervention or control program);</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3 months and last week of the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Urine sample to measure albuminuria.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline -  before and after VO2max test
6 month follow-up before and after VO2max test</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Aerobic capacity: VO2max using a treadmill(Bruce or Modified Bruce test)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Knee strength with the short form of the Physiological Profile Assessment 
Grip strength with a hand dynamometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria
1) T2DM as diagnosed by fasting blood glucose greater or equal to 7 mmol/L or HbA1C greater than 6.4 % or 2 hr post-prandial glucose greater than 11 mmol/L according to current American Diabetes Association Guidelines. 
2) Age 50-75 years
3) Be willing and able to participate in a structured exercise program for 6-months.  
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria: 
1) any severe medical condition that precludes safe participation in exercise;
2) moderate or severe dementia 
3)Known central nervous system disorders that may have confounding effects on cognitive function (e.g. tumour, multiple sclerosis, Parkinsons disease)
4)contra-indication to MRI; 
5) exercising greater than the equivalent of 30 minutes once a week in the last 3 months.

</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomised by central automated allocation procedure based on computer-generated random numbers</concealment>
    <sequence>Block randomized within two age strata of 50-65 years and 65-75 years with equal allocation between strata and random block sizes within strata</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>An important aim of this pilot study is to obtain preliminary data on which to base sample size estimates for the main study. The distributions of outcome and study factors will be summarised by means and standard deviations for continuous variables, and by frequencies and percentages for categorical variables. The efficacy analyses will be undertaken as planned in the main study but only for the purpose of estimating change and variability of change in the outcome measures. They will be performed on an intention-to-treat basis, and both without and with multiple imputation of missing data. In addition, we will perform per-protocol analyses of those participants who meet the criterion of at least 70% adherence to their exercise prescription. Adverse event data will be summarised and presented by treatment group and time point in summary tables. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>28/03/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>26/06/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>TAS</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Michele Callisaya</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Stroke and Ageing Research Group
Southern Clinical School, Monash University
Level 5 E Block Monash Medical Centre 246 Clayton Road, Clayton Victoria 3168 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Alzheimers Australia Dementia Research Foundation Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1 Frewin Place, Scullin,
ACT, 2614</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Associate Professor Velandai Srikanth</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Stroke and Ageing Research Group
Southern Clinical School, Monash University
Level 5 E Block, Monash Medical Centre 246 Clayton Road, Clayton Victoria 3168 
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Type 2 Diabetes (T2DM) is a significant risk factor for dementia in older people, and vascular disease may underlie this relationship.  Greater physical activity is associated with better brain function and is also recommended for people with T2DM to reduce cardiovascular risk. However, it is currently unknown as to whether an exercise intervention can preserve or improve brain health in people with T2DM.  

The aim of this project is to examine the efficacy of a six month structured exercise program in preserving brain health in late middle aged people with T2DM, and evaluate whether this occurs by improving vascular health. This will be done by using MRI scans to measure brain perfusion and structure, sophisticated measures of large and small artery health, and cognitive function before and after the intervention. 

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee (Tasmania) Network</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Tasmania 
Private Bag 01 
Hobart Tasmania 7005</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/01/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H13664</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Deakin University Human Research Ethics Committee (DUHREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>70 Elgar Road Burwood Victoria
Postal: 221 Burwood Highway
Burwood Victoria 3125 Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/02/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2014-012</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Building 3E Clayton Campus
Monash University Clayton Victoria</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/02/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CF14/281-201400009</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Office of The University of Western Australia</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Western Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/01/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>RA/4/1/6611</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michele Callisaya </name>
      <address>Stroke and Ageing Research Group
Southern Clinical School
Level 5 E Block, 
Monash Medical Centre Monash Univeristy
246 Clayton Road, Clayton Victoria 3168 
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 62264785</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michele.callisaya@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michele Callisaya</name>
      <address>Stroke and Ageing Research Group
Southern Clinical School
Level 5 E Block, 
Monash Medical Centre Monash Univeristy
246 Clayton Road, Clayton Victoria 3168 
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 62264785</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michele.callisaya@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michele Callisaya</name>
      <address>Stroke and Ageing Research Group
Southern Clinical School
Level 5 E Block, 
Monash Medical Centre Monash Univeristy
246 Clayton Road, Clayton Victoria 3168 
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 62264785</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michele.callisaya@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michele Callisaya</name>
      <address>Stroke and Ageing Research Group
Southern Clinical School
Level 5 E Block, 
Monash Medical Centre Monash Univeristy
246 Clayton Road, Clayton Victoria 3168 
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 62264785</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michele.callisaya@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>