<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363500">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/01/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/01/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000059763</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The role of FTO Gene Variants on Metabolic Flexibility and Training Adaptations following a 12 Week High Intensity Exercise Intervention</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The role of FTO Gene Variants on Metabolic Flexibility and Training Adaptations in Relatively Healthy Males following a 12 Week High Intensity Exercise Intervention</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1138-5521</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Metabolic Flexibility
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Overweight and Obesity
</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human Genetics and Inherited Disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other human genetics and inherited disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be asked to submit to a 12 week exercise training intervention. Thirty six (36) training sessions will be conducted in total over the 12 week period. This intervention will involve participants cycling at 150% VO2max for 20 seconds with 40 seconds passive recovery per minute during each session. The frequency and duration of sessions will be incremented in 4 x 3 week blocks (weeks 1-3, 2 x 20 minutes per week; weeks 4-6, 3 x 20 minutes per week; weeks 7-9, 3 x 30 minutes per week; weeks 10-12, 4 x 30 minutes per week).

Prior to and following the 12 week exercise training intervention participants will be asked to perform exercise tests during two testing sessions (total of four testing sessions). One exercise test will involve a single bout of cycle ergometer exercise at 80% (HI) VO2max for 38 minutes which expends ~400 kcal. This is a crossover study with the order of the exercise tests being randomised. The second test will occur a minimum of 2 days following the commencement of the first exercise test (maximum of up to 1 week). The second exercise test will involve a single bout of cycle ergometer exercise at 40% (LO) VO2max for 70 minutes which expends ~400 kcal.  This washout period will be based on participants and workplace availability.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants with the FTO rs9939609 risk allele (A) and participants with two FTO rs9939609 wild type alleles (TT) will be there own controls (crossover study). Participants will be asked to perform a single bout of cycle ergometer exercise at 40% (LO) VO2max for 70 minutes which expends ~400 kcal. This will be conducted prior to and following a 12 week exercise training intervention.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To understand whether genetic variants of the FTO gene influence the skeletal muscles ability to utilise carbohydrates, proteins and fats at a genetic and tissue level in response to a 12 week high intensity intermittent exercise training intervention.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints to be assessed will be the same for all 4 testing sessions (2 exercise testing sessions conducted before the intervention, and 2 exercise testing sessions after the intervention). The timepoints are at baseline/prior to exercise testing (DNA, serum &amp; muscle), every 10 minutes during exercise (serum), immediately following exercise (serum), 15 minutes following exercise (serum &amp; muscle), and 3 hours following exercise (serum &amp; muscle).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be considered relatively healthy males with the FTO rs9939609 risk allele (A) or two FTO rs9939609 wild type alleles (TT). Participants will be included if they have adequate glucose handling (no diagnosed diabetes, fasting blood glucose must be less than 7.0 mmol/L), not performing any regular fitness training (i.e. greater than 30 minutes, 3 times per week) for the past 6 months, not taking contraindicated prescription medication (i.e. thyroid, hyperlipidmeic, hypoglycemic, or antihypertensive), do have physician approval (if BMI over 25kg.m-2), and not current involvement in other research studies. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria> Participants will be excluded from participating within the project for the following reasons: diagnosed diabetes (fasting blood glucose greater than 7.0 mmol/L or HbA1ctest greater than 6.5%), performing any regular fitness training (i.e. greater than 30 minutes, 3 times per week) for the past 6 months, taking contraindicated prescription medication (i.e. thyroid, hyperlipidmeic, hypoglycemic, or antihypertensive), no physician approval (if BMI over 25kg.m-2), and current involvement in other research studies. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The order of the exercise testing (LO vs. HI) will be decided by coin toss by an individual independent to the project.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Data will be analysed using SPSS for Windows Version 18 software (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL).  An independent samples t-test will be calculated on all dependent variables to determine if significant differences exist at baseline between the two groups (healthy obese  versus healthy lean controls).  MANOVAs (grouped for variables of skeletal muscle protein, and skeletal muscle mRNA) will be used to analyse the pre- and post-exercise data to account for any dependent variables that may be related to one another.  In addition, the use of a MANOVA analysis also prevents the chance of committing a Type I error that could result from the use of repeated univariate ANOVA procedures. For all dependent variables, repeated measures multivariate analysis of variance (MANOVA) will be utilized.  Separate t-tests on each dependent variable will be conducted as follow-up tests to the MANOVA.  To control for alpha inflation of the ANOVA, the Bonferroni test will be utilized. Data will be considered significantly different when the probability of error is 0.05 or less. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/03/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Victoria University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>McKechnie Street, St Albans VIC 3021</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Victoria University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>McKechnie Street, St Albans VIC 3021</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this project is to understand whether specific FTO risk gene variants influence the skeletal muscles ability to utilise carbohydrates and fats at a genetic and tissue level following a 12 week high intensity intermittent exercise training intervention. Ten (10) healthy males with the FTO rs9939609 risk allele (A) and 10 healthy males with two FTO rs9939609 wild type alleles (TT) between the ages 20 - 50 will be recruited to participate in this study. Following a buccal swab and venous blood sampling to obtain a genetic and metabolic signature profile, participants will perform a low (40% VO2max-LO) and high-intensity (80% VO2max-HI) exercise bout for approximately 70 and 38 minutes, respectively. This second test will occur a minimum of 2 days following the commencement of the first exercise test (maximum of up to 1 week). Venous blood will be sampled prior to, immediately after, 15 minutes, and 3 hours following completion of the exercise. Urine samples will be collected prior to and 3 hours following the completion of the exercise. A 12 week exercise training intervention will then be employed. 36 training sessions will be conducted in total over the 12 week period. This intervention will involve participants cycling at 150% VO2max for 20 seconds with 40 seconds passive recovery per minute, and the frequency and duration of sessions will be incremented in 4 x 3 week blocks. Following this intervention the LO and HI exercise tests will be repeated (following the same procedures as indicated above).This project will provide important information on whether low or high intensity exercise is more effective to stimulating glucose and fat metabolism in skeletal muscle, and whether high intensity intermittent exercise training can influence the metabolic profile of those with FTO obesity risk variants. This project may also provide genetically susceptible individuals with an insight in to risk-reducing behaviours that can be effective in prevention of obesity.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Victoria University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ballarat Rd, Footscray VIC 3011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/01/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Christos Stathis</name>
      <address>Victoria University (Footscray Park Campus), Ballarat Rd, Footscray VIC 3011</address>
      <phone>+61 03 9919 4293</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christos.stathis@vu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Jessica Danaher</name>
      <address>Victoria University (St Albans Campus), McKechnie Street, St Albans VIC 3021</address>
      <phone>+61 421 479 868</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jessica.danaher@live.vu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Jessica Danaher</name>
      <address>Victoria University (St Albans Campus), McKechnie Street, St Albans VIC 3021</address>
      <phone>+61 421 479 868</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jessica.danaher@live.vu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Jessica Danaher</name>
      <address>Victoria University (St Albans Campus), McKechnie Street, St Albans VIC 3021</address>
      <phone>+61 421 479 868</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jessica.danaher@live.vu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>