<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362747">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/07/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/07/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000745842</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Rehabilitation in Patients Hospitalised with An Acute Exacerbation of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of exercise training versus usual care on exercise capacity, muscle strength and functional performance in patients hospitalised with an acute exacerbation of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1132-4282</utrn>
    <trialacronym>AECOPD: Acute Exacerbation of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute Exacerbation of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (requires hospitalisation)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients allocated to the treatment group will receive two individual training sessions daily during the five weekdays, in which the morning session will be supervised, and the afternoon session will be unsupervised. The training sessions will comprise of walking and resistance exercises and will be carried out by a trained physiotherapist. The training will commence within 48 hours of admission until the patients are allowed to be discharged from the hospital. We expect each session (supervised or unsupervised) to take no longer than 30 minutes (inclusive of rests).

Resistance training includes sit to stand, half squats and step exercises. Initial prescription will be determined by one set of individualised number of repetition based on the baseline Sit-To-Stand-Test score. The exercise prescription will be increased by one set on every second day of training.

Walking training will be prescribed based on the baseline two-minute walk distance (2MWD) and progressed on every second day of training by increasing the distance walked during each session by 20%.</interventions>
    <comparator>Patients allocated to the control group will receive the usual medical and physiotherapy care given to patients admitted with an acute exacerbation of COPD according to the Malaysian Clinical Practice Guideline (CPG). It is expected that patients will receive usual care each weekday and the duration of the treatment will range between 15 to 30 minutes (depending on their individual needs). 

In this guideline, a patient will be discharged if they meet all the criteria for discharge listed. Therefore, patients allocated to the control group will be involved in this study until they are allowed to be discharge from the hospital. 

Patients allocated to the control group will receive usual care which includes: 

Usual Medical care as described in the Malaysian COPD Clinical Practice Guidelines (CPG).

Usual Physiotherapy care may comprise airway clearance (if required), strategies to minimise dyspnoea (e.g. pursed lip breathing and positioning), and encouragement to mobilise in the ward.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional exercise capacity will be measured using the two-minute walk test (2MWT).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurement at baseline and prior to discharge.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Peripheral muscle strength will be measured using a force gauge.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurement at baseline and prior to discharge.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional performance will be measured using the Sit-To-Stand-Test (STST)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurement at baseline and prior to discharge.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity will be measured using a StepWatch Activity Monitor (SAM).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurement during the hospitalisation period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional performance will be measured using the Timed-Up and Go (TUG) test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurement at baseline and prior to discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients who are admitted with an AECOPD.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(i)	any contraindication to exercise as listed by the American College of Sports Medicine 
(ii)	hospitalisation within the previous 14 days
(iii)	inability to understand or speak English or Malay</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation to intervention will be concealed by using sealed opaque envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computerised sequence generation will be used. The randomisation sequence will be stratified according to the hospital from which the patients were recruited (i.e. Hospital Selayang or Institute of Respiratory Medicine) and the patient’s baseline 2MWD. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size calculation:
Assuming a between-group difference of 15% +/- 14% (alpha = 0.05, 1 - beta = 0.8), a sample size of 15 participants per group was needed (30 in total). This number was increased from 30 to 38 to allow for a 20% attrition rate

Data analyses:
Within- and between-group differences were analysed using a two-way repeated measures analysis of variance (two-way RM-ANOVA). Differences were expressed as mean difference (MD) and 95% confidence interval (CI). Analyses were undertaken according to an intention-to-treat basis.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>30/07/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>27/01/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>4/08/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>38</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>38</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/01/2014</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>8/08/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <state>Kuala Lumpur</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>School of Physiotherapy and Curtin Health Innovation Research Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Curtin University
Kent Street
Perth
Western Australia 
6102 
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Malaysian Thoracic Society Research Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Malaysian Thoracic Society 
Suite 2-3, Medical Academies of Malaysia, 
210 Jalan Tun Razak, 
50400 Kuala Lumpur </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Malaysia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Faculty of Medicine, MARA University of Technology</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Hospital Selayang
Lebuhraya Selayang-Kepong, 
68100 Batu Caves, Selangor Darul Ehsan.</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Malaysia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The present study aims at investigating the effects of a standardised exercise training program that comprises of walking and resistance exercises on exercise capacity, quadriceps muscle strength and functional performance in patients hospitalised with an AECOPD.

Study hypotheses
In patients with COPD who are hospitalised with an acute exacerbation of their disease, those who are allocated to the treatment group will show a significantly greater improvement in 2MWD, quadriceps muscle force, performance in the STST and TUG, and physical activity compared to the control group.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Tahirah F, Jenkins S, Othman SK, Ismail R, Ismail T &amp; Hill K. A randomised controlled trial of individualised, progressed early exercise in patients hospitalised with an acute exacerbation of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease. European Respiratory Journal 2015; 46: Supplement 59, PA 743.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committees of Malaysia Ministry of Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Jawatankuasa Etika &amp; Penyelidikan Perubatan (Medical Research &amp; Ethics Committee),
Kementerian Kesihatan Malaysia,
INstitut Pengurusan Kesihatan,
Jalan Rumah Sakit, Bangsar.
59000 Kuala Lumpur</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/12/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>NMRR-12-971-12644</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/10/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Malaysia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committees of Universiti Teknologi MARA</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Faculty of Meedicine, 
UiTM Sungai Buloh Campus,
Jalan Hospital
47000 Sungai Buloh
Selangor Darul Ehsan</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/04/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>600-RMI (5/1/6)</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/02/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Malaysia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committees of Curtin University </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Curtin University,
Kent street,
Bentley, 6102.
Western Australia,
Australia.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/01/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HR 13/2013</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>8/01/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>A/Prof Sue Jenkins</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy and Curtin Health Innovation Research Institute
Curtin University
Kent Street
Perth
Western Australia 
6102 
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 3639</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9266 3699</fax>
      <email>S.Jenkins@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Fatim Tahirah Mirza</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy and Curtin Health Innovation Research Institute
Curtin University
Kent Street
Perth
Western Australia 
6102 
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61892669443</phone>
      <fax>+61892663699</fax>
      <email>f.mirzamoh.postgrad@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Fatim Tahirah Mirza</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy and Curtin Health Innovation Research Institute
Curtin University
Kent Street
Perth
Western Australia 
6102 
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61892669443</phone>
      <fax>+61892663699</fax>
      <email>f.mirzamoh.postgrad@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Fatim Tahirah Mirza </name>
      <address>PO Box No 9,
Batu 10 Jalan Taiping,
34300 Bagan Serai,
Perak</address>
      <phone>+6057215739</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>fatim_mirza@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>