<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370288">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/04/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/06/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000792426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Lactate metabolism in Intensive Care Unit (ICU) patients with severe sepsis / septic shock with normal and elevated lactate values.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Description of muscle lactate metabolism in ICU patients with severe sepsis/septic shock in a two-compartment model using stable isotopes. An experimental, descriptive, open clinical trial. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1180-4871</utrn>
    <trialacronym>2PLS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Severe sepsis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Septic shock</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other inflammatory or immune system disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All patients will be given primed infusions of both D5-labelled Phenylalanine (bolus of 0.5 mg/kg and infusion of 0.5 mg/kg/h) and 13C-labelled Lactate (bolus of 1 mg/kg and infusion of 3.65 mg/kg/h) during 3 hours, when these will have reached steady state. Patients will receive a femoral venous catheter, blood samples will be collected and blood flow in the leg examined using doppler-ultrasound. Clinical data will be collected from electronic charts.</interventions>
    <comparator>The study aims to describe and compare lactate metabolism in patients with severe sepsis / septic shock with normal lactate (&lt;2mmol/L) and elevated lactate (&gt;3mmol/L)</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Difference in whole body lactate kinetics between the groups. 

By analyzing blood samples for relationship between labelled and unlabelled lactate with Gas Chromatography-Mass Spectrometry (GC-MS), lactate kinetics (rate of appearance and rate of disappearance) can be derived through mathematical models.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Serial blood samples (n=4) will be drawn every five minutes between t=195 and t=210 after start of the infusions. Lactate kinetics will be calculated for each of these data points as well as means of the four. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Difference in skeletal muscle lactate kinetics between the groups. 

By analyzing blood samples for relationship between labelled and unlabelled lactate with Gas Chromatography-Mass Spectrometry (GC-MS), lactate kinetics (rate of appearance and rate of disappearance) can be derived through mathematical models. By taking simultaneous samples from artery and vein and combining them with femoral blood flow, quantification of production and uptake in the leg can be performed  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Serial blood samples (n=4) will be drawn every five minutes between t=195 and t=210 after start of the infusions, from artery and femoral vein. Lactate kinetics will be calculated for each of these data points as well as means of the four. 
Blood flow will be measured before and after the sampling and mean will be used for quantification of lactate kinetics. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Difference in whole body Phenylalanine kinetics between the groups. 

By analyzing blood samples for relationship between labelled and unlabelled phenylalanine with Gas Chromatography-Mass Spectrometry (GC-MS), kinetics (rate of appearance and rate of disappearance) can be derived through mathematical models.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Serial blood samples (n=4) will be drawn every five minutes between t=195 and t=210 after start of the infusions. Lactate kinetics will be calculated for each of these data points as well as means of the four. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mortality</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days after study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Severe sepsis / septic shock within 72 hours of onset. Lactate &lt;2mmol/L or &gt;3mmol/L</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Muscle disorders, Metformin treatment within the last five days, ongoing dialysis at time of investigation, lack of informed consent.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Assuming a variation twice that of healthy volunteers in our previous study, the study is powered to have 80% chance to detect a 30% difference in whole body, and 50% difference in muscle, rate of appearance between the groups with high and normal lactate, with a alpha-level of a=0.05. These numbers can be compared to the change in rate of appearance caused by adrenaline of 300% (which increased plasma levels from 1.1 to 4.0 mmol/L). Student´s t-test will be used for comparisons between the groups.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>22/08/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>28/02/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Stockholm</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Karolinska Institutet</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Clintec, dept of Anesthesiology and Intensive Care
141 86 Stockholm</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Sweden</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Stockholm County</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Box 22550, 104 22 Stockholm</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Sweden</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Severe sepsis / septic shock are leading causes of death in ICU:s all around the world. Improvements have been made through early identification and standardization of resuscitation (through initiatives such as Surviving Sepsis Campaign and others). In the later versions of the resuscitation guidelines a bigger focus has been put on the measurements of plasma-lactate. Increased levels have been shown to correlate with worsened outcome but a normal lactate does not exclude critical condition.
Even though it is used in clinical decision-making concerning potentially lifesaving treatment, the actual metabolism of lactate in sepsis is surprisingly poorly described. 
In this project we aim to describe the lactate metabolism (rate of appearance and rate of disappearance) in ICU patients with severe sepsis/septic shock with normal (&lt;2mmol/L) or elevated (&gt;3mmol/L) levels of lactate. After recruitment and informed consent subjects will receive a femoral venous catheter and infusions of labeled lactate and phenylalanine will start. After reaching steady state concentration blood samples will be drawn from arterial and femoral lines and blood flow in the femoral artery will be assessed using Doppler ultrasound. Data from patients charts will be collected and they will be followed for 28-day mortality.
Through this project we will be able to describe lactate metabolism in whole body as well as in the leg. Hopefully this increased knowledge will deepen our understanding and help us to optimize the use of lactate for clinical decision making in the future.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Regional Ethical Review Board in Stockholm</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Nobels vag, 
171 65 Solna</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/02/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016/106-31/4</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/01/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Sweden</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Olav Rooyackers</name>
      <address>Karolinska University Hospital
Dept. of Anesthesiology and Intensive Care 
K31 141 86 Stockholm</address>
      <phone>+46739661645</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>olav.rooyackers@ki.se</email>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jonathan Grip</name>
      <address>Karolinska University Hospital
Dept. of Anesthesiology and Intensive Care 
K31 141 86 Stockholm</address>
      <phone>+46736230906</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jonathan.grip@ki.se</email>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jonathan Grip</name>
      <address>Karolinska University Hospital
Dept. of Anesthesiology and Intensive Care 
K31 141 86 Stockholm</address>
      <phone>+46736230906</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jonathan.grip@ki.se</email>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jonathan Grip</name>
      <address>Karolinska University Hospital
Dept. of Anesthesiology and Intensive Care 
K31 141 86 Stockholm</address>
      <phone>+46736230906</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jonathan.grip@ki.se</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>