<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82079">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/06/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/06/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000340437</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An Observer-Blinded Study to Determine the Feasibility of Pressure-Based Swedish Adjustable Gastric Band (SAGB) Adjustments in aiding weight loss</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An Observer-Blinded Study to Determine the Feasibility of Pressure-Based Swedish Adjustable Gastric Band Adjustments in aiding weight loss</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Bariatric Banding
Weight Loss</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2 />
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Gastric Band adjustments are performed to vary the degree of restriction the band delivers hence allowing more or less food consumption.  The adjustment is made by injection of saline into the band. The frequency of routine band adjustment is dependent on degree of weight loss.

The subject will be asked to swallow a measured amount of water, the band will be adjusted per standard hospital procedure, then another measured amount of water and one of three food or juice substances will be consumed.  A pressure transducer (sensor) which is connected to the standard adjustment equipment (outside the body) will detect the pressure within the gastric band as the food is swallowed.  The pressure will be recorded on a computer. The procedure may take up to 30 minutes.  The measurements will be taken during one adjustment only.

The study consists of three parts, Phase one Part one assesses which substance provides the most consistent pressure pattern, Phase 1 Part 2 tests what volume provides the most consistent pressure reading.  Phase 2 tests the differences and consistency in pressures within the band. 

Assignment to each phase is sequential and is dependent on the preceeding  number of patients enrolled.</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Effective weight loss after insertion of an adjustable Gastric Band is dependent on patient selection, surgical placement and close patient follow up, including intermittent band adjustments.  Too little inflation can result in inadequate restriction and weight loss while too much inflation can result in too much restriction and an increased risk of oesophageal and gastric pouch complications.  To date band adjustment are based on the volume of fluid used to inflate the band.  The volume is usually assessed on patient feedback.  The current approach is not objective.

The information gained from this study will be used to determine if it is feasible to use pressure based adjustments of the Swedish Adjustable Gastric Band.  If it is successful an alternative objective method may be used to determine if a gastric band is adjusted appropriately.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The assessment will be made at the time of adjustment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine which media and volume produces the optimal most consistent intra-band pressure patterns.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All assessments will be measured at the time of band adjustment.  Only one adjustment will be made.  Measurements wil include Maximum pressure, number of peak pressure readings, time to return to baseline.  Incidence of adverse events.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine the variability of static and dynamic pressure measurments.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>All assessments will be measured at the time of band adjustment.  Only one adjustment will be made.  Measurements wil include Maximum pressure, number of peak pressure readings, time to return to baseline.  Incidence of adverse events.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Provide informed consent.  Documented date of Gastric Band insertionUndergoing 1st, 2nd or 3rd band adjustment</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Females known to be pregnantKnown food allergies to the test mediaHistory of port obstructionCurrent port infectionHistory of revision of band systemHistory of oesophageal dysmotility or dilationConsumption of solid food within 4 hours of study band adjustmentConsumption of liquids within 2 hours of study band adjustmentAny condition that in the opinion of the investigator may jeopardize the subject's well-being and/or the soundness of the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The investigator will not be permitted to view the computer screen showing the pressure readings during band adjustment.  Only the trained study assistant will have access to the data at any given time.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/07/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>592</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Ethicon Endo-Surgery</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ethicon Endo-Surgery</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Johnson and Johnson Medical</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is being conducted in order to learn more about a potential new way to monitor the adjustments of the Swedish Adjustable Gastric Band.  Currently doctors generally monitor band adjustments based on the volume of fluid that is used to inflate the band.  This study will evaluate whether it is possible to consistently measure the pressure within the gastric band.  The information obtained will be used to establish if it is feasible to use pressure based adjustments in the future</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Human Research Ethics Committee-the Institute of Weight Control in Baulkham Hills</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Human Research Ethics Committee-The Adelaide Bariatric Centre</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Fiona Smith</name>
      <address>Johnson and Johnson Medical
1-5 Khartoum Rd
North Ryde NSW 2113</address>
      <phone>+61 2 98789000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>fsmith2@medau.jnj.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Fiona Smith</name>
      <address>Johnson and Johnson Medical
1-5 Khartoum Rd
North Ryde NSW 2113</address>
      <phone>+61 2 98789000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>fsmith2@medau.jnj.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>