<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364814">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/08/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/08/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000942752</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Touch-screen video game technology on cognitive and behavioral symptoms for community-living older adults with mild to moderate dementia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Computer assisted intervention using touch-screen video game technology on cognitive and behavioral symptoms for community-living older adults with mild to moderate dementia</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Dementia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dementias</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Subjects assigned to the intervention group will be invited to participate in the computer assisted intervention 2 days a week over an 8 week period (45 minutes per session) provided by a trained research assistant. A selection of touch-screen video games will be used, including Able-X (mosquito splat), Brain Gym (mahjong flip and Its going to rain), fun discovery and lets find it etc.</interventions>
    <comparator>Subjects assigned to the control group will receive conventional remedial activities such as pegboard games, card games, chess board etc. It will be conducted by a trained research assistant 2 days a week over an 8 week period and is expected to last for 45 minutes per session.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change of the Chinese version of the Neuropsychiatric Inventory (CNPI) apathy score after the intervention when compared with the baseline level.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention (8 weeks)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive function (will be measured by the Chinese version of the Mini-Mental State Examination (CMMSE))</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention (8 weeks)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neuropsychiatric symptoms (will be measured by the Chinese version of Neuropsychiatric Inventory (CNPI))</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention (8 weeks)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Agitated behavior (will be measured by the Chinese version of the Cohen-Mansfield Agitation Inventory (CCMAI))</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention (8 weeks)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression (will be measured by the Chinese version of the Corrnell Scale for Depression in Dementia (CSDD))</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention (8 weeks)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mood state (will be measured by a simplified face scale)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention (8 weeks)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Social interaction and communication (subjects emotion expression towards video games and their participation will be charted on every-one-minute basis with the observation table by reviewing videotaped clips after each intervention session)</outcome>
      <timepoint>After each intervention session over 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Community-living older adults aged 60 years and above will be screened using Chinese version of the Mini-Mental State Examination (CMMSE). Those who score between 13 and 23 will be further clinically adjudicated by a panel of clinical experts. Criteria for a diagnosis of dementia will be based on the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM-IV). Severity of dementia will be determined using Clinical Dementia Rating (CDR). Only subjects with mild to moderate dementia (CDR 1 or 2) will be invited to participate.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Subjects will be excluded if they have medical conditions severe enough to affect the patients ability to complete the treatment course and/or follow-up.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>This is a single blind randomized controlled trial. After eligibility check, subjects and their carergivers who agree to join the study will be randomly allocated into either the control or intervention group. Simple randomization will be adopted using computer-generated random numbers, sealed in an opaque envelope. Treatment assignment will be done by an independent person by opening the envelopes with consecutive numbers for eligible subjects. Subjects and their carergivers will aware of the treatment assigned. The outcome assessors will remain blinded to treatment allocation until the data entry is complete.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/10/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>164</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Ruby YU</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>10/F, Clinical Sciences Building,
Prince of Wales Hospital, Shatin, Hong Kong.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Hong Kong</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Health and Medical Research Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Research Office 
Food and Health Bureau 
9/F, Rumsey Street Multi-storey Carpark Building
2 Rumsey Street, Sheung Wan
Hong Kong.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Hong Kong</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>With the substantial increase of dementia in older adults, computer assisted intervention using touch-screen video game technology would be a novel and potential alternative intervention for older people with mild to moderate dementia in enhancing cognitive function and reducing behavioural and psychological symptoms, therefore reducing nursing / healthcare worker loads. The information obtained will promote the awareness to health professionals that touch-screen video game training is a useful cognitive and behaviour intervention in older people with mild to moderate dementia and could be incorporated as part of routine programs amongst the elderly in both community care and hospital settings in Hong Kong.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ruby YU</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine &amp; Therapeutics,
10/F., Clinical Sciences Building,
Prince of Wales Hospital, Shatin, Hong Kong.</address>
      <phone>+852, 26322190</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rubyyu@cuhk.edu.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ruby YU</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine &amp; Therapeutics,
10/F., Clinical Sciences Building,
Prince of Wales Hospital, Shatin, Hong Kong.</address>
      <phone>+852, 26322190</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rubyyu@cuhk.edu.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ruby YU</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine &amp; Therapeutics,
10/F., Clinical Sciences Building,
Prince of Wales Hospital, Shatin, Hong Kong.</address>
      <phone>+852, 26322190</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rubyyu@cuhk.edu.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>