<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371969">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/02/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/02/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000246381</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Is there educational value in providing individualised feedback in addition to generic feedback to online course participants?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effectiveness of individualised and generic feedback compared to generic feedback alone on participation, satisfaction, knowledge acquisition and change in practice in fitness professionals enrolled in an online course.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1192-8399</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Older adults at risk of falls</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Provision of individualised feedback on assignment tasks in addition to generic feedback to fitness professionals participating in an online short course titled 'Exercise Prescription for Falls Prevention'.
The generic feedback is a collation of the main strengths and weaknesses of the group as a whole for each assignment task.  This feedback is standardardized for all participants and will be developed by the course facilitators after examining the assignment tasks.  The course facilitators are physiotherapists with a minimum of 5 years experience in the area of falls prevention.
The individualised feedback will be feedback specifically developed for each participant based on their own assignment task.  Both positive aspects of the task along with some constructive criticism relating to the task goals and possible areas of improvement will be given.  This feedback will be provided by the same course facilitators who provide the generic feedback.
The mode of delivery of both the individualised and generic feedback will be the online learning platform (Moodle) used for the online course which can be set up to send email notifications.  Both interventions will be provided for each of the four assessment tasks.  All participants will be able to direct questions to their course facilitator based on the feedback given.  Participants receiving individualised feedback will be encouraged to engage in the feedback given.
The overall duration of the course is 6 weeks.  This contains four weeks of active facilitation with an additional 2 weeks when educational materials will remain available for participants and it is expected the final knowledge test and course evaluation should be completed.</interventions>
    <comparator>Provision of generic feedback to fitness professionals participating in an online short course titled 'Exercise prescription for Falls Prevention'.
The control group will receive generic feedback only.
The generic feedback is a collation of the main strengths and weaknesses of the group as a whole for each assignment task.  This feedback is standardized for all participants and will be developed by the course facilitators after examining the assignment tasks.  The course facilitators are physiotherapists with a minimum of 5 years experience in the area of falls prevention.
The mode of delivery will be the online learning platform (Moodle) used for the online course which can be set up to send email notifications.  Generic feedback will be provided for each of the four assessment tasks.  All participants will be able to direct questions to their course facilitator based on the feedback given.
The overall duration of the course is 6 weeks.  This contains four weeks of active facilitation with an additional 2 weeks when educational materials will remain available for participants and it is expected the final knowledge test and course evaluation should be completed.  </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participant satisfaction with content and its relevance and with the support and facilitation measured with a post course evaluation questionnaire designed specifically for a previous study involving this web-based course (Maloney S, Haas R, Keating JL, Molloy E, Jolly B, Sims J, Morgan P, Haines T. Effectiveness of web-based versus face-to-face delivery of education in prescription of falls-prevention exercise to health professionals: Randomised Trial. J Med Internet Res 2011:13(4):e116). 
Participants will be asked to respond to the following statements with response options of strongly disagree, disagree, neutral, agree or strongly agree: 
1. The course was pitched at an appropriate knowledge level.
2. I found the tasks and quizzes relevant to my learning.
3. I found the resources relevant to my learning
4. I feel better prepared to prescribe exercise for falls and balance clients
5. Overall, completing the course has improved my confidence in exercise prescription for falls and balance clients. 
6. The course content (i.e. topics and skills) was relevant to my current work role. 
7. The course content (i.e. topics and skills) was relevant to my career aspirations.
8. I felt supported throughout the course. 
9. I was satisfied with the quantity of feedback available on my progress and performance in the course (i.e. provided through answers to self-directed quizzes, feedback on task submissions, answer/feedback sought form the facilitator). 
10. Overall I was satisfied with the facilitation of this short-course. 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>within 2 weeks of course completion</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Willingness to pay for course measured using open ended contingent evaluation question. 
At the beginning of the course, we asked you how much was the maximum amount that you would have been willing to pay out of your own pocket to undertake this course.
Now that you have completed this course and know what was contained within the course and what you have learnt, please tell us what the maximum amount you would now be willing to pay of your own money to complete this course?</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 2 weeks of course completion.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participant engagement in course materials measured via computer-generated usage reports.  Engagement will be measured by number of minutes of online usage with the learning platform, Moodle.  This is automatically collected for each participant as they interact with the online course materials.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From course commencement till course completion (6 week time period)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participant change in clinical behaviour measured by self-reported change in practice since completing the program.  Participants will be asked to respond to the following statements with response options of strongly disagree, disagree, neutral, agree or strongly agree:
1. Since completing the course, I offer greater assistance/advise to other clinicians within falls prevention..
2. Since completing the course, I feel I communicate more effectively with falls prevention clients.
3. Since completing the course, I attempt to use more motivational interviewing techniques..
4. Since completing the course, I manage falls prevention clients more safely.
5. Since completing the course, I have increased my effort to help clients adhere to their falls and balance programs.
6. Since completing the course, I feel I incorporate more evidence-based practice into the management of falls and balance clients.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 2 weeks of course completion and again 3 months following course completion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participant knowledge of exercise prescription for falls prevention measured using 1 hour multiple choice knowledge test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 2 weeks of course completion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All fitness professionals enrolled in an online short course titled 'Exercise Prescription for Falls Prevention'</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>All enrolled course participants are eligible to participate.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by computer</concealment>
    <sequence>Generation of a computerised random number sequence using permuted blocks.
Participants will be stratified according to gender and level of experience.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>This will be a pilot study using all possible participants of online short course.
Differences between the intervention and control group in knowledge test and assignment scores will be analysed using the Mann-Whitney U test (assuming data is not normally distributed).
Previously used survey questions measuring participant satisfaction and change in behaviour will undergo factor analysis.  Differences between intervention and control group in participant satisfaction and change in clinical behaviour will be examined by linear regression using the factor score as the dependent variable and intervention group as the independent variable.
Responses to open-ended qualitative questions will be analysed thematically.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/02/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>27/02/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>3/03/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>6/03/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>98</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>96</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>9/04/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash University Peninsula Campus</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>McMahons Rd, Frankston, 
Victoria, 3199</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to assess the effect of providing individualised feedback in addition to generic feedback compared to generic feedback alone on learning outcomes of a web-based educational course related to falls prevention.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash University Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Monash Research Office
26 Sports Walk
Monash University
Victoria, 3800</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/02/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>8070</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>13/02/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Romi Haas</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy
Department of Physiotherapy
School of Primary Health Care
Monash University
McMahons Rd,
Frankston,
VIC, 3199</address>
      <phone>61 409010626</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>romi.haas@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Romi Haas</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy
School of Primary Health Care
Monash University
McMahons Rd,
Frankston,
VIC, 3199</address>
      <phone>61 409010626</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>romi.haas@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Romi Haas</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy
School of Primary Health Care
Monash University
McMahons Rd,
Frankston,
VIC, 3199</address>
      <phone>61 409010626</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>romi.haas@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Romi Haas</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy
School of Primary Health Care
Monash University
McMahons Rd,
Frankston,
VIC, 3199</address>
      <phone>61 409010626</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>romi.haas@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>