<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373315">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/08/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/08/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001148369</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A pilot randomised control trial assessing a web-based training program on paediatric medical traumatic stress and trauma-informed care for emergency department staff.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot randomised control trial assessing emergency department staff improvement in knowledge of paediatric medical traumatic stress and trauma-informed care following a web-based training program.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1199-3787</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Paediatric medical traumatic stress</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention consists of a web-based training program for emergency department staff (Peadiatric medical  traumatic stress and trauma-informed care principles training for emergency department staff). The training program is comprised of a single module 15 minute evidenced based educational video. Participants in the intervention group can complete this training in one session or they can choose to complete the training in smaller blocks of time. Participants can access the training until training is complete. 
Topics covered in the training include: peadiatric medical traumatic stress following childhood injuries and the signs, symptoms and risk and prognostic factors; and the principles and strategies of trauma-informed care that can be used by emergency department staff to minimise distress and facilitate social support for these children and families. Adherence will be monitored and recorded via the training website which records the duration of time the video was played.
Note: this study assesses a training program aimed at improving medical practitioner knowledge of paediatric medical traumatic stress and is not a assessing a treatment for this condition. </interventions>
    <comparator>1-month, no treatment, waitlist control condition.
Participants in the waitlist control conditions will complete measures at all three time points without receiving any intervention. Following completion of measures at all three time points participants in the waitlist control condition will be given access to the training intervention. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Emergency staff knowledge of paediatric medical traumatic stress as assessed by the knowledge scale of the Psychosocial Care Survey (Alisic et al., 2016). This scale includes 7 questions assessing knowledge of paediatric medical traumatic stress in injured children. </outcome>
      <timepoint>The psychosocial care survey will be completed by both the intervention and control groups at the following time points:
Baseline (pre-intervention)
1 week follow up (intervention group - 1 week post intervention; control group - 1 week post baseline)
1 month follow up (intervention group - 1 month post intervention; control group - 1 month post baseline)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dropout rate. 
The dropout rate will be assessed comparing the number of participants who complete the baseline measures to the number of participants who complete measures at the 1 week and 1 month follow up.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week follow up (intervention group - 1 week post intervention; control group - 1 week post baseline)
1 month follow up (intervention group - 1 month post intervention; control group - 1 month post baseline)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measures of Feasibility and Acceptability
Participants will be asked questions relating to the training. The feasibility and acceptability questionnaire designed for this study includes four multiple choice questions and two open answer questions to assess satisfaction with the intervention, perceived confidence in incorporating the training into practice following the intervention and perceived usefulness of the intervention.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week follow up (intervention group - 1 week post intervention) - (intervention group only)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Nurses and physicians working in emergency care in Australia and New Zealand, who are fluent in english and have access to the internet. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>There is no further exclusion criteria. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be determined to be eligible to participate in the trial via response to an online form indicating they meet inclusion criteria prior to being allocated to either the intervention or control group or providing additional demographic or baseline data. Following confirmation of eligibility the researcher can access the next allocation via a sealed opaque envelope. </concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomly assigned at 1:1 allocation using blocked randomization procedures with randomly permuted block sizes of 2, 4 and 6 the intervention group or a waitlist control group. The randomization sequence will be created using Stata 9.0 (StataCorp, College Station, TX) statistical software.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>An intention-to-treat analysis will be conducted (data from all randomised participants will be included in analysis; multiple imputation will be applied to account for missing data; post randomisation exclusions will only be applied to participants who dropout prior to baseline assessment and intervention).
To assess group differences in changes in emergency department staffs knowledge of paediatric medical traumatic stress across time points (i.e., pre-intervention, post-intervention, and 1 month follow-up),  analyses of variance (ANOVA) will be conducted.
To assess the feasibility and acceptability of this brief training to ED staff descriptive statistics will be conducted to examine responses to the 4 feasibility and acceptability questions. In addition a qualitative analysis of the themes of 2 free text questions will be conducted.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>18/04/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/09/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>71</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/10/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Eva Alisic</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Monash University Accident Research Centre
Monash University 
Clayton
Victoria 3800</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Research Training Program Scholarship,  Department of Education and Training </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Education and Training
GPO Box 9880
Canberra ACT 2601
Victoria</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Monash University, Faculty of Medicine, Nursing and Health Sciences</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>School of Psychological Sciences
Building 17
18 Innovation Walk
Monash University 
Wellington Road
Clayton
Victoria 3800</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Early Career Fellowship (#1090229), National Health and Medical Research Council </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Claire Hoysted </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Psychological Sciences
Building 17
18 Innovation Walk
Monash University 
Wellington Road
Clayton 3800
Victoria</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Laura Jobson</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Psychological Sciences
Building 17
18 Innovation Walk
Monash University 
Wellington Road
Clayton 3800
Victoria</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to  evaluate the short- and mid-term effects of a brief web-based intervention to increase emergency department staffs knowledge of paediatric medical traumatic stress. This training program is designed to educate emergency department staff on peadiatric medical traumatic stress following childhood injuries and detail trauma-informed care principles and strategies that can be used by emergency department staff to minimise distress and facilitate social support for these children and families.
Additionally, this study aims to assess the feasibility and acceptability of this web-based training program for ED staff.
All participants who complete participation receive a $30 gift voucher. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://www.trainingemergencycare.com</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Monash University Human Research Ethics Committee (MUHREC)
Room 111, Building 3e
Research Office, Monash University, Clayton, VIC, 3800
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/01/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2017-0626-10807</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/01/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Eva Alisic</name>
      <address>Monash University Accident Research Centre
Monash University
Clayton 3800
Victoria </address>
      <phone>+61 3 9905 4371</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Eva.Alisic@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Claire Hoysted</name>
      <address>School of Psychological Sciences, 
Monash University
Clayton 3800
Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61402772620</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>claire.hoysted@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Claire Hoysted </name>
      <address>School of Psychological Sciences, 
Monash University
Clayton 3800
Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61402772620</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>claire.hoysted@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Claire Hoysted </name>
      <address>School of Psychological Sciences, 
Monash University
Clayton 3800
Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61402772620</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>claire.hoysted@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>