<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336931">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/07/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/08/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000879965</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The HS-Troponin study: the effect of 5th generation versus 4th generation troponin-based care on patients with acute coronary syndromes(ACS).</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised clinical trial comparing the relative effects of high-sensitivity 5th generation troponin-based care versus 4th generation troponin-based-care in patients with a suspected acute coronary syndrome on clinical events (death, myocardial infarction, recurrent myocardial infarction, revascuarisation, bleeding, stroke) up to 12-months.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1121-5016</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute coronary syndromes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>High sensitivity 5th-generation Analytic-Sensitvity troponin T(hsTNT) is a blood assay used to refine the diagnostic sensivity of chest pain clinical pathways. It has a detection limit of down to 0.002 micrograms per litre with a 99th percentile of the upper reference limit observed at 0.014 micrograms per litre. It is measured at presentation for medical care and at 3 and 6 hours from baseline and is repeated following coronary revascularisation.</interventions>
    <comparator>4th-generation Analystic-Sensistivity troponin T (cTNT) is a blood assay used to refine the diagnostic sensivity of chest pain clinical pathways. It has a detection limit of 0.010 micrograms per litre with an unknown 99th percentile of the upper reference limit. However a level of 0.03 micrograms per litre is used to identify patients at elevated risk and a rise and/or fall of beyond 0.1 micrograms per litre to identify myocardial infarction. It is measured at presentation for medical care and at 3 and 6 hours from baseline and is repeated following coronary revascularisation.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cumulative composite endpoint of all cause mortality and new or recurrent acute coronary syndrome(ACS) measured beyond the first 24 hours of enrolment. All admissions will be evaluated for evolving ACS and myocardial infarction(MI) after admission using clinical assessment data and test results. All biomarker elevations will be referred for MI adjudication and assessed in a blinded manner to confirm time of criteria and timing of event.</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days, 6 months and 12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiovascular mortality from deprtment of health data linkage systems</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days, 6 months and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Unplanned hospital admission for: non-elective coronary revascularsiation, cerebrovascular accident, atrial or ventricular arrythmias, CCF without MI, peripheral revacsularistaion as documented by a hospital discharge summary or diagnosis related gorup report</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days, 6 months and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Significant bleeding using the GUSTO, TIMI and ACUITY definitions</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days, 6 months and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diagnostic test evaluation for: 
the temporal troponin release among patients with and without adjudicated index MI and ACS, assayed at baseline, 3 and 6 hrs after presentation.
Cardiovascular mortality
Index ACS</outcome>
      <timepoint>First 24 hours from presentation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health economic evaluation of participants:
In-hospital care from hospital cost data
Resource utilisation from medical benefits schedule(MBS) and pharmaceutical benefits scheme(PBS) data</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health economic evaluation of participants:
Health-related quality of life collectd by questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 30 days, 6 months and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Presenting to the emergency department with:
- Clinical features in whom the treating physician seeks to  measure the serum troponin level.
- Willing to give informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Patients with ST-segment elvation on the presenting ECG
- Inability to complete clinical history questionnaire due to language of co-morbidity.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>- Patients who have had a troponin test ordered will be approached for study information delivery and consent. 
- Consenting patients are then risk stratified according to Heart Foundation ACS risk strata. 
- The research coordinator selects from the appropriately labeled 'risk' box, the next numerically ordered sealed opaque envelope containing the randomisation allocation. This will be concealed from treating clinicians and study personnel in the following way:
each opaque envelope will contain 3 pre-printed pathology forms, each with the same coloured sticker in the top corner.</concealment>
    <sequence>The sample of 2000 patients will be randomised according to National Heart Foundation risk stratification sub-categories;
Suspected non-ST-segment elevation acute coronary syndrome with high risk features.
Suspected non-ST-segment elevation acute coronary syndrome with intermediate risk features.
Suspected non-ST-segment elevation acute coronary syndrome with low risk features.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>28/07/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>26/03/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>1937</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>Noarlunga Health Service - Noarlunga Centre</hospital>
    <postcode>5042</postcode>
    <postcode>5011</postcode>
    <postcode>5000</postcode>
    <postcode>5112</postcode>
    <postcode>5168 - Noarlunga Centre</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Flinders medical centre/Flinders clinical research</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>1 Flinders Dve
Bedford park SA 5041</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>South Australian Department of Health (SA health)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>8/45 Grenfell St
Adelaide
SA 5000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council:ID1024008</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>NH&amp;MRC, GPO Box 1421, Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A prospective, single-blind, multicentre, randomised clinical trial to evaluate the clinical impact and resource implications of the high-sensitvity troponin assay in the care of patients presenting with suspected ACS. The study will enroll 2000 patients presenting to an emergency department with clinical features in whom the treating physician seeks to measure serum troponin level. The study will be run across 5 metropolitan public hospitals in Adelaide, South Australia. Patients will be randomised to either the 4th generation or 5th generation troponin reporting system. Information will be collected on presenting chest pain characteristics. Clinical outcomes (death, new/re-MI, bleeding, stroke, revascularisation) including quality of life will be sought in-hospital and at 30 days, 6-months and 12-months and cost effectiveness will be measured at 12-months.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>None</trialwebsite>
    <publication>None</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Adelaide Clinical Human Research ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Ethics office
Room 2A221
Flinders Medical Centre
SA 5042</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/06/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1/11/0217</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/05/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Derek Chew</name>
      <address>Flinders Medical Centre, level 6, FPH, Department of Cardiology, 1 Flinders Dve Bedford Park SA 5042</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8404 2001</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8204 5625</fax>
      <email>derek.chew@flinders.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Carolyn Astley</name>
      <address>Flinders Medical Centre, level 6, FPH, Department of Cardiology, 1 Flinders Dve Bedford Park SA 5042</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8204 6061</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8204 5625</fax>
      <email>carolyn.astley@flinders.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Carolyn Astley</name>
      <address>Flinders Medical Centre, level 6, FPH, Department of Cardiology, 1 Flinders Dve Bedford Park SA 5042</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8204 6061</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8204 5625</fax>
      <email>carolyn.astley@flinders.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Derek Chew</name>
      <address>Deprtment of cardiology
Flinders Medical Centre
level 6, FPH
1 Flinders dve
Bedford Park SA 5042</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8404 2001</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>derek.chew@flinders.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>