<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363217">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/10/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/11/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001295730</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The importance of technique of reperfusion in liver transplantation</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The importance of the technique of reperfusion in liver transplantation: regulation of hepatic microcirculation and the pathophysiological role of endothelin-1 and stress inducible vasoactive mediators</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1136-5219</utrn>
    <trialacronym>MERP-TRANSPLANT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Patient undergoing liver Transplant</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Reperfusion technique in liver transplantation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The patients are randomised in two groups, simultaneous arterial and portal revascularization (SR group)  and Initial
 portal reperfusion (IPR).
In the IPR group the graft is revascularized through the portal vein, and the hepatic artery is subsequently performed.  In the SR group the graft is 
revascularized simultaneously through the portal vein, and hepatic artery. Both techniques are used in the clinical practice, it is based on the personal
 preference of the surgeon. There is no evidence that one technique of reperfusion is superior to another or harmful. However, there is a theoretical advantage
to the simultaneous technique.
A non-invasive device (called Sidestream Dark Field imaging), that allow for clinical observation of the microcirculation will be used 30 minutes after reperfusion. 
It is hand-held probe with a sterile extension for direct contact with target tissue. The objective of the device can be sterilized with a sterile cover and drape.
Sidestream Dark Field imaging uses the absorption of hemoglobin to visualize the microcirculation using a polarized light technique, as consequence it is 
completely safe. Sidestream Dark Field imaging is used at the end of reperfusion for 5 minutes
Blood sample for the serum assessment of ET-1 and other markers will be taken at indiction of anaesthesia amd post operative day 1-3-5-7.</interventions>
    <comparator>The patients are randomised in two groups, simultaneous arterial and portal revascularization (SR group)  and Initial
 portal reperfusion (IPR) which will be deemed as the control group.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To verify the optimal technique of reperfusion in liver transplantation.
Liver functional test, endothelia-1</outcome>
      <timepoint>liver functional test at Post operative day-1,3,-5,7.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mortality, prospectve data collection using custom made forms,</outcome>
      <timepoint>90 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>graft failure (defined as need for re-transplantation or patient death secondary to liver failure). </outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>patient candidate to Liver transplant at Royal prince alfred hospital   older than 18 years</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Split liver</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The patients are randomised in two groups, simultaneous arterial and portal revascularization (SR group)  and Initial
 portal reperfusion (IPR). Central randomization by computer software will be used.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using a randomisation table created by computer software. Patients stratified according the kind of donor used, Donor afer cardiac death versus brain dead donor</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australian national liver transplantation unit Royal prince alfred hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>missenden road
Camperdown NSW, 2050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian national liver transplantation unit, Royal prince alfred hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>missenden road
Camperdown NSW, 2050</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Fifty patients undergoing liver transplant will be included in the study. The participants will be randomized in two groups using a software application. In SR group, simultaneous portal vein and hepatic artery reperfusion, while in IPR group an initial portal reperfusion and the hepatic artery reperfusion is subsequently performed. Both techniques are used in the clinical practice, it is based on the personal preference of the surgeon the type of perfusion technique used. There is no evidence that one technique of reperfusion is superior to another or harmful.Data regarding preoperative variables, intraoperative and postoperative variables are prospectively collected. 
A non-invasive device (called Sidestream Dark Field imaging), that allow for clinical observation of the microcirculation will be used. 
It is hand-held probe with a sterile extension for direct contact with liver parenchyma.  
Liver biopsies are performed to assess Immunohystochemical intensity of ET-1 and other markers. The tissue to be acquired in this study will be obtained from surgical specimens taken from consented participants having routine hepatic surgery or  liver transplantation.
 The study additionally requires the provision of a blood sample for the serum assessment of ET-1 and other markers. This blood sample will be taken at the time of clinically indicated vensection. The risks involved in drawing blood from the arm include discomfort at the site of insertion of the needle and possible bruising/swelling around the injection site. There is a very rare risk of infection. There is also a remote possibility of fainting while blood is being drawn.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethic review committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Royal prince alfred Hospital
Camperdown NSW 2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/03/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>hrec/12/rpah/528</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>31/10/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Carlo Pulitano</name>
      <address>royal prince alfred hospital
Missenden road
transplant unit
Camperdown 2050, NSW</address>
      <phone>+61 458 003 482</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>carlo.pulitano@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Carlo Pulitano</name>
      <address>royal prince alfred hospital
Missenden road
transplant unit
Camperdown 2050, NSW</address>
      <phone>+61 458 003 482</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>carlo.pulitano@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Carlo Pulitano</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+61 458 003 482</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>carlo.pulitano@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Carlo Pulitano</name>
      <address>Royal prince alfred hospital
Missenden road
transplant unit
Camperdown 2050, NSW</address>
      <phone>0458003482 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>carlo.pulitano@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>