<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370739">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/05/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/06/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000722493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparing self-reported speed of eating with an objective measure of eating rate.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparing self-reported speed of eating with an objective measure of eating rate in healthy young adults.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1183-5035</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Eating rate</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The time to eat a lunch meal will be recorded on three occasions. Each meal will weigh 550g. The composition of the meals will differ with the proportion of starchy carbohydrate and non-starchy vegetables . The starchy carbohydrate will be rice or penne pasta. The composition of the meals are: Stir-fried beef (100g); Dolmio pasta sauce (100g); white rice or penne pasta (100g); and mixed vegetables (250g). Stir-fried beef (100g); Dolmio pasta sauce (100g); white rice or penne pasta (150g); and mixed vegetables (200g). Stir-fried beef (100g); Dolmio pasta sauce (100g); white rice or penne pasta (200g); and mixed vegetables (150g). 

The washout will be one week. Participants will be asked to arrive having fasted for a minimum of 2.5 hour. </interventions>
    <comparator>Participants will self-report on their general eating habits using a previously published validated eating habits questionnaire (Stunkard AJ, Messick S. The three-factor eating questionnaire to measure dietary restraint, disinhibition and hunger. Journal of Psychosomatic Research. 1985;29(1):71-83).
Self-reported speed of eating will be specifically assessed using a previously published question (Sasaki S, Katagiri A, Tsuji T, Shimoda T, Amano K. Self-reported rate of eating correlates with body mass index in 18-y-old Japanese women. Int J Obes (Lond). 2003;27(11):1405-10).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of subjective (self-reported) and objective (timed) eating rate. The subjective rate will be self-reported using a previously published question (Sasaki S, Katagiri A, Tsuji T, Shimoda T, Amano K. Self-reported rate of eating correlates with body mass index in 18-y-old Japanese women. Int J Obes (Lond). 2003;27(11):1405-10). The objective eating rate will be determined by the investigator recording the time taken to eat each meal. As each person consumes a meal on three occasions, the average time taken (minutes) will be calculated. </outcome>
      <timepoint>The questionnaire regarding self-reported eating rate will be administered at baseline and then again two weeks after the completion of the last meal.

Objective eating rate will be measured on three occasions: after baseline at one week intervals thereafter.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of eating (g/min): The amount a participant consumes at the lunch meal will be divided by the meal duration to determine grams of food eaten per minute.

A digital clock will be used to determine start and stop times of all participants. These times will be recorded to the nearest second to determine meal duration. The start and stop points will be defined as when food first enters the participants mouth, and when the participant swallows their last mouthful. Participants will be unaware of their meal duration and eating rate being recorded. </outcome>
      <timepoint>The start and stop points are defined as when food first enters the participants mouth, and when the participant swallows their last mouthful. Each of the three meals, seperated by one week, will be timed.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of meal: The start and stop points of eating will be recorded by the researcher when food first enters the participants mouth and when the participant swallows their last mouthful. The duration of the meal (in minutes and seconds) will be calculated as the difference between the start and stop times. </outcome>
      <timepoint>The duration of meal will be measured on three occasions: after baseline at one week intervals thereafter.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>University students</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>People with special dietary requirements that we cannot cater to</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>2/03/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>4/03/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>78</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Otago</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Otago</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Human Nutrition
PO Box 56
Dunedin
9054</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Otago</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Human Nutrition
PO Box 56
Dunedin
9054</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Self-reported eating rate is commonly used on a population level to show associations between eating rate and health-risks/non-communicable diseases. However, there is little to suggest the applicability of self-reported eating rate in a clinical setting, as well as, clear clarification as to what is fast and slow eating and at which rates do these risks occur. The primary objective of this study was to compare objective eating rate with self-reported eating rate to establish the applicability of self-reported eating rate in a clinical setting. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Otago Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Department of Human Nutrition
PO Box 56
Dunedin
9054</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/02/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>14/204</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/02/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Bernard Venn</name>
      <address>Department of Human Nutrition
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin
9054</address>
      <phone>+6434795068</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bernard.venn@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Bernard Venn</name>
      <address>Department of Human Nutrition
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin
9054</address>
      <phone>+6434795068</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bernard.venn@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Bernard Venn</name>
      <address>Department of Human Nutrition
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin
9054</address>
      <phone>+6434795068</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bernard.venn@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>