<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336456">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/01/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/01/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000092998</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Randomized clinical trial investigating effects of a multi-nutrient combination on mood, stress, sleep and cognition in healthy young adults</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomized clinical trial investigating effects of a multi-nutrient combination on mood, stress, sleep and cognition in healthy young adults</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cognitive Function</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cerebral Blood Flow</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Stress</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Sleep quality</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Oxidative Stress</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Swisse Women's Ultivite Multi-Vitamin Mineral &amp; Anti-Oxidant with Herbs Formula 1 Dietary Supplement (ARTG Entry 134520) is taken by 40 women, and placebo is taken by 40 women.  Swisse Men's Ultivite Multi-Vitamin Mineral &amp; Anti-Oxidant with Herbs Formula 1 Dietary Supplement (ARTG Entry 134521) is taken by 40 men, and placebo is taken by 40 men.  There are hence four treatment groups in total.  For all treatment groups 1xTablet is taken daily over a 4 month (16 week) period.  A subset of participants (20 females receiving placebo and 20 females receiving Ultivite, as well as 20 males receiving placebo and 20 males receiving Ultivite) will be given mobile phones for weekly cognitive and mood testing from home.  Another subset of participants (20 females receiving placebo and 20 females receiving Ultivite, as well as 20 males receiving placebo and 20 males receiving Ultivite) will have EEG/SST brainwave recording at each of the study visits baseline, 2 months and 4 months.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo, is identical to the active treatments in terms of taste and appearance, but does not contain any of the active ingredients</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>General Health Questionnaire (GHQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 months, 4 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Other cognitive tasks:
Swinburne University Cognitive Ageing Battery (SUCCAB)
Purple Multitasking Framework
Arrow Flankers</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 months, 4 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mood/Stress questionnaires:
Profile of Mood States (POMS)
Bond-Lader Visual Analogue Scales - subjective measure of mood and alertness
Visual Analogue scales for Stress, Concentration, Fatigue (Mental/Physical) and Anxiety
State Anxiety (STAI)
Occupational Stress Inventory (OSI)
Chalder Fatigue Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 months, 4 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cerebral Blood flow (using transcranial doppler ultrasound) and Artierial Stiffness (using Sphygmocor)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 months, 4 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood measures:
Homocysteine, Cytokines, C-Reactive Protein, Brain Derived Neurotrophic Factor (BDNF), Telomere Length, Total Triglycerides, High-density Lipoprotein (HDL), Low-Density Lipoprotein (LDL).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 months, 4 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 months, 4 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Saliva Cortisol - measure of chronic stress</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 months, 4 months (4 measurements taken on the day preceeding each study visit to track diurnal changes in cortisol secretion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive Tests on Mobile Phones</outcome>
      <timepoint>A subset of participants (40 females and 40 males) will take home mobile phones and complete cognitive and mood tests once a week (16 timepoints in total).
The cognitive tests include:  Serial Sevens, Little Man (mental rotation) and Associative Learning.  The mood scales include the Bond-Lader Visual-Analogue scale as well as visual analogue scales of Stess, concentration, fatigue (mental/physical) and anxiety.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Steady State Probe Topography (SST) brainwave recording.</outcome>
      <timepoint>A subset of pariticipants (40 females and 40 males) will have their brainwaves (EEG) recorded using the SST electrophysiological recording technique.  This will occur at baseline, 2 months and 4 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Healthy non-smoking males and females aged between 25 and 45 years.

2.	Currently in at least part-time employment and/or a student in higher education or TAFE.

3.	No history of anxiety, depression, psychiatric disorders or epilepsy 

4.	No history of / do not currently suffer from heart disease or high blood pressure or diabetes.

5.	Not taking any medication, herbal extracts, vitamin supplements or illicit drugs which might reasonably be expected to interfere with cognition or mood for 4 weeks prior to (and duration of) study.

6.	Not taking any form of medication within 5 days of admission (except for prophylactic antibiotics, or other routine medications to treat benign conditions, such as antibiotics to treat acne) and agree not to take any medication throughout the study

7.	No health conditions that would affect food metabolism including the following: food allergies, kidney disease, liver disease and/or gastrointestinal diseases (e.g. Irritable bowel syndrome, coeliac disease, peptic ulcers)

8.	Not pregnant or possibility of being pregnant

9.	No hearing impairment 

10.	Not allergic to gluten/wheat 

11.	Are willing and able to participate in all scheduled visits, treatment plan, dietary restrictions, tests and other trial procedures according to the protocol. Also comfortable with computers.

12.	Are willing to provide blood samples throughout the testing phases

13.	Understand the rating scales and computer tests (as judged by the study coordinator)

14.	Provide a personally signed and dated informed consent indicating that the participant has been informed of all pertinent aspects of the trial.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>25</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Cigarette smoker

2.	Heavy drinker of alcohol (averages more than 2 standard drinks per day). 

3.	Diagnosis of Type 1 or Type 2 diabetes 

4.	History of anxiety, depression, psychiatric disorders or epilepsy

5.	History of / currently suffers from heart disease or high blood pressure.

6.	Evidence or history of any clinically significant (in the judgment of the investigator) renal, endocrine, pulmonary, gastrointestinal, cardiovascular, psychiatric, neurological, within the last 5 years

7.	Use of any over-the-counter herbal extracts, vitamin supplements and/or other dietary supplements which might influence cognition or mood for four weeks prior to the practice day

8.	Currently taking any illicit drugs and/or a history of substance abuse.

9.	Health conditions that would affect food metabolism including the following: food allergies, kidney disease, liver disease and/or gastrointestinal diseases (e.g. have Irritable bowel syndrome, peptic ulcers)

10.	Pregnant or possibility of being pregnant

11.	Allergy to gluten/wheat

12.	Hearing impairment

13.	Are not willing to provide blood samples throughout the testing phases

14.	Current participation in any other trials involving investigational or marketed products within 30 days prior to the practice day.

15.	History of head injury/stroke

16.	Any clinically relevant abnormalities in a volunteers medical history, physical examination, or results of laboratory tests.

17.	Currently taking Warfarin</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will respond to advertisements and pass a phone screen before coming in for their screening and enrolment.  Participants will be allocated a participant number that will be assigned to a treatment code.  Participants in male and female groups will be randomly allocated to either active or placebo using a computerised random number generator.  The products used in this study will be coded A and B for females or C and D for males.  The person who determined if a participant was eligible for inclusion in the trial was unaware, when this decision was made, to which group the participant would be allocated.  Allocation was concealed by numbered containers.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be allocated a participant number that will be assigned to a treatment code.  Participants in male and female groups will be randomly allocated to either active or placebo using a computerised random number generator.The products used in this study will be coded (A, B, C and D).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This is a chronic, placebo-controlled, double-blind, randomized, single centre, clinical trial with 2 treatment groups for females:  Women's Ultivite F1 or placebo, and 2 treatment groups for males:  Men's Ultivite F1 or placebo.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>160</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Swisse Vitamins Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>36-38 Gipps Street
Collingwood, Victoria, 
3066</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Swisse Vitamins Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>36-38 Gipps Street
Collingwood, Victoria, 
3066</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Participants attend Swinburne University Hawthorn for one practice visit where they go through the screening questions and provide informed consent.  They also practice all cognitive and mood tasks that they will be doing on their subsequent testing sessions.  They are then randomised to receive either the multivitamin treatment or placebo for 4 months.  Participants come in for 3 testing sessions, the first one week later (V1), the second 2 months later (V2) and the third and final visit after 4 months (V3).  At each testing session they complete congitive and mood assessments, together with blood flow, arterial stiffness, saliva cortisol, sleep quality and blood biomarker assessments.  A subset of participants (40 males and 40 females) will also complete weekly cognitive and mood tests from home using mobile phones provided.  Another subset of participants (40 males and 40 females) will also complete Steady State Probe Topography (SST) brainwave recording at Baseline, V2 and V3.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Swinburne University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 218
Hawthorn VIC 3122</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/12/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>SUHREC 2010/261</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Andrew Pipingas</name>
      <address>Centre for Human Psychopharmacology,  Room 10.13, Advanced Technologies Centre (ATC) 427-451 Burwood Rd, Hawthorn, Victoria, 3122</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9214-5215</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>apipingas@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Andrew Pipingas</name>
      <address>Centre for Human Psychopharmacology,  Room 10.13, Advanced Technologies Centre (ATC) 427-451 Burwood Rd, Hawthorn, Victoria, 3122</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9214-5215</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>apipingas@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr David Camfield</name>
      <address>Centre for Human Psychopharmacology,  Room 10.09, Advanced Technologies Centre (ATC) 427-451 Burwood Rd, Hawthorn, Victoria, 3122</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)412 008 578</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>david.camfield@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>