<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="81598">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/09/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/09/2006</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000406505</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Clinical efficacy of Moxifloxacin in the treatment of Bacterial Keratitis: A Randomised Clinical Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Clinical efficacy of Moxifloxacin in the treatment of Bacterial Keratitis: A Randomised Clinical Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Bacterial Keratitis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>To determine clinical efficacy and safety for topical moxifloxacin (1.0%) in patients treated with bacterial keratitis. A comparison will be made to patients treated with topical ofloxacin (0.3%) or topical fortified tobramycin  (1.33%)/cephazolin(5%). After corneal specimens are obtained, the assigned study medication is to be instilled every hour day and night for 48 hours and on the third day every hour by day and every two hours at night.  For days four and five one drop every two hours by day and every four hours at night and for days six and seven one drop every four hours. After day seven, the antibiotic is to be tapered to six hourly and stopped when when the ulcer has healed.</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess efficacy and safety of moxifloxacin (1.0%) in patients treated with bacterial keratitis. A comparison will be made to patients treated with topical ofloxacin (0.3%) or topical fortified tobramycin  (1.33%)/cephazolin(5%).  

A patient is to be evaluated for efficacy if they have completed the study as planned (i.e., treated for the length of time necessary for the ulcer to heal) or if they are considered a treatment failure.  A patient is defined as a treatment failure if their corneal ulcer does not respond, necessitating a change in therapy. Patient data is also eligible for analysis of efficacy if the study eye had a culture positive for bacterial organisms at the initial visit. Fungal, viral and acanthamoeba infections are not to be evaluated for efficacy. These cases are to be evaluated for safety only.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Examination finding are recorded on days 2, 4, 7, 14, and &gt;16. A final follow-up examination is scheduled for between 2 and 3 months after commencement of treatment. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary efficacy variables include the number of days of therapy required and  required healing time until the ulcer is cured. Cured is defined as no evidence of active bacterial infection, wound healing (re-epithelialisation) complete, i.e. absence of macropunctate staining, and inflammation resolved.</outcome>
      <timepoint>A clinical sign score summarizing the keys signs from the biomicroscopic examination on days 2, 4, 7, 14, and &gt;1 will be used as a secondary measure of efficacy. The sign score is the sum of the severity grading (0, 1, 2 or 3) of the following features: erythema swelling, conjunctival discharge, bulbar conjunctival injection, superficial punctuate keratopathy, intensity of infiltration, maximal depth of stromal loss and anterior chamber reaction (cells and flare).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients at least one year of age, of any race and either sex.Have a diagnosis of bacterial keratitis based on clinical observation.Must be able to understand and sign an informed consent form that has been approved by the Human Research and Ethics Committee.  If the patient is under 18 years of age, the informed consent must be understood and signed by the patients legally authorized representative (parent or guardian).Must agree to comply with the visit schedule and other requirements of the study.  The parent or guardian must agree to ensure compliance of patients less than 18 years of age.If patients have an infection in both eyes, then only one will be treated with the study medication.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>1</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Known allergy to fluoroquinolones, aminoglycosides, penicillins, cephalosporins or benzalkonium chloride.Pregnant females.Patients under 1 year of age.Suspected fungal, viral (e.g. Herpes simplex) or Acanthomoeba infection based on clinical observation.Patients to be treated with subconjunctival injection(s) of antibiotic(s).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Bottle(s) of the assigned drug(s) will be issued by patient number according to a simple randomisation by using a computer generated randomised code.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Subjects will be blinded within this study</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>9/10/2002</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>229</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Centre for Eye Research Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname> Alcon Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Centre for Eye Research Australia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To determine the clinical efficacy and safety of moxifloxacin (1.0%) in patients treated with bacterial keratitis compared with patients treated with ofloxacin (0.3%) or fortified tobramycin (1.33%)/cephazolin (5%).</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Human Research Ethics Committee of the Royal Victorian Eye and Ear Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>02/473H</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Grant Snibson</name>
      <address>32 Gisborne St East Melbourne, VIC</address>
      <phone>03 9929 8434</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gsnibson@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Marios Constantinou</name>
      <address>32 Gisborne St East Melbourne VIC</address>
      <phone>03 9929 8434</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mariosc@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>