<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371360">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/09/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001208493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy of umeclidinium bromide and vilanterol (UMEC/VI) for the slowing of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) development in smokers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Continuous maximal bronchodilatation with UMEC/VI as first line treatment for smokers at risk of developing COPD</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>The ECOS Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Umeclidinium bromide 62.5mcgs with vilanterol 25 mcgs (Anoro) via Ellipta (inhalation), once daily for 12 months. Adherence will be monitored by empty drug returns. </interventions>
    <comparator>Matched placebo via Ellipta, once daily for 12 months. The placebo is a white free flowing powder composed of lactose monohydrate blended with magnesium stearate to match the umeclidinium inhalation powder.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of decline of FEV1 (expressed as mls/year), measured by spirometry, during and at the end of a 12 month intervention on active study treatment or placebo</outcome>
      <timepoint>Visits are conducted at 0, 6 and 12 months. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline to 12 months in small airway function as measured by the forced oscillation technique (FOT).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Visits are conducted at 0, 6 and 12 months. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline to 12 months in ventilation heterogeneity by using the multiple breath nitrogen washout (MBNW) method</outcome>
      <timepoint>Visits are conducted at 0, 6 and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline to 12 months in lung volume as measured by assessing lung diffusing capacity for carbon monoxide (DLCO).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Visits are conducted at 0, 6, and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the effect of bronchodilators on symptoms using the breathlessness, cough, and sputum scale (BCSS) over 12 months.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Visits are conducted at 0, 6, and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess differences in reported adverse events between the intervention and placebo treatment groups over 12 months of treatment. Only information on the following adverse events will be collected by medical examination or participant self-report: dry mouth, visual difficulty/blurred vision, palpitations and cardiac events, tremor, pneumonia and upper respiratory tract infections, urinary symptoms or allergic reactions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Visits are conducted at 0, 6 and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Aged 25-45 years
2. Current and continuing smoker
3. History of 10-25 pack years tobacco exposure
4. Normal post-bronchodilator spirometry (FEV1&gt;80% pred, FEV1/FVC&gt;70%) or GOLD Stage 1 (FEV1&gt;80% pred, FEV1/FVC&lt;70%)
5. Abnormal multiple breath nitrogen washout (MBNW) (Sacin, Scond or both derived from MBNW)
6. Willingness and ability to give written informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>25</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Unable to perform the tests
2. Have had lung surgery
3.Currently have asthma, defined as a doctor diagnosis of asthma and current symptoms i.e. within 12 months prior to screening
4. Regularly used respiratory preventer/controller medication in the past 5 years
5. Have required frequent use of bronchodilator in the last 5 years (on average&gt;once/week)
6. Have bronchiectasis
7. Have had heart failure
8. Have uncontrolled/unstable arrhythmia
9. Have an upper or lower respiratory tract infection within 6 weeks of screening
10. Cease smoking at the time of the smoking cessation intervention 
11. Taking any respiratory medications or other regular medications that could affect respiratory function
12. Regularly smoke tetrahydrocannabinol (THC) &gt;= once/week
13. Considered unlikely to be able to adhere to taking study medication over the full 12 months of the treatment period </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The allocation sequence will be by sequentially numbered, opaque, sealed envelopes and will be generated by the data management team at The George Institute for Global Health</concealment>
    <sequence>Patients will be allocated to treatment (placebo or active study drug) using computer-generated random numbers. There will be no stratification.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/09/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>19/12/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>320</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal North Shore Hospital - St Leonards</hospital>
    <hospital>Concord Repatriation Hospital - Concord</hospital>
    <hospital>Campbelltown Hospital - Campbelltown</hospital>
    <hospital>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research - Glebe</hospital>
    <postcode>2065 - St Leonards</postcode>
    <postcode>2139 - Concord</postcode>
    <postcode>2560 - Campbelltown</postcode>
    <postcode>2037 - Glebe</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The George Institute for Global Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 5
1 King Street 
Newtown  
NSW  2042  
Australia </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>GlaxoSmithKline</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>82 Hughes Avenue
Ermington
NSW 2115</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Cigarette smoking produces inflammation in small airways and development of emphysema in about 20-40% of susceptible individuals. The presence of small airway pathology leads to uneven distribution of ventilation in the lungs as well as excessive airway closure which may produce excessive biomechanical stress leading to further progression of pathology. These changes produce a greater than the normal age-related rate of decline of lung function as measured by the FEV1 and this can lead to the clinical features of COPD. We hypothesise that:
1. The early pathological changes can be identified by tests derived from the multiple breath nitrogen washout (MBNW) and these tests may identify individuals at risk of developing COPD.
2. Bronchodilatation will reduce airway closure and normalise the distribution of ventilation thereby reducing biomechanical stress and may thus lead to reduction in the rate of decline of lung function.
The primary objective is to asses the rate of decline of FEV1 during and at the end of a 12 month intervention with or without active study treatment.
The secondary objective is to assess the change from baseline in small airway function and ventilation heterogeneity, change in FOT, and the effect of bronchodilators on spirometry, DLCO and BCSS symptoms.
The study is a double-blind, placebo controlled, parallel design study comparing:
1. Umeclidinium bromide with vilanterol (Anoro) via the Ellipta dry powder inhalation device at a dose of 62.5mcg/25mcg once daily with
2. Matched placebo once daily
A total of 320 participants will be randomised from four centres in NSW, Australia. Subject will attend clinic visits at screening, randomisation, 26 weeks and 52 weeks. Monthly telephone calls will be made to each participant to record adverse events, concomitant medications, adherence to medication and current smoking status.
Study measurements will include spirometry pre and post bronchodilator, body plethysmography to measure lung volumes and DLCO, MBNW, FOT and BCSS symptoms.

The student t-test will be used to compare the annual rate of decline of the FEV1 between the active treatment and placebo groups. Statistical methods for analysing the secondary outcomes will be by a linear regression model adjusted for baseline measurements if applicable.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Sydney Local Health District</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Office
Kolling Building, Level 13
Royal North Shore Hospital
Reserve Road
St Leonards
NSW 2065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/03/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/HAWKE/489</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/11/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Christine Jenkins</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health
Level 5, 1 King Street 
Newtown  NSW  2042  Australia </address>
      <phone>+61 2 8052 4300</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christine.jenkins@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Francesca Tang</name>
      <address>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research
The University of Sydney
431 Glebe Point Road
Glebe
NSW2037</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9114 0400</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>smokers@woolcock.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Christine Jenkins</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health
Level 5, 1 King Street 
Newtown  NSW  2042  Australia </address>
      <phone>+61 2 8052 4300</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christine.jenkins@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Allison Humphries</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health
Level 5, 1 King Street 
Newtown  NSW  2042  Australia </address>
      <phone>+61 2 8052 4383</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ahumphries@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>