<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="81883">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/02/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/01/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000024347</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The acceptability, safety and tolerability of combined methadone-naloxone in methadone maintained individuals aged between 18 - 65</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>To investigate the pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of orally administered methadone-naloxone in a 50:1 ratio in partcipants who are opioid dependant and methadone maintained individuals aged between 18- 65</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Participants are opiod dependant and methadone maintained individuals aged between 18-65</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A cross over design is used for the trial, therefore both the subjects and controls will recieve 14 days of their usual daily oral methadone dose, and 14 days of the daily oral study medication: Methadone-Naloxone in a ratio of 50:1 (0.1mg/ml). Participants will be randomly allocated to either recieve 14 days of their usual methadone dose first or the study medication; methadone-naloxone first.</interventions>
    <comparator>Methadone</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome measure is severity of opioid withdrawal symptoms.
Measured: Subjective opioid withdrawal scale  (SOWS)  
Measure: Objective opioid withdrawal scale  (OOWS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Research assessments will occur on day 0 and 2, and then twice weekly for the duration of the study prior to medication administration</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Craving 
measured: by mean difference in visual analogue scale scores</outcome>
      <timepoint>Twice weekly for the duration of the study prior to medication administration</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mood 
Measured: by mean difference in Profile Of Mood States (POMS) score</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 0, 13, 27</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Opioid Use:
Measured: by mean difference in days of self reported opioid use</outcome>
      <timepoint>Research assessments will occur on day 0 and 2, and then twice weekly for the duration of the study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intoxication 
Measured: by mean difference in Morphine-Benzedrine Group Scale (MBG)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Research assessments will occur on day 0 and 2, and then twice weekly for the duration of the study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Absorption
Measured: by mean difference in peak and trough ng/ml of racemic methadone</outcome>
      <timepoint>Research assessments will occur on day 0 and 2, and then twice weekly for the duration of the study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sleep quality
Measured: by mean difference in Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index score</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 13, 27</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Constipation
Measured: by mean difference in number of bowel movements</outcome>
      <timepoint>Research assessments will occur on day 0 and 2, and then twice weekly for the duration of the study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria> Opioid dependent clients;
 In treatment for greater than 2months
 Stabilised on current dose for greater than 4 weeks
 Willing to remain on current dose for duration of the trial
 Venous access
 Able to provide voluntary informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria> Considered unwilling, unable or unlikely to comply with the study protocol
 Lactating and pregnant women
 Active psychotic illness</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>centralised by fax</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation. The sequence will be generated by drawing slips of paper from an envelope</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The subjects, researcher, therapist and data analyst are blind in the study.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Pharmacokinetics / pharmacodynamics</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>10</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>2010</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Langton Centre</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Surry Hills</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Biomed Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Auckland</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The acceptability, safety and tolerability of combined methadone-naloxone:
Is oral methadone-naloxone indistinguishable from mono-methadone?  Does injection of methadone-naloxone precipitate withdrawal?

Robert Graham, Suzanne Rizzo, Kristy Korompay, James Bell

Introduction:  Daily methadone and buprenorphine dosing is associated with high costs and rigidity. Maintenance models that predominantly employ dispensed medication (i.e. unsupervised dosing) may be more cost effective and preferable to clients and health departments. However, takeaway doses are often used in unintended ways including being injected by the client or other persons. The addition of naloxone to methadone has the potential to discourage the diversion of takeaway doses. 
Aims: To ascertain the safety and tolerability of oral methadone-naloxone in a 50:1 ratio by investigating aspects of its pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic properties, and in a second study, to investigate the effectiveness of the combination in precipitating withdrawal when administered intramuscularly.
Methods: A randomised phase II study, double-blind, crossover design was used for the oral study. 10 subjects attending methadone clinics who were on a stable dose of least 20mg methadone volunteered and were given either methadone-naloxone or methadone alone for 14 days and then switched to the alternative for a total of 28 day study period. The second study was a Phase II, single group before-after design. Five of the subjects from the first study were administered IM saline solution followed by IM 10mg methadone/0.2mg naloxone prior to their scheduled methadone dose and were observed for 60 minutes. In the absence of objective signs of withdrawal at 30 minutes, participants were administered an additional 20mg methadone/0.4mg naloxone intramuscularly and observed for a further 60 minutes.

Findings: Oral methadone naloxone in a 50:1 ratio appeared to be well tolerated.
The same preparation reliably precipitated opioid withdrawal upon injection among methadone maintained individuals.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>N/A</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Australasian Professional Society for Alcohol and Drugs (APSAD) Conference, November 2007 Auckland New Zealand</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Langton Centre</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/06/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>05/270</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Anni Ryan</name>
      <address>The Langton Centre
591 South Dowling St
Surry Hill 2010</address>
      <phone>9332 8777</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>anni.ryan@sesiahs.health.nsw.gov</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Anni Ryan</name>
      <address>The Langton Centre
591 South Dowling St
Surry Hill 2010</address>
      <phone>9332 8777</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>anni.ryan@sesiahs.health.nsw.gov</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>James Shearer</name>
      <address>591 South Dowling Street
Surry Hills NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>02 9332 8777</phone>
      <fax>02 9332 8700</fax>
      <email>james.shearer@sesiahs.health.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>