<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369216">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/08/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/09/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000964516</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The six minute walk test in pregnant women and in women of childbearing age  a reference range study </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The six minute walk test in pregnant women and in women of childbearing age  a reference range study </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1173-7990</utrn>
    <trialacronym>6MWT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pregnancy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the cardiovascular system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Six Minute Walk Test, conducted as specified by the National Heart Foundation of Australia, with two walk tests performed and this should take a maximum of 30 min to complete including the breaks. </interventions>
    <comparator>N/A</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>This will be metres walked in six minutes (average of two tests with a 15 minute break to allow for return to baseline values  this will be confirmed by return to baseline heart rate).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of the second six minute walk test completion</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure (BP) measured by automatic blood pressure device</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the beginning and the end of the second six minute walk test</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Oxygen saturation (SpO2) measured by a pulse oximeter</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the beginning and the end of the six minute walk test</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Heart rate measured by the pulse oximeter</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the beginning and the end of the six minute walk test</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rating of Perceived Exertion (RPE) Category Scale (actual and expected) measured by answering questions to a structured questionnaire - National Heart Foundation of Australia</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of the six minute walk test </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Numerical value on dyspnoea scale (actual and expected) National Heart Foundation of Australia </outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of the six minute walk test</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Respiratory rate measured by counting the participants respiratory rate in 20 seconds and multiplying by 3</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the beginning and end of the 6 minute walk test</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy pregnant nulliparous women will be defined as American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) Classification I or II, with no significant medical or surgical illnesses, and aged 18 - 40 years. Second trimester women will be recruited from 140 to 236 weeks gestation. Term pregnant women will be recruitment from 360 weeks gestation until delivery. Healthy non-pregnant nulliparous women will be defined as American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) Classification I or II, with no significant medical or surgical illnesses, and aged 18 - 40 years.
 a. Women less than 24 weeks pregnant will be included if body mass index is less than or equal to 32 kg/m2 at the time of the study
b. Women equal to or greater than 36 weeks pregnant will be included if body mass index is less than 35 kg/m2 at the time of the study
c. Non-pregnant women will be included if body mass index is equal to or less than 30 kg/m2 at the time of the study
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any woman with pre-existing conditions that limit ability to exercise (joint, muscle, bone, neurological), pre-existing or gestational diabetes, pre-existing or pregnancy acquired cardiovascular disease, multiple pregnancy, smokers, any woman in labour or postpartum and inability to consent to study.

 a. Women less than 24 weeks pregnant will be excluded if body mass index is greater than 32 kg/m2 at the time of the study
b. Women equal to or greater than 36 weeks pregnant will be excluded if body mass index equal to or greater than 35 kg/m2 at the time of the study
c. Non-pregnant women will be excluded if body mass index is greater than 30 kg/m2 at the time of the study

</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Data presentation and analysis: Demographic and obstetric data will be displayed as mean and standard deviation, median with interquartile ranges, or number and percentage as appropriate. Total distance walked and secondary end-points will be presented as mean and standard deviation and range.
Sample size: Regarding the sample size there are so few patients in the 20-40 age group in published studies and only one pregnancy study of 37 patients we have not performed a sample size calculation. We do not aim to compare the groups in this study. We aim to generate three independent sets of data and reference ranges.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>True</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype>Hours</followuptype>
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/11/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>16/12/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>500</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Women's Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Cape Town</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Royal Women's Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Locked Bag 300, Corner Grattan Street and Flemington Road, Parkville, Victoria, Australia 3052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Royal Women's Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Locked Bag 300, Corner Grattan Street and Flemington Road, Parkville, Victoria, Australia 3052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Chelsea &amp; Westminster Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>369 Fulham Rd, London SW10 9NH UK </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>United Kingdom</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Mowbray Maternity Hospital</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>12 Hornsey Rd, Mowbray 
Cape Town, 7700, South Africa 
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>South Africa</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This international multicentre prospective observational study, performed at the Royal Womens Hospital, Melbourne, Australia, and Chelsea &amp; Westminster Hospital, London, UK, and Mowbray Maternity Hospital, Cape Town, South Africa aims to determine the reference range for an exercise test, the six minute walk test, in healthy pregnant women and non-pregnant women of childbearing age. This test is commonly used in non-pregnant adults to determine cardiovascular fitness and as a prognostic test in adults with chronic medical conditions. Its utility has not been investigated in pregnant women. It is hoped that this study will provide the baseline data for further studies investigating the usefulness of this test in pregnant women and non-pregnant women of childbearing age. Specifically, the use of this test to predict women who will develop new onset hypertension in pregnancy, the use of this test as part of a pre-pregnancy exercise intervention program to reduce the likelihood of developing new onset hypertension in pregnancy, and the use of the test to quantify symptoms of fatigue and breathlessness in pregnancy.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Royal Women's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee (EC00259)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Locked Bag 300, Corner Grattan Street and Flemington Road, Parkville, Victoria, Australia 3052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/10/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/09/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Alicia Dennis</name>
      <address>The Royal Womens Hospital, 
Locked Bag 300, Corner Grattan Street and Flemington Road, Parkville, Victoria, Australia 3052
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8345 2000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alicia.dennis@thewomens.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Alicia Dennis</name>
      <address>The Royal Womens Hospital, 
Locked Bag 300, Corner Grattan Street and Flemington Road, Parkville, Victoria, Australia 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8345 2000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alicia.dennis@thewomens.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Alicia Dennis</name>
      <address>The Royal Womens Hospital, 
Locked Bag 300, Corner Grattan Street and Flemington Road, Parkville, Victoria, Australia 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8345 2000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alicia.dennis@thewomens.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Alicia Dennis</name>
      <address>The Royal Womens Hospital, 
Locked Bag 300, Corner Grattan Street and Flemington Road, Parkville, Victoria, Australia 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8345 2000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alicia.dennis@thewomens.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>