<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368380">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/09/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/09/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000995572</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Cardiac Rehabilitation and the 'active couch potato' phenomenon.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In cardiac patients attending a Phase II cardiac rehabilitation program does the active couch potato phenomenon exist and what effect does it have on health outcomes? An international collaboration approach.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1169-3409 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known.</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>coronary heart disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants attending a phase II (outpatient) cardiac rehabilitation program will be included in this study. The outpatient cardiac rehabilitation program involves exercise and education sessions (1 hour each), twice a week, for 6 weeks. Participants physical activity levels and sedentary behaviour will be observed over 7-days at the start and end of the cardiac rehabilitation program, and at 6 and 12 months after admission into the cardiac rehabilitation program. One of the core components of cardiac rehabilitation is to increase participants exercise capacity and physical activity levels, aiming to achieve the public health physical activity guidelines (150 minutes of moderate-to-vigorous physical activity per week). There is some  evidence in healthy adults that even if you achieve the physical activity guidelines, if you sit for too long, you are more likely to die from any cause (the active couch potato phenomenon). It is unknown if the active couch potato phenomenon exists in cardiac rehabilitation participants, and if it exists what effect this has on risk factors for heart disease. 

This is an observational study and eligible cardiac rehabilitation participants will be encouraged to adhere to the cardiac rehabilitation program, with no additional encouragement to change their physical activity and/or sedentary behaviour provided over the 12-month data collection period.</interventions>
    <comparator>Nil. Observational study.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity (accelerometry, Active Australia Survey)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sedentary behaviour (accelerometry, Past-Day Adults' Sedentary Time questionnaire)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body mass index (BMI). BMI (kg/m2) will be recorded using a calibrated set of scales and a stadiometer. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Waist-to-hip ratio (WHR).Waist circumference and hip circumferences will be measured in centimetres using a tape measure. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood triglycerides. Fasting blood samples will be taken from participants and will be analysed using the Abbott Architect Ci16200 system, according to the manufacturers guidelines. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood glucose level. Fasting blood samples will be taken from participants and will be analysed using the Abbott Architect Ci16200 system, according to the manufacturers guidelines. Each sample will be assessed for the glucose level. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure. Blood pressure levels will be obtained using a mercury sphygmomanometer on the right arm of seated subjects. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Exercise Capacity.The 6-minute walk test (6MWT) is a commonly used objective measure of functional exercise capacity in cardiac rehabilitation. The distance an individual is able to walk along a flat 25-30 m walkway over a 6 minute period, with breaks as required, is recorded. The test is a self-paced, submaximal test of exercise capacity, and has been found to have a moderate-to-high reliability and validity. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health-related quality of life. The MacNew questionnaire will be used for the assessment of heart disease specific health-related quality of life. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety. The Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale questionnaire will be used for the assessment of anxiety. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Total cholesterol. Fasting blood samples will be taken from participants and will be analysed using the Abbott Architect Ci16200 system, according to the manufacturers guidelines. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks, 6 and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>High-density lipoprotein- HDL. Fasting blood samples will be taken from participants and will be analysed using the Abbott Architect Ci16200 system, according to the manufacturers guidelines. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks, 6 &amp; 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Low-density lipoprotein. Fasting blood samples will be taken from participants and will be analysed using the Abbott Architect Ci16200 system, according to the manufacturers guidelines. Low-density lipoprotein will be determined using the Friedewald formula </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 week, 6 &amp; 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression. The Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale questionnaire will be used for the assessment of depression. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks, 6 &amp; 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Attending a phase II (outpatient) cardiac rehabilitation program, with stable coronary heart disease and receiving optimal medical treatment +/- revascularisation, that is, coronary artery bypass graft surgery, percutaneous transluminal coronary angioplasty or another transcatheter procedure, or have had a myocardial infarction</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants will be excluded if they have New York Heart Association class II-IV symptoms of heart failure (or documented signs and symptoms of chronic heart failure, with ejection fraction &lt; 45%), uncontrolled arrhythmias, severe chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, uncontrolled hypertension, symptomatic peripheral artery disease, unstable angina, uncontrolled diabetes, are unable to perform a submaximal walking test (6-minute walk test), or are unable to wear an accelerometer due to disability, for example, if they are confined to a wheelchair.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>The number of minutes per day spent in sedentary behaviour will be calculated using standard count-based intensity threshold values of counts per minute: &lt; 100 for sedentary behaviour (&lt;1.5 MET). Four further summary measures of sedentary behaviours will calculated per day and averaged over valid days: (a) percentage of the wear-day spent in sedentary behaviour (b) number of sedentary bouts (defined as a period of consecutive minutes where the accelerometer registered &lt;100 counts/minutes) (c) average duration of sedentary bouts and (d) number of sedentary breaks (defined as at least 1 min where the accelerometer registered &gt;= 100 counts/minute following a sedentary bout). The Freedson Combination energy expenditure algorithm will be used to determine the intensity cut-points for MVPA. This outcome variable will be used to investigate whether participants have reached the World Health Organisation physical activity guidelines. 
Linear regression models will be performed at each data collection point, where the dependent variables will be each of the health variables available. The models will have the different summary measures of sedentary behaviour (i.e. one model will be performed with each one) as main independent variables, and models will also be performed for MVPA and each of the different physical activity intensities (i.e. light, moderate and vigorous physical activity). If it is the case, quadratic trends might be explored. The models will be adjusted for total time of activity (i.e. counts per min &gt;= 100), gender, socioeconomics variables, BMI and other potential confounders available. 
Additional analyses will be completed with a one-way repeated measures analysis of variance (ANOVA) to test for differences in physical activity and sedentary behaviour (with a 95% confidence interval (CI)) within the Australian sample over 12 months. Intention-to-treat analysis will be used at 6-weeks, 6 and 12-months where data is missing, bringing the last value forward. A maximum of three attempts will be made to contact participants so outcome measures can be obtained, making the analysis more complete.

Sample size
The G*Power software v.3.1.9.2 was used to a priori determine the required sample size. Previous recommendations for sample size estimation in Multiple Linear Regression problems were used. With a desired effect size of f2 = 0.5 (large), given a maximum of 10 predictor variables including potential confounders, a sample size of n= 59 is needed to achieve a power of 0.95 in a test based on a = 0.05. Assuming a dropout rate of 25%, 75 participants will be recruited for the Australian study.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>28/09/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>15/02/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>75</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Canberra Hospital - Garran</hospital>
    <postcode>2605 - Garran</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Nicole Freene</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Canberra, University Drive, Bruce, ACT, 2617</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Canberra</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University Drive
Bruce, ACT, 2617</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Canberra Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Yamba Drive, Garran, ACT, 2605</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Borja del Pozo Cruz</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University of Auckland, Victoria Street West, Auckland 1142</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Prof Rachel Davey</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University of Canberra, University Drive, Bruce, ACT, 2617</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>One third of all heart attacks are repeat events. It is unknown whether the risk of having another cardiac event can be reduced by simply sitting less. We will assess sitting time, physical activity and the active couch potato phenomenon in those with heart disease attending cardiac rehabilitation (CR) over 12 months. We will assess the potential independent impact of these behaviours on the CR participants cardio-metabolic health, health-related quality of life, exercise capacity, anxiety and depression, both locally and internationally.  Outcomes will inform CR research, policy and practice and lead to better health outcomes for those with heart disease.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Nil currently</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>ACT Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Canberra Hospital, Yamba Drive, Garran, ACT, 2605</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>31/08/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>ETH.5.12.076</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/04/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nicole Freene</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy
University of Canberra
University Drive
Bruce
ACT 2617</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6201 5550</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nicole.freene@canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nicole Freene</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy
University of Canberra
University Drive
Bruce
ACT 2617</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6201 5550</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nicole.freene@canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nicole Freene</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy
University of Canberra
University Drive
Bruce
ACT 2617</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6201 5550</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nicole.freene@canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nicole Freene</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy
University of Canberra
University Drive
Bruce
ACT 2617</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6201 5550</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nicole.freene@canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>