<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371355">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001190493p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Device to aid in the administration of glyceryl tri-nitrate sublingual spray for patients with angina and impaired manual dexterity. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Adaptive study of prototype assistive angina spray device for patients with angina and a coexisting arthritic, neuromuscular or other disability.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1178-9034</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cardiac rehabilitation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Angina</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Arthritis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Neuromuscular disability</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The device used to facilitate the GTN spray has been called the GT'NHaler. The device is used to assist with the administration of glyceryl tri-nitrate sublingual spray in patients with angina and impaired manual dexterity caused by arthritic, neuromuscular or other disability. The device consists of a tube into which the GTN spray canister is inserted. A l lever attached .to the top of the device is used by the patient to provide downwards pressure to the top of the canister thereby activating administration of the GTN spray. The device will be used every time the participant's standard care glyceryl tri-nitrate sublingual spray is administered over the 1 month period of the study. The patient's use of the device and their opinions on its effectiveness and ease of use will be recorded in a questionnaire booklet. </interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Satisfaction with the device, assessed by a questionnaire designed specifically for this study.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>One month after starting using the device</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Difficulty using the device during the 1 month period of the study, assessed by a questionnaire designed specifically for this study.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>One month after starting using the device</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of participants who report not being able to use the device adequately, An inability to use the device will be defined as failure to use the device on two consecutive administrations of GTN spray in any given day. The number of consecutive failures over the 30 days of the trial will be counted. </outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month after the start of using the device</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Angina
Impaired manual dexterity that hinders administration of angina spray</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Inability or unwillingness to use the spray device</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Not applicable</concealment>
    <sequence>not applicable</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Not applicable</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Analysis of patient written responses in questionnaire.  No statistical power calculations were carried out as the study is a qualitative assessment of the GTN device, making statistical assumptions difficult to construct. The number of 20 subjects with 30 days of responses/observations (600 data points) was considered adequate to provide information that could be used to adapt or modify the GTN device. . </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 0</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/08/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/11/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Canterbury</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Via Innovations, </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>4th floor, 32 Oxford Tce
Christchurch 8011</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Via Innovations,</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>4th floor, 32 Oxford Tce
Christchurch 8011</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Not applicable</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is an adaptive study.  The objective is to field test a device for assisting with the administration of angina spray in patients who have difficulty using proprietary GTN spray devices and evolve the prototype based on this experience so that a final version can be produced. Firstly patients will be selected for the study because they have expressed difficulty using the proprietary GTN spray devices.  Alternatively they will have been observed to be experiencing difficulty using the devices.  The Christchurch Hospital cardiac rehabilitation programme or Arthritis Society will provide useful settings for these patients to be identified.  The cardiac rehabilitation programme provides aftercare for patients who have been in hospital having experienced a cardiac event for example myocardial infarction.  It is hoped that sufficient patients will be identified in this manner for a meaningful trial of the device to be undertaken.  If insufficient numbers of patients are identified an alternative avenue would be through General Practice.    Once identified, patients will be shown and instructed in the use of the device, and if they are interested in becoming part of the trial will be given a prototype device to use. Patients will be followed up to obtain their feedback about the use of the device, with information being sought on the ease of administration, durability, ease of changing to a new spray once expired or used up, and other issues that may arise.  Modifications to the device can then be made based upon feedback obtained..</summary>
    <trialwebsite>None</trialwebsite>
    <publication>None</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Freyberg Building
20 Aitken St
PO Box 5013
wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/08/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Arthur Collins</name>
      <address>Travis Medical Centre
225 Travis Road
Christchurch 8083</address>
      <phone>+64 27 3394095</phone>
      <fax>+64 3 3289223</fax>
      <email>cobrastarno@gmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Ruth Davison</name>
      <address>Department of Cardiology
Christchurch Hospital
2 Riccarton Ave
Christchurch Central 4710</address>
      <phone>+64 3 3641093  Ext 81093</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ruth.davison@cdhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Arthur Collins</name>
      <address>Travis Medical Centre
225 Travis Road
Christchurch 8083</address>
      <phone>+64 27 3394095</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cobrastarno@gmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Brett Shand</name>
      <address>30 Bay View Road
Moncks Bay
Christchurch 8081
</address>
      <phone>+64 220346400</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>shandbrett@gmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>