<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320487">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/09/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/09/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000793213</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Prevention of Depressive Symptoms in Children in a Rural Setting</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of a mental health promotion program, called Positive Thinking Skills, on depressive and anxiety symptomatology, attribution style, and social and emotional functioning in children aged 8 to 9 years of age in a rural setting.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Mental health promotion program, titled, Positive Thinking Skills. Consists of ten, 60 minute weekly sessions, taught in schools by regular school teachers. The program is based on cognitive and behavioural theories, and includes strategies to promote emotional competence, social and cognitive skills to prevent depression and anxiety. All activities are developmentally appropriate for 8  9 year olds. The lessons focus on identifying feelings in self and others, promoting awareness of a range of feelings and how they are expressed. Cognitive and behavioural skills will be taught using games, activities and role plays. The sessions include: Week 1 - confidentiality and group rules; Week 2: Identifying my Feelings; Week 3: Comfortable and Uncomfortable Feelings; Week 4: Feelings and Situations; Week 5: Catching Your Thoughts; Week 6: Being Brave; Week 7: Thought, Feeling Connection; Week 8: Helpful and Unhelpful Thinking; Week 9: Changing your Thoughts; Week 10: Self -Esteem and Being Brave.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual Care Condition, this being the delivery of the Western Australian Department of Education, Heatlh Curriculum</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 1: depression symptomatology as indicated by Mood and Feelings questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time-point: at baseline and immediately after the intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 2: anxiety symptomatology as indicated by Spence Children's Anxiety Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time-point: at baseline and immediately after the intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 3: attribution style as indicated by the Children's Attributional questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time-point: at baseline and immediately after the intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 1: social and emotional functioning as indicated by Strengths and Difficulties questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time-point: at baseline and immediately after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Children aged between 8 to 9 years of age and have received consent to participate from both parent/guardian and child; attending Wagin and Corrigin District High Schools, Western Australia.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>8</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>9</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>No exclusion criteria</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>The flip of a coin will be the method used to allocate the two schools in the control or intervention condition.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>29/07/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>72</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Curtin University of Technology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Kent Street, Bentley, WA, 6102, 
GPO Box U1987, Perth WA 6845</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to use an updated and more developmentally appropriate version of the Positive Thinking Skills Program to investigate the efficacy of the intervention amongst children aged 8-9 years old, in a rural setting. Rural areas have been identified to pose an increased risk of depression and other mental health problems (Kane, Day &amp; Roberts, 2000), and therefore this program will provide a valuable mental health prevention program in an identified area of need.  The program will be provided universally to children by their teachers and hence will avoid stigmatisation of children identified as at risk. This project is significant as it has the potential to impact upon the prevalence of depression amongst a much younger group of children (8- 9 years) than most of the current research demonstrates (Rooney, Roberts, Kane, Pike, Winsor, White &amp; Brown, 2006).  The potential prevention of internalising disorders in middle childhood may also result in a positive long term impact in various areas of a childs life such as family, peer relationships academic performance and recreational activities as well as a reduction of the risk of further episodes of depression in adolescence and adulthood (Kovacs &amp; Devlin, 1998).
Hypotheses
	It is predicted that the Positive Thinking Skills program will be associated with fewer depressive symptoms; improved social and emotional functioning; a more positive attiributional style and fewer anxiety symptoms.  
H1:	Compared to the control group, the intervention group will report lower levels of depressive symptomatology at post-test (as measured by the 	Mood and Feelings Questionnaire )
H2:	Compared to the control group, the intervention group will report                                higher levels of social and emotional functioning at post-test (as measured by the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire) 
H3:	Compared to the control group, the intervention group will report lower levels of anxiety symptomatology at post-test (as measured by the Spence Childrens Anxiety Scale) 
H4:	Compared to the control group, the intervention group will report a less 	pessimistic attribution style (as measured by the Childrens Attributional Questionnaire)</summary>
    <trialwebsite>nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin University Human Research Ethics Comittee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Kent Street, Bentley, WA, 6102, 
GPO Box U1987, Perth WA 6845</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/07/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HR63-2009</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Rosie Rooney</name>
      <address>GPO Box U1987, Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 3050,</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.rooney@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Clare Roberts</name>
      <address>GPO Box U1987, Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 7992,</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c.roberts@curtin.edu.au.</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Rosie Rooney</name>
      <address>GPO Box U1987, Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 3050,</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.rooney@curtin.edu.au,</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>