<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364286">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/06/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/06/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000636752</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Feasibility of an Australianised Mediterranean diet in healthy volunteers aged 65 years and older - MedLey Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Feasibility of an Australianised Mediterranean diet in healthy volunteers aged 65 years and older - MedLey Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>MedLey Pilot</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Nutrition and dietetics</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Volunteers will be recruited from a list of participants from previous trials who expressed their willingness to participate in future studies and through word of mouth. Volunteers who respond will be telephoned to participate in a screening questionnaire to determine eligibility and enrolled in the study. The study is comprised of 3 clinic visits. At the first visit, volunteers will provide consent and will have their weight and height measured. They will be asked to maintain their habitual diet for 1 week. During this week they will complete dietary quesitonnaires including a food frequency questionnaire and a 4 day weighed food record to collect dietary information including amount, frequency and portion size. At the end of this week volunteers will return to  the Nutritional Physiology Research Centre with their dietary questionnaires. Weight will be assessed.  Volunteers will then meet with the research dietitian for 30-45 minutes and the AusMed diet will be explained in detail. They will receive a resource pack which contains a menu guide, sample menu, fruit and vegetable lists, tips for eating out and recipe modification, a recipe book, as well as two weekly dietary checklists. The AusMed diet will be adjusted to meet energy needs and individual taste preferences. Volunteers will receive staple foods to aid with compliance. For the following 2 weeks, volunteers will follow the AusMed diet using the instructions provided. During this 2 week period volunteers will fill out a second weighed food record. After 2 weeks volunteers will return to the Nutritional Physiology Research Centre to return their dietary checklists and weighed food records. Weight will be measured a third time. Volunteers will be asked to fill in a second Food Frequency Questionnaire based on their intake over the last 2 weeks (i.e. while on the AusMed diet). Volunteers will be required to fill out a feasibility questionnaire, which will capture how the volunteers felt about adhering to the AusMed diet and any problems they encountered. This feasibility questionnaire will also assess the usefulness of the resource pack provided. </interventions>
    <comparator>N/A - this is a single group study</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acceptability of AusMed diet will be determined using a questionnaire developed by the researchers to specifically capture this information. This questionnaire captures information on satiety, how easy it was to follow, were there any difficulties faced with following the AusMed diet and the usefulness of provided resources such as the recipe book etc.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after particpants have completed 2 weeks of consuming the AusMed diet.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Satiety of AusMed diet will be determined using a questionnaire developed by the researchers to specifically capture this information. This questionnaire captures information on satiety, how easy it was to follow, were there any difficulties faced with following the AusMed diet and the usefulness of provided resources such as the recipe book etc.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after particpants have completed 2 weeks of consuming the AusMed diet.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Palatability of the AusMed diet using a questionnaire developed by the researchers to specifically capture this information. This questionnaire captures information on satiety, how easy it was to follow, were there any difficulties faced with following the AusMed diet and the usefulness of provided resources such as the recipe book.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after particpants have completed 2 weeks of consuming the AusMed diet.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ease of incorporation AusMed diet into an Australian lifestyle including cost, time of food preparation, ability to shop for and cook the foods recommended on the diet, will be determined using a questionnaire developed by the researchers to specifically capture this information. This questionnaire captures information on satiety, how easy it was to follow, were there any difficulties faced with following the AusMed diet and the usefulness of provided resources such as the recipe book etc.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after particpants have completed 2 weeks of consuming the AusMed diet.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nutrient intake compared to habitual diet will be assessed using a food frequency questionnaire and a 4 day weighed food record</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nutrient intake will be assessed at the end of the first week and then again at the end of the study at 3 weeks, following 2 weeks of consumption of the AusMed diet. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of dietary intake data between Food Frequency Questionanire and 4 day Weighed Food Record</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and then after 2 weeks of consumption of the AusMed diet.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Usefulness of resources provided including sample menu, recipe book, advice for eating out, and appropriateness of foods given using feedback obtained using a questionnaire developed by the researchers to specifically capture this information. This questionnaire captures information on satiety, how easy it was to follow, were there any difficulties faced with following the AusMed diet and the usefulness of provided resources such as the recipe book etc.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of the study at week 3.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Free living men and women, omnivorous, free of dementia and cognitive impairment, proficient in English, aged 65 years and above.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Person considered by the investigator to be unwilling, unlikely or unable to comprehend or comply with the study protocol
Actively undertaking a weight loss program
Use of appetite suppressants or Orlistat (Xenical)
Previous stroke
History of traumatic head/brain injury, neurological or psychiatric conditions
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Volunteers will be recruited from a list of participants from previous trials who expressed their willingness to participate in future studies, and through word-of-mouth. These participants will receive a letter in the mail, after which they will be contacted by phone or email. Volunteers who express interest will leave their contact details with the investigators. At a convenient time, the volunteer will be telephoned to participate in a screening questionnaire to determine eligibility. If eligible, volunteers will be informed over the phone and they will be enrolled in the study and allocated an ID code. Allocation is not concealed. </concealment>
    <sequence>NA</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Volunteers will maintain their habitual diet for 1 week then consume the AusMed diet for 2 weeks. </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>For dietary data, descriptive statistics will be peformed for nutrient intakes, and Cohen's D effect sizes calculated for mean intakes and survey responses. Paired sample t-tests will be performed for dietary data and survey data where Likert scales have been used. Statistical significance will be set at P = 0.05. Statistical analyses will be performed using SPSS for Windows (version 20.0; SPSS, Chicago, IL). 

10 volunteers with similar characteristics to the larger MedLey trial (ACTRN12613000602729) will be recruited to pilot test the AusMed diet. This is based on a similar study by Patch CS et al 20xx JADA.  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>27/05/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>27/05/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>10/06/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>31/05/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>10</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Karen Murphy (Chief Investigator)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of South Australia
GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of South Australia - Internal Project Grant Development scheme</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of South Australia
GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Janet Bryan</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University of South Australia
GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Prof Carlene Wilson</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Flinders University 
GPO Box 2100
Adelaide, SA 
5001</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Prof Jonathan Hodgson</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University of Western Australia
35 Stirling Highway
CRAWLEY WA 
6009</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a pilot study designed to test how easy it is to follow an Australianised Mediterranean Diet (AusMed diet) for 2 weeks. This includes an investigation into consumption of nutrients, BMI stability, palatibility, satiety and cost of the diet, and other lifestyle factors which might be affected by the diet. The information we collect will then be used to help refine and change the diet to make it easier to follow in the long term. We hypothesise that with some minor changes, it will be feasible to follow the AusMed diet for 2 weeks. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Davis C, Bryan J, Hodgson J, Wilson C, Murphy KJ.  Older Australians can adhere to a traditional Mediterranean style diet over two weeks: a pilot dietary intervention study. BMC Nutrition 2015, 1:28 (12 November 2015) </publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of South Australia</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Mawson Lakes Campus, Mawson Lakes Boulevard, Mawson Lakes, 5095, South Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/05/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>0000031163</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Karen Murphy</name>
      <address>University of South Australia Nutritional Physiology Research Centre GPO Box 2471 Adelaide, SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 1033</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>karen.murphy@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Karen Murphy</name>
      <address>University of South Australia Nutritional Physiology Research Centre GPO Box 2471 Adelaide, SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 1033</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>karen.murphy@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Karen Murphy</name>
      <address>University of South Australia Nutritional Physiology Research Centre GPO Box 2471 Adelaide, SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 1033</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>karen.murphy@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Karen Murphy</name>
      <address>University of South Australia Nutritional Physiology Research Centre GPO Box 2471 Adelaide, SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 1033</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>karen.murphy@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>