<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371255">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/09/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001357448</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy of  intravenous muscle relaxants for supplying regional muscle relaxation in order to improve relaxation of leg muscles in patients undergoing knee arthroscopy.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy of regional intravenous muscle relaxant injection for improving relaxation of lower extremity muscles in patients undergoing knee arthroscopy under peripheral nerve blocks</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1186-1117</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>knee arthroscopy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other anaesthesiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Randomised, double blind, placebo controlled trial to evaluate the degree of muscle relaxation of lower extremity of patients undergoing elective knee arthroscopy under combined sciatic and femoral paravascular nerve blocks. The main target of this study is to objectively prove the benefit of adding an intravascular muscle relaxant drug injection through dorsal feet vessels to improve the insufficiency of muscle relaxation during peripheral nerve block anesthesia.
A total of 22 patients between the ages of 18-65 yr, ASA physical status I and III, scheduled for elective knee arthroscopic surgery under combined sciatic and femoral paravascular nerve blocks will be studied.
Method:
1-	Basal values of Motor Evoked Potentials (MEP) will be recorded through adductor magnus, rectus femoris, tibialis anterior and gastrocnemius muscles. MEPs will be recorded using Magistar 200^2 transmagnetic electric stimulator and Medelec Synergy electroneuromyography instrument. This procedure will be held by the physiatrist who is blind to the study groups.
2-	After recording basal MEP values peripheral nerve blocks will be applied. Sciatic nerve block procedure will be followed by femoral paravascular nerve block. By the end of block procedures; MEPs will be recorded for a 30 minutes period with 5 min intervals. In the same time period pinprick and manuel muscle evaluation tests will be done to evaluate the sensory and motor blocks respectively. This will be held by a consultant anesthetist who is blind to the study groups.
3-	After the last evaluations (MEP's, pinprick and manuel muscle tests) at 30 minutes following nerve block application; a  the thigh tourniquet will be applied by the surgeon team and a 22G intravascular canula will be inserted on the dorsum of the foot on the side of the knee to be operated by the consultant anesthetist. Afterwards; In Group I, 5 mg of atracurium diluted in 20 mL 0,9% NaCl solution will be injected through the canula. In Group II (control group) only 20 mL 0,9% NaCl solution will be injected. The injections will be done by an anesthetist who takes part in the study.
4-	MEP values, pinprick test and manuel muscle test results will be recorded at 5 and 10 minutes following the injections. Determinations will be held by the  physiatrist and the consultant anesthetist who are blind to the study groups.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group will receive a placebo (20 mL 0,9% NaCl solution without muscle relaxant) injection.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of participants with a greater than or equal to 50% reduction in amplitude of MEP values following muscle relaxant injection as compared to measurement at 30th minute after local anesthetic injection during peripheral nerve block.
MEPs will be recorded using Magistar 200^2 transmagnetic electric stimulator and Medelec Synergy electroneuromyography instrument through adductor magnus, rectus femoris, tibialis anterior and gastrocnemius muscles. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Basal MEP values will be recorded prior to peripheral nerve blocks. By the end of block procedures; MEPs will be recorded for a 30 minutes period with 5 min intervals. The decrease in MEP's through 30 minutes period will be compared to basal values reflecting the effect of local anesthetic solution and the possibly maximum muscle relaxation achieved by the peripheral nerve block.

MEP values will be recorded at 5 and 10 minutes following the muscle relaxant injection and these values will be compared to MEP value recorded at 30 minutes following nerve block reflecting the further muscle relaxation achieved by the muscle relaxant injection</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of participants with a reduction in muscle tension, assessed by manual muscle relaxation test following muscle relaxant injection.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Following 5 and 10 minutes after the end of muscle relaxant/placebo injection.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Surgeon satisfaction with muscle relaxation.
Satisfaction will be assessed using an 11-point scale with 0 = extremely dissatisfied and 10 = extremely satisfied. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Surgeon satisfaction with muscle relaxation will be questioned immediately following the surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients (aged of 18-65 yr) with American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) physical status I-III, scheduled for elective knee arthroscopy under combined sciatic and femoral paravascular nerve blocks were included in the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Refusal to participate, ASAphysical status IV-V, patients with serious hepatic, renal or cardiovascular disease, neurologic/neuromuscular disease, epilepsy,
peripheral neuropathy, chronic analgesic consumption, unable to cooperate with this research due to cognitive impairment (neuro-psychiatric disease), under medication with anticoagulants, allergy to local anesthetics, pregnancy or breastfeeding, infection at the site of injection and patients with metallic implants (cardiac pacemaker, aneurysm clip etc..)

</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocations were concealed with opaque envelopes, which will only be opened by the assistant who will dispense the local anesthetic solution.</concealment>
    <sequence>computerised sequence generation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/10/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/08/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>22</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/08/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>Ankara</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr MD Irfan Gungor</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Gazi University Faculty of Medicine
Dep of Anaesthesiology and Reanimation
Boulevard of Mevlana
Besevler/ANKARA
(Postal Code: 06500)</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Turkey</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Republic Of Turkey Social Security Institution</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Sosyal Guvenlik Kurumu
Ziyabey Cad. No:6
06520 Balgat/ANKARA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Turkey</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Knee arthroscopy can be applied under either general anesthesia, spinal/epidural anesthesia or  peripheral nerve blocks (PNB). Muscle relaxation may be insufficient in PNB when compared to general anesthesia. The aim of this study is to improve the lack of muscle relaxation by intravenous injection of a muscle relaxant (atracurium). The injected solution will be restricted in the area between the injection point on the foot and the tourniquet applied on the thigh. The tourniquet will prevent the drug to leak into the circulation like mentioned in the technique described in Bier's block or regional intravenous anesthesia (RIVA). 
The main hypothesis is that the possible insufficiency of muscle relaxation by local anesthetics in PNB's may be improved using a muscle relaxant in a restricted area from the main vascular circulation.
The primary outcome of improvement in muscle relaxation will be monitored with the decrease in MEP's.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Dr. Zekai Tahir Burak Women's Health Research and Education Hospital Clinical Trials Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Zekai Tahir Burak Kadin Sagligi Egitim Ve Arastirma Hastanesi
Talatpasa Street     
Samanpazari / ANKARA
Postal Code: 06230</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/01/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Karar No: 1/2016</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/06/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Turkey</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371255-Ethics approval.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Irfan Gungor</name>
      <address>Gazi University Faculty of Medicine Dep of Anaesthesiolgy and Reanimation 
Besevler/ANKARA
Postal Code: 06560</address>
      <phone>+905057757490</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>irfan.gungor@gazi.edu.tr</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Irfan Gungor</name>
      <address>Gazi University Faculty of Medicine Dep of Anaesthesiolgy and Reanimation 
Besevler/ANKARA
Postal Code: 06560</address>
      <phone>+905057757490</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>irfan.gungor@gazi.edu.tr</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Irfan Gungor</name>
      <address>Gazi University Faculty of Medicine Dep of Anaesthesiolgy and Reanimation 
Besevler/ANKARA
Postal Code: 06560</address>
      <phone>+905057757490</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>irfan.gungor@gazi.edu.tr</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Irfan Gungor</name>
      <address>Gazi University Faculty of Medicine Dep of Anaesthesiolgy and Reanimation 
Besevler/ANKARA
Postal Code: 06560</address>
      <phone>+905057757490</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>irfan.gungor@gazi.edu.tr</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>