<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336678">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/03/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/03/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000303943</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Effect of a High fat Meal on Brivanib in Normal Healthy Subjects.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 1 Study to determine the effect of a high fat meal on the pharmacokinetics of Brivanib in Healthy Subjects.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1120-0905</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>The study will be performed in healthy volunteers.  This study is investigating the effect of a high fat meal on the use of a drug for cancer.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is an open-label, randomized, 2-period, 2-treatment crossover study in healthy volunteers.  Each subject will receive Treatment A: brivanib alaninate 800 mg (2 x 400 mg tablets) as a single oral dose under
fasted conditions AND Treatment B: brivanib alaninate 800 mg (2 x 400 mg tablets) as a single oral dose within 5 minutes of consuming a standard high-fat breakfast.  There will be at least a 7 day washout between each treatment.</interventions>
    <comparator>Each participant will be given both treatment A and treatment B over the course of the study.  
Treatment A: brivanib alaninate 800 mg under
fasted conditions. (Intervention treatment)
Treatment B: brivanib alaninate 800 mg  within 5 minutes of consuming a standard high-fat breakfast (Comparator treatment)
A standard high fat breakfast consists of 2 fried eggs, 2 slices of toasted white bread, 1 tablespoon butter, 1 tablespoon jam, 3 strips fried bacon, hash brown potatoes and one glass full cream milk.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome is to assess the effect of a high-fat meal on the PK of brivanib in healthy subjects.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be measured via blood analysis at multiple time points on Days 1, 2, 3, 8, 9 and 10.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To further describe the safety and tolerability of brivanib alaninate under fasted and fed conditions measured through safety laboratory assessments and observation throughout the study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Safety laboratory assessments will be performed via blood sampling.  Each participant will also be asked questioned 3-4 times daily and observed by the study team throughout the inpatient stay to determine if any adverse events have been experienced.  Blood pressure, heart rate and temperature, along with ECG measurements will also be taken 4-5 times throughout the study to confirm participant safety.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the effect of plasma collection matrix on measurement of brivanib concentrations (tubes with glycine versus no glycine stabilizer). This will be evaluated at multiple time points on Days 1, 2, 3, 8, 9 and 10.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be evaluated at multiple time points on Days 1, 2, 3, 8, 9 and 10 by blood analysis.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy Men and Women aged 18-55 years inclusive.
Women who are not of child bearing potential
Body Mass Index of 18.0-30.0 kg/m2 inclusive</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any significant acute or chronic illness.
Any clinically significant illness, laboratory findings or allergies.
History of hypertension (&gt; 140/90 mmHg consistently on two separate measurements without treatment).
Inability to tolerate oral medication.
Inability to be repetitively venipunctured and/or tolerate venous access.
Any history of cardiovascular disease including congestive heart failure of any grade, thromboembolic disease, myocardial infarction, any angina, stroke, transient ischemic attack, or any other ischemic event or symptoms (eg,intermittent claudication).
Resting heart rate less than 45 beats per minute.
Resting blood pressure greater than 140/90 mmHg.
Any of the following on 12-lead ECG prior to study drug administration,confirmed by repeat:
i) PR greater than or equal to 210 millisecond (msec)
ii) QRS greater than or equal to 120 msec
iii) QT greater than or equal to 500 msec
iv) QTcF greater than or equal to 450 msec
Current use of tobacco (eg, smoker, chew) or recent history (within 1 month of screening) of regular tobacco use or a nicotine replacement product.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Subjects will be randomized to 1 of 2 treatment sequences according to a computer generated randomization scheme</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Bio-availability</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>29/03/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Bristol-Myers Squibb Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 39
Noble Park, VIC, 3174</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Bristol-Myers Squibb Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 39
Noble Park, VIC, 3174</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is being run to determine if eating a high fat breakfast will change the way that the body absorbs brivanib.  Brivanib is a drug being developed for use in patients with cancer.  
Based on previous studies performed with this drug, a high fat meal is not expected to change the way that the body absorbs brivanib.  
The study will involve each participant in the study being given a single dose of brivanib whilst fasted and 7 days later being given a single dose of brivanib following consumption of a high  fat breakfast.  Following each dose, participants will have numerous blood samples collected to determine the levels of brivanib present in the blood and to perform standard laboratory testing to ensure the safety of the participants.  
Participants will also have their blood pressure, heart rate and temperature monitored; along with ECG monitoring, physical examinations and general observation throughout the in-patient stay to ensure participant safety.  
Participants will be required to be inpatients for 3 nights for each treatment and there must be at least 7 days between each dose of brivanib.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>N/A</trialwebsite>
    <publication>N/A</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Alfred Hospital
55 Commercial Road
Melbourne, Victoria 3004</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>21/02/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Prof Peter Hodsman</name>
      <address>Nucleus Network
5th Flr, Burnet Tower
AMREP Precinct, 89 Commercial Road
Melbourne, Victoria 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 8960</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9076 8911</fax>
      <email>P.Hodsman@nucleusnetwork.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Annette Leahy</name>
      <address>Nucleus Network
5th Flr, Burnet Tower
AMREP Precinct, 89 Commercial Road
Melbourne, Victoria 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 9005</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9076 8911</fax>
      <email>A.Leahy@nucleusnetwork.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>David Wilks</name>
      <address>PO Box 39
Noble Park, VIC, 3174</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8562 1362</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 8562 1393</fax>
      <email>meaghan.read@bms.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>