<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368144">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/03/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/04/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000307505</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Systematic glaucoma screening and diagnostic effectiveness: can early detection improve patient outcomes?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>For glaucoma patients and suspects, does better diagnostic effectiveness of the referring optometrist result in improved outcomes?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1167-9629</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Glaucoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients at risk, suspects or monitored for glaucoma will be followed over a 5 year period. Biannual exams as recommended by the "NHMRC guidelines for the screening, prognosis, diagnosis, management and prevention of glaucoma 2010" will be performed and results will be compared to an age-related control group. Exams include patient history, refraction, slit lamp exam, visual field test (SAP), Gonioscopy, Pachymetry, OCT scan, HRT, and optic disc photography.</interventions>
    <comparator>Patients with no or low risk of developing glaucoma or age-matched patients with other common eye disorders, such as age-related macular degeneration, monitored and managed according to standard clinical care will serve as control. Control patients will be monitored for at least 2 years or until 5 exams have been obtained.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diagnostic accuracy measured as the proportion of true positive referrals defined as those patients referred as glaucoma suspects or with suggested glaucomatous changes that are confirmed during examination.</outcome>
      <timepoint>five years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Predictors for earlier diagnosis defined as exam outcomes that show a better correlation with the determined patient glaucoma status than the primary outcome. Multivariate regression models will be applied to identify those exam outcomes that result in the best prediction of the patient disease status at the study end point.</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria: 18-80 year, gonioscopically open angles, IOP below 32 in either eye, normal optic disc at initial clinical examination and on stereoscopic photographs as determined by the two independent ophthalmologists with specialty in glaucoma, 2 normal and reliable visual field tests per eye at initial examination as determined by the two independent ophthalmologists with specialty in glaucoma.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Glaucoma other than primary open angle glaucoma, previous intraocular surgery (other than uncomplicated cataract extraction with posterior chamber lens implantation), and any disases capable of causing visual field loss or optic disc deterioration.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>True</patientregistry>
    <followup>5</followup>
    <followuptype>Years</followuptype>
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Both</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>30/10/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1500</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>250</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2052 - Unsw Sydney</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Prof Michael Kalloniatis</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Centre for Eye Health
UNSW Australia
Ruperts Myers building (south wing)
Barker St, Gate 14
Kensington NSW 2052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Guide Dogs NSW/ACT</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>2-4 Thomas Street
Chatswood NSW 2067</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In Australia ~75% of eye examinations are delivered by Optometrists.  Optometrists have a legal and moral obligation to identify eye disease, manage suitable cases and refer others requiring medical or surgical intervention to ophthalmologists.
With an aging population, the management of chronic eye disease is an increasing issue for the already stretched health system.  The NHMRC glaucoma guidelines encourage development of shared-care models between primary health care providers and ophthalmologists. The guidelines also highlight the need for low-risk glaucoma patients to be monitored by primary eye care providers and not referred to Ophthalmology thereby minimizing the possibility that the health system is overloaded with false positive referrals.
Until now, this new model of glaucoma management has been largely unexplored, especially with regards to assessing the effectiveness of the current optometric profession in clinical diagnosis, referral quality, appropriately utilization of new technologies and integrating with complementary facilities and services.
The Centre for Eye Health (CFEH), a joint Guide Dogs NSW/ACT and UNSW initiative is leading the way in promoting a shared care model for eye-care in Australia. Ophthalmic practitioners refer patients to CFEH for visual assessment using the latest technology. Over 830 optometrists in NSW/ACT have registered with CFEH. It is proposed that this pool of participants be analysed with regards to current glaucoma practice characteristics, effectiveness in clinical diagnosis, referral quality, appropriate utilisation of new technologies and integration with complementary facilities and services. 
The research will inform current models of Glaucoma management and the evidence will have direct policy implications for the regulatory partners.  Ultimately, more cohesive and patient-focused service delivery will lead to improved quality of life for patients and a reduced economic burden of eye disease nationally.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Reserach Ethis Advisory Panel 'H', Science and Engineering UNSW Australia</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>UNSW Australia
Sydney NSW 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/04/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>08/2014/36</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Reserach Ethis Advisory Panel 'H', Science and Engineering UNSW Australia</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>UNSW Australia
Sydney NSW 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/08/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>08/2014/37</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Michael Kalloniatis</name>
      <address>Centre for Eye Health
UNSW Australia
Rupert Myers Building (south wing)
Barker St, Gate 14
Kensington NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8115 0710</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>MKalloniatis@cfeh.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Michael Kalloniatis</name>
      <address>Centre for Eye Health
UNSW Australia
Rupert Myers Building (south wing)
Barker St, Gate 14
Kensington NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8115 0710</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>MKalloniatis@cfeh.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Michael Kalloniatis</name>
      <address>Centre for Eye Health
UNSW Australia
Rupert Myers Building (south wing)
Barker St, Gate 14
Kensington NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8115 0710</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>MKalloniatis@cfeh.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Barbara Zangerl</name>
      <address>Centre for Eye Health
UNSW Australia
Rupert Myers Building (south wing)
Barker St, Gate 14
Kensington NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>(02) 8115 0793</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>BZangerl@cfeh.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>