<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83526">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/01/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/02/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000130268</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Preoperative and postoperative physiotherapy versus postoperative physiotherapy alone following elective upper abdominal surgery  A randomised trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A comparison of preoperative and postoperative physiotherapy versus postoperative physiotherapy alone for patients undergoing elective upper abdominal surgery. A randomised controlled trial investigating the effects on patient anxiety, postoperative pulmonary complications and overall physiotherapy contact time.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Elective upper abdominal surgery</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients randomised to the treatment group will receive postoperative physiotherapy. This includes tansferring out of bed on the first postoperative day with the assistance of the physiotherapist, as well as the completion of specifically targeted breathing, lower limb exercises and graduated walking. These patients will continue to receive physiotherapy, aimed at progressing the patient's mobility and respiratory function, until it is deemed no longer necessary by the treating physiotherapist. The frequency and duration of the postoperative physiotherapy sessions will be at the discretion of the treating physiotherapist, as individual patients may require more or less physiotherapy input depending on their rate of progression. Patients in the treatment group will also receive a single session of physiotherapy preoperatively of 30-45 minutes duration (45 minutes will be allowed for patients requiring an interpreter).This preoperative session will take place approximately 1-2 weeks prior to surgery. During this preoperative session, the physiotherapist will collect information including the patients past medical history, social history and details of their pre-morbid physical functioning. The patients will be educated regarding their surgery, the complications often associated with surgery that may be reduced by participating in physiotherapy, and the rationale for postoperative physiotherapy. They will be given the opportunity to practise the specific breathing and lower limb exercises to be performed postoperatively and to ask the physiotherapist any questions.</interventions>
    <comparator>Postoperative physiotherapy, which is standard treatment. The patient receives physiotherapy commencing on the first postoperative day, which continues on subsequent days until deemed no longer necessary by the treating physiotherapist. The postoperative physiotherapy program includes transferring out of bed on the first postoperative day with the assistance of the physiotherapist, specifically tailored breathing and lower limb exercises, as well as graduated walking and stair climbing as appropriate. The frequency and duration of the postoperative physiotherapy sessions will be at the discretion of the treating physiotherapist, as individual patients may require more or less physiotherapy input depending on their rate of progression.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient anxiety will be measured using the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS). Patients in both groups will be assisted to complete the questionnaire by a research assistant (blinded as to group allocation). Only the anxiety sub-scale of the HADS will be used. It is a self-report rating scale of 7 items (score 0-3 for each item).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately prior to the physiotherapist assisting the patient out of bed on the first postoperative day.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The incidence of postoperative pulmonary complications (PPC) will be measured using the following criteria:
A patient will be deemed to have developed a PPC if 2 or more of the following criteria is present on &gt;/= 2 consecutive days within the first 6 postoperative days: (1) Cough or sputum production, which is different from preoperative assessment; (2) Abnormal breath sounds on auscultation; (3) Temperature &gt;/= 38degrees Celsius (4) Chest radiograph demonstrating atelectasis or new infiltrate; and (5) Physician documentation of atelectasis or pneumonia. [adapted by Brooks-Brunn (1997) from Seymour and Pringle (1983)]</outcome>
      <timepoint>Presence of the above criteria will be assessed by the treating physiotherapist every day for the first 6 postoperative days.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall physiotherapy contact time will be calculated using routinely entered physiotherapy statistics. At The Northern Hospital, statistics are entered into the "Healthpower" computer program. For patients in the intervention group, the preoperative physiotherapy session time will be added to the total postoperative physiotherapy session time.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Calculations of overall physiotherapy contact time will be made once the patient has been discharged from The Northern Hospital.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Each patient will be assessed as either low or high risk of developing a PPC by an independent researcher (blinded to group allocation), using the Postoperative Pneumonia Risk Index (Arozullah et al 2001).</outcome>
      <timepoint>The Postoperative Pneumonia Risk Index will be completed by the blinded researcher on the first postoperative day.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients undergoing elective upper abdominal surgery presenting to the Preadmission Clinic at The Northern Hospital.
Patients 18 years and older.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Failure to consent; and
Score &lt; 7 on the Abbreviated Mental Test Score (AMTS)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealment using sealed opaque envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using computerised sequence generation.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>16/03/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>256</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Northern Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Northern Hospital,
185 Cooper Street,
Epping, Victoria, 3076</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Northern Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The Northern Hospital,
185 Cooper Street,
Epping, Victoria, 3076</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Upper Abdominal Surgery (UAS) is a common surgical procedure, with average hospitalisation of 11.4 days. Breathing problems are a major contributor to longer periods of hospitalisation following UAS, and account for nearly 25% of deaths within 6 days of surgery. The incidence of such breathing problems following UAS is as high as 53%. There is a need for evidence-based approaches to reduce these rates, with potential benefits including reduced hospitalisation and healthcare costs, improved quality of care, and improved patient outcomes and quality of life.   
Research suggests that postoperative physiotherapy should be targeted towards high-risk patients, and is effective in reducing the incidence of breathing complications compared to no postoperative physiotherapy. However, potential benefits of additional preoperative physiotherapy for patients undergoing elective UAS have not been established. A randomised trial will be undertaken comparing current practice (postoperative physiotherapy only) to a program incorporating a preoperative physiotherapy session combined with postoperative physiotherapy.
It is proposed that a single, preoperative physiotherapy session in the Pre Admission Clinic (PAC) setting would improve the quality of physiotherapy care for these patients. The aims of this preoperative session would be to: (a) Reduce the incidence of breathing problems; (b) Reduce patient anxiety during the first postoperative physiotherapy session; (c) Decrease the physiotherapists overall patient contact time, thus improving efficiency of the physiotherapy service.
The study will investigate 4 questions: (a) Does preoperative physiotherapy reduce the incidence of breathing problems compared with standard management? (b) Does the timing of physiotherapy intervention (preoperative and postoperative vs. postoperative only) affect patient anxiety during the first postoperative physiotherapy session?  (c) Does preoperative physiotherapy reduce overall physiotherapy contact time compared with standard management? (d) Should preoperative physiotherapy only be provided to patients at high risk of postoperative breathing problems?</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Health Human Research and Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Northern Hospital,
185 Cooper Street,
Epping, Victoria, 3076</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/02/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sarah Threlfall</name>
      <address>Bundoora Extended Care Centre,
1231 Plenty Road
Bundoora, Victoria, 3148</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9495 3382</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sarah.threlfall@nh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sarah Threlfall</name>
      <address>Bundoora Extended Care Centre,
1231 Plenty Road
Bundoora, Victoria, 3148</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9495 3382</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sarah.threlfall@nh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sarah Threlfall</name>
      <address>Bundoora Extended Care Centre,
1231 Plenty Road
Bundoora, Victoria, 3148</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9495 3382</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sarah.threlfall@nh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>