<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82849">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/06/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/08/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000430336</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>ACRP Study (Anterior Cervical Retraction Pressure Study)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A comparison of intra-operative retraction pressure during anterior cervical surgery between a novel retractor system and conventional retractor system  a pilot study.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>voice change</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>dysphagia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>sore throat</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In this study the recruited candidates are prospectively randomized into two groups. In one group Casper retraction system will be used and in the other group Seex's retraction system will be used for anterior cervical surgical procedures. For each patients one procedure will be done with one retractor system. In all the patients an online pressure transducer (Tekscan pressure measurement system) will be applied to the rear side of the medial retractor blade on to the food pipe and pressure changes will be recorded electronically throughout the period of retraction.
The retractor system randomized for a particular patient will be used through out the period of retraction which is needed to complete the proposed procedure. Retraction period may vary between patients
proposed period of study is 18 months.</interventions>
    <comparator>The group with conventional retractor system</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The retraction pressure on wind pipe and food pipe in patients under going neck operations using the conventional Casper retraction system and Seex retractor system.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Continuously throughout the period of retraction</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A self-assessment of sore throat, difficulty in swallowing and voice change by the participants using a chart of rating score.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hrs, 1 week and 4weeks after operation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All the patients scheduled for spinal operations from the front of the neck in Nepean hospital, Kingswood, NSW</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>previous neck operations, radiation to the neck or those with history of tumors</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomization information is kept in serially numbered sealed opaque envelopes. Those envelopes are kept in the office of the Head of neurosurgery Nepean hospital. The recruited candidates are serially numbered as per the order in which they are coming to theater for operation. This serial number will be used for randomization purpose. Operation theater staff contacts the office of the Head of neurosurgery and finds out which retractor system is randomized for the serial number</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomization by using a randomization table created by an online computer program (www.graphpad.com/quickcalcs/randomN1.cfm)</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Nepean Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Derby st
Kingswood
NSW 2751</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ananthababu Pattavilakom</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Dept of Neurosurgery, Nepean Hospital
Derby st
Kingswood
NSW 2751</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Operations of the spine, when performed from the front of the neck can cause problems like sore throat, difficulty in swallowing and voice change during postoperative period. Often these problems are temporary, but they are common. Most of the patients feel these symptoms are very uncomfortable. These symptoms are attributed to the retraction of structures like wind pipe and food pipe during the operation. The retraction causes pressure on to these structures and results in direct damage as well as damage due to reduced blood flow during the period of retraction. The more the pressure the more will be the damage and the worse will be the symptoms. Conventional retractor systems are designed to mount directly on to the soft tissues during the operation, causing direct transmission of retraction pressure on to them. A novel retractor system (Seex retractor system) has been introduced in to surgical practice. The new system is mounted/fixed directly on to the bones (vertebrae) during the procedure so that the amount of direct pressure transmission to wind pipe or food pipe is theoretically much less than the conventional retractors. Cadaver studies conducted by the researchers agree with that. In this pilot study the researchers prospectively measure the pressure variations on windpipe and food pipe in the two groups of patients under going neck operations with conventional retraction system and the new system. They will also assess sore throat, difficulty in swallowing and voice change in patients of both the groups during postoperative period using rating score chart. Data collected in this unblinded pilot study will be used to design a subsequent randomized controlled trial, if the new system appears to be a better one.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Sydney West Area Health Service HREC, Nepean Campus</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Nepean Campus
Derby st
Kingswood
NSW 2751</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/06/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC Project No. 07/007:</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ananthababu Pattavilakom</name>
      <address>Dept of Neurosurgery, Nepean Hospital
Derby st
Kingswood
NSW 2751</address>
      <phone>(02) 47342000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ananthababu@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ananthababu Pattavilakom</name>
      <address>Dept of Neurosurgery, Nepean Hospital
Derby st
Kingswood
NSW 2751</address>
      <phone>(02) 47342000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ananthababu@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ananthababu Pattavilakom</name>
      <address>Dept of Neurosurgery, Nepean Hospital
Derby st
Kingswood
NSW 2751</address>
      <phone>(02) 47342000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ananthababu@hotmail.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>