<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364252">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/05/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/05/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000573752</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Increasing Motivation and Self-control to Reduce Alcohol Consumption among Undergraduate Students</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An Intervention Using Process and Outcome Mental Simulation Exercises and Self-control Training to Reduce Alcohol Consumption among Undergraduate Students</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>alcohol consumption</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other public health</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants are randomly allocated into 4 groups. The trial will involve two independent conditions using a 2 (mental simulation: mental simulation vs. control irrelevant visualization exercise) x 2 (self-control training: difficult training vs. active control easy training) design. For the mental simulation intervention, participants randomized to receive the intervention will be required to imagine the steps they will take to change their alcohol consumption known as process mental simulation and imagine how they would feel on achieving the outcomes known as 'outcome mental simulation'. Participants will be given a process mental simulation script adapted from Pham and Taylors (1999) article. The targeted behaviour is adapted as drinking within recommended safe limits. Participants need to follow instructions, read the script, and rehearse it with eyes closed under quiet conditions. Then, they need to write down their responses in the space provided and remember it throughout the research period. Written responses will be content analysed to check for compliance with the task. This mental simulation task should take no longer than 10 minutes. Participants randomized to the control condition will not receive any relevant visualization exercise but will be asked to imagine a recent visit to the cinema or shopping centre to maintain equivalent information load to the active mental simulation condition for 10 minutes. 

For the self-control training, participants randomized to receive the difficult intervention will be required to complete a computerised response-inhibition task (incongruent version of the Stroop colour-naming task). Participants randomized to receive the control easy training condition will receive an easy version of the response inhibition task (congruent version of the Stroop colour-naming task. This response-inhibition task should take no longer than 5 minutes. Participants will complete the task to which they have been assigned immediately after the visualization task in the initial session and then repeat this on a daily basis throughout the intervention period of four weeks.The response inhibition task system will be used to monitor participants adherence by logging each trial and uploading participant responses to a remote server via internet providing compliance data with the training task. Also, four reminder emails or text messages will be sent to prompt participants to practice the Stroop task.

The design is therefore 2 (IV1) x 2 (IV2) design with 4 arms. Arm 1: mental simulation &amp; difficult self-control training incongruent Stroop task; Arm 2: mental simulation &amp; control easy self-control training congruent Stroop task (congruent version of Stroop task does not affect response inhibition); Arm 3: irrelevant control visualization task &amp; difficult self-control training incongruent Stroop task; Arm 4: irrelevant control visualization task &amp; control easy training congruent Stroop task (active control group).</interventions>
    <comparator>Active control.
The control group will be asked to perform irrelevant control visualisation task (to maintain information load with the intervention group but with no effect on motivation toward alcohol consumption) and a 'control' easy training congruent Stroop task (that does not affect response inhibition).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>alcohol consumption measured by participant self-report at follow-up. Participants will be asked to report number of units of standard drinks they had consumed and the number of occasions when they binge drank weekly over the previous four weeks. Participants reported their drinking behaviour by answering the questionnaire. The measure is based on the time-line follow back technique to obtain the estimates of drinking (Sobell et al., 1979).</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks post-intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>self-reported levels of self-control by participants are the proposed mechanisms for the effect of the self-control manipulation. It is measured by state self-control capacity measure (Ciarocco, Twenge, Muraven, &amp; Tice, 2011). This is a psychometric instrument with scaled responses to items (e.g. I feel discouraged) with responses made on 7-point Likert scales ranging from 1 (no true) to 7 (very true).</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported levels of self-efficacy by participants are proposed mechanisms for the effect of the mental simulation manipulation. It is measure by standardised measures of the Theory of Planned Behaviour used in previous study (Hagger, Lonsdale, &amp; Chatzisarantis, 2011). This is a psychometric measure asking participants to rate their confidence with respect to reducing alcohol intake (e.g. How motivated are you to keep your alcohol drinking to within safe limits on each individual occasion or session over the next four weeks?) with responses made on 6-point scales ranging from 1 (not at all motivated) to 6 (extremely motivated).</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All participants should be over 18 years old, non-abstinent with respect to alcohol consumption and undergraduate students</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>non alcohol drinkers</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be recruited via advertising and online recruitment using a dedicated online participant pool for undergraduate psychology students incentivised by course credit or a prize draw for shopping vouchers. Participants will be allocated to a study condition on recruitment according to a permuted block randomisation schedule drawn up a priori generated using a random number generator. Block randomisation is used to ensure equal numbers per group. The conditions in the schedule will be labelled A-D and the experimenter administering the intervention will be blinded to the condition content by having an independent researcher code the content of the intervention conditions and allocate them to study information packs labelled A-D accordingly. The experimenter will be aware of the conditions only after the intervention.</concealment>
    <sequence>permuted block randomisation will be used generated using a random number generator (www.randomizer.org)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Factorial</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Data will be analysed using a 2 (mental simulation condition: mental simulation vs. no mental simulation) x 2 (response inhibition self-control training condition: challenging (incongruent) vs. easy (congruent)) factorial between-groups analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) with self-reported alcohol consumption at follow-up as the dependent variable and baseline self-reported alcohol consumption as the covariate. Assuming a medium effect size based on a previous meta-analysis from the current laboratory (Hagger et al., 2010) and setting power at .80 and alpha at .05, we anticipate a total sample size of 128 participants.  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/05/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>24/05/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/08/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>128</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Ging Ging Wong</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Curtin University, Kent St  Bentley WA 6102</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>curtin university</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Kent St  Bentley WA 6102</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This experimental study will examine the effectiveness of increasing motivation and self-control to reduce alcohol consumption among undergraduate students..It is proposed that motivation and self-control are two psychological factors that can influence alcohol consumption. Adopting theoretical perspectives from the Pham and Taylors (1999) model on mental simulations and the strength model of self-control (Baumeister et al., 1998), people who are motivated via a process mental simulation manipulation and have self-control practice on a Stroop task will be more likely to reduce their alcohol consumption.The aim of this research is to test the hypothesis that individuals who receive motivation and self-control manipulations will have higher reduction in alcohol consumption than a control group comprising individuals that did not receive manipulation. Also, we hypothesise that combined experimental manipulations of motivation and self-control is more effective than either of the motivation and self-control manipulations alone in reducing alcohol consumption</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin University School of psychology and Speech Pathology Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Kent St  Bentley WA 6102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/03/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Psych and SP 2013 - 05</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Martin Hagger</name>
      <address>Curtin University, Kent St  Bentley WA 6102</address>
      <phone>+61412879953</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>martin.hagger@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Martin Hagger</name>
      <address>Curtin University, Kent St  Bentley WA 6102</address>
      <phone>+61412879953</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>martin.hagger@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Martin Hagger</name>
      <address>Curtin University, Kent St  Bentley WA 6102</address>
      <phone>+61412879953</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>martin.hagger@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Martin Hagger</name>
      <address>School of Psychology and Speech Pathology
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth
Western Australia 6845
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61892662215</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>martin.hagger@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>