<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362485">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/05/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/05/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000508875</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Whole-body vibration and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy of whole-body vibration on exercise tolerance and functional performance of the lower limbs for people with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1130-6211</utrn>
    <trialacronym>WBV and COPD</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study is a non-randomised placebo cross-over intervention based in a community setting. Participants diagnosed with COPD will complete six weeks of whole-body vibration training and then after a two week washout period, will complete a six week placebo training intervention. Participants will complete training sessions twice a week. The duration of the study is 14 weeks. Community-dwelling older adults with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease will provide informed voluntary consent to participate. Outcome measures will include selected variabes of exercise tolearance and functional performance of the lower limbs.

The WBV intervention will consist 12 WBV sessions over a consecutive six week period.  The participants will complete two vibration sessions per week separated by at least 48 hours.  Efficacy of session frequency had been previously established for healthy community dwelling older adults.  A WBV session will consist of five, 60 second vibration bouts, interspersed with 60 seconds of passive rest.  Although the most effective protocol is yet to be established, the selected protocol had been used previously to establish efficacy of WBV interventions.  During rest, the participant will remain on the vibration platform and will be encouraged to stand with a posture that resembles the anatomical position.  More specifically, the participant assumes a standing position with the feet together, the arms to the side, and the head, eyes and palms facing forwards. The forearms are supinated.     

 A side alternating vibration platform will be used.  For each vibration bout, platform frequency will be 25 Hz, peak-to-peak displacement 2.0 mm, peak acceleration ~24.67 m.s-2, and gravitational force ~2.52 g.  The vibration platform peak-to-peak displacement and frequency were validated prior to this proposal in an unpublished pilot study.  Foot placement (second toe) will be equidistant, 20 cm from axis of rotation.  The participant will wear flat soled shoes.  Skidding will be checked according to the recommended method of the International Society of Musculoskeletal and Neuronal Interactions.  A piece of paper will be placed under the foot during a vibration bout to ensure constant contact with the vibration platform.  The participant will be required to stand with ~20 degrees knee flexion to allow transmission of vibration about the lower limbs.  Knee angle will be filmed, and later quantified across the intervention for each participant.</interventions>
    <comparator>A prototype vibration platform will be used for the PLACEBO intervention.  For each vibration bout, platform frequency will be 25 Hz, peak-to-peak displacement ~0.0 mm, peak acceleration ~0.00 m.s-2, and gravitational force ~0.0 g (cognisant that the Earths gravitational force is constant 1.0 g). Participants will be required to follow the same procedure of the WBV intervention.  Participants will be told the PLACEBO intervention is an ultra-low frequency vibration intervention that is very different to the aforementioned WBV intervention.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome 1: the 5-chair stands test quantified with stop watch</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and every 2 weeks across the 14 week study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome 2: the timed up and go test quantified with stop watch</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and every 2 weeks across the 14 week study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcome 1: stride length quantified with electronic walkway</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and every 2 weeks across the 14 week study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcome 2: stride time quantified with electronic walkway</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and every 2 weeks across the 14 week study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcome 3: stride velocity quantified with electronic walkway</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and every 2 weeks across the 14 week study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcome 4: perceived dyspnoea quantified with VAS</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and every 2 weeks across the 14 week study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcome 5: heart rate (beats per minute)</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and every 2 weeks across the 14 week study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcome 6: saturation of haemoglobin (%) quantified with pulse oximeter</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and every 2 weeks across the 14 week study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants must be fully independent in residence and have well managed, stable Stage II COPD according to the Global initiative for chronic Obstructive Lung Disease (GOLD) criteria. Participants must be free of contraindicators to physical activity as well as contraindicators to whole-body vibration.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>90</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>not community dwelling (functionally dependent on external care)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation was not used</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>3938</postcode>
    <postcode>3810</postcode>
    <postcode>3178</postcode>
    <postcode>3977</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australian Catholic University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>115 Victoria Parade, 
Fitzroy, Victoria 3065</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Monash Medical Centre</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Southern Health
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Road
Clayton, Victoria, 3168</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) is a respiratory condition characterised by dyspnoea, excessive sputum production, chronic cough, bronchitis and emphysema.  Functionally, exercise tolerance is poor for people with COPD and is linked to difficulty in performing daily tasks. More specifically, exercise difficulties are due partly to dyspnoea and lower limb skeletal muscle dysfunction. The benefits of gentle exercise that does not exacerbate the disease while improving exercise tolerance is salient. Whole-body vibration is a mode of gentle exercise known to improve muscular function of the lower limbs, yet efficacy has not been investigated for a whole-body vibration intervention conducted in a community setting for people with COPD.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Health Human Research Ethics Committee A</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Directorate
Southern Health
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Road
Clayton, Victoria, 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/09/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>11222A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Australian Catholic University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>115 Victoria Parade,
Fitzroy, Victoria 3065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/04/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>V2011 01</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Trentham Furness</name>
      <address>School of Exercise Science
Australian Catholic University
115 Victoria Parade, 
Fitzroy, Victoria 3065</address>
      <phone>+61399533538</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>trentham.furness@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Trentham Furness</name>
      <address>School of Exercise Science
Australian Catholic University
115 Victoria Parade, 
Fitzroy, Victoria 3065</address>
      <phone>+61399533538</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>trentham.furness@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Trentham Furness</name>
      <address>School of Exercise Science
Australian Catholic University
115 Victoria Parade, 
Fitzroy, Victoria 3065</address>
      <phone>+61399533538</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>trentham.furness@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>