<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365791">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/02/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/02/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000185662</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Narrow band ultraviolet-B (UVB) light for patients with Clinically Isolated Syndrome</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In patients with Clinically Isolated Syndrome, can narrow band UVB therapy decrease the risk of developing Multiple Sclerosis over the 12 months from their first demyelinating event?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1153-2803</utrn>
    <trialacronym>PhoCIS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Clinically Isolated Syndrome</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Multiple Sclerosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Multiple sclerosis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients will be given narrow band (311 nm) UVB light to their full body on 3 occasions per week. Patients will receive a total of 24 administrations over 8 weeks. They will receive the narrow band UVB light as they stand up in a small cubicle. The exposure to the light will range from 1 to 4 minutes each time.</interventions>
    <comparator>No administration of narrow band UVB therapy</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phototherapy-associated changes in the mRNA transcripts and properties of cells in freshly isolated peripheral blood.

The types of cells in freshly isolated blood, the mRNA levels in these cells, and the immunological function of blood cells will be assessed by standard laboratory protocols</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 month measurement compared to baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Development of a new demyelinating event defined as either (a) a confirmed clinical relapse, or (b) a new cerebral T2 lesion and/or newly Gadolinium-enhancing cerebral lesion as measured in a cerebral MRI.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 month measurement compared to baseline MRI scan</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phototherapy-associated changes in quality of life measures for the participants with Clinically Isolated Syndrome.

This will be measured by Questionnaires (SF36v2, specially designed lifestyle questionnaires, Fatigue Severity Table)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 month measurement compared to baseline measurement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cerebral MRI volume changes.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 month measurement compared to baseline measurement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Recently diagnosed (within 120 days) with a first isolated, well-defined, uni- or multi-focal first demyelinating event (FDE).
Able to receive their first phototherapy within 120 days of FDE symptom onset.
An MRI brain scan that is supportive of demyelinating disease (Paty A or Paty B criteria, i.e. the presence of at least four T2 lesions greater than 3 mm, or at least three T2 lesions greater than 3 mm, one of which must be periventricular, respectively).
An EDSS between 0 - 6.5 (inclusive)
Must be able to give informed consent and sign the informed consent form
Must be able to comply with all study procedures, and attend 24 phototherapy sessions and centres for venepuncture on multiple occasions during and after phototherapy
If female of child-bearing age, must be willing to use effective contraception
Must be willing to avoid use of sunbeds
Must be able to stand in the phototherapy cubicle for up to 5 minutes at a time
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Known co-morbid illnesses that might be exacerbated by phototherapy, including lupus erythematosus and  xeroderma pigmentosum 
A history of melanoma, multiple non melanoma skin cancers
Previous prolonged courses of UVB or photochemotherapy (PUVA), or use of sunbeds
Cardiovascular or respiratory disease that would prevent standing in the treatment cubicle
Bullous disease
Use of photosensitizing medications
Very fair skin that burns with very minimal sun exposure (as judged by the dermatologist involved) 
Corticosteroids within 3 months, or current immunosuppressive drug therapy (beta-interferon, glatiramer acetate, natalizumab, mitoxantrone, or other chemotherapy agent specifically for demyelinating disease) prior to CIS diagnosis. (*Note that requirement for immunomodulatory therapy in the course of MS disease management will not exclude patients during follow-up; treatment variables will be collected and analysed in both the intervention and control arms in the planned analysis).
Current pregnancy, breastfeeding or planning to become pregnant in the next 12 months.
A second clinical demyelinating event prior to randomisation
Concurrent diagnosis of other neurological, psychiatric or other disease, which, in the opinion of the investigator, could impair capacity to provide informed consent or interfere with study compliance.
Current enrolment in another interventional trial
Any contraindication to MRI scanning or intravenous Gadolinium including: Cardiac Pacemaker, Cardiac Defibrillator, Metal fragments in the eye, Any other non-MRI compatible medical device/implant or medical condition, Previous allergic reaction to Gadolinium, Severe claustrophobia

</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be invited to join the trial by neurologists who are treating their first demyelinating event. Once participants have given written informed consent, they will be randomised to receive, or not receive, UVB phototherapy. 

Allocation concealment will be performed by a central computer randomisation. It will be obvious to the participants into which group they have been allocated. </concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomised according to computer generated random number table made in Xcel for 60 participants</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Participants who have undergone 2 weeks (6 sessions) of narrow band UVB phototherapy will qualify for intention-to-treat analysis. 

Differences in continuous responses between groups will be tested for significance using one-way ANOVA/t-tests or Kruskal-Wallis/Mann-Whitney tests as appropriate to the characteristics of the data. Covariate adjustment will be accommodated via general linear models. Comparisons of binary or categorical variables will be based on Fisher exact or Chi-squared tests, or logistical regression models to incorporate covariate adjustment. Repeated measurements over time will be analysed by longitudinal mixed models. 

If new MRI lesions are expected in 90% of CIS patients over 1.5-2 years (CHAMPS, ETOMS, BENEFIT, PRECISE studies), then a treatment effect (ie reduction of 10%) should be discernible with a sample size of 30 patients. Further, in forerunner experiments, in measures of changes in the transcriptome (for 10 transcription factors analysed, blood cells from 11 to 27 patients were required to measure season-related changes to 80% power).
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>5/09/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St John of God Hospital, Subiaco - Subiaco</hospital>
    <postcode>6008 - Subiaco</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Western Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>35 Stirling Hwy, Crawley WA 6009</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC),
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress> Level 1, 16 Marcus Clarke St, 
Canberra ACT 2601 

 Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>People who have experienced for the first time an episode of inflammation within the brain, spinal cord or optic nerves (called a first demyelinating event) are at risk of developing Multiple Sclerosis. In this study, we will test whether a course of narrow band UVB phototherapy decreases their risk of developing Multiple Sclerosis.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Belberrry Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>129 Glen Osmond Road, Eastwood, SA 5063</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/03/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2014-02-083</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/02/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Prue Hart</name>
      <address>Telethon Kids Institute, PO Box 855, West Perth WA 6872</address>
      <phone>61 8 9489 7887</phone>
      <fax>61 8 9489 7700</fax>
      <email>Prue.Hart@telethonkids.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Prue Hart</name>
      <address>Telethon Kids Institute, PO Box 855, West Perth WA 6872 </address>
      <phone>61 8 9489 7887</phone>
      <fax>61 8 9489 7700</fax>
      <email>Prue.Hart@telethonkids.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Prue Hart</name>
      <address>Telethon Kids Institute, PO Box 855, West Perth WA 6872 </address>
      <phone>61 8 9489 7887</phone>
      <fax>61 8 9489 7700</fax>
      <email>Prue.Hart@telethonkids.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Prue Hart</name>
      <address>Telethon Kids Institute, PO Box 855, West Perth WA 6872 </address>
      <phone>61 8 9489 7887</phone>
      <fax>61 8 9489 7700</fax>
      <email>Prue.Hart@telethonkids.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>