<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336580">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/02/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/02/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000214932</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Primary Care-Aging Services Partnership in Dementia Care</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of physician training and support, combined with community Alzheimer's disease and related disorders (ADRD) service provision, on physician rates of diagnosis and treatment of ADRD, referrals to community service providers, caregiver well-being and health service costs when compared to usual dementia care.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1119-5749</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Alzheimer's Disease and related disorders</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dementias</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A one-day intensive dementia care preceptorship for primary care physicians, including resource materials, newsletter updates and informal neurological consultations if desired.

Linkage to a direct, single entry point referral system through Project CARE ("Caregiver Alternatives to Running on Empty") via phoned or faxed referrals from the physicians trained at the preceptorship. This is a family consultant program for families caring for someone with dementia at home which will link families to a host of services including in home evaluations, respite care, legal services, etc. Services will be studied in the 10 months post-preceptorship but will be available indefinitely as the funding provides.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual dementia care (i.e. no primary care education, no access to Project CARE resources until after research period has ended, thus delayed intervention)</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of patients diagnosed with Alzheimer's disease and related disorders (ADRD) via Medicare records</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 10 months post-preceptorship</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Satisfaction with services and caregiving burden reported by family caregivers via a single 10 minute telephone interview.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 10 months post-preceptorship</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health care costs as estimated via Medicare records</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 10 months post-preceptorship</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measures of impact of physician training activities via physician-completed questionnaires created for this study</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-training, immediately post-training, 6 months and 12 months post training</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Referral and service provision rates for intervention physicians' ADRD patients via service provider records</outcome>
      <timepoint>Over the course of 12 months post-training</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Providers must be active primary care MDs (with Internal Medicine or Family Medicine specialties) who practice in the 4 targeted counties (Alamance, Guilford, Rockingham and Caswell, NC) and provide care for large numbers of community dwelling older persons.

Patients and their caregivers (both interviewed and studied through existing Medicare data only) will be included if the patient is community-dwelling with the caregiver at the time of data request, are diagnosed with dementia (using a list of diagnostics codes for dementia), and are active patients of enrolled physicians who have been seen in the office post-preceptorship. For the caregivers, they must have English as their primary spoken language</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Non-English speaking caregivers will be excluded.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A list of eligible physicians will be obtained by asking for recommendations of those who may be interested in dementia care from community leaders as well as via NC medical board website.

A statistician using computer generated randomization method will provide a list of intervention vs. delayed intervention physicians</concealment>
    <sequence>A statistician using computer generated randomization method will provide a list of intervention vs. delayed intervention physicians. Recruitment of physicians will follow the random order of this list.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/02/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <state>NC</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Philip Sloane, MD</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Sheps Center for Health Services Research
725 MLK Jr Blvd
Chapel Hill NC 27514</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>US Administration on Aging</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>One Massachusetts Avenue NW
Washington, DC 20001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to compare an intervention consisting of  an intensive Alzheimers Disease and related disorders (ADRD) training and continuing support for primary care providers as well as enhanced availability of community counseling and support resources for their referred patients and caregivers, to usual dementia care. Outcomes of interest include perceived knowledge and practice changes of physicians post-training, numbers of ADRD diagnoses and referrals, satisfaction with services and caregiving burden reported by caregivers, rates of hospitalization and nursing home placement of persons with ADRD and estimated costs of services received and health services utilized.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of North Carolina Institutional Review Board</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>CB # 7097, Medical Building 52
105 Mason Farm Road
Chapel Hill NC 27599</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/01/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1/10/2275</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/12/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>United States of America</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Philip Sloane</name>
      <address>Sheps Center for Health Services Research
725 MLK Jr Blvd
Chapel Hill NC 27514</address>
      <phone>+ 1 919 966 7173</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>psloane@med.unc.edu</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Christine Lathren</name>
      <address>Sheps Center for Health Services Research
725 MLK Jr Blvd
Chapel Hill NC 27514</address>
      <phone>+ 1 919 966 7173</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lathren@schsr.unc.edu</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>