<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371250">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001074482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Secure My Intravascular Line Effectively (SMILE): a pilot randomised controlled trial to improve the dressing and securement of arterial catheters inserted in the adult intensive care unit.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Pilot randomised controlled trial testing alternative securement (integrated securement device) to prevent arterial catheter failure for catheters inserted in the adult intensive care unit.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1186-1790</utrn>
    <trialacronym>The SMILE Trial: Adult Arterial Catheters</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Arterial device failure prior to completion of therapy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants in this study will have intra-arterial catheters (IAC) inserted in adult intensive care departments. Consenting patients will have their IAC dressed and secured with one of the two following randomly assigned options:

Arm 1 (Control): Simple polyurethane dressing (SP), with gauze/foam applied as per hospital policy

Arm 2: Integrated securement device. Integrated securement devices (ISDs) are simple polyurethane dressings which combine both dressing and securement properties into one product.

Patients will be monitored daily to ensure protocol adherence. The randomly allocated dressing will be applied from device insertion and changed as clinically indicated until removal of device.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group patients will have their arterial catheter secured with a simple polyurethane dressing, with gauze/foam applied as per hospital policy, (standard care) at the time of catheter insertion until device removal.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary aim of this study is to pilot test the feasibility of a randomised trial that compares the effectiveness of new generation securement and dressing products for intra-arterial catheters. Feasibility measures will include: patient eligibility (more than 80% of those screened); consent (more than 80% agree to enrol); protocol adherence (more than 90% receive the allocated intervention); and retention (less than 5% of enrolled patients lost to follow up).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of trial completion.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>All cause IAC failure

A composite of infection (laboratory confirmed local or bloodstream infection), occlusion, dislodgement (complete or partial), infiltration / extravasation, local arterial inflammation, thrombosis, and inaccurate arterial pressure trace. This composite measure incorporates the multifocal path to the same endpoint; IAC failure. These will be assessed by either the Research Nurse (during daily checks); recorded on a 1 page data collection sheet at the patient's bedside by the treating clinician; or identified in a review of the patient's medical record.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of IAC removal.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Infection (laboratory confirmed local or bloodstream infection): IAC skin and tip samples for culture may be collected by RNs upon IAC removal if clinical suspicion of local infection. Blood cultures may be be collected by RNs throughout the life of the device if clinical suspicion of systemic infection.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Whilst the IAC is insitu and on device removal</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Occlusion: Defined as the IAC will not aspirate, infuse, or leakage occurs when fluid is infused.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily from IAC insertion until the time of IAC removal.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dislodgement (partial or complete)
Partial - Change in IAC length at insertion site (inner catheter visible). This will be assessed by either the Research Nurse (during daily checks), or (if identified by the treating clinician) recorded on a 1 page data collection sheet at the patient's bedside or in the patient's medical record.
Complete - IAC completely leaves the artery. This will be recorded on a 1 page data collection sheet at the patient's bedside or in the patient's medical record by the treating clinician.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily from IAC insertion until the time of IAC removal.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Local inflammation of the artery: defined as 2 or more of pain, redness, swelling and a palpable cord. This will be assessed by either the Research Nurse (during daily checks), or (if identified by the treating clinician) recorded on a 1 page data collection sheet at the patient's bedside or in the patient's medical record.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily from IAC insertion until the time of IAC removal.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Thombosis (either suspected or confirmed): 
Suspected - As per treating clinician. This will be assessed by the treating clinician, recorded on a 1 page data collection sheet at the patient's bedside or in the patient's medical record.
Confirmed - Ultrasound confirmed thrombosed vessel at the IAC site. This will be identified by a review of the patient's medical records (including ultrasound findings).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily from IAC insertion until the time of IAC removal.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Interruption of arterial pressure trace: unable to accurately measure blood pressure via device
This will be assessed by either the Research Nurse (during daily checks), or (if identified by the treating clinician) recorded on a 1 page data collection sheet at the patient's bedside or in the patient's medical record</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily from IAC insertion until the time of IAC removal.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>IAC dwell time: Research staff will calculate time (in hours) from device insertion until removal using relevant information as recorded by clinical staff on a 1 page data collection sheet at the patients bedside and in the patients medical record.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of IAC removal</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Skin safety: Skin reactions related to dressings and securements will be monitored including itch; rash (raised or not raised); maceration; blistering; skin tearing; bruising; and pressure areas. This will be assessed by either the Research Nurse (during daily checks), or (if identified by the treating clinician) recorded on a 1 page data collection sheet at the patient's bedside or in the patient's medical record.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily from IAC insertion until the time of IAC removal.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Infiltration and Extravasation: Defined as an infusion leaking into subcutaneous tissue with/without surrounding tissue damage. This will be assessed by either the Research Nurse (during daily checks), or (if identified by the treating clinician) recorded on a 1 page data collection sheet at the patient's bedside or in the patient's medical record.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily from IAC insertion until the time of IAC removal.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>First dressing duration: time until first dressing requires changing due to non-routine causes
This will be assessed by either the Research Nurse (during daily checks), or (if identified by the treating clinician) recorded on a 1 page data collection sheet at the patient's bedside or in the patient's medical record</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily from IAC insertion until the time of first dressing change.
This will be assessed by either the Research Nurse (during daily checks), or (if identified by the treating clinician) recorded on a 1 page data collection sheet at the patient's bedside or in the patient's medical record</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Non-routine dressing change frequency
This will be assessed by either the Research Nurse (during daily checks), or (if identified by the treating clinician) recorded on a 1 page data collection sheet at the patient's bedside or in the patient's medical record</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily from IAC insertion until the time of IAC removal.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Staff and patient acceptability of the intervention - assessed on a 0-10 Likert scale .</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of IAC removal.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Informed written consent
2. IAC to be inserted
3. IAC scheduled/expected use &gt;24 hours
4. Patient aged 16 years or above
5, Patients admitted to the Intensive Care Unit</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Known, current bloodstream infection (within 48 hours)
2. Non-English speakers without interpreter
3. IACs inserted through diseased, burned or scarred skin
4, IACs inserted into the femoral artery
5. Other types of vascular access devices
6. Current skin tear/papery skin at high risk of tear
7. Known allergy to any study product
8. Previous enrolment in the current study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Research nurses (RNs) will screen patients daily and liaise heavily with the staff responsible for inserting the majority of IACs (anaesthetists, intensive care doctors). All eligible patients (or their representative) will be approached for written informed consent by the RN or inserter. If this is given, the staff member will log in to a centralised web-based randomisation service customised for the trial and be advised of group allocation. Computer generated allocation is provided by an independent randomisation service. Allocation is fully concealed until the patient is randomised.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated. Randomisation will be in a 1:1 ratio between the two study groups</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>28/04/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/11/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>110</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>9</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>20/11/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <hospital>The Prince Charles Hospital - Chermside</hospital>
    <postcode>4102 - Woolloongabba</postcode>
    <postcode>4032 - Chermside</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Griffith University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Menzies Health Institute Queensland
Griffith University
170 Kessels Road
Nathan, QLD, 4111</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Griffith University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Menzies Health Institute Queensland
Griffith University
179 Kessels Road
Nathan, QLD, 4111</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Not applicable</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Not applicable</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary aim of this study is to pilot test the feasibility of a randomised trial that compares the effectiveness of new generation securement and dressing products for intra-arterial catheters (IAC). The RCT aims to (i) identify clinical, cost-effective methods to prevent catheter failure due to infection, phlebitis, occlusion, and dislodgement; (ii) compare usual care dressings with a novel method; (iii) evaluate the acceptability of these devices to patients and health professionals; and (iv) study adverse effect profiles.

You may be eligible to participate in this trial if you are an intensive care patient over the age of 16 and are having an intra-arterial catheter inserted as part of your therapy (which is expected to remain in place for at least 24 hours).

All participants enrolled in this trial will be randomly allocated (by chance) to receive one of two IAC securement options. These will be either (i) the standard simple polyurethane dressing; or (ii) an integrated securement device and simple polyurethane dressing combined into a single device

The allocated dressing will be applied from device insertion until the time of device removal. Participants will be asked to rate the acceptability of the device and dressing, and the device will be observed closely to examine side effects, and device failures. It is hoped that the findings of this trial will provide information on which IAC securements  are most effective in preventing IAC failure.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>	Children's Health Queensland Hospital and Health Service Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 7, Centre for Children's Health Research
Lady Cilento Children's Hospital Precinct
62 Graham Street, South Brisbane, QLD, 4101</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/05/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/QRCH/75</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/04/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Griffith University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office for Research
Bray Centre, Nathan Campus
170 Kessels Rd
Nathan, QLD, 4111</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/06/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>NRS/2016/487</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/05/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Claire Rickard</name>
      <address>NHMRC Centre for Research Excellence in Nursing
Griffith University, Nathan Campus
170 Kessels Road
Nathan, QLD, 4111 </address>
      <phone>+61 7 3735 4886</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c.rickard@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Amanda Ullman</name>
      <address>NHMRC Centre for Research Excellence in Nursing
Griffith University, Nathan Campus
170 Kessels Road
Nathan, QLD, 4111</address>
      <phone>+61737357854</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.ullman@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Amanda Ullman</name>
      <address>NHMRC Centre for Research Excellence in Nursing
Griffith University, Nathan Campus
170 Kessels Road
Nathan, QLD, 4111</address>
      <phone>+61737357854</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.ullman@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>