<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83265">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/10/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/11/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000585325</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Early loading of mandibular single implant overdentures using a novel implant and attachment system: A randomized controlled clinical trial with laboratory component</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomized controlled clinical trial on the early loading of mandibular single implant overdentures using a novel implant and attachment system to resolve complete tooth loss in the mandible</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Total tooth loss- edentulism</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The participants will be randomly allocated into 3 groups, 2 test groups (groups 1 and 2) and 1 control group (group 3).  Test group 1 participants will each receive a single wide (8mm) diameter, roughened-surface, externally-hexed, screw-shaped implant (Max-8, Southern Implants, Irene, South Africa).  This implant has been originally developed by its manufacturer for immediate placement in fresh extraction sockets of molar teeth. The novel attachment system that will be used with this type of implant is made-up of a custom-made large ball abutment (5.9 mm) with a corresponding large plastic cap. Test group 2 participants will each receive a single regular (4mm) diameter, roughened-surface, screw-shaped implant (Neoss International, Harrogate, UK). The attachment system that will be used with this type of implant is the Locator attachment system. The control group participants (group 3) will each receive a single regular (3.75mm) diameter roughened-surface, externally hexed, screw-shaped implant (Southern Implants, Irene, South Africa). The attachment system that will be used with this type of implant is the standard (2.25mm) ball abutment with gold matrix. Surgical implant placement procedures for all 3 groups will follow a standardized one stage surgical approach with healing abutment connected to implants at surgery. Each single implant will be placed at the midline of the edentulous mandible of each participant. All the surgical procedures for implant placement are one-off procedures.
The loading protocol adopted in this trial is an early loading protocol at 6 weeks and described as follows: After 6 weeks of healing after implant surgery, the healing abutments (for all groups) will be removed and the final abutments (corresponding the type of implant used in each group) will be fitted.  A closed-mouth reline impression will be used to incorporate the corresponding matrix of each attachment into the mandibular denture of each participants thus converting into an implant overdenture.</interventions>
    <comparator>The regular diameter implant (Southern Implants, Irene, South Africa) together with its attachment system used for the control group has been successfully documented in the literature with several short-term randomized controlled clinical trials (Payne et al , 2003; Tawse-Smith et al, 2002) and hence used as control for test group 1 with the wide diameter implant and novel attachment system and for test group 2 which has regular diameter ( 4mm) implant and attachment system comparable to that of the control group but no documented published outcome available for their use yet. All procedures involved in the 3 groups are one-off procedures.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the surgical outcome (success) of using single midline implants to support mandibular overdentures for 1 year following early loading protocol at 6 weeks. The implant success will be measured according to the criteria prescribed by Albrektsson and Zarb (1998) which require marginal bone loss around the implant to be &lt; than 1.0 mm in the first year and &lt; than 0.2 mm every year after. This will be determined using standardized peri-apical radiographic procedures (Payne et al 2001).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessment of baseline bone level will be carried out at 6 weeks post-op when implants are loaded with the overdentures. The measurement will then be repeated 1 year later. Each participant will be subjected to one measurement annually. The marginal bone level measurements will be carried out using standardized peri-apical radiographs.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the prosthodontic outcome of mandibular single implant overdentures following early loading protocol at 6 weeks. The prosthodontic outcome will be measured by recording all maintenance events that will be endured by the implant overdenture starting from baseline (6 weeks post-op) up to the end of first year of service. These maintenance events will be allocated to 1 of 12 different categories of following the proposal of Payne et al (2001). The outcome of the implant overdenture at the end of the first year of service (based on these categories) will then be assigned to 1 of 6 objectively defined outcome fields: Success, Survival, Unknown, Dead, Retreatment (repair), and Retreatment (replace) otherwise known as the  Six-Field Protocol for Implant Overdentures (Payne et al, 2001).</outcome>
      <timepoint>The maintenance events recording will start from baseline (6 weeks post-op) which corresponds to the start of loading and continues all through and up to the end of the first year of service.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Elderly edentulous patients with history of difficulties with their complete mandibular dentures and with minimum height and width of bone at the midline of the mandible to accommodate a 7X8 mm diameter implants</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>90</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria: Any systemic or local condition contradictory to implant surgery; Bruxism, Irradiated or grafted jaws; Smoking &gt; 10 cigarettes a day; Drug abuse; Un-willingness to attend regular recalls.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients meeting the inclusion and exclusion criteria were enrolled and allocated to interventions using sealed envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>36</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Southern Implants</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Southern Implants, No. 1 Albert Road Irene 1675, South Africa</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>South Africa</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Southern Implants</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Southern Implants, No. 1 Albert Road Irene 1675, South Africa</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>South Africa</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Neoss International</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Neoss International, Windsor Building, Cornwall Road, Harrogate,  HG1, 2PW, UK</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>United Kingdom</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to test a new implant overdenture treatment design that is surgically less invasive and more affordable to elderly patients. It uses only a single wide implant in the middle of the lower jaw and a new attachment system that would hopefully require less maintenance.  The pool of participants will be from the Oral Implantology Research Group, Sir John Walsh Research Institute, School of Dentistry, University of Otago, Dunedin, New Zealand. The hypothesis to be tested are:
The first hypothesis is that there is no difference in the success rate between single wide diameter implants and standard diameter single implants supporting lower jaw overdentures for one year after early loading protocol at 6 weeks after surgical placement.
The second hypothesis is that there is no difference in the prosthodontic maintenance in the first year of service of lower jaw overdentures supported by single wide diameter implants and that of lower jaw overdentures supported by single regular diameter implants</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Lower South Regional Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Alan Payne</name>
      <address>Oral Implantology Resaearch Group
Sir John Walsh Research Institute
School of Dentistry
University of Otago
Great King Street, Dunedin 9016, New Zealnd</address>
      <phone>+ 64 3 479119</phone>
      <fax>+ 64 3 4795079</fax>
      <email>alan.payne@dent.otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Alan Payne</name>
      <address>Oral Implantology Resaearch Group
Sir John Walsh Research Institute
School of Dentistry
University of Otago
Great King Street, Dunedin 9016, New Zealnd</address>
      <phone>+ 64 3 479119</phone>
      <fax>+ 64 3 4795079</fax>
      <email>alan.payne@dent.otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>