<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335434">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/05/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/05/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000377033</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Hemiparetic Gait: A Comparison Between Overground And Treadmill</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>After 15 minutes of treadmill walking patients with hemiparesis showed equivalence in most of the spatial-temporal and angular variables during overground walking</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hemiparetic gait</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Evaluation of kinematic of the hemiparetic lower limb and apatial-temporal data of hemiparetic gait overground and on the treadmill with the same speed. The overground walking data was obtained first of all with patients walking on a 8-m long walkway. Then was assessed the treadmill walking during 15 minutes, wich was subdivided into three 5-minute collections. A three-minute rest period was allowed between each collection. The images on the treadmill condition were captured at the 4th minute of each collection.</interventions>
    <comparator>All participants take part in the overground and treadmill walking. The overground walking data act as the comparator treatment of the results obtained at the three 5-minutes collections on the treadmill walking.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>There were alterations in some of the spatio-temporal characteristics on the treadmill walking compared to overground walking registered by the Motion Capture System (Qualisys AB). Cadence increased 3,8%, stride lenght and paretic limb step time decreased 5% and 4,9% respectively.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 5 minutes of treadmill walking.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>There were alterations in some of the Kinematic characteristics on the treadmill walking compared to overground walking registered by the Motion Capture System (Qualisys AB).There were a increase of 26.8% in knee angle at initial contact, 9.7% and 14.3% in hip and knee amplitude respectively. There were a decrease of 61.4% in maximum knee stance extension and 24% in maximum ankle dorsiflexion in the stance fase.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 5 minutes of treadmill walking.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hip amplitude, knee angle at initial contact and maximum knee stance extension were not significantly altered on the treadmill walking compared to overground walking registered by the Motion Capture System (Qualisys AB).</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 15 minutes of treadmill walking.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>There were increases of 3.6% in cadence and 14% in knee amplitude on the treadmill walking compared to overground walking registered by the Motion Capture System (Qualisys AB). There were decreases of 5% in stride lenght, 6,1% in paretic limb step time and 27,3% in maximum dorsiflexion on the treadmill walking compared to overground walking registered by the Motion Capture System (Qualisys AB).</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 15 minutes of treadmill walking.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Hemiparesis resulting from a single ischemic or hemorrhagic stroke event; lesion time of more than 6 months; levels 1 and 2 on the modified Ashworth Scale for the paretic lower limb; Functional Ambulatory Category 3 -5;  absence of clinical signs of cardiac alterations, arrhythmia or angina (New York Heart Association degree I); and little or no treadmill experience.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>39</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>76</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Inability to complete 15 minutes of treadmill walking due to phobia, for exceeding 75% of maximum cardiac frequency or for increasing 10mmHg in the sistolic arterial pressure of the beginning of the evaluation.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures>The subjects underwent to one day of assessment for the following procedures: overground walking and treadmill walking.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/01/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Natal, Rio Grande do Norte.</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Federal University of Rio Grande do Norte</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Av. Senador Salgado Filho, 3000 Caixa Postal 1524 - CEP:59072-970 Natal - Rio Grande do Norte</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Brazil</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Cientifico e Tecnologico</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>SEPN 507, Bloco B - Ed. Sede do CNPq, Brasilia - Distrito Federal -CEP 70740-901</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Brazil</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study was to analyze the angular variables of the paretic lower limb and the spatial-temporal characteristics of overground and treadmill walking at different time intervals. A total of 17 individuals with chronic hemiparesis who walked on a treadmill took part in the study. After the first 5 minutes of treadmill walking there was a 3.8%increase in cadence, 26.8% in knee angle at initial contact, 9.7% and 14.3% in hip and knee amplitude respectively and a 5% decrease in stride length, 4,9% in paretic limb step time, 61.4% in maximum stance extension and 24% in maximum ankle dorsiflexion in the stance phase compared to  overground walking. After 15 minutes of treadmill walking, cadence, knee amplitude, stride length, paretic limb step time and maximum dorsiflexion continued to differ from the overground condition, with increases of 3.6% and 14% and a decrease of 5%, 6.1% and 27.3%, respectively. Subjects with hemiparesis showed equivalence in most of the spatial-temporal and angular variables during overground walking and after 15 minutes of treadmill walking, suggesting that continuous exposure to a treadmill allowed for task repetition and approximation to the overground gait pattern.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Not published yet. Submitted to Gait&amp;Posture.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Research Ethics Committee of the Federal University of Rio Grande do Norte</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Av. Senador Salgado Filho, 3000 Caixa Postal 1524, Natal - Rio Grande do Norte -CEP:59072-970</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/10/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>266/2008</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Brazil</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Luciana de Andrade Mendes</name>
      <address>R. Souza Machado, 1030, Tirol, Natal - RN
CEP 59015-080</address>
      <phone>55 84 9928 1101</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lumendes_pe@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ana Raquel Rodrigues Lindquist</name>
      <address>Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Norte - UFRN Departamento de Fisioterapia Centro de Ciencias da Saude Av. Senador Salgado Filho, 3000, Natal-RN Caixa Postal 1524 - CEP:59072-970</address>
      <phone>55 84 3342 2010</phone>
      <fax>55 84 3342 2000</fax>
      <email>raquellindquist@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ana Raquel Rodrigues Lindquist</name>
      <address>Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Norte - UFRN Departamento de Fisioterapia Centro de Ciencias da Saude Av. Senador Salgado Filho, 3000, Natal-RN Caixa Postal 1524 - CEP:59072-970</address>
      <phone>55 84 3342 2010</phone>
      <fax>55 84 3342 2000</fax>
      <email>raquellindquist@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>