<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373163">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/06/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001076369p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Assessing the use of vaginal pessaries to assist women with symptomatic utero-vaginal prolapse in low-income countries</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of vaginal pessaries for women with symptomatic pelvic organ prolapse in low-income countries</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>utero-vaginal prolapse</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other renal and urogenital disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Using vaginal pessaries in the management of women with symptomatic pelvic organ prolapse and teaching women to self-manage the pessary.

All eligible women presenting with symptomatic pelvic organ prolapse will be invited to participate.
All women participating or not, will be have a gynaecological history taken and examined. The pelvic organ prolapse will be documented using the standardised Pelvic Organ Prolapse Quantification (POPQ) score.
Women participating will have the vaginal pessary, its use and self-management instructions given in the local language by the local nurses. The pessary will initially be inserted by the local nurse and then by the woman as she learns to self-manage the pessary. The pessary is to be worn 24 hours per day for 3 days.
The woman will be shown how to remove the pessary, clean the pessary and how to reinsert the pessary by the local nurse. The nurse will provide one-on-one verbal and hands-on instructions. 
No written instructions will be give as the women are usually illiterate and there are a number of local languages. No instructional images will be given as not to offend some women and their families by the gynaecological images because of cultural beliefs.

The pessary is a soft silicone device, round or oval in shape inserted into the vagina like a tampon, The pessary acts as a mechanical support device for the pelvic organ prolapse. This is an established method of treatment for pelvic organ prolapse.

On day 1 and day 3, the women will be reviewed by the nurses to ascertain if there are any problems with the pessary - did it fall out, is it comfortable, is it holding the prolapse up or if the woman has any other questions.</interventions>
    <comparator>no control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome - pessary staying in-situ to support the pelvic organ prolapse.
Patients self-report and the local nurses reviews the patients </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline - insertion of pessary, 1 day post-insertion of pessary , 3 days post-insertion of pessary</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Local nurse will review daily on removal and reinsertion of pessary
Yes - to adequate self-removal and reinsertion of pessary
No - unable to remove and reinsert pessary


</outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 1-3.
Patient reviewed by local nurses</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient comfort using Visual Analogue score (0-100%).
0 = no pain
100% = severe pain</outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 1-3.
Review by local nurses</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Whether the women are able to self-manage the pessary.
The local nurse will review the women - either the women are able to remove and insert the pessaries themselves or not.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline- insertion of pessary, 1 day post-insertion of pessary, 3 days post-insertion of pessary</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All women presenting with symptomatic pelvic organ prolapse</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Women without prolapse
Women who refuse to try the pessary as a management option for prolapse
Women with cultural/religious beliefs precluding the use of pessary</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>not applicable</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Uganda</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Myanmar</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Bangladesh</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Judith Goh  AO</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Suite 209
Ramsay Specialist Centre
Newdegate Street
Greenslopes Hospital
Greenslopes QLD 4120</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Health and Development Aid Abroad</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 733
Ashmore City  QLD 4214

(patient care/pessary donated. Researcher's time not funded)</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Pelvic organ prolapse is a common problem for women throughout the millennia. About 50% of women who have had vaginal births will develop a vaginal prolapse later in life but only about 10% are symptomatic. The prolapse is similar to a hernia, presenting as a lump protruding out of the vagina. The management of prolapse includes pelvic floor physiotherapy, vaginal pessary and surgery.  Surgery is generally limited to women who have completed their family. The pessary for prolapse is a mechanical support device, inserted into the vagina to elevate the prolapse. 

The use of pessaries to assist women with uterovaginal prolapse have been used for over 2 thousand years. Hippocrates used sea-sponge or half a pomegranate, inserted into the vagina to elevate the prolapse. Over the years, as technology improved, different materials and shapes of pessaries have been used. Today, common materials used include PVC, plastics and silicone. Pessaries are used in Australia today, often as first line treatment of prolapse.

Women in low income countries develop significant prolapse because of the high number of children they deliver and the heavy workload e.g. carrying buckets of water, firewood, digging in the fields. For these women, the vaginal lump causes significant social issues and often their husbands do not accept their condition. Health care, in particular operations, are often too expensive for the women in poor rural areas.

Although there is ample data and trial in the use of pessaries for prolapse in high income countries, little is available for low income countries. This is partly due to lack of resource, knowledge and cost. Some women prefer to return to the doctor every 4-6 months for review of pessary. This can be avoided if the women are able to and willing to self-manage the pessary. Self-management of pessaries would reduce the cost as there will not be any transportation or health professional fees. 

The aim of this study is to assess the feasibility of using vaginal pessaries in low income countries and to teach women to self-manage the pessaries.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>not applicable</trialwebsite>
    <publication>not applicable</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Nil</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Greenslopes Ethics &amp; Research Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Greenslopes Hospital
Newdegate Street
Greenslopes QLD 4120</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/06/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373163-Patient Information Sheet pessary_JGoh .docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373163(v20-06-2017-07-56-08)-Consent Form_JGoh.docx</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Judith Goh  AO</name>
      <address>Suite 209
Ramsay Specialist Centre
Newdegate Street
Greenslopes Private Hospital
Greenslopes QLD 4120</address>
      <phone>+61 7 38479909</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 38476433</fax>
      <email>jtwgoh@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Judith Goh  AO</name>
      <address>Suite 209
Ramsay Specialist Centre
Newdegate Street
Greenslopes Private Hospital
Greenslopes QLD 4120</address>
      <phone>+61 7 38479909</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 38476433</fax>
      <email>jtwgoh@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Judith Goh  AO</name>
      <address>Suite 209
Ramsay Specialist Centre
Newdegate Street
Greenslopes Private Hospital
Greenslopes QLD 4120</address>
      <phone>+61 7 38479909</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 38476433</fax>
      <email>jtwgoh@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Judith Goh  AO</name>
      <address>Suite 209
Ramsay Specialist Centre
Newdegate Street
Greenslopes Private Hospital
Greenslopes QLD 4120</address>
      <phone>+61 7 38479909</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 38476433</fax>
      <email>jtwgoh@hotmail.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>