<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373214">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/06/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000989347</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pain assessment and management for older people with dementia in hospitals</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Nursing practice of pain assessment and management for older people with dementia in hospitals</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1198-4495</utrn>
    <trialacronym>OPWD</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pain </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Dementia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dementias</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Undermanaged pain among older patients with dementia continues to be of concern. The reviewed evidence indicated that pain has not been well assessed and pain assessment tool has not been routinely used for patients with dementia. This requires an attention among the health care professionals in pain and dementia care, in particular for older patients with dementia who may have difficulty report their pain through verbal communication. 

The aims of this study are to explore if older people with dementia self-report pain while hospitalised and to examine whether routinisation of pain assessment by nurses has an effect on pain management for older patients with dementia in acute care settings. 
The study will be conducted in two local health district hospitals (Gosford and Wyong). Four units will be randomly assigned into two for intervention units and two for control units.    

The study will use both quantitative and qualitative methods. A quasi-experimental design will be employed as quantitative methodology. The study will conduct auditing of patients' medical records, surveying nurses, and delivering the information sessions, An individual interview and document analysis will be employed as qualitative approaches. The study will use a developed pain checklist for conducting an audit, Tool for Evaluating the ways Nurse Assess Pain (TENAP) for nurses' survey, ASK 4 brochures and ASK 4 portable cards for the information sessions and in nurses' daily practice. 

The study comprises three stages: pre-intervention stage, intervention stage, and post-intervention stage. In pre-intervention stage, the study will audit of patients medical records (Document analysis) using a developed pain checklist. Nurses' survey (TENAP) will be distributed to all the participation units. For the intervention stage, the study will held several Information/education sessions. The  information sessions will take place in every week throughout 6 weeks of the intervention program, and it will take about 20-30 minutes for each information session. The nurses (n=30-40) who work in the two intervention units will be invited to attend the information sessions for the entire 6 weeks of the intervention program. The intervention 'ASK 4' algorithm will be introduced. The ASK 4 comprised 4 simple steps that prompt nurses to initiate a pain assessment when caring for patients with dementia. The Ask 4 includes 1.DO YOU HAVE PAIN? 2. DOCUMENT THE SCORE 3. PROVIDE NURSING ACTION 4. REASSESS and ENTER in nursing progress notes. Nurses attending the information sessions will be informed about how to implement ASK 4 into their routine vital sign round including 1). the importance of patients self-report pain, 2). utilise the pain assessment tools including self-report and observation pain tools into routine practice, 3). take action into pain management, 4). reassessment, and documentation. The designed ASK 4 cards will be distributed as a reminder of the everyday practice of pain in dementia. The researcher who is an experienced Registered Nurse and PhD candidate will deliver the information sessions. The dementia care providers are the Registered Nurses (RNs) who work regularly in the participantion units. Those RNs include senior, experienced, and new graduated nurses on the wards. The care provided is part of their routine practice. There is no direct contact to the patients with dementia. After the intervention stage, the study will conduct auditing of medical records, TENAP nurses' survey again and interview of the individual nurses.. 



  

</interventions>
    <comparator>Four participation units will be randomly assigned into two for intervention units and two for control units. The nurses who work in the intervention units have a choice of whether to participate in the intervention program. For nurses who work in the control units will not receive information session for the 'ASK 4' intervention. There is no direct contact with patients. The auditing of patient's medical records will be recruited according to inclusion criteria which are patients with dementia and age 65 and over.        
The study will compare the differences between the intervention groups and the control groups, and the group differences between the pre and post of the intervention program.   </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome measure of the study is to measure if patients with dementia self-reported pain. Both control and intervention units' patient medical records will be assessed for self-pain reports in patient with dementia by measuring the use of Numeric rating scale (NRS), Visual analogue scale (VAS), FACE scale, and Face, Legs, Activities, Cry, Cosolidation (FLACC) pain tools. The pain tools used and the level of pain score documented will be recorded into Stata 14 to examine if the proportion of patients with dementia are able to self report their pain while hospitalised.    </outcome>
      <timepoint>the timepoint for measuring the primary outcome will be evaluated in 4 weeks in pre-intervention stage and 4 weeks after the intervention </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>An additional primary outcome of the study is to test if nominalising a pain assessment as 5th vital sign has an effect on nurses' pain management for older people with dementia. By auditing patients medical records using the developed pain checklist before and after the intervention program, we will be able to measure the difference before and after the intervention program in nurses' everyday pain practice in patients with dementia.    </outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be evaluated 4 weeks before and after the intervention program</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The nurses knowledge, attitude, report pain practice before and after the intervention program will be measured by TENAP survey. The data drawn from the individual interview will also provide a deep understanding about nurses knowledge and experience in the process of implementation . </outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be evaluated 4 weeks before and 4 weeks after the intervention program  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The study will generate secondary outcome about if there are any incident report is related to pain issue in patient with dementia. This will be measured by document analysis of the qualitative data from the pain checklist. The study will record the cause of the incident report in patients with dementia to measure if pain is correlated to the incident report (types of incident) during hospitalisation.      </outcome>
      <timepoint>The secondary timepoint will be measured 4 weeks in pre-intervention stage and 4 weeks after the intervention program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The study will also reveal the pain prevalence among hospitalised older patients with dementia by aggregation the numbers of pain report in patients with dementia. Pain has been defined as ''whatever the experiencing person says it is, existing whenever the experiencing person say it does  (McCaffery, 1968, p.95.). Thus the pain report from the pain score documented will reveal that if patient has pain during the admission. Pain score other than 0 is considering the perception of pain.       </outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be measured 4 weeks in pre-intervention stage and 4 weeks after the intervention stage. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary outcome of the study will also reveal if pain is related to an extended hospital stay. By document analysis of the patients' medical records, we shall be able to assess what is the causes for the patients with dementia to stay in the hospital longer than its primary diagnosis. We will measure how many of the patients with dementia extending the hospitalisation because of the pain issue.       </outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be measured 4 weeks in pre-intervention stage and 4 weeks after the intervention stage.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients:
Patients aged 65 years and over who have a diagnosis of dementia will be included in the study. Dementia diagnosis is confirmed with a structured clinical assessment based on international DSM-IV criteria, and or had a clear documented dementia diagnosis in the electronic medical record system (EMR).
Nurses:
The Registered Nurses (RNs) who work in the participation units on a regular basis and have a direct involvement in the care of older patients with dementia will be recruited. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients without dementia diagnosis and documented
All Registered Nurses in the participation units will be included </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>NA</concealment>
    <sequence>NA</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Quantitative data
All quantitative data will be entered into password-protected excel spreadsheet and import into Stata 14 (StataCorp. 2015. Stata Statistical Software) for analysis. Descriptive statistics will be used to report the participants (nurses and patients) demographic data. Patients types of dementia behaviours, types of incident report and extended of hospitalisation that were correlated to pain will be summarised with descriptive statistic using mean, median and standard deviation (SD). For the patient groups, we are comparing two independent samples (patients are likely to be different before and after the intervention program due to fast hospital admissions and discharges. And it will be the different sample group between the intervention groups and the control groups). Assuming that the data are normally distributed, a parametric test of two independent sample t-test will be used (or if, non-parametric test). For the nurse groups, we are comparing two dependent sample (RN survey participants), a one sample dependent t-test will be used. The categorical data such as types of pain tool used, types of dementia, types of pain medication prescribed and administered between the groups will be tested with Chi-square test. Those variable differences between the groups will be examined by Logistic regression. 

Qualitative data
For the qualitative data, the interview will be audio recorded and transcribed verbatim. All qualitative data will be analysed using direct content analysis with NPT to identify themes and underlying meaning of the text (Graneheim &amp; Lundman, 2004; Potter &amp; Levine-Donnerstein, 1999). The process will be a series of moving back and forth to achieve saturation, including reading transcripts several times, coding the data, generating the themes among each independent researchers (Ngulube, 2015; Streubert &amp; Carpenter, 2011). The qualitative data will be recorded in word document and use NVivo 11 (QSR International's NVivo 11 Software) to facilitate data analysis.     
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/07/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>29/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>29/12/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Gosford Hospital - Gosford</hospital>
    <hospital>Wyong Public Hospital - Hamlyn Terrace</hospital>
    <postcode>2250 - Gosford</postcode>
    <postcode>2259 - Hamlyn Terrace</postcode>
    <postcode>2259 - Wyong</postcode>
    <postcode>2250 - North Gosford</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Sarah Jeong</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Newcastle
Ourimbah campus
10 Chittaway Road
Ourimbah NSW 2258
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The university of Newcastle</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University Dr, Callaghan NSW 2308</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Undermanaged pain among older patient with dementia continues to impact on patient centre care provided among acute care settings. As the dementia population continues to grow, there is a need to address this issue by finding the solution for a better outcome. The challenges in assessing pain in dementia play a major barrier for nurses in conducting effective pain management (Bruneau &amp; Benjamin, 2014; Coker et al., 2008; De Witt Jansen et al., 2017; Laflamme et al., 2012; Rantala, Kankkunen, Kvist, &amp; Hartikainen, 2014b). This intervention study aims to investigate if nurses daily pain assessment and management for older patients with dementia can be improved by a simple and routinised intervention program. The project will introduce an innovative intervention program, which prompts nurse participants to undertake pain assessment during their routine vital sign round, that is, pain become embedded as a fifth vital sign.

The study aims:
1). To explore if older people with dementia provide self-report of pain while hospitalised; 2). To examine whether routinisation of pain assessment and subsequent management by nurses has an effect on pain management in older people with dementia in hospital settings.

Study hypothesis:
H0:	1. There are no differences before and after the intervention program in the level of self-reported pain by older patients with dementia between two groups; intervention groups and control groups.
2. There are no effect on nurses practice in the routinisation of pain assessment and management for older patients with dementia before and after the intervention program between two groups; intervention groups and control groups.
Ha: 1. There are differences before and after the intervention program in the level of
self-reported pain by older patients with dementia between two groups; intervention groups and control groups.
2. There are effect on nurses practice in routinisation of pain assessment and management for older patients with dementia before and after the intervention program between two groups; intervention groups and control groups.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Local Health District (HNELHD) Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Hunter  New  England  Local  Health  district,  Locked  Bag  1,   New
Lambton, NSW, 2305
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/12/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HNEHREC Reference No: 16/12/14/5.09 NSW HREC Reference No: LNR/16/HNE/578</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/12/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Central Coast Local Health District (CCLHD) Site Specific Assessment</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>RESEARCH - Central Coast Local Health District
 Holden St, level 1 health service building, Gosford NSW 2250 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/04/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>0117-009C</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>31/01/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373214-1612145.09 Ongoing LNR Approval Single-site LeadHREC.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373214-0117-009C - CCLHD - SSA LNR - Approval Letter.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373214-Appendix 4 Participant information statement.doc</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Sarah Jeong</name>
      <address>The University of Newcastle 
Ourimbah Campus
10 Chittaway Road
Ourimbah NSW 2258
Australia
</address>
      <phone> +61 2 4349-4535</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Sarah.Jeong@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sharyn Hunter</name>
      <address>The University of Newcastle 
Callaghan Campus
University Drive, Callaghan
NSW 2308, Australia
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4921 5957</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Sharyn.Hunter@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>I-Pei Tsai</name>
      <address>The University of Newcastle
Ourimbah Campus
10 Chittaway Road
Ourimbah NSW 2258
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 451115318</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>I-Pei.Tsai@uon.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>I-Pei Tsai</name>
      <address>The University of Newcastle
Ourimbah Campus
10 Chittaway Road
Ourimbah NSW 2258
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 451115318</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>I-Pei.Tsai@uon.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>