<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320801">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/11/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/11/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609001023246</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A prospective randomized control trial comparing a non adherent dry dressing with a silver foam dressing in the management of Kirscher wire (K-wire) pin sites in the closed fractures of the hand.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A prospective randomized control trial comparing a non adherent dry dressing with a silver foam dressing in the management of Kirscher wire (K-wire) pin sites in the closed fractures of the hand.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>The incidence of infection after K-wire insertion using a dry non-adherent and a wet wound dressing</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>The ease of application and removal between the two dressings</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Comparison of the  ease of application and removal between the two dressings</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Comparison of pain assoicated with the application and removal of the two dressings</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fractures</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The K-wire is inserted as per normal surgical practice.  The wound is dressed using  the dry dressing.  As per standard clinical practice - the patient attends outpatients weekly for up to 8 weeks The dressing is assessed at each appointment as to whether it needs changing.  .K-wire removal usually occurring after 4 weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>The K-wire is inserted as per normal surgical practice.  The wound is dressed with  the silver foam dressing which is a wet dressing (compared to the dry control dressing).  As per standard clinical practice - the patient attends outpatients weekly for up to 8 weeks.  The dressing is assessed at each appointment to assess whether it needs changing. K-wire removal usually occurring after 4 weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The wound will be photographed at each weekly outpatient appointment and assessed on a pin infection rate scale (Sims and Saleh 1996). Temperature, Full blood examination (FBE),  erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR), c-reactive protein (CRP), X-ray will be done if the infection is graded at 3 or above.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weekly until removal of K-wire (usually up to 8 weeks)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ease of removal and application at each dressing change will be assessed using a  5 point scale (very easy through to very difficult)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At each dressing change</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain on removal of dressing will be assessed using a visual analog pain scale ( 0 - 10)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At each dressing change</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Need for cleanining of pin site will be assessed using Yes (pin site needs cleaning) or No (pin site is clean)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At each dressing change</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Closed fractures of the hand distal to the wrist crease</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>1</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>100</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Open fractures</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All subjects fitting the inclusion criteria will be invited to participate in the study. Allocation to a treatment group will be done by sealed envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Peninsula health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 52
Frankston  VIC 3199</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Peninsula health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 52
Frankston  VIC 3199</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Smith and Nephew</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>P O Box 242
Mount Waverley VIC 3149</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study looks at two types of surgical wound dressing used after fixing fractures of the hand with a pin called a K-wire and whether there is a difference in infection rates and the ease of , and pain associated with, application and removal. 
When a person fractures a bone they may have a closed fracture or an open or compound fracture.  A closed fracture is when the broken bone does not penetrate the skin.  In this study, we are only looking at patients with closed fractures.  In addition, for inclusion in this study, the fracture must be of the hand higher (distal) than the wrist crease.
The Kirscher Wire Pin (commonly known as a K-wire) is a sharpened, sterilised metal pin that is used to hold the fractured bone fragments together.  After insertion of the K-wire, the wound is dressed and then assessed on a weekly basis for infection.  Infection is common (about 10% of cases) because the insertion of the wire through the skin into the bone creates a passage for bacteria. The area around the wire may become red and swollen and there may be a discharge.  Antibiotics may have to be prescribed and sometimes the pin needs to be removed prematurely.
Current practice involves dressing the wound in Melolin  a dry non-adherent sterile dressing and Mefix  a surgical tape.  In this study we would like to compare this dressing with a new anti-microbial barrier dressing which contain nanocrystalline silver.  This type of silver has long been known for its antimicrobial properties. 
The patients would be consented prior to surgery and then randomly allocated one of the two wound dressings.  For both arms of the study, the patients will be followed up and assessed in exactly the same manner.  
If a patient does not wish to participate in the trial the wound will be dressed in the dry dressing as is current practice.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Peninsula Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 52
Frankston  VIC 3199</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/11/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2009-66</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/10/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Patricia Terill</name>
      <address>Frankston Hospital
PO Box 52
Frankston  VIC 3199</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9784 7777</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>arizzitelli@phcn.vic.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Patricia Terill</name>
      <address>Frankston Hospital
PO Box 52
Frankston  VIC 3199</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9784 7777</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>arizzitelli@phcn.vic.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alexandra Rizzitelli</name>
      <address>Department of Surgery 
Frankston Hospital
PO Box 52
Frankston  VIC 3199</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>arizzitelli@phcn.vic.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Patricia Terrill</name>
      <address>Frankston Hospital, department of surgery
PObox52
Frankston Vic3199</address>
      <phone>613 9784 8416</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>arizzitelli@phcn.vic.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>