<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363067">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/09/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/10/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001090808</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Monitoring the Efficacy of Artesunate+Sulfadoxine-Pyrimethamine and Artemether Plus Lumefantrine in Uncomplicated Falciparum Malaria in Pakistan</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Monitoring the Efficacy of Artesunate+Sulfadoxine-Pyrimethamine and Artemether Plus Lumefantrine in Uncomplicated Falciparum Malaria in Pakistan</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Malaria</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>To assess the efficacy and safety of artesunate+sulfadoxine-pyrimethamine for the treatment of uncomplicated P. falciparum malaria in three sentinel sites in Pakistan.  The daily dose of artesunate (4 mg/kg) over 3 days co-administered with a single dose of sulfadoxine/pyrimethamine (25 mg sulfadoxine/1.25 mg pyrimethamine per kg) on day 0 will be administered orally.</interventions>
    <comparator>To assess the efficacy and safety of artemether-lumifantrine for the treatment of uncomplicated P. falciparum malaria in three sentinel sites in Pakistan.  An oral dose of artemether-lumefantrine (a tablet containing artemether 20 mg plus lumefantrine 120 mg): six-dose course over 3 days  (2 doses daily) according to weight bands (1 tab: 5-14kg, 2 tabs: 15-24kg, 3 tabs: 25-34kg  and 4tabs: greater than 35kg).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percent of treatment failures (early treatment failure + late clinical failure + late parasitological failure)

Enrolled patients will be assessed for parasitological (using microscopy), clinical responses during the 28 days follow-up and treatment outcomes will be classified according to the latest WHO protocol.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At day 28 following initiation of treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percent of adverse event will be documented. Parents or guardians of all enrolled patients will be asked routinely about previous symptoms and about symptoms that have emerged since the previous follow-up visit. When clinically indicated, patients will be evaluated and treated appropriately. All adverse events will be recorded on the case report form.

Possible medicine related adverse effects include dizziness, itching, vomiting, abdominal pain, flatulence, headache, bodyache, diarrhoea, tinnitus and increased hair loss, macular rash, reduction in neutrophil counts and convulsions. However, it is likely that many of these effects are disease-related rather than medicine-induced.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At day 28 following initiation of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Age greater than 6 months, excluding 12-17 old female minors and unmarried females aged 18 years and above;
2. mono-infection with P. falciparum detected by microscopy;
3. Parasitaemia of 1000  250000 / microlitre asexual forms for sites in Sindh, Balochistan and Khyber Pakhtoonkwa.
4. Presence of axillary temperature equal to or greater than 37.5 degrees celsius  or history of fever during the past 48 h;
5. Ability to swallow oral medication;
6. Ability and willingness to comply with the study protocol for the duration of the study and to comply with the study visit schedule; and
7. Informed consent from the patient or from a parent or guardian in the case of children.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Months</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Presence of general danger signs in children aged under 5 years or signs of severe falciparum malaria according to the definitions of WHO;
2. Mixed or mono-infection with another Plasmodium species detected by microscopy;
3. Presence of severe malnutrition (defined as a child whose growth standard is below 3 z-score, has symmetrical oedema involving at least the feet or has a mid-upper arm circumference less than 110 mm);
4. Presence of febrile conditions due to diseases other than malaria (e.g. measles, acute lower respiratory tract infection, severe diarrhoea with dehydration) or other known underlying chronic or severe diseases (e.g. cardiac, renal and hepatic diseases, HIV/AIDS);
5. Regular medication, which may interfere with antimalarial pharmacokinetics;
6. History of hypersensitivity reactions or contraindications to any of the medicine(s) being tested or used as alternative treatment(s); and
7. 12-17 old female minors and unmarried females aged 18 years and above;</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>People with uncomplicated malaria who meet the study inclusion criteria will be enrolled, treated on site with artesunate+sulfadoxine/ pyrimethamine or Artemether plus Lumifantrin, monitored for 28 days. The follow-up will consist of a fixed schedule of check-up visits and corresponding clinical and laboratory examinations.</concealment>
    <sequence>N/A This surveillance study is 2 x one-arm prospective evaluation of clinical and parasitological responses to directly observed treatment for uncomplicated malaria with either artesunate/amodiaquine or artemether/lumefantrine. Patients will be treated with artesunate+sulphadoxine /pyrimethamine in two sites (Women and Children Hospital Bannu in Khyber Pakhtoonkwa and DHQ Hospital Zhob) or with artemether-lumefantrine will be evaluated in two sites (University Hospital Jamshoro Hyderabad and DHQ Zhob).</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Nil</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/10/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>240</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Pakistan</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Bannu Medical College</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Bannu City,
Khyber Pakhtoonkhwa Province</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Pakistan</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>World Health Organization</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Avenue Appia 20
1211 Geneva 27</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Switzerland</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Efficacy and safety of artesunate + sulfadoxine+pyrimethamine and artemether/lumefantrine for the treatment of uncomplicated Plasmodium falciparum malaria in three sites in Pakistan</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>National Bioethics Committee (NBC) Pakistan</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Pakistan Medical Research Council
Shahrah-e Jamhuriat
Off Constitution Avenue
Sector G-5/2
Islamabad</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/09/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>4-87/12/NBC-101/RDC/863</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/06/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Pakistan</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethical Review Committee, World Health Organization</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Avenue Appia 20
1211 Geneva 27</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/08/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>RCP535</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/08/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Switzerland</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Shuaib Khan</name>
      <address>Bannu Medical College
Bannu City
Khyber Pakhtoonkhwa</address>
      <phone>+92 862 4305</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mshoaibkhan2003@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Pakistan</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Shuaib Khan</name>
      <address>Bannu Medical College
Bannu City
Khyber Pakhtoonkhwa</address>
      <phone>+92 862 4305</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mshoaibkhan2003@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Pakistan</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Alison Osborne</name>
      <address>Global Malaria Programme
World Health Organization
Avenue Appia 20
1211 Geneva 27</address>
      <phone>+41 22 791 2782</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>osbornea@who.int</email>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>