<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370693">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/05/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/05/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000636459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Early Capsule Endoscopy in Acute Upper Gastrointestinal Bleeding.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A prospective randomised control trial of Early Capsule Endoscopy in patients with Acute Upper Gastrointestinal Bleeding.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1182-8556</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute upper gastrointestinal bleeding</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This research involves procedures and clinical care which are performed as standard practice currently. Patients with a negative gastroscopy will be randomised to either the control group and receive a Colonoscopy, or the intervention group and receive a Capsule Endoscopy as their second investigation.
Those patients randomised to the Capsule Endoscopy group will be orally administered a single disposable endoscopy capsule which will pass through the gastrointestinal tract taking continuous images that will be sent to a data receiver, This data will be downloaed and interpreted by a trained gastroenterologist. This will all be completed during athe same inpatient hospital admission.</interventions>
    <comparator>Patients in the control group will be randomised to receive a colonoscopy following a negative gastroscopy, which is part of current standard clinical practice. A consultant gastroenterologist will perform the procedure of approximately 30 minutes duration, with anaesthesia provided by a consultant anaesthetist.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome will be the proportion of patients in whom a source of bleeding is identified on capsule endoscopy or colonoscopy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The primary timepoint will be 1 day after the colonoscopy or capsule endoscopy.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A secondary outcome will be number of blood transfusions received by a patient which will be determined through review of their electronic medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months after initial presentation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A secondary outcome will be length of hospital stay which will be determined through review of electronic medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months after initial presentation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A secndary outcome will be number of hospital representations which will be determined through review of the electronic medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months after initial presentation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be males or females who present with acute melaena and/or haematemesis and have a negative gastroscopy. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients less than 18 years of age and pregnant females will be excluded form this study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/06/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/05/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Gold Coast Hospital - Southport</hospital>
    <postcode>4215 - Southport</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>QLD Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Gold Coast University Hospital
1 Hospital Blvd
Southport, 4215, QLD</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Gold Coast University Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Gold Coast University Hospital
1 Hospital Blvd
Southport, 4215, QLD</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>All patients with upper gastrointestinal bleeding (UGIB) undergo a gastroscopy urgently. However, in a significant proportion of these patients a source is not identified. Small bowel bleeding is highly likely to be the source in a large number of these patients. This may be identified by capsule endoscopy. Proximal colonic bleeding is also likely in patients with melaena and is identifiable by colonoscopy.
As per current standard practice, patients will undergo a colonoscopy frequently or a capsule endoscopy (CE) less often, in an attempt to find the cause of bleeding. Capsule endoscopy is noninvasive, better tolerated and preferred by patients as bowel prep and anaesthesia are not required. However,it is uncertain who will benefit most by having a capsule endoscopy as the second test.
The focus of our study is to look at the subgroup of patients who will benefit most by having early Capsule Endoscopy in this context. The study aims to compare two groups of patients, one having capsule endoscopy VS the other having colonoscopy as the second test following a negative gastroscopy to determine differences in ability to detect bleeding source and therefore change patient outcome.
All patients with UGIB with a negative gastroscopy will be considered for the study.
This is a prospective randomised control trial. Primary endpoint measured will be identification of the source of bleeding. Secondary endpoints measured will be reduced blood transfusions, reduced length of stay, reduced number of investigations and reduced hospital admissions.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Gold Coast Hospital and Health Services Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Gold Coast University Hospital
1 Hospital Blvd, Southport, QLD, 4215</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/07/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/05/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/370693-Research Protocol - Early Capsule Endoscopy.docx</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tegan Stevenson</name>
      <address>Gold Coast University Hospital, 
1 Hospital Blvd
Southport, QLD, 4215</address>
      <phone>+61405736406</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tegan.stevenson@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tegan Stevenson</name>
      <address>Gold Coast University Hospital, 
1 Hospital Blvd
Southport, QLD, 4215</address>
      <phone>+61405736406</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tegan.stevenson@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tegan Stevenson</name>
      <address>Gold Coast University Hospital, 
1 Hospital Blvd
Southport, QLD, 4215</address>
      <phone>+61405736406</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tegan.stevenson@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tegan Stevenson</name>
      <address>Gold Coast University Hospital, 
1 Hospital Blvd
Southport, QLD, 4215</address>
      <phone>+61405736406</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tegan.stevenson@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>