<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83061">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/08/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/09/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000457347</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The efficacy of a novel, non-robotic intervention to train reaching post stroke</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>To investigate in stroke survivors undergoing inpatient rehabilitation, the degree of recovery of upper limb motor function that accrues from (A) usual care vs. (B) a non-robotic device (SMART Arm) alone + usual care vs. (C) SMART Arm with triggered electrical stimulation + usual care.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>SMART arm</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention group 1 - will undergo 30mins of SMART arm training + 30mins of usual care, 5 times per week, for 4 weeks. SMART arm training will involve the patient performing repetitive, incremental goal-oriented reaching tasks in sitting. Participants will be instructed to push along a linear slide to achieve full range elbow extension at a comfortable speed while receiving real-time visual feedback of performance. Each participant will perform consecutive movement trials for 30 minutes per session. Usual care will involve occupational therapy and physiotherapy intervention aimed to improve function and reduce impairments, performed by their treating therapist. It is likely to incorporate task-oriented activities with manual assistance given if the participant is unable to perform independently.
Intervention group 2 - will undergo 30mins of SMART arm training with triggered electrical stimulation + 30mins of usual care, 5 times per week, for 4 weeks. In this group, the SMART arm reaching tasks will be performed whilst electrical stimulation of triceps is provided concurrently.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group - will undergo 60mins total of usual care from occupational and physiotherapy combined for the upper limb.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Motor Assessment Scale item 6 (upper arm function).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, 1 month, 6 months and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Distance reached</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, 1 month, 6 months and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Force during reaching, as measured with a strain gauge</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, 1 month, 6 months and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Motor Assessment Scale items 7 and 8. These items assess upper arm function and hand activities.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, 1 month, 6 months and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Stroke Impact Scale. This measures how the stroke has impacted on health and life.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, 1 month, 6 months and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Individuals will be included if they: have a diagnosis of first ever stroke which occurred within 3mths of the initial test date, be unable to independently perform a standardised reaching task, and be admitted to the Princess Alexandra Hospital (PAH) or QEII hospitals, Brisbane Australia.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Individuals will be excluded if they have co-morbidities relating to the upper extremity that limit function, such as arthritis, brain injury, Parkinson disease or are unable to tolerate stimulation (e.g. due to hypersensitivity or a skin condition); if they are medically unstable; or are unable to understand the instructions or provide informed consent.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Potential participants will be identified by physiotherapy or occupational therapy staff who will approach patients to inform them of the trial if the treating medical officer is in agreement. Trial staff with then provide trial information sheets and answer queries. Allocation will be concealed through the use of numbered, opaque sealed envelopes and will be maintained at a central location.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be stratified by functional level (MAS-6 on admission) and will be performed offsite by an independent person using a computer generated random number sequence. Random permuted blocks will be used to ensure that the three groups have equal numbers after every block of participants.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>75</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Division of Physiotherapy, 
School of Health &amp; Rehabilitation Sciences 
Building 84A, Services Rd,
The University of Queensland St Lucia, Qld, 4072</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council GPO Box 1421 Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Up to 50% of stroke survivors are left with upper limb disability that limits their daily activities. Several studies have established that recovery of function post stroke is maximised by active, repetitive use of the involved limb in task oriented training programs. Unfortunately for many stroke
survivors, the degree of hemiparesis (or paralysis) is so severe that they are unable to generate enough strength to be involved in exercise training. To address this, a low cost, non-robotic training device (The SMART Arm) was developed by the investigators to provide a smooth and guided track to make reaching easier in people with severe weakness. Using the device with and without triggered electrical stimulation has led to improvements in function and strength in chronic stroke survivors. The current study aims to investigate the ability of the SMART arm with and without triggered stimulation to improve arm impairment, activity and participation in acute stroke survivors.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Queensland Medical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ground Floor, Cumbrae-Stewart Building (72)
Research Road
The University of Queensland St Lucia, Qld, 4072</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/12/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2007001628</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Princess Alexandra Hospital Medical Research Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Centres for Health Research Level 2, Building 35, Princess Alexandra Hospital Ipswich Rd Woolloongabba, Qld, 4102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/03/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2008/046</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Sandra Brauer</name>
      <address>School of Health &amp; Rehabilitation Sciences
Building 84A, Services Rd
The University of Queensland
St Lucia, Qld, 4072</address>
      <phone>07 3365 2317</phone>
      <fax>07 3365 1622</fax>
      <email>s.brauer@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Sandra Brauer</name>
      <address>Division of Physiotherapy
School of Health &amp; Rehabilitation Sciences
Building 84A, Services Rd
The University of Queensland
St Lucia, Qld, 4072</address>
      <phone>07 3365 2317</phone>
      <fax>07 3365 1622</fax>
      <email>s.brauer@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Sandra Brauer</name>
      <address>School of Health &amp; Rehabilitation Sciences
Building 84A, Services Rd
The University of Queensland
St Lucia, Qld, 4072</address>
      <phone>07 3365 2317</phone>
      <fax>07 3365 1622</fax>
      <email>s.brauer@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>