<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367987">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/02/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/03/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000224527</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Motivational Electronic Intervention Study for Patients Diagnosed with Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of a Motivational Electronic Intervention Study for Patients Diagnosed with Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus (T2DM) (not currently on prescribed insulin) to determine whether blood HbA1c levels can be successfully and significantly reduced through exercise and healthy eating over a 26-week period.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>The MEDS Clinical Trial </trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus (T2DM) </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention in this clinical trial relates to electronic/ internet aids (mobile phone text messaging, emails, website usage and the constant wearing of a fitness tracker wristband) that will prompt patients diagnosed with T2DM to provide timely information of their lifestyle changes as part of the clinical study assessment requisite for this trial. The duration of this study is 26 weeks. Text messages and emails will be sent to participants daily. Participants are asked to use the website at least once per day to log their food. Lifestyle changes from prospective participants in this clinical trial will be captured throughout the study, through a food log submitted though the website portal and exercise data collected through a fitness tracker wristband worn by participants constantly throughout the study. Participants will utilise the website daily to log food. The electronic intervention can be used by clinicians to tailor personalised health goals for patients diagnosed with T2DM. The electronic intervention is aimed at motivating, promoting and guiding the participant to execute a modest exercise and activity regime and dietary plan to reduce blood HbA1c levels. The Personalised e Health website contains diabetic friendly recipes, physical activity research and exercise tips, motivational quotes and facts on T2DM. Participants will be financially reimbursed (at beginning and end of trial) for their time to attend the screening visit and information visit at the clinic. The second payment at the end of the trail acts as an incentive to follow and complete the full trial. Participants also get to keep the fitness tracker wristband after the completion of the trial. If participants abandon the trial, the wristband will be taken back and financial travel reimbursement will discontinue. Stool samples will also be required on two occasions (baseline and 26 weeks), which will be collected by the participant in their own home and used to assess faecal microbial profiles. Participants will be provided with a specialised kit to collect the stool samples, which will be couriered to Bioscreen in Melbourne, at no cost for the participant.</interventions>
    <comparator>Baseline vs 26 weeks of intervention</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>HbA1c changes over duration of the study.  This will be assessed by Pathology testing- a 10 mL whole blood (EDTA or heparinized) sample will be collected from participants for HbA1c analyte. </outcome>
      <timepoint>26 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in participants weight over 26 week period, measured via scales.</outcome>
      <timepoint>26 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in blood pressure measured by blood pressure monitor</outcome>
      <timepoint>26 week study duration</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in waist circumference with tape measure</outcome>
      <timepoint>26 week study duration</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stool samples will be required on two occasions, which will be collected by the participant in their own home and used to assess faecal microbial profiles.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 26 weeks </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) Participants between 18 years and 75 years old
2) Ownership and ability to operate a smart phone and personal computer
3) Willingness to wear a fitness tracker wristband day and night (24 hours) 
throughout the entire study
4) Non-insulin-dependent type T2DM of more than 1 years duration
5) HbA1c no greater than 9.0% (75 mmol/mol) measured at the time of recruitment to the study
6) No chronic disease apart from (minor) complications of T2DM
7) Cognitive ability to give informed consent to participate</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) History of alcohol or substance abuse including use of illicit drugs
2) Female participants who are lactating or pregnant
3) Presence of significant diagnosed disease unrelated to T2DM
4) Presence of diagnosed psychiatric disease which would impair participation or where     participation could adversely the subject
5) Any other clinically relevant condition or abnormality, which, in the judgment of the clinical investigator, would make the subject unsuitable for the trial (e.g., dietary allergies, psychiatric symptoms, visual impairment etc.) 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>n-of-1 intervention trial with no control group</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>N/A</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>There was no statistical power and sample analysis carried out as there are no published studies on the use of electronic interventions to improve blood glucose management in type 2 diabetics.  As such, the current study was designed as a pilot probing study.   Furthermore, the data obtained from this study will allow for a more robust future study to be carried out.  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/06/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>17/07/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2015 - Alexandria</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Personalised e-Health Clinic</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>66 McCauley St, Alexandria, NSW 2015.
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Personalised e-Health Clinic</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>66 McCauley St, Alexandria, NSW 2015.

</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A preliminary trial to assess the effectiveness of lifestyle and dietary intervention for the management of T2DM using electronic reminders, a fitness tracker wristband collecting exercise data and a web-based questionnaire to encourage participation. The question to be answered is whether the provision of quality dietary and exercise information known to be of benefit in T2DM control is better adopted by diabetics using simple electronic reminders and easy access to that information. There will be no control group, and this is an "n-of-one" trial in which each participant acts as their own control the beginning of the study. The degree of the participation will be matched to the outcome measures (HbA1c) to determine effectiveness of the entire approach. There is potential for follow-up of willing participants at 12 months.

The hypothesis investigated for this clinical trial proposes to demonstrate that blood HbA1c levels can be successfully and significantly reduced through a healthy eating / exercise programme that is implemented at baseline to 25 weeks participation. Blood levels of HbA1c is an objective and accurate marker of metabolic syndrome status and T2DM progression. A 13.5 % (from at least e.g., 55.5 mmol/mol to 48 mmol/mol) reduction in blood HbA1C level will be associated with significant improved health outcomes from baseline. This benefit may translate into a significant reduction in health care costs associated with T2DM. The electronic intervention serves as a motivating tool and guide that supports patient programme compliance, resulting in fewer doctor and other allied health affiliated practitioner visits and most importantly decreased T2DM disease progression. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.personalisedehealth.com.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>National Institute of Integrative Medicine</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>21 Burwood Rd Hawthorn VIC 3122</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/02/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mark Donohoe</name>
      <address>Cremorne Medical Practice
1 Guthrie Ave, Cremorne, NSW, 2090 


</address>
      <phone>+ 61 (0)2 8969 6600</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 (0)2 8569 0185</fax>
      <email>doctormark@me.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Tessa Nikov</name>
      <address>Medlab Clinical 
66 McCauley St Alexandria NSW 2015</address>
      <phone>(02) 8188 0311</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tessa_nikov@medlab.co</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Luis Vitetta </name>
      <address>Medlab Clinical 
66 McCauley St Alexandria NSW 2015</address>
      <phone>+61281880311</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>luis_vitetta@medlab.co</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Tessa Nikov</name>
      <address>Medlab Clinical 
66 McCauley St Alexandria NSW 2015</address>
      <phone>+61401632036</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tessa_nikov@medlab.co</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>