<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343064">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/06/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/06/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000617965</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>New treatments for troublesome bleeding in Implanon users</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparison of two combined oral contraceptive regimens and an intravaginal hormonal ring against placebo for management of bleeding problems in women using Implanon, the sub-dermal contraceptive implant</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>None</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Unacceptable bleeding pattern in women using the progestogen-only sub-dermal contraceptive implant</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Contraception</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>To set up and perform a pilot double-blind randomised clinical Randomised trial of two regimens and an open-label arm to examine the effects of the following treatments on prolonged or frequent uterine bleeding in women using Implanon, the etonogestrel-releasing sub dermal contraceptive implant:

*7 days daily intake of oral capsule containing containing ethinyl oestradiol 30micrograms plus desogestrel 150 micrograms followed by 14 days oral placebo capsules
*21 days daily intake of oral capsules containing ethinyl oestradiol 30micrograms plus desogestrel 150 micrograms 
*21 days NuvaRing contraceptive vaginal ring releasing ethinyl oestradiol 15micrograms plus etonorgestrel 120 micrograms dailyleft in situ for 21 days 
 *21 days daily oral placebo capsules
Treatment will be for one cycle of 21 days</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group will take placebo capsules
Comparisons will be made between the three treatment groups against placebo and also against each other</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The number of days to stop bleeding after initiation of each treatment group and placebo determined from menstrual diaries completed by subjects</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 3 weeks of starting therapy</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>*The number of days of bleeding and spotting immediately following initiation of the 7 day Marvelon course of therapy compared with placebo
*The number of bleeding and spotting days immediately following insertion of NuvaRing compared to placebo
*The number of days of bleeding and spotting immediately following initiation of the 21 day Marvelon course of therapy compared with placebo</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 3 weeks of initiating treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The number of days of to stop bleeding following initiation of each therapy compared to the other treatment groups. determined from menstrual diaries</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 3 weeks of initiating treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of the number of days duration of the first bleeding and spotting-free interval after the initiation of treatment between  treatments and  placebo determined from menstrual diaries,</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 90 days of starting treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The mean total number of bleeding and spotting days during the 90 day "treatment" reference period compared with the pre-treatment reference period (calculated as percentage reduction) for each group and a comparison between treatment groups  and placebo and compared to the other treatment groups determined from menstrual diaries kept for 90 days prior to starting treatment and for 90 days from initiation of treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after starting treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The mean number of episodes of bleeding and spotting during the 90 day "treatment" reference period compared with the pre-treatment reference period (calculated as percentage reduction) for each group and a comparison between treatment groups  and placebo	determined from menstrual diaries kept for 90 days prior to starting treatment and for 90 days from initiation of treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months after starting treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The mean duration of individual bleeding and spotting episodes in the 90 day "treatment" reference period, compared with pre-treatment reference period (calculated as percentage reduction), and between treatments and placebo determined from menstrual diaries kept for 90 days prior to starting treatment and for 90 days from initiation of treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after starting treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>*Implanon users,   with a complaint of episodes of prolonged (10 days or greater) or frequent bleeding (more than 4 bleeding episodes in a 90 day reference period).
*Women who are willing to participate in a research investigation of new approaches for the management of troublesome bleeding.
*Women who are willing to maintain a 90 day bleeding diary prior to and post treatment initiation.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Women who have currently or previously had 
*Heart attack or stroke
*Blood clot in a vein
*High blood pressure
*Severe liver or kidney disease
*Blood pressure &gt; 135 mm systolic or &gt;85 mm diastolic
*Migraine with aura
*Breast cancer or any genital cancer
*Severe chronic liver or kidney disease
*Women with known sensitivity to ethinyl oestradiol, progestogens
*Women taking phenytoin, carbamazepine or phenobarbitol 
*Women who are pregnant
*Women who are lactating
*Women who are unwilling to keep a daily menstrual diary or otherwise unwilling to follow the study criteria</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>#Implanon users who indicate on a 90 day bleeding diary that they comply with the definition of frequent or prolonged bleeding will be allocated randomly to to one of the three treatment groups or placebo.
The medications will be packed in sequentially numbered and sealed opaque envelopes (independent of the investigators</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be performed by computer generation of a random number table with equal numbers in each of the four groups.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The NuvaRing group will be randomly allocated but will not be blinded either to the subject or the investigator. However, the analysis of results willl be blinded.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Edith Weisberg</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Sydney Centre for Reproductive Health Research
FPNSW
328-336 Liverpool Road
Ashfield
NSW 2131</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>MSD</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 4, 66 Waterloo Road
North Ryde
NSW 2113</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Ian Fraser</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Queen Elizabeth II Research Institute fior Mothers and Babies.
University of Sydney
Camperdown
NSW 2006</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Recruited subjects will maintain a daily menstrual diary chart for a minimum of 90 days, and will be enrolled into the treatment phase provided that they have met one of the World Health Organization criteria for prolonged or frequent bleeding (in the 90 day reference period one episode of bleeding and/or spotting lasting &gt; 10 days, or more than 4 bleeding/spotting episodes)
Following the initial 90 day record, women will begin designated treatment on day 1 of the next episode of bleeding or spotting.  Analysis of the subsequent menstrual pattern will begin from day 1 of treatment and will continue through 90 days.  Analysis of the pre-treatment menstrual pattern will include the 90 days immediately preceding the bleeding episode in which treatment starts.

Menstrual pattern analysis will be carried out according to World Health Organization definitions and clinically important bleeding pattern criteria.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.fpnsw.org.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Family Planning Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>328-336 liverpool Road

Ashfield
NSW 2131</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/06/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00120</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/03/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Edith Weisberg</name>
      <address>Sydney Centre for Reproductive Health Research,
FPNSW
328-336 liverpool Road
Ashfield
NSW
2131</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8752 4342</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 8752 4394</fax>
      <email>edithw@fpnsw.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sarah Robertson RN</name>
      <address>Sydney Centre for Reproductive Health Research,
FPNSW
328-336 liverpool Road
Ashfield
NSW
2131</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8752 4345</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 2 8752 4394</fax>
      <email>sarahr@fpnsw.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Edith Weisberg</name>
      <address>Sydney Centre for Reproductive Health Research,
FPNSW
328-336 liverpool Road
Ashfield
NSW
2131</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8752 4342</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 8752 4394</fax>
      <email>edithw@fpnsw.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>