<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347784">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/11/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/12/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611001239954</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Association between oral health and nutritional status in Guarani indigenous people from Florianopolis region.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Indigenous population: relationship between oral health and nutritional status.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Oral health</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>nutritional status</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Oral health and comfort in the oral cavity are pre-requisites for a good chewing function and may have an impact on food quality and nutritional status. These influences may be related to quantity, quality and consistency of food eaten. The study of the relationship between oral health and nutritional status is scarce in the different age groups and virtually nonexistent among the indigenous population. Associated with this relation between eating habits and oral health, are linked to socio-economic, cultural and psychological and are influenced by the practices of health care in the family routine. Despite the nutritional profiles and the influence of changes in the way of life of indigenous peoples are largely unknown, the nutritional question is a dimension privileged to seek to identify and understand the consequences in their living conditions, health and nutrition. Cross-sectional study, with two years of duration, was carried out with Guarani indigenous people from Florianopolis region. The sample consisted of 251 children and adolescents and 123 adults. In this study was measured the association between oral health and nutritional status. The oral health status was assessed by a dmft index (decayed, missing or filled primary teeth) and DMFT index (permanent teeth decayed, missing and filled) determined using the codes and criteria established by the World Health Organization (1997) only once. The classification of nutritional status was performed according to criteria adopted by the World Health Organization (WHO, 2006, 2007), based on anthropometric indices, height-for-age (H/A), weight-for-age (W/I) and Body Mass Index (BMI) for age. The nutritional status for adults and elderly patients was classified according to the cutoffs recommended by World Health Organization (WHO, 2008).</interventions>
    <comparator>Uncontrolled</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of oral health status in Indigenous population:
 
Oral health status was assessed by a single calibrated operator under natural light. The dmft index (decayed, missing or filled primary teeth) and DMFT index (permanent teeth decayed, missing and filled) were determined using the codes and criteria established by the World Health Organization (1997). The oral health status was classified into satisfactory and unsatisfactory, according to age, adapted indexes, established for oral health by the WHO (1997) and SB-Brazil Project (2004). For ages between five and under twelve years was considered satisfactory when dmft/DMFT equal to zero and unsatisfactory when dmft/DMFT more than zero. For individuals with twelve years was considered satisfactory when DMFT less than or equal one and unsatisfactory when DMFT more than one. For ages more than twelve years and less than or equal to nineteen years was considered satisfactory when Missing Teeth (MT equal zero) and unsatisfactory when MT more than zero. For ages between twenty years and less than or equal to sixty-five years was considered satisfactory when DMFT less than or equal 13 and unsatisfactory when DMFT more than 13. For individuals with more than to sixty-five years was considered satisfactory when DMFT less than or equal 20 and unsatisfactory when DMFT more than 20. Habits related to oral health care were investigated through an interview with questions that relate to the following variables: frequency of consumption of foods with sugar and visit to the dentist. The oral health status was classified in relation to the risk of dental caries, of periodontal disease, and changes in soft tissues employing the codes and criteria recognized by the Office for Programmes and Development of Health Policies (CODDEPS, 2006).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Indigenous population was evaluated only once at the end of study.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of nutritional status in Indigenous population:
 
For the evaluation of body weight was used a portable electronic scale (Marte MS-160 with platform, Sao Paulo, Sao Paulo, Brazil), with a sensibility of 50 g and maximum capacity of 160 kg. To check this, was following this procedures: light clothes and without shoes, the individual remained standing on the center of scale platform, with your weight evenly distributed on both feet, with arms side of the body. Weight was recorded in kilograms (kg) and grams (g) (WHO, 1995). For children under 2 years was used a digital pediatric scale (Filizola Baby, Sao Paulo, Sao Paulo, Brazil) 15 kg, with a minimum load of 125 g and divisions of 5 g. To check the height was used an anthropometer (Alturaexata, Belo Horizonte, Minas Gerais, Brazil), with a precision of 0.1 cm, as recommended by WHO (1995). The classification of nutritional status was performed according to criteria adopted by the World Health Organization (WHO, 2006, 2007), based on anthropometric indices, height-for-age (H/A), weight-for-age (W/I) and Body Mass Index (BMI) for age. Being classified as: H/A - stunted (z score less than minor two Stander (S) Deviation (D) and normal height (z score more than minor two SD); and W/A - malnutrition (z score less than minor two SD) for normal weight (with Z scores between minor two SD and plus two SD), and overweight those children with Z scores more than plus two SD. For this study are compared with previous data was also used the parameters of the National Center for Health Statistics (NCHS) published by Hamill et al. (1979). Being classified as: W/A - malnourished children with Z scores less than minor two SD; normal weight when Z scores between minor two SD and plus two SD; and overweight those children with Z scores more than plus two SD. The diagnosis of nutritional status was also determined from the percentages proposed by the National Center for Health Statistics/Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (NCHS/CDC, 2000), for comparison with the WHO (2007). It was considered the age of 12 in 12 months. The nutritional status for adults and elderly patients was classified according to the cut offs recommended by World Health Organization (WHO, 2008): underweight (BMI less than 18.5 kg/square metre), normal weight (BMI equal to 18.50 until 24.99 kg/ square metre), overweight (BMI equal to 25.00 until 29.99 kg/ square metre), obesity class I (BMI equal 30.00 until 34.99 kg/ square metre), class II obesity (BMI equal 35.00 until 39.99 kg/ square metre), class III obese (BMI more than or equal to 40.00 kg/ square metre). The triceps skinfold (TSF) was collected with the skinfold compass (Lange Skinfold Caliper, Santa Cruz, California, USA) in the right hemibody, according to the methodology of the World Health Organization (1995). This measurement was performed in triplicate and the mean was used in the computations. For TSF were used the reference values of Frisancho (1981). Nutritional status was assessed according to TSF distributed in percentiles: less than percentile 5 equal malnutrition; more than or equal to percentile 5 and less than percentile 85 equal eutrophy; more than or equal percentile 85 and less than percentile 95 equal overweight; more than or equal percentile 95 equal obesity). The waist circumference (WC) was collected using the procedure described by Callaway et al. (1991). Were used a flexible tape measure with a precision of 1 mm. The values of waist circumference for children and adolescents are presented as percentiles, with the cutoff points by age and sex according to Cook et al. (2009). The classification of central obesity in adults and older met the criteria suggested by WHO (2000). To measurement the circumference of the calf was used the methodology of the World Health Organization (1995). Was used a tape measure graduated, flexible, inelastic, with an accuracy of 0.1 cm. There were two measures, by calculating the arithmetic mean of the same. The cut off point for circumference of the calf of less than 30.5 cm was considered malnutrition, according to Bonnefoy et al., 2002.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Indigenous population was evaluated only once at the end of study.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Individuals and/or guardians indigenous who agreed to participate in the study after reading and signing the consent form free and clear.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>1</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnant and individuals that suffering from organic limitations that compromised the data collection.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>374</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Santa Catarina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Emilia Addison Machado Moreira</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina (UFSC), Centro de Ciencia da Saude, Departamento de Nutricao - Campus Reitor Joao David Ferreira Lima, Trindade, s/n, Florianopolis, Santa Catarina, ZIP: 88.040-970.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Brazil</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Arlete Catarina Tittoni Corso</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina (UFSC), Centro de Ciencia da Saude, Departamento de Nutricao - Campus Reitor Joao David Ferreira Lima, Trindade, s/n, Florianopolis, Santa Catarina, ZIP: 88.040-970.</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Brazil</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Background: The literature reports an interface between nutritional status and oral health status, as there is a close relationship between oral health, chewing function and dietary intake. Studies on the health of indigenous peoples suggest the need to prioritize effective actions aimed at health promotion. Interactions with non-indigenous society in the quest for friendly relationships cause changes in subsistence, eating habits and physical activity, leading to a process of epidemiological transition and inequalities in health.
Objective: The objective of this study was to examine the relationship between oral health status and nutritional status. 
Subjects and methods: The cross-section study was carried out with Guarani indigenous people from Florianopolis region. The sample consisted of 251 children and adolescents and 123 adults. The aassessment of nutritional status in Indigenous population was the according to World Health Organization (1995). The classification of nutritional status was performed according to criteria adopted by the World Health Organization (WHO, 2006, 2007), based on anthropometric indices, height-for-age (H/A), weight-for-age (W/I) and Body Mass Index (BMI) for age. Assessment of oral health status in Indigenous population was assessed by a single calibrated operator under natural light. The dmft index (decayed, missing or filled primary teeth) and DMFT index (permanent teeth decayed, missing and filled) were determined using the codes and criteria established by the World Health Organization (1997). The oral health status was classified in relation to the risk of dental caries, of periodontal disease, and changes in soft tissues employing the codes and criteria recognized by the Office for Programmes and Development of Health Policies (CODDEPS, 2006).
Outcome: When the nutritional status and oral health were related, the unsatisfactory def-t/DMF-T, the presence of teeth with caries and unfilled, as well as the moderate and high risk of development of caries was prevalent in the diagnosis of eutrophic through the body mass index and when the waist circumference was considered unaltered. On the other hand, it was observed that altered calf circumference that is, the indication of reduced lean mass, was prevalent for these same indicators. It is concluded that a relationship exists between oral condition and nutritional status.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>MOURA, P.G. Indigenous population: oral condition and nutritional status of mother and child. 2007. 117 f. Dissertation (Masters degree in Dentistry Public Health)  Post-graduate Programme in Dentistry, Federal University of Santa Catarina, Florianopolis.

BATISTA, L.R.V. Indigenous population: relationship between oral condition and nutritional status. 2011. 241 p. Thesis (Doctorate in Dentistry Public Health)  Post-graduate Programme in Dentistry, Federal University of Santa Catarina, Florianopolis.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Committe for Researchs with Humans of Federal University of Santa Catarina (UFSC).</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Pro-Reitoria de Pesquisa e Extensao. Campus Universitario - Trindade - Florianopolis/SC. ZIP: 88040-970. Caixa Postal 476.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/04/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>024/2006</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>13/02/2006</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Brazil</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>National Committee for Ethics in Research.</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Esplanada dos Ministerios, Bloco G - Edificio Anexo, Ala B Andar 1 - Sala 103B. ZIP: 70058-900 - Brasilia, DF.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/05/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>404/2007</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/04/2006</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Brazil</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Authorization of FUNAI for entry into indigenous lands.</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Fundacao Nacional do Indio - FUNAI - SEPS Quadra 702/902 Projeto A, Ed. Lex 70.390-025 - Brasilia/DF.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/08/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>0905/2007</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/05/2007</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Brazil</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Emilia Addison Machado Moreira</name>
      <address>Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina (UFSC), Centro de Ciencia da Saude, Departamento de Nutricao, Campus Reitor Joao David Ferreira Lima, Trindade, s/n, Florianopolis, Santa Catarina, ZIP: 88040-970.</address>
      <phone>+55 (48) 3721-9784 (for Santa Catarina, Brazil)</phone>
      <fax>+55 (48) 3721-9542 (for Santa Catarina, Brazil)</fax>
      <email>addison@ccs.ufsc.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Emilia Addison Machado Moreira</name>
      <address>Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina (UFSC), Centro de Ciencia da Saude, Departamento de Nutricao, Campus Reitor Joao David Ferreira Lima, Trindade, s/n, Florianopolis, Santa Catarina, ZIP: 88040-970.</address>
      <phone>+55 (48) 3721-9784 (for Santa Catarina, Brazil)</phone>
      <fax>+55 (48) 3721-9542 (for Santa Catarina, Brazil)</fax>
      <email>addison@ccs.ufsc.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Emilia Addison Machado Moreira</name>
      <address>Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina (UFSC), Centro de Ciencia da Saude, Departamento de Nutricao, Campus Reitor Joao David Ferreira Lima, Trindade, s/n, Florianopolis, Santa Catarina, ZIP: 88040-970.</address>
      <phone>+55 (48) 3721-9784 (for Santa Catarina, Brazil)</phone>
      <fax>+55 (48) 3721-9542 (for Santa Catarina, Brazil)</fax>
      <email>addison@ccs.ufsc.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>