<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365444">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/12/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/12/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001355763</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Blockade of Aldosterone Receptors as promising treatment for Type-1 Diabetes

</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Delaying or preventing the complications of Type-1 diabetes by adding the selective mineralocorticoid receptor antagonist eplerenone to standard medication for patients with Type-1 Diabetes.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1151-1682 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>BART-1</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 1 diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Eplerenone 50mg orally once daily for 12 weeks 

Proof-of-concept, non-randomized, open-label study.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Only the patients with Type 1 diabetes will receive eplerenone.

There is a control group of healthy participants who will not receive Eplerenone are included to determine the features of healthy heart function and blood pressure in healthy individuals to compare the areas of the heart that are not working properly in Type 1 diabetic individuals and identify novel biomarkers. 
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in composite outcome of ambulatory blood pressure, resting blood pressure, heart rate, pulse wave velocity and cardiac function and structure: left ventricular indices such as mass, mass index, ejection fraction, diastolic function, left atrial size and right ventricular function at 12 weeks after intervention commencement.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline and at 12 weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in haemostatic functions: 
-reduction in prothrombotic and haemostatic/inflammatory factors such as von Willebrand Factor (vWF) antigen, platelet/granulocyte aggregates, thromboxane B2, whole blood aggregometry, fibrinogen, CRP, IL6, Factor VIII:c, Overall Haemostatic Potential (OHP) and cortisol at 12 weeks after intervention commencement.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline and at 12 weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in central macula thickness (CMT) as measured by Optical Coherence Tomography (OCT). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline and at 12 weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in metabolic variables: including glycaemic control, determined by glycosylated HbA1c, fasting plasma glucose, fasting insulin, number of patients taking insulin compared to baseline, insulin dose and other medications at 12 weeks after intervention commencement.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline and at 12 weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Idenitification of disease biomarkers such as microRNA, fibrosis and oxidative stress biomarkers by collecting plasma from both the healthy volunteer group (control) and comparing microRNA, protein markers of fibrosis and oxidative stress between the 2 groups. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline and at 12 weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Impact on the individual's quality of life as assessed by questionnaires - Quality of Life (QOL) and Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index.
 </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline and at 12 weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Confirmed diagnosis of Type 1 diabetes for at least 10 years prior to informed consent;
2. Male and female participants must have optimal dose, or maximally tolerated dose of standard diabetes medication including ACE inhibitors/ARBs and diuretics (documented) such that minimal or no dose changes of other medications are required;
3. HbA1c greater than or equal to 7.0% and less than or equal to 9% at Visit 1 before entering the treatment period;
4. Mild non-proliferative retinopathy at Visit 1;
5. Participants must have ability to swallow pills.
6. Signed and dated written informed consent by date of Visit 1 in accordance with Good Clinical Practice (GCP) and local legislation.


Group 2: Control Group of healthy participants
Inclusion criteria: 
- must not have been diagnosed with diabetes (type 1 or 2); 
- have stable metabolic control (BP, lipids, blood sugar levels); 
- Age 18-50 years;
- signed and dated written informed consent in accordance with Good Clinical Practice (GCP) and local legislation.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Serum potassium level greater than 5.0 mmol/l; 
2. Indication of renal dysfunction defined by serum creatinine greater than 220 µmol/L;
3. Indication of impaired renal function, defined as estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) less than 45 ml/min/1.73m2;
4. Participants who have known allergy to aldosterone receptor antagonists or are currently taking an aldosterone receptor antagonist;
5. Participants enrolled in other trials or participation in the follow-up period of another trial;
6. Participants who have a contra-indication to cardiac MRI, including administration of gadolinium-based IV contrast;
7. Indication of liver disease, defined by serum levels of either ALT (SGPT), AST (SGOT), or alkaline phosphatase above 3 x upper limit of normal (ULN) as determined during Visit 1;
8. Participants with significant vascular disease, stroke or TIA within 3 months prior to informed consent; co-existing cardiac disease including nonsinus rhythm, left bundle branch block, history of established epicardial CAD, previous revascularisation or previous myocardial infarction and severe hypertension greater than 180/110;
9. Participants with suboptimal echocardiographic image quality or ischaemia.
10. Known contraindications to eplerenone according to the local label;
11. Medical history of cancer (except for basal cell carcinoma) and/or treatment for cancer within the last 5 years;
12. Known blood dyscrasias or any disorders causing hemolysis or unstable red blood cell count (e.g. malaria, babesiosis, haemolytic anemia) due to the short lifespan of the RBC and its impact on HbA1c;
13.Current treatment with systemic steroids (orally taken or parenteral) at time of informed consent or change in dosage of thyroid hormones within 6 weeks prior to informed consent or any other uncontrolled endocrine disorder except T1D;
14. Premenopausal women (last menstruation =1 year prior to informed consent) who:
- are nursing or pregnant or
- are of childbearing potential and are not practicing an acceptable method of birth control, or do not plan to continue using this method throughout the trial and do not agree to submit to periodic pregnancy testing during participation in the trial. Acceptable methods of birth control include tubal ligation, transdermal patch, intra uterine devices/systems (IUDs/IUSs), oral, implantable or injectable contraceptives, complete sexual abstinence (if acceptable by local health authorities), double barrier method and vasectomised partner
15. Alcohol or drug abuse within the 3 months prior to informed consent that would interfere with trial participation or any ongoing condition leading to a decreased compliance to trial procedures or trial drug intake, in the judgment of the investigators.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Open-Label study, allocation is not concealed.

Patients with Type 1 diabetes who meet the eligibility criteria for the study will be identified from the RNSH Diabetes Clinic Registry and contacted by phone by one of the research team who will explain the study and answer questions. A copy of the Participant Information Sheet will be provided to participants to read and discuss with family and friends. Patients will attend the Diabetic Clinic where the informed consent form will be collected. 

Participants in the control group will be recruited by advertisement (newspaper or noticeboards) and will only have the initial measurements.</concealment>
    <sequence>Open label, non-randomised trial</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>There will be 2 groups  Participants with Type 1 diabetes for at least 10 years who will receive eplerenone. The second group is the Control Group, who do not receive eplerenone but are included to determine the features of healthy heart function and blood pressure in healthy individuals to compare the areas of the heart that are not working properly in Type 1 diabetic individuals and identify novel biomarkers.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Currently there are no studies that have examined the impact of eplerenone on the hemodynamic, haemostatic and inflammatory factors and cardiac imaging measures we will be assessing in patients with type 1 diabetes. 

Our pilot study will provide us with the magnitude of the treatment effect on each of these measures. 

Intention-to-treat analysis for the various variables at completion of treatment compared to baseline.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/01/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>9/12/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal North Shore Hospital - St Leonards</hospital>
    <postcode>2065 - Royal North Shore Hospital</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Pfizer Australia and New Zealand</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>38-42 Wharf Road, West Ryde, NSW 2114</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Northern Sydney Local Health District
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Royal North Shore Hospital
Reserve Road, St Leonards,
NSW 2065
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Type 1 diabetes (T1D) incidence is rising globally at a rate of 35% per year with patients having increased susceptibility to macrovascular complications and diabetic retinopathy a major microvascular complication of diabetes. Cardiovascular disease is the major cause of disability and death, with diabetic retinopathy the leading cause of blindness and significant burden to the individual and society. Current treatments target elevated blood glucose, high blood lipids and blood pressure, however diabetic patients continue to have 2- to 4-fold greater risk of a heart attack (MI), hence the optimum treatment for minimising this complication during diabetes has not yet been established, and additional treatment strategies are urgently needed. 

Hormones of the renin-angiotensin-system (RAS) are key mediators of adverse complications in diabetes, with blockade of this system by medications known as angiotensin converting
enzyme inhibitors (ACEI) or angiotensin receptor blockers (ARB) are routinely used as therapy for diabetes; although there are mixed reports for their efficacy in diabetic retinopathy. We propose this variability is due to the action of aldosterone, another steroid hormone in the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (RAAS). Aldosterone exerts adverse actions via activation of mineralocorticoid receptors (MR), often referred to as aldosterone receptors. Our hypothesis is that adding a medication known as aldosterone receptor antagonist to standard treatment for T1D will delay or prevent
progression of complications of diabetes. Although this medication is used treat patients with heart failure and MI,
there are no clinical trials investigating this medication in T1D. 

The design is open label, 9 week duration, proof-of-concept
study to assess the efficacy of the selective "aldosterone receptor" antagonist, eplerenone in T1D. Twenty patients with T1D will be recruited from the Diabetes clinic. They will have baseline measures within the first week and then receive eplerenone for 12 weeks in addition to standard treatment. The same measures are repeated in each patient at the end of the treatment period; hence the proof-of-concept is baseline versus treatment for each person. The patients will return 7 days after completing the study for routine clinical visit. A separate group of 20 age matched, healthy volunteers will be recruited for comparing the same measures to establish prognostic markers. 

Our specific objectives are: 
1. Prevent and arrest the complications of diabetes on cardiac structure and function, including platelet activation and reactivity and endothelial dysfunction; 
2. Prevent progression to diabetic retinopathy; 
3. Improve metabolic control; 
4. Provide prognostic and predictive biomarkers for clinical
management.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Sydney Local Health District Human Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Office, 
Level 13, Kolling Building, 
Royal North Shore Hospital, 
Pacific Highway, St. Leonards, NSW 2065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/11/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Anastasia Susie Mihailidou</name>
      <address>Level 13 Kolling Building
Royal North Shore Hospital
Pacific Highway
St Leonards, NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9926 4956</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9926 4044</fax>
      <email>anastasia.mihailidou@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Anastasia Susie Mihailidou</name>
      <address>Level 13 Kolling Building
Royal North Shore Hospital
Pacific Highway
St Leonards, NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9926 4956</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9926 4044</fax>
      <email>anastasia.mihailidou@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Anastasia Susie Mihailidou</name>
      <address>Level 13 Kolling Building
Royal North Shore Hospital
Pacific Highway
St Leonards, NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9926 4956</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9926 4044</fax>
      <email>anastasia.mihailidou@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Anastasia Susie Mihailidou</name>
      <address>Level 13 Kolling Building
Royal North Shore Hospital
Pacific Highway
St Leonards, NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9926 4956</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9926 4044</fax>
      <email>anastasia.mihailidou@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>