<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362986">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/12/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/04/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000361707</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The impact of whole body heating on blood flow distribution and temperature regulation in chronic heart failure patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of repeated whole body heating on blood flow distribution to skin, muscle and cerebral vessel beds and thermoregulatory responses in chronic heart failure patients.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>New York Heart Association Class I-III chronic heart failure (aetiology either ischaemic or idiopathic dilated cardiomyopathy)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Responses to warm water immersion (maintained at a constant temperature of approximately 36 degrees celcius), to the waist level for a period of 30 minutes.  During this period, skeletal muscle, cerebral and skin blood flows will be measured as well as sweat rate production and core temperature changes.

Subsequently, the warm water heating protocol will be repeated 3 times per week for a period of 10 weeks. CHF subjects will be randomised to either the warm water heating in a bath for 30 minutes 3 times a week or to a euthermic bath control group.  

Warm water immersion will be conducted in custom-made water bath, whereby participants will sit immersed in water to the waist level. This method of heating the body has been chosen because it allows the study to be performed in a supervised environment. It also allows us to measure the effect of heating on the whole body, including body parts not immersed in the heating stimulus (i.e. the arms, which will be kept out of the water). The bath temperature will be similar to that which would be experienced in a warm bath or spa at home (ie 32-38 degrees C).  The water temperature is thermostatically controlled using specialised equipment (iCool, Queensland). Blood pressure and heart rate will be continuously monitored during these sessions to provide information regarding each subject's tolerance of the warm bath. If this becomes uncomfortable at any stage, the water temperature will be cooled or the participant will be allowed to leave the bath. 

The group allocated to the euthermic water exposure will be positioned in an identical custom-made bath for 30 minutes and will be monitored in an identical fashion to those allocated to warm water immersion, however, the temperature of the water in the euthermic group will be thermostatically controlled to room temperature using specialised equipment (iCool, Queensland). 

</interventions>
    <comparator>In the observational element of the study (a preliminary assessment which will take place prior to the start of the 10-week intervention) haemodynamic and thermoregulator responses to 30 minutes of acute heat (warm water; approximately 36 degrees Celsius) exposure will be assessed in CHF and matched healthy control subjects to provide a basis for determination of differences in blood perfusion and thermoregulation due to CHF. 

In the interventional element of the study, CHF subjects will be randomised to either the warm water heating (approximately 36 degrees Celsius) in a bath for 30 minutes 3 times a week or to a euthermic bath control group (approximately 28 degrees Celsius). The control group will be exposed to euthermic water immersion for 30 minutes 3 times a week to allow us to investigate the impact of water immersion per se.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Brachial, carotid and cerebral artery blood flow asssesed by high resolution ultrasonography</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline prior to randomisation and following the 10 week intervention. Additionally measurements will be taken at fortnightly intervals during the intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Skin blood flow assessed by microdialysis infusion of locally acting blocking agents and laser Doppler flowmetry.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline prior to randomisation and following the 10 week intervention. Additionally measurements will be taken at fortnightly intervals during the intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sweat rate production assessed by a water vapour vapour pressure sensitive capacitor.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline prior to randomisation and following the 10 week intervention. Additionally measurements will be taken at fortnightly intervals during the intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Skin and core body temperature assessed using external (skin) and internal (rectal) thermistors.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline prior to randomisation and following the 10 week intervention. Additionally measurements will be taken at fortnightly intervals during the intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients with New York Heart Association Class I-III CHF (aetiology either ischaemic or idiopathic dilated cardiomyopathy)


A group of  subjects who do not have CHF will be recruited as controls.  These control subjects will be matched for age, sex and body composition.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>
Recent history of syncope (past 6 months)
Systolic blood pressure &lt; 90mmHg
New York Heart Association Class IV
Recent exacerbation of heart failure resulting in hospitalisation (&lt; 2months)
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Perth Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Royal Perth Hospital
197 Wellington Street 
Perth
Western Australia 
6000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Heart Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Heart Foundation
334 Rokeby Road 
Subiaco 
Perth
Western Australia 
6008</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Western Australia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University of Western Australia
35 Stirling Highway
Crawley
Perth
Western Australia
6009</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Patients with chronic heart failure (CHF) have an impaired capacity to regulate body temperature. This study will investigate the acute effects of body heating in patients with CHF and also the effects of repetitive exposure to whole body heating. Participants will be recruited from general Cardiology at RPH, from private Cardiology clinics and from the Cardiac Transplant Unit and Advanced Heart Failure Service at RPH.

Study hypotheses: 
1. Patients with CHF will exhibit impaired cardiovascular responses to an acute bout of body heating, compared to age, gender and BMI matched controls.

2. Repeated whole body heating will improve abnormal cardiovascular function evident in response to body heating in patients with CHF.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrew Maiorana</name>
      <address>Royal Perth Hospital
197 Wellington Street
Perth
Western Australia
6000
</address>
      <phone>+61 0433567369</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Andrew.Maiorana@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrew Maiorana</name>
      <address>Royal Perth Hospital
197 Wellington Street
Perth
Western Australia
6000
</address>
      <phone>+61 0433567369</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Andrew.Maiorana@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrew Maiorana</name>
      <address>Cardiac Transplant Unit
Royal Perth Hospital
197 Wellington Street
Perth
Western Australia
6000

</address>
      <phone>+61 0433567369</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Andrew.Maiorana@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>