<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336620">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/03/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/03/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000229976</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Exercise rehabilitation programs for chronic low back pain</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In patients with chronic non-specific low back pain, are core stability exercise programs as good or better than general exercise for relief of pain</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>University of Western Sydney HREC Approval Number H8878</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic non-specific low back pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>8-week exercise rehabilitation program.  Pilates based exercise involving stretching, floor based exercise, reformer based whole body exercise. Prescription is 3 x 1 hours sessions per week for 8-weeks.  All directly supervised in a group format (10 people per group session).</interventions>
    <comparator>General exercise group.  3 x 1 hour sessions per week for 8-weeks.  Group session (10 per group) directly supervised by an instructor.  Intervention to include cycling at 70% maximal heart rate, intermittent walking and stepping tasks, lower limb stretching work.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Low back pain (Visual Analogue Pain Scale)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (pre) and 8-weeks (post program)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Oswestry disabilty index for low back pain related functional capacity (ODI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (pre) and 8-weeks (post program)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Abdominal feedforward activation measured using surface electromyography.  Test used is a rapid shoulder movement task.  Onset of abdominal muscles relative to deltoid prime mover is used for analysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (pre) and 8-weeks (post program)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fear of movement associated with back pain measured with the Fear Avoidance Beliefs Questionnaire (FABQ).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (pre) and 8-weeks (post program)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-rated anxiety and depression measured using the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (pre) and 8-weeks (post program)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Beliefs about pain assessed using the Pain Catastrophizing Scale (PCS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (pre) and 8-weeks (post program)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Male and female participants with chronic non-specific low back pain.  This group excludes those with specific low back pathologies (as assessed from described history of
participants), which introduces confounding factors for interpretation of the results.
Participants will have had LBP for at least 12 weeks and have provided written informed consent confirming
their participation. Participants must have a minimum level of disability caused by their LBP that scores at
least 15% in the Oswestry Functional Disability Index (ODI) to be included in the study. This will discriminate
the level of disability from that experienced by the normal population.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants will be excluded for the following reasons: presence of severe postural abnormality or
neuromuscular disorder, previous diagnosis of pathology (confirmed by previous magnetic resonance
imaging or radiograph), presence of pain radiating below the knee with a passive straight leg raise indicating
disc and nerve involvement.
Participants must not have engaged in any specific core stability training program in the last 3-months, and
must not be regularly seeing a physiotherapist or any spinal manipulation practitioner.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>52</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr. Paul Marshall</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Western Sydney
Locked Bag 1797 Penrith South 2751, NSW</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Western Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Locked Bag 1797 Penrith South 2751, NSW</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr. Chris Lonsdale</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University of Western Sydney
Locked Bag 1797 Penrith South 2751, NSW</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Of significant concern for healthcare treatment costs around the world are those individuals
with chronic low back pain (LBP). While exercise is a first-choice treatment for LBP there is no
consensus on the best type of exercise to use, with all modes of exercise equally effective.
Core stability exercises are movements for the trunk with bodyweight resistance. Core stability
training is thought to be the most effective exercise mode to improve neuromuscular control of
the trunk, however research evidence to support this is lacking. Improving neuromuscular
control of the trunk is one of the primary physiological mechanisms by which improvement in
low back pain patients is observed.
There is a lack of research comparing core stability training to other modes of exercise for low
back pain. If the literature reviews are indeed correct that no one mode of exercise is superior
to any other, it may be likely that an exclusively aerobic training modality may be just as
effective as a core stability program for improving pain, disabilty, fear avoidance, and
neuromuscular control of the trunk.
The aim of this study is to randomly assign participants with chronic low back pain to an 8
week exercise trial of either core stability or general aerobic exercise. Both groups will be
directly supervised, and measurements of pain, disability, fear avoidance beliefs, and trunk
neuromuscular control will be made before and after the 8 week program.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Western Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>H8878</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Paul Marshall</name>
      <address>University of Western Sydney, 
Locked Bag 1797 Penrith South 2751, NSW</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4620 3915</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.marshall@uws.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Paul Marshall</name>
      <address>University of Western Sydney, 
Locked Bag 1797 Penrith South 2751, NSW</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4620 3915</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.marshall@uws.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Paul Marshall</name>
      <address>University of Western Sydney, 
Locked Bag 1797 Penrith South 2751, NSW</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4620 3915</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.marshall@uws.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>