<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308057">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/06/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/06/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000484246</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Single  blinded evaluation of the effectiveness of Neuro Psycho Physical Optimization protocol with Radio Electric Asymmetric Conveyer  in stress-related disorders, assessed with Symptom Checklist-90 (SCL-90) and Psychological Stress Measure Test.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Single  blinded evaluation of the effectiveness of Neuro Psycho Physical Optimization protocol with Radio Electric Asymmetric Conveyer  in stress-related disorders, assessed with Symptom Checklist-90 (SCL-90) and Psychological Stress Measure Test.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>sbsclmsp</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>emotional and psychophysical disorders  stress related</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention comprises: A cycle of auricular  treatment protocol with Radioelectric Asymetric Conveyer (REAC). The REAC is a Radioelectric medical device. The protocol used, called Neuro Psycho Physical Optimization (ONPF), involves the application of a probe of the REAC on specific points of the auricular pavilion for an activation time of roughly 500 mms. The ONPF protocol is activated in a precise sequence on seven auricular points. . The protocol envisages 18 sessions of ONPF treatment lasting approximately 3,5 seconds each on alternating days, for eight (8) weeks. Assessment, at baseline and immediately at the end of treatment, with SCL-90 and Psychological Stress Measure Test</interventions>
    <comparator>Evaluate the effectiveness  on the subjective perception of stress and stress-related symptom between the treated group and the placebo group (treted with inactive REAC).The inactive REAC is the exact same machine but with a modified probe. The frequency and overall duration in which the inactive REAC will be applied, is the same as for the intervention group, 18 sessions of treatment on alternating days lasting 3,5 seconds per session for eight (8) weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To test if the use of the Neuro Psycho Physical Optimization (ONPF) auricular protocol with REAC - is effective in reducing the subjective perception of stress, and stress-related symptoms, assessed with SCL-90 and Psychological Stress Measure Test</outcome>
      <timepoint>At time zero and immediatly after the therapy cycle.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Wellbeing assessed with Psychological stress measure test (PSM)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At time zero and immediatly after the therapy cycle.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy Subjects without organic diseases, over 18 years old, who claimed to be stressed, with any type of stress-related symptoms and with Psychological stress measure test (PSM) total score over 45 points. No history of drug abuse, nor severe mental illness or personality disorder. No medications, known to affect cognitive functioning nor undergoing psychological interventions.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Diagnosis of psychiatric pathology, organic central nervous system (CNS) pathology, preceding skull traumas with loss of conscience longer than 5 minutes, dementia, alcohol dependence, current therapy with medications known to affect cognitive functioning.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The subjects, blindway, was allocated randomly to treatment or control group by an external operator</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by an external operator - computerized sequence generation at the reception desk</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Only doctors who administered treatment knew whether it was real or placebo. The normal and the placebo REAC device will be indistinguishable.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/12/2003</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Istituto Rinaldi Fontani</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Via Nazionale 23, 50123 Firenze</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Italy</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Istituto Rinaldi Fontani</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Via Nazionale 23, 50123 Firenze</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Italy</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Societa di Ottimizzazione Neuro Psico Fisica e CRM Terapia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Via Nazionale 23, 50123 Firenze</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Italy</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is evaluate the efficacy of the Neuro Psycho Physical Optimization  (NPPO) protocol treatment with Radioelectric Asymmetric Conveyer (REAC) in the improvement of the psychic and symptomatic stress-related disorders in a group of subjects revealing high values of psychological stress. These randomized, single-blinded controlled study, was conducted on subjects that voluntarily came to our Institute declaring to feel stressed. One hundred twenty four  (124) subjects (females, n = 81, males, n = 43) with psychological distress symptoms, were recruited an randomized to REAC therapy or placebo. 
Eighteen sessions of NPPO protocol treatment with REAC, or placebo (inactivated REAC), was applied to seven specific points of the auricular pavilion and were administered on alternate days, lasting about four weeks. Psychological stress symptoms  were assessed by Psychological Stress Measure (PSM) and Symptomatic Check List (SCL-90), pre and post intervention. Data were analyzed using the Statistical Package for Social Sciences (SPSS), version 13.0
Data conformed to a Gaussian distribution. There was a significant reduction in PSM test and SCL-90 scores in the treated group as compared to the placebo group. Results of the psychometric tests showed that the subjects that underwent the effective therapy showed a statistically relevant reduction in their level of stress and psychological disorders compared to the control placebo group.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Societa di Ottimizzazione Neuro Psico Fisica e CRM Terapia</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Via Nazionale 23 50123 Firenze</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Italy</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Salvatore Rinaldi M.D.</name>
      <address>Via Nazionale 23 50123 Firenze</address>
      <phone>+39 055 290307</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>srinaldi@irf.it</email>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Fontani Vania M.D.</name>
      <address>Via Nazionale 23 50123 Firenze</address>
      <phone>+39 055 290307</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vfontani@irf.it</email>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>