<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366514">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/06/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/06/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000679684</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Feasibility of creating an enriched environment and subsequent impact on activity levels for stroke patients in an Acute Stroke Unit.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of an enriched environment on activity levels compared to usual care in people admitted to an Acute Stroke Unit with a diagnosis of stroke.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>EESI</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute Stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a study to determine if it is feasible to create an enriched environment in an Acute Stroke Unit and if it will increase patient activity in the Acute Stroke Unit. The study involves a prospective non-randomized quasi-experimental block design with 30 people with stroke recruited to the usual care group (block 1) and 30 people with stroke recruited to the enriched environment group (block 2). Each block is estimated to last for 12 weeks. No change in staffing levels will occur during the study. 

In the usual care group, usual assessment and management of people with stroke admitted to the Acute Stroke Unit will occur.

In the enriched environment group, the physical and social environment of the Acute Stroke Unit will change to promote greater physical, social and cognitive activity. This will include a mix of individual and group therapies. Group activities will be organized to focus on different factors of stroke recovery e.g. education, emotional support, physical activities and leisure activities. 

Communal areas will be created e.g., patients can have breakfast and lunch in the treatment room together with other patients under staff supervision. Different types of equipment will be available to stimulate physical, cognitive and social activity e.g., iPads, iPods, books, games, puzzles, music. Equipment will be accessible during and outside of therapy hours. Staff members will re- organise their work routine to facilitate patient activity during the day.

The enriched environment design requires being flexible from a day-to-day basis due to a fast changing patient population in the Acute Stroke Unit. A flexible week schedule with approximate 3 defined activity periods for 1 hour will be scheduled from Monday till Friday to organize and structure the enriched environment. 

All patients and their visitors enrolled in the experimental group (second block) will be informed that activity after stroke enhances stroke recovery and they will be encouraged to utilize communal areas and materials to facilitate activity. Family will be asked to bring the patients own clothing and items of interest to contribute to patient activity. Staff members from the Acute Stroke Unit will stimulate patients to attend the communal areas and to utilize the materials to increase their activity level during the day. Patients, visitors and staff will be advised to respect the 1-hour rest time period after lunch. 

To minimize risk and monitor for adverse events, blood pressure and temperature observations of patients will be performed 4 times a day. Two of the four time periods will always occur at 7.00 AM and 14.00 PM to ensure safety before peak activity levels. If SBP is greater than or equal to 200 and/ or Temperature greater than or equal to 38 degrees the subsequent activity period will be missed. After the missed period, blood pressure and temperature measurements will be repeated. When measurements are within safe limits the patient can continue to participate with the activities. When measurements are not within safe limits the patient will miss the subsequent activity period.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard care in an Acute Stroke Unit</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Activity levels: Percentage of the day the patient is engaged in physical, social and cognitive activity. This will be collected through direct observation using behavioral mapping. Trained staff will observe the participant for 1 minute and will document the main activity performed during this minute. Staff will also document the type of activity, level of assistance required, location, positioning and all people who are present.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Behavioral mapping will commence the first behavioral mapping day after the patient is recruited to the study and continued until discharged from the Acute Stroke Unit. Behavioral mapping will occur every Tuesday, Thursday and Saturday from 7.30am till 7.30pm during each block.
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stroke survivor, main carer and clinical staff experience 
In both blocks the participant and main carer will complete a survey designed specifically for this study to capture their service experience at discharge from the Acute Stroke Unit. Clinical staff will also be asked to participate in a staff survey specifically designed for this study when the standard care cohort is in week 6, and in week 6 in the enriched environment design.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patient and main carer survey at discharge from the Acute Stroke Unit. Staff surveys when standard care cohort is in week 6, and when enriched environment cohort is in week 6.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary complications will be defined as any adverse event or serious adverse event occurring during their admission to the Acute Stroke Unit. Adverse events that will be recorded are falls, pneumonia, pressure areas, cardiac problems, seizures, reduced GCS, stroke, TIA, urinary tract infection, depression, constipation and malnutrition. Severity of the adverse event and study intervention relationship will be determined.

Serious adverse events will be described as an adverse event that led to death or led to serious deterioration in health of a patient or other that: 1. Results in life threatening illness 2. Results in permanent impairment of a body structure 3. Requires prolonged hospitalisation 4. Results in medical or surgical intervention to prevent permanent impairment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Adverse events and serious adverse events reported during the time the patient is admitted in the Acute Stroke Unit will be recorded. Serious adverse events will also be recorded at three months post stroke via telephone.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional outcomes
Mean Modified Rankin Scale scores. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Initial and at discharge from the Acute Stroke Unit. The MRS will also be completed at three months post stroke via telephone interview.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional outcome
Mean Modified Barthel Index.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Initial and at discharge from the Acute Stroke Unit.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ambulatory function
Score on the Mobility Scale for Acute Stroke patients.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Initial and at discharge from the Acute Stroke Unit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ambulatory function
Time to complete the 10-meter walk test.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Initial and at discharge from the Acute Stroke Unit.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression and anxiety
Mean score on the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Initial and discharge from the Acute Stroke Unit.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nutritional intake
Mean percentage nutritional intake. 
Consumed percentage of breakfast, lunch and dinner will be recorded during daily audits. All other nutritional intake will be recorded on food charts and accordingly calculated.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Food Audit and food charts starts the day after recruitment and will be performed from Monday through to Saturday till the patient gets discharged from the Acute Stroke Unit.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nutritional intake
Mean weight.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The participants weight will be measured during initial and discharge assessment and routinely on Thursdays and Sundays.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Living arrangement 
During the three months post stroke telephone interview the living arrangement will be determined.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post stroke.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health State Score
During the three months post stroke telephone interview the Health State Score will be determined.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post stroke.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adults who are 1) admitted to the Acute Stroke Unit with the diagnosis of a stroke (ischaemic and haemorrhagic) within 24-72 hours after onset, 2) able to complete a transfer with the assistance of 2 persons or less, 3) able to follow one stage commands, 4) requires assistance for basic ADLs, 5) premorbid MRS 2 or less and able to walk independently. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patient diagnosed with a rapid deteriorating health condition and/or with an active and uncontrolled mental health condition.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Prospective quasi-experimental design. Participants are allocated by block, as the intervention is a change to the hospital environment in one Acute Stroke Unit.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Total activity will be expressed as a percentage of the total number of observations performed, as will activity within domains of physical, social and cognitive activity. The first 14 days of observations will be considered as the primary exposure profile. Difference in measure between the two blocks will be determined using one-way ANCOVA, with covariates including age, stroke severity and premorbid function. Using data of 'any activity' from a recent study of the effect of an enriched environment on activity conducted during inpatient rehabilitation, a sample size calculation determined that with an alpha level of 0.05, 26 participants per group are required to give the trial 80% power to detect a moderate effect size of 0.7. 

All secondary outcomes measures will be compared between experimental and control group using ANCOVA, with covariates including age, stroke severity and premorbid function. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>26/06/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/04/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Nambour General Hospital - Nambour</hospital>
    <postcode>4560 - Nambour</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Mrs Ingrid Rosbergen</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Allied Health Department, Medical Services,
Nambour General Hospital
Hospital Road
Nambour 4560 QLD
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Wishlist Sunshine Coast Health Foundation; Novice Researcher Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 2610, Nambour West Qld 4560</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Allied Health Professions Office; Health Practitioner Research Grant </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1 15 Butterfield Street
Herston QLD 4006
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Allied Health Department, Medical Services, Nambour General Hospital
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Hospital Road
Nambour 4560 QLD</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Clinical Practice Improvement Payment; Statewide Stroke Clinical Network, Queensland Health

</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Statewide Stroke Clinical Network
C/- Clinical Access &amp; Redesign Unit
GPO Box 48
Brisbane Qld 4001
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>The University of Queensland;
School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Brisbane Qld 4072</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Stroke survivors who are in an Acute Stroke Unit have been found to spend the majority of their day inactive and alone. Growing evidence recommends that stroke survivors should retrain activities of daily living and ambulatory function as early and frequently as possible. One approach found to increase activity levels during inpatient rehabilitation is the use of an enriched environment whereby physical, cognitive and social activity is enhanced by creating a stimulating environment. The effect of an enriched environment in an Acute Stroke Unit has yet not been explored. 

This prospective non-randomized quasi-experimental block design intervention study is focusing on enhancing exposure to an enriched environment to increase activity in an Acute Stroke Unit. We will re-organize the Acute Stroke Unit and staffing to create an enriched environment that safely stimulates patients to be more active on a physical, cognitive and social level without increasing staffing levels.

The study will determine if an enriched environment can increase activity levels in people with a stroke in an Acute Stroke Unit within existing staffing levels. We hypothesize that activity levels will increase and that there will be a corresponding trend towards fewer secondary complications and improved functional outcomes for stroke survivors. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Metro North Hospital and Health Service, The Prince Charles Hospital, Human Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Rode Road, Chermside QLD 4032</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/03/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC:14/QPCH/21</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>8/02/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University Of Queensland, Medical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Road, Brisbane Qld 4072</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/03/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2014000371</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Ingrid Rosbergen</name>
      <address>Allied Health Department,
Nambour General Hospital,
Hospital Road,
Nambour Qld 4560
</address>
      <phone>+ 61 7 54706747</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ingrid.rosbergen@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rohan Grimley</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine,
Nambour General Hospital,
Hospital Road,
Nambour Qld 4560
</address>
      <phone>+61 7 53134270</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rohan.grimley@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Sandra Brauer</name>
      <address>The University of Queensland, 
School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences,
Brisbane Qld 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 33652317</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.brauer@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Ingrid Rosbergen</name>
      <address>Allied Health Department,
Nambour General Hospital,
Hospital Road, 
Nambour Qld 4560
</address>
      <phone>+61 7 54706747</phone>
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>