<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369120">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/08/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/09/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000924550</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Simple solutions to gastro-intestinal symptoms in chemotherapy patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Can upper gastric chemotherapy symptoms be predicted by taste genetics and will mouth wash solutions of water, salt, sodium bicarbonate, sugar, ginger or peppermint water improve taste changes, nausea or vomiting in patients receiving chemotherapy of cyclophosphamide or 5-FU</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1173-2105 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Patients receiving intravenous chemotherapy of cyclophosphamide or 5 fluorouracil</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Any cancer</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>At base line before chemotherapy commmenced genetic test strips will be used to screen for taste sensitivities Genetic taste test strips will be used to screen for genetically inherited taste recognition thresholds using taste testing strips which are impregnated with either 30mg thiourea, 30mg phenylthiocarbamide (PTC), or 30mg sodium benzoate. Participants were asked to trial each taste test strip in a random order by applying a strip to their moistened tongue and reporting whether it had no taste or tasted bitter, salty, sour, sweet, or any other taste. Patients will be classified as non-tasters with no taste reported, tasters when a recognisable taste is identified, and hyper-tasters if a strong taste was elicited. 
Number of taste buds counted by placing a drop of blue food colouring on tip of dry tongue A 6mm round hole in filter paper placed over the area dyed and the number of papillae counted within this space.
Patients will be asked about their symptoms during cycle 2. Those reporting symptoms will be asked to trial  mouth rinses during cycle 3 when symptoms are reported to be greatest.
Mouth washes of various common oral fluids will be trialled for 12 hours in random order as often as patient requires but at least twice for six consecutive days with overnight wasout periods. They will complete a questionaire daily to see which mouth washes improve taste and symptoms in chemotherapy.
a)Distilled cold water 500ml
b)Salt 5 g in 500ml cold water
c)Sodium bicarbonate 5 g in 500ml cold water
d)Sugar 25g in 500ml cold water
e)Ginger 2 gram in 500ml cold water 
f) Peppermint oil 0.2 ml in 500ml coldwater 

Monitoring for adherence is by questionaire completion and container return.</interventions>
    <comparator>Comparison of 5 different solution with distilled water</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine if the genetics of taste can predict development of upper gastric symptoms in patients receiving chemotherapy.The composite outcomes use genetic taste testing and counting number of taste buds.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline before commencement of chemotherapy</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of participants with any improvements in taste and symptoms (composite), assessed using questionnaire designed for this study for each of the mouthwashes over 6 days during cycle3 of chemotherapy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcomes will be assessed during chemotherapy Cycle 3 Days 3-10. Each mouthwash response will be assessed by questionaire after each 12 hour trial</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Competent patients aged 18-85 to receive intravenous chemotherapy of cyclophosphamide on regimens AC, TC, AC-T or FEC-D or 5-FU on regimens Modified FOLFOX6 or modified de gramont
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Unable or unwilling to sign the consent form
Patients with head and neck cancer
Patients having concurrent radiotherapy
Patients already receiving chemotherapy</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients planned to receive chemotherapy of cyclophosphamide or 5-FU will be recruited from the Austin Health oncology day care outpatient clinic on the chemotherapy information day.
Patients will be asked about GI symptoms during cycle 2 of chemotherapy and those reporting symptoms will be allocated the 6 solutions to be trialled in randomised order determined by computerised sequence generation by a uninvolved person.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computerised sequence generation.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>All the patrticipants receive all the interventions in different sequences during the study thereby acting as their own control. On selection of the solution that improves that patients symptoms the most, the solution code will be revealled and the patient will continue using this solution as required </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A convenience sample of 60 patients is to be recruited for taste genetics analysis.
From a sample file audit of patients who met inclusion criteria ~60% reported upper GI symptoms. Therefore it is estimated a sample of 60 patients planned to undergo the study chemotherapy should result in a convenience sample of 36 patients to trial the mouth washes as a secondary outcome.
 The participants' demographic, clinical and laboratory characteristics will be compared using independent sample t-tests for continuous data and Fisher exact tests for ordinal data.  The strength of association between genetic taste testing and upper GI symptoms will be estimated using the Spearman rank correlation method. Frequency of response will be used for upper GI symptoms and the relationships between response to solutions and nature of the mouthwash (sugar, salt, sodium bicarbonate, ginger, mint and water) will be dichotomised as better/much better versus worse/same then analysed using random-effect logistic regression model. Statistical significance will be set at p&lt;0.05</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/03/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>3/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>31</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Austin Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Austin Health
145 Studley Rd
Heidelberg
Victoria 3084</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Austin Medical Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Austin Health
145 Studley Rd
Heidelberg
Victoria 3084</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary> The primary purpose of this study is to determine whether simple mouthwashes can decrease symptoms of poor appetite, taste changes, nausea and vomiting due to chemotherapy. The study also aims to predict which patients will develop the most symptoms based on genetic and taste bud counting tests. 
Who is it for? You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged 18-85 years and due to receive intravenous chemotherapy of cyclophosphamide or 5-FU. 
Study details Prior to the first cycle of chemotherapy, genetic characteristics of each participant's taste will be tested using saliva samples, and the number of taste buds on the tongue will be counted. After 2 cycles of chemotherapy, participants will be asked to rate their symptoms of appetite, taste changes, nausea and vomiting. Patients with these symptoms will then test 6 different simple mouthwashes, including salt, sodium bicarbonate, sugar, ginger and peppermint oil, in a random order for 1 day per mouthwash. Patients will be asked to rate the effectiveness of each of the mouthwashes in reducing symptoms via questionnaire. 
It is hoped that these simple mouthwashes may be able to minimise symptoms, thus improving chemotherapy patient well-being, potentially increasing oral intake and thereby improving nutritional status. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Austin Health
145 Studley Rd
Heidelberg
Victoria 3084</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/02/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/Austin/414</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>17/09/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Karen Manley</name>
      <address>Austin Health
145 Studley Rd
Heidelberg
Vic 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94965646</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 94963168</fax>
      <email>karen.manley@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Karen Manley</name>
      <address>Austin Health
145 Studley Rd
Heidelberg
Vic 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94965646</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 94963168</fax>
      <email>karen.manley@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Karen Manley</name>
      <address>Austin Health
145 Studley Rd
Heidelberg
Vic 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94965646</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 94963168</fax>
      <email>karen.manley@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>