<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82421">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/11/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/03/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000246088</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>SUSTAIN For PAIN</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>SUSTAIN For PAIN: Subcostal UltraSound guided Transversus Abdominis plane INfusions for Pain relief of Abdominal INcisions</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Post-operative laparotomy patients</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Ropivacaine Transversus Abdominis Plane infusion at a rate of 0.1ml/kg/hr bilaterally up to a maximum of 7ml/hr bilaterally via transversus abdominis plane catheter for 48 hours. The infusion rate will be rounded down to the nearest integer (e.g. a 68 kg patient will receive an infusion rate of 6 ml/hr bilaterally).</interventions>
    <comparator>Normal saline Transversus abdominis plane  infusion at a rate of 0.1ml/kg/hr bilaterally up to a maximum of 7ml/hr bilaterally via transversus abdominis plane catheter for 48 hours. The infusion rate will be rounded down to the nearest integer (e.g. a 68 kg patient will receive an infusion rate of 6 ml/hr bilaterally).</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary endpoint of the trial will be the ratio of total morphine administration between 24-48 hours postoperatively and 0-24 hours post-operatively.</outcome>
      <timepoint>48 hrs post-operatively.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A sedation score greater greater than 2.
Sedation scores will be noted, with gradings as follows:
0 = alert.
1 = mild: Sometimes drowsy, easy to rouse and can stay awake once woken.
2 = moderate: Constantly drowsy, still easy to rouse, unable to stay awake once woken.
3 = severe: Constantly drowsy (somnolent), difficult to rouse, severe respiratory depression.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 hours, 24 hours, and 48 hours post-operatively.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Presence or absence of nausea and/or vomiting in the interval prior to assessment will be noted.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 hours, 24 hours, and 48 hours post-operatively.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Presence or absence of pruritis (itch). A yes/no question answered by the patient.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 hours, 24 hours, and 48 hours post-operatively.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain Visual Analogue Score.
Patient pain will be assessed using a visual analogue score (VAS), where patients rate their pain on a 100 mm horizontal line, with one end of the line representing no pain and the other end representing severe pain. 
Patients will be asked to note their VAS at rest and on movement or coughing.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 hours, 24 hours, and 48 hours post-operatively.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The patient's Functional Activity Score will be noted. This is a self-assessed score with gradings as follows: 
0 = no limitation - activity is unrestricted by pain. 
1 = mild limitation - activity is mild to moderately restricted by pain.
2 = severe limitation - the ability to perform the activity is severely limited by pain.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 hours, 24 hours, and 48 hours post-operatively.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total morphine use 0-48 hours post-operatively.</outcome>
      <timepoint>48 hours post-operatively.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients age 18 years or over. 
Elective or semi-elective surgery requiring a mid-line abdominal incision.
Planned intraoperative Transversus Abdominis Plane blocks and postoperative morphine patient controlled analgesia.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Plan for epidural and/or spinal analgesia.
Surgeon or anaesthetist refusal to placement of catheters. 
Inability to communicate in English due to a language barrier, cognitive deficit or intellectual disability.
Inability of patient to use patient controlled analgesia (PCA) pump postoperatively or to understand visual analogue pain score. 
Patients flagged for postoperative ventilation. 
Asthma if exacerbated by non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) or asthma if a patient has never taken a NSAID. 
Acute abdomen, with clinical signs of abdominal peritonism. 
Septicaemia involving positive bacterial blood cultures. 
Localised infection at the site of proposed needle insertion.
Opioid tolerant patients, i.e. any of the following: 
-Patient taking an average of 8 Panadeine  Forte tablets per day for a greater than one week. 
-Patients taking greater than 40 mg oxycodone per day for greater than one week. 
-Patients receiving 20 mg morphine parenterally per day for greater than one week. 
-Patients on a fentanyl patch of dose greater than 12.5 mcg/hour for greater than one week. 
-Any patient receiving buprenorphine. 
-Any patient receiving methadone. 
-Any patient receiving naltrexone or naloxone as part of an opioid abstinence program. 
Any history of injected or inhaled illicit drug use in the previous six months. 
A clinical history of chronic pain, where patients may benefit from early commencement of ketamine.
Renal impairment with creatinine clearance less than 60 mL/min.
Severe hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh score greater than or equal to 10).
Patients with unstable or uncontrolled epilepsy. 
Allergy or contraindication to morphine, ropivacaine, tramadol, parocoxib, sulphonamides or paracetamol. 
Patients on ketaconazole, fluconazole, monoamine oxidase inhibitors, selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs), serotonin noradradrenaline reuptake inhibitors (SNRIs), tricyclic anti-depressents, carbemazepine, quinidine, antipsychotics, zidovudine or warfarin.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Eligible patients to be indentified prior to surgery using surgical lists. They will be approached by research personel to explain trial and obtain consent. Patients will be randomised at the end of surgery to receiving either local anaesthetic or saline infusion. Randomization will be concealed from the investigators and patients as the randomization sequence will be held by the Pharmacy Department. When a patient is recruited, Pharmacy will be contacted and directed to make up the study solution as per the randomization schedule. The log of the bag numbers and the bag contents will be kept by Pharmacy and be available to the Principal Investigator in case of requirement for unblinding. Additionally, a sealed envelope labeled with the patient number will be attached to the infusion bags. This envelope will contain the details of the bags' contents. The envelope will be removed when the study drug comes to theatre, and kept in a locked filing cabinet in the Department of Anaesthesia of the Hospital. This will provide the means for unblinding if Pharmacy is unavailable, for example after hours.</concealment>
    <sequence>When a patient is recruited, they will be assigned a unique 5 digit study code. The first digit codes for the hospital; the next three digits represent the patient number for that hospital; and the final digit will be a check digit, being the sum of the previous four digits. 

Patients will be randomized from a pre-determined computer-generated list (random number generator with numbers 0-0.499 coding for placebo and 0.5-1.0 coding for treatment). The program will be cycled until equal numbers in each group are obtained. The column of numbers generated will be placed next to the second column of numbers listing the eighty study codes. Randomization will be stratified by centre. Randomization will be concealed from the investigators and patients as the randomization sequence will be held by the Pharmacy Department. 
When a patient is recruited, Pharmacy will be contacted and directed to make up the study solution as per the randomization schedule. 

The log of the bag numbers and the bag contents will be kept by Pharmacy and be available to the Principal Investigator in case of requirement for unblinding. Additionally, a sealed envelope labeled with the patient number will be attached to the infusion bags. This envelope will contain the details of the bags’ contents. The envelope will be removed when the study drug comes to theatre, and kept in a locked filing cabinet in the Department of Anaesthesia of the Hospital. This will provide the means for unblinding if Pharmacy is unavailable, for example after hours.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>3011</postcode>
    <postcode>3051</postcode>
    <postcode>3677</postcode>
    <postcode>3220</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Western Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>148 Gordon St 
Footscray  3011
VIC</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Society of Anaesthetists</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Suite 603 Eastpoint Tower
180 Ocean Street
EDGECLIFF NSW 2027
Postal: PO Box 600</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Australian and New Zealand College of Anaesthetists</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>ANZCA House
630 St Kilda Road
Melbourne 3004
VIC</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To evaluate whether local anaesthetic running via a catheter in the abdominal wall improves analgesia following abdominal surgery</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Melbourne Health Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Royal Melbourne Hospital
Grattan St
Parkville 3051
VIC</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/06/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Elizabeth Hessian</name>
      <address>Western Hospital
148 Gordon St
Footscray 3011
VIC</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8345 6639</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 83456572</fax>
      <email>elizabeth.hessian@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Elizabeth Hessian</name>
      <address>Western Hospital
148 Gordon St
Footscray 3011
VIC</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8345 6639</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 83456572</fax>
      <email>elizabeth.hessian@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Elizabeth Hessian</name>
      <address>Western Hospital
148 Gordon St
Footscray 3011
VIC</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8345 6639</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 8345 6572</fax>
      <email>elizabeth.hessian@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>