<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363160">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/10/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/10/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001127897</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of pole walking on functional abilities and psychosocial wellbeing in older adults: A randomized controlled trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of moderate intensity pole walking and regular walking on functional and psychosocial health in older adults: a randomized controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Functional measures</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>psycho social measures</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>joint pain</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>physical activity levels</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention consists of a pole walking program in which participants will walk with poles, similar to cross country ski poles. Each site will have one group of 10 pole walkers. The intervention group will exercise outdoors for up to 60 minutes, 3 times weekly, for 12 weeks. Intensity will be self-assessed during the exercise sessions using the Borg scale at a level of 3-4 (moderate). Qualified exercise instructors who have undergone training in the pole walking technique will instruct the PW participants in the first session, and subsequently supervise all pole walking exercise sessions.</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator program is a walking program in which participants will walk without poles. The program will be identical to the pole walking program, as follows: Each site will have one group of 10 walkers.  The group will exercise outdoors for up to 60 minutes, 3 times weekly, for 12 weeks. Intensity will be self-assessed during the exercise sessions using the Borg scale at a level of 3-4 (moderate). Qualified exercise instructors will supervise all walking exercise sessions.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional fitness, as measured b the Senior Fitness Test</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life as measured by the SF-12</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Vitality, as measured by the Vitality plus scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Social support, as measured by the Broadhead 8-item scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity, as measured by accelerometry, the Active Australia Survey, and the 5-domain sitting questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain, as measured by the Numerical Rating Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>older adults</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exercising over 150 mins per week over 5 or more days in the previous week, medical approval to participate in a walking programme denied, unable to speak or understand English , having a shoulder and elbow flexion range of motion (ROM) of less than 90 degrees, having pathological conditions of the upper extremity.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>60 participants will be recruited from four senior living facilities at different geographic locations. Initial phone contact to the organisations will be followed by an email or letter that will be given to organisation leaders to introduce the study and the lead researcher. “Active Aging” seminars will be offered to the residents at the facilities through the facility gatekeepers . The seminars will consist of presentation of information and discussion on the benefits of physical activity for aging. Participants will be recruited through the seminars at the senior living facilities . An opportunity for participants to join the study will be presented at the end of the seminars. An information brochure, with inclusion and exclusion criteria, will be given to all participants in the seminar. Interested individuals will be asked to contact (telephone or email) the project supervisor who will provide additional written information on the background and aim of the study, the study protocol, and the personal costs and benefits for the participants. Respondents will be screened to ascertain medical eligibility by using the Australian College of Sports Medicine Pre-exercise screening tool. Potential participants will be assessed in an initial testing session at a convenient indoor location to the participants. Prior to any data collection, individuals will receive both verbal and written information about the study. Prior to enrollment in the study, participants will be asked to sign a consent form indicating their understanding of study requirements. They also should be willing to be randomised to participate in one of two 12 week groups targeting walking during the working day. Testing sessions will be conducted using trained assessors who are not aware of participants’ groups in an individual baseline test session before the trial commences. Allocation concealment will be done as follows: Participants in each location will be randomized into either a pole walking group or a walking group using cental randomisation by computer. The statistical computer program SPSS will be used to randomly assign participants at each of the four intervention sites into the pole walking  or the walking group.</concealment>
    <sequence>The statistical computer program SPSS will be used to randomly assign participants at each of the three intervention sites into the pole walking group (n=10) or the walking group (n=10).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>3 sites will be used, with each site hosting two groups of participants, one a pole walking group, and one a walking group.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/03/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>14/05/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>28/06/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>28/06/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <state>Kentucky</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>St Lucia, 4072
Brisbane QLD</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Queensland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>St Lucia, 4072
Brisbane, QLD</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>60 participants over 65 years old will be recruited from four senior independent living facilities. They will undergo a pre-exercise test session. In it they will complete a a self administered questionnaire which will include questions on general health and wellbeing, physical activity levels, joint pain levels, sitting behaviours, vitality, and social support. Measurements of blood pressure, height, weight, and waist circumference, hand grip strength will be taken. Functional fitness tests will be administered which will include a 30-second chair-stand test, a 30-second arm-curl test, a 3 meter, up-and go test, and a 6-minute walk test. Daily physical activity levels will be recorded and measured by a small activity monitoring device (accelerometer) worn during 5 consecutive week days by participants. In addition, subjects will fill in a brief activity diary to verify the time the accelerometers were worn. The participants will then be randomised into two groups of up to 8 participants per site. Both groups will exercise outdoors for up to 60 minutes, 3 times weekly, for 12 weeks at a moderate intensity. Exerstrider (registered trademark) walking poles and walking technique will be used in the experimental group. Following the 12 week exercise period, a post exercise test consisting of the same measures as the pre-test will be undertaken. 	 	</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Queensland ethics committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ethics Officer
Research &amp; Innovation Division
Cumbrae-Stewart Building (72)
THE UNIVERSITY OF QUEENSLAND, St Lucia, 4072
Brisbane
QLD</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/12/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/10/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Juliette Fritschi</name>
      <address>The School of Human Movement Studies
Level 5, Human Movement Studies Building (26B), Blair Drive
The University of Queensland
St Lucia QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 6240</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3365 6877</fax>
      <email>juliette.fritschi@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Juliette Fritschi</name>
      <address>The School of Human Movement Studies
Level 5, Human Movement Studies Building (26B), Blair Drive
The University of Queensland
St Lucia QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 6240</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3365 6877</fax>
      <email>juliette.fritschi@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Juliette Fritschi</name>
      <address>The School of Human Movement Studies
Level 5, Human Movement Studies Building (26B), Blair Drive
The University of Queensland
St Lucia QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 6240</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3365 6877</fax>
      <email>juliette.fritschi@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Juliette Fritschi</name>
      <address>C/O School of Human Movement Studies
The University of Queensland
St Lucia, QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61, 7, 3365 6240</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>juliette.fritschi@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>