<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343225">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/07/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/07/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000776909</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial investigating the efficacy of Eleutherococcus senticisus (Araliacae: Siberian ginseng) on the amelioration of the symptoms of overtraining syndrome in Ironman triathletes</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial investigating the efficacy of Eleutherococcus senticisus (Araliacae: Siberian ginseng) on the amelioration of the symptoms of overtraining syndrome in Ironman triathletes</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1123-0477</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Overtraining syndrome</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Conditions of unknown or disputed aetiology (such as chronic fatigue syndrome/myalgic encephalomyelitis)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Herbal remedies</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Eleutherococcus senticosus (Araliacae: Siberian ginseng).  Two tablets each taken twice daily. Each tablet contains 1g of Eleutherococcus senticosus.  Total daily dose of Eleuthrococcus senticosus is 4 g per day.  Participants will take the tablets for the final 6 weeks of the 12 week trial.  The first 6 weeks of the trial involves elucidating from the daily heart rate and core temperature measurement as well as the blood samples and time trials whether the individuals are at risk of developing overtraining syndrome or not.  Participants will take the herbal remedy for a total of 6 weeks as this is the standard time that this rememdy is given.  This will make it comparable to clinical situations.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo consisting of microcellulose coated to have an identical appearance to the intervention tablets</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>No decrease in performance times in the Ironman event.  A performance decrement of 10% or greater of elapsed time in the Ironman event which cannot be explained by any other means (wind, waves, cureents, punctures, injuries) is regarded as overtraining syndrome.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Performance decrease in time trials.  These time trial consist of a 400m swim in a 50m heated outdoor pool, a 4 km run held on an enclosed, but open roofed running track, and a 20 km simulated time trial on a cycle ergometer using the Tacx System</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 weeks, 6 weeks and 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in blood concentrations of corticotrophic releasing hormone (CRH), adrenocorticitrophic releasing hormone (ACTH) and cortisol</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 weeks, 6 weeks, 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>No jump in day to day waking pulse of 5 beats per minute or more.  Pulse is taken manually by the participant and counted for one full minute</outcome>
      <timepoint>The pulse is taken daily and any jump in waking heart rate from one day to the next of 5 beats per minute or more is regarded as indicative of overtraining syndrome. The pulse rate is therefore assessed over the entire 12 week period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Daily waking rectal temperature is taken and monitored. Temperature is taken by an Omron electronic digital thermometer. No mercury is involved</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily for 12 weeks.  Changes in core temperature is taken as evidence that the hypothalamic control of core temperature has been altered</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Any changes in blood concentration of CRH, ACTH and cortisol will be correlated to performce decrements</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 weeks, 6 weeks, 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Athletes entered in an Ironman triathlon</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Medically diagnosed conditions, medically diagnosed cognitive impairment, participants currently on prescribed medication for any condition except the oral birth control pill</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Double blind randomised placebo controlled trial.  There is allocation concealment.  The active remedy and the placebos will be given to the researchers supervisor located in the central administration who will allocate numbers by random number generator to containers.  He will note what numbers are allocated to active substance or placebo.  Neither the researcher nor the participants will have access to the numbering system nor whether it is placebo or active ingredient.  This will only be given to the researcher after statistical analysis of the results are made.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerised random number generator</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The participants will be effectively differentiated into the control group and the active ingredient group.  They will receive the intervention in the final 6 weeks of the study.  Traditionally Eleutherococcus senticosus and other adaptogenic herbal remedies are only given for a 6 week period.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>66</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Murdoch University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>South Street
Murdoch WA 6150</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Damon Kendrick</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>2/11 Pearce Street, Ermington NSW2115</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Australian College of Physical Education</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>1 Figtree Drive, Sydney Olympic Park, NSW 2127</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The hypothesis is that overtraining syndrome due to hypothalamic dysfunction and that Eleutherococcus will assist in preventing overtrainign syndrome.  Evidence for hypothalamic dysfunction is made by changes in waking core body temperature, and also by measuring changes in corticotrophic releasong hormine (CRH) which is released by the hypothalamus in times of stress.  This hormone CRH in turn stimulates the pituitary gland to release adrenocorticotrophic hormone (ACTH) which stimulates the adrenal cortex to release cortisol.  Cortisol is a stress hormone.  All three of these hormones are measured at 0, 6 and 12 weeks.  The study will determine if there is any difference in these hormones between the control cohort and the active ingerdient cohort</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Endeavour College of Natural Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>170 Wellington Street
East Perth WA 6004</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/05/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1/11/0027</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>8/04/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Murdoch University HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>South Street
Murdoch WA 6150</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>EC00269</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/08/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Damon Kendrick</name>
      <address>2/11 Pearce Street, Ermington NSW2115</address>
      <phone>+61410441306</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>damonkendrick@optusnet.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Damon Kendrick</name>
      <address>10 Manners Street
East Victoria Park WA 6101</address>
      <phone>+61410441306</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>damonkendrick@optusnet.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Damon Kendrick</name>
      <address>2/11 Pearce Street, Ermimgton NSW 2115</address>
      <phone>+61410441306</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>damonkendrick@optusnet.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>