<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320710">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/10/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/10/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000924257</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial of Plasmalyte148 with 5% dextrose compared to 0.45% sodium chloride with 5% dextrose for maintenance intravenous fluid therapy in hospitalised children.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In hospitalised children requiring maintenance intravenous therapy, does Plasmalyte148 with 5% dextrose compared to 0.45% sodium chloride with 5% dextrose result in less hyponatraemia?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>PIMS (Paediatric Intravenous Maintenance Solution)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Royal Children's Hospital HREC 29071</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>Royal Children's Hospital HREC 29071</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Prevention of iatrogenic hyponatraemia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Conditions of unknown or disputed aetiology (such as chronic fatigue syndrome/myalgic encephalomyelitis)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Plasmalyte148 with 5% dextrose
Mode of administration: intravenous infusion
Rate of infusion: to be determined by the treating clinician, but must be between 50 - 150% of standard maintenance rates (based on the 100/50/20 or 4/2/1 rule).
Duration of infusion: Subjects will remain in the trial while they are receiving intravenous fluids at a rate of at least 50% maintenance, or for 72 hours (whichever is sooner).</interventions>
    <comparator>0.45% sodium chloride with 5% dextrose  Mode of administration: intravenous infusion Rate of infusion: to be determined by the treating clinician, but must be between 50 - 150% of standard maintenance rates (based on the 100/50/20 rule as described by Holliday and Segar). Duration of infusion: Subjects will remain in the trial while they are receiving intravenous fluids at a rate of at least 50% maintenance, or for 72 hours (whichever is sooner).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome is the proportion of subjects in each treatment group that develop hyponatraemia [serum sodium measurement that is below the normal range minimum (135mmol/L) and has decreased by at least 3mmol/L compared with the baseline measurement] at any time point during the treatment period.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Subjects will remain in the trial while they are receiving at least 50% of standard maintenance fluid rates, or for 72 hours (whichever is sooner).  They will have blood tests performed at 0, 6, 24, 48 and 72 hours, while they remain in the trial.  Additional blood tests may be performed between these time points, as determined by the treating clinician.  There is no maximum number of blood tests which may be performed.  All blood tests performed may be used in the analysis.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of subjects in each treatment group with a measurement of hypernatraemia (serum sodium &gt;145 with an increase of at least 3mmol/L compared with the baseline measurement) at any time during the study period.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Subjects will remain in the trial while they are receiving at least 50% of standard maintenance fluid rates, or for 72 hours (whichever is sooner).  They will have blood tests performed at 0, 6, 24, 48 and 72 hours, while they remain in the trial.  Additional blood tests may be performed between these time points, as determined by the treating clinician.  There is no maximum number of blood tests which may be performed.  All blood tests performed may be used in the analysis.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of subjects in each treatment group with a measurement of severe hyponatraemia (serum sodium &lt;130 with a decrease of at least 3mmol/L compared with the baseline measurement) at any time during the study period.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Subjects will remain in the trial while they are receiving at least 50% of standard maintenance fluid rates, or for 72 hours (whichever is sooner).  They will have blood tests performed at 0, 6, 24, 48 and 72 hours, while they remain in the trial.  Additional blood tests may be performed between these time points, as determined by the treating clinician.  There is no maximum number of blood tests which may be performed.  All blood tests performed may be used in the analysis.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of subjects in each treatment group with a measurement of severe hypernatraemia (serum sodium &gt;150 with an increase of at least 3mmol/L compared with the baseline measurement) at any time during the study period.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Subjects will remain in the trial while they are receiving at least 50% of standard maintenance fluid rates, or for 72 hours (whichever is sooner).  They will have blood tests performed at 0, 6, 24, 48 and 72 hours, while they remain in the trial.  Additional blood tests may be performed between these time points, as determined by the treating clinician.  There is no maximum number of blood tests which may be performed.  All blood tests performed may be used in the analysis.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A comparison of fluid status in each treatment group.  This will be clinically assessed by the treating clinician who will state whether the subject is clinically dehydrated, euvolaemia or overhydrated.  They will also record which clinical features or investigations resulted in this assessment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Clinical assessments will occur at 0, 6, 24, 48 and 72 hours as well as at the end of treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean serum sodium at each time point</outcome>
      <timepoint>The mean serum sodium at 6, 24, 48 and 72 hours will be examined, while the subject remains in the trial.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in weight from baseline using standard calibrated digital scales.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change in weight at 6, 24, 48 and 72 hours will be examined, while the subject remains in the trial.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of intravenous (IV) cannula reinsertions required.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Number of reinsertions required for each subject throughout the study period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of electrolyte imbalances in each study group including hyperchloraemia, high serum bicarbonate and high serum magnesium.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Subjects will remain in the trial while they are receiving at least 50% of standard maintenance fluid rates, or for 72 hours (whichever is sooner). They will have blood tests performed at 0, 6, 24, 48 and 72 hours, while they remain in the trial. Additional blood tests may be performed between these time points, as determined by the treating clinician. There is no maximum number of blood tests which may be performed. All blood tests performed may be used in the analysis.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean urinary sodium</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours after starting treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients with seizures in each study group.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the study period: Subjects will remain in the trial while they are receiving at least 50% of standard maintenance fluid rates, or for 72 hours (whichever is sooner). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cerebral oedema, confirmed by neuroimaging (CT or MRI).</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the study period: Subjects will remain in the trial while they are receiving at least 50% of standard maintenance fluid rates, or for 72 hours (whichever is sooner). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>To be eligible for this study, each subject must be aged between 3 months and 18 years old, be a patient at the Royal Children's Hospital in Melbourne and be assessed by an independent clinician as requiring intravenous fluid therapy at a rate of at least 50% and up to 150% recommended maintenance.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>3</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Months</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>An initial plasma sodium level of &lt;130 or &gt;150. A known abnormality of antidiuretic hormone secretion. Diabetic ketoacidosis. Renal disease requiring dialysis. A known disorder causing excessive renal sodium excretion. Pre or postoperative neurosurgical or craniofacial patients, requiring opening of the cranial cavity. Oncology patients requiring protocol-determined chemotherapy hydration. Children with inborn errors of metabolism requiring protocol determined fluid therapy. Proven meningitis. Severe liver disease. Conditions where intravenous fluids are anticipated to be given for less than six hours. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Initially sealed opaque envelopes.  It is anticipated that an on-line enrollment program will be available within two months of the study commencing - at this point this computerised system will be used for treatment allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation sequence will be developed by a statistician using block randomisation.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>21/12/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>690</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Children's Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Flemington Rd,
Parkville, Victoria, 3052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Murdoch Children's Research Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Flemington Rd,
Parkville, Victoria, 3052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Anaesthesia, Royal Children's Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Flemington Rd,
Parkville, Victoria, 3052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>When children are hospitalised, they often require fluid through an intravenous line (or drip).  This is usually because they cant eat or drink enough to stay hydrated.  The fluid is made up of water, sugar and some salts.  

There is uncertainty regarding the ideal sodium concentration for fluid given through a drip.  Sodium is a salt which is naturally contained in the body.  However, when sodium levels in the body rise or fall suddenly, it is dangerous.  In rare cases, this has led to brain damage and death.  

Currently, when children need intravenous fluid, they are usually given a fluid that contains about half the concentration of sodium that the blood in the body naturally contains.  This fluid is called 0.45% sodium chloride.  For most children, this doesnt have a bad effect.  However, in some sick children, this fluid dilutes the blood, causing the blood sodium level to drop quickly.  This side effect is rare, but is potentially very serious.

We believe that we can make the fluid safer by increasing the sodium concentration.  This should make it less likely that the sodium level in the blood will drop suddenly.  This, in turn, should reduce the number of children who have bad side effects.

We will conduct a study that compares the fluid we currently use (0.45% sodium chloride) with a fluid that contains more sodium (Plasmalyte148).  Plasmalyte148 contains approximately the same concentration of sodium as is naturally contained in the blood.  This is approximately double the concentration of sodium when compared with 0.45% sodium chloride.  

Children at the Royal Childrens Hospital who require fluid through a drip will be asked to participate in the trial.  They will be randomly allocated either to 0.45% sodium chloride or to Plasmalyte148.  The participants will not know the type of fluid they receive, nor will their doctors.  The participants will be monitored with regular blood tests.   

The children will stay in the study for three days, or until they no longer require most of their hydration through a drip.  We will compare blood test results for the children in each group (the 0.45% sodium chloride group compared with the Plasmalyte148 group).  We will determine whether Plasmalyte148 results in more normal blood sodium results when compared with the fluid we currently use.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee, Royal Children's Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Flemington Rd,
Parkville, Victoria, 3052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/10/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>29071</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Sarah McNab</name>
      <address>c/o Centre for International Child Health
Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Rd
Parkville, Victoria, 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9345 4154</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sarah.mcnab@rch.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Sarah McNab</name>
      <address>c/o Centre for International Child Health
Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Rd
Parkville, Victoria, 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9345 4154</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sarah.mcnab@rch.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Sarah McNab</name>
      <address>c/o Department of General Medicine
Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Rd
Parkville, Victoria
Australia
3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9345 4154</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sarah.mcnab@rch.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>