<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82063">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/06/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/06/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000306415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>How do people with a spinal cord injury sing?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An investigation into the mechanisms used when singing by people with a spinal cord injury</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Quadriplegia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of the normal brain and nervous system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Observational study comparing respiratory function and voice projection between quadriplegics and able-bodied, matched controls when singing and speaking. Physiological assessments of respiratory function and acoustic and perceptual assessments of voice projection (approx 1 hour each in duration) will constitute outcome measures for the study.</interventions>
    <comparator>There is no treatment as such, just an assessment which is the same for both the quadriplegic subjects and the able-bodied matched controls</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>None</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Respiratory capacity - Ventilatory function and upper airway function will be assessed using maximal flow-volume loops to determine maximal inspiratory and expiratory flow rates, and timed lung volumes.  Static lung volumes will be measured using whole-body plethysmography in those subjects able to sit in the plethysmograph, or by inert-gas dilution otherwise.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured when the participant enters the study and undergoes all the physiological and voice assessments.  This single measurement (comprising both the physiological and voice assessments) is the basis for comparison between subjects. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Respiratory muscle strength (specifically maximal sniff and inspiratory (MIP) muscle pressures) - Respiratory muscle strength will be assessed by measuring maximal inspiratory (MIP), expiratory (MEP) and sniff (SNIP) pressures.  Patterns of tidal respiration will be assessed using calibrated respiratory-inductive plethysmography (Respitrace) to document relative contributions to ventilation of thoracic and abdominal compartments. Surface measurements of muscle (EMG) activity will be made to examine the relative timing and magnitude of the contribution from respiratory and postural muscles.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured when the participant enters the study and undergoes all the physiological and voice assessments.  This single measurement (comprising both the physiological and voice assessments) is the basis for comparison between subjects. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quantitative measures of voice (pitch, amplitude) - Spectrum analysis of vocal data will be conducted by extracting acoustic parameters (e.g., pitch, amplitude, and spectral characteristics) produced during speech/voice production using calibrated recording equipment and speech analysis software. These analyses will provide quantitative measures of voice quality. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured when the participant enters the study and undergoes all the physiological and voice assessments.  This single measurement (comprising both the physiological and voice assessments) is the basis for comparison between subjects. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measures of thoraco-abdominal motion, indices of respiratory flow and volume and qualitative assessments of voice. Patterns of tidal respiration will be assessed using calibrated respiratory-inductive plethysmography (Respitrace) to document relative contributions to ventilation of thoracic and abdominal compartments. Surface measurements of muscle (EMG) activity will be made to examine the relative timing and magnitude of the contribution from respiratory and postural muscles. A standardized perceptual voice assessment (Frenchay Dysarthria Assessment) will be conducted by an experienced speech pathologist. The assessment period for when these outcomes will be measured is when the participant enters the study and undergoes all the physiological and voice assessments.  This single measurement (comprising both the physiological and voice assessments) is the basis for comparison between subjects. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured when the participant enters the study and undergoes all the physiological and voice assessments. This single measurement (comprising both the physiological and voice assessments) is the basis for comparison between subjects</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Quadriplegia C4-C6, at least 1 year post injury. Currently resident in Victoria and able to travel to assessment sessions. English speaking and stable general health without pulmonary disease at the time of assessment.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Previous history of speech disorder, respiratory disease, psychiatric disorder, or neurological impairment prior to SCI. Tracheostomy. Currently receiving singing or voice tuition.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Case control</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Austin Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 5555, Studley Rd, Heidelberg, Victoria 3084, Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Victorian Neurotrauma Incentive</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 14, 222 Exhibition St, Melbourne, Victoria, 3000, Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Institute for Breathing and Sleep</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Bowen Centre, Austin Hospital, PO Box 5555, Studley Rd, Heidelberg, Victoria 3084, Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Spinal Cord Injury (SCI) is a sudden and traumatic event causing permanent paralysis and ongoing disability. Respiratory dysfunction is a major cause of morbidity and mortality in SCI, causing reduced lung volumes and air flow rates. Some people living with quadriplegia (the loss of function in both arms and legs) are able to sing far more effectively than would be predicted on the basis of their injury level and severity alone. This study aims to determine the mechanisms by which these individuals achieve such impressive functional outcomes. Ten chronic cervical SCI subjects and 10 matched controls will be assessed during singing and speech using standardised phrases. Physiological tests including spirometry and EMG analysis will be utilised in addition to acoustic analysis of vocal amplitude. It is expected that in order to achieve the increased respiratory support required when singing, patients with quadriplegia will use innovative muscle recruitment and control strategies. The results of this investigation have important implications for therapeutic singing interventions during rehabilitation. Given that respiratory dysfunction is a major cause of morbidity and mortality after SCI, the effect of singing on respiratory function warrants further, rigorous investigation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health,</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 5555, Studley Rd, Heidelberg, Victoria, 3084, Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/12/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H2007/02932</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/05/2007</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jeanette Tamplin</name>
      <address>Institute for Breathing and Sleep, Bowen Centre, Austin Hospital, PO Box 5555 Studley Rd, Heidelberg, 3084, Victoria, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94963877 or 0402019753</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 94907329</fax>
      <email>jeanette.tamplin@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jeanette Tamplin</name>
      <address>Institute for Breathing and Sleep, Bowen Centre, Austin Hospital, PO Box 5555 Studley Rd, Heidelberg, 3084, Victoria, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94963877</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 94907329</fax>
      <email>jeanette.tamplin@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jeanette Tamplin</name>
      <address>Institute for Breathing and Sleep, Bowen Centre, Austin Hospital, PO Box 5555 Studley Rd, Heidelberg, 3084, Victoria, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94963877</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jeanette.tamplin@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>