<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365012">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/12/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/01/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000094673</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Clinical Evaluation of the Cook Advance (Registered Trademark) Scoring Balloon in treating stenoses of mature native arteriovenous (AV) hemodialysis access circuit </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Clinical Evaluation of the Advance (Registered Trademark) 35 Scoring Percutaneous Transluminal Angioplasty (PTA) Balloon Dilatation Catheter in treating stenoses of a mature native arteriovenous (AV) hemodialysis access circuit</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ADVANCE</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Stenoses of a mature native arteriovenous (AV) hemodialysis access circuit</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Advance Scoring Balloon is a balloon catheter used to perform angioplasty in narrowed blood vessels. In this study it is used to treat narrowing of a hemodialysis fistula in order to improve the effectiveness of dialysis. Angiography and intravascular ultrasound will be used during the procedure to examine the effectiveness of the study procedure. The procedure should take approximately 45 minutes. After the procedure, participants are required to complete follow-up visits at 1, 3, and 6 months to undergo clinical assessment. An angiogram will also be performed at 3 and 6 months post-procedure.</interventions>
    <comparator>No comparator/control treatment.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Procedural peformance of the device, specifically:
1. Extent of residual stenosis (less than 30 %) within the treated lesion immediately after angioplasty, assessed by angiography
2. Inflation pressure of scoring balloon, measured using a balloon inflation device with atmospheric pressure guage
3. Adverse events, e.g. aneurysm; vessel dissection, perforation, rupture or injury; pain and/or discomfort at stenosis during treatment; hematoma 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout the duration of the procedure and immediately after the procedure. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Short term perfomance of the device assessed by resumption of normal dialysis and target lesion patency at 6 months post-procedure.
Resumption of normal dialysis will be assessed by obtaining dialysis treatment information on the patient following the study procedure.
Target lesion patency will be assessed based on continued successful dialysis treatment, need for re-intervention or abandonment of access site, and angiography at 6 months. </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post-procedure</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Short term perfomance of the device assessed by target lesion patency at 1 and 3 months post-procedure.
Target lesion patency will be assessed based on continued successful dialysis treatment, need for re-intervention or abandonment of access site, and angiography at 3 months (angiography not performed at 1 month). </outcome>
      <timepoint>1 and 3 months post-procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. A greater than 50% stenosis (when compared to the reference vessel diameter) of a mature native AV dialysis access circuit in the upper extremity
2. Clinical or physiological abnormalities which indicate dialysis access dysfunction</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Any related surgical or interventional procedure of the access circuit less than or equal to 30 days prior to the enrollment
2. Medical condition or comorbid conditions that would limit life expectancy to less than 6 months
3. Scheduled for a kidney transplant
4. Known hypersensitivity or contraindication to contrast agent that, in the opinion of the investigator, cannot be adequately pre-medicated
5. Synthetic AV dialysis access graft
6. Current or previous history of thrombosis anywhere within the AV dialysis access circuit
7. Evidence of systemic or local infection associated with the AV dialysis access circuit
8. History of bleeding diathesis or coagulopathy or will refuse blood transfusions
9. Stent or stent graft in the AV dialysis access circuit
10. Hemodynamically significant central venous stenosis, unless successfully treated prior to treating the study lesion
11. Presence of occlusion in the AV dialysis access circuit such that a guidewire cannot pass through the lesion
12. Target lesion is greater than or equal to 4 cm in length
13. Reference vessel diameter is greater than 12 mm
14. Presence of more than two distinct lesions (stenoses) in the AV dialysis access circuit</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>25/03/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>12/03/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>28</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Cook Incorporated</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>750 Daniels Way
Bloomington, IN 47404
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cook Incorporated
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>750 Daniels Way
Bloomington, IN 47404
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to assess the safety and performance of the Cook Advance Scoring Balloon in treating narrowed blood vessels to improve the effectiveness of haemodialysis treatments. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern A Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
No 1 The Terrace
Wellington
6011
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/10/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>13/NTA/160</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/09/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Andrew Holden </name>
      <address>Radiology Department
Auckland City Hospital 
Park Road
Grafton 1142
Auckland</address>
      <phone>+64 (0)9 3074949 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>AndrewH@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Helen Knight </name>
      <address>Radiology Department
Auckland City Hospital 
Park Road
Grafton 1142
Auckland</address>
      <phone>+64 (0)21 405 586</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>HKnight@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Andrew Holden </name>
      <address>Radiology Department
Auckland City Hospital 
Park Road
Grafton 1142
Auckland</address>
      <phone>+64 (0)9 3074949 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>AndrewH@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Berneen Gardiner</name>
      <address>William A. Cook Australia Pty Ltd
95 Brandl Street
Eight Mile Plains
Brisbane
QLD 4113</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)7 3841 1188</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>berneen.gardiner@cookmedical.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>