<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335192">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/04/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/04/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000339055</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Reducing cervical cancer risks: a toolkit for a young woman</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised trial of web-based toolkit for applying evidence in the general practice cervical cancer prevention visit</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cervical cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Cervical (cervix)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Women in the intervention group will be receiving an online decision tool prior to the consultation. They will be sent a study ID to access the online tool as soon as they register to the trial. They can visit the website as many times as they like before their Pap visit. The tool will be a one-stop source of information for cervical cancer prevention.It will incorporate evidence-based information cervical cancer risk reduction options such as lifestyle factors, Pap smear (conventional and LBC), HPV vaccination. The tool will also use epidemiological estimates of cumulative risks and text based information with quantitative estimates of outcomes. We will show women in absolute terms the chances of low-grade intraepithelial lesion (LSIL), high-grade intraepithelial lesion (HSIL and cervical cancer at their age and their reduction in risk with Pap smear, Liquid based cytology (LBC), Human papillomavirus (HPV) vaccine and lifestyle changes (smoking cessation, condom use...).
The overall duration of the study will be 6 months. Two months for recruiting participants, 2 months for collecting data and 2 months follow up for participants who have not attended their Pap smear consultation.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care: it involves women routine one on one Pap consultation with their General Practitioner (GP). The duration of the consultation will differ on a case by case basis.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of young women adequately informed about Human papillomavirus (HPV) without increasing consultation time. HPV knowledge will be assessed using an online questionnaire that women will have to complete after their Pap visit. The consultation time will be collected from GPs softwares by a data extraction tool called Canning which is modified specifically for the purpose of this study by Canning Division.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within a week after women's consultation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Knowledge about cervical cancer test accuracy and co-factors. This outcome will be assessed by an online questionnaire that women will have to complete after their Pap visit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within a week after women's consultation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>HPV vaccine uptake. This outcome will be collected from GPs softwares by a data extraction tool called Canning which is modified specifically for the purpose of this study by Canning Division.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within a week after women's consultation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Uptake of liquid-based cytology. This outcome will be collected from GPs softwares by a data extraction tool called Canning which is modified specifically for the purpose of this study by Canning Division.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within a week after women's consultation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self reported change in smoking and other co-factor behaviours. This outcome will be assessed by an online questionnaire that women will have to complete after their Pap visit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within a week after women's consultation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Provider communication. This outcome measures young women's perceptions
of communication with the GP regarding Pap smear. This outcome will be assessed using Provider-Adolescent Communication Scale (PACS) questionnaire. This will be completed online by women after their Pap visit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within a week after women's consultation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>19-26 year old women living in Australia who have internet access and a reasonnable command of the english language and who are considering to have cervical cancer prevention visit.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>19</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>26</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>No internet access , poor english, younger than 19 years or older than 26 years.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Elegible participants who agree to be in the study will be asked a few questions, including their age, mailing and email adress. Participant will be assigned then an ID code generated by computer. Women in the intervention arm will be sent a passeword to access the online cervical cancer prevention toolkit before their Pap test visit. Once participants have registred and completed the online consent, they will be randomised into either intervention or control group using an algorithm which will ensure equal distribution of the intervention and control arm of the study.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>890</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Lyndal Trevena</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Room 321b Edward Ford Building (A27)
University of Sydney NSW 2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cancer Council NSW</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>153 Dowling Street Woolloomooloo
NSW 2011</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Kirsten McCaffery</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Edward Ford Building (A27)
University of Sydney NSW 2006</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Alexandra Barratt</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Edward Ford Building (A27)
University of Sydney NSW 2006</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Julie-Anne Leask</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>The Children's Hospital at Westmead
Locked Bag 4001
Westmead NSW 2145</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Julia Brotherton</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Level 1, 250 Victoria Pde, East Melbourne 3002</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study looks the effectiveness of a web-based toolkit for young women, explaining how to reduce the risks of cervical cancer. You can join this study if you are a woman aged 19-26 years, have access to the internet and are considering a GP visit to discuss cervical cancer prevention. Trial details Participants visiting their GP will be divided into two groups. One group will be provided with an online decision tool prior to the consultation. The other group will have a standard consultation only. The web-based toolkit will be a one-stop source of information for the latest information about cervical cancer, and will also provide feedback on consultation length, HPV knowledge, etc. Women will ideally learn to access the tool before their Pap test every two years. The aim is see whether the toolkit is effective in increasing the proportion of young women adequately informed about HPV without increasing the consultation time. The preparation of patients before the consultation is an important model that could be transferable to other aspects of general practice.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Sydney HUMAN RESEARCH ETHICS COMMITTEE</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Camperdown 
2006 NSW</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/03/2005</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>10696</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Lyndal Trevena</name>
      <address>Room 321b Edward Ford Building (A27)
University of Sydney NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 7788</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351 5049</fax>
      <email>lyndalt@health.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Lyndal Trevena</name>
      <address>Room 321b Edward Ford Building (A27)
University of Sydney NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 7788</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351 5049</fax>
      <email>lyndalt@health.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mbathio Dieng</name>
      <address>Room 125 Edward Ford Building (A27)
University of Sydney NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 3137</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351 5049</fax>
      <email>mdieng@health.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>