<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369695">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/12/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/01/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000028404</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The efficacy of adjunctive Garcinia mangostana linn (mangosteen) pericarp for bipolar depression: A 24-week double-blind, randomised, placebo controlled trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The efficacy of adjunctive Garcinia mangostana linn (mangosteen) pericarp for bipolar depression: A 24-week double-blind, randomised, placebo controlled trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>MANGO BD</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Bipolar depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>1000mg/day of oral (2 capsules, once a day) of adjunctive Garcinia Mangostana Linn. (mangosteen) pericarp will be trialled against placebo for 24 weeks to determine the efficacy of mangosteen pericarp for the treatment of bipolar depression.  Adherence will be monitored by participants returning all bottles of investigational product, including any unused capsules. </interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo (inactive starch)</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>change in severity of mood symptoms, measured using the Montgomery Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Conducted at all trial visits - Baseline (week 0) and every four weeks after that (week 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Clinical Global Impressions - Improvement Scale (CGI-I)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Conducted at all trial visits - Baseline (week 0), every four weeks after that (week 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24) and week 28 (4 weeks post discontinuation).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Clincial Global Impressions - Severity Scale (CGI-S)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Conducted at all trial visits - Baseline (week 0), every four weeks after that (week 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24) and week 28 (4 weeks post discontinuation).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in anxiety symptoms based on the Hamilton Anxeity Rating Scale (HAM-A)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Conducted at all trial visits - Baseline (week 0), every four weeks after that (week 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24) and week 28 (4 weeks post discontinuation).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in bipolar symptomology as measured by Bipolar Depression Rating Scale (BDRS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Conducted at all trial visits - Baseline (week 0), every four weeks after that (week 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24) and week 28 (4 weeks post discontinuation).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in mania symptomology measured by the Young Mania Rating Scale (YMRS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Conducted at all trial visits - Baseline (week 0), every four weeks after that (week 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24) and four weeks post-discontinuation at week 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Patient Global Impression Scale (PGI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Conducted every four weeks after baseline (week 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24) and week 28 (4 weeks post discontinuation).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in quality of life measured by Quality of life Enjoyment and Stisfaction Questionnaire - Short Form (Q-LES-Q-SF)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Conducted at all trial visits - Baseline (week 0), every four weeks after that (week 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24) and week 28 (4 weeks post discontinuation).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Functioning measured by Social Occupational Functioning Scale (SOFAS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Conducted at all trial visits - Baseline (week 0), every four weeks after that (week 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24) and week 28 (4 weeks post discontinuation).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Functioning measured by Range of Impaired Functioning Tool (LIFE-RIFT)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Conducted at all trial visits - Baseline (week 0), every four weeks after that (week 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24) and week 28 (4 weeks post discontinuation).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in oxidative stress (malondialdehyde) markers</outcome>
      <timepoint>Bloods collected from consenting participants at baseline and week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in severity of mood symptoms following discontinuation of trial medication, measured using MADRS</outcome>
      <timepoint>The post-discontinuation of treatment (week 28) will be analysed both between week 24 and week 28.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in inflamatory (IL-6, TNF-alpha and CRP) markers</outcome>
      <timepoint>Bloods collected from consenting participants at baseline and week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in neuroprotection (Bcl-2) markers</outcome>
      <timepoint>Bloods collected from consenting participants at baseline and week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Must be required to meet DSM-5 criteria for bipolar disorderI or II, cyclothymic disorder or bipolar disorder not elsewhere classified (NEC),

2. Have a current episode of depressive illness with a MADRS score greater than or equal to 20

3. Have capacity to consent to the study and comply with study procedures

4. Any form of therapy must be stable for the last month 

5. Using effective contraception if female, sexually active and of child bearing potential

6. Be able to speak, read, write and understand the English language,

7. Participants will be required to nominate a current treating physician and will not be eligible to enter the study until one is identified.

8. Have the capacity to consent to the study and comply with study procedures,</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Participants with a known or suspected active systemic medical disorder, 

2. Individuals who are pregnant or lactating (participants will be requested to conduct a urine pregnancy test if sexually active and of child-bearing age), 

3. Participants currently enrolled in any other intervention study will be excluded,

4. Individuals who are intolerant, allergic to or have had an anaphylactic reaction to any components of the preparation,

5. Inability to comply with either the requirements of informed consent or the treatment protocol. 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>An independent researcher utilising a block design will develop the computer-generated randomisation plan. Trial clinicians will allocate packs sequentially, and bottles are identical so as to conceal treatment allocation and blinding. To facilitate the double-blinding process, the trial medications will be dispensed by an independent pharmacist in identical numbers and capsule forms in sealed containers. </concealment>
    <sequence>Permutated block randomisation utilising a block design on a computer-generated randomisation. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>All analyses will be conducted in accordance with the International Conference on Harmonization E9 statistical principles, and are based on all randomised participants with at least one post-baseline observation (intention to treat population). Reporting of research findings will be done in accordance to CONSORT guidelines. The statistician responsible for the analysis of outcome data will be blind to group allocation. The primary efficacy analysis will assess average treatment group differences for the primary outcome measure MADRS total score over the entire study period and will use a likelihood based mixed-effects model, repeated measures approach (MMRM). The MMRM model includes the fixed, categorical effects of treatment, investigator, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction, as well as the continuous, fixed covariates of baseline score and baseline score-by-visit interaction. The MMRM includes all available data at each time point and is the preferred method of analyzing clinical trial data in psychiatry as compared to more traditional repeated measures analysis of variance (ANOVA) and analysis of covariance models (ANCOVA). Planned comparisons will be done with the MMRM models to determine between group differences in change of symptoms measures from baseline to week 24. Results from the analysis of dichotomous data will be presented as proportions, with 95% confidence interval, and Fishers exact p-value where appropriate. Non-parametric statistics will be used when assumptions for parametric methods are violated. Effect sizes will be calculated using Cohens guidelines. All tests of treatment effects will be conducted using a two-sided alpha level of 0.05 and 95% confidence intervals. Change scores in symptoms and in biological markers will be derived. Pearson Product Moment Correlations will be used to examine the relationships between the change scores for symptoms and the change scores for biological markers in the two groups. Using Fishers z transformation, we will test whether the correlations obtained for each group are statistically different in terms of strength.

We are aiming for a target sample size of 150 participants. For a two tailed analysis with alpha=0.05, Z alpha = 1.96 and with ß=0.2, Zß = 0.8, N=120, the study should be powered at 80% to detect a true difference in MADRS scale score between the mangosteen pericarp and placebo groups if the effect size is Cohens d=0.362 or greater.  This is a conservative estimate, based on the results of the pilot data.  However, in our previous trial of N-acetylcysteine specifically investigating bipolar depression, effect sizes for depressive symptoms (BDRS, MADRS), clinical global impression of depressive severity (CGI BP-depression), as well as all functional measures have shown effects similar to or above the effect size the sample has been calculated for. Based on our previous trials we typically have an attrition rate of 20%. Therefore, although power calculations indicated 120 participants will be sufficient to detect between group differences, we plan to recruit 150 participants to account for attrition.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>6/06/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/01/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Melbourne Clinic - Richmond</hospital>
    <hospital>Albert Road Clinic - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3121 - Richmond</postcode>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Barwon Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Research Ethics, Governance and Integrity (REGI) Unit
PO BOX 281 
Geelong Victoria 3220</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Deakin University, IMPACT SRC Seed Funding Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>IMPACT SRC 
PO BOX 281 
Geelong Victoria 3220</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)
16 Marcus Clarke St, 
City West, 
Canberra, 
ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of Melbourne</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>The University of Melbourne
Victoria 3010</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Aims
The primary aim of this study is to investigate the efficacy of adjunctive mangosteen pericarp 1000mg/day for the treatment of bipolar depression using a 24 Week randomised, placebo controlled trial. The primary outcome measure will be the change in severity of mood symptoms, measured using the Montgomery Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS). Secondary outcomes include global psychopathology, substance use, functioning, quality of life, and safety and tolerability data. A follow-up interview will be conducted 4 weeks posttreatment to determine any outcomes following cessation of the trial agent. 

Method
We plan to recruit a total of 150 participants aged 18+years with moderate to severe bipolar depression (having a DSM5 diagnosis of bipolar I or II, cyclothymic disorder or bipolar disorder not elsewhere classified (NEC), determined using the Structured Clinical Interview for DSM Disorders 5 (SCID5) and meeting criteria of a Montgomery Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS) score of greater than or equal to 20. 

Participants will attend a screening visit to ascertain suitability and once randomized they will receive a months supply of either 1000mg/day of mangosteen or matched placebo to be taken in addition to their treatment as usual. Participants take two capsules per day.

Participants will visit the study site at weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 20 24 and 28 (4 weeks posttreatment discontinuation) where a battery of validated outcome measures will be administered by trained research staff. Participants will be asked to discuss their symptoms, side effects and any issues the participant would like to raise regarding the trial. Participants will be notified of which arm of the study they took part in and a summary of results at the completion of the study.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Barwon Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Ethics, Governance and Integrity (REGI) Unit
PO BOX 281 
Geelong Victoria 3220</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/11/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/08/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Melbourne Clinic Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>130 Church St 
RICHMOND, VIC 3121</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/08/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>31/07/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Deakin University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Burwood Campus
Postal: 221 Burwood Highway
Burwood Victoria 3125 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/12/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/12/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Olivia Dean</name>
      <address>IMPACT SRC
P.O. Box 281
Geelong, Victoria
3220</address>
      <phone>+61 3 4215 3300</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 4215 3491</fax>
      <email>oliviad@barwonhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Olivia Dean</name>
      <address>IMPACT SRC
P.O. Box 281
Geelong, Victoria
3220</address>
      <phone>+61 3 4215 3300</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 4215 3491</fax>
      <email>oliviad@barwonhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Olivia Dean</name>
      <address>IMPACT SRC
P.O. Box 281
Geelong, Victoria
3220</address>
      <phone>+61 3 4215 3300</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 4215 3491</fax>
      <email>oliviad@barwonhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Melanie Ashton</name>
      <address>Professorial Unit, The Melbourne Clinic
130 Church St 
RICHMOND 3121</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9487 4658</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9421 0704</fax>
      <email>melanie.ashton@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>