<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347660">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/11/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/11/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611001202954</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A comparison of arthroscopic synovial biopsy based targeted biologic therapy versus conventional therapy in rheumatoid arthritis (RA)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A comparison of arthroscopic synovial biopsy based targeted biologic therapy versus conventional therapy on the time to achieve remission in adults with rheumatoid arthritis (RA)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1125-5934</utrn>
    <trialacronym>ARBITRATE</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Rheumatoid Arthritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Rheumatoid arthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This trial will randomize patients to either of 2 arms; both arms will have an arthroscopic synovial biopsy at the onset and at 6 months. The arthroscopic synovial biopsy is expected to take around 30 minutes, and will be done with a small bore arthroscopy; the site will of arthroscopy will be a clinically involved joint and the procedure will be done in the operating theatre under an anaesthetic agent (type of anaesthesia as per the anaesthesiologist's preference). 

The first arm will be the study group (will commence immediately post synovial biopsy). Participants in this group will receive a biologic disease modifying anti rheumatic drug (bDMARD), either abatacept (T cell co stimulation inhibitor, abatacept administered subcutaneously- 125 mg weekly after a single intravenous dose of ~10 mg/kg ) or a tumor necrosis factor (TNF) inhibitor (adalimumab, subcutaneously 40 mg every other week), depending on the immunohistochemistry of their synovium. The bDMARD will be given for 6 months.

The other arm will be the comparator arm.</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator arm will receive standard combination conventional DMARD therapy (methotrexate, sulfasalazine, hydroxychloroquine with further sequential addition, if indicated, of gold, azathioprine, cyclosporine). Doses (oral): Methotrexate 10 mg/week, Sulfasalazine 500 mg twice a day (increasing to 1g bd over 2 weeks), hydroxychloroquine 200 mg bd; methotrexate dose will be increased if remission not achieved to a maximum dose of 25 mg weekly (and changed to subcutaneous formulation if not tolerated). If necessary, the other drugs will be added to the protocol, if the patient does not achieve remission on this combination.

If after 6 months of conventional therapy, participants have active disease and qualify for PBS (pharmaceutical benefits scheme, Australia) subsidized bDMARDs, they will go on to that bDMARD.

If not eligible at 6 months, patients will be continued on combination DMARD therapy long term.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to achieve remission between the two study arms using composite measures of disease activity: DAS28 (disease activity score using 28 joint count) and ACR (American College of Rheumatology) and EULAR (European League against Rheumatism) response criteria</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months, 12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Indicators of disease activity by clinical assessment, xray at baseline 0, 6, 12 months, MRI (wrist/ hand) at baseline and 6 months.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 3, 6, 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Synovial and serum biomarkers predictive of treatment response</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse events, related to drug toxicity; the events monitored will be generally common for all the oral DMARDs used (except hydroxychloroquine for which visual field testing will be done by the ophthalmology unit at baseline and yearly thereafter). Detailed information sheets will be given  to patients, and adverse events for DMARDs will be assessed on basis of symptoms (nausea and vomiting, gastrointestinal symptoms, rash) and abnormal blood counts, renal and liver function tests. In addition for methotrexate and leflunomide, baseline lung function tests will be done, if patients have a history of smoking; these tests may be repeated in case of new and persistent respiratory symptoms (like dry cough and shortness of breath). 
Symptoms with DMARDs will lead to withdrawing the offending agents, if not able to be controlled by simple means (for e.g. control of nausea secondary to methotrexate by giving folic acid).

For biologic DMARDs (bDMARDs), serious adverse events (recurrent / serious infections, cancers except non-melanoma skin cancer) will lead to withdrawal of the agent.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0. 6. 12 months, as well as monitoring during each follow up visit (except for hydroxychloroquine as mentioned in the secondary outcome box above).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Anti cyclic citrullinated peptide (CCP) positive active (&gt;/=2 joints) rheumatoid arthritis, duration of disease &lt;/=12 months</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Previously received DMARD/ bDMARD for RA; ANA positive &gt;320, hepatitis B/ C/ HIV positivity, concomitant treatment with experimental drug</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Simple randomisation by using a randomisation table created by computer software (computerised sequence generation by a statistician offsite). The person who determined if a subject was eligible for inclusion in the trial will be unaware, when this decision was made, to which group the subject would be allocated.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using a randomisation table created by computer software (computerised sequence generation).</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>17/04/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>29/07/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>104</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>5041</postcode>
    <postcode>5000</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Malcolm D Smith</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Rheumatology Unit
Repatriation General Hospital
Daws Road
Daw Park SA 5041</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Mihir D Wechalekar</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Rheumatology Unit
Repatriation General Hospital
Daws Road
Daw Park SA 5041</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Jennifer Walker</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Rheumatology Unit
Repatriation General Hospital
Daws Road
Daw Park SA 5041</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>A/ Prof Susanna Proudman</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Rheumatology Unit
Royal Adelaide Hospital
Level 4, Eleanor Harrald Building
Frome Road
Adelaide SA 5000</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Prof John Slavotinek</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Medical Imaging
Flinders Medical Centre
Bedford Park SA 5042</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>A/Prof Michael Ahern</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Rheumatology Unit
Repatriation General Hospital
Daws Road
Daw Park SA 5041</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Leslie G Cleland</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Rheumatology Unit
Level 4 Eleanor Harrald Building
Frome Road
Adelaide SA 5000</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to investigate if the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis (RA) based on the results of analysis of a biopsy of the involved joint lining is better than usual therapy (not based on the results of biopsy). 
The way standard care or bDMARD therapy will be chosen will be by the process called randomization (which will happen only once at the beginning of the study), which essentially is the equivalent of tossing a coin and deciding the treatment option on the basis of the result. This gives equal chance of going to either the bDMARD or standard care treatment arm. Once the patient has chosen to participate, they will receive an arthroscopic biopsy from the lining of an inflamed joint (called the synovium). The bDMARD will be chosen on the basis of the biopsy.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Flinders Medical Centre Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Southern Adelaide Clinical Human Research Ethics Committee
SA Local Health Network
Room 2A221 - Inside Human Resources
Flinders Medical Centre, Bedford Park SA 5042</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/09/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1/10/0199</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Ethics Committee 
Royal Adelaide Hospital
Level 3 Hanson Institute 
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace, Adelaide  SA  5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/10/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>100911b</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mihir D Wechalekar</name>
      <address>Rheumatology Unit
Repatriation General Hospital
Daw Park SA 5041</address>
      <phone>+61882751819</phone>
      <fax>+61883744276</fax>
      <email>mihir.wechalekar@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mihir D Wechalekar</name>
      <address>Rheumatology Unit
Repatriation General Hospital
Daw Park SA 5041</address>
      <phone>+61882751819</phone>
      <fax>+61883744276</fax>
      <email>mihir.wechalekar@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mihir D Wechalekar</name>
      <address>Rheumatology Unit
Repatriation General Hospital
Daw Park SA 5041</address>
      <phone>+61882751819</phone>
      <fax>+61883744276</fax>
      <email>mihir.wechalekar@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Malcolm D Smith</name>
      <address>Rheumatology Unit
Repatriation General Hospital
Daws Road
Daw Park SA 5041</address>
      <phone>+61882751819</phone>
      <fax>+6183744276</fax>
      <email>malcolm.smith@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>