<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370377">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/03/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/05/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000590460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Two methods of treatment of men with lumbar discopathy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Kaltenborn-Evjenth Manual Therapy in combination with Cryotherapy (KEOMT-C) versus Kaltenborn-Evjenth Manual Therapy in combination with Kinesiotaping (KEOMT-K) for treatment of men with lumbar discopathy: a randomised trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1181-1715</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>low back pain  </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>1. KEOMT - by all participants [40 males, 10 treatments, 2 per week, for 5 weeks, duration - will last 45 min. KEOMT will  include: lumbar segmental traction - supine position, lumbar segmental mobilization (flexion, extension, gliding therapy grade III), and soft tissue mobilization]. The physiotherapist will  deliver the intervention. 
Local cryotherapy -  KEOMT-C [20 males, 10 treatments, 2 per week, for 5 weeks at the end of each session of manual therapy, duration - 3 minutes, application -  paraspinal muscles on both sides of the lumbar spine up to the place of radiation pain. Local cryotherapy will be performed using KRIOPOL R30 (Kriomedpol, Poland). A stream of cold nitrogen vapor at temperature -130 degrees celsius will be applied to the paraspinal muscles on both sides of the lumbar spine up to the place of radiation pain. The distance among the apparatus nozzle and patients body surface - 10 centimeters.  The physiotherapist will  deliver the intervention]. 
 Kinesiotaping - KEOMT-K [20 males, 10 treatments, 2 per week, for 5 weeks at the end of each session (after manual therapy), application - the place of pain. The group will receive taping with 2 strips (15 cm  length x 5 cm  width; Kinesio Registered Trademark Tex Gold). Duration - 20 minutes. The physiotherapist will  deliver the intervention]. 
2. The location - Physiotherapy department.  Once a week for 5 weeks - sessions will be administered.  
 3. Post isometric relaxation (PIR) - a part of KEOMT - both groups. PIR - quadratus lumborum and erector spinae muscles. PIR rules: 1. Bring the muscle to its maximum length without stretching, taking up the slack. There should be only minimal or no pain. 2. The patient is asked to resist with only minimal force (isometrically) and to breathe in for 10 seconds.  3. The patient is then told to ,,let go" (relax) and exhale slowly. It is important for the physiotherapist to wait and feel the relaxation. The physiotherapis could wait 10 to 20 seconds or longer as long as relaxation is taking place. Due to pure relaxation there should be an increase in the range of motion. 4. If the patient has difficulty relaxing, hold the isometric phase for 30 seconds before having the patient ,,let go." 5. Usually three to five times is all that is necessary to obtain spontaneous stretch each session.  6. Along with the breathing, having the patient look up (eyes only). This helps facilitate the inspiration, which facilitates the muscle. Have the patient look down during expiration to aid in relaxation.  
 The independent resercher will assess the scores of treatment. </interventions>
    <comparator>KEOMT-K - control group.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>low back pain using a 10 cm Visual Analogue Scale (VAS),and Laitinen scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, post-intervention (immediately)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>quality of life (QOL) using short form-36 questionnaire (SF-36)</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, post-intervention (immediately)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>minimum age of 30 years, men diagnosed with Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) scan on the lumbar disc disease, pain associated with disc disease (failure of the intervertebral disc and herniated of disc), pain radiating to the extremities associated with compression and irritation of the nerve roots (inflammation of the nerve roots)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>30</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>osteoporosis, untreated hypertension, heart failure, coronary artery disease, advanced atherosclerosis, chilblains, hypothyroidism, blood disorders, cancer, hypersensitivity to cold, skin changes, depression and other mental illness, inflammation (ankylosing spondylitis, rheumatoid arthritis), spine injuries (subluxation in intervertebral joints, spondylosis, spinal compression fractures, vertebral transverse process fractures), congenital and acquired disorders of statics of the spine (scoliosis, spondylolisthesis, sacralization of L5, lumblization of S1, spina bifida)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The allocation sequence will be concealed from the researchers enrolling and assessing participants in sequentially numbered opaque, sealed and stapled envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>Individuals who consent to take part in the study and fulfill all inclusion and exclusion criteria will be assigned on 1:1 ratio using a simple random number table into two treatment groups: a KEOMT-C group and a KEOMT-K one.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>25/04/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>7/05/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>14/05/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>60</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>20/06/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Silesia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Holycross College</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>51, Mielczarskiego Str.
25-709 Kielce</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Poland</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Holycross College</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>51, Mielczarskiego Str.
25-709 Kielce</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Poland</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Lumbar discopathy is one of the main reasons for disability of the people in high, middle and low-income countries. Numerous modalities of therapeutic interventions are available for treatment of lumbar discopathy: manipulation, physical therapy, drugs, behavior therapy, and neural blockade. In cases resistant to conservative treatment, surgical treatment is used. Despite numerous studies, there are controversial opinions on the treatment of lumbar discopathy. Therefore, the objective of this study is to compare the efficiency of KEOMT-C versus KEOMT-K for the treatment of lumbar disc herniation. In present study we have taken hypothesis that  KEOMT-C and KEOMT-K reduce the pain, improve the quality of life (QOL) as well as  one of them more effectively treats  lumbar discopathy. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Holycross College Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>51, Mielczarskiego Str.
25-709 Kielce</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/03/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>04/172016KB</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/03/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Poland</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Wojciech Kobza</name>
      <address>Bielski College named after Tyszkiewicz
12, Nabrzezna Str.
43-300 Bielsko-Biala</address>
      <phone>+48 695 951 456</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>centrumkosmetyki@gazeta.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Pawel Lizis</name>
      <address>Holycross College
51, Mielczarskiego Str.
25-709 Kielce</address>
      <phone>+48663793834</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pawel_lizis@poczta.onet.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Pawel Lizis</name>
      <address>Holycross College
51, Mielczarskiego Str.
25-709 Kielce</address>
      <phone>+48663793834</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pawel_lizis@poczta.onet.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Pawel Lizis</name>
      <address>Holycross College
51, Mielczarskiego Str.
25-709 Kielce</address>
      <phone>+48663793834</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pawel_lizis@poczta.onet.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>