<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370535">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/04/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/05/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000666426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Theta Burst Stimulation (TBS) in Treatment Resistant Obsessive Compulsive Disorder.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Theta Burst Stimulation (TBS) in Treatment Resistant Obsessive Compulsive Disorder.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1199-6860 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>TBS for OCD</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obsessive Compulsive Disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>It is a parallel group clinical trial where participants will receive bilateral TBS to either the orbital frontal cortex (OFC) or the supplementary motor area (SMA). Each treatment course will involve TBS treatment twice daily for 2 weeks (10 treatment days). Each treatment session will involve the application of 2 TBS trains, 15 minutes apart (a total of 4 trains per day and 40 trains per treatment course). Patients who do not respond to treatment will be crossed over and provided the alternate treatment one month after their initial treatment had ended. 

During treatment patients will be reclined in a comfortable chair and will be alert and awake. The sensation associated with treatment is usually well tolerated with most people describing it as a tapping sensation. TBS will be applied in a single 40 - second train per application. Three pulses per burst will be applied at 50 Hz and the bursts repeated at 5 Hz. The treatment intensity for both rTMS and TBS will be 120% of resting motor threshold which is measured by administering single pulse TMS to the muscle controlling area of the brain.</interventions>
    <comparator>Two treatment arms (TBS to SMA and TBS to OFC) are both considered intervention arms, with neither to be allocated as the control.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Yale-Brown Obsessive-Compulsive Scale (YBOCS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>The YBOCS will be administered at baseline, at week 2 post start of treatment  and at 4 - 6 weeks post treatment completion.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Beck Depression Inventory (BDI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>The BDI  will be administered at baseline, at week 2 post start of treatment  and at 4 - 6 weeks post treatment completion.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Beck Anxiety Inventory (BAI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>The BAI will be administered at baseline, at week 2 post start of treatment  and at 4 - 6 weeks post treatment completion.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Clinical Global Impression (CGI) scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The CGI  will be administered at baseline, at week 2 post start of treatment  and at 4 - 6 weeks post treatment completion.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Have DSM-IV diagnosis of OCD
- Are treatment resistant
- Have had no changes in medications in 6 weeks prior to screening</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria> - An unstable medical condition, neurological disorder, history of seizure disorder or currently pregnant or lactating
-A current diagnosis of substance abuse or dependence, a personality disorder or other psychiatric disorder, except depression or another anxiety disorder
- Any contraindication to TMS </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The treatment group is determined by a computer program that generates random numbers. The researcher with access to this program and who is not involved in patient selection securely provides the treatment group to a member of the treatment team by email or in a sealed envelope. The staff member in receipt of the treatment group is not involved in assessing a patient's eligibility at the baseline assessment.
</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation to one of two treatment conditions will occur via the generation of a single computer number sequence (no stratification).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The primary analysis will be conducted on YBOCS scores from baseline to week 2. Student t tests and Chi-squared tests will be used to examine for differences between demographic and clinical characteristics between the groups for continuous and categorical variables following testing for normality of the data. Mixed model analysis of the primary and secondary outcome variables will be computed to look for differences in group scores across the study time points with treatment type as the between-group and time as the within-subject factor. Concurrent medication use will be included in these analyses as a covariate. We will conduct an exploratory analysis to investigate whether the type of OCD symptoms is related to response to treatment at either site. 

We aim to recruit 30 patients into each group (total n=60) allowing for a non-completion rate of 5 subjects per group. Twenty five patients per group will provide an 90% chance of detecting a difference of 5.5 points on the YaleBrown ObsessiveCompulsive Scale (YBOCS) scale with treatment within each treatment group assuming a standard deviation of 8.0 (2-tailed analysis, p&lt;0.05). If there are differences in efficacy between the groups, this will provide an 80% chance of detecting a difference of 7 points on the YaleBrown ObsessiveCompulsive Scale (YBOCS) scale between the groups (also assuming a standard deviation of 8.0 (2-tailed analysis, p&lt;0.05)). Given a baseline YBOCS level of around 35  this will mean a 20% difference between the groups in final YBOCS score, which is likely to be of clinical significance. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/08/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/09/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>17/06/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>2</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Epworth Rehabilitation Camberwell - Camberwell</hospital>
    <postcode>3124 - Camberwell</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Epworth HealthCare</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Epworth Camberwell
888 Toorak Road
Camberwell 
VICTORIA 3124</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Epworth HealthCare</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Epworth Camberwell
888 Toorak Road
Camberwell 
VICTORIA 3124</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Monash Alfred Psychiatry Research Centre (MAPrc)</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Level 4 - 607 St Kilda Road
Melbourne VIC 3004</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is assessing the efficacy of Theta Burst Stimulation (TBS), a form of Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (TMS), in treating Obsessive Compulsive Disorder (OCD). It is a randomised control trial where participants will receive bilateral TBS to one of two different brain cortical regions. Each treatment course will involve TBS twice daily for 2 weeks (10 treatment days). Each treatment session will involve the application of 2 TBS trains, 15 minutes apart (a total of 4 trains per day and 40 trains per treatment course). Patients who do not respond to treatment will be crossed over and provided the alternate treatment. 

During treatment patients will be reclined in a comfortable chair and will be alert and awake. The sensation associated with treatment is usually well tolerated with most people describing it as a tapping sensation. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Melbourne Clinic Research Ethics Comittee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>130 Church Street
Richmond VIC 3121</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/08/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>#266</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Epworth HealthCare Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Epworth HealthCare
89 Bridge Road
Richmond VIC 3121</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>EH2017-182</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>13/02/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Paul Fitzgerald</name>
      <address>Epworth Camberwell
888 Toorak Road 
Camberwell 
VICTORIA 3124</address>
      <phone>+613 9805 4287</phone>
      <fax>+613 9805 4388</fax>
      <email>paul.fitzgerald@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sally Herring</name>
      <address>Epworth Camberwell
888 Toorak Road 
Camberwell 
VICTORIA 3124</address>
      <phone>+613 9805 4126</phone>
      <fax>+613 9805 4388</fax>
      <email>sally.herring@epworth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Paul Fitzgerald</name>
      <address>Epworth Camberwell
888 Toorak Road 
Camberwell 
VICTORIA 3124</address>
      <phone>+613 9805 4287</phone>
      <fax>+613 9805 4388</fax>
      <email>paul.fitzgerald@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sally Herring</name>
      <address>Epworth Camberwell
888 Toorak Road 
Camberwell 
VICTORIA 3124</address>
      <phone>+613 9805 4126</phone>
      <fax>+613 9805 4388</fax>
      <email>sally.herring@epworth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>