<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366312">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/05/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/05/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000534684</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Low Back Pain and Stretching Exercise </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Effect of Stretching Hamstring, Gastrocnemius, Iliopsoas and Back Muscles on Pain and Functional Activities in Patients with Chronic Low Back Pain: A Randomized Clinical Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic low back pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All subjects attended the physical therapy sessions three times per week for six weeks. Experimental group performed manual passive stretching exercises for hamstring, gastrocnemus, hamstring and back muscles. The patient sits on long sitting position with knees fully extended and the feet together in dorsiflextion and against the wall to stretch the gastrocnemius muscle. We asked the patient to bend forward from the hips to reach towards the feet with the head in flexion. The physical therapists came behind the patient and push him/her forward to stabilize the patients position and knees and hold the position for 30 seconds, then relax for 30 seconds, with three repetitions per set, three sets per visit and three visits per week for a period of six weeks.
Subjects also performed stretching exercise for iliopsoas muscle. The patient lies on a crock lying position with both lower limbs hanging out of the end of the table holding one knee to the chest, the therapist is in front of both lower limbs and one hand holds the flexed knee while the other hand stretches the other leg by pushing down and hold the position for 30 seconds, then relax for 30 seconds with three repetitions per set, three sets per visit and three visits per week for a period of six weeks.
Strengthening exercises were performed in both groups. Performing sitting up from a supine position with hips and knees flexed used for abdominal muscles strengthening exercises. Head and shoulders are lifted with a gradual curl to touch the knees with the hands. The abdominal muscle becomes more efficient. Thus isotonic abdominal exercise should begin with the hips and knees flexed. A strengthening exercise program for abdominal muscles performed ten repetitions, ten seconds hold and ten to 15 seconds relax for ten sets per visit and three visits per week for a period of six weeks. 
Stretching and strengthening exercises were undertaken during 3 x 1 hour sessions per week for a period of 6 weeks. Participants in both groups received health education for low back pain by researchers including correct posture and appropriate behavior changes to enhance functional outcomes</interventions>
    <comparator>In the control group, patients performed manual passive stretching exercises for hamstring and back muscles. The patient sits on long sitting position with knees fully extended and the feet together free or on planter flexion. We asked the patient to bend forward from the hips to reach towards the feet with the head in flexion. The physical therapists came behind the patient and push him/her forward to stabilize the patients position and knees and hold the position for 30 seconds, then relax for 30 seconds, with three repetitions per set, three sets per visit and three visits per week for a period of six weeks. 
Subjects also performed stretching exercise for iliopsoas muscle. The patient lies on a crock lying position with both lower limbs hanging out of the end of the table holding one knee to the chest, the therapist is in front of both lower limbs and one hand holds the flexed knee while the other hand stretches the other leg by pushing down and hold the position for 30 seconds, then relax for 30 seconds with three repetitions per set, three sets per visit and three visits per week for a period of six weeks.
Strengthening exercises were performed in both groups. Performing sitting up from a supine position with hips and knees flexed used for abdominal muscles strengthening exercises. Head and shoulders are lifted with a gradual curl to touch the knees with the hands. The abdominal muscle becomes more efficient. Thus isotonic abdominal exercise should begin with the hips and knees flexed. A strengthening exercise program for abdominal muscles performed ten repetitions, ten seconds, hold and ten to 15 seconds, relax for ten sets per visit and three visits per week for a period of six weeks. 
Stretching and strengthening exercises were undertaken during 3 x 1 hour sessions per week for a period of 6 weeks. Participants in both groups received health education for low back pain by researchers including correct posture and appropriate behavior changes to enhance functional outcomes</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome measurement was pain on visual analogue scale (VAS). It ranges from zero (no pain) to ten (unbearable pain) grades, from 1 to 10 means graduation intensities of pain. The subjects were asked to indicate the level of lower back pain by placing a dash at the appropriate level on the 10 cm horizontal line. The subjects were provided with an Arabic version of VAS with no pain on the right side and worst pain on the left side.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcome measurements were taken at baseline and the end of week six after the study was begun. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary outcomes were Modified fingertip-to-floor test for measuring the range of motion of lumbar flexion. The distance between the tip of the middle finger and the floor is usually measured with a tape measure to measure changes in lumbar flexion of patients with LBP. Also, a stool with height 19 cm has been used for subjects to stand on in order to measure the ROM. The measurements are taken with the modified fingertip-to- floor method by having the patient forward bend while standing on a stool in an attempt to touch the floor with the fingertips and then measuring the distance between the tip of the middle finger and the top of the stool</outcome>
      <timepoint>The outcome measurements were taken at baseline and at the end of week six after the study was begun.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary outcome is Oswestry questionnaire disability for LBP, which is a Low back pain disability questionnaire. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcome measurements were taken at the baseline and the end of week six after the study was begun.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary outcome measurement was Lateral view of loading x-ray, which is used to detect any change in the lordotic curve by measuring lumbo-sacral (LS) angle.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The outcome measurements were taken at the baseline and the end of week six after the study begun.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The inclusion criteria were patients diagnosis of low back pain and complaint of pain for more than three months.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>25</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any pathological involvement such as disc herniation, tumor, cancer, spinal stenosis, vertebral fracture or neurological deficits.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The patients were randomly assigned into two groups by drawing of forty identical envelopes that are labeled A (control group) and B (experimental group)</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomization by creating randomization table using a computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/08/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>20/08/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>8/01/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <state>Cairo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Ashraf Ramadan Hafez</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>23 Kasr Al Ainy street, Cairo University Hospital, Cairo, Egypt.
Post code: 11562

</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Egypt</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Aqeel M Alenazi</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Physical Therapy and Rehabilitation Department, College of Applied Medical Sciences, Salman Bin Abdulaziz University, AlKharj, Saudi Arabia. PO BOX. 422 Alkharj 11942</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Saudi Arabia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Aqeel M Alenazi</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Physical Therapy and Rehabilitation Department, College of Applied Medical Sciences, Salman Bin Abdulaziz University, AlKharj, Saudi Arabia. PO BOX. 422 Alkharj 11942</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Saudi Arabia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study was to compare the clinical outcomes between two different exercise programs for the management of patients with chronic low back pain. We hypothesized that individuals treating by a program, which includes stretching exercises for back, hamstring and iliopsoas and gastrocnemius muscles followed by strengthening exercises for abdominal muscle and functional activities postural instructions, would achieve better outcomes compared with individuals receiving another program, which includes stretching exercises for back, hamstring and iliopsoas without gastrocnemius muscles stretching followed by strengthening exercises for abdominal muscle and activities of daily living postural instructions.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname> Ethical Review Board at Cairo University Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>23 Kasr Al Ainy street, Cairo University Hospital, Cairo, Egypt.
Post code: 11562
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/07/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>27024/1434</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/07/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Egypt</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Aqeel M Alenazi</name>
      <address>Physical Therapy and Rehabilitation Department, College of Applied Medical Sciences, Salman Bin Abdulaziz University, AlKharj City, KSA
P.O 422 Alkharj 11942</address>
      <phone>+966501677557</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>aqeeel_86@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ashraf R Hafez</name>
      <address>23 Kasr Al Ainy street, Cairo University Hospital, Cairo, Egypt.
Post code: 11562</address>
      <phone>+201116915026</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ashrafrh1989@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ashraf R Hafez</name>
      <address>23 Kasr Al Ainy street, Cairo University Hospital, Cairo, Egypt.
Post code: 11562</address>
      <phone>+201116915026</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ashrafrh1989@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Aqeel M Alenazi</name>
      <address>Physical Therapy and Rehabilitation Department, College of Applied Medical Sciences, Salman Bin Abdulaziz University, AlKharj City, KSA
P.O 422 Alkharj 11942</address>
      <phone>+966501677557</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>aqeeel_86@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>