<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364724">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/08/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/08/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000951752</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Phase I, Randomised, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled,Ascending
Single- and Repeat-Dose Study of the Safety,Tolerability and
Pharmacokinetics of Orally Administered PRN473.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase I, Randomised, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled,Ascending
Single- and Repeat-Dose Study of the Safety,Tolerability and
Pharmacokinetics of Orally Administered PRN473</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Healthy Volunteers</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Placebo-controlled, First-In-Human study assessing the safety and tolerability of PRN473. 
Approximately 64 participants in up to 6 cohorts will take part in Part A of the study. Participants in Part A of the study will receive a single dose of PRN473 (starting dose 50mg and increasing each cohort thereafter). Part A participants will receive a liquid formulation whilst fasting with the exception of 2 cross over cohorts; participants in Cohort 4a will receive the liquid formulation administered with and without food (with up to a 7 day washout between doses) and participants in Cohort 4b   will be administered a tablet equivalent with and without food (with up to a 7 day washout between doses). 
Approximately 50 participants in  up to 5 cohorts will take part in Part B of the study. Participants in Part B of the study will receive one dose of PRN473 (tablet or liquid formulation) per day for up to 14 days (doses to be assigned based on data from part A i.e. a dose that gives roughly 30% occupancy of the target). Tablet or liquid formulation will be chosen on the basis of emerging PK and PD data from Part A of the study. 
Study subjects are domiciled during the study and adherence will be monitored by study staff observations and notes, and tablet accountability or weighing the dosing syringes before and after dosing as applicable.</interventions>
    <comparator>The liquid formulation placebo will be prepared for each cohort at the study site by dissolving the formula amount of hydroxypropyl-beta-cyclodextrin, vitamin E TPGS (d-alpha tocopheryl polyethylene glycol 1000 succinate), citric acid and sucralose in Water for Irrigation.

The placebo tablet is presented as an oval, scored, white tablet of approximately 1 g total weight. The tablet contains the following compendial excipients; hydroxypropyl-beta-cyclodextrin, microcrystalline cellulose, vitamin E TPGS (d-alpha tocopheryl polyethylene glycol 1000 succinate), croscarmellose sodium, and magnesium stearate. The tablets are packaged in high-density polyethylene (HDPE) containers, induction sealed, capped and labelled. Each bottle contains 30 tablets. The tablets are stored at 28 degrees celsius. The tablets will be administered orally to the study subject as per the clinical protocol. The tablets should be swallowed without chewing, and followed by the consumption of approximately 240 mL of water.
</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and tolerability will be assessed through frequent collection of laboratory safety tests, vital signs and ECGs, and clinical monitoring of participants.</outcome>
      <timepoint>PartA: Up to 6 (+/-1) days after dosing
Part B: Up to 21 (+/-2) days after dosing
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.adult males and/or females, 18 to 55 years of age (inclusive) at the time of screening
2. Body mass index (BMI) &gt;18.0 and &lt; 30.5 (kg/m2) (inclusive) 
3. Able to participate and comply with all study procedures and restrictions, and willing to provide written informed consent 
4. If male, agrees to be sexually abstinent or to use a condom or other adequate method of contraception 
5. Female participants must be surgically sterile or post-menopausal 
6. Negative urine drug/alcohol breath testing at screening and check-in (Day -1). </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Pregnant or lactating females, and male partners of women who are pregnant or lactating
2. Females of child-bearing potential
3. Positive testing for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg), or hepatitis C antibodies (HCV)
4. Any active acute or chronic disease judged to be clinically significant by the Investigator
5. Use of more than 1-2 tobacco/nicotine-containing products per month within 6 months prior to begining the study 
6. History or presence of alcoholism or drug abuse within the 2 years prior to begining the study 
7. History of any significant (as determined by the Invest
igator) drug-related allergic reactions 
8. Use of any over-the-counter (OTC) medication 
9. Participation in another clinical trial of a drug or device within 60 days. 
10. Surgery within the past three months 
11. Hypertension 
12. Hypersensitivity to lactose 
13. Regular alcohol consumption &gt;14 units per week (1 unit = 1/2 pint beer, 25 mL of 40% spirit or a 125 mL glass of wine) 
14. History or presence of any clinically significant cardiovascular, pulmonary, hepatic, renal, hematological, gastrointestinal, endocrine, immunologic, dermatologic, neurological, or psychiatric disease
15. Any acute illness within 30 days prior to Day 1 of the study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be recruited from the study site's internal database. Eligible subjects will be allocated to a treatment by contacting the holder of the study allocation schedule.  The treatmetn allocation will be concealed from the particpant and the investigator. </concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation software.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/09/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>7/04/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>3/12/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>114</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Clinical Network Services</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 4, 88 Jephson Street, Toowong, Queensland, Australia 4066</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Principia Biopharma Australia Pty Ltd.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 29, 525 Collins Street, Melbourne, VIC, 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Placebo-controlled, First-In-Human study assessing the safety and tolerability of PRN473 in healthy volunteers. Partipants in Part  A of the study will recive a single dose of PRN473. Partipants in Part  B of the study will recieve one dose of PRN473 per day for up to 14 days.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Belberry HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>229 Greenhill Road
Dulwich,
South Australia 5065

</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/08/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2013-07-385</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/08/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Janakan Krishnarajah</name>
      <address>Linear Clinical Research
Level 1, B Block, QEII Medical
Centre, Hospital Ave,
Nedlands WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61863825100</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>JKrishnarajah@linear.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Dougal Thring</name>
      <address>Linear Clinical Research
Level 1, B Block, QEII Medical
Centre, Hospital Ave,
Nedlands WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61863825100</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Dthring@linear.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Janakan Krishnarajah</name>
      <address>Linear Clinical Research
Level 1, B Block, QEII Medical
Centre, Hospital Ave,
Nedlands WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61863825100</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>JKrishnarajah@linear.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Claudia Gregorio-King</name>
      <address>Clinical Network Services
Level 4, 88 Jephson St, Toowong, Queensland 4066</address>
      <phone>+61737196000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Claudia.Gregorio-King@clinical.net.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>