<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362781">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/07/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/07/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000791831</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Humira for active hand osteoarthritis (HUMOR Trial)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of Adalimumab (Humira) on hand pain in erosive hand osteoarthritis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>HUMOR</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hand Osteoarthritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Adalimumab 40 mg subcutaneous injection eow (every other week) for 3 months, crossover with 60 day washout.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo (saline injection) eow (every other week) for 3 months</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adalimumab 40 mg eow (every other week) will be superior to placebo for pain (measured by 100mm visual analogue scale (VAS)) at 3 months in osteoarthritis of the hand with prevalent bone marrow lesions and/or synovitis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain VAS at one month and two months</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month, 2 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>AUSCAN Hand Osteoarthritis Index VA3.1 total score at one, two and three months</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month, 2 months, 3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bone Marrow Lesion (BML) size at 3 months assessed by MRI</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Synovitis at 3 months assessed by MRI</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety assessed by monitoring and reporting any adverse events.  Adverse events include any changes in the health of a participant and will be self-reported.
Participants will be asked to report any adverse events at each monthly clinic visit. Participants will also be able to report events between clinic visits by telephoning the coordinator.  Adverse events may include, for example, a reaction at the injection site, attendance at a hospital emergency department, hospitalisation.  All adverse events will be reported to the Prinicpal Investigator at each site who will determine the relationship (or otherwise) to Adalimumab.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 1 month, 2 months, 3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Hand OA based on physician diagnosis and ACR criteria.
Hand pain &gt;50 on 100mm VAS.
Morning stiffness &gt;30 minutes.
Subject is judged to be in good general health as determined by the Prinicpal Investigator based upon results of medical history, physical examination, laboratory profile and chest X-ray (CXR).
Subject has negative QuantiFERON-TB Gold test and negative CXR (PA and lateral view).
Subjects must be able and willing to provide written informed consent and to comply with the requirements of the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>A subject will not be eligable for study participation if he/she meets any of the following criteria:
Subject has been treated with any investigational drug of a chemical or biologic nature with a minimum of 30 days or 5 half-lives (whichever is longer) of the drug prior to baseline visit.
Any infection(s) requiring treatment with intravenous (IV) anti-infectives within 30 days prior to baseline visit or oral anti-infectives within 14 days prior to baseline visit.
Known hypersensitivity to adalimumab or its excipients.
History of demyelinating disease (including myelitis) or neurologic symptoms suggestive of demyelinating disease.
History of invasive infection (e.g., listeriosis and histoplasmosis), human immunodeficiency syndrome (HIV), or chronic or active Hepatitis C. 
Subjects with an active systemic viral infection or any active viral infection that based on the investigator's clinical assessment make the subject an unsuitable candidate for the study. 
Hepatitis B:  HBs Ag positive (+) or detected sensitivity on the HBV-DNA PCR qualitative test for HBc Ab/HBs ab positive subjects.
Chronic recurring infections or active TB.
History of moderate to severe congestive heart failure (NYHA class III or IV), recent cerebrovascular accident and any other condition which, in the opinion of the investigator, would put the subject at risk by participation in the protocol. 
Evidence of dysplasia or history of malignancy (including lymphoma and leukemia) other than a successfully treated non-metastatic cutaneous squamous cell or basal cell carcinoma or localized carcinoma in situ of the cervix.
Subject received any live vaccine within 3 months prior to study drug administration.
Subject has a history of clinically significant hematologic (e.g., severe anaemia, leukopenia, thrombocytopenia), renal or liver disease (e.g., fibrosis, cirrhosis, hepatitis).
History of clinically significant drug or alcohol abuse in the last 12 months.
Clinically significant abnormal screening laboratory results as evaluated by the investigator.
Subject is considered by the investigator, for any reason, to be an unsuitable candidate for the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Enrolment of subject by allocation to next random number.  Random number generation to allocate drug or placebo performed by researcher not involved in this trial.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using a randomization table created by a computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/08/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>6/07/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>6/07/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>42</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Tasmania</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Menzies Research Institute Tasmania
University of Tasmania
Private Bag 23
Hobart
Tasmania 7001</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Abbott Australasia Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Locked Bag 5106
Botany
NSW 1455</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Paul Bird</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Optimus Research
95 Kareena Rd
MIRANDA
NSW 2228</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to determine the efficacy of Adalimumab for active hand osteoarthritis. Primary hypothesis is Adalimumab will be superior to placebo for pain at 3 months in osteoarthritis of the hand.  The design is a randomised, double blind, placebo controlled, crossover trial.  Subjects will be randomised to Adalimumab/placebo followed by a 60 day washout and then the converse Adalimumab/placebo.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee (Tasmania) Network</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Research Services
University of Tasmania
Private Bag 1
Hobart
Tasmania 7001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/05/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H12149</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/10/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Graeme Jones</name>
      <address>Menzies Institute for Medical Research
University of Tasmania
Private Bag 23 
HOBART  TAS 7001</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)3 6226 7705</phone>
      <fax>+61 (0)3 6226 7764</fax>
      <email>g.jones@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Graeme Jones</name>
      <address>Menzies Institute for Medical Research
University of Tasmania
Private Bag 23 
HOBART  TAS 7001</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)3 6226 7705</phone>
      <fax>+61 (0)3 6226 7764</fax>
      <email>g.jones@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Laura Laslett</name>
      <address>Menzies Institute for Medical Research
University of Tasmania
Private Bag 23 
HOBART  TAS 7001</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)3 6226 7736</phone>
      <fax>+61 (0)3 6226 7704</fax>
      <email>Laura.Laslett@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Graeme Jones</name>
      <address>Menzies Institute for Medical Research
University of Tasmania
Private Bag 23 
HOBART  TAS 7001</address>
      <phone>+61 3 6226 7705</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Graeme.Jones@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>