<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368723">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/06/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/07/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000697583</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Developing an educational intervention for high risk women with Gestational Diabetes Mellitus (Eat for your baby)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Use of a web-based educational intervention to improve healthy diet and lifestyle habits in high risk women with Gestational Diabetes Mellitus, in comparison to standard clinic-based education.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Gestational Diabetes Mellitus in pregnant women</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fetal medicine and complications of pregnancy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>We have developed an education program (a web-based program) with pictures of food and simple instructions that can be accessed at an information kiosk (touch screen computer) at the hospital diabetes clinic, home computer, and mobile phone. This educational program will be used by women with gestational diabetes and by health professional involved in their care.  

Pregnant women who agree to take part will be assigned to a group: Intervention group and control group.

Group 1 (Intervention group) will be asked to use an online touch screen/ computer program which is located at diabetes clinic, or mobile phone or computer at their own homes. Women who decide to use the program at their homes, they will be given the website link and password to access to the program. The program will introduce women to information on healthy diet and healthy lifestyle (with pictures and simple instructions) for pregnant women with GDM.  The program will take 15-30 minutes to complete. Women will be asked to complete a questionnaire after using the program. The clinic staff, dieticians, diabetes nurses will supervise women when they are using the touch screen computer at the clinic. 

The overall duration of the web-based education program can be completed at one sitting and they can re-enter the website as often as they wish. There are 4 modules/lessons in the web-based program which include:

- Lesson 1: A step by step for testing blood glucose level
- Lesson 2: Outlines healthy food choices
- Lesson 3: Health habits - healthy life
- Lesson 4: Emotions, family and food

All lessons only use pictures and simple instruction that are very easy for women to understand. The program also includes some extra information for women. Such as, "what is gestational diabetes (GDM)?", "Healthy eating and exercise in GDM", "What to do if you're still hungry?", and "a guide to healthy shopping". This information also use images and simple instruction.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Group 2 (Comparator/Control group) will receive education at the clinic and will be required to complete a questionnaire at the end of the class.

The group education class provides for pregnant women with GDM (control group) at the clinic, it is a small class where it involves 5-8 pregnant women with GDM. The education on healthy diet, healthy exercise, healthy lifestyle and how to monitor blood sugar level will be presented to these women by dieticians and diabetes educators. The education class is one-off 2 hours class. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Women's weight following delivery as assessed using calibrated digital scales.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint at 8 weeks post delivery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Newborn baby weight in normal range (&gt;2500g - &lt;4500g) - dichotomous outcome Yes/No assessed using calibrated digital scales.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint at birth, Baby weights at birth</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Normal Oral Glucose Tolerance Test (OGTT) - dichotomous outcome Yes/No. 
-  Normal fasting is &lt; 5.1 mmol/L; 
- 1-hour glucose following 75g oral glucose load is &lt;10.0 mmol/L ; 
- 2-hour glucose following 75g oral glucose load is &lt;8.5mmol/L. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint at 8 weeks after delivery  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Knowledge level on healthy diet and lifestyle habits following intervention, assessed by written test designed specifically for this study.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks after using an educational program </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants in both groups 1 and 2 are expected to have the same criteria. Pregnant women who are aged between 18-45 years old, diagnosed with GDM, singleton pregnancy, attended pregnancy diabetes clinic at Sunshine Hospital, will be asked to participate in the study.  

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnant women who had pre-existing diabetes (types 1 and 2),  are unable to write and understand English, women with a cognitive impairment, an intellectual disability or a mental illness, and women dependent on medical care (eg, anti-depressants, or any psychiatric medication)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/12/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>10/12/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Victoria University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Victoria University
College of Health and Biomedicine
PO Box 14428,
Melbourne 8001
Victoria
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Funding from Ian Potter Foundation
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Ian Potter Foundation 
Level 3, 111 Collins Street
Melbourne, VIC 3000
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Diabetes Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Diabetes Australia
GPO BOX 3156
CANBERRA  ACT  2601

Office Location: Level 1, 101 Northbourne Ave
TURNER  ACT  2612</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Western Health Sunshine Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>176 Furlong Road
St Albans
Victoria 3021</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Objectives: The approved project aimed to develop an effective educational program for use by Australian women with gestational diabetes mellitus (GDM) and by health professionals involved in their care. Educational materials from this project include an information booklet, a web-based program that can be accessed at an information kiosk (touch screen computer) at the hospital diabetes clinic, home PCs, and mobile technologies. Educational materials are initially available in English and Vietnamese languages. Programs contain culturally appropriate information such as typical food for the different ethnic groups, relevant in the area. 
Methods: Pregnant women aged 18-45 years with GDM who have a singleton pregnancy, are eligible to participate in this study. Women who agree to participate in the study will be given a participant information sheet and consent form. Participants will be recruited from the Pregnancy diabetes Clinic, at Sunshine Hospital and introduced to the GDM educational modules using the touch screen computer located in the clinic. Participants will also be given the URL to access to the program and they can learn the modules at home by using their home PCs, mobile phones, or tablets. At the end of the 4 weeks programs, participants will be asked to complete the questionnaire. The final result will be analysed by using statistic software SPSS v. 20. An appropriate statistical analysis will be used to find out the effectiveness of a web-based educational program on women's knowledge of GDM, including the influence of the program on weights of the women after delivery, baby weights and blood glucose level after delivery. The biostatistician will be consulted when the study is published.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Western Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Western Health Sunshine Hospital
176 Furlong Road
St Albans
Victoria 3021</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/10/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/11/WH/81</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/08/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Mary Carolan-Olah</name>
      <address>Victoria University
College of Health and Biomedicine
PO BOX 14428 
Melbourne 8001
Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9919 2325 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mary.carolan@vu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Padaphet Sayakhot</name>
      <address>Victoria University
College of health and Biomedicine
PO BOX 14428 
Melbourne 8001
Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 99192512</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>padaphet.sayakhot@vu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Padaphet Sayakhot</name>
      <address>Victoria University
College of Health and Biomedicine
PO BOX 14428 
Melbourne 8001
Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 99192512</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>padaphet.sayakhot@vu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Padaphet Sayakhot</name>
      <address>Victoria University
College of Health and Biomedicine
PO BOX 14428 
Melbourne 8001
Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 99192512</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>padaphet.sayakhot@vu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>