<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370032">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/01/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/03/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000312448</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of quinoa on blood lipids and circulating adiponectin in humans.  </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of quinoa on blood lipids, circulating adiponectin, blood markers and physical activity in overweight/obese humans. Dose response trial compared to control group</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1175-4070 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Hyperlipidaemia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants are randomly allocated into one of the four different treatment groups receiving either 0, 25, 50, or 100 grams of quinoa per day during 12 weeks intervention period. Participants are advised to consume the white quinoa seeds supplied at their convenience filling a quinoa calendar provided every day when quinoa is consumed, this calendar is returned in the following appointment.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control treatment receive 0 gr of quinoa.</comparator>
    <control>Dose comparison</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood Sample is taken into an SST tube (Serum Separating Tube) to analyse Circulating adiponectin</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point: Baseline which includes 1hr and 2hrs after quinoa breakfast consumption and 6 and 12 weeks follow the first appointment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood sample is taken into an SST tube (Serum Separating Tube) to analyse Lipid profile</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline which includes 1 hr and 2 hrs after consumption of quinoa breakfast, 6 and 12 weeks intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body composition measured using a DEXA scan</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 and 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical Activity measure an ActiGraph Activity Monitor</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants are checked against eligibility criteria before inclusion in the study. Inclusion criteria includes: BMI greater than 25, be able to communicate in English, age between 18 and 65 years old. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria includes BMI lower than 25, diagnosis diabetes or heart disease, pregnancy and also those taking medication for blood cholesterol management.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Recruited participants are checked against the inclusion and exclusion criteria prior the enrollment for the study. Participants are randomly allocated into one of the four treatment groups by computer generated random number conducted by holder of the allocation schedule (Not the trial coordinator). </concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation is done by block randomisation generating a list of random number in a computer program stratifying by gender. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Statistical analysis will be performed by applying appropriate statistical tests using SPSS Inc. software Version 21, p &lt;0.05 will be considered statistically significant.  Of note, this is a pilot/ study of 100 participants, comprising 25 in each of the four treatment groups. A drop out rate of 20% or less is expected, this will equate to a minimum expected completion of 20 participants per treatment group which is considered suitable for the exploratory study.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>2/02/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>15/09/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>31/05/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>75</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>19/08/2016</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>31/08/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3083 - Bundoora</postcode>
    <postcode>3086 - La Trobe University</postcode>
    <postcode>3088 - Greensborough</postcode>
    <postcode>3087 - Watsonia</postcode>
    <postcode>3089 - Diamond Creek</postcode>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>La Trobe University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Kingsbury Dr/Plenty Rd, Bundoora VIC 3086</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>La Trobe University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Kingsbury Dr/Plenty Rd, Bundoora VIC 3086</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Quinoa (Chenopodium quinoa) seed is catalogued as a pseudocereal due to the similarity with the cereal family but with a different nutrient composition. Quinoa is a crop related to beetroot and spinach, grown primarily for its edible seeds.   Cultivated in the Andean region between Bolivia and Peru, recent interest in this plant has been due to the nutritional value of the seeds in comparison to other cereals.  Comparative to other cereals, quinoa is high in protein and rich in antioxidants (Vega-Galvez et al., 2010; Gorinstein et al., 2007).  The quinoa seeds are highly nutritious and contain 60% starch and 15% protein.  In addition, quinoa is a rich source of anti-oxidants including flavonoids, phenolic acids and squalene. Research has shown a potential role for quinoa in reducing oxidative stress which is increased in response to a high sugar diet (Pasko et al., 2010), and has also been reported to reduce adiposity in response to a high fat diet (Foucault et al., 2012).  

We have recently shown quinoa, contributing to 25% of the diet, to significantly increase adiponectin levels in C57BL/6 mouse models of obesity.  Several studies have shown the benefits of increased circulating adiponectin particularly in the prevention of cardiovascular diseases, some cases of type 2 diabetes and the Metabolic Syndrome (Hotta et al., 2000; Spranger et al., 2003; Matsuzawa et al., 2004). Whilst body composition did not significantly change, a number of markers of health including lipid profiles were improved.  The current study aims to assess the effect of quinoa seeds in varying quantities on adiponectin levels, blood lipid profiles and physical activity and body composition in overweight and obese humans. We hypothesise that inclusion of quinoa in the human diet will increase adiponectin levels and improve blood lipid profile in overweight and obese humans

Participants receive either 25, 50, or 100 grams of quinoa per day for 12 weeks and results compared to a control group (0 grams quinoa/day).</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>La Trobe University Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Kingsbury Dr/Plenty Rd Bundoora VIC 3086</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/10/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HEC 14 - 065</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>8/08/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Diana Navarro - Perez</name>
      <address>La Trobe University, Bundoora VIC 3086


</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9479 6039</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d2navarroperez@students.latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Diana Navarro - Perez</name>
      <address>La Trobe University, Bundoora VIC 3086</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9479 6039</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>D.NavarroPerez@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Markandeya Jois</name>
      <address>La Trobe University, Bundoora VIC 3086</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9479 2172</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>M.Jois@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Diana Navarro - Perez</name>
      <address>La Trobe University, Bundoora VIC 3086</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9479 6039</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d2navarroperez@students.latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>