<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343440">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/09/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/09/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000956909</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Healthy Eating Learning Program (HELP) Study for Children with Feeding Difficulties</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In children with feeding difficulties, is traditional operant conditioning intervention more effective than novel systematic desensitisation intervention at improving dietary variety and nutrition, and decreasing maladaptive mealtime behaviours and parental stress?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1124-2919</utrn>
    <trialacronym>HELP Study for children with feeding difficulties</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Feeding Difficulties</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Children with a complex medical history (e.g. cardiorespiratory disease, gastrointestinal disease, history of cancer or ex-premature birth &lt;37 weeks) where medical issues are currently well controlled.</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Children with a non-medically complex history. Children defined as non-medically complex have never received treatment by a specialist physician for a medical condition. </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Arm One: Operant conditioning therapy. Run in a 30-60 minute individual session for 10 sessions with a primary therapist (speech pathologist or occupational therapist). Involves providing a verbal prompt to encourage consumption of spoonfuls of new food/s with positive reinforcement (verbal and/or with toys) upon consumption of these foods. Parents initially observe from behind a one-way mirror and assist in collecting information about the behaviours they are observing in their child with a second therapist. As sessions continue, parents are transitioned into the room, and are trained to offer new foods and provide positive reinforcement by the end of the therapy block. Parents will also receive standardised education about nutrition, behaviour management and feeding development.

Arm Two: Systematic desensitisation therapy. Run in a 30-60 minute individual or small group session for 10 sessions with a primary therapist (speech pathologist or occupational therapist). Involves the child being exposed to gradually more challenging modelling and play with food (based on a hierarchy of look&gt;smell&gt;touch&gt;taste). Parents initially observe the sessions from behind a one-way mirror with a second therapist and assist in observing transitions and reactions for their child. As the block continues, parents are rotated in and out of the room to assist in modelling play using the hierarchy. Parents will also receive standardised education about nutrition, behaviour management and feeding development. 

Therapy will be offered in an intensive format (10 times over 1 week) or in a weekly format (10 times over 10 weeks). This will be based on parent choice.</interventions>
    <comparator>There will be a natural control group who is on the wait-list to receive therapy. Following assessment, and in determining eligibility for intervention, these children will either be offered input via an intensive schedule (as described above) or during subsequent 10-week block. As recruitment for this study will occur in an ongoing fashion, there will be multiple opportunities for therapy even if it's not immediately available.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adequacy of diet and overall increase in dietary variety. Assessed via 3-day weighed food diary, and a list of foods consumed ("HELP Study Current, Previous and Goal Foods") provided by the parents. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline
Immediately post-intervention
3 months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in fat-free mass as measured by Bioelectrical Impedance Analysis (BIA). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline
Immediately post-intervention
3 months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in growth (weight and height)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline
Immediately post-intervention
3 months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvement in mealtime behaviours (% desirable vs undesirable behaviours; mealtime duration)

Measured via Behavioural Paediatrics Feeding Assessment (Adapted from Crist et al., 2001), and self-developed HELP Study: Eating Skills and Behaviour Questionnaire. Questionnaire involves parent-rated likert scales (parents rate how often their child presents with a certain behaviour from 0 = never to 4 = always).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline
Immediately post-intervention
3 months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvement in mealtime interactions between parent and child measured via Dyadic Parent-Child Interaction Coding System (Revised) (Eyeberg, 1994). A video-tape is taken of the parent interacting with their child in a non-food related activity, a parent offering their child a preferred food and the parent offering their child a non-preferred food. All videos will be rated externally by the team psychologist who will not be working directly with the children involved.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline
3 months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvement in parental stress (overall and mealtime specific)

Measured via a self-developed HELP Study: Parent Perceived Stress Questionnaire and the Parenting Stress Index - Short form.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline
Immediately psot-intervention
3 months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Increase interest in trying unfamiliar foods Measured with the Children's Picky Eating Questionnaire (Adapted from Carruth and Skinner, 2000) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline
Immediately post-intervention
3 months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Children will be eligible for assessment to further determine suitability for participation if:
*Child is aged between 2 and 6 years
*Child must present with at least one of the following features:
1. Limited range of textures (e.g. only eats puree); 
2. Limited range of foods (&lt;10 carbohydrates, &lt;10 proteins, &lt;10 fruits/ vegetables); 
3. Prolonged mealtime duration (&gt;30 minutes); 
4. Battles or problematic behaviour at mealtimes that are contributing to parental stress</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>2</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>6</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>* Acutely unwell children
* Children with severe oral motor disorders/ oropharyngeal dysphagia where aspiration is occurring
* Children who are nutritionally unstable (severe malnutrition, gut malabsorption disorders, allergy/intolerance to &gt; 2 food types).
* Children who are tube-fed
* Children whose parent/carer has a documented mental health condition
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomly generated numbers have been placed in sealed envelopes by a colleague who is not involved with the study. After children have received their initial assessment and are deemed eligible to receive intervention, the next envelope in the sequence will be opened.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer generated random number sequence will be used to allocate the numbers to sealed envelopes.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Inter-rater reliability for assessments requiring objective scoring will be viewed by a blinded clinician. Coders for dietary variety measures and parent-child interaction measures will be blinded.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>12/09/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>20/09/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>64</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Pamela Dodrill</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Boston Childrens Hospital 
Dept of Otolaryngology &amp; Communication Enhancement
300 Longwood Ave
Boston, MA 02115</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Lady Cilento Children's Hospital
Children's Health Queensland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Speech Pathology  Allied Health Outpatients 
Level 6a
Lady Cilento Childrens Hospital
501 Stanley Street, South Brisbane 
Queensland
4101
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Children's Nutrition Research Centre
Queensland Children's Medical Research Institute
The University of Queensland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Old Milk Kitchen
Cnr Fourth and Back Roads
(off Bramston Terrace)
Royal Children's Hospital
Brisbane
Queensland
4029</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Children's Health Queensland</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Speech Pathology  Allied Health Outpatients 
Level 6a
Lady Cilento Childrens Hospital
501 Stanley Street, South Brisbane 
Queensland
4101
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is a randomised clinical trial designed to evaluate the clinical benefits of two child-focused feeding intervention programs for children with feeding difficulties and restricted range of dietary intake. Baseline assessments will include parent-completed questionnaires, on-site assessment, and feeding and growth evaluations. 

After assessment, participants will be randomised into one of two intervention arms. Arm One is an individual operant conditioning program. Arm Two involves systematic desensitisation therapy. Although dose of intervention will be the same (10 sessions), intervention will either be provided in a weekly (once/ week for 10 weeks), or intensive format (all 10 sessions within a week). Parents will be able to choose between weekly or intensive therapy.

Some outcome measures will be reviewed immediately post-treatment, and the participants will return for a full evaluation at 3-months post treatment.  </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Children's Health Service Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>C / Department of Paediatrics &amp; Child Health
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston Rd, Herston, QLD 4029</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/03/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/10/QRCH/30</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Queensland Medical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Ethics Unit
The University of Qld
St Lucia, QLD, 4068</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/05/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2010000677</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jeanne Marshall</name>
      <address>Speech Pathology  Allied Health Outpatients 
Level 6a
Lady Cilento Childrens Hospital
501 Stanley Street, South Brisbane
Queensland
4101</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3068 2850 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jeanne.marshall@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jeanne Marshall</name>
      <address>Speech Pathology  Allied Health Outpatients 
Level 6a
Lady Cilento Childrens Hospital
501 Stanley Street, South Brisbane
Queensland
4101
</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3068 2850 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jeanne.marshall@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jeanne Marshall</name>
      <address>Speech Pathology  Allied Health Outpatients 
Level 6a
Lady Cilento Childrens Hospital
501 Stanley Street, South Brisbane
Queensland
4101</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3068 2850 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jeanne.marshall@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Pamela Dodrill</name>
      <address>Boston Childrens Hospital 
Dept of Otolaryngology &amp; Communication Enhancement
300 Longwood Ave
Boston, MA 02115
</address>
      <phone>+1 617 919 3648</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Pamela.Dodrill@childrens.harvard.edu</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>