<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367237">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/10/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/10/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001126606</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The OnTrack Diabetes Web-based Program for Type 2 Diabetes and Dysphoria Self-Management:  A Randomised Controlled Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of Functional Imagery Training (FIT) on health outcomes in patients with Type 2 diabetes who receive access to an online self-management program, OnTrack Diabetes.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1162-7436</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 diabetes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Dysphoria</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants receive access to an online self-guided diabetes management program, OnTrack Diabetes, and regular therapist support phone calls wherein FIT techniques are utilised. The therapist is a provisionally registered Psychologist who contacts participants twice in the first week of study enrolment, and once every fortnight until 3 months has elapsed.  The first 2 calls last approx. 45mins, all remaining calls are 15mins. Participants are encouraged to practise FIT at home every day.  The approach assists them to develop and maintain personalised changes to their diabetes self-care behaviours.  The therapist reinforces the imagery-based activities already included in the OnTrack Diabetes program and extends these by encouraging additional imagery rehearsal to further enhance motivation.
FIT is grounded in the Elaborated Intrusion Theory of Desire which postulates that motivation is a process that involves elaboration of a mental representation of a target (often in the form of an image), to increase desire for that target. Therefore FIT attempts to increase the vividness and frequency of images of targets, where targets are functional behaviour (i.e. exercising). This is achieved by asking participants to elaborate on details of their goals and the benefits of those goals, while on the phone to the research therapist. The OnTrack Diabetes program offers modules on diet, physical activity, blood-sugar testing, adherence to medication and mood. These modules allow participants to consider if they want to make a change to these areas, and if so, how. Participants are encouraged to login to the modules a minimum of once a week. They may work at their own pace through the program. Tenants of Social Cognitive Theory, motivational interviewing, and CBT based problem-solving techniques are the foundation to the modules, such that participants are able to set and achieve their health goals. This is a 6-month trial, where participants are being tested for adherence via surveys at baseline, 3 and 6 months.</interventions>
    <comparator>There are 2 control groups. Participants who only receive access to OnTrack Diabetes, without FIT; and participants who continue with their usual care for 3-months, followed by access to OnTrack Diabetes
The participants who continue with usual care are asked to manage their diabetes as they always have (i.e. whether that is seeing health practitioners regularly, or making modifications on their own). Neither of these control groups will receive FIT after 3 months.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence behaviours (assessed using questionnaires - Serves of fruit, vegetables, sweets, and fat per week (new survey designed for OnTrack Diabetes to assess diet), Active Australia Survey (physical activity), AusDiab Study Survey (medication + blood sugar testing)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3, 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mental health (assessed by questionnaires - Depression, Anxiety, Stress Scale; Diabetes Distress Scale)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3 and 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>HbA1c (assessed by blood sample from their GP)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3, and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life (EQ-5D)</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 3, 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self Efficacy (Diabetes Self-Efficacy Scale)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3, 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(a) Type 2 diabetes diagnosis (by a medical doctor and/ according to WHO criteria) for 3 or more months; (b) aged 18 years or older; (c) living in Australia without plans to leave within 12 months; (d) regular computer and internet access ; (e) contactable by phone; (f) clear command of written English (at least year 5 education); and (g) stable diabetes pharmacotherapy (medication dose stable for past 4 weeks; medication type stable past 3 months).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(a) current diagnosis of mental disorder other than depression or anxiety (participant is asked if a condition has been diagnosed and if so they are informed that they will receive access to the program but not be included in the trial); (b) current suicidal risk (assessed via suicide risk assessment); (c) significant cognitive disorder (e.g. from head trauma or dementia); (d) currently on steroid medication , or likely to commence these in the next 12 months; (e) pregnant or likely to become pregnant in the next 12 months.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Recruitment and screening. Ineligible participants offered access to program. Eligible participants asked to obtain current HbA1c or provide most recent HbA1c (must be within last 4 weeks). Participants then complete a baseline survey related to their clinical status, demographics, lifestyle and experience of diabetes. Once completed participants are randomly allocated to one of the 3 groups.</concealment>
    <sequence>The online program OnTrack Diabetes randomly allocates participants to one of the 3 groups when we activate them after they complete the baseline survey.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The OnTrack Diabetes program (www.ontrack.org.au/diabetes) stores participants details. A researcher approves the participant once they have completed the baseline survey and the program then randomly allocates the participant to one of the 3 research groups (delayed, immediate, or immediate + FIT)</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Preliminary analyses assess for baseline differences, and subsequent analyses control for any observed differences.  The primary analyses will comprise multiple regressions, predicting post-treatment and follow-up results from Baseline measures and treatment contrasts, with multiple imputation being used to predict missing data.  Mixed models ANOVAs with repeated measures will also be applied, to confirm whether effects are still obtained without imputations.  Both methods allow an intention-to-treat (ITT) approach to the data.  Repeated Measures ANOVAs will be used to evaluate differences in change scores between the study time points between the three study conditions.
User satisfaction, perceived ease of use, and usefulness are examined with ANOVAs, and
program reach, acceptability, implementation feasibility and outreach are assessed using the RE-AIM framework.  This will be operationalised using the OnTrack Diabetes Evaluation Questionnaire, which asks about users perceptions of the progams acceptability, issues with feasibility and outreach (i.e. ability to access the program, barriers to access including poor broadband network availability).  The inclusion of residents of rural and regional areas enriches this evaluation, as will quantitative data about participants exposure to the program. 
A total of 210 participants will be recruited to observe a small effect size (f2 = .046).</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>210</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Wesley Hospital - Auchenflower</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Queensland University of Technology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>QUT
Victoria Park Rd, Kelvin Grove QLD 4059</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Wesley St Andrews Research Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>461 Coronation Drive
Auchenflower QLD
4066</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The RCT compares three treatments:  (i) Delayed Program Access  undertakes usual diabetes care for 3 months Post-Baseline, followed by access to the full OnTrack Diabetes program, (ii) Immediate Program  receives full access to the self-guided program from Baseline onwards, and (iii) Immediate Program plus Therapist Support.  Measures are administered at Baseline, and at 3, 6, and 12 months Post-Baseline.  Outcomes are glycosylated haemoglobin A1c (HbA1c) level and diabetes-specific distress, depression, anxiety, diabetes self-care, self-efficacy and adherence, and quality of life.  Exposure data in terms of program uptake, use, time on each page, and program completion as well as implementation feasibility, will be conducted.
It is predicted that OnTrack Diabetes will improve adherenec to diabetes self-care behaviours and FIT will enhance this effect. This is the first known trial of an automated, self-guided, web-based support program that uses a holistic approach in targeting both Type 2 diabetes self-management and dysphoria.  Findings will inform the feasibility of implementing such a program on an ongoing basis, including in rural and regional locations.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.ontrack.org.au/diabetes</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Cassimatis, M., Kavanagh, D.J., Hills, A.P., Smith, A.C., &amp; Scuffham, P.A. (2013). Study Protocol of The OnTrack Diabetes Project: Randomised Trial of An Automated, Interactive, Web-based Type 2 Diabetes Self-management and Dysphoria Intervention. Journal of Medical Internet Research. 

Cassimatis, M., Kavanagh, D.J., Hills, A.P., Smith, A.C., &amp; Scuffham, P.A. (2013). Development of the OnTrack Diabetes Program and Design of a Randomized Controlled Evaluation Trial. Journal of Medical Internet Research. 
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Uniting Care Health, Queensland</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 5
193 North Quay
Brisbane QLD
4000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/06/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Cassimatis9111</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sophie Parham</name>
      <address>PO Box 499 Toowong QLD 4066

or

Level 8, East Wing, The Wesley Hospital 
451 Coronation Drive Auchenflower QLD 4066</address>
      <phone>+61 07 3721 1721</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sparham@wesleyresearch.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sophie Parham</name>
      <address>PO Box 499 Toowong QLD 4066

or

Level 8, East Wing, The Wesley Hospital 
451 Coronation Drive Auchenflower QLD 4066</address>
      <phone>+61 07 3721 1721</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sparham@wesleyresearch.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sophie Parham</name>
      <address>PO Box 499 Toowong QLD 4066

or

Level 8, East Wing, The Wesley Hospital 
451 Coronation Drive Auchenflower QLD 4066</address>
      <phone>+61 07 3721 1721</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sparham@wesleyresearch.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sophie Parham</name>
      <address>PO Box 499 Toowong QLD 4066

or

Level 8, East Wing, The Wesley Hospital 
451 Coronation Drive Auchenflower QLD 4066</address>
      <phone>+61 07 3721 1721</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sparham@wesleyresearch.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>