<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363152">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/10/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/10/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001102864</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Spatial Repellent and Malaria Attack Rates II</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Impact of spatial repellents on malaria transmission among residents in southwest Sumba district, Indonesia and its entomological correlates</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>SPIRIT SUMBA II</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Malaria</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study is a a cluster-randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled  trial to demonstrate the impact of spatial repellents against the malaria in human population in Southwest Sumba and to prove that impact associated with the entomological correlates.
Forty five school age participants (6-13 year old)  in each of the four study clusters will be recruited and enrolled. Subjects will be asked to complete a supervised malaria radical cure (regardless of blood film status at enrolment) consisting of dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine and primaquine prior to the coil intervention.  We will give oral tablet of dihydroartemisinin (DHA) + piperaquine (PP) along with a single daily dose oral tablet of 0.6 mg/kg bodyweight (BW) primaquine (PQ) for 14 days. One tablet of DHA-PP contains 40mg of DHA and 320 mg of PP. It is administered based on body weight (BW) targeting a total dose of 6.4 and 51.2 mg/kg BW of dihydroartemisinin and piperaquine, respectively, given in three equally divided daily doses.  All drugs will be administered with food and water. 
For Coil Intervention, each cluster in the village will be assigned to receive either active repellent (i.e. 0.0097% Metofluthrin) in a standard mosquito coil (manufactured to burn for 12 hours) or a placebo coil containing no known chemical repellent and being otherwise identical to the active coil with composition:
Arm 1.  90 subjects in two cluster will be given insecticide-treated coil for 6 months.
Arm 2. 90 subjects in two clusters will be given blank coil Each of the study areas (cluster)  will be randomly assigned to be given either  active or placebo coils for 6 months.
Four coils will be placed in each house, and burned for 12 hours (commencing at 6PM each evening).</interventions>
    <comparator>Blank mosquito coil</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcomes of this study are : 
1.	Malaria attacks rates among the volunteers in each intervention arm
The malaria attack in each subject  will be checked weekly by performing blood smear. Subjects found malaria positive will be drop from the study</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point: every week during the coil intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2.	Malaria vector abundance, human blood indices, parity rates, sporozoites rate and Spatial repellent action
The above entomologic parameter will be monitored by Human landing Catch (HLC), larval collection, blood meal, and resting collection.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point: every other week during the coil intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1.    Incident cases of acute slide-confirmed malaria among all residents reporting to the study clinic with complaint of illness analysed by coil assignment of the cluster in which they reside</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: throughout the 6-month duration of coil intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2.	To measure indoor anopheline feeding activity according to coil assignment.

Twenty houses, 5 in each cluster,  will be selected as sentinel sites for measuring vector abundance within study site. All mosquitoes landing on collectors (to include anophelines, and culicines) will be captured using mouth aspirators with the aide of a flashlight. These collections will be performed and specimens processed  using standard methods: parity, CSP-ELISA.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: once a week during the coil intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-	Children between 6 - 13 years of age 
-	Weight &gt; 20 kg
-	G6PD normal on a qualitative screen
-	No severe anaemia 
-	No significant chronic illness
-	Sleeps in village &gt;90% of nights during any given month
-	No plans for extended travel during study
-	Willingness to sign informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>13</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-	Having severe / chronic disease
-	G6PD deficiency</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>One hundred and eighty school age participants at the study site will be recruited and enrolled. Parents/guardians of participants will be asked to permit their children to join the study.  The participants will complete a 14-day supervised malaria radical cure (regardless of blood film status at enrolment) consisting of concurrent dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine (3 days) and primaquine (14 days) immediately prior to the coil intervention. During the intervention, they will be asked to contribute a blood film once a week to check on their malaria status.  All participants are resident in Wainyapu village in Southwest Sumba District.   Incident cases of slide-confirmed malaria among all residents will be monitored through passive case detection reporting to study clinics complaining of illness. Moreover, the study site physician will conduct a routine physical examination and make a determination as to the physical fitness of the volunteer to serve as a subject of this research. Allocation is not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Four clusters, 2 coastal and 2 inlands in Wainyapu village will be will be randomly assigned to be given either active or placebo coils in double blinded fashion. The simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>180</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Indonesia</country>
      <state>Southwest Sumba, Nusa Tenggara Timur</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Eijkman Institute for Molecular Biology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Jl. Diponegoro No. 69
Jakarta 10430</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Indonesia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>500 Fifth Avenue North
Seattle, WA 98102</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>SC Johnson</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>SC Johnson
1525 Howe Street
Racine, WI 53403</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>United States of America</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Faculty of Medicine
Hasanuddin University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Jl. Perintis Kemerdekaan KM 10
Makassar 90245</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Indonesia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other Collaborative groups</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Eijkman Oxford Clinical Research Unit</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Jl. Diponegoro No. 69
Jakarta 10430</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Indonesia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study is a cluster-randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled  trial to demonstrate the impact of spatial repellents against malaria in human population in Southwest Sumba and to prove that impact associated with the entomological correlates. One hundred and eighty school age participants at the study site will be recruited and enrolled. Participants will be asked to complete a 14-day supervised malaria radical cure (regardless of blood film status at enrolment) consisting of concurrent dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine (3 days) and primaquine (14 days) immediately prior to the intervention. During the intervention, they will be asked to contribute a blood film once a week to check on their malaria status.  All participants will be resident in Wainyapu village in Southwest Sumba District.  Four clusters, 2 coastal and 2 inlands in the village will be will be randomly assigned to be given either active or placebo coils in double blinded fashion. Incident cases of slide-confirmed malaria among all residents will be monitored through passive case detection reporting to study clinics complaining of illness. Further, mass blood surveys will be conducted on a randomly selected sample of residents prior to, during, and at the end of the coil intervention. The team will distribute and light mosquito coils to each household in each cluster in order to ensure compliance and correct coil assignment.  The primary endpoint will be the malaria attack rate among the radically cured school age children living in cluster with active versus placebo coils. Secondary endpoints will include rates of slide confirmed malaria among all residents according to coil assignment of the cluster they reside, along with human landing anopheline mosquitoes captured inside of homes analysed by active or placebo coil assignment.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>N/A</trialwebsite>
    <publication>N/A</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Research Ethics Committee, Faculty of Medicine, Hasanuddin University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Jl. Perintis Kemerdekaan Km 10
Makassar 90245</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/09/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>UI12080231</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/08/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Indonesia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Din Syafruddin</name>
      <address>Eijkman Institute for Molecular Biology, 
Jalan Diponegoro 69
Jakarta 10430</address>
      <phone>+62-21-3917131</phone>
      <fax>+62-21-3147982</fax>
      <email>din@eijkman.go.id</email>
      <country>Indonesia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Puji BS Asih, BSc, PhD.</name>
      <address>Eijkman Institute for Molecular Biology, 
Jalan Diponegoro 69
Jakarta 10430</address>
      <phone>+62-21-3917131</phone>
      <fax>+62-21-3147982</fax>
      <email>puji@eijkman.go.id</email>
      <country>Indonesia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dian Sidik, MSc</name>
      <address>Eijkman Institute for Molecular Biology, 
Jalan Diponegoro 69
Jakarta 10430</address>
      <phone>+62-21-3917131</phone>
      <fax>+62-21-3147982</fax>
      <email>diansidik@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Indonesia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>