<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366343">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/05/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/05/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000537651</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Living well with long term neurological conditions: The living well toolkit</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The living well toolkit: a practical solution to facilitate two-way communication, self-management and continuum of care for people living with a long-term neurological condition, a pilot study.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1156-5004 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>long term neurological conditions</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This trial is a pilot study where 6 to 9 consenting participants will be introduced to a toolkit, 2 weeks prior to their discharge home or transition into another service.  The introduction will be through one of the participating health professionals involved in that person's care who will have attended an information and education session on the purpose of the toolkit and how to use the toolkit. It is then anticipated that the health professional will introduce this to one of their clients who fits the inclusion criteria. This toolkit can be in paper form or an electronic data file that will allow the participant (person living with a neurological condition) to record important information and exchange this with other service providers, that will give them the skills and resources to take charge of their condition and to live well with this condition, and that will assist with the continuum of care over a lifespan. The participant (person living with a neurological condition) will be able to choose which toolkit suits them best, either electronic or paper based. The content of the toolkit, electronic or paper, will be identical; only the media of delivery and format will be different. The toolkit is currently under construction.
The Participants (people living with neurological conditions) and consenting family members/carers or support staff, and health professional involved in the introduction of the toolkit will be asked to provide feedback on the usability and value of the toolkit approximately 1 week after implementation and at 3 months follow up. This will happen by means of a semi-structured focus group (for health professionals), face to face interviews (for people living with a neurological condition and their family) or a short phone interview (carers or support staff). An implementation coordinator will monitor the adherence to the intervention.</interventions>
    <comparator>we will not use a control group. Non-participants will receive the standard discharge or transition processes used in that locality</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>qualitative study - feedback on value and usability will be sought through semi-structured interviews.
The interviews are with participating health professionals by means of a one-off locality focus group or individual face to face interview (if more practical or preferred). We will also seek feedback from people living with a neurological condition and their family (together) by means of a face to face interview. And we will seek feedback on the usability of the toolkit from nominated and consenting carers / support workers via a one-off phone interview.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week post intervention </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Face to face interviews with participating people living with a neurological condition and their family will be held to further evaluate the toolkit's value and use in the longer term</outcome>
      <timepoint>A 3 month follow- up </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>We have 3 participant groups:
1) people living with a long-term neurological condition
- at the point where they are close to discharge or transitioning into another service
- older than 18 years ( adults able to consent)
2)nominated family/ carers/ support staff, older than 18 years and able to consent, and being a significant other or support person involved in the care of the person living with a neurological condition
3) health care providers such as nurses, physio's, OT's, SLT', social workers, key workers etc. involved in the care of people living with a neurological condition.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>not able to give consent
not 18 years of age
not having a long-term neurological condition (patient participants)
not having the cognitive capacity to express their thoughts on the experience of using the toolkit (patient participants)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>We will recruit 6 to 9 consenting health care providers from 3 to 6 of our primary recruiting localities including in-patient and community/primary care settings. They will be asked to nominate 6 to 9 consenting people living with a long term condition (their client), who are close to being discharged home or who are close to being transitioned into another service. Participating health care providers will be trained in the use of the toolkit and will be asked to introduce the toolkit to their participating client  and family/carers and implement the toolkit as part of the discharge/transition process. 
The participating client will be asked to nominate a family member involved in their care and one or two carers/ support workers also willing to participate in this study.</concealment>
    <sequence>This study uses a non-random approach. We will include suitable potential health provider participants in order of consent to participate, however we will seek to recruit from a variety of localities (inpatient, rehabilitation, community etc.). Potential client participants (people living with neurological conditions) will need to meet the inclusion criteria and where possible we will seek diversity in age, gender, ethnicity and diagnosis. 
Family and carers will be nominated by participating clients.
</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Traditional content analysis will be used incorporating methods of constant comparison according to Charmaz (2006) to identify categories and themes of importance such as key strengths of the toolkit,  issues or concerns and recommendations for future wider implementation. Rigour checks will include independent coding by two members of the research team, team analysis meetings, and knowledge user committee involvement in checking interpretation. key findings will be synthesised with existing knowledge from prior research to inform the development the final version(s) of the toolkit and implementation protocol.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>17/05/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/06/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>15/12/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>45</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>25</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Stopped early</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>8/03/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis>Data collected is being analysed</dataanalysis>
    <withdrawnreason>Participant recruitment difficulties</withdrawnreason>
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>AUT University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Rehabilitation and Occupation Studies
North Shore Campus
90 Akoranga Drive
Northcote
Auckland, 1020</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname> Health Research Council (HRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 3 ,  110 Stanley Street,
1010 ,Auckland
PO BOX 5541 (Wellesley Street, Auckland 1141)
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Peter Larmer</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>AUT University
90 Akoranga Drive
Northcote 
Auckland, 1020
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Long term neurological conditions result in great personal, whanau/family and societal burdens associated with long term neurological conditions; which evidence tells us, can be achieved by improving two-way communication, by equipping people living with a neurological condition (PLWNC) and their whanau/families with skills that allow them to do as much as possible for themselves, and by better coordinating the provision of care over a lifespan. This study aims to develop and implement a workable solution, the living well toolkit", to meet these three health needs. This application relates to phase II of the study, where we intend to further develop and refine the toolkit based on the findings from Phase I, and existing knowledge gained from former research. In this phase, we will also pilot the toolkit with six to nine consenting participants, recruited from the primary recruitment localities or Non-Governmental Organisations (NGO's) identified in Phase I. We will purposefully select participants who are transitioning from in-patient hospital care to Primary Health Care or in-patient rehabilitation, or from rehabilitation to community services. Where discharge timeframes are predictable we will introduce the toolkit approximately two weeks before planned discharge. Information concerning the utility of the toolkit will be obtained through semi-structured interviews with the individual participants and their whanau/family, one week after they start using the toolkit and at 3 months follow-up. Data on the usability of the toolkit will also be obtained by asking participants to nominate 1 or 2 current health professionals/carers willing to participate in a 15 -20 minute phone interview at three months follow-up. Health providers who were involved with the introduction of the toolkit at discharge/transition, will also be invited to share their experience in a one-off locality based focus group.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname> Health and Disability Ethics Committees (HDEC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
c/ MEDSAFE, Level 6, Deloitte House
10 Brandon Street
PO BOX 5013
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/08/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>22/05/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/366343-Research Protocol.docx</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Suzie Mudge</name>
      <address>Centre for Person Centred Research
AUT University
90 Akoranga Drive
Auckland, 1142
Private bag 92006</address>
      <phone>+64 9 9219999 ext 7096</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>suzie.mudge@aut.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Ann Sezier</name>
      <address>Centre for Person Centred Research
AUT University
90 Akoranga Drive
Auckland, 1142
Private bag 92006</address>
      <phone>+64 9 9219999 ext 7029</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>asezier@aut.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Suzie Mudge</name>
      <address>Centre for Person Centred Research
AUT University
90 Akoranga Drive
Auckland, 1142
Private bag 92006</address>
      <phone>+64 9 9219999 ext 7096</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>smudge@aut.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Ann Sezier</name>
      <address>Centre for Person Centred Research
AUT University
90 Akoranga Drive
Auckland, 1142
Private bag 92006</address>
      <phone>+64 9 9219999 ext 7029</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>asezier@aut.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>