<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368947">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/07/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/08/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000807550</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparing the efficacy of cognitive-behavioral guided self-help and health at every size guided self-help for disordered eating.  </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomized controlled trial of the effects of cognitive-behavioural vs. health at every size guided self-help on symptoms of subclinical disordered eating in Australian adults. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Disordered eating </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Eating disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This project is a randomised controlled trial (RCT) of two psychological interventions for disordered eating. The proposed study targets both males and females aged between 18 and 65 years. 
The interventions include:
Cognitive-behavioural guided self-help (CBT G-SH) is one intervention based on the self-help manual, Overcoming Binge Eating (Fairburn, 2013), which has received considerable empirical support for reducing eating disorder behaviours and cognitions. It is a program designed to target the cognitive, behavioural and emotional processes that maintain the core symptoms of eating disorders. There are 8 serial steps in this program that are designed to modify dysfunctional eating disorder cognitions (e.g. extreme concerns about weight and shape) and behaviours (e.g. restrictive dieting and binge eating). For this program, there will be 8 sessions that run over 10 weeks. The first 2 weeks of the program will enable participants to read the first half of the book  a psychoeducation section that teaches people about the nature of dieting and binge eating. The remaining 8 weeks will be devoted to the treatment program. Participants will meet face to face weekly with a provisional clinical psychologist who will guide them through the program. Sessions will take between 35-50 minutes, and participants will get a chance to review their progress, discuss any obstacles to change, and discuss any challenges they are having with the program. To monitor adherence to the program, a visual analogue scale will be used to ask participants to indicate their level adherence over the preceding week. Lack of adherence to the program will allow the facilitator to discuss any potential barriers to adherence while also allowing for discussion of strategies that might facilitate adherence in successive sessions. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparative treatment includes a non-dieting Health at Every Size (HAES) guided self-help intervention, based on the book If not dieting, then what? by Dr Rick Kausman. This book contains psychoeducation chapters that explains the nature and link between body image and self-evaluation, dieting, reasons for non-hungry eating, and the evidence for the long-term success of current weight-loss methods. In addition several interrelated techniques are provided in this book that help participants (1) reduce their disinhibited/binge eating by helping people eat mindfully, (2) reduce the negative body image people have by teaching people to appreciate the diversity of body shape (3) to eliminate restrictive dieting and food avoidance by helping people develop a positive relationship with food. There will be 8 face to face sessions of this program, run by a provisional clinical psychologist, that last a total of 10 weeks. The first two weeks participants will get a chance to read the entire book before they start implementing the techniques. The following 8 weeks will allow both facilitator and participant to go through individual modules outlined in the chapters. During sessions, which lasts between 35-50 minutes, participants will be educated about nutrition principles and importance of regular (enjoyable) physical activity, the importance of disentangling feelings of self-worth from their weight and shape and getting in touch with their physiological hunger and satiety cues. Opportunities to discuss barriers to change and challenges to the intervention will also be discussed in session. This is consistent with other HAES interventions on weight-preoccupied individual (e.g. Bacon Stern, Van Loan, &amp; Keim, 2005). To monitor adherence to the program, a visual analogue scale will be used to ask participants to indicate their level adherence. Lack of adherence to the program will allow the facilitator to discuss any potential barriers to adherence while also allowing for discussion of strategies that might facilitate adherence in successive sessions.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Eating disorder psychopathology, assessed by the Eating Disorder Examination Questionnaire (EDE-Q) Global Score </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-treatment, 6 month follow-up and 24 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Objective Binge Eating abstinence: Assessed by an individual item on the EDE-Q - 'on how many days have you consumed what others would regard as unusually large amount of food, and of these days is there a sense of loss of control"?</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-treatment, 6 month follow up and 24 month follow up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean AQoL (Assessment of quality of life) and short-form-36 scores. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-treatment, 6 month follow up and 24 month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean depression and anxiety subscale scores on the depression anxiety stress scale. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-treatment, 6 month follow up and 24 month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean dichotomous thinking in eating disorder scale scores</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-treatment, 6 month follow up and 24 month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean disinhibition subscale scores on the three factor eating questionnaire </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-treatment, 6 month follow up and 24 month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean clinical impairment questionnaire scores (Clinical Impairment Questionnaire)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-treatment, 6 month follow up and 24 month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean total intuitive eating scores on the Intuitive Eating Scale-2</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-treatment, 6 month follow up and 24 month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean body appreciation scores</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-treatment, 6 month follow up and 24 month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in dietary restraint over preceding 7 days (assessed by a single item on the EDE-Q 'Have you deliberately tried to limit the amount of food you eat to influence your weight or shape'?)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Session 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in objective binge eating episodes over the past 7 days (Assessed by single item on the EDE-Q 'on how many days have you consumed what others would regard as unusually large amount of food, and of these days is there a sense of loss of control")</outcome>
      <timepoint>Session 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in shape concern over prior 7 days (assessed by single item on the EDE-Q; 'How dissatisfied have you been with your shape'?)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Session 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8 </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in weight concern over prior 7 days (assessed by single item on the EDE-Q; 'How dissatisfied have you been with your weight?)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Session 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8 </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in eating behaviour self-efficacy (assessed by single item on the Eating Behaviour Self-efficacy Scale 'how difficult is it to control our overeating')</outcome>
      <timepoint>Session 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8 </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Regular eating adherence, assessed by daily recall of number of snacks and meals consumed </outcome>
      <timepoint>Session 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8 </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in motivation for exercise in past 7 days (assessed by individual item on the Exercise motivation inventory 'I exercise for enjoyment')</outcome>
      <timepoint>Session 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8 </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in intuitive eating in past 7 days (assessed by single item on the Intuitive Eating Scale-2 'I  rely on my hunger and satiety cues to tell me when to eat')</outcome>
      <timepoint>Session 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8 </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in body appreciation in past 7 days (assessed by single item on the body appreciation scale 'I feel good about my body')</outcome>
      <timepoint>Session 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8 </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Frequency of weight checking in prior 7 days (assessed by participant recall)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Session 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria includes: age between 18-65 years, exhibit symptoms of disordered eating that are not of clinical severity (i.e. objective and subjective binge eating occurring less than once per week over prior 3 months; Eating disorder examination questionnaire global score &lt; 4), can meet the requirements for face to face contact. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria includes: Age &lt;18 years and &gt;65 years, any DSM-5 psychiatric disorder, unable to complete the full duration of treatment, pregnancy, seeking psychological treatment concurrently, BMI&lt;18.5. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/08/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>112</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Jake Linardon</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of psychology
Australian Catholic University
Level 5,17 Young Street, 
Fitzroy VIC 3065 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Catholic University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>115 Victoria Parade
Fitzroy 
Victoria 3065</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>A/Prof Leah Brennan</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of psychology 
Australian Catholic University
Level 5,17 Young Street, 
Fitzroy VIC 3065</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to compare the efficacy of two psychological interventions for disordered eating. Males and females, aged between 18-65 years, will be randomised into either a cognitive-behavioural guided self-help or a health at every size guided self-help condition. 
Participation is free and is running in Melbourne between September 2015 and September 2016. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Australian Catholic University Human Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Australian Catholic University
Research Services
North Sydney Campus
PO Box 968
North Sydney, New South Wales, 2059
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/07/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec> 2015-58H</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Leah Brennan </name>
      <address>School of psychology
Australian Catholic University 
Level 5, The Daniel Mannix Building, 
17 Young Street, 
Fitzroy, VIC 3065</address>
      <phone>+613 9953 3662 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Leah.Brennan@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Jake Linardon</name>
      <address>School of psychology
Australian Catholic University 
Level 5, The Daniel Mannix Building, 
17 Young Street, 
Fitzroy, VIC 3065</address>
      <phone>+613 9230 8073</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Jake.linardon@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Leah Brennan</name>
      <address>School of psychology
Australian Catholic University 
Level 5, The Daniel Mannix Building, 
17 Young Street, 
Fitzroy, VIC 3065</address>
      <phone>+613 9953 3662 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Leah.Brennan@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Jake Linardon</name>
      <address>School of psychology
Australian Catholic University 
Level 5, The Daniel Mannix Building, 
17 Young Street, 
Fitzroy, VIC 3065</address>
      <phone>+613 9230 8073</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Jake.linardon@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>