<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365983">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/03/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/04/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000389606</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Intravenous Dexmedetomidine   Infusion In Adult Patients Undergoing  Open Nephrolithotomy


</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Intravenous Dexmedetomidine   Infusion In Adult Patients Undergoing  Open Nephrolithotomy: Effects On  Intraoperative Hemodynamics And Blood loss.

Clinical research study
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn> U1111-1154-5834</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Intraoperative Hemodynamics </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Intraoperative Blood loss.</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Nephrolithotomy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other anaesthesiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients will  randomly allocated  using a closed envelop technique into two groups (n= 25).

Group D: will receive a bolus dose of dexmedetomidine (Precedex, Abbot Laboratories Inc., Abbot Park, IL, USA) 1ug/kg over 10 min before induction of anesthesia then dexmedetomidine  iv infusion of 0.1 ug-0.5ug/kg/h infused continuously throughout the operation. guided by hemodynamics

Group P: will receive a bolus dose of 10 ml ringer solution  before induction of anesthesia, and continuous intraoperative infusion 10 ml /h ringer solution
</interventions>
    <comparator>Group P: will receive a bolus dose of 10 ml ringer solution  before induction of anesthesia, and continuous intraoperative infusion 
</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Heart rate 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored continuously intraoperative with ECG</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Volume of blood loss:in the suction drain and  swabs </outcome>
      <timepoint>measured  intraoperative</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of  packed red blood cells  transfused
</outcome>
      <timepoint>measured  intraoperative</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Laboratory Hb </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre, intra and immediate post-operative</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Laboratory haematocrite concentration</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre, intra and immediate post-operative</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>ASA I and II   males  and  females patients aged 20-60 years old, planned for  elective open  nephrolithotomy under general anesthesia   </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>ASA more than  II ,  had a known cardiac arrhythmias ,significant liver disease defined as (serum alanine aminotransferase and serum aspartate aminotransferase &gt;2.5 times normal),significant renal disease defined as (serum creatinine &gt;1.5 mg/dl or creatinine clearance &lt;40 ml/min),pregnant patient, significant coagulopathy defined as (INR &gt;1.5),use of antiplatlets or anticoagulants ,anemic patients with Hb% less than 10 gm/dl
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The study drugs will be prepared by a senior  anesthetia resident unaware of the  study protocol
Patients will  randomly allocated  using a closed envelop technique into two groups
</concealment>
    <sequence>The study drugs will be prepared by a senior  anesthetia resident unaware of the  study protocol
Patients will  randomly allocated  using a closed envelop technique into two groups
Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Statistical analysis:
After a pilot study in ten patients, the mean  intraoperative blood loss (SD) was 621 (143) and 782 (338) in the dexmedetomidine group and the placebo group, respectively. Therefore, the sample size was calculated using the program of biostatistics version 3.01 twenty five per group was needed to show a difference of intraoperative blood loss 161 ml (SD 195 ml) between groups with the power was set at 80% and the a-error level was fixed at 0.05.
Data are presented as mean ± standard deviation (SD) or median (range) or numbers as appropriate , Numerical data were analyzed by using Students unpaired ttest.Nonparametric data were analyzed by using the Mann
Whitney U-test. A value of P &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant. 


</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/04/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/09/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>1/09/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <state>benisuef</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>benisuef university hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>egypt,

benisuef university,faculty of medicine

 -,mokbel,mohamad anwar hassan street, 62511
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Egypt</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>egypt ,benisuef governerate 
benisuef university
 mokbel</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress> egypt,

benisuef university,faculty of medicine

 -,mokbel,mohamad anwar hassan street, 62511

</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Egypt</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Patients and Methods:
After approval of the ethical committee in Beni  suef University (FMBUS REC,Egypt) the study was  registered at ANZCTR clinical trial registry  ,(registration number ACTRN12614000389606),a written informed consents were obtained from 50 patients ASA I and II   males  and  females aged 20-60 years old, scheduled  for  elective open  nephrolithotomy under general anesthesia from March 2014 to September 2014.   
Patients were excluded if they were ASA more than  II ,  had a known cardiac arrhythmias, significant liver disease defined as (serum alanine aminotransferase and serum aspartate aminotransferase &gt;2.5 times normal),significant renal disease defined as (serum creatinine&gt;1.5 mg/dl or creatinine clearance &lt;40 ml/min),pregnant patient, significant coagulopathy defined as (INR &gt;1.5),use of antiplatlets or anticoagulants, anemic patients with Hb% less than 10 gm/dl.
 In the operating room, two  intravenous cannula was inserted , monitors were connected   including     Electrocardiogram,  pulse oximetry, non-invasive arterial blood pressure at 5 minutes intervals and BIS monitor strip (BIS Sensor; Aspect Medical Systems, USA, Toll free 1-888-BIS Index)
The study drugs were prepared by a senior anesthesia resident unaware of the  study protocol
Patients were randomly allocated using a closed envelop technique into two groups (n= 25 each).
Group D: received  in a separate cannula a bolus dose of dexmedetomidine (Precedex, Abbot Laboratories Inc., Abbot Park, IL, USA) 1 micogram/kg over 10 min before induction of anesthesia then iv infusion of 0.1 -0.5 micogram/kg/h guided by the hemodynamics.
Group P: received a bolus dose of 10 ml ringer lactate solution before induction of anesthesia then continuous infusion till the end of the operation. 
Preoxgenation for 3- 5 minute with 100% oxygen by facemask, then induction of anesthesia in all patients was  with the use of    i.v. fentanyl 2 micogram / kg, propofol 2 mg/ kg, , atracurium (0.5mg/kg) and  ventilated manually with sevoflorane  2 volume % ,oxygen 100% via a face mask  then  oral cuffed endotracheal tube was inserted  when the BIS value reached (40-60) which indicate optimal  hypnotic  state , anesthesia was maintained with oxygen 100%, sevoflurane (according to the depth of  anesthesia  guided by BIS to be between 40%-60%),muscle relaxation was maintained by additional doses of  atracurium, guided by peripheral nerve stimulator ( Life-Tech EZstimII), mechanical ventilation with maintenance of end tidal carbon dioxide 36-40mmHg,all patients received 15mg/kg Pefalgan and 2 micogram /kg fentanyl IV. A wide bore IV cannula was  also inserted. Hypotension defines as systolic blood pressure less than 90 mmHg was treated by decreasing the dexmedetomidine concentration and or sevoflorane concentration and ephedrine in 3 mg IV  increments of needed, bradycardia is defined  as heart rate less than 60 beat per minute  and  was managed by decreasing the dexmedetomidine concentration in D group   or atropine 0.5mg IV if needed.

At the end of surgery, 0.25% bupivacaine
was injected by the surgeon at the surgical wound, neuromuscular blockade was  reversed with IV neostigmine 0.04mg/kg  and atropine 0.02 mg/kg, the trachea was extubated when the patient respond to commands, all patients were transferred to PACU,  where they received oxygen via face mask 3-4 L/min and were  monitored.
The following parameters were evaluated and recorded by senior anesthesia resident unaware of the  study protocol:
1.	Patientss characteristics : age, sex, height, weight, ASA physical status and duration of  surgery.

2.	Heart rate, systolic and diastolic arterial blood pressure, arterial oxygen saturation (SpO2): before induction, after induction of anesthesia, then every 15 minutes  intraoperative.



3.	Volume of blood loss (ml) :in the surgical swabs and suction bottle 

4.	Laboratory Hb and hematocrit concentration :(Pre, intra and immediate post-operative)
5.	Number of  units PRBCs transfused 
6.	Urine output (ml) 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>paper sent for evalution</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>research ethical comittee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>benisuef university faculty of medecine
(FMBSU) 
egypt,



 -,mokbel,mohamad anwar hassan street, 62511

</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/03/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>17/03/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Egypt</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/365983-protocol 2.docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/365983-ethical aproval.docx</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>doaa rashwan</name>
      <address> doaa rashwan   egypt
 benisuef governerate mokbel

egypt,

benisuef university,faculty of medicine

 -,mokbel,mohamad anwar hassan street, 62511

</address>
      <phone>+2020822318605</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>doaa_rashwan2007@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>doaa rashwan</name>
      <address> doaa rashwan    egypt benisuef governerate mokbel
egypt,

benisuef university,faculty of medicine

 -,mokbel,mohamad anwar hassan street, 62511

</address>
      <phone>+20822318605</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>doaa_rashwan2007@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>doaa rashwan</name>
      <address> doaa rashwan   egypt
 benisuef governerate 


benisuef university,faculty of medicine

 -,mokbel,mohamad anwar hassan street, 62511

</address>
      <phone>+20822318605</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>doaa_rashwan@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>doaa rashwan</name>
      <address>egypt</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>doaa_rashwan2007@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>