<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370266">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/03/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/03/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000301460p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of automated control of oxygen therapy in extremely preterm infants: the SCION trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of automated control of oxygen therapy in extremely preterm infants: the SCION trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1180-3867</utrn>
    <trialacronym>SCION Trial</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NHMRC APP1128104</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Extremely premature birth</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Respiratory insufficiency of prematurity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Oxidative stress of prematurity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Complications of newborn</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Automated control of inspired oxygen therapy will be administered using a custom-built device incorporating a novel, adaptive and intuitive control algorithm (VDL1.1.). This device receives SpO2 input from an oximeter, compares the value with the midpoint of the desired SpO2 range, and provides an output, which is an updated value for FiO2. In subjects randomised to automated control, this device will be applied before 48 hours of life (i.e. within 24 hours of randomisation) and used until 36 weeks post-menstrual age or until respiratory support has ceased. The SpO2 target range will be 90-94%. Compliance with automated control will be monitored by local research personnel. </interventions>
    <comparator>Manual control of inspired oxygen therapy will be by bedside clinical staff, aiming to keep SpO2 in the target range (90-94%). This is the usual approach to SpO2 targeting, and will continue until 36 weeks post-menstrual age, or for as long as respiratory support is required.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Eupoxia - proportion of time with oxygen saturation (SpO2) in the desired target range, or above the desired target range when no supplemental oxygen is being administered. This is assessed by analysis of data received from the pulse oximeter at a sampling frequency of 1 Hz.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout the period from birth to 36 weeks post-menstrual age.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of time in various degrees of hypoxia (SpO2 &lt;80%, 80-84%, 85-89%), assessed by analysis of data received from the pulse oximeter at a sampling frequency of 1 Hz.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout the period from birth to 36 weeks post-menstrual age.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of time in degrees of hyperoxia when in oxygen (SpO2 &gt;96%, &gt;98%), assessed by analysis of data received from the pulse oximeter at a sampling frequency of 1 Hz.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout the period from birth to 36 weeks post-menstrual age.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of episodes per hour of prolonged hypoxia and hyperoxia (&gt;=30 and &gt;=60 sec), assessed by analysis of data received from the pulse oximeter at a sampling frequency of 1 Hz.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout the period from birth to 36 weeks post-menstrual age.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of manual FiO2 adjustments per 24 hours, assessed by analysis of data received from an oxygen analyser at a sampling frequency of 1 Hz.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout the period from birth to 36 weeks post-menstrual age.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of overshoot episodes (hypoxic event followed by prolonged hyperoxia), assessed by analysis of data received from the pulse oximeter at a sampling frequency of 1 Hz.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout the period from birth to 36 weeks post-menstrual age.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Frequency of hypoxia and bradycardia (HR &lt;100) after respiratory pauses and apnoea, assessed by analysis of data received from the pulse oximeter and a cardiorespiratory monitor at a sampling frequency of 1 Hz.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout the period from birth to 36 weeks post-menstrual age.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Markers of oxidative damage, measured by assay of 8-hydroxydeoxyguanosine, malondialdehyde, and protein carbonyl content in serum. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 1, 7, 28 and at 36 weeks post-menstrual age</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma VEGF concentration</outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 1, 7, 28 and at 36 weeks post-menstrual age</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Survival to 40 weeks PMA free of bronchopulmonary dysplasia (BPD), necrotizing enterocolitis (NEC) and retinopathy of prematurity (ROP), assessed by review in patient records and intensive care charts.</outcome>
      <timepoint>40 weeks post-menstrual age.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In hospital mortality</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days, 40 week post-menstrual age and throughout hospitalisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>BPD (physiological and clinical definitions), assessed by review of intensive care charts including documentation of results of air trial if necessary. </outcome>
      <timepoint>36 weeks post-menstrual age</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Necrotising enterocolitis Stage IIb or greater, assessed by review of medical records and operative notes.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout hospitalisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Retinopathy &gt; stage 2 in at least one eye, assessed by trained ophthalmologist.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>40 weeks post-menstrual age.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Retinopathy requiring laser therapy or bevacizumab, assessed by trained ophthalmologist.</outcome>
      <timepoint>40 weeks post-menstrual age.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severe intraventricular haemorrhage (grades III and IV), assessed by serial cranial ultrasound examination.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout hospitalisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Other complications of prematurity, assessed by review of medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout hospitalisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disability free survival, assessed by medical examination and psychometric assessment using the Bayley III developmental assessment tool.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years post-menstrual age</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Moderate-severe cerebral palsy, assessed by medical assessment with determination of the gross motor function classification system.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years post-menstrual age</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive function (&lt;2SD below mean), medical examination and psychometric assessment using the Bayley III developmental assessment tool.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years post-menstrual age</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Visual disturbance, corrected vision worse than 6/60 in better eye, assessed by ophthalmologic and optometric examination.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years post-menstrual age</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Gestation at birth 23 weeks 0 days to 27 weeks 6 days by best obstetric estimate.
Age &lt;24 hours, and managed in room air or supplemental oxygen.
Signed parental consent.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>24</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Hours</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Withdrawal of active treatment being considered.
Congenital anomaly likely to adversely affect outcome.
Lack of availability of automated control device or study personnel.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The randomisation procedure will be by central randomisation using a web-based randomisation server. </concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated randomisation sequence from randomly permuted blocks, stratified by study centre and by gestation (23-25 weeks and 26-27 weeks).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Statistical analysis will follow standard methods for randomised trials, with the primary analysis being by intention to treat. For continuous outcomes, including the primary outcome, comparison will be of differences between mean values, using linear regression models for stratification adjustments. For dichotomous outcomes, proportions will be compared using the odds ratio with 95% CI, obtained from a logistic regression analysis.  

Sample size has been calculated in relation to the primary outcome of eupoxia time throughout the intervention period. In our recent study of automated control in 20 infants, mean eupoxia time during manual control was 56%, with standard deviation (SD) 11%. In other studies variability in eupoxia has been greater (SD up to 16%), and an SD of 16% will be assumed. An absolute increase in eupoxia time of 8% (as was achieved in the largest published study of automated control) would represent a clinically significant benefit, and one that could have the potential to alter outcomes for extremely preterm infants. Detecting an improvement of this magnitude with 90% power and a = 0.05 (two-sided) would require 86 infants per group, which will be increased to 90 per group (180 subjects in total) to account for withdrawals and incomplete data. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/01/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>180</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>TAS</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Hobart Hospital - Hobart</hospital>
    <postcode>7000 - Hobart</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Menzies Institute for Medical Research, University of Tasmania</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Liverpool St
Hobart
TAS 7000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
 16 Marcus Clarke Street
 Canberra ACT 2601 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>N/A</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>N/A</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This research proposal seeks funding to conduct a vanguard randomised controlled trial (RCT) of automated control of oxygen therapy in preterm infants &lt;28 weeks gestation in Australian neonatal Units. Our hypothesis is that automated oxygen control using a control device developed by our research team can produce a sustained improvement in time in the desired oxygen saturation (SpO2) target range over many weeks of hospitalisation, reduce blood markers of oxygen toxicity and oxygen debt, and thus have the potential to improve outcome. 

Background
Almost all extremely preterm infants &lt;28 weeks gestation receive supplemental oxygen during their first hospitalisation, with fraction of inspired oxygen (FiO2) titrated to target a preferred SpO2 range. Both hypoxia and hyperoxia are known to be associated with adverse outcomes, including mortality, chronic lung disease, retinopathy and necrotizing enterocolitis. SpO2 targeting is, however, fraught with difficulty, with manual oxygen control targeting the desired SpO2 range less than 50% of the time. Automated oxygen control may offer a solution, and existing control algorithms increase time in target range by around 10% in short term studies. Whether automated control can produce sustained improvements in SpO2 targeting, and do so in all individuals, are unknown. 

Research Proposal
Preterm infants 23+0 to 27+6 weeks gestation (N=180) will be randomly allocated to automated oxygen control, or standard manual control, from early life until 36 weeks post-menstrual age (PMA). Automated control will be applied for as much of the time as possible, and with all manner of respiratory support modalities. FiO2 and SpO2 will be logged continuously, and blood markers of oxygen toxicity and debt examined at days 1, 7, 28 and at 36 weeks PMA. Time in the SpO2 target range (primary outcome), blood markers of oxidation and hypoxia, survival and complications of prematurity will be compared between groups.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Tasmania Health and Medical Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Tasmania
Private Bag 01
Hobart Tas 7001
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/07/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Dargaville</name>
      <address>Dept. of Paediatrics
Royal Hobart Hospital
Liverpool St
Hobart
TAS 7000</address>
      <phone>+61362227546</phone>
      <fax>+61362227381</fax>
      <email>peter.dargaville@dhhs.tas.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Dargaville</name>
      <address>Dept. of Paediatrics
Royal Hobart Hospital
Liverpool St
Hobart
TAS 7000</address>
      <phone>+61362227546</phone>
      <fax>+61362227381</fax>
      <email>peter.dargaville@dhhs.tas.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Dargaville</name>
      <address>Dept. of Paediatrics
Royal Hobart Hospital
Liverpool St
Hobart
TAS 7000</address>
      <phone>+61362227546</phone>
      <fax>+61362227381</fax>
      <email>peter.dargaville@dhhs.tas.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Dargaville</name>
      <address>Dept. of Paediatrics
Royal Hobart Hospital
Liverpool St
Hobart
TAS 7000</address>
      <phone>+61362227546</phone>
      <fax>+61362227381</fax>
      <email>peter.dargaville@dhhs.tas.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>