<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366607">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/06/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/09/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000974606</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Tools for resilience: A mobile phone and web-based intervention for improving mental wellbeing and reducing distress in adolescents and young adults with Type 1 diabetes
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In adolescents and adults with diabetes, does a mobile phone and web intervention, compared with a placebo intervention, improve mental wellbeing and reduce distress?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U111-1158-4960</utrn>
    <trialacronym>FIDO - Feeling in charge of Diabetes Online</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Type 1 diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants randomised to the intervention condition will have full use of a freely available mobile phone and web intervention called 'myCompass' for seven weeks.  The intervention has been developed as a self-help intervention with no therapist input for people with mild-to-moderate levels of depression, anxiety and stress.

The intervention allows participants to: (a) monitor moods, symptoms and/or behaviours (e.g. physical activity, depression, anxiety, irritability, sleep, alcohol use, user-defined health signs); (b) schedule short message service (SMS) or email self-monitoring reminders; (c) receive and print graphical feedback about monitoring which is presented alongside meaningful contextual information (i.e., where they were, what they were doing and who they were with at the time of rating); and (d) receive helpful facts, mental health-care tips or motivational statements by SMS or email.

In addition, myCompass offers a number of psychological modules for users to complete via the internet.  Modules derive from Cognitive Behaviour Therapy, as well as Interpersonal Psychotherapy, Problem Solving Therapy and Positive Psychology, and cover topics such as Solving Problems, Managing Fear and Anxiety, Tackling Unhelpful Thinking, Managing Loss and Major Life Change.  Each module comprises three 10-minute sessions and has practice tasks assigned.  Participants may use (or not use) the intervention at their discretion.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants randomised to the placebo intervention will use an Internet delivered lifestyle intervention.  Developed by the research team to match myCompass on duration and mode of delivery, the program also contains practice activities, home tasks and factual SMS messages to replicate the interactivity of myCompass, but has no therapeutic content.  Topics will include skin care, mobile phone use, home environment, casual work, healthy food and relationships.  Participants may use (or not use) the full intervention at their discretion across a seven week period.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychological wellbeing, assessed using the Warwick-Edinburgh Mental Well-being Scale 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention only</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>General psychological distress and functioning (depression, anxiety), as assessed by the Patient Health Questionnaire 9 (PHQ9) and the Generalized Anxiety Disorder-7 (GAD7)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention only</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diabetes-specific distress, assessed using the Diabetes Distress Scale </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention, 3 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diabetes self-care, assessed by Summary of Diabetes Self-Care Activities scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention only</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mental health self-efficacy, as assesssed by the Mental Health Self-Efficacy Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention only</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Work and social functioning, as assessed by Work and Social Adjustment Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention, 3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported glycaemic control, assessed by the Hyperglycaemia and Hypoglycaemia scales</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention only</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>* Have at least mild diabetes-related distress, as measured by the Diabetes Distress Scale, and/or
* Have at least mild depressive symptoms, as measured by the Patient Health Questionnaire, PHQ-9; and 
* Be aged 16 to 25 years; 
* Have T1D diabetes, diagnosed by an endocrinologist;  
* Have access to an internet-enabled mobile phone and computer/tablet; and
* Provide informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>25</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>* Inability to read English with ease; 
* Severe mental health problems (i.e., psychotic symptoms); 
* Non-residence in Australia; and 
* Previous experience with the myCompass program.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be enrolled into the study following completion of an online screening tool.  People who screen as eligible will be automatically directed to the online baseline questionnaire.  Researchers will receive an email confirmation once a baseline questionnaire is complete, and participant information will be downloaded and de-identified (i.e., ID numbers allocated).  ID numbers will be forwarded to a person outside the research team for randomisation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerised random number generation.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Analyses will be based on the intention-to-treat sample and will used mixed modelling techniques to deal with missing data issues that arise as a consequence of study attrition.

The RCT of myCompass yielded an average between-group effect size for the intervention on symptom outcomes of 0.5.   Assuming an attrition rate of 50%, a total sample of 240 participants (120 per arm) is the minimum required to detect between-group differences on self-report outcomes of .5 standard deviations with 80% power.  Nevertheless, we will recruit 280 participants (140 per arm) as we have pilot data showing that this will enable us to detect a clinically meaningful change in HbA1c (0.3 - 0.5%) with power at 80% (assuming standard deviations between 1 and 1.3).
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>22/09/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>29/10/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>13/11/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>280</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>62</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Terminated</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Darlinghurst) - Darlinghurst</hospital>
    <hospital>Westmead Hospital - Westmead</hospital>
    <hospital>Sydney Children's Hospital - Randwick</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Black Dog Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Hospital Road
Randwick  NSW  2031</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Rotary Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 3455 Parramatta NSW 2124</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Young people with Type 1 diabetes are at greater risk of mental health problems and poor psychological wellbeing than their counterparts without diabetes.  Young people are high users of mobile and internet-technology, and increasingly use these tools for health information and support.

The projects primary objective is to test the hypotheses that psychological well-being will be significantly improved, and that symptoms of psychological (i.e., depression, anxiety and stress) and diabetes-related distress will be significantly reduced, in participants who use a mobile phone and web-based mental health intervention, myCompass, for seven weeks compared with those in a placebo control group.

The projects secondary objective is to test the hypothesis that diabetes self-care, work and social functioning, glycaemic control (glycosylated haemoglobin, HbA1c), and quality of life will be significantly improved for participants who receive the myCompass intervention.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://fido.ehat.com.au/</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Clarke et al., A mobile phone and web-based intervention for improving mental wellbeing in young people with type 1 diabetes: Design of a randomised controlled trial. JMIR Res Protoc 2015, 4:e50
doi:10.2196/resprot.4032
http://dx.doi.org/10.2196/resprot.4032</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>390 Victoria Street
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/04/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/SVH/31</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/02/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Judy Proudfoot</name>
      <address>Black Dog Institute
Hospital Road
Randwick  NSW  2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9382 3767</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.proudfoot@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Janine Clarke</name>
      <address>Black Dog Institute
Hospital Road
Randwick  NSW  2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9382 3719</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>janine.clarke@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Janine Clarke</name>
      <address>Black Dog Institute
Hospital Road
Randwick  NSW  2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9382 3719</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>janine.clarke@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Janine Clarke</name>
      <address>Black Dog Institute
Hospital Road
Randwick  NSW  2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9382 3719</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>janine.clarke@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>