<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362654">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/10/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/10/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001126808</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Physiotherapy versus corticosteroid injection for chronic lateral hip pain: a randomized clinical trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>To compare the short and long term effectiveness of a specific physiotherapy programme and corticosteroid injection in the management of people with gluteal muscle tendinopathy.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1131-9517</utrn>
    <trialacronym>The LEAP [LatErAl hiP pain] Project</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Gluteal tendinopathy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Arm 1: Eight Week Physiotherapy Exercise Intervention. This group will receive detailed advice and education on tendon care (handouts, DVD and oral explanation by the treating physiotherapist), as well as a comprehensive exercise programme, to be performed both at home daily and in the form of individual supervised exercise sessions at the physiotherapy clinic. The exercises will include functional retraining, targeted strengthening for the hip and thigh muscles, as well as exercises using Pilates equipment (i.e. a Reformer). The participant will attend an initial 1 hour physiotherapy session in Week 1, where assessment, education and training of the exercises will occur. In Week 2, the participant will attend a half hour session to reinforce all information, assess progress and technique and continue exercise progressions. For the remaining 6 weeks, the participant will attend two half hour sessions per week at the physiotherapy clinic for re-assessment of responses and progress, and progression of the exercise programme as able. There will be 14 sessions in total. The prescribed home exercise programme will consist of no more than four exercises, in order to facilitate compliance, and will be performed daily, taking no more than 15 to 20 minutes. Response to the exercises will be re-assessed at each physiotherapy session in order to modify and progress the home exercises as appropriate to the individual.

Arm 2: A single ultrasound guided Corticosteroid injection (Celestone (1 ml) or Kenacort (1 ml ), with Bupivacaine (2 ml)) around the tendons at the hip, performed under ultrasound guidance by an experienced sports physician or radiologist, as well as receiving basic advice on tendon care.

Arm 3: Patients will attend a single half hour session with a trial physiotherapist of their choice, where they will be advised to adopt a wait and see policy in which they will be given advice on how to take care of their condition themselves and assurance that the condition will resolve over time. Taking over the counter pain relief medication will be permitted should the patient feel it is required. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Arm 3 of the study is a Wait and See approach, in which no active intervention is involved. This is considered to be the control.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain Numerical Rating Scale: An 11 point scale
anchored by no pain at all at 0 and worst pain
imaginable at 10 will be used to rate the worst
and average level of pain severity the patient
experienced in the past week.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4 weeks, 8 weeks, 12 weeks, 26 weeks and 52 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Global Rating of Change Score -  an 11-point scale in which the participant is asked to rate their perceived overall change in condition of their hip from the time that they began the study until the present, as Worse, No Change, or Better</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks, 8 weeks, 12 weeks, 26 weeks and 52 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Lateral Hip Pain Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4 weeks, 8 weeks, 12 weeks, 26 weeks and 52 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Patient Specific Functional Scale. Patients are asked to identify up to five activities they are unable to perform or are having difficulty with because of their problem. They are then asked to rate the current level of difficulty associated with each activity on an 11-point scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4 weeks, 8 weeks, 12 weeks, 26 weeks and 52 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The EuroQOL questionnaire. The participant indicates in tick boxes which statements about mobility, personal care, usual activities, pain and anxiety/depression best describe their health status.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4 weeks, 8 weeks, 12 weeks, 26 weeks and 52 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Active painfree hip abductor muscle strength, measured using a hand-held dynamometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Active Lag of hip abduction, measured with an inclinometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Pain Catastrophising Scale (labelled the Pain Thoughts Scale), The Patient Health Questionnaire-9, the Pain Self-Efficacy Questionnaire, the Active Australia Survey are incorporated into one booklet to explore the psychological aspects of chronic lateral hip pain</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4 weeks, 8 weeks, 12 weeks, 26 weeks, 52 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Economic costs data, obtained from a modified version of the Osteoarthritis Costs and Consequences Questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>VISA-G: is an equivalent to the other VISA questionnaires (for Achilles and Patellar tendinopathy), which consists of 8 items, covering pain and function. Total possible score is 100, which represents a perfect score.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4 weeks, 8 weeks, 12 weeks, 26 weeks, 52 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Subjects will be included in the study if they experience lateral hip pain, worst over the area of the greater trochanter, which has been present for a minimum of three months.  There should be tenderness on palpation of the greater trochanter and reproduction of lateral hip pain on at least one of 5 diagnostic clinical tests, as well as demonstrated tendon pathology on MRI.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>35</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Subjects will be excluded if they have any significant groin pain or known hip joint pathology, significant lower back pain, or known lumbar pathology, previous surgery to the back or hips, any other lower limb pathology that may impact on their ability to participate in an exercise programme, any systemic diseases affecting the muscular or nervous system, any systemic inflammatory diseases, presence of tumour, any factors that would preclude them from having an Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) (e.g., pregnancy, pacemaker, claustrophobia), previous cortisone injection around the greater trochanter (lateral hip) in the last 12 months, or physiotherapy intervention for lateral hip pain in the last 3 months, any allergy to corticosteroids, any phobia of needles, and obesity (BMI&gt;30).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Recruitment via advertisements in local newspapers, medical and physiotherapy clinics, and flyers. Respondents will undergo an initial phone screening and then a physical examination, as well as MRI/XRay investigation to confirm diagnosis before inclusion. Concealed allocation by a computerised randomisation schedule developed by an off-site independent central trial unit (Queensland
Clinical Trial Centre)</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated randomisation schedule</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Pragmatic, single-blind, multi-centre randomised controlled trial</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>4/04/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>15/10/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>201</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>205</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>27/10/2016</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>9/11/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>4000</postcode>
    <postcode>3000</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Bill Vicenzino</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
Therapies Building 84A
Therapies Road
University of Queensland
St Lucia QLD 4072</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council Programme Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Kim Bennell</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Centre for Health, Exercise and Sports Medicine,
School of Health Sciences,
University of Melbourne,
Berkeley St.,
Parkville, Victoria, 3052</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Lateral hip pain is very common in the community and particularly in active women. Some studies state that 1 in 4 women over 55 have this problem. The pain at the side of the hip, or lateral gluteal region, can be very debilitating and often affects sleep, walking, going up stairs, prolonged sitting and getting up after sitting. The management of lateral hip pain is difficult and the pain can persist for months or even years. Previously this was incorrectly diagnosed as bursitis, but recent medical imaging research using ultrasound and MRI has shown the problem is usually due to tendinopathy or a tear in the tendons of the muscles at the side of the hip called the gluteus medius and gluteus minimus. The bursitis (a collection of fluid) appears to be secondary to the tendon injury. Common approaches to management include a corticosteroid injection or a physiotherapy program, yet there is a lack of quality research regarding which is more effective, or if in fact these treatments are any better than adopting a wait and see approach to allow the condition to resolve spontaneously. The purpose of this study is to compare the effects of three possible approaches to treating long standing lateral hip pain: (a) a single cortisone injection, (b) an eight-week physiotherapy exercise program and (c) adopting a wait and see approach. The results will contribute to the development of improved and more effective exercise treatment programs to manage this condition.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Grimaldi A, Mellor R, Nicolson P, Hodges P, Bennell K, Vicenzino B. Utility of clinical tests to diagnose MRI-confirmed gluteal tendinopathy in patients presenting with lateral hip pain. Br J Sports Med. 2016 Sep 15. pii: bjsports-2016-096175. doi: 10.1136/bjsports-2016-096175 [Epub ahead of print]
Mellor R, Grimaldi A, Wajswelner H, Hodges P, Abbot JH, Bennell K, Vicenzino B. Exercise and load modification versus corticosteroid injection versus wait and see for persistent gluteus medius/minimus tendinopathy (the LEAP trial): a protocol for a randomized clinical trial. BMC Musculoskeletal Disord. 2016 Apr 30: 17(1): 196. doi: 10.1186/s12891-016-1043-6.
Grimaldi A, Mellor R, Hodges P, Bennell K, Wajswelner H, Vicenzino B. Gluteal Tendinopathy: A review of mechanisms, assessment and management. Sports Medicine. 2015 Aug 4(8): 1107-19. doi: 10.1007/s40279-015-0336-5.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Medical Research Ethics Committee (MREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The University of Queensland
Cumbrae-Stewart Building
Research Road
Brisbane Qld 4072 Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/10/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2012000930</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/07/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Bill Vicenzino</name>
      <address>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
Therapies Building 84A
Therapies Road
University of Queensland
St Lucia QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 2781</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 33651622</fax>
      <email>b.vicenzino@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Bill Vicenzino</name>
      <address>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
Therapies Building 84A
Therapies Road
University of Queensland
St Lucia QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 2781</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 33651622</fax>
      <email>b.vicenzino@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Bill Vicenzino</name>
      <address>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
Therapies Building 84A
Therapies Road
University of Queensland
St Lucia QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 2781</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 33651622</fax>
      <email>b.vicenzino@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Bill Vicenzino</name>
      <address>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences 
Therapies Building 84A 
Therapies Road
University of Queensland
 St Lucia QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 2781</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>b.vicenzino@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>