<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371007">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/07/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000906459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can transcranial direct current stimulation enhance cognition in older adults?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Can transcranial direct current stimulation enhance cognition in older adults?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>cognition and ageing</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>tDCS involves the application of a very weak electrical current applied using two surface electrodes (anode and cathode) to the scalp. tDCS has been shown to alter the excitability of brain cells by shifting their membrane potentials in a de- or hyperpolarising direction; thus making the brain cells more or less likely to fire. Stimulation of brain cells under the anode appears to increase brain activity whereas stimulation under the cathode generally has the opposite effect.  Stimulation will be delivered using the StarStim system which allows for programming of active and sham tDCS. Active tDCS will be delivered using standard EEG size electrodes placed within the Starstim system cap. The anode, or activating, electrode will be placed over F3 according to the 10-20 international system for EEG placement, which has been determined to be an accurate estimate of the left DLPFC. The cathodal, or reference, electrode will be placed over the right supraorbital space. Stimulation will be applied at 0.0057 ma/cm for 20mins. Each 20 minute stimulation will be separated by an hour break and a total of sixteen stimulation sessions will be completed within a 2 week period (Monday to Friday). Participants will receive a maximum of two 20 minute stimulation sessions within 24 hours. A/Prof Kate Hoy determines the scheduling of the sessions over the two week period according to her experience and expertise developed through 13 years of co-ordinating brain stimulation clinical trails of this nature.</interventions>
    <comparator>Sham (placebo) tDCS is achieved by switching off stimulation after approx. 30s; which occurs within the software of the Starstim system allowing for administrator and participant blinding. There is no evidence that 30 seconds of tDCS induces any changes in the brain. The provision of stimulation for 30 seconds allows participants to experience the initial physical sensations of tDCS, which typically fade after 30seconds, thus providing a robust sham.  This is a standard method of blinding for tDCS.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>level of cognitive impairment will be assessed using the Mini Mental State Examination (MMSE)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and endpoint (i.e. pre and post sixteen sessions of tDCS) as well as at one month post final tDCS treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Global Deterioration Scale (GDS) will be used to gauge the stage of cognitive decline of participants. It is a tool used to assess level of cognitive impairment in dementia and is separated into 7 stages. Stages 1-3 are pre-dementia and stages 4-7 are the dementia stages.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and endpoint (i.e. pre and post sixteen sessions of tDCS) as well as at one month post final tDCS treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Functional Activities Questionnaire (FAQ) will be used to determine cognitive decline ine level of ability to carry out everyday tasks such as paying bills, keeping track of current events or shopping alone.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and endpoint (i.e. pre and post sixteen sessions of tDCS) as well as at one month post final tDCS treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>TMS-EEG data:

TMS-EEG is performed by stimulating the scalp over the DLPFC while simultaneously recording brain activity via surrounding EEG electrodes. The TMS pulse produces a neurophysiological response in the underlying cortex, referred to as a TMS evoked potential (TEP), which is recorded on EEG and the TEP amplitude gives an index of cortical excitability.</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and endpoint (i.e. pre and post 16 sessions of tDCS stimulation)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>episodic memory will be assessed using the Rey Auditory Verbal Learning Test (RAVLT)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and endpoint (i.e. pre and post sixteen sessions of tDCS) as well as at one month post final tDCS treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Episodic memory will be assessed using the Brief Visuospatial Memory Test (BVMT-R)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and endpoint (i.e. pre and post sixteen sessions of tDCS) as well as at one month post final tDCS treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Episodic memory will be assessed using the Rey Complex Figure Task</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and endpoint (i.e. pre and post sixteen sessions of tDCS) as well as at one month post final tDCS treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Working memory will be assessed using the forward and backward components of the digit span task from the Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale battery.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and endpoint (i.e. pre and post sixteen sessions of tDCS) as well as at one month post final tDCS treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Working memory will be assessed using an arithmetic task from the Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale battery.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and endpoint (i.e. pre and post sixteen sessions of tDCS) as well as at one month post final tDCS treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Executive functioning will be assessed using the Stroop test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and endpoint (i.e. pre and post sixteen sessions of tDCS) as well as at one month post final tDCS treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Executive functioning will be assessed using a verbal fluency task. Namely, the Controlled Oral Word Association Test (COWAT)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and endpoint (i.e. pre and post sixteen sessions of tDCS) as well as at one month post final tDCS treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Processing speed will be measured using a digit symbol coding task</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and endpoint (i.e. pre and post sixteen sessions of tDCS) as well as at one month post final tDCS treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Processing speed will be assessed using a trail making task </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and endpoint (i.e. pre and post sixteen sessions of tDCS) as well as at one month post final tDCS treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The CogState is a composite measure of cognitive functioning.  Subtests that measure reaction time and associative learning will be used.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and endpoint (i.e. pre and post sixteen sessions of tDCS) as well as at one month post final tDCS treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- competent to consent based on their ability to provide a spontaneous narrative description of the key elements of the study, as assessed by a clinical staff member independent of the research project
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- have a DSM-IV history of substance abuse or dependence in the last 6 months
- have a concomitant major and unstable medical, psychiatric or neurological illness
- are pregnant
- are currently taking medications shown to interfere with the effects of tDCS; namely benzodiazepines
- are professional drivers
- have any contraindications to brain stimulation ass assessed using the TMS/tDCS safety screen</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is concealed; by the research assistant contacting the principal investigator who has a computer generated random sequence for treatment groups after the participant is deemed eligible and has consented for the study. </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. Microsoft Excel)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/12/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>A/Prof Kate Hoy</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Monash Alfred Psychiatry Research Centre (MAPrc), Monash University
Level 4,
607 St Kilda Road,
Melbourne,
3004,
VIC</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Monash University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Monash Alfred Psychiatry Research Centre (MAPrc), Monash University
Level 4
607 St Kilda Rd
Melbourne,
Vic 3004</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>tDCS has been shown to have a positive effect on cognition in older adults. However, to date, there has been very limited investigation of the effects of repeated sessions of tDCS on age related cognitive decline.  The current research will investigate the effects of repeated sessions of tDCS on cognition in healthy older adults. These investigations are critical in order to establish the potential of this approach to reduce symptoms of cognitive decline, or even to delay further progression. In addition, an understanding of the neurobiological mechanisms of how tDCS may work to ameliorate brain activity underlying cognitive decline is lacking and needed in order to appropriately assess the relevance of this technique to this population.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Alfred Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ground Floor
Linay Pavilion
The Alfred Hospital
55 Commercial Rd
Melbourne 
VIC 3004,</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/06/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>257/16</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/06/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Kate Hoy</name>
      <address>Monash Alfred Psychiatry research centre (MAPrc)
Level 4
607 St Kilda Rd
Melbourne
Vic, 3004</address>
      <phone>	+613 9076 5034</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kate.hoy@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Kate Hoy</name>
      <address>Monash Alfred Psychiatry research centre (MAPrc)
Level 4
607 St Kilda Rd
Melbourne
Vic, 3004</address>
      <phone>	+613 9076 5034</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kate.hoy@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Kate Hoy</name>
      <address>Monash Alfred Psychiatry research centre (MAPrc)
Level 4
607 St Kilda Rd
Melbourne
Vic, 3004</address>
      <phone>	+613 9076 5034</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kate.hoy@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kirsten Gainsford</name>
      <address>Monash Alfred Psychiatry research centre (MAPrc)
Level 4
607 St Kilda Rd
Melbourne
Vic, 3004</address>
      <phone>+613 9076 6592</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kirsten.gainsford@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>