<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335186">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/02/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/03/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000184077</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Coherex-PFO-Sleep Hypoxia: A multi-center study to determine the response to closure of patent foramen ovale (PFO) with the Coherex FlatStentTM EF PFO Closure System (EF is part of the trade mark name and stands for Enhanced Foam) in patients diagnosed with PFO and significant oxygen desaturation in obstructive sleep apnea (OSA)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A feasibility study of 30-50 patients to evaluate the clinical response to Patent Foramen Ovale (PFO) closure using Coherex FlatStentTM EF PFO Closure System (EF is part of the trade mark name and stands for Enhanced Foam) in Obstructive Sleep Apnea (OSA) patients with significant right-to-left shunting and oxygen desaturation as demonstrated during sleep studies.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>COHEREX-PFO-SLEEP-HYPOXIA</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Significant oxygen desaturation associated with right-to-left shunts through a PFO in Obstructive Sleep Apnea(OSA) patients</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Coherex FlatStentTM EF Patent Foramen Ovale (PFO) Closure System is a permanent implant placed percutaneously by an interventional cardiologist into a patent foramen ovale to close the congenital defect.  The procedure takes approximately 30 minutes.  Patients will be observed for 6 months after the permanent device placement.</interventions>
    <comparator>No Comparator.  This is a registry feasibility study.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome will be measured by the percentage of high-risk OSA patients enrolled in the study with a right-to-left shunt whose oxygen desaturation index demonstrates improvement during polysomnogram (PSG) after PFO closure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>A polysomnogram (PSG) will be done at 90 days post procedure if PFO is confirmed closed by transcranial doppler (TCD).  If not closed, a PSG will be done at 180 days post procedure</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse events at 90 days post intervention
This will include observed or self reported events that are adverse changes in the patients baseline health status.  All adverse events will be recorded in the patient file.

Possible adverse effects include, but are not limited to:Death, Acute myocardial infarction, Air, tissue, or thrombotic embolization, Hemorrhage or hematoma, Stroke/cerebrovascular accident or transient ischemic attacks, Arrhythmias, including ventricular fibrillation and ventricular tachycardia, Drug reactions, allergic reaction to contrast media or device components, Device embolization or migration, Amputation, Endocarditis, Cardiac tissue trauma, Renal insufficiency, kidney failure, Bleeding complications requiring transfusion, Hypotension/hypertension, Damage to implanted stent, Patient infection, Vessel spasm, Vessel dissection</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patient follow up at 90 days post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvement of right to left shunt and rates of closure of the PFO as assessed by contrast transesophogeal echocardiography(view of the heart through the esophagus using ultrasound).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patient follow up at 90 and 180 days post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Diagnosis of OSA and a polysomnogram within the past year that demonstrated an apnea index &gt; 20 seconds (AI20) of greater than 5 and an oxygen desaturation index &gt; 6% (ODI6) of greater than 5 associated with apnic events.  Patients willing to under go transcranial doppler (TCD) and demonstrates a Grade IV or Grade V right-to-left shunt.  Patients must demonstrate a PFO amenable to transcatheter closure with the Coherex FlatStentTM EF PFO Closure System.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Candidates will be excluded from the study if ANY of the following conditions apply: 1. Long-term requirement for anti-platelet therapy, anticoagulation, or coagulopathy. 2. Contraindication and/or allergy to aspirin, clopidogrel, Nitinol, Dacron, polyurethane, nickel, stainless steel or other stent materials. 3. Concurrent enrollment in another clinical study. 4. Body mass index &gt; 40. 5. Botox treatment within the past 90 days. 6. Other known structural heart disease, coronary artery disease, or atrial fibrillation. 7. Chronic liver disease, kidney disease, or organ failure. 8. Auto-immune disease. 9. Psychiatric illness, which in the investigators opinion, will interfere with completion of the study. 10. Degenerative neurologic disorders. 11. Any known active bacterial infection. 12. Malignancy or other illness with a life expectancy less than two years. 13. Pregnancy or desire to become pregnant during course of study. 14. Right-to-left shunt besides PFO detected prior to enrollment. 15.Uncontrolled hypertension defined as blood pressure greater than140/90 mmHg. 16. Immunosuppressive therapy. 17.Diabetes requiring insulin or blood glucose greater than 200 mg/deciliter on oral diabetic medications. 18. Concomitant pulmonary disorder (chronic obstructive pulmonary disorder [COPD], asthma, etc.) requiring treatment. 19. Any medical disorder that would interfere with study completion. 20. Known severe pulmonary hypertension (requiring medication). 21.Patients who have had a major stroke within the past two months or a minor stroke within the past two weeks (see National Institutes of Health (NIH) Stroke Scale). 22. Patients who require a transseptal puncture to access the left atrium. 23. Patients with known sustained arrhythmia.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Persons with OSA referred to investigators for PFO closure who meet inclusion/exclusion criteria will be invited to participate and be enrolled if the PFO size is appropriate for the use of the Coherex FlatStentTM EF PFO Closure System</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>12/08/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Frankfurt</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Paris</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Coherex Medical Inc.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>3598 West 1820 South Salt Lake City, UT 84104</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Coherex Medical Inc.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>3598 West 1820 South Salt Lake City, UT 84104</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The Coherex-PFO-Sleep Hypoxia is a multi-center study for up to 50 patients to determine the response to closure of patent foramen ovale (PFO) with the Coherex FlatStentTM EF PFO Closure System in patients diagnosed with PFO and significant oxygen desaturation in obstructive sleep apnea (OSA)</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Freiburger Ethik-Kommission International</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Mozartstrasse 21 79104 Freiburg</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/03/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>None</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/01/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Germany</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Randall K. Jones MD</name>
      <address>3598 West 1820 South 
Salt Lake City, Utah 84104</address>
      <phone>+1 (801) 433-9900</phone>
      <fax>+1 (801) 433-9901</fax>
      <email>rjones@coherex.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Randall K. Jones MD</name>
      <address>3598 West 1820 South 
Salt Lake City, Utah 84104</address>
      <phone>+1 (801) 433-9900</phone>
      <fax>+1 (801) 433-9901</fax>
      <email>rjones@coherex.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Randall K. Jones MD</name>
      <address>3598 West 1820 South 
Salt Lake City, Utah 84104</address>
      <phone>+1 (801) 433-9900</phone>
      <fax>+1 (801) 433-9901</fax>
      <email>rjones@coherex.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>