<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308013">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/06/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/07/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000644268</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of patellar tape on patellar malalignment and pain in people with patellofemoral osteoarthritis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of patellar tape on patellar malalignment and pain in people with patellofemoral osteoarthritis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Patellofemoral osteoarthritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>a) application of tape
Taping to correct patellar alignment was applied in a standardized manner by the same investigator who is an experienced physiotherapist. Where necessary, skin was shaved prior to tape application. Two pieces of rigid tape (Leuko Sportstape Premium Plus, Beiersdorf Australia Ltd) were used to apply a medial patellar glide, as well as a medial and superior tilt to the patellar. To unload the infrapatellar fat pad, another two pieces of tape were applied distal to the patella. Hypoallergenic tape (Fixomull (registered trademark) stretch, Beiersdorf Australia Ltd) was applied beneath the rigid tape to prevent skin irritation. Participants were asked to report any symptoms of skin irritation while they wore the tape, and the knee was inspected after the tape was removed.
b) tape was applied immediately prior to testing and worn only for the duration of testing (ie 30 - 60 minutes)
c) duration between intervention and control was 30 - 60 minutes</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator treatment was no tape. The duration between the two interventions was 30-60 minutes. Therefore, if a person was randomised to receive tape first, there was a 30-60 minute break between removal of tape and the control (no tape) testing; if a person was randomsied to the control condition (no tape) first, this was followed by a break of 30-60 iminutes before the tape was applied</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>patellar alignment, measured from axial scans of magnetic resonance imaging</outcome>
      <timepoint>immediately after application of tape and no tape</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>pain during squatting, measured on a 100mm visual analogue scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>immediately after application of tape and no tape</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>inclusion was based on: (i) history of knee pain in the preceding week on at least two of the following activities: stair ambulation, squatting, rising from sitting and locomotion (walking and/or jogging); (ii) average overall knee pain &gt;3 points on a 10 point numerical pain scale; (iii) primary area of pain described in the anterior or retropatellar regions; (iv) physical examination revealing tenderness in the peri-patellar region; and (v) radiographic evidence of either an osteophyte of severity at least grade 2, or joint space narrowing of at least grade 1 with concurrent grade 1 osteophyte(s) in the patellofemoral joint (PFJ) on skyline x-ray. Individuals with concomitant tibiofemoral joint (TFJ) osteoarthritis (OA) were included if the predominant source of symptoms was deemed to be from the PFJ.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(i) pain at a site distant to the patellar; (ii) concomitant injury or pathology in the lumbar spine, hip or other knee joint structures; (iii) history of fracture, arthroplasty or osteotomy of the knee or hip; (iv) inability to understand written and spoken English; (v) history of allergic reaction to tape; or (vi) contraindications for magnetic resonance (MR) imaging (eg implanted metal in vital organs).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>After consent, the investigator opened the envelope that indicated the order of the taping condition (tape, no tape).</concealment>
    <sequence>Sinple randomisation, computer generated</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>14</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Early Career Research Scheme</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Melbourne
Parkville, Victoria 3010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>ANZ Charitable Funds</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>ANZ Charitable Services
ANZ Executors &amp; Trustee Company Limited
GPO Box 389D, Melbourne, Victoria, 3001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Objective: Patellar taping is a conservative treatment that may reduce patellar malalignment and pain in people with patellofemoral (PFJ) osteoarthritis (OA). This study aimed to evaluate immediate effects of patellar taping on patellar alignment and pain in people with PFJ OA 
Methods: Patellar malalignment was measured from magnetic resonance (MR) (15 degress knee flexion) in 14 individuals with PFJ OA. In the PFJ OA group, MR data were collected in two randomly allocated conditions (tape; no tape). Patellar alignment indices were measured from de-identified axial scans by one examiner. Pain during squatting was recorded in the two conditions (tape; no tape).
Results:  In the PFJ OA group, patellar tape resulted in a significant lessening of lateral malalignment, with reduced lateral displacement (p = 0.028) and increased lateral patellar tilt angle (p &lt; 0.001). Mean pain during squatting decreased with patellar tape by 15 mm on a 100mm scale (p = 0.045). 
Conclusions: Patellar tape may reduce malalignment and pain associated with PFJ OA.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>n/a</trialwebsite>
    <publication>one publication under review</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Melbourne Research Office
University of Melbourne, VIC, 3010
Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/07/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>0714623.1</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kay Crossley</name>
      <address>Melbourne School of Engineering
Department of Mechanical Engineering
The University of Melbourne
Victoria, 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 383448646</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.crossley@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kay Crossley</name>
      <address>Melbourne School of Engineering
Department of Mechanical Engineering
The University of Melbourne
Victoria
3010</address>
      <phone>+61 383448646</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.crossley@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kay Crossley</name>
      <address>Melbourne School of Engineering
Department of Mechanical Engineering
The University of Melbourne
Victoria, 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 383448646</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.crossley@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>