<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="807">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/09/2005</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/09/2005</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12605000566639</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Strength training for people with Parkinson's disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of a randomized trial of community-based progressive strength training for people with Parkinson's disease</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Parkinson's disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Parkinson's disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is a 10-week program of progressive resistance strength training based upon the recommendations of the American College of Sports Medicine (American College of Sport Medicine ACSM Position Stand 2002). The resistance exercise program is based on the Strong for Life protocol described by Jette et al. (1999). A physiotherapist will assess the participants' ability to complete the exercise program as described and will modify the exercises as appropriate. Participants will attend an exercise group twice per week for 10-weeks. In addition, the participants will be asked to complete a set progressive resistance strengthening program once per week in their own hom</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Muscle Strength
Maximum force generated during an isometric muscle contraction will be measured using a hand-held dynamometer to assess the strength of the muscle group: plantar flexors.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Muscle Strength
Maximum force generated during an isometric muscle contraction will be measured using a hand-held dynamometer to assess the strength of the following muscle groups: knee extensors.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Muscle Strength
Maximum force generated during an isometric muscle contraction will be measured using a hand-held dynamometer to assess the strength of the following muscle groups: elbow flexors.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Muscle Strength
Maximum force generated during an isometric muscle contraction will be measured using a hand-held dynamometer to assess the strength of the following muscle groups: elbow extensors.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The maximum weight that can be lifted for a single repetition will also be used as a measure of the maximum isokinetic force that can be generated. Maximum force will be measured for a seated chest press and seated leg extension.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Footstep patterns
Footstep patterns will be measured using the GAITRite® instrumented walkway system. The following footstep parameters will be measured: walking speed, step length, cadence, step width and double limb support time as a percentage of the gait cycle.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Walking endurance
Walking endurance will be measured using the six-minute walk test (6mwt) (Lipkin, Scriven et al. 1986), which is a sub-maximal test of endurance. The test requires the participant to walk as far as possible during the test period although participants are allowed to sit down to rest as required.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Upper extremity function
The Upper Extremity Functional Index (Stratford, Binkley et al. 2001) is a self-rated questionnaire that requires the participants to rate the level of difficulty in performing 20 upper limb tasks on a 5 point Likert Scale. The questions require the participant to evaluate their performance in tasks such as vacuuming, sweeping, using tools or appliances and lifting a bag of groceries.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure of participation 
Participation restrictions will be measured using the London Handicap Scale (LHS) (Harwood, Gompertz et al. 1994), which is a self-rated measure of disadvantage associated with chronic disease. The scale assesses six domains related to participation: mobility, physical independence, occupation, social integration, orientation and economic self-sufficiency.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse events
Adverse events that may be related to participation in the progressive resistance strength training program will be recorded by the physiotherapist who is supervising the program. The physiotherapist will ask each participant at the beginning and the end of each group training session if they have noticed any injuries or other problems that may be related to the training program. All reports of injuries or problems will be recorded in detail using an incident report form.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>i. Diagnosis of Pari. Diagnosis of Parkinson's disease confirmed using the United Kingdom Brain Bank Parkinson's disease criteria; ii. Medical clearance to participate in a strength training program;iii. Rated between Grade I and Grade IV on the Hoehn &amp; Yahr staging of Parkinson's disease. This will include people whose disease severity is not so severe that it would prevent them from participating in a group exercise training program; and iv. Able to walk without physical assistance for at least 14 meters (this is because one of the aims of this investigation is to improve walking ability and requires the assessment of walking). Kinson's disease confirmed using the United Kingdom Brain Bank Parkinson's disease criteria; ii. Medical clearance to participate in a strength training program; iii. Rated between Grade I and Grade IV on the Hoehn &amp; Yahr staging of Parkinson's disease. This will include people whose disease severity is not so severe that it would prevent them from participating in a group exercise training program; and iv. Able to walk without physical assistance for at least 14 meters (this is because one of the aims of this investigation is to improve walking ability and requires the assessment of walking).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>i. Rated Grade V -VI on the Hoehn &amp; Yahr staging of Parkinson's disease. This will exclude people who would be unlikely to have the physical capacity to participate in the progressive strength training program due to severe symptoms of PD;ii. Significant cognitive impairment (less than 16 on the Mini Mental Status Examination) and therefore unlikely to be able to follow instructions used in the implementation of the training program; andiii. Unable to travel to the Ballarat Community Health Centre to participate in the exercise program.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Prior to participant recruitment, a set of opaque sealed envelopes numbered 1-15 will be prepared for each stratum (disease severity I -II and III - IV). The envelopes will be prepared by Associate Professor K. Dodd who will not be involved in enrolling participants into the study, assessment or intervention. The research co-ordinator who will not be involved in either enrolling the participants or generating the allocation sequence will assign each participant in each stratum a number that is determined by their order of assessment. The participants name will be written on the envelop that matches their number and then the envelop will be opened to reveal if the participant has been allocated to the intervention or control group.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will then be randomly allocated to the intervention or control group using stratification for disease severity. Stratification will be based upon the Hoehn &amp; Yahr disease severity classification and will be used to assist in the allocation of equal numbers of people with disease severity I or II and III or IV in each group. A block randomization list will be produced for disease severity I -II and III - IV. The allocation sequences will be generated using blocks to minimise the risk of unequal group sizes. For each block, there are six possible allocation sequences. The allocation sequences will be generated using a random digit table, where an odd number will indicate intervention group and an even number will indicate control group.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2005</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>28</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Ballarat Community Health Centre</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ballarat Community Health Centre</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ballarat Health Services</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Ballarat Health Services</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Ballarat</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>La Trobe University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary />
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ballarat Health Services</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Ballarat</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>La Trobe University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Belinda Bilney</name>
      <address>Ballarat Health Services
Queen Elizabeth Centre
102 Ascot St
Ballarat VIC 3350</address>
      <phone>+61 3 53203994</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>belindab@bhs.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Belinda Bilney</name>
      <address>Ballarat Health Services
Queen Elizabeth Centre
102 Ascot St
Ballarat VIC 3350</address>
      <phone>+61 3 53203994</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>belindab@bhs.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>