<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370537">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/01/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/01/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000124336</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Insulin Pump therapy for Reducing Diabetic complications (InsPyReD) study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy of Insulin Pump Therapy for Reducing Diabetic complications in adults with type 1 diabetes (InsPyReD) </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>InsPyReD Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Type 1 diabetes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Diabetic Neuropathy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Neurodegenerative diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Eligible participants will be randomised to either control (standard multiple daily insulin injections) or the intervention group (insulin pump therapy) for a period of 2 years. 

The intervention, insulin pump therapy (using model MMT-754 Medtronic MiniMed Paradigm Veo), will be administered at the Diabetes Centre at the Prince of Wales Hospital via standard clinical procedures; this typically involves intensive consultation with an Endocrinologist (Director of the Diabetes Centre and CIC, Dr Ann Poynten) and a nurse educator on pump use, in addition to multiple appointments to ensure pumps are calibrated appropriately to achieve glucose control whilst minimising risk of hypoglycaemic events. These appointments last about 1 hr and typically occur once a week for the first 2-3 weeks after pump initiation. Once pumps are calibrated appropriately, standard endocrinology follow-up appointments will occur for approximately 30 minutes at 6, 12, 18 and 24 months. At these time  points, outcome measures for the trial will also be obtained and take approximately 1 hr. 
Documentation provided: Participants will also be educated on the use of the pump in face to face appointments and provided with information and documentation specific to the model of the pump being implemented (provided as part of the standard commercial pump package). Participants will also be provided with contact details of the trial co-ordinator (Dr Natalie Kwai) and in the case of an emergency related to their diabetes, CIC Poynten's on-call contact details. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>A control group (patients treated with a standard insulin injection regimen) will be monitored similarly to those in the intervention arm for comparison.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Corneal confocal microscopy will be used to determine the level of nerve damage in the eye. Nerve fiber density, length and tortuosity will be assessed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6, 12, 18 AND 24 MONTHS ON INTERVENTION OR STANDARD CARE</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severity of Neuropathy will be assessed using the Total Neuropathy Score. The score consists of neurological clinical assessment of sensation, strength and nerve conduction studies. </outcome>
      <timepoint>6, 12, 18, 24 MONTHS ON INTERVENTION OR STANDARD CARE
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nerve Excitability Composite score.
Nerve excitability is a non invasive test which provides indication of intrinsic nerve function and involves using surface electrodes to stimulate a nerve in the wrist and record a response distally. A composite score of the Nerve Excitability parameters hyperpolarising threshold electrtonus (90-100ms), depolarising threshold electrotonus (10-20ms) and subexcitability will be used.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6, 12, 18, 24 MONTHS ON INTERVENTION OR STANDARD CARE</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neuropeptide Y concentration in patient tears.
Neuropeptide Y is released from corneal nerves in response to damage. </outcome>
      <timepoint>6, 12, 18, 24 MONTHS ON INTERVENTION OR STANDARD CARE</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neuropathy related quality of life.
Quality of life specific to neuropathy will be assessed using a validated tool termed the NeuroQoL Questionnaire (Vileikyte et al., 2003). NeuroQoL scores degree of symptom effect as a function of presence/frequency and level of bother. </outcome>
      <timepoint>6, 12, 18, 24 MONTHS ON INTERVENTION OR STANDARD CARE</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Glucose Variability.
Glucose variability will be assessed in terms of Mean Amplitude of Glycaemic Excursions (Brownlee and Hirsch, 2006) using a continuous subcutaneous sensor. MAGE is calculated over a consecutive 48 hour period and participants will keep the sensor in situ for six days to ensure a consecutive 48 hours is captured in full.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>At screening and trial closeout for enrolled participants. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>History of type 1 diabetes, currently on multiple daily insulin injections but deemed suitable for continuous subcutaneous insulin infusions (CSII/Pump therapy) by treating endocrinologist. 18-45 years of age.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>a. Previous insulin pump therapy
b. Severe neuropathy, leading to difficulty with performing neurophysiological assessments.
c. Administration of another investigational drug within 30 days prior to randomisation.
d. Significant neurological or psychiatric disorders.
e. History of other conditions aside from type 1 diabetes that cause neuropathy (e.g end stage kidney disease).
f. Known pregnancy. 
g. Known medical history causing reduced corneal sensation and neurotrophic keratitis (e.g. viral infections, chemical burns, corneal surgery, excessive use of topical anaesthetic, history of fifth nerve palsy and multiple sclerosis).

</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods> The three excitability measures that comprise the primary endpoint (hyperpolarizing threshold electrotonus at 90-100 ms, depolarizing threshold electrotonus at 10-20 ms and subexcitability) can be combined into an excitability index using the linear coefficients (1,-1,-1 respectively).  This results in index values ranging between 30 and 80 having an approximate normal distribution (standard deviation 11.6).  Two groups of 30 patients randomly allocated to either CSII or MDII, would provide 80% power to detect a difference of up to 8.5 index points.  The 3 measurements will be required on all patients.  This study will enable evaluation of later neuropathy rates in these 2 groups.  95% confidence intervals for these groups will be no wider than (33%, 66%) if 15/30 patients go on to develop symptoms. Correlation with the index will be evaluated and inform its potential role as a surrogate marker for use in subsequent studies.
Methods of statistical analysis of finalised data will be adjusted for disease duration and HbA1c% between groups as these clinical parameters may differ between CSII and MDII-treated patients.  Data will be described using standard statistical methods (mean and standard deviation, median and interquartile range or frequency and percentage, depending on the variable type) to characterise the patient population and their neurophysiological, clinical and patient-reported outcomes. Linear models, with adjustment for specified a priori factors including age, duration of diabetes, HbA1c% and pre-existing neuropathy will be used to examine associations between MAGE and both measures of axonal function and long-term development of clinical evident DPN.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Prince of Wales Hospital - Randwick</hospital>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of New South Wales Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>UNSW Australia
Kensington 
NSW 2052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Medtronic Australasia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>5 Alma Road
Macquarie Park
NSW, 2113

N.B. This study is an investigator initiated project for which Medtronic is providing in-kind support </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Prince of Wales Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Prince of Wales Hospital
Hight street
Randwick
NSW 2031</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to determine whether insulin pump therapy can prevent nerve injury in patients with type 1 diabetes

Who is it for?
You can join this study if you have type 1 diabetes, aged 18-45 years and have not received insulin pump therapy before

Trial details
In this study, participants are randomly (by chance) divided into two groups. One group will receive an insulin pump free of charge for a period of 2 years. The other group will receive standard insulin injection therapy. Participants will undergo non-invasive nerve and eye tests to determine their suitability for the trial and when enrolled, will undergo these follow-up assessments at 6, 12, 18 and 24 months, coinciding with their usual endocrinology appointments. Both groups will receive continuous glucose monitoring at the beginning and end of the trial to determine the effect of glucose variability on nerve function. Participants will also undergo assessments of their quality of life specific to any nerve damage they may have. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Executive Committee South Eastern Sydney Local Health District</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Support Office
G71, East Wing
Edmund Blacket Building
Prince of Wales Hospital
Avoca Street
Randwick NSW 2031 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/04/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>15/058 (HREC/16/POWH/109)</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>21/10/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Arun Krishnan</name>
      <address>Institute of Neurological Sciences
Level 2 High Street Building
High Street
Prince of Wales Hospital
Randwick NSW 2031
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9382 2413</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>arun.krishnan@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Natalie Kwai</name>
      <address>Institute of Neurological Sciences
Level 2 High Street Building
High Street
Prince of Wales Hospital
Randwick NSW 2031
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9382 2413</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>natalie.kwai@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Arun Krishnan</name>
      <address>Institute of Neurological Sciences
Level 2 High Street Building
High Street
Prince of Wales Hospital
Randwick NSW 2031
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9382 2413</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>arun.krishnan@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Natalie Kwai</name>
      <address>Institute of Neurological Sciences
Level 2 High Street Building
High Street
Prince of Wales Hospital
Randwick NSW 2031
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9382 2413</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>natalie.kwai@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>