<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365105">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/10/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/10/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001129774</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Study on Clinical Outcomes of Piperacillin-Tazobactam Extended Infusion in Patients Hospitalised with a Bacterial Infection or Neutropenic Fever</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Study on the Clinical Outcomes of Piperacillin-Tazobactam Extended 4-hour Infusion as compared to Piperacillin-Tazobactam Traditional 30-minute Infusion in Patients Hospitalised for a Bacterial Infection or Neutropenic Fever - A Prospective Clinical Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1148-8097</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Infection</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention group would receive extended 4-hour intravenous infusion of Piperacillin-Tazobactam. Piperacillin-Tazobactam extended 4-hour infusion would be dosed according to renal function.
Creatinine clearance (estimated by Cockcroft Gault equation) &gt;/= 20ml/min: 4.5gram every 8 hours
Creatinine clearance (estimated by Cockcroft Gault equation) &lt; 20ml/min: 4.5gram every 12 hours

Participants would receive the extended 4-hour intravenous infusion of Piperacillin-Tazobactam after treatment assignment until Piperacillin-Tazobactam was decided to be discontinued by attending physician according to clinical condition and culture sensitivity results.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group would receive traditional 30-minute intravenous infusion of Piperacillin-Tazobactam. Piperacillin-Tazobactam traditional 30-minute intravenous infusion would be dosed according to renal function.
Creatinine clearance (estimated by Cockcroft Gault equation) &gt; 40ml/min: 4.5gram every 6 to 8 hours
Creatinine clearance (estimated by Cockcroft Gault equation) 20-40ml/min: 2.25gram every 6 hours to 4.5gram every 8 hours
Creatinine clearance (estimated by Cockcroft Gault equation) &lt;20ml/min: 2.25gram every 6 to 8 hours

Participants would receive the traditional 30-minute intravenous infusion of Piperacillin-Tazobactam after treatment assignment until Piperacillin-Tazobactam was decided to be discontinued by attending physician according to clinical condition and culture sensitivity results.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Primary clinical outcome is the 14-day mortality rate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>14 days after patient assignment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In-hospital mortality rate</outcome>
      <timepoint>Until the subject discharged from hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to defervescence  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Until the subject experience persistence of temperature below 37.5 degree Celsius for 24 hours.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of days receiving mechanical ventilator support</outcome>
      <timepoint>Until the subject weans off mechanical ventilator support.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of intensive care unit (ICU) stay</outcome>
      <timepoint>Until the subject discharged from ICU</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of hospital stay</outcome>
      <timepoint>Until the subject discharged from hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients were eligible if they were aged 18 years or older; were hospitalized in an acute medical unit or intensive care unit; either had received a diagnosis of bacterial infection or suffered from neutropenic fever; planned to receive treatment of Piperacillin-Tazobactam for at least 48 hours. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients would be excluded if they are pregnant, had received more than 48 hours of effective antibiotics, as defined by specimen culture sensitivity results, within five days of initiation of extended 4-hour infusion or traditional 30-minute infusions of Piperacillin-Tazobactam; had been receiving other beta-lactam antibiotics concomitantly.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All hospitalized patients would receive a computer generated hospital number, also known as "HN number", in which the assigned method of numbering is not known to the investigators and treating physicians.
Patients carrying a hospital number ended with an even number, excluding the alphabetical letter, would be assigned to the study group whereas patients carrying a hospital number ended with an odd number, excluding the alphabetical letter, would be assigned to the control group.</concealment>
    <sequence>Patients carrying a hospital number ended with an even number, excluding the alphabetical letter, would be assigned to the study group whereas patients carrying a hospital number ended with an odd number, excluding the alphabetical letter, would be assigned to the control group.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A sample size calculation was carried out based on previous retrospective cohort (Raymond J. Yost et al. The Retrospective Cohort of Extended-infusion Piperacillin-Tazobactam (RECEIPT) Study. Pharmacotherapy 2011; 31(8):767-775) demonstrating a significant reduction in mortality from 20.2% to 9.7% for extended 4-hour Piperacillin-Tazobactam infusion. A sample size of 360 was required to provide more than 80% power using a two sided alpha-level of 0.05 to detect a relative risk reduction in mortality rate of 50 percent between the extended 4-hour infusion and traditional 30-minute infusion of Piperacillin-Tazobactam.
Categorical variables were compared using Chi-square test. Continuous variables were compared using Students t test or Mann-Whitney U test. A P value of less than 0.05 was considered to indicate statistical significance, and all tests were two-sided. All calculations were performed using SPSS version 16 for Windows.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/10/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/12/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>31/08/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>360</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>367</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>30/09/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <state>Hong Kong</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Fan Sheung Yin</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Pharmacy department, G/F, Main Block,
Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital
3 Lok Man Road, Chai Wan</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Hong Kong</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Not applicable</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Not applicable</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Not applicable</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Not applicable</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Antibiotic resistance and its associated increasing mortality are ever-growing problems in Hong Kong. Infectious Diseases Society of America stated that the optimization of the antimicrobial dosing, based on pharmacokinetic (PK) and pharmacodynamic (PD) characteristics, was an important part of antibiotic stewardship . In view of the growing need to fight against resistant pathogens, piperacillin-tazobactam (Pip-Tazo) extended 4-hour infusion has been catching worldwide attention in the past few years.
Piperacillin-Tazobactam is a widely use broad-spectrum beta-lactam antibiotic in hospitals in Hong Kong for the treatment of bacterial infections. The bactericidal effect of Pip-Tazo is maximized by maintaining the free drug concentration (Cf) above the minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) for greater than fifty percent of time (T) . PK and PD studies carried out in the past decade on Pip-Tazos time-dependent killing (50% CfT&gt;MIC) property had revealed that by extending its infusion time from 30 minutes to 4 hours, the probability of attaining the target (50% CfT&gt;MIC) was highly increased for pathogens with MIC greater than 1mcg/ml , .
Further studies had lent support to the clinical efficacy of Pip-Tazo extended infusion. A retrospective cohort study had shown that the 14-day mortality rate and median duration of hospital stay were significantly reduced for patients who received extended 4-hour infusion of Pip-Tazo compared to those who received intermittent 30-minute infusion for patients with Acute Physiological and Chronic Health EvaluationII (APACHE II) scores greater than 173. Another retrospective study had also demonstrated significant mortality reduction for extended 4-hour infusion of Pip-Tazo . 
To the knowledge of the investigators, there had not been any prospective clinical trial studies carried out on Chinese population on the clinical outcomes of extended 4-hour infusion of Pip-Tazo in comparison to traditional non-extended 30-minute infusion of piperacillin-tazobactam. 

It had been expected that the patients receiving extended 4-hour infusion of Pip-Tazo would have a lower 14-day and in-hospital mortality rate, shorter time to defervescence, shorter number of days receiving mechanical ventilator support and length of ICU and hospital stay in comparison to the traditional 30-minute infusion.

The results of this research may guide the future dosing strategy of Pip-Tazo.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Fan, S.-Y., Shum, H.-P., Cheng, W.-Y., Chan, Y.-H., Leung, S.-Y. M. and Yan, W.-W. (2017), Clinical Outcomes of Extended Versus Intermittent Infusion of Piperacillin/Tazobactam in Critically Ill Patients: A Prospective Clinical Trial. 
Pharmacotherapy, 37: 109119. doi:10.1002/phar.1875</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hong Kong East Cluster Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Room 133, 2/F, Main Block, Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital, 3 Lok Man Road, Chai Wan</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/09/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/07/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Hong Kong</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Fan Sheung Yin</name>
      <address>Pharmacy Department,
G/F, Main Block, 
Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital,
3 Lok Man Road, Chai Wan</address>
      <phone>+85264600823</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>fsy229@ha.org.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Fan Sheung Yin</name>
      <address>Pharmacy Department,
G/F, Main Block, 
Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital,
3 Lok Man Road, Chai Wan</address>
      <phone>+85264600823</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>fsy229@ha.org.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Fan Sheung Yin</name>
      <address>Pharmacy Department,
G/F, Main Block, 
Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital,
3 Lok Man Road, Chai Wan</address>
      <phone>+85264600823</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>fsy229@ha.org.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Fan Sheung Yin</name>
      <address>Pharmacy Department,
G/F, Main Block, 
Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital,
3 Lok Man Road, Chai Wan</address>
      <phone>+85264600823</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>fsy229@ha.org.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>