<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82880">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/06/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/07/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000531213</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>T-cell Therapy for CMV (Cytomegalovirus) Disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Adoptive immunotherapy for the treatment of cytomegalovirus (CMV) reactivation and disease after transplantation.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>QR2009-CMV1a</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Queensland Institute of Medical Research project number P1211</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>CMV disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Allogeneic or autologous ex vivo expanded human CMV-specific T cells will be administered by intravenous infusion. Up to six doses will be given at weeks 0, 2, 4, 6, 10, and 14.</interventions>
    <comparator>none</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility of generating HCMV-specific T cells from HCMV-seropositive allogeneic HSCT donors, or if unavailable, Hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (HSCT) recipients.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The investigational product for each study participant will be assessed post production. Interim assessment will be made when 10 study participants have received at least 2 treatments. Overall assessment will be made after treatment of all participants has finished. Stringent quality control tests (sterility media inoculation, cell viability testing, cell counting, staining for phenotypic analysis) will also be performed and a Certificate of Manufacture will be issued when products are released from the facility. The phenotype (CD3, CD4, CD8, CD56 and CD16) of the T cell lines will be analysed by FACS analysis. The degree of HCMV specificity in the final T cell product will be determined by peptide-specific interferon-gamma secretion in a 6-hour intracellular cytokine secretion assay.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety of adoptive transfer of up to six doses of HCMV-specific cytotoxic T cells in allogeneic HSCT recipients.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Safety will be assessed by adverse event monitoring. Patients will be questioned and toxicities recorded according to the common terminology for adverse events up to one hour post eacht treatment (fortnightly for 4 treatments then each 4 weeks for a further 2 treatments), and each 4 weeks until one year after the first treatment. Interim assessment will be made when 10 study participants have received at least 2 treatments. Overall assessment will be made after treatment of all participants has finished. Physical examination and vital observations will be performed at each clinic visit. Concurrent medications, including immunosuppression and antiviral treatment, will be documented at each visit. GVHD will be scored on a standardised scale (appendix II). Full blood count (FBC) and liver function tests (ELFT) will be performed on a regular basis and HCMV viral load will be determined by quantitative PCR. In patients with target organ disease, repeat tissue biopsy is encouraged where feasible, particularly when HCMV is not detected in peripheral blood at time of enrolment. Adverse events will be recorded at each scheduled visit.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the immunological effect of CMV-specific T cell transfer. This would include measurement of CMV-specific T cell numbers and function by tetramer analysis, ELISPOT, and CMV-Quantiferon.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of each treatment (fortnightly for 4 treatments then each 4 weeks for a further 2 treatments), and each 4 weeks until one year after the first treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the clinical effect of CMV-specific T cell transfer. This would include clinical assessment, measurement of CMV viral load, and where applicable, tissue biopsy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of each treatment (fortnightly for 4 treatments then each 4 weeks for a further 2 treatments), and each 4 weeks until one year after the first treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) HSCT/SOT recipients who were transplanted by, and/or are currently under the care of, a haematologist or physician at the appropriate clinical facility. 
2). CMV infection that falls into one of the following categories: 
(a) Recurrent CMV reactivation (as defined by PCR) or disease (as defined by histology) following successful initial therapy, or 
(b) Persistent CMV disease (no response to 2 weeks of salvage foscarnet or other second line antiviral agent), or 
(c) Persistent CMV replication (more than 6 weeks by PCR) despite appropriate antiviral therapy, or 
(d) Any CMV reactivation or disease where anti-viral therapy is contraindicated on the basis of intolerance or end organ limitation (e.g. renal impairment, marrow dysfunction). 
3) Absence of uncontrolled intercurrent infection 
4) Patient able to provide informed consent 
5) Age 18 to 75</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1 Uncontrolled intercurrent infection
2 Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG)status &gt; 3 (Karnofsky performance score &lt; 30: disabled, no self-care. Totally bedridden, or confined  to chair) 
3 Markers of active Hepatitis B virus (HBV), Hepatitis C virus (HCV) or  Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection (presence of Hepatitis B surface Antigen (HBsAg), Hepatitis C (HepC) antibody, or HIV antibodies)
4 Uncontrolled Graft versus Host disease (GVHD)
5 Steroid doses &gt; 1mg/kg of prednisone, or equivalent</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence>Not applicable (non randomised trial)</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>21/05/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>17/10/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Queensland Institute of Medical Research</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>300 Herston Rd
Herston 
Queensland 4006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Research Infrastructure Support Services (R.I.S.S)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 5103 Melbourne, Victoria 3001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421 Canberra, Australian Capital Teritory 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Since the inception of human organ transplantation, HCMV remains single most-important cause of infectious morbidity and mortality in immunocompromised transplant patients. This project is designed to develop immunotherapeutic strategies based on adoptive transfer of virus- specific killer T cells for the treatment of HCMV infection in transplant patients.

Who is it for?
You can join this study if you have had an allogeneic haematopoietic stem cell transplant or a renal transplant at the Royal Brisbane Hospital and have a CMV infection. 

Trial details
Blood will be collected from your stem cell donor (for SCT patients) or yourself and the CMV killer T cells grown in the laboratory (this takes about 3 weeks.) The cells are then tested for sterility and specificity. Once the cells pass these checks they will be infused into yourself: 4 doses at 2 weekly intervals and then a further 2 doses at 4 weekly intervals provided sufficient cells are produced. 

The effects of the treatment will be studied by monitoring your signs and symptoms and by blood tests. This will be done at the time of each treatment and then monthly for up to a year from the first treatment. Your total length of involvement will be no longer than 18 months.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Smith, C. and KHANNA, R. Immune regulation of human herpesviruses and its implications for human transplantation.
Am. J. Transplantation (2013) 13:9-23. 

Tey, S.K, Davenport, M., Hill, G. Kennedy, G., Durrant, S., KHANNA, R. and Cromer, D. Post-transplant cytomegalovirus-specific T cell immune reconstitution in the absence of global T cell immunity is associated with a high risk of subsequent virus reactivation" by Bone Marrow Transplant (2014) In press 

Tey, S.K., Kennedy, G.A., Cromer, D., Davenport, M.P., Walker, S., Jones, L.I., Crough, T., Durrant, S.T., Morton, J.A., Butler, J.P., Misra, A.K., Hill, G.R. and KHANNA, R. Clinical assessment of anti-viral CD8+ T cell immune monitoring to identify high risk allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplant patients with CMV infection complications. PLoS ONE (2013) 8: e74744. 

KHANNA, R. and Smith. C. Cellular immune therapy for viral infections in transplant patients. Indian J Med Res (2013) 138:  796-807. 
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Queensland Institute of Medical Research Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Queensland Institute of Medical Research,
Post Office Royal Brisbane,QLD, 4029</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/04/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/09/QRBW/197</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>22/04/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Ethics
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital 
Level 7, block 7, 
Butterfield Street
QLD 4029</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/06/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Rajiv Khanna</name>
      <address>Queensland Institute of Medical Research, 300 Herston Road, Herston 4006 Brisbane</address>
      <phone>61-7- 3362 0385</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 7 3845 3510</fax>
      <email>rajiv.khanna@qimr.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Katherine Matthews</name>
      <address>Queensland Institute of Medical Research, 300 Herston Road, Herston 4006 Brisbane</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3362 0412</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3845 3510</fax>
      <email>Katherine.Matthews@qimr.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sashika Naidoo</name>
      <address>Queensland Institute of Medical Research, Regulatory Affairs, 300 Herston Road, Herston 4006 Brisbane</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3362 0433</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 7 3362 0109</fax>
      <email>Sashika.Naidoo@qimr.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Rajiv Khanna</name>
      <address>Queensland Institute of Medical Research, 300 Herston Road, Herston 4006 Brisbane</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3362 0385</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3845 3510</fax>
      <email>Rajiv.Khanna@qimr.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>