<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336752">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/04/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/05/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000521921</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy and safety of artesunate+mefloquine for the treatment of uncomplicated Plasmodium falciparum malaria in Mae Hong Son, Kanchanaburi, Ubonratchathani and Surin provinces in Thailand</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy and safety of artesunate+mefloquine for the treatment of uncomplicated Plasmodium falciparum malaria in Mae Hong Son, Kanchanaburi, Ubonratchathani and Surin provinces in Thailand</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Uncomplicated falciparum malaria patients</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A combination of artesunate+mefloquine+primaquine. The total oral dosage is 12 mg/kg artesunate plus 25 mg/kg mefloquine plus 30 mg primaquine. Treatment regimen is 4 mg/kg artersunate plus 15 mg/kg mefloquine on day 0, 4 mg/kg artesunate plus 10 mg/kg mefloquine on day 1 and 4 mg/kg artesunate plus 30 mg primaquine on day 2.</interventions>
    <comparator>The study will be done in 4 sentinel sites for Artesunate+Mefloquine combination treatment.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Treatment outcomes will be classified on the basis of an assessment of the parasitological and clinical outcome of antimalarial treatment according to the latest World Health Organization (WHO) guidelines. Thus, all patients will be classified as having early treatment failure, late clinical failure, late parasitological failure or an adequate clinical and parasitological response.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1, 2, 3, 7, 14, 21, 28, 35 and 42 for the treatment of uncomplicated falciparum malaria by artesunate+mefloquine</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The incidence of any adverse event such as nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, etc. will be documented. All patients will be asked routinely about the previous symptoms and about symptoms that have emerged since the previous follow-up visit. When clinically indicated, patients will be evaluated and treated appropriately. All adverse events will be recorded on the case report form. Serious adverse events must be reported to the sponsor.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day0, 1, 2, 3, 7, 14, 21, 28, 35 and 42 for the treatment of uncomplicated falciparum malaria by artesunate+mefloquine</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-Age 6 months and above;
-Mono-infection with Plasmodium falciparum detected by microscopy
-P. falciparum parasitaemia of 500-1000000/ul asexual forms
-presence of axillary or tympanic temperature equal or more than 37.5C or history of fever during the past 24 h
-Ability to swallow oral medication
-Ability and willingness to comply with the study protocol for the duration of the study and to comply with the study visit schedule and 
-Informed consent from the patient or from a parent or guardian in the case of children</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Months</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-Presence of general danger signs in children aged under 5 years or signs of severe falciparum malaria according to the definitions of WHO -mixed or mono-infection with another Plasmodium species detected by microscopy -presence of severe malnutrition (defined as a child whose growth standard is below -3 z-score, has symmetrical oedema involving at least the feet or has a mid-upper arm circumference &lt;110 mm) -presence of febrile conditions due to diseases other than malaria or other known underlying chronic or severe diseases -Regular medication, which may interfere with antimalarial pharmacokinetics -history of hypersensitivity reactions or contraindications to any of the medicine being tested or used as alternative treatment -Female of child-bearing potential with ages 12-17 years old inclusive -A positive pregnancy test or breastfeeding -Unable to or unwilling to take contraceptives for pregnancy negative married women of child-bearing age</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Thailand</country>
      <state>Kanchanaburi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Thailand</country>
      <state>Ubonratchathani</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Thailand</country>
      <state>Surin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Thailand</country>
      <state>Mae Hong Son</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Bureau of Vector-Borne Disease</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Disease Control, Ministry of Public Health, Tiwanon Road, Muang District, Nonthaburi 11000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Thailand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>World Health Organization</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>WHO-Mekong Malaria Programme (MMP) Faculty of Tropical Medicine, Mahidol University, 400/6 Ratchawithi Road, 10400 Bangkok, Thailand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Thailand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Title: Efficacy and safety of artesunate-mefloquine for the treatment of uncomplicated Plasmodium falciparum malaria in Mae Hong Son, Kanchanaburi, Ubonratchathani and Surin provinces in Thailand 
Background: Current first-line treatment for P. falciparum in Thailand is a 3-day artesunate-mefloquine combination. The second-line treatment is 7-day quinine-doxycycline combination. Study conducted in 2008 in 5 sentinel sites revealed high efficacy of the 3-day artesunate-mefloquine combination (96.8-100%). In 2009, the efficacy of the artesunate-mefloquine combination declined to 87-92.7% in 4 sentinel sites. The monitoring the efficacy of the first line treatment to generate valuable information for updating the national treatment policy is critical. 
Objective: To assess the efficacy and safety of artesunate-mefloquine for the treatment of uncomplicated Plasmodium falciparum malaria in Mae Hong Son, Kanchanaburi, Ubonratchathani and Surin provinces in Thailand
Methods: Antimalarial drug efficacy trials will be conducted in 4 sites for uncomplicated falciparum infection. The participants will be febrile patients aged 6 months and above with confirmed uncomplicated P. falciparum infection. Falciparum malaria patients will be treated with artesunate (4 mg/kg over 3 days) co-administered with mefloquine (15 mg/kg on day 0 and 10 mg/kg on day 1). 30 mg of primaquine will be given on day 2. Clinical and parasitological parameters will be monitored over a 42-day follow-up period to evaluate drug efficacy for falciparum malaria. The study will be conducted from June 2011 to May 2012. The results of this study will be used to assist the Ministry of Public Health of Thailand in assessing the current national treatment guidelines for uncomplicated P. falciparum malaria.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Ethical Committee for Research in Human Subjects</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Department of Disease Control, Ministry of Public Health, Tiwanon Road, Muang District, Nonthaburi 11000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/04/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Thailand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Kanungnit Congpuong</name>
      <address>Bureau of Vector-borne Disease,
Department of Disease Control,
Ministry of Public Health, 
Tiwanon Road, Muang District,
Nonthaburi, 11000</address>
      <phone>662 965 9608</phone>
      <fax>662 591 8422</fax>
      <email>kanungnitcongpuong@ymail.com</email>
      <country>Thailand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Kanungnit Congpuong</name>
      <address>Bureau of Vector-borne Disease,
Department of Disease Control,
Ministry of Public Health, 
Tiwanon Road, Muang District,
Nonthaburi, 11000</address>
      <phone>662 965 9608</phone>
      <fax>662 591 8422</fax>
      <email>kanungnitcongpuong@ymail.com</email>
      <country>Thailand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Kanungnit Congpuong</name>
      <address>Bureau of Vector-borne Disease,
Department of Disease Control,
Ministry of Public Health, 
Tiwanon Road, Muang District,
Nonthaburi, 11000</address>
      <phone>662 965 9608</phone>
      <fax>662 591 8422</fax>
      <email>kanungnitcongpuong@ymail.com</email>
      <country>Thailand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>