<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335289">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/03/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/03/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000241033</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A pilot project investigating the feasibility and effects of a 6 month peer support program commencing 3 months prior to discharge from a specialist first-episode psychosis treatment center</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot study examining whether or not the provision of a 6 month peer support program commencing 3 months prior to discharge from a specialist first-episode psychosis treatment center can improve treatment adherence and other outcomes among young people</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>First-episode psychosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Psychosis and personality disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>An individual peer support program delivered to young people from 3 months prior to, until 3 months post discharge from a specialist first episode psychosis center.  People will receive 2 hours of contact per fortnight from the peer support worker which will include an in-reach and out-reach service and will include supportive informal contact, assistance making health related appointments, assistance with public transport to appointments and support in accessing new services. Participants will receive the peer support intervention plus standard care.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard care as determined by the case manager</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Increased engagement and treatment adherence, as measured by The Psychosocial Treatment Compliance Scale (Tsang, et al., 2006), by specific questions included in a treatment questionnaire and via a telephone call made by the Research Assistant (RA) to the new treating clinician asking about attendance at appointments and medication compliance</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline
6 months (post intervention)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Increased perceived social support and increased quantity and improved quality of information provided, as measured by the Multi-dimensional Scale of Perceived Social Support (Zimet et al., 1988).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline
6 months (post intervention)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Increased service satisfaction, as measured by the Verona Service Satisfaction Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline
6 months (post intervention)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduced risk of suicide, as measured by  The Reynolds Suicidal Ideation Questionnaire (Reynolds, 1988).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline
6 months (post intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Increased quality of life as measured by the World Health Organisation Quality of Life Scale (Heinrichs et al., 1984).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline
6 months (post intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Aged 15-24 and being discharged from a specialist first-episode psychosis center; the Early Psychosis Prevention and Intervention Center (EPPIC) having been treated for first-episode psychosis</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>15</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>24</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>A recent history of violence against the person
An inability to provide informed consent
Inability to speak English</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The study team comprises researchers and representatives from the clinical program.  The research assistant (RA) will attend the regular clinical meetings held at EPPIC in order to identify young people who are about to commence the discharge planning period. Once the discharge planning process is about to begin the RA will contact the young person and see if they are interested in the study. If so they will obtain written consent and conduct the baseline assessment. Once the baseline assessment is conducted the young person’s details will be passed to an independent statistician who will randomise them into either the treatment or control group. Those in the control group will receive treatment as usual (TAU) whilst those in the treatment group will receive treatment as usual plus the peer support intervention (TAU+PSI).

Once randomisation has taken place the statistician will contact either the project supervisor or the Peer Support Coordinator directly that the intervention can begin.  The Peer Support Coordinator will allocate a peer support worker (PSW) who will make contact with the participant and will deliver the intervention. By doing this in this way the RA can remain blind to treatment.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation procedure will follow the consort guidelines. The subjects will be randomized to the treatment group or control group with equal allocation. Computer generated random numbers will be used to carry out the randomization.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>36</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Terminated</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Orygen Youth Health Research Centre</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>35 Poplar Road
Parkville
Vic, 3052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Orygen Youth Health Research Centre</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>35 Poplar Road
Parkville
Vic, 3052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Myer Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 18
8 Exhibition Street
Melbourne, Victoria 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Participants will be approximately 36 young people, aged 15-24, who are being discharged from EPPIC.  EPPIC is a government funded public mental health service serving North West Metropolitan Melbourne. All participants will be recruited through the service.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Mental Health Research and Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office for Research
Level 6 East, Main Building
Grattan Street
The Royal Melbourne Hospital
Parkville,  VIC  3050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>2010.050</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/01/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jo Robinson</name>
      <address>Orygen Youth Health Research Centre
35 Poplar Road
Parkville, 
Vic, 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3  9342 2866</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9342 2941</fax>
      <email>jo.robinson@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jo Robinson</name>
      <address>Orygen Youth Health Research Centre
35 Poplar Road
Parkville, Vic, 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9342 2866</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9342 2941</fax>
      <email>jo.robinson@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jo Robinson</name>
      <address>Orygen Youth Health Research Centre
35 Poplar Road
Parkville, Vic, 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9342 2866</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9342 2941</fax>
      <email>jo.robinson@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>