<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362912">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/10/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/11/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001164886</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Improving Dementia end of life care at local aged care facilities.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Cluster randomised controlled trial of facilitated case conferencing versus usual care for improving end of life outcomes in aged care residents with advanced dementia and their families.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1136-2430</utrn>
    <trialacronym>IDEAL Project</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Advanced dementia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dementias</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention will be implemented over 18 months.

We will use a train-the-trainer model, whereby a paid Palliative Care Planning Coordinator (PCPC) is trained and then supported to train other nursing and personal care staff at each intervention residential aged care facility (RACF). PCPCs will be the team leader in each RACF responsible for implementing the case conferencing (CC) model as per the protocol and providing ongoing education and mentoring to other RACF staff. PCPCs from all 10 intervention facilities will attend an initial training programme for 1 week. They will learn to identify triggers that warrant initiation of a Facilitated Case Conferencing (FCC). Where a trigger for FCC has been identified, the point of disease progression will be mapped onto relevant domains to indicate whether survival time will likely be measured in months, weeks or days. The map for each resident will highlight issues for discussion at CC, including pre-emptive planning for predicted deterioration. Training in facilitating general practitioner involvement will also be given to PCPCs. Ongoing support in the Intervention arm will be provided following initial training and for the rest of the study period. The team will liaise monthly with each PCPC to discuss progress and difficulties and plan support of staff training and CCs where monitoring data indicate this is required. Finally, training will assist RACF staff to provide a palliative space (an area which provides the resident and family a quiet, homelike private environment 24 hours per day. 

PCC training will make use of experiential and adult learning approaches, guidance on how family members can be involved as much as possible in decision-making about care planning, implementation and monitoring, and support reconceptualisation from a service focus to person-centred focus.</interventions>
    <comparator>This is a cluster randomised trial with whole RACFs randomised to either Intervention or Control. There will be no additional education, training or support provided to Control RACFs but there will also be no restriction on service-provider education and training where this is current practice. The level, duration and type of such initiatives will be documented.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Family-rated end of life (EOL) outcomes will be measured using the End of Life in Dementia (EOLD) Scales. 

The EOLD Scales will be used to measure symptom-related comfort during the last seven days of life (CAD-EOLD), symptom management in the last 90 days of life (SM-EOLD) and family satisfaction with care during the last 90 days of life (SWC-EOLD).</outcome>
      <timepoint>The primary outcome will be measured 4 weeks following resident deaths.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nurse-rated symptom-related comfort and symptom management will be measured using the CAD-EOLD and SM-EOLD Scales.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks following resident death.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nurse-rated resident quality of life (QOL) measured using the Quality of Life in Late-stage Dementia (QUALID) Scale and EQ-5D-5L for economic evaluation purposes</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 6 weekly</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>RACF person-centred approach to care will be measured by the Care &amp; Activities, &amp; Interpersonal Relationships &amp; Interactions domain of the Person-Centred Environment &amp; Care Assessment Tool (PCECAT).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 and 18 monthly</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>RAC staff attitudes to, knowledge of &amp; confidence in providing palliative/EOL care to residents with advanced dementia will be evaluated using the Palliative Care for Advanced Dementia Questionnaire (PCADQ), a 42-item tool developed by the current team. Attitudes to dementia care more generally will be evaluated using the Dementia Attitudes Scale (DAS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and after staff training</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of end of life care will be measured by rates of (inappropriate) acute care episodes and aggressive medical interventions (e.g. ventilation).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 3 monthly</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Eligibility criteria for clusters/RACF: 
- &gt;100 high care beds
- &gt;50% residents with dementia.

Eligibility criteria for residents: 
- a diagnosis of dementia &amp; advanced disease as determined by Functional Assessment Staging Tool (FAST) in dementia greater than or equal to 6a, 
- stable for 1 month according to RACF staff; 
- Australiamodified Karnofsky Performance Status (AKPS) of less than or equal to 50; 
- availability of a person legally responsible to give informed consent on their behalf; 
- informed consent from a family member or other who knows the resident well.

Eligibility for family/friend informant (ideally the person legally responsible): 
- visits the resident at least once a fortnight; 
- knew the resident prior to their dementia diagnosis; 
- is willing to be involved in decisions about the residents care; 
- English proficiency sufficient to complete outcome measures

RAC staff: 
all permanent nursing/personal care staff at participating RACFs. 

Other health professionals (e.g. GPs):
all health professionals involved in case conferencing for participating residents will also be eligible to participate. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>None.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Aged care facilities will be selected for approach from comprehensive lists of all facilities in each geographical area by means of a randomisation schedule intended to minimize selection bias. Facility managers will be approached via letter and telephone by the research team to canvass their initial interest. Managers expressing initial interest will be sent an information and consent form, followed by a follow-up phone call. 
Facility managers and staff will be asked to identify residents who: 1) have dementia, probably in the advanced stages (with or without a confirmed diagnosis); 2) have a family member or friend who visits on a regular basis; and 3) have a person responsible to give consent to participate on their behalf.
Facility staff with care responsibilities (i.e. nurses and assistants in nursing) will also be eligible to participate. Staff will be told about the study verbally at staff meetings, provided with information and consent forms.
Finally, other health professionals who take part in case conferences for participating residents will be approached to take part. 
Allocation will occur only after RACFs, staff, residents and family members have enrolled and baseline measures have been taken. Recruitment and outcome measurement will be by research assistants blinded to the purpose of the study, and each will visit only RACFs in either the Intervention or Control arm. The statistician analysing data will be blind to the identity of the RACFs. The project manager, who will need to remain unblinded to liaise with RACFs, will play no role in measuring outcomes.</concealment>
    <sequence>Block randomisation will be 1:1 and occur using two stratification factors (dementia specific unit or not; part of organisation or stand alone facility) using a computer generated random allocation sequence. This method will facilitate balance in the allocation of RACFs to the FCC and UC groups.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/10/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>19/02/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>10/06/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>240</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>286</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>31/12/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>HammondCare</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 2, 447 Kent St
Sydney, NSW, 2000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Department of Health and Ageing</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 9848,
Canberra
ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Dementia is a terminal disease. Care for people with advanced dementia requires a palliative approach that is targeted to the illness trajectory and tailored to the needs of each individual and his/her family. Currently, the quality of care in residential aged care (RAC) is compromised by lack of staff expertise and poor communication between staff, family and health professionals. Residents suffer unnecessary hospitalisations and aggressive treatments, while symptoms often go unmanaged. Facilitated case conferencing (FCC) is an approach that brings together RAC staff, health professionals and families to plan person-centred management based on best practice. FCC has improved outcomes in other palliative settings but evidence is lacking for RAC residents with advanced dementia. This study will compare the efficacy and cost-effectiveness of FCC compared with usual care for improving end of life outcomes and quality of care for people with advanced dementia in residential aged care.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Agar M, Beattie E, Luckett T, Phillips J, Luscombe G, Goodall S, Mitchell G, Pond D, Davidson PM, Chenoweth L. Pragmatic cluster randomised controlled trial of facilitated family case conferencing compared with usual care for improving end of life care and outcomes in nursing home residents with advanced dementia and their families: the IDEAL study protocol. BMC Palliative Care.  2015;14(1):63.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of New South Wales (UNSW)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>UNSW Grants Management Office
Rupert Myers Building, Level 3, South Wing
The University of New South Wales 
SYDNEY NSW 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/09/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HC12455</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Technology Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>C/- Research &amp; Innovation Office University of Technology, Sydney Level 14, Tower Building Broadway NSW 2007</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/10/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2012-367R</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Queensland University of Technology</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Ethics Unit, Office of Research, Level 4, 88 Musk Ave, QUT Kelvin Grove QLD 4059</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/12/2510</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tim Luckett</name>
      <address>University of Technology Sydney (UTS), Faculty of Health, Building 10, Level 7, 235-253 Jones St, Ultimo, NSW 2007</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9514 4861</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9514 4474</fax>
      <email>tim.luckett@uts.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tim Luckett</name>
      <address>University of Technology Sydney (UTS), Faculty of Health, Building 10, Level 7, 235-253 Jones St, Ultimo, NSW 2007</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9514 4861</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9514 4474</fax>
      <email>tim.luckett@uts.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tim Luckett</name>
      <address>University of Technology Sydney (UTS), Faculty of Health, Building 10, Level 7, 235-253 Jones St, Ultimo, NSW 2007</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9514 4861</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9514 4474</fax>
      <email>tim.luckett@uts.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Meera Agar</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health, University of Technology Sydney, Building 10, Jones St, Ultimo, NSW 2007</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9514 4243</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>meera.agar@uts.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>