<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362421">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/04/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/05/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000479808</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of Fluorodeoxyglucose Positron Emission Tomography (F18-FDG PET) scans in infection of the extremities</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of F18 FDG PET/CT in infection of the extremities.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Infection of the extremities</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Following study enrolment each patient will undergo a FDG PET-CT in addition to a labelled leukocyte study +/- bone scan. The labelled leukocyte study +/- bone scan are routine clinical care, and the FDG PET-CT scan of the peripheries is in addition to routine care. The routine care options for participants will differ on a case by case basis, and are listed in the Comparator/Control field below.The white cell scans and the FDG PET-CT scan will be performed within a week of each other. Patients will be followed for up to 3 months to record subsequent treatment regimens: antibiotics, surgery, radiological and clinical responses to therapy and biopsy results when performed. 

Patients will be required to fast for 4-6 hours An intravenous cannula will be inserted into a peripheral vein and the blood sugar level (BSL) recorded. If fasting BSL &gt; 11.1mmol/l the reporting PET physician will decide if study is to proceed or be re-scheduled. Aporoximately 4 MBq/kg of 18F-FDG (maximum 250 MBq) will be administered intravenously. Patient will rest quietly for one hour. Mobilisation is discouraged during the uptake phase.
PET-CT imaging will be performed on Siemens PET-CT, one hour following FDG administration, over 2-3 bed positions with CT field of view limited to area of interest in extremities. Image reconstruction will include CT attenuation correction.</interventions>
    <comparator>All participants will undergo one of the current routine care options listed below but all participants will undergo the FDG PET-CT scan intervention.
Bone scan (routine care)
Via a peripheral intravenous cannula approximately 1000 MBq 99mTc-HDP (dose will be adjusted to patient weight) will be injected into the patient. Dynamic images of the extremities are obtained after tracer injection, followed by bloodpool static images for 2 minutes on a gamma camera. At least 6 hours after injection, static images of the extremities will be obtained for 5 to 15 minutes, supplemented by Single Photon Emission Computed Tomography/Computed Tomography (SPECT/CT) at reporting clinicians discretion (30 minutes).

Oxine Labelled Autologous White Blood Cell (WBC) study (routine care). Patients white blood cells (WBCs) are labelled with 10-20MBq of Indium-111 oxine, Then 20-24 hrs after re-injection of patient's Indium111 Oxine Labelled WBCs in a peripheral vein, static images are obtained over 10-15 minutes supplemented by SPECT/CT at reporting clinicians discretion (40 minutes).

Dual Technetium 99 (99m-Tc) HDP bone scan and Indium 111 (111In) Oxine Labelled White Blood Cell (WBC) (routine care). A blood sample is taken from the patient and white cells are labelled with 10-20 MBq of Indium-111 oxine and re-injected back into a peripheral vein. Approximately 1000 MBq 99mTc-HDP (dose adjusted to patient weight) will be administered intravenously and dynamic images of the extremities are obtained. At 20-24 hrs after 99mTc-HDP and autologous 111In-labelled leukocyte injection, dual tracer planar images with similar incidence to the delayed bone scan are obtained during 10-15 minutes on SPECT/CT of the extremities (40 minutes) at reporting clinicians discretion.

99mTc HMPAO labelled Autologous White Blood Cell (routine care). Usually performed 48 hours after a bone scan. The patients blood will be taken and WBCs will be labelled with 200 - 250 MBq of 99mTc-HMPAO, At 4 hours after re-injection with the autologous labelled white cells, static images of the extremities are obtained for 5 to 15 minutes, supplemented by SPECT/CT (40 minutes).</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 1 On PET-CT focal accumulation of F18 FDG in bone and FDG SUVmax in sites of osteomyelitis at anatomically comparable sites to those identified by the bone scan or white cell scan.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 2: Clinical/microbiological confirmation of osteomyelitis based on clinical follow-up or biopsy results.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Follow-up over three months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Image misregistration events</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline The technologists and reporting physicians will look at the images obtained to assess if there is misregistration. If it is the case and if the patient agrees the scan will be performed a second time.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time (days) between request received and completion of imaging</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline. The date of request is written by the requesting physician on the request form and the date of completion of images is written by the technologists on their worksheet and the screensaves of the study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Imaging time (minutes) total time patient on camera</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline. This data is obtained from the technologist(s) who performs the images in the Nuclear Medicine Department and complete a technologist worksheet</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of rescheduled or failed tests, failed IV access, BSL&gt;11.1 mmols etc.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline. This is obtained from the technologists who complete the technologist worksheet at the time of scanning the patient. The research nurse may also inform the technologists if the study needs to be rescheduled.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient comfort score based on the answers to the participant questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline. The study participants will select options on the questionnaire consistent with their level of comfornt during the procedures.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Image quality score (rate of score greater or equal to 3)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline. Case report forms will record image quality for FDG PET-CT and for white cell scan.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Inter-reporter agreement</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline. The case reports forms for FDG PET-CT and white cell scan. Two reporting physicians will be randomly assigned to complete the case report form in isolation. For each scan, the case report forms will be compared to each other.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Suspected osteomyelitis/septic arthritis of the extremities
Able to undergo study procedures
Able to provide informed consent
Over 18 years of age</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Under 18 years
Pregnant or lactating at the time of SPECT-CT and PET-CT scan/s
Unable to provide informed consent.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The study compares for each patient a new imaging technique: FDG PET-CT to the technique used in routine clinical practise: white cell scan. The white cell can be labelled with either 111-Indium or 99m-technetium.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/05/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>15/05/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>5/09/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>30</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Hospital Avenue,
Nedlands, 
Perth
Western Australia
6009</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Nuclear Medicine / WA PET Service</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Hospital Avenue
Nedlands
Perth
Western Australia
6009</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to compare labelled white cell scintigraphy (99mTc-HMPAO or 111-In labelled leukocytes) +/- 99mTc-HDP bone scintigraphy to FDG PET-CT in suspected osteomyelitis of the extremities to evaluate the feasibility of FDG PET-CT for infection imaging and to gain preliminary data on the agreement between FDG PET-CT and labelled white cell imaging/bone scan in infection imaging of the peripheries.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>N/A as yet</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sir Charles Gairdner Group Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Hospital Avenue
NEDLANDS, PERTH
Western Australia 
6009</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/12/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2011-019</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tatiana Segard</name>
      <address>Department of Nuclear Medicine / WA PET Service
Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Hospital Avenue
NEDLANDS, WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9346 2322</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9346 3610</fax>
      <email>Tatiana.Segard@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Elaine Campbell</name>
      <address>Department of Nuclear Medicine /WA PET Service
Nuclear Medicine Department
Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Hospital Avenue
NEDLANDS, WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9346 2322</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9346 3610</fax>
      <email>Elaine.Campbell@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Roslyn Francis</name>
      <address>Department of Nuclear Medicine/WA PET Service
Level 1, G Block
Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Hospital Ave, 
Nedlands, WA, Perth, 6009</address>
      <phone>+61893462322</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Ros.Francis@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>