<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368505">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/05/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/06/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000563561</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Bell's Palsy in Children: A Multi-centre, double-blind, Randomised, Placebo-controlled Trial to Determine Whether Prednisolone Improves Recovery at 1 Month.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A multi-centre randomised controlled trial of children aged between 6 months and 18 years presenting to emergency departments with symptoms of Bell's palsy, to determine whether treatment with oral prednisolone versus a placebo, increases the proportion of children who have complete recovery at 1 month, where complete recovery is defined as grade 1 on the House Brackmann scale. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1169-9918</utrn>
    <trialacronym>BellPIC</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Bell's Palsy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other inflammatory or immune system disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention: Prednisolone.
Prednisolone is a corticosteroid that has strong evidence for effectiveness in reducing the length of facial palsy symptoms in adults suffering from Bell's palsy.
Participants assigned to the intervention will receive 1mg/kg/day of prednisolone (dosing is based on weight categories) up to a maximum of 50mg/day for 10 days. 
The prednisolone will be administered as an oral solution as a once daily dose. 
Strategies used to monitor adherence will be a survey relating to compliance at the end of the 10 day course of treatment, in addition to the return of the bottles.  </interventions>
    <comparator>control treatment: placebo.
The placebo will be supplied in glass bottles identical to the intervention by the same supplier that produces the intervention. It will be manufactured to look and taste identical to that of the intervention
The placebo will be an oral liquid with the same ingredients as the intervention solution minus the active drug, prednisolone. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome is complete recovery at one month post randomisation, where recovery is defined as a House Brackmann facial grading score of 1. Recovery will be assesed by a specialist clinician in a face to face setting</outcome>
      <timepoint>One month post randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Complete recovery at 1 month using the Sunnybrook facial grading scale assessed by a specialist physician</outcome>
      <timepoint>One month post randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Complete recovery at 3 months using the Sunnybrook facial grading scale assessed by a research assistant</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three months post randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Complete recovery at 3 months using the House Brackmann facial grading scale assessed by a research assistant</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three months post randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Complete recovery at 6 months using the Sunnybrook facial grading scale assessed by a research assistant</outcome>
      <timepoint>Six months post randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Complete recovery at 6 months using the House Brackmann facial grading scale assessed by a research assistant</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parent/guardian and participant (where aged &gt;8 years) perception of facial nerve recovery at 1, 3 and 6 months using a lay translation of the House Brackmann facial grading scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>One, three and six months post randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life: Emotional and functional wellbeing of the participant assessed by the parent/guardian and participant using the Pediatric Quality of Life Inventory scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>One, three and six months post randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain assessed using child assigned visual analogue scale or Faces Pain Scale Revised (for participants aged 5 and older) and using parent assigned VAS for participants at any age. Pain scales are numbered 0 to 10</outcome>
      <timepoint>One, three and six months post randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prevalence of sykinesis or autonomic dysfunction using the Sunnybrook scale augmented by a synkinesis assessment questionnaire, assessed by a specialist clinician and/or research assistant</outcome>
      <timepoint>One, three and six months post randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health utilisation costs assessed via Child Health Utility 9D and via capture of cost information from the parent/guardian/participant related to in-patient, out-patient, or ED visits and to any other health facilities including general practitioner attendance for treatment or investigation</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months following randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life: Emotional and functional wellbeing of the participant assessed by the parent/guardian and participant using the Child Health Utility 9D scale and sections of the Harter scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>One, three and six months post randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life: Emotional and functional wellbeing of the participant assessed by the parent/guardian and participant using sections of the Harter scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>One, three and six months post randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients must be aged between 6 months to less than 18 years, weigh greater than or equal to 5kg, be diagnosed with Bell's Palsy by their treating doctor and have an acute onset of symptoms of Bell's palsy for less than 72 hours prior to randomisation</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Months</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Likely to be unable to complete the 1 month study assessment fo Bell's palsy symptoms
- Previously episode of Bell's Palsy or previously randomised in the study
- Contraindication to prednisolone, including: active or latent tuberculosis, systemic fungal infection, known hypersensitivity to prednisolone or any of the excipients in the liquid, diminished cardiac function, diabetes mellitus, peptic ulcer or chronic renal failure, multiple sclerosis, recent active herpes zoster or chickenpos
- use of systemic or inhaled steroid within 2 weeks prior to the onset of symptoms
- current or past oncological diagnosis
- pregnancy or breastfeeding
- currently receiving concomitant medications in which predinisolone is contraindicated
- immunisation with a live vaccine within the previous 1 month
- requirement for a live vaccine within 6 weeks of the first dose of the study drug
- signs of upper motor neurone VII nerve palsy
- diagnosis by a medical doctor of acute otitis media concurrently or within 1 week prior to the onset of Bell's palsy symptoms
-Evidence of vesicles on the ear drum suggestive of herpes simplex related Ramsay Hunt syndrome
-known facial trauma within 1 week prior to the onset of symptoms that in view of the clinician may have caused or contributed to facial palsy
- any other condition at risk of being influenced by the study treatment or that might affect completion of the study
- any concern regarding parent/guardian/participant ability to comply with the study protocol
- refusal to participate in the study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>in the event of a child being diagnosed with Bell's palsy, a senior doctor from the ED or a member of the resarch team will review the medical history for initial determination of eligibility. They will then approach the potential participant to explain the study to them, and conduct the informed consent process.
Once written informed consent has been obtained, demographic information and medical history will be elicited. Study eligibility will be confirmed and the patient will be randomised.
To randomise the patient, the senior doctor or the research team will select the lowest number study pack. This study pack will either contain prednisolone or placebo made up by the central study pharmacist according to a computer generated randomisation schedule. </concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomised stratified by site in a 1:1 ratio to one of two treatment arms: intervention (prednisolone) or matched placebo.
An independant statistician will generate a randomisation schedule using variable block sizes, stratified by site.
This schedule will be used by the central phyarmacist at RCH to undertake the blinding, labelling and distribution of the study drugs to participating sites by putting together study packs of the required drug labelled with sequential study numbers for each site. 
Randomisation at the site will be undertaken at the site by the doctor or research team by selecting the lowest numbered study pack (next pack system) from the study drug store in the ED</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size estimation:
The primary outcome is the proportion of subjects who have complete recovery at 1 month post randomisation. Based on our observational data, we expect 60% of children without prednisolone to have complete recovery at 1 month. A study in adults found an improvement of 12% with prednisolone compared with placebo which was deemed to represent a clinically important difference. 
To enable us to identify an increase in recovery from 60% to 72% or larger with 80% power requires a study with 244 subjects in each treatment group based on a two-sided test with a=0.05. Hence we aim to recruit 270 per group (540 in total) to allow for 10% loss to follow-up at 1 month. 
Statistical Analysis:
Data will be analysed on an intention-to-treat basis where primary outcome data are available. 
Primary outcome will be presented as a difference in proportions in each treatment group, with a comparison between the groups presented as a difference in proportions and as an odds ratio from a logistic regression model adjusted for site, with a 95% CI and p-value.
Secondary outcomes will be summarised by treatment group. Binary outcomes will be presented as proportions, with comparisons betwen the groups presented as a difference in proportions and as odds ratios from logistic regression adjusted for site, with 95% CIs and p-values.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>540</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,SA,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Childrens Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Clayton campus - Clayton</hospital>
    <hospital>Sunshine Hospital - St Albans</hospital>
    <hospital>The Children's Hospital at Westmead - Westmead</hospital>
    <hospital>John Hunter Children's Hospital - New Lambton</hospital>
    <hospital>Womens and Childrens Hospital - North Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>Princess Margaret Hospital - Subiaco</hospital>
    <hospital>Lady Cilento Children's Hospital - South Brisbane</hospital>
    <hospital>Gold Coast Hospital - Southport</hospital>
    <hospital>The Townsville Hospital - Douglas</hospital>
    <hospital>Logan Hospital - Meadowbrook</hospital>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
    <postcode>3021 - St Albans</postcode>
    <postcode>2145 - Westmead</postcode>
    <postcode>2305 - New Lambton</postcode>
    <postcode>5006 - North Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>6008 - Subiaco</postcode>
    <postcode>4101 - South Brisbane</postcode>
    <postcode>4215 - Southport</postcode>
    <postcode>4814 - Douglas</postcode>
    <postcode>4131 - Meadowbrook</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Franz Babl</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Murdoch Children's Research Institute
Flemington Road
Parkville
VIC 3052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra
ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Emergency Medicine Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>2/15 Lang Parade Milton QLD 4064</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Children diagnosed with Bell's palsy have a sudden weakness of facial muscles on one side of their face. Bell's palsy usually improves in children in about four to six weeks without treatment. However, in some children it may be a year before the facial weakness has completely resoved and in a small number of cases, the facial muscle weakness is permanent. 
Recent research in adults with Bell's palsy has shown that a short course of treamtent with steroids (prednisolone) led to improved recovery time. Prednisolone is believed to reduce the irritation to the facial nerve. There are no similar studies in children and, because children's bodies respond different to adults', it is not known whether a short course of prednisolone will help children to recover more quickly. Currently, some doctors treat with prednisolone and others do not resulting in confusion and variability in medical care. 

The study aims to answer the following question: In children presenting to Emergency Departments with recent onset of Bell's palsy, does treatment with prednisolone result in a higher proportion of children with recovery at 1 month compared with placebo. 

Up to 13 hospitals in Australia and New Zealand will participate in enrolling 540 children/young people, aged 6 months to 18 years, who present to ED's within 72 hours of symptom onset. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>1. Babl FE, Mackay MT,Borland ML, Herd DW, Kochar A, Hort J, Rao A, Cheek JA, Furyk J, Barrow L, George S, Zhang ,, Gardiner K, Lee KJ, Davidson A, Berkowitz R, Sullivan F, Porrello E, Dalziel KM, Anderson V, Oakley E, Hopper S, Williams F, Wilson C, Williams A, Dalziel SR; PREDICT (Paediatric Research In Emergency Departments International Collaborative) research network. 
Bell's Palsy in Children (BellPIC): protocol for a multicentre, placebo-controlled randomized trial. BMC Pediatr. 2017 Feb 13;17(1):53. doi: 10.1186/s12887-016-0702-y.

2. Babl FE, Gardiner KK, Kochar A, Wilson CL, George SA, Zhang M, Furyk J, Thosar D, Cheek JA, Krieser D, Rao AS, Borland ML, Cheng N, Phillips NT, Sinn KK, Neutze JM, Dalziel SR; PREDICT (Paediatric Research In Emergency Departments International Collaborative).
Bell's palsy in children: Current treatment patterns in Australia and New Zealand. A PREDICT study. J Paediatr Child Health. 2017 Feb 8. doi: 10.1111/jpc.13463. </publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Royal Children's Hospital, Melbourne- Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Flemington Road
Parkville VIC 3052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/03/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>35035A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Franz Babl</name>
      <address>Emergency Research Department
Murdoch Childrens Research Institute
Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Road
Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61399366748</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>franz.babl@rch.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Franz Babl</name>
      <address>Emergency Research Department
Murdoch Childrens Research Institute
Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Road
Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61399366748</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>franz.babl@rch.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Franz Babl</name>
      <address>Emergency Research Department
Murdoch Childrens Research Institute
Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Road
Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61399366748</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>franz.babl@rch.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Amanda Williams</name>
      <address>Emergency Research Department
Murdoch Childrens Research Institute
Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Road
Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61399366635</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amanda.williams@rch.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>