<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335482">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/05/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/05/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000429055</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of Treadmill Inclination on the Gait of Individuals with Chronic Hemiparesis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of treadmill inclination on angular alterations, amplitude of hip and knee movement, and stance time of the paretic lower limb in individuals with chronic hemiparesis resulting from a single ischemic or hemorrhagic stroke event</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hemiparetic gait</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The subjects were assessed for functional independence (Measure of Functional Independence) and balance (Berg Balance Scale). Spatial-temporal variables of the hemiparetic lower limb were observed as well as the angular variation of the hip, knee and ankle in the sagittal plane while the individuals walked on the treadmill at three different inclinations (0%, 5% and 10%) during 2 minutes in each condition. The treadmill was then turned on and the speed gradually increased until it reached the velocity calculated during the 10-meter test. After two minutes, a 30-second capture was made (dynamic collection). All the individuals were submitted to collections on the treadmill with inclinations of 0%, 5% and 10%. A three-minute rest period was given between the different conditions. The overall duration of the treadmill session was of approximately 14 minutes.</interventions>
    <comparator>Spatial-temporal variables were observed as well as the angular variation of the hip, knee and ankle in the sagittal plane while the individuals walked on the treadmill at three different inclinations (0%, 5% and 10%).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparing of variables between 0% and 5% of inclination as measured by digitised video analysis showed that the stance time increased 4,8%.
In the hip, flexion at initial contact increased 13%, flexion at swing increased 10,2%, there was a decrease of 13% in maximum extension during terminal stance.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After two minutes in 5% of inclination</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparing of variables between 0% and 10% of inclination as measured by digitised video analysis showed that the stance time increased 6%. 
In the hip, flexion at initial contact increased 29,7%, flexion at swing increased 25,2%. There was a decrease of 25,2% in maximum extension during terminal stance. An increase of 8,7% was also observed in range of motion in the hip.
In the knee,  flexion at initial contact increased 30%,  maximum stance flexion increased 21,4%, range of motion increased 5,8%. In the  ankle, there was decrease of 67,7% in the plantar flexed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After two minutes in 10% of inclination</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparing of variables between 5% and 10% of inclination as measured by digitised video analysis showed in the hip, flexion at initial contact increased 14,8%, flexion at swing increased 13,6%. There was a decrease of 14% in maximum extension during terminal stance. An increase of 6,0% was also observed in range of motion in the hip.
In the knee, flexion at initial contact increased 19,6%,  maximum stance flexion increased 17%. In the ankle, there was increase of 43,6% in the maximum swing dorsiflexion.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After two minutes in 10% of inclination</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Hemiparesis resulting from a single ischemic or hemorrhagic stroke event, spasticity classified between levels 0 and 2 on the Modified Ashworth Scale of Muscle Spasticity for the lower limb affected; ambulatory capacity classified between levels 3 and 5 on the Functional Ambulatory Classification - FAC; minimum sequela time of 6 months; absence of clinical signs of cardiac alterations, arrhythmia or angina (New York Heart Association, degree I); absence of other orthopedic or neurological impairment that caused gait alterations; not using orthesis on the paretic lower limb; and capacity to obey simple verbal commands.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>39</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>76</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Individuals whose systolic blood pressure rose 10mmHg during the treadmill test or whose heart rate exceeded 75% of age-adjusted maximum heart rate and those who were phobic.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/11/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>18</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Norte</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Av. Senador Salgado Filho, 3000
Caixa Postal 1524
Natal - RN
CEP 59072-970</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Brazil</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Fundacao de Apoio a Pesquisa do Rio Grande do Norte - FAPERN</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>BR 101 - KM 4 - Centro Administrativo, s/n.
Lagoa Nova
Natal - RN
CEP 59064-901</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Brazil</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study was to analyze the effects of electric treadmill inclination on the gait of individuals with chronic hemiparesis. Eighteen individuals, mean age of 55.3±9.3 years and lesion time of 36±22.8 months. The subjects were assessed for functional independence (Measure of Functional Independence) and balance (Berg Balance Scale). Spatial-temporal variables were observed as well as the angular variation of the hip, knee and ankle in the sagittal plane while the individuals walked on the treadmill at three different inclinations (0%, 5% and 10%). There was an increase in stance time between 0% and 5% and 0% and 10%. The other spatial-temporal variables did not change. During initial contact there was an increase in the hip, knee and ankle flexion angle. An increase in hip amplitude was also observed between 0% and 10%  and 5% and 10% and in knee amplitude between 0% and 10%, as well as decreased hip extension and increased dorsiflexion. Treadmill inclination promoted angular alterations such as an increase in hip, knee and ankle angle during initial contact and the swing phase and an increase in the AOM (amplitude of movement) of the hip and knee, as well as an increase in stance time of the paretic lower limb.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Not published yet. Submitted to Archives of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Comite de Etica em Pesquisa do Hospital Universitario Onofre Lopes</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Av. Nilo Pecanha, 620
Petropolis
Natal - RN
CEP 59012-300</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/05/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1/07/0007</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Brazil</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Cinthia de Carvalho Moreno</name>
      <address>Rua Praia de Buzios, 184
Nova Parnamirim
Parnamirim - RN
CEP 59151-450</address>
      <phone>55 84 3208 5778</phone>
      <fax>55 84 3234 3980</fax>
      <email>cinthiacmoreno@yahoo.com.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ana Raquel Rodrigues Lindquist</name>
      <address>Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Norte
Centro de Ciencias da Saude
Departamento de Fisioterapia
Av. Senador Salgado Filho, 3000
Caixa Postal 1524
Natal - RN
CEP 59072-970</address>
      <phone>55 84 3342 2010</phone>
      <fax>55 84 3342 2000</fax>
      <email>raquellindquist@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ana Raquel Rodrigues Lindquist</name>
      <address>Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Norte
Centro de Ciencias da Saude
Departamento de Fisioterapia
Av. Senador Salgado Filho, 3000
Caixa Postal 1524
Natal - RN
CEP 59072-970</address>
      <phone>55 84 3342 2010</phone>
      <fax>55 84 3342 2000</fax>
      <email>raquellindquist@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>