<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368957">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/07/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/08/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000863538</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of hip strengthening on outcomes following total knee arthroplasty: a randomised controlled trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of hip strengthening compared to usual care on physical performance measures following total knee arthroplasty.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1172-3570</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Post-operative total knee arthroplasty</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention involves usual care rehabilitation with additional hip strengthening exercises following total knee arthroplasty (TKA). The exercises in the usual care program are representative of usual care following TKA at Donvale Rehabilitation Hospital and focus on quadriceps, hamstring and calf muscle strengthening, and increasing knee range of movement. The exercises performed are static quadriceps contractions, knee extension over a fulcrum, forward step-ups, squats, leg press and forward step downs (for quadriceps strengthening), hamstring curls in prone and standing (for hamstring strengthening), calf raises (for calf strengthening), knee flexion, exercise bike and knee extension stretches (for increasing knee range of movement). The additional hip strengthening exercises are hip abduction, hip extension, sideways walking and hip hitching. The intervention will commence on admission to inpatient rehabilitation (approximately 7 days post-operatively). The intervention will continue for 1 hour sessions, twice daily for 10 days as an inpatient, followed by 1 hour sessions approximately twice per week for 3-4 weeks as an outpatient.The number of outpatient physiotherapy sessions delivered will be determined by the treating physiotherapist based on clinical progress. The intervention will be delivered by the treating physiotherapists. The participants will complete a home exercise program to continue the intervention independently after discharge.The exercises to be performed will be identical to those performed in the physiotherapy session with instructions for progression, e.g. the addition of resistance. The participants will be given a booklet with diagrams and descriptions of the exercises to be performed for 1 hour once daily until the final follow-up period at 6 months post-operatively. Adherence will be monitored by participant notes kept by the treating physiotherapist at the physiotherapy sessions which include the type of exercises and dosage. Following discharge from outpatient physiotherapy, patients will record daily exercises in a diary.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control treatment is the usual care received post total knee arthroplasty at the rehabilitation hospital with additional general exercises to account for the extra time spent on hip exercises by the intervention group. The general exercises are based on improving functional activities such as sit to stand, marching and walking. The control treatment will commence on admission to inpatient rehabilitation (approximately 7 days post-operatively). The usual care treatment  will continue for 1 hour sessions, twice daily for 10 days as an inpatient, followed by 1 hour sessions approximately twice per week for 3-4 weeks as an outpatient. The usual care treatment will be delivered by the treating physiotherapists. The patients will complete a home exercise program and diary to continue the intervention independently after discharge.The home exercises will be identical to those performed in the physiotherapy session with instructions for progression, e.g. the addition of resistance. The participants will be given a booklet with diagrams and descriptions of the exercises to be performed for 1 hour once daily until the final follow-up period at 6 months post-operatively. Adherence will be monitored by participant notes kept by the treating physiotherapist at the physiotherapy sessions which include the type of exercises and dosage. Following discharge from outpatient physiotherapy, patients will record daily exercises in a diary.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Isometric hip abductor muscle strength, measured using a hand held dynamometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Approximately 7 days post TKA), 3 weeks, 6 weeks, and 6 months post TKA.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Knee Injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS), a self-report measure of pain, other symptoms, function in daily living and sport/recreation, and quality of life.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (approximately 7 days post TKA), 3 weeks, 6 weeks, and 6 months post TKA.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Timed stair climb, a test of stair mobility.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Approximately 7 days post TKA), 3 weeks, 6 weeks, and 6 months post TKA.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Timed 6 minute walk test, a test of aerobic capacity and long distance walking ability.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Approximately 7 days post TKA), 3 weeks, 6 weeks, and 6 months post TKA.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Timed Up and Go, a test of mobility.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Approximately 7 days post TKA), 3 weeks, 6 weeks, and 6 months post TKA.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Timed 40m fast-paced walk test, a test of short distance walking ability.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Approximately 7 days post TKA), 3 weeks, 6 weeks, and 6 months post TKA.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>30-second chair stand test (number of repetitions), assesses sit-to-stand ability, lower limb strength and dynamic balance.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Approximately 7 days post TKA), 3 weeks, 6 weeks, and 6 months post TKA.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Step test, a functional dynamic test of standing balance.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Approximately 7 days post TKA), 3 weeks, 6 weeks, and 6 months post TKA.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Isometric quadriceps muscle strength, measured using hand held dynamometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Approximately 7 days post TKA), 3 weeks, 6 weeks, and 6 months post TKA.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lower Extremity Functional Scale (LEFS), a self-report measure of lower extremity functional status.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Approximately 7 days post TKA), 3 weeks, 6 weeks, and 6 months post TKA.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>SF-12, overall health.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Approximately 7 days post TKA), 3 weeks, 6 weeks, and 6 months post TKA.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients will be eligible if they have had a primary unilateral total knee arthroplasty for end-stage knee osteoarthritis in the previous two weeks and are admitted for inpatient rehabilitation followed by outpatient rehabilitation at Donvale Rehabilitation Hospital.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients will be excluded if they have unstable medical conditions preventing them from participating in the rehabilitation programs, history of ipsilateral hip replacement, ipsilateral hip osteoarthritis or lateral hip pain, neurological or any other conditions affecting strength or function of the lower limbs.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Eligible patients will be identified by the senior inpatient physiotherapist who is responsible for allocation of inpatients to treating physiotherapists. The treating physiotherapist will inform the patient of the study and give them the patient information sheet. If the patient is still interested in participating, the patient will  meet with the researcher to discuss any questions and sign the consent form. Eligible patients will then be randomised by a computer-generated list of random numbers. The treating physiotherapist will be given a sealed opaque envelope containing the allocated group for the patient. The patients will be told that there are two different rehabilitation programs but will not be told that one program is specifically targeting hip strengthening so that they are blinded to the nature of the two arms of the study.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer-generated list of numbers 1 and 2 will be used to allocate patients to either the hip strengthening group or the usual care group.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>
    </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>An estimate of sample size was obtained using a 2-tailed t-test, power=0.8, significance level of a=0.05 and 15% loss to attrition from 2 calculations. A within group calculation using data from tests of isometric hip abduction strength and KOOS function results before and after a hip strengthening exercise program estimated at least 45 patients per group will be required. To account for 15% loss to follow-up 52 participants per group will be recruited (total 104 participants).

Patient characteristics and baseline data will be summarized by descriptive statistics. T-tests for parametric data (or a chi-squared test for categorical data) will be used to determine the comparability of the two groups at baseline.
Intention to treat: any missing data will be replaced by the last observation carried forward. Repeated measures ANOVA (group by time) calculations to determine the main effects and interactions of group (hip abductor strengthening  vs usual care exercises) and time (repeated factor: baseline, 3 weeks, 6 weeks, 6 months) for all outcome measures. Statistical analysis will be completed using SPSS software (version 22) and the significance level set at P&lt;0.05.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/10/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>7/10/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>104</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Donvale Rehabilitation Hospital - Donvale</hospital>
    <postcode>3111 - Donvale</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Margaret Schache</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Donvale Rehabilitation Hospital
1119 Doncaster Rd, Donvale, Victoria 3111</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Donvale Rehabilitation Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1119 Doncaster Road, Donvale, Victoria, 3111</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>La Trobe University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Plenty Road and Kingsbury Drive, Bundoora, Victoria, 3086</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of this study is to compare the effects of targeted hip strengthening with those of traditional care in a total knee replacement rehabilitation program. The hypotheses of this study are: 1. The targeted hip strengthening program will result in greater performance and patient reported outcomes when compared to usual care rehabilitation. 2. The targeted hip strengthening program will result in greater increases in hip strength than the usual care rehabilitation program. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Faculty Human Ethics Committee, Faculty of Health Sciences</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>La Trobe University
Plenty Road and Kingsbury Drive,
Bundoora, Victoria, 3086</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/12/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>FHEC 14/256</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Margie Schache</name>
      <address>Donvale Rehabilitation Hospital
1119 Doncaster Rd,
Donvale, Victoria, 3111</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9841 1257</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>schachem@ramsayhealth.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Margie Schache</name>
      <address>Donvale Rehabilitation Hospital
1119 Doncaster Rd,
Donvale, Victoria, 3111</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9841 1257</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>schachem@ramsayhealth.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Margie Schache</name>
      <address>Donvale Rehabilitation Hospital
1119 Doncaster Rd,
Donvale, Victoria, 3111</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9841 1257</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>schachem@ramsayhealth.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Margie Schache</name>
      <address>Donvale Rehabilitation Hospital
1119 Doncaster Rd,
Donvale, Victoria, 3111</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9841 1257</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>schachem@ramsayhealth.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>