<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366337">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/05/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/07/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000732684</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Aboriginal Cardiovascular Omega-3 Randomised Controlled Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of omega-3 supplementation on adverse cardiovascular (CV) events among Indigenous Australians with stable coronary artery disease: A randomized controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>atherosclerosis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>factors associated with thrombus formation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>heart rate variability</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Coronary Artery Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Arm 1
a. AlaskOmega® 400200 TG 1000mg (Bioriginal, Nehterlands) (containing 400mg EPA and 200mg DHA per capsule), ensuring the patients receive 1800 mg of n-3 LCPUFA

b. softgel oral capsule

c. 3 capsules once daily for minimum 6 months


All study drugs will be given to participants in a 28-day Webster pack. Participants will have their monthly supply delivered to them (at home or clinic) by a member of the clinical team. The study participant will be asked to return the used and unused containers at each visit. Accountability of IP consumption will be evaluated by a member of the clinical team through subject interview and the counting of unused study drug. Compliance (percent) = (the number consumed) ÷ (the number prescribed) x 100. Lost or discarded IP should not be included in the calculation. This information will be recorded on a standard reporting form and monitored across the program. If compliance is less than 80%, subjects will receive additional instructions about treatment regimens.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Arm 2
placebo
a. 1000 mg oil blend containing palm oil, gelatin, glycerol, sunflower oil, rapeseed oil, mixed tocopherols and a small amount of fish oil (for taste) to aid blinding

b. softgel oral capsule

c. 3 capsules once daily for minimum 6 months.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The impact of Omega 3 (n-3 PUFA) supplementation on non-HDL-C levels assessed by serum assay</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of the impact of Omega 3 (n-3 PUFA) supplementation on reducing blood levels of triglycerides, total cholesterol, and LDL cholesterol assessed by serum assay

</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of the impact of Omega 3 (n-3 PUFA) supplementation on increasing HDL cholesterol levels assessed by serum assay

</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of the impact of Omega 3 (n-3 PUFA) supplementation on improving lipid functionality as measured by cholesterol efflux and plasma cholesteryl ester transfer protein [CETP] activity.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>6 months after randomisation</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>6 months after randomisation</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>6 months after randomisation</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of the impact of Omega 3 (n-3 PUFA) supplementation on reducing the cumulative rate of combined Major Adverse Cardiac Events - including death, non-fatal myocardial infarction or unstable angina, non-fatal stroke, revascularisation (e.g. coronary artery bypass graft, percutaneous coronary intervention) and cardiac related hospital admissions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>* Men or women, self-identified as Indigenous
* Aged over 18 years
* Have confirmed Coronary Artery Disease [CAD] (according to nationally consistent definitions): 
       * Prior hospitalisation for myocardial infarction/acute coronary syndrome
        * Prior revascularisation
        * Proven coronary stenosis &gt;50%
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>* Non-residents of South Australia  or Alice Springs, NT.
* Patients with significant neurological/cognitive impairment that prevents consent
* Hypersensitivity or documented allergy to the study drug
* Known bleeding disorder or end-stage renal disease requiring dialysis</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>central randomisation by computer</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>All analyses will be performed on an intention-to-treat basis. Comparison of baseline and end-point data will involve chi-square analysis (with calculation of OR and 95% CI) for discrete variables, Students t test for normally distributed continuous variables and Mann-Whitney tests for non-normally distributed variables. Kaplan-Meier survival curves will be constructed using time-dependent, all-cause survival and event-free survival data. Survival and event-free data will be further analysed (log-rank and Breslow test) for any differences in the number and/or timing of events. Where applicable, study end-points will be calculated as the frequency of events/patient/month of follow-up. The change from baseline markers will be analysed by a mixed-model, repeated measures ANOVA. The model will include effects of treatment, time period, and treatment-by-time interactions and changes from baseline to 12 months compared by a two-sample t-test.

Based on a two-sided alpha of 0.05, a total of 85 patients in each group (170 in total) will provide 90% power to detect a clinically significant 15% additional reduction in non-HDL cholesterol as the primary endpoint for those randomised to n-3 PUFA compared to placebo. 15% decreases in atherogenic lipid parameters are considered clinically relevant by contemporary trials and regulatory authorities for approval of lipid lowering drugs. We will aim to recruit a total of 220 participants (110:110) to allow for 25% loss to follow-up over the 12-month intervention period.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/05/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>220</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NT,SA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>South Australian Health and Medical Research Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>North Terrace
Adelaide, SA 5000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Heart disease is the single biggest cause of death for Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander people and the main reason for the difference in life expectancy between Indigenous and non-Indigenous Australians. Indigenous Australians are 3 times more likely to suffer heart attacks than non-Indigenous Australians and are 1.5 times more likely to die as a result.
Recent studies suggest that Omega 3 polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFAs) may help prevent heart attacks in people who already have coronary artery disease. 
Coronary artery disease is caused by plaque building up along the inner walls of the arteries of the heart, which narrows the arteries and reduces the blood flow to the heart. 
Omega 3 oil is a polyunsaturated fatty acid (PUFA) found in some plants, seafood, and, to a lesser extent, eggs and meat. Omega-3 is seen as "essential" because the human body can't produce it and so we must get it from foods or supplements.
Several studies around the world have shown a decrease in the risk of sudden cardiac death (SCD) associated with increased consumption of fish or fish oils.
This study is likely to be very important for understanding the main cause of death and life expectancy gap for Aboriginal people, as well as providing evidence to guide policy and clinical practice. 
The purpose of this study is to test the effectiveness of Omega-3 Long Chain Polyunsaturated Fatty Acid supplementation in Aboriginal adults with established coronary artery disease (CAD) to determine effects on factors implicated in adverse cardiovascular (CV) events including: atherogenic and protective lipid factors, Inflammatory factors, factors associated with thrombus formation, arrhythmic risk as measured by heart rate variability, and major adverse cardiovascular events (MACE).
The Aboriginal Cardiovascular Omega 3 (AC Omega 3) trial aims to find out if Aboriginal patients who have coronary artery disease will be better protected from having heart attacks by taking an Omega 3 oil supplement and if so how does it help do this. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Aboriginal Health Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Aboriginal Health Council of South Australia 
PO Box 981, Unley SA 5061</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/04/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>04-14-556</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>North Terrace 
Adelaide, SA 5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/08/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/06/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Central Australian Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Department of Health and Community Services
PO Box 721
Alice Springs
NT 0871</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/09/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC-16-381</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/04/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Alex Brown</name>
      <address>Wardliparingga Aboriginal Research Unit, SAHMRI 
PO Box 11060, Adelaide, SA 5001
</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8128 4210 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alex.brown@sahmri.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Alex Brown</name>
      <address>Wardliparingga Aboriginal Research Unit, SAHMRI 
PO Box 11060, Adelaide, SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8128 4210 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alex.brown@sahmri.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Alex Brown</name>
      <address>Wardliparingga Aboriginal Research Unit, SAHMRI 
PO Box 11060, Adelaide, SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8128 4210 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alex.brown@sahmri.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Helen Loudis</name>
      <address>SAHMRI 
PO Box 11060, Adelaide, SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8128 4493</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>helen.loudis@sahmri.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>