<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369117">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/08/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/09/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000929505</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy of cognitive behavioural therapy for social anxiety disorder, and the use of stress and sex hormones for predicting response to treatment</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy of cognitive behavioural therapy for social anxiety disorder, and the use of stress and sex hormones for predicting response to treatment</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Social Anxiety Disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will complete three sessions of cognitive-behaviour therapy (CBT) per week over four weeks (12 sessions in total). Each session will involve the participant and the therapist meeting in an individual treatment format to reduce the factors maintaining the participant's anxiety (i.e., unhelpful thoughts and unhelpful behaviours). To reduce the unhelpful thoughts, cognitive interventions are used and to reduce the unhelpful behaviours exposure therapy is used. Exposure therapy involves gradually confronting feared stimuli in a controlled and systematic way. The sessions involve:
Session 1 - Psychoeducation
Session 2 - Introduction to cognitive distortions and challenging unhelpful cognitions
Session 3 - Challenging unhelpful cognitions
Session 4 - Advanced cognitive strategies - challenging core beliefs
Session 5 - Introduction to exposure therapy and the development of an exposure hierarchy
Session 6 - Exposure I (saliva sample collection)
Session 7 - Exposure II
Session 8 - Exposure III (saliva sample collection)
Session 9 - Exposure IV
Session 10 - Exposure V (saliva sample collection)
Session 11 - Exposure VI
Session 12 - Relapse prevention. 

Participants will provide a saliva sample (10ml saliva) via the passive drool method immediately before and 30 minutes after exposure therapy in sessions 6, 8, and 10 in order to examine the endogenous cortisol response to exposure therapy.     

Therapy sessions will be delivered individually with either a provisional or registered psychologist. The duration of sessions will be 60 minutes. The treatment is manualised and the content of sessions will include psycho-education, cognitive restructuring and in-vivo exposure. 

Adherence to the treatment will be measured by monitoring session attendance. Between session adherence will be measured based on homework compliance (a rating on a scale of 0-4 is given to each participant at each session based on the homework compliance). </interventions>
    <comparator>This is an uncontrolled trial</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Social Phobia Inventory (which will measure the severity of social anxiety symptoms)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline
Post-treatment
3-month follow up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Social Phobia Scale (which will measure the severity of social anxiety symptoms)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline
Post-treatment
3-month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Social Interaction Anxiety Scale (which will measure the severity of social anxiety symptoms)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline
Post-treatment
3-month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression Anxiety Stress Scales (which will measure symptoms of depression, anxiety, and stress)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline
Post-treatment
3-month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sheehan Disability Scale (which will measure functional impairment)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline
Post-treatment
3-month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mini Social Phobia Inventory (which will measure the severity of social anxiety symptoms)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Each treatment session</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cortisol levels will be measured from saliva sample</outcome>
      <timepoint>Session 6
Session 8
Session 10</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Estrogen levels will be measured from saliva sample</outcome>
      <timepoint>Session 6
Session 8
Session 10</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progesterone levels will be measured from saliva sample</outcome>
      <timepoint>Session 6
Session 8
Session 10</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Primary diagnosis of SAD
- Aged 18 and 65 years
- Able to read and write English fluently
- Able to attend treatment sessions 3 times per week.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Pregnant (due to hormonal/cortisol changes)
- Severe depression, suicidality or psychosis
- History of abnormal menstrual cycles, hormonal disorder or endometriosis
- Intellectual or cognitive impairment that interferes with ability to provide informed consent or to engage in CBT
- History of brain injury or neurological disorder.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Pre-treatment to post-treatment and pre-treatment to 3-month changes on outcome measures will be analysed with multi-level linear models. Within-group effect sizes using Cohen's d will be calculated based on pooled standard deviations for both the entire sample using the estimated marginal means and completer samples. Clinically significant change will be determined using the Jacobson and Truax (1991) criteria based on the primary outcome measure (SPIN). Clinically significant change will be determined based on those participants meeting the Jacobson and Truax (1991) criteria for reliable change as well as scoring 2 standard deviations below the pre-treatment mean on the SPIN.
Acceptability will be measured with descriptive statistics only. 
Cortisol measures will be taken at baseline and following exposure therapy in sessions 6, 8 and 10.  To test whether baseline cortisol (prior to exposure) predicts response to CBT we will use regression with baseline cortisol level as the IV and the subjective units of distress scale (0-100 point scale of anxiety) as the DV. Change in cortisol levels across sessions will also be used as a predictor variable alongside pre-treatment social anxiety measures, and depression severity to assess capacity of cortisol change to predict treatment outcome (indexed by change on the total SPIN scores).
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>8/09/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>8/09/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>1/12/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>15</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Stopped early</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>30/12/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis>Data analysis is complete</dataanalysis>
    <withdrawnreason>Other reasons/comments</withdrawnreason>
    <withdrawnreasonother>Both investigators left the institution for new positions and it was not possible to continue data collection. </withdrawnreasonother>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>TAS</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Tasmania</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Division of Psychology 
School of Medicine
Faculty of Health
University of Tasmania
Private Bag 30 
Hobart 
TAS 7001</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Tasmania</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>School of Medicine
Faculty of Health
University of Tasmania
Private Bag 30 
Hobart 
TAS 7001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The main aims of the current study are to:  (a) investigate the efficacy of intensive individual cognitive behavioural therapy (CBT) for social anxiety disorder (SAD) and (b) examine the capacity of the stress hormone cortisol to predict treatment response to intensive CBT in individuals with SAD. This project will test these aims in a preliminary, single group open trial design. Treatment will consist of three 60-minute sessions of CBT each week over four weeks, (12 hours in total). Saliva samples will be collected at 3 of these 12 sessions in order to measure cortisol levels in response to exposure therapy.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Tasmanian Health and Medical Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/08/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H0014961</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Bethany Wootton</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
Department of Behavioural, Cognitive and Social Sciences
University of New England
Armidale
NSW, 2350</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6773 5798</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bwootton@une.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Bethany Wootton</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
Department of Behavioural, Cognitive and Social Sciences
University of New England
Armidale
NSW, 2350</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6773 5798</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bwootton@une.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Bethany Wootton</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
Department of Behavioural, Cognitive and Social Sciences
University of New England
Armidale
NSW, 2350</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6773 5798</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bwootton@une.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Bethany Wootton</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
Department of Behavioural, Cognitive and Social Sciences
University of New England
Armidale
NSW, 2350</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6773 5798</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bwootton@une.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>