<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83173">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/09/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/11/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000553370</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of an Online Fatigue Self-management Group Intervention for Adults with Multiple Sclerosis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effectiveness of an online fatigue self-management program on quality of life, fatigue and activity participation in adults with fatigue secondary to multiple sclerosis in comparison with a face-to-face group and a no intervention group</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Fatigue secondary to Multiple Sclerosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Multiple sclerosis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Fatigue Management online intervention group: This 7-week intervention will follow the published protocol outlined in Managing fatigue (Packer et al., 1995). Full participation requires 2 hours per week of online contribution. Each session is highly structured and includes an education session, practice activities, discussions and homework assignment. The topics include the importance of rest, communication and body mechanics , organizing work stations, setting priorities and standards, balancing schedules and setting goals. All teaching content, worksheets, and homework assignments are provided online. Also participants can share information, express their ideas or feelings and offer advice or support to one another. The intervention will be run by facilitators who have been trained.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group 1: No Intervention (control) Group: Participants in this group will receive only the routine care provided for people with multiple sclerosis ranging from nothing to specialist care and/or community care. The participants in this group will complete the pre, post and follow up tests.

Control group 2: Face-to-face intervention group: The intervention will follow the published protocol outlined in  Managing fatigue (T. Packer et al., 1995) including one 2-hour session weekly for 6 weeks. Each session is highly structured and includes an education session, practice activities, discussions and homework assignment. All teaching content, worksheets, handouts and homework assignments are standardized and provided. Based on self-efficacy theory (Bandura, 1997) each session incorporates strategies known to increase confidence in the ability to engage in specific behaviours. Each face-to-face course will be taught at a community setting easily accessible to group participants. Face-to-face programs will be offered at a minimum of 3 States through the Multiple Sclerosis Society of that State. Facilitators administering the interventions will be qualified health professionals (occupational therapists, nurses or social workers) who have completed a 2-day training course.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 1: Fatigue impact on persons' life measured by the Modified Fatigue Impact Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: At baseline, after completion of the intervention and 3 months later</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 2: Quality of life measured by the Leeds Multiple Sclerosis Quality of Life Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: At baseline, after completion of the intervention and 3 months later</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 3: Activity Participantion measured by the Australian version of  Activity Card Sort</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: At baseline, after completion of the intervention and 3 months later</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 1: Sleep quality measured by the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: At baseline, after completion of the intervention and 3 months later</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 2: Disease progression measured by the Patient Determined Disease Steps</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: At baseline, after completion of the intervention and 3 months later</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 3: Multiple sclerosis-associated disability measured by the Performance Scales</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: At baseline, after completion of the intervention and 3 months later</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 4: Social support measured by the Duke Social Support Index</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: At baseline, after completion of the intervention and 3 months later</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 5: Self-efficacy measured by the Multiple Sclerosis Self-Efficacy</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: At baseline, after completion of the intervention and 3 months later</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 6: Depression, anxiety and stress measured by the Depression Anxiety Stress Scale - short form</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: At baseline, after completion of the intervention and 3 months later</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Diagnosis of multiple sclerosis;
Aged 20 or older at time of selection;  
A Fatigue Severity Scale (Dittner, Wessely, &amp; Brown, 2004) score of 4 or higher (i.e. moderate-to-high fatigue impact).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Previous participation in a 'Fatigue Management' face-to-face or an online self-management group intervention.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be enrolled once time one questionnaires were completed and then allocated to group. Allocation will be concealed by central randomization of participants by sealed envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomization by using sealed envelopes.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The online program has originally been developed to provide service to the group of people who live in rural and remote areas and have no access to the face-to-face programs. Therefore a two stage allocation process will be required. On enrolment, participants with access to transportation (i.e. they can be present in community setting either by themselves or by somebody elses help one day a week for 6 weeks) will participate in face-to-face intervention. All the others will be randomly allocated to one of the two groups (an online fatigue self-management program or a no intervention group) through randomization using sealed envelopes.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>240</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Curtin University of Technology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Occupational Therapy and Social Work, GPO Box U1987, WA 6845</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Multiple Sclerosis Research Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Neurology, Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital, Hospital Avenue, Nedlands, WA 6009</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Multiple Sclerosis Society of WA (Inc)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>29 Parkhill Way, Wilson WA 6107</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>MS Society of Victoria</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>391 Hagreaves Street, Bendigo VIC 3550</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>MS Society of South Australia &amp; Northern Territory</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>274 North East Road, Klemzig, SA 5087</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>MS Society of Queensland</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>286 Gladstone Road Dutton Park QLD 4102</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>MS Society of New Soth Wales</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Studdy MS Centre, Joseph Street Lidcombe NSW, 2141</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>MS Society of Australian Capital Territory</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Gloria McKerrow House, 117 Denison Street, Deakin, ACT 2600</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>MS Society of Tasmania</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Locked Bag 4, Sandy Bay, Tas 7005</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Fatigue is one of the most troublesome symptoms of many neurological conditions, including multiple sclerosis.  It is also one of the least well managed by medication. Self-management programs provide people with chronic conditions with information, problem-solving skills and strategies to manage life with a chronic condition. This includes not only management of the symptoms but also the emotional consequences of living with a chronic condition and the day to day roles and responsibilities. Self-management interventions assist people with chronic conditions to manage their symptoms and retain a higher level of quality of life and activity participation. 
This study will test a novel way to manage fatigue secondary to multiple sclerosis. While the only evidence-based fatigue self-management program (Packer et al., 1995) is offered face-to-face in some parts of Australia, most Australians cannot access it.  
Therefore the aim of this study is to evaluate the effectiveness of an online fatigue self-management group intervention in comparison with a face-to-face group and a control group on quality of life, activity participation and fatigue impact on life among a sample of adults with multiple sclerosis. If effective, people with MS in Australia will have available an evidence-based intervention, accessible to people who face transportation barriers, the tyranny of distance or inability to attend at set times.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.livingeffectively.net.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin University Human research Ethics</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Reseach and Development, Curtin University of Technology, GPO Box U1987, WA 6845</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/09/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HR 114/2008</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Prof. Tanya L. Packer</name>
      <address>School of Occupational Therapy, Curtin University of Technology, GPO Box U1987, WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 3621</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9266 3636</fax>
      <email>t.packer@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms. Setareh Ghahari</name>
      <address>School of Occupational Therapy, Curtin University of Technology, GPO Box U1987, WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 1790</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9266 3636</fax>
      <email>s.ghahari@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms. Setareh Ghahari</name>
      <address>School of Occupational Therapy, Curtin University of Technology, GPO Box U1987, WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 1790</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9266 3636</fax>
      <email>s.ghahari@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>