<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369095">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/08/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/10/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001124527</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Early active arm movement to drive recovery following stroke.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>What is the effect of an early intensive arm movement program in patients who have suffered a stroke within the past four weeks.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Prescription of an early active movement arm program to patients with arm weakness in the acute stage post-stroke by a Physiotherapist. This will be provided in addition to usual care and routine therapy.
An evidence-based algorithm in the form of an smartphone application developed by an international working party including the applicant will be used to guide the intervention for the intervention group. This algorithm directs the therapist towards the most appropriate evidence-based therapy interventions based on the amount of residual movement in their affected arm (www.viatherapy.org/about). This will allow for the most appropriate therapy to be provided to the patient.
The research physiotherapist will prescribe a set of exercises, based on this approach, and teach them to the patient with the assistance of either their carer (where available) or the research assistant. Participants will be asked to complete their exercises for one hour each day, every day for 4 weeks. They will complete an exercise diary, and their exercises will be reviewed, progressed and updated weekly. </interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care and routine therapy provided by a Physiotherapist. This currently involves daily physiotherapy in the acute hospital, and daily sessions of up to hour each for physiotherapy and occupational therapy on transfer to the rehab setting.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>We will determine feasibility with a composite outcome including number of sessions completed and total exercise time, time spent in supervised therapy with the research assistant or caregiver, and adherence to the program. 
Participants will be required to keep a diary of exercises completed, and duration of each exercise session, with the aim of achieving 60 mins of exercise each day. This diary will be reviewed by the research physiotherapist each week, as the exercise program is updated.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline assessment on admission, post-intervention at four weeks, final follow-up at 6 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Amount of affected arm movement as determined by the accelerometry data. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline assessment on admission, post-intervention at four weeks, final follow-up at 6 months.
These will be analyses within and between groups, over time.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in upper limb function (ARAT).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline assessment on admission, post-intervention at four weeks, final follow-up at 6 months.
These will be analyses within and between groups, over time.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in amount of arm use (MAL).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline assessment on admission, post-intervention at four weeks, final follow-up at 6 months.
These will be analyses within and between groups, over time.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients admitted to the Royal Adelaide Hospital (RAH) stroke unit with a confirmed diagnosis of stroke. 

An ability to provide informed consent to participate in the study or a guardian/family members approval to participate. 

Patients within the acute stage post-stroke (first 4 weeks post­stroke, first or recurrent stroke), with an upper-limb impairment. 

All ranges of stroke severity, ages, genders and past medical history.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients deemed for palliative care. 

Patient and/or therapist refusal to provide consent. 

Patients unable to provide consent (dysphasia or language barrier), unable to seek guardian consent or inability to communicate in English). 

Patients &lt;18 years of age. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is concealed via a web based randomisation system. Once a participant consents to involvement in the study, the partipant will be assessed and randomly allocated by a third party to one of these two groups using a computer generated randomisation schedule. All databases will be secured by the use of passwords.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be performed using secure web based computer generated randomisation schedule.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The assessor who conducts the ARAT and MAL will be blinded to group allocation.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The proposed analysis of this study will involve using descriptive statistics. These will describe the amount of use and quality of use with the arm. A between-group analysis using mixed models to examine time effects, group effects and group by time effects will be conducted. As there has been no research published in this area, using family members to assist with early arm rehab, we will be conducting a pilot study with 10 participants in each group.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/11/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>30/12/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>2/05/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>20</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>28/11/2016</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>16/11/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Michelle McDonnell</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of South Australia
School of Health Sciences
GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ian Potter Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 3, 111 Collins Street
Melbourne VIC 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Purpose of study is to explore the effect of an early intensive arm movement program in patients who have suffered a stroke within the past four weeks, in order to see if greater neuroplastic changes are driven resulting in improved functional recovery.

It is hypothesised that an increase in the amount of arm movement by patients in the intervention (early intensive arm movement) group will have greater arm functional recovery compared to patients in the control (usual care and routine therapy) group.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital Research Ethics Committee (EC00192)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>North Terrace
Adelaide SA 5000
Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>31/08/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/RAH/328</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/07/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of South Australia Human Research Ethics Committee (EC00196)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research and Innovation Services 
University of South Australia
General Purpose Building
Mawson Lakes Campus
Mawson Lakes Boulevard
Mawson Lakes, SA, 5095 
Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michelle McDonnell</name>
      <address>School of Health Sciences, University of South Australia 
GPO Box 2417 
Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 1684</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michelle.mcdonnell@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michelle McDonnell</name>
      <address>School of Health Sciences, University of South Australia 
GPO Box 2417 
Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 1684</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michelle.mcdonnell@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michelle McDonnell</name>
      <address>School of Health Sciences, University of South Australia 
GPO Box 2417 
Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 1684</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michelle.mcdonnell@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>