<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="307970">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/05/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/11/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610001052022</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Acupuncture and mucosal immunity in the upper respiratory tract</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of acupuncture on mucosal immunity in the upper respiratory tract in allergic rhinitis patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Allergic Rhinitis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Each acupuncture session will last for approximately 30 minutes including 20 minutes of needle retention time between the insertion and withdrawal of the needles. These 30 minute sessions will occur twice weekly for 8 weeks.
Manipulation refers to a broad range of traditional Chinese acupuncture techniques. In this study the real acupuncture group will receive a manipulation known as ping bu ping xie (even supplementation and draining) which is a combination of simultaneous lift and thrust (ti cha bu xie) and twist and rotate (nian zhuan bu xie). This technique involves minute changes to the depth of the needle combined with minute rotation of the needle handle (less than 180o). Manipulation does not refer to either the insertion or withdrawal of the needle, but is confined to techniques applied to the needle between insertion and withdrawal.
The 8 sites for the real acupuncture group will be: GV 23, Yintang (both on the midline); LI 20, LI 4, ST 36 will be needled bilaterally. All real acupuncture points will be located according to the WHO Standard Acupuncture Point Locations in the Western Pacific Region published by the World Health Organisation, Western Pacific Regional Office.</interventions>
    <comparator>Each acupuncture session will last for approximately 30 minutes including 20 minutes of needle retention time between the insertion and withdrawal of the needles. These 30 minute sessions will occur twice weekly for 8 weeks.
Sham acupuncture protocols currently used in acupuncture research typically use either non-invasive simulations of acupuncture on real acupuncture points (such as the Streitberger/Kleinhenz, Park or Takamura placebo acupuncture needle devices) or skin-penetrating acupuncture with a normal acupuncture needle at points which are either real acupuncture points which are regarded as clinically irrelevant to the condition treated, or else at sites which do not correspond to real acupuncture points and which do not lie on known acupuncture channels/meridians. In this trial, skin-penetrating acupuncture (with 0.25 x 40 mm needles, the same needles as the real acupuncture group) at non-channel points will be used. The sham acupuncture group will be needled at a total of 8 non-channel points, and to match the real acupuncture group, these points will also be located on the head, face, hands and legs</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Modulation of the immune response in the upper respiratory tract by acupuncture in patients with allergic rhinitis</outcome>
      <timepoint>Clinical assessment will occur at weeks 0, 9 and 13 after the commencement of treatment.
Daily symptom and medication diary.
Rhinmanometry at weeks 0, 9 and 13. 
Immune parameters in salia samples at weeks 0, 3, 6, 9 and 13.
Immune paraameters in blood samples at weeks 0, 9 and 13.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction in markers of mucosal inflammation. Mucosal inflammation with be assessed by measuring cytokines in saliva.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immune parameters in saliva samples at weeks 0, 3, 6, 9 and 13 Immune parameters in blood samples at weeks 0, 9 and 13</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improved quality of life scores</outcome>
      <timepoint>A Rhinoconjunctivitis Qualify of Life Questionnare (RQLQ) will be conducted at weeks 0, 9 and 13</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Males or females aged 18-30 years with more than a 2 year history of moderate to severe allergic rhinitis, positive skin prick test and radio-allergosorbent test to Dermatophagoides. pteronyssinus or Bermunda grass.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Non allergic rhinitis; negative on skin prick test and radioallergosorbent test to D. pteronyssinus or Bermuda grass; acupuncture treatment for allergic rhinitis or specific immunotherpy in the previous 2 years; respiratory diseases, such as asthma, nasal polyposis and Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease; infectious diseases; medications which effect salivary flow and components such as systemic corticosteroids, diuretics and antidepressants.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Following consent and the respective entry criteria being met, participants will be randomly assigned to a treatment group using a computer generated, blocked random-allocation sequence by a research officer not associated with the study. This research officer will then inform the researchers of the treatment assignment. As this will be an open study neither participants nor researchers will be blinded to the treatment assignment.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomly assigned to a treatment group using a computer generated, blocked random-allocation sequence</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>29/06/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>27/10/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/05/2012</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>7/06/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>108</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>152</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>23/08/2012</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Allan Cripps</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Gold Coast campus
Griffith University  QLD  4222</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO BOx 1421
CANBERRA
ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>A/Prof Peter Smith</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Queensland Allergy Services
5/123 Nerang Street 
Southport QLD
4215</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>A/Prof Caroline Smith</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>University of Western Sydney
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith South DC  
NSW 1797</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There is evidence to suggest that acupuncture can modulate both non-specific and specific immunity. Published literature suggests that this modulation is most prominent in subjects with chronic inflammatory diseases including allergic rhinitis. Claims are also made regarding the uniqueness of acupuncture treatment in that it can have differing effects with an identical stimulus, depending on the starting state of the organism. The overall objective of this research is to investigate the effects of acupuncture on the mucosal immune response in the upper respiratory tract. We will study patients with allergic rhinitis where there is evidence that acupuncture treatment is clinically beneficial. We will also study healthy subjects without allergic disease to investigate any differences in effects that the same acupuncture treatment might have on mucosal immune responses compared to patients with allergic rhinitis.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>1.	McDonald, JL,. Cripps, AW, Smith, PK, Smith, CA, Xue, CL,  Golianu, B    
(2011) The Effects of Acupuncture on Mucosal Immunity in the Upper  
Respiratory Tract. (poster)  Gold Coast Health and Medical Research  
Conference, Seaworld Nara Resort, Gold Coast, Queensland, Australia
2.	McDonald, J.L., Cripps, A.W., Smith, P.K., Smith, C.A., Xue, C.C. &amp; Golianu, B. (2013) The Anti-inflammatory Effects of Acupuncture and Their Relevance to Allergic Rhinitis: A Narrative Review and Proposed Model. Evidence-Based Complementary and Alternative Medicine, Vol 2013, Article ID 591796.
3.	McDonald, JL,. Cripps, AW, Smith, PK, Smith, CA, Xue, CL,  Golianu, B    
(2013) The effects of acupuncture on mucosal immunity in perennial  
allergic rhinitis: a randomised, subject-and-assessor-blinded, sham- 
controlled clinical trial. World Federation of Acupuncture-Moxibustion  
Societies 8th World Conference on Acupuncture, Sydney
4.	McDonald, J.L., Cripps, A.W., Smith, P.K., Smith, C.A., Xue, C.C. &amp; Golianu, B. (2013) The effects of acupuncture on mucosal immunity in perennial allergic rhinitis: a randomised, subject-and-assessor-blinded, sham-controlled clinical trial [WFAS Sydney 2013 selected peer-reviewed conference abstracts] Australian Journal of Acupuncture and Chinese Medicine 8(2):30-31
5.	McDonald, JL,. Cripps, AW, Smith, PK, Smith, CA, Xue, CL,  Golianu, B    
(2014) The effects of acupuncture on mucosal immunity in persistent allergic rhinitis: a randomised, subject-and-assessor-blinded, sham-controlled clinical trial: final results. Australasian Acupuncture &amp; Chinese Medicine Annual Conference (AACMAC), Melbourne 
6.	McDonald, JL, Cripps, AW, Smith, PK, Smith, CA, Xue, CL, Golianu, B    
(2015) Acupuncture modulates mucosal immunity and improves signs and symptoms and quality of life in persistent allergic rhinitis. Australasian Acupuncture &amp; Chinese Medicine Annual Conference (AACMAC), Adelaide 
7.	McDonald, JL, Cripps, AW, Smith, PK, Smith, CA, Xue, CL, Golianu, B    
(2015) Acupuncture down-regulates house dust mite sepcific IgE and substance P and improves signs and symptoms and quality of life in adults with persistent allergic rhinitis Society for Acupuncture Research Conference, Boston, 2015 (poster)
8.	McDonald, J.L., Cripps, A.W., Smith, P.K. (2015) Mediators, Receptors and Signalling Pathways in the Anti-Inflammatory and Antihyperalgesic Effects of Acupuncture. Evidence-Based Complementary and Alternative Medicine, Vol 2015, Article ID 975632.
9.	McDonald, J.L., Cripps, A.W., Smith, P.K., Smith, C.A., Xue, C.C. &amp; Golianu, B. (2016) Effect of acupuncture on house dust mite specific IgE, substance P, and symptoms in persistent allergic rhinitis. Annals of Allergy, Asthma &amp; Immunology (116) 6: 497505


</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Griffith University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office for Research
Bray Centre
Nathan Campus
Griffith University
Nathan QLD 4111</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/05/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>MED/02/09/HREC</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>17/04/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Allan Cripps</name>
      <address>Gold Coast campus
Griffith University  QLD  4222</address>
      <phone>+61 7 56780711</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 56780795</fax>
      <email>allan.cripps@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Allan Cripps</name>
      <address>Gold Coast campus
Griffith University  QLD 4222</address>
      <phone>+61 7 56780711</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 56780795</fax>
      <email>allan.cripps@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Allan Cripps</name>
      <address>Gold Coast campus
Griffith University QLD  4222</address>
      <phone>+61 7 56780711</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 56780795</fax>
      <email>allan.cripps@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Allan Cripps</name>
      <address>Gold Coast Campus
Griffith University QLD 4222</address>
      <phone>+61 7 56780711</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 56780795</fax>
      <email>allan.cripps@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>