<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370409">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/03/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/04/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000445471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A phase Ib clinical evaluation of Venetoclax in combination with chemotherapy in older patients with Acute Myeloid Leukemia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A phase Ib clinical evaluation of Venetoclax in combination with chemotherapy in older patients with Acute Myeloid Leukemia</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1181-3420</utrn>
    <trialacronym>CAVEAT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute myeloid leukaemia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Leukaemia - Acute leukaemia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Dosage for Cohort 1

Induction cycle: Venetoclax 50mg oral tablet days 1-14 (of 28), Cytarabine 100mg/m2/d CIV days 8-12, Idarubicin 12mg/m2/d IV bolus days 9-10
Continuation (4 cycles) for patients achieving CR, Cri, PR, PRm: Venetoclax 50mg oral tablet days 1-14 (of 28), Cytarabine 100mg/m2/d CIV days 8-9, Idarubicin 12mg/m2/d IV bolus day 8
Maintenance (max 7 cycles at discretion of physician and patient): Venetoclax 50mg oral tablet days 1-14 (of 28)
Venetoclax monitoring through empty bottle return.

Subsequent Cohorts
Cytarabine and Idarubicin doses to remain the same for subsequent cohorts (up to 6). Venetoclax dosage increasing per cohort in increments of up to 100mg per day to a maximum possible dose of 800mg per day. Dose levels for each subsequent cohort to be determined following review by dose escalation committee.
</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the safety of Venetoclax in combination with idarubicin and cytarabine in frontline AML therapy through analysis of dose limiting toxicity during induction in each cohort. Fever, low red blood cell count, low white blood cell count, low platelet count, fever, tumor lysis syndrome and other adverse reactions/events to be assessed through review of peripheral blood examinations  and other medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Analysis during induction cycle</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite clinical response rate (LeukemiaNet criteria - Complete Response, Complete Response with Incomplete Recovery, Partial Response, Partial Marrow Response, Failure) assessed through review of bone marrow and peripheral blood examination and other medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After completion of induction therapy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Response duration by review of medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at the end of each cycle of treatment and thereafter until last date of follow up or relapse/progression</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall survival as assessed through medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>From day 1 of therapy until last date of follow-up or death</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to full hematopoietic recovery defined as median days from day 1 of investigational therapy until first day neutrophils 1 x 10^9/L and  platelets 100 x 10^9/L  (only evaluated in those with CR).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed days 1-8 and 28 of investigational therapy until end of induction cycle and thereafter at the end of each cycle until time of full hematopoietic recovery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite rate of clinical &amp; laboratory tumor lysis syndrome (severity determined using Cairo-Bishop criteria)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Upon reporting of adverse events at any point during the induction cycle.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient reported outcomes through completion of EORTC-QlQ C30 and EQ5D quality of life questionnaires</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of each cycle of continuation therapy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health resource utilization measured by reported days in hospital</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of induction and continuation cycles</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to partial hematopoietic recovery defined as median days from day 1 of investigational therapy until first day neutrophils 0.5 x 10^9/L and  platelets 50 x 10^9/L  (only evaluated in those with CRi).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed days 1-8 and 28 of investigational therapy until end of induction cycle and thereafter at the end of each cycle until time of full hematopoietic recovery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. De novo, secondary or therapy-related AML (except Acute Promyelocytic Leukaemia) without prior exposure to induction chemotherapy (not including hydroxyurea, low-dose cytarabine eg ~20mg bd, hypomethylating agents or non-chemotherapy-based investigational agents)
2. Age greater than or equal to 65
3. Or Age greater than or equal to 60 and monosomal karyotype
4. ECOG performance status 0-1
5. Adequate hepatic function as defined by bilirubin less than or equal to 1.5 x the upper limit of normal (ULN, excluding Gilberts syndrome) and AST &amp; ALT less than or equal to 2.5 x ULN (unless due to leukemic involvement) 
6. Adequate renal function as defined by eGFR&gt;50ml/min as assessed by eCCr =(140  Age) x (Weight in kg) x [1.23 if Male, 1.04 if Female]/Serum Creatinine (micromol/L)
7. WCC less than 25 x 109/L (hydroxyurea allowable to reduce WCC prior to day 1 of study)
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Prior investigational anti-leukemia agents within 14 days of day 1 of study drug; demethylating agents within 14 days of day 1 of study drug; and hydroxyurea within 24 hrs prior to day 1 of study drug.
2. Prior exposure to Venetoclax or other BCL2 inhibitors
3. Prior anthracycline exposure for previous cancer
4. Any serious medical condition which the investigator feels may lead to an unacceptably high risk of treatment related death from 5+2 induction
5. Concurrent malignancy likely to affect treatment safety or study procedures 
6. Known HIV infection
7. Uncontrolled viral hepatitis type B or C
8. Males with a female partner of childbearing potential must agree to use at least 2 effective contraceptive methods throughout the study and for 30 days following the date of last dose
9. Cardiac ejection fraction &lt;45%
10. Subject has received the following within 7 days prior to the initiation of study treatment:
*Potent CYP3A inducers such as rifampin, carbamazepine, phenytoin, and St. John's wort;
*Warfarin or requires the use of warfarin (due to potential drug-drug interactions that may potentially increase the exposure of warfarin and complications of this effect).
11. Subject has received the following within 5 days prior to the initiation of study treatment:
* CYP3A inhibitors such as fluconazole, ketoconazole, and clarithromycin.
12. Subject has consumed grapefruit, grapefruit products, Seville oranges (including marmalade containing Seville oranges) or Starfruit within 3 days prior to the initiation of study treatment.
13. Subject has a history of other malignancies prior to study entry, with the exception of:
*Adequately treated in situ carcinoma of the breast or cervix uteri;
*Basal cell carcinoma of the skin or localized squamous cell carcinoma of the skin;
*Previous malignancy confined and surgically resected (or treated with other modalities) with curative intent.
*Prior malignancy treated &gt;4 years ago and no evidence of active disease
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Up to 6 dose escalation cohorts with each subsequent cohort dose determined by dose escalation committee following analysis of dose limiting toxicity during induction. </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>This is a Baysesian study design. Up to 8 patients will be included in each cohort with the aim of demonstrating DLT to be &lt;33% at each dose. 6 dosing cohorts will be examined with the total number of participants not exceeding 48.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1 / Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>12/07/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>48</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - City campus - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
    <postcode>3050 - Royal Melbourne Hospital</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Alfred Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Commercial Road, Melbourne, Victoria, 3004</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Victorian Cancer Agency</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>50 Lonsdale St, Melbourne, VIC, 3001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Abbvie</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1 North Waukegan Road North Chicago, IL 60064</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of this trial is to evaluate the safety and efficacy of venetoclax in combination with chemotherapy for the treatment of acute myeloid leukaemia (AML) in elderly patients. 
Who is it for? 
You may be eligible to participate in this trial if you are aged 60 or over with monosomal karyotype, or aged 65 or over with any karyotype, and have been diagnosed with AML for which you have received no induction chemotherapy. 
Study details 
All participants enrolled in this trial will be administered Venetoclax in combination with modified-dose chemotherapy. The dose provided will depend on the time of enrolment - each sequentially enrolled group of participants will be administered with a slightly higher dose than the previous group, pending a review of the safety of the previous dose. Participants will have an induction treatment consisting of 14 days  Venetoclax tablets, 5 days IV Cytarabine   and 2 days IV Idarubicin. For participant achieving a response to treatment there will be up to 4 further cycles of 14 days Venetoclax, 2 days Cytarabine and 1 day Idarubicin or until adequate blood count recovery. 
Participants will be assessed through blood samples taken daily during initial hospitalisation and then at the end of each cycle of treatment, bone marrow samples taken 3 times during induction and then every other cycle as well as a physical exam every cycle in order for researchers to monitor whether the treatment is safe and whether it is effectively treating the AML. 
It is hoped that the findings of this trial will provide information on the optimal dose of Venetoclax in combination with chemotherapy for the safe and effective treatment of AML in elderly patients.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Health Human Research Ethic Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Commercial Road, Melbourne, VIC, 3004</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/02/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/09/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Andrew Wei</name>
      <address>Alfred Hospital, Commercial Road, Melbourne, VIC, 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 90763451</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 90762298</fax>
      <email>a.wei@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Nola Kennedy</name>
      <address>Malignant Haematology &amp; Stem Cell Transplantation Service, Alfred Hospital, Commercial Road, Melbourne, VIC, 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 90762217</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 90765531</fax>
      <email>n.kennedy@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Andrew Wei</name>
      <address>Alfred Hospital, Commercial Road, Melbourne, VIC, 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 90763451</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 90762298</fax>
      <email>a.wei@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Nola Kennedy</name>
      <address>Malignant Haematology &amp; Stem Cell Transplantation Service, Alfred Hospital, Commercial Road, Melbourne, VIC, 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 90762217</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 90765531</fax>
      <email>n.kennedy@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>