<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370614">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/04/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/05/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000657426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Percutaneous cannulation of the thoracic duct in acute pancreatitis to achieve external lymph drainage</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Developing and evaluating techniques for peripheral transvenous cannulation of the
thoracic duct to study the role of lymph in acute pancreatitis and critical illness</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1175-6314</utrn>
    <trialacronym>PerCTD</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute Pancreatitis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other inflammatory or immune system disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a method development study comprised of two sequential phases. The second phase is dependent on the success of the first. 
Phase 1: Inguinal lymphangiogram performed by a consultant interventional radiologist. 6 patients with acute pancreatitis exhibiting a SIRS response will be recruited and consented. Using a sterile technique under local anaesthetic and ultrasound guidance an inguinal lymph node will be injected with 3-6mL of iodized oil.  Fluoroscopy will then be used to identify opacification of the thoracic duct and its junction with the venous system. Optimal timing of this opacification will also be assessed. This is expected to take up to 2.5 hours. The volume of contrast and number of lymph nodes injected may need to be varied to improve the fidelity of this project depending on initial results. 

Phase 2: Inguinal lymphangiogram, percutaneous thoracic duct cannulation and external drainage of thoracic duct lymph performed by a consultant interventional radiologist.
12 patients with acute pancreatitis exhibiting a SIRS response will be recruited and consented. Patients in this phase will receive all three interventions immediately after each other provided that the proceeding intervention is successful. 
Intervention 1:  An inguinal lymphangiogram (developed in Phase 1) will be used to visualise the thoracic duct. Success of the inguinal lymphangiogram in identifying whether the junction of the thoracic duct with the venous system is suitable for cannulation will be determined by the interventional radiologist performing the procedure. 

Intervention 2:  Under a sterile technique and ultrasound guidance the venous system will be accessed from the left antecubital fossa in a manner similar to a PICC line.  Thoracic duct cannulation will be attempted from the subclavian vein using standard interventional radiology techniques, guided by lymphangiography and confirmed by the aspiration of lymph. A Pruitt type balloon catheter (or similar) will be placed to simultaneously occlude the thoracic duct and achieve external lymph drainage.  Interventions 1 &amp; 2 are expected to  take up to 2.5 hours. Intervention 2 will only occur if intervention 1 is successful. This will be determined by the successful aspiration of lymph from the thoracic duct catheter. The guide wires and catheters used may need to be varied to improve the success of this intervention. 

Intervention 3: The thoracic duct catheter will be connected to a biliary drainage bag to facilitate external thoracic duct lymph drainage for 7 days while the patient is in hospital.  Matched peripheral plasma samples will be taken 12 hourly.  The volume of lymph drained will be replaced mL:mL with either Plasmalyte or 4% albumin.  SIRS, APACHE II and modified Marshall scores along with daily CRP will be recorded to assess patient response to external lymph drainage.  Intervention 3 will only occur if interventions 1 &amp; 2 are successful.. If the thoracic duct catheter stops draining lymph before the end of 7 days regular (12 hourly hep saline (50IU in 3mL) flushes will be trialled to maintain patency.  
</interventions>
    <comparator>No control. </comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Successful aspiration of lymph from catheter placed in the thoracic duct. 

When the interventional radiologist believes the thoracic duct catheter has been correctly placed in the thoracic duct under fluoroscopic visualisation this will be confirmed by attaching a 5mL syringe to the end of the thoracic duct catheter. If lymph is aspirated this will confirm the correct placement of the catheter. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Aspiration of lymph at time of attempted thoracic duct cannulation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Achieving 7 days of continual lymph drainage from the thoracic duct catheter without occlusion of the catheter. Occlusion will be assessed with firstly with heparinized saline flushing and if it does not resolve with contrast fluoroscopy. </outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days following cannulation if continual lymph drainage achieved
Time following cannulation that catheter becomes occluded.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in SIRS score from recruitment until the end of 7 days </outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days following cannulation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in APACHE II score from recruitment to the end of 7 days</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days following cannulation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The change in serum CRP level will be calculated by subtracting the CRP level at 7 days following cannulation from the CRP on day of cannulation. </outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days following cannulation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Modified Marshall score from recruitment until the end of 7 days.</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days following cannulation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Project 1: Patients over 40 with acute pancreatitis admitted to Auckland City Hospital.

Project 2: Patients over 18 with acute pancreatitis exhibiting a SIRS response within 24 hours of admission to Auckland City Hospital. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>*Pregnancy
*Concurrent MODS 
*Requirement for either a central venous catheter or PICC line prior to thoracic duct cannulation
*Coagulopathy
*Patients actively bleeding
*Previous thoracic duct injury, intervention or ligation 
*Previous left neck dissection
*Previous groin dissection 
*Any skin or subcutaneous infection in the groin or antecubital fossa
*Previous deep vein thrombosis or pulmonary embolism 
*Platelet count greater than 800
*Concurrent malignancy
*Previous mastectomy or axillary node dissection to the same side as proposed cannulation</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>N/A</concealment>
    <sequence>N/A</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This study is a method development study comprised of two sequential projects, hence no randomisation. The first project with 6 patients will develop the inguinal lympangiogram procedure to identify the junction of the thoracic duct with the venous system. The second project will use the inguinal lymphangiogram technique to identify the thoracic duct and attempt to cannulate it. If this is successful lymph will be drained externally for 1 week. </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>This study is designed to develop a methodology rather than to assess efficacy. The sample sizes for projects 1 and 2 were determined on clinical grounds taking into account anatomical variability and disease severity to develop the methodology of percutaneous thoracic duct cannulation before it is formally evaluated in an appropriately powered RCT. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>18</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Auckland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Research Office
Level 10
49 Symonds Street
Private Bag 92019
Auckland Mail Centre 1142</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Maurice and Phyllis Paykel Trust</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 37 760 
Parnell
Auckland 1151 
New Zealand 
 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Abstract
Background
The systemic inflammatory response syndrome (SIRS) and multiple organ dysfunction syndrome (MODS) are features of critical illness that result from a range of aetiologies including trauma, sepsis, haemorrhagic shock and acute pancreatitis. Persistent organ failure is the most common cause of mortality in critical illness. Experimental evidence indicates that gut-lymph draining via the thoracic duct drives SIRS and MODS. Human studies (to confirm the toxicity of thoracic duct lymph in critical illness, analyse its composition and to develop lymph targeted treatments) have been hampered by the inability to easily and reliably access thoracic duct lymph.

Aim
The aims of this study are 
i)	to optimise the technique of thoracic duct lymphangiography
ii)	to develop and evaluate a safe, percutaneous, peripheral and transvenous technique of thoracic duct cannulation
iii)	to determine the composition of human thoracic duct lymph and matched plasma samples during acute pancreatitis
iv)	to identify factors responsible for toxicity of human thoracic duct lymph

Methods
This application contains three projects in patients with acute pancreatitis. 
The first project (n=6) will confirm the technical feasibility and time required to achieve an optimal thoracic duct lymphangiogram by ultrasound guided contrast injection of an inguinal lymph node.  
The second project (n=12) will refine and develop the technique of peripheral transvenous cannulation of the thoracic duct (PTCTD). 
The third project will use the thoracic duct lymph collected from patients during the course of the second project to determine the composition and toxicity of the lymph using established laboratory assay platforms.  The composition of matched lymph and plasma will also be compared as part of this study.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern A Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Health and Disability Ethics Committees
Ministry of Health
Freyberg Building
20 Aitken Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/04/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>16/NTA/35</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/03/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>John Windsor</name>
      <address>Department of Surgery
The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland Mail Centre 1142
</address>
      <phone>+64 21 901 930</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.windsor@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>John Windsor</name>
      <address>Department of Surgery
The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland Mail Centre 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 21 901 930</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.windsor@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>John Windsor</name>
      <address>Department of Surgery
The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland Mail Centre 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 21 901 930</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.windsor@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>John Windsor</name>
      <address>Department of Surgery
The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland Mail Centre 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 21 901 930</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.windsor@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>