<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370146">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/03/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/05/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000638437p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of Shuzi Technology on Inflammation</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of Shuzi Technology on Inflammation in adults diagnosed with mild to moderate inflammatory condtitions</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1179-8237</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Inflammatory Conditions</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Rheumatoid arthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Autoimmune diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other inflammatory or immune system disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will attend the clinic for an initial consultation where a Patient Info Sheet, Consent form and SF36 Health Questionnaire will be completed and signed. The CO-Investigator is a qualified lymphatic therapist who has worked with a number of inflammatory conditions, will assess and review all documentation to ensure the inclusion criteria are met.  It is proposed that the participants will provide documentation from their doctor to confirm their inflammatory condition. Participants will receive blood test paperwork and a shuzi bracelet. The Shuzi sports bracelet is a nylon bracelet embedded with a 2mm x 0.5mm metal disk composed of gold, nickel, zinc, and copper. Prior to embedding the metal disk into the bracelet, the disk is exposed to audio frequencies which were determined over a year of research and experiments to provide a proprietary range that is between 20Hz and 20kHz for 60 minutes, using a computer program.  The volume of the audio is 85dB. Each participant will present at PathLab for blood testing.  Blood will be analysed for CBC, CRP and DHEA with results being sent directly to the Clinic after analysis at the PathLab.  On completion of blood testing, participants will put on the Shuzi bracelet and will wear it continuously throughout the six weeks including sleeping and showering.  A diary will be issued to the Candidates to fill out each day.  This will record if they have worn the bracelet or removed for any circumstances. Subjects will wear the bracelet for 6 weeks and then return to the clinic for a follow-up consultation and completion of another SF36 questionnaire.  They will be issued with another blood test form and return to PathLab for repeat blood work, once completed they will return the Shuzi bracelet to the Clinic.</interventions>
    <comparator>All participants wear a bracelet.  1/2 of the group will wear a nylon bracelet with the metal disk impeded in the bracelet and 1/2 will wear a nylon bracelet without a metal disk..</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>C-Reactive Protein. Standard serum assay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timeline 1: Baseline Timeline 2: 6 Weeks.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Complete Blood Count. Standard assay</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timeline One: Baseline, Timeline Two: 6 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dehydroepiandrosterone.  Standard serum assay</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timeline One:  Baseline, Timeline Two: 6 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>SF36 Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timeline One: Baseline, Timeline Two: 6 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Diagnosed with inflammatory conditions including Rheumatoid Arthritis, Osteoarthrities and bursitis, formally diagnosed by a GP or specialist.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnant or maybe pregnant
Currently undertaking immune suppressing drugs or anti-inflammatory drugs
Active severe inflammatory condition and/or active severe viral condition e.g flu</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Standard randomisation software with sealed opaque envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>Standard randomisation software</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>This is an independent pilot trial funded by the manufacturer.  Therefore the sample size is based on a pure data collection at this stage and a power calculation has not been performed.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/06/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Withdrawn</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason>Other reasons/comments</withdrawnreason>
    <withdrawnreasonother>Protocol was not approved by the ethics committee due to variables of blood results that would occur between inflammatory and non-inflammatory conditions.</withdrawnreasonother>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>New Zealand Centre of Integrated Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Suite 6, Promed House, 10th Avenue, Tauranga  3110</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Shuzi New Zealand Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>10 Selwyn Street
Tauranga   3110</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Anna Rolleston</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Cardiac Clinic
103 Third Ave
Tauranga  3110</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The Shuzi bracelet has been available for a number of years on the market and reported changes to date are reduced pain, a sense of calmness and reduction of arthritic conditions.  In order for this technology to be recognised as a product that can provide anti-inflammatory support, a high quality research pilot trial showing changes to inflammatory markers will allow the opportunity for further research to be undertaken to acknowledge that this product can assist condition based issues.  Fourty participants will be recruited from the Tauranga area. To be eligible for enrollment individuals will be diagnosed with mild to moderate inflammatory condition. At the initial consultation the candidate will fill out and sign a Patient Info Sheet, Consent form and SF36. All documentation will be reviewed to ensure inclusion criteria is met.  Participants will undertake blood testing of Complete Blood Count (CBC), C-Reactive Protein (CRP) and dehydroepiandrosterone(DHEA). After blood tests have been taken a shuzi bracelet will be issued.  This study does have a control group of 20 candidates and therefore only 20 candidates will receive a bracelet with the technology built in to the bracelet and the remaining 20 candidates will have a bracelet with no technology. Subjects will wear the bracelet for 6 weeks and then return to the clinic for a followup consultation, to complete another SF36 questionnaire and be reissued with a blood test form to repeat blood work.  The bracelet will then be returned to the clinic upon completion of the blood work.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Ethics Department
Freyberg Building
Reception  Ground Floor
20 Aitken Street
Wellington  6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/05/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Anna Rolleston</name>
      <address>Cardiac Clinic
103 Third Ave
Tauranga  3110</address>
      <phone>+6475786624</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>anna@thecardiacclinic.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Desiree De Spong</name>
      <address>New Zealand Centre of Integrated Health
PO Box 15066
Tauranga 3144
or Suite 6, Promed House, 71 Tenth Ave, Tauranga  3110</address>
      <phone>+64275443424</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>desiree@aetiology.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Anna Rolleston</name>
      <address>Cardiac Clinic
103 Third Ave
Tauranga  3110</address>
      <phone>+6475786624</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>anna@thecardiacclinic.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Desiree De Spong</name>
      <address>NZCIH
PO Box 15066, Tauranga 3144
or Suite 6, Promed House, 71 Tenth Ave, Tauranga</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>