<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343160">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/07/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/07/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000710921</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Antenatal Education for Epidural Anaesthesia in Labour - A Pilot Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>To determine the efficacy of the use of multimedia patient education technology in the antenatal education process, particularly regarding the use of epidural anaesthesia in labour, in primigravida women who are planning on having a normal vaginal delivery.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pain during labour in primigravida women planning to have a normal vaginal delivery.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Antenatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Childbirth and postnatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention arm will be given the opportunity to watch a multimedia patient education module (approximately 20 minutes in length) on the use of epidural anaesthesia in labour during their antenatal education classes at 32 weeks gestation.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control arm will have the usual antenatal education regarding the process of labour which includes being given a pamphlet promulgated by the Australian Society of Anaesthetists.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The study aims to examine the opinions of women regarding their concerns about pain relief in labour by comparing the efficacy of a pamphlet and of a multimedia module in explaining risks and benefits of epidural anaesthesia in labour and to determine whether patient anxiety levels are influenced by being given information regarding epidural anaesthesia in labour.  Patients will be asked to complete a knowledge based questionnaire prior to information delivery as well as a state-trait anxiety questionnaire.  A knowledge questionnaire and anxiety questionnaire will also be completed by the patients after receiving the information.  At 2 week post delivery of a healthy baby the midwife who conducted the classes will get the patients to complete a questionnaire regarding their experience with epidural anaesthesia during the birthing process.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The outcome will be assessed immediately after information delivery and also at 2 weeks post delivery during the patients routine checkup.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To obtain subjective assessment of patients regarding whether they believed the antenatal education that they received adequately prepared them for what they experienced, particularly regarding epidural anaesthesia in labour.</outcome>
      <timepoint>In the two weeks following delivery of a healthy baby.  This will be assessed via a postnatal questionnaire conducted by the midwife during the patients postnatal check up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients must be primigravida women who are planning on having a normal vaginal delivery.  Patients must be aged between 20 and 40 years, have no past history of epidural or spinal anaesthesia, english must be their first language, have achieved grade 11 or greater secondary education and be able to read a plain English patient information consent form.  Patients also need to be attending the antenatal education classes conducted by Ms Cathryn Curtin at the Epworth Freemasons Maternity Hospital.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria are maternal age less than 20 or greater than 40 years, English not primary language, poor eyesight and/or hearing, previous epidural or spinal anaesthesia and planned caesarean section.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients who fit the inclusion criteria will be identified by their Obstetrician - Dr Len Kliman.  Dr Kliman will explain the study and instruct patients to confirm their willingness to participate in the trial when they book their antenatal classes.  During classes confirmed participants will be randomly allocated to the pamphlet or multi media module groups.  Patients will be randomly allocated into the two groups using sealed envelopes produced by the Clinical Trials and Research Centre.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/08/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Epworth Foundation - Foot and Ankle Research Fund</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>32 Erin Street
Richmond
Vic 3121</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Epworth Foundation - Foot and Ankle Research Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>32 Erin Street
Richmond
Vic 3121</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>We hypothesise that multi-media patient education technology is superior to pamphlet delivery of this information.  A secondary hypothesis is that increased understanding of epidural anaesthetic in labour will increase patient anxiety levels.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Epworth Healthcare</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>89 Bridge Road
Richmond
Victoria
3121</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/08/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kate Claxton</name>
      <address>Epworth Centre
Suite 6.3, Level 6
32 Erin Street
Richmond
Vic 3121</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9428 9944</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9428 3444</fax>
      <email>kate@footsurgeon.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kate Claxton</name>
      <address>Epworth Centre
Suite 6.3, Level 6
32 Erin Street
Richmond
Vic 3121</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9428 9944</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9428 3444</fax>
      <email>kate@footsurgeon.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kate Claxton</name>
      <address>Epworth Centre
Suite 6.3, Level 6
32 Erin Street
Richmond
Vic 3121</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9428 9944</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9428 3444</fax>
      <email>kate@footsurgeon.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>