<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370439">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/03/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/04/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000437460p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A pilot study evaluating the safety of intravenously administered human amnion epithelial cells for the treatment of hepatic fibrosis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot study evaluating the safety of intravenously administered human amnion epithelial cells for the treatment of hepatic fibrosis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1181-4339</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>cirrhosis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>liver fibrosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a pilot study to examine the safety of human amnion epithelial cells administered to patients with compensated cirrhosis.  To determine whether patients have compensated cirrhosis and to avoid including patients with decompensated cirrhosis, the hepatic venous pressure gradient will be measured, which is the most accurate way to make this determination. Human amnion epithelial cells ( hAEC) are derived from the placenta, specifically the amnion epithelium that lines the sac in which the fetus develops, We have shown that hAEC have intrinsic immune modulating characteristics that can induce hepatic fibrosis regression and stimulate liver regeneration. We have developed a method to isolate the cells that is free of animal products and compliant for clinical use. Once isolated, the cells are frozen until ready for infusion, i.e. they do not undergo any further manipulation or expansion.  Twelve patients in total will be studied.  They will be divided into four cohorts and each cohort will include three patients.  In Cohort 1, three patients will receive hAEC (500,000 cells/kg) as a single intravenous injection. If no serious adverse events (SAE) occur within 5 days, a further three patients will be enrolled in Cohort 2 and receive hAEC (1,000,000 cells/kg) as a single IV injection. If no SAE occur within 5 days, a further three patients will be enrolled in Cohort 3 and receive hAEC (1,000,000 cells/kg) as a single IV injection at 0 and 30 days. If no SAE occur within 5 days, a further three patients will be enrolled in Cohort 4 and receive hAEC (1,000,000 cells/kg) as a single IV injection at days 0, 30 and 60.  The hAEC will be administered by peripheral intravenous infusion over 30 minutes at a concentration of 250,000 cells/ml. The number of cells infused and the number of infusions will be determined by the specific cohort. The cell infusions will be done by trained nurses in the Clinical Trial Centre of the Monash Health Translational Research Facility. Patients will be monitored for 24 hours after the infusion in the Clinical Trial Centre by nursing and medical personnel. .The CTC has direct access to Monash Medical Centre.</interventions>
    <comparator>Four cohorts of three patients each will be assessed (12 patients in total).  The first cohort will be given a single infusion of 500,000 cells/kg, the second cohort will be given a single infusion of 1,000,000 cells/kg, the third cohort will be given an infusion of 1,000,000 cells/kg on days 0 and 30, and the fourth cohort will be given an infusion of 1,000,000 cells/kg on days 0, 30 and 60.</comparator>
    <control>Dose comparison</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome of this first-in-man study is to determine the safety and tolerability of human amnion epithelial cells in patients with compensated cirrhosis.  Safety will be determined by clinical assessment during the cell infusion with monitoring for 24 hours afterwards in the Clinical Trial Centre.  Safety assessment for days 2 - 4 will be by telephone and on day 5 at a clinic visit. A further clinical assessment will occur 8 weeks after the infusion. 
There is a possible risk of local and systemic side effects akin to those following blood transfusions. We will specifically assess for local skin reactions, anaphylaxis (acute deterioration of respiratory and cardiovascular parameters (trouble breathing, shortness of breath, changes in blood pressure or heart rhythms).  We will also look for infection or features of cell rejection with changes in liver or kidney tests. 
An independent group of experts  will also evaluate our study (a data and safety monitoring board). These experts will review the data from each infusion and must give approval to enrol the next patient.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patients will be assessed during cell administration then daily for 5 days. A further assessment will occur 8 weeks following cell administration.  All patients will be followed at 6 monthly intervals for two years. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcomes will include assessment of efficacy (reduction in liver fibrosis or regression of cirrhosis).  These data will be used to inform phase 2 clinical trials.  Several methods will be used for this assessment.  The most accurate method of assessing the risk of developing serious complications of cirrhosis (ascites, variceal bleeding, death) is to measure the pressure in the veins entering the liver (the hepatic venous pressure gradient).  This is done by a radiologist who places a catheter into a vein in the neck and guides it into the liver where the pressure is measured.  The procedure is done with sedation and takes about 20 minutes.  If the pressure measurement is lower after the cell infusion, this would indicate that the treatment is effective in treating cirrhosis. We will also use Fibroscan, a non-invasive test similar to an ultrasound, that estimates the amount of collagen (scar tissue) in the liver and also blood tests that estimate the amount of collagen. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurement of the hepatic venous pressure gradient will be done twice, once before the cells are infused and once at 8 weeks following the last cell infusion (this time varies according to the patient cohort).  The Fibroscan and blood tests will be performed at baseline, on day 5 after each infusion and 8 weeks after the last infusion. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adult female or male patients, age 18 years to 70 years

Liver disease due to non-alcoholic fatty liver disease, alcohol related liver disease (must be abstinent for at least 3 months), hepatitis C virus infection (treated or not treated), hepatitis B virus infection (on nucleoside analogues with normal ALT and HBV DNA viral load) or inactive phase, HIV co-infection with HCV/HBV with virological suppression &gt;12 months, cryptogenic cirrhosis, haemochromatosis (on maintenance venesection)

Cirrhosis, defined as one of: liver biopsy confirming cirrhosis, transient elastography (Fibroscan) with a liver stiffness measurement (LSM) &gt;12.5 kPa, FIB 4 &gt;3.25, or clinical and radiological features that in the opinion of the investigator are consistent with a diagnosis of cirrhosis. Compensated cirrhosis will be defined as a hepatic venous pressure gradient between 6 - 10 mmHg.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients will be excluded from the study if they have current or previous episodes of decompensated liver disease, including variceal haemorrhage, hepatic encephalopathy, ascites, are listed for liver transplantation, have primary biliary cholangitis, autoimmune hepatitis or other active autoimmune disease (IgG &gt;2xULN), renal insufficiency (eGFR &lt; 70mL/min/1.73m2), HIV infection (untreated or uncontrolled viraemia), HBV DNA &gt;200 IU/mL, fulminant hepatitis (severe acute hepatitis withencephalopathy), primary sclerosing cholangitis, portal/hepatic vein thrombosis, significant comorbidity (chronic heart failure, COAD, pulmonary hypertension, diabetes or other in the investigators opinion), pregnancy, fibrotic liver disease other than cirrhosis (nodular regenerative hyperplasia), inability or unwillingness to provide informed consent</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Four cohorts of three patients each will be assessed (12 patients in total). The first cohort will be given a single infusion of 500,000 cells/kg, the second cohort will be given a single infusion of 1,000,000 cells/kg, the third cohort will be given an infusion of 1,000,000 cells/kg on days 0 and 30 and the fourth cohort will be given an infusion of 1,000,000 cells/kg on days 0, 30 and 60. </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>There will be no formal statistical analysis of this phase I trial, but descriptive and inferential statistical analysis will be conducted to develop a sound statistical framework for later phase clinical trials of hAEC cell therapy</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>9/01/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>12</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Clayton campus - Clayton</hospital>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>246 Clayton Road, Clayton Victoria 3168</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Monash Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>246 Clayton Road, Clayton Victoria 3168</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Monash University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Wellington Road, Clayton, 3800, Victoria</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>We propose a first-in-man clinical trial of human amnion epithelial cells (hAEC), a type of stem cell obtained from the placenta, The placenta is normally discarded after delivery so the use of hAEC does not pose any ethical issues. In laboratory studies we have shown that these cells can reduce liver fibrosis (scar tissue in the liver) and stimulate regeneration of liver cells..  Worldwide, cirrhosis is the sixth most common cause of death and liver transplantation remains the only chance for survival for some people with cirrhosis. In this study we will assess the safety and tolerability of giving hAEC to patients with stable liver cirrhosis.  Our long-term goal is to develop hAEC as a clinically useful therapy to reduce the need for liver transplantation. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Monash Medical Centre
Level 2, I Block
246 Clayton Road
Clayton VIC 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/02/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>William Sievert</name>
      <address>Gastroenterology and Hepatology Unit
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Road
Clayton VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+613 9594 3177</phone>
      <fax>+613 9594 6250</fax>
      <email>William.Sievert@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>William Sievert</name>
      <address>Gastroenterology and Hepatology Unit
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Road
Clayton VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+613 9594 3177</phone>
      <fax>+613 9594 6250</fax>
      <email>William.Sievert@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>William Sievert</name>
      <address>Gastroenterology and Hepatology Unit
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Road
Clayton VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+613 9594 3177</phone>
      <fax>+613 9594 6250</fax>
      <email>William.Sievert@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>William Sievert</name>
      <address>Gastroenterology and Hepatology Unit
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Road
Clayton VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+613 9594 3177</phone>
      <fax>+613 9594 6250</fax>
      <email>William.Sievert@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>