<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363947">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/04/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/04/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000425796</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Office hysteroscopy in the diagnosis of Cervical Intra-epithelial Neoplasia.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Office hysteroscopy in the diagnostic workup of cervical glandular intraepithelial neoplasia in patients with cervical intraepithelial neoplasia.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1141-2377</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cervix cancer screening</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Cervical (cervix)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Office hysteroscopy for evaluation of endocervix in cases with CIN

The office hysteroscopic procedure is carried out with:
1. A 4-mm continuous-flow office operative hysteroscope with a 30-degree rod lens 1.9-mm optic.
2. A xenon light source of 175 W. Because the endocervix
is generally small-sized, the light intensity should be as low as possible to avoid the reflection phenomenon, which may hamper the identification of the acetowhite areas.
3. A digital endo-camera
4. A high resolution monitor .
5. Distension of the endocervix is obtained using saline solution.  

The next step is the application of 2 mL of 5% acetic acid on the endocervix through the operative channel.  

a vaginoscopic approach may be used. The vagina may be distended by introducing the fluid distention medium through the hysteroscope placed into the lower vagina at the same pressure used for the subsequent distention of the uterine cavity. As soon as the external uterine orifice is visualized, the irrigation of saline is stopped and a syringe with 2 mL of 5% acetic acid is connected to the inflow channel of the hysteroscope. In this way the impregnation of the cervix may be directly and clearly visualized, provided that a few minutes elapse before reconnecting the continuous-flow irrigation to the hysteroscope
the duration of patient observations depending on the results of gold standard histopathology (period from diagnostic hysteroscopy till results of histopathology)
The observation period of the trial will be 6 months 
</interventions>
    <comparator>N/A</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>assessment of the ability of office hysteroscopy for diagnosis of endocervical lesions. The assessment based on visualization of the endocervical abnormalities by office hysteroscopy and after application of 5 % acetic acid to delineate the abnormalities. these finding will be compared to endocervical curettage. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At time of examination, all abnormalities will be recorded and will be compared with the results of endocervical curettage. At the end of the study the overall results of hysteroscopy will be compared with the overall results of endocervical curettage.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The prevalence of endocervical lesions in patents referred with abnormal cytology and/or abnormal visual inspection of the cervix after application of acetic acid (VIA) testing of the cervix.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of the study. the percentage of histological proven endocervical abnormalities will be calculated.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1-	  negative pregnancy test.
2-	  histopathologically proven SIL.
3-	 Had a satisfactory colposcopic examination (visualization of the squamocolumnar junction and the entire lesion)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>21</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1-	Suspicion or evidence of invasive lesions on Papanicolaou smear, biopsy, or colposcopic examination.
2-	Positive pregnancy test.
3-	Current pelvic inflammatory disease, cervicitis, or other gynecological infection
4-	Poor compliance.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Data analysis will be performed with statistical software (SPSS version 20, IBM Corporation, Armonk, NY). The data will be assessed with visual (histogram and probability plot) and analytical methods (Kolmogorov-Smirnov test) to evaluate
normal distribution. The ?² test (chi-square test) or Fisher exact test will be used to compare proportions of outcome grades in different groups. Pearson product moment correlation will be performed for correlations. Statistical significance is defined by P = .05.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/05/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>140</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <state>Minia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Minia Maternity University Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Minia- Minia University. Faculty of Medicine. Egypt.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Egypt</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Minia maternity University Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Minia University. Faculty of Medicine. Egypt</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Egypt</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of our study is to evaluate the role of office hysteroscopy (endocervicoscopy) as a new technique for the diagnostic work-up of cervical intraepithelial neoplasia. This technique combines, conventional hysteroscopic instrumentation with the colposcopic classification system for the evaluation of the endocervical mucosa</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>scientific ethical committee of the department of Obstetrics and Gynecology</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>minia University, Minia Maternity University Hospital. Misr -Aswan main road, Minia city, minia Governorate, postcode: 61111</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/04/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Egypt</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Institutional Review Board of the University Hospital-Quality control unit of the Faculty of Medicine, Minia University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Faculty of Medicine, Minia University. Misr -Aswan main road, Minia city, minia Governorate, postcode: 61111</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/11/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Egypt</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ahmad Sameer Sanad</name>
      <address>Minia University, Minia Maternity University Hospital. Misr -Aswan main road, Minia city, minia Governorate, postcode: 61111</address>
      <phone>+201000222994</phone>
      <fax>+2-086-2332666</fax>
      <email>asasanad@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ahmad Sameer Sanad</name>
      <address>Minia University, Minia Maternity University Hospital, Misr -Aswan main road, Minia city, minia Governorate, postcode: 61111</address>
      <phone>+201000222994</phone>
      <fax>+2-086-2332666</fax>
      <email>asasanad@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ahmad Sameer Sanad</name>
      <address>Minia University, Minia Maternity University Hospital, Misr -Aswan main road, Minia city, minia Governorate, postcode: 61111</address>
      <phone>+201000222994</phone>
      <fax>+2-086-2332666</fax>
      <email>asasanad@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ahmad Sameer Sanad</name>
      <address>Minia University, Minia Maternity University Hospital</address>
      <phone>+201000222994</phone>
      <fax>+2-086-2332666</fax>
      <email>asasanad@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>