<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372880">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/06/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/06/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000945325</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effectiveness of a Herbal and Nutritional Supplement on Cognitive Function in Older Adults with Subjective Cognitive Complaints</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A 6 month clinical trial of the efficacy and safety of Cognition Support Formulation (BioCeuticals) on cognitive function in older adults with subjective cognitive complaints</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1196-9548</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Subjective Cognitive Complaints (SCCs)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Double-blind, randomised placebo controlled trial.
Participants will be randomised into either the placebo or active treatment groups and complete a battery of neuropsychological and psychophysiological tasks over a 6 month period.
Active treatment is 1 tablet taken twice daily of Cognition Support Formula (Bioceuticals).
Each active tablet contains: Bacopa monnieri (bacopa whole plant) 4g, Ginkgo biloba (ginkgo leaf) 3g, Panax ginseng (Korean ginseng root) 212mg, R, S alpha-lipoic acid 300mg

</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo tablet (1 taken twice daily) is matched on colour, taste, smell and size to that of the active tablet.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the efficacy of 6 months treatment with Cognition Support Formula to improve cognition in older adults with Subjective Cognitive Complaints as measured by the CogState Pre-Clinical Alzheimer's battery.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (0 months), midpoint (3 months) and endpoint (6 months).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the safety and adverse effects of Cognition Support Formula compared to placebo at baseline (0 months), midpoint (3 months) and endpoint (6 months).
Separately, minor adverse effects have been reported for brahmi, ginseng and Alpha-lipoic acid including: minor gastrointestinal upset and insomnia, compared to placebo.  Participants will complete a diary and will document any adverse effects throughout the course of the study.  Adverse effects will be discussed with participants at each midpoint, endpoint and 4 weeks after endpoint sessions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (0 months), midpoint (3 months) and endpoint (6 months).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the efficacy of 6-months treatment (at 3 different time-points: baseline, midpoint and endpoint) of Cognition Support Formula compared to placebo on mood, as measured by the Depression, Anxiety, Stress Scale (DASS-42).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (0 months), midpoint (3 months) and endpoint (6 months).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the efficacy of a 6-month treatment of Cognition Support Formula on neurocognition compared to placebo by utilising psychophysiological measures (EEG) at baseline and endpoint.
EEG will provide objective information pertaining to the mechanisms of action of Cognition Support Formula and the neuronal substrates of cognition in older adults with SCCs. 
EEG participants (64 in total) will be matched on sex and age.  Half will be derived from the active group, and half from the placebo group.  Participants will be recruited for all procedures including EEG until the quota for the EEG component has been reached.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (0 months) and endpoint (6 months).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the efficacy of 6-months treatment of Cognition Support Formula compared to placebo on mood, as measured by the Short Health Anxiety Inventory (SHAI).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (0 months), midpoint (3 months) and endpoint (6 months).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the efficacy of 6-months treatment of Cognition Support Formula compared to placebo on fatigue and energy levels, as measured by the Functional Assessment of Chronic Illness Therapy Fatigue Scale (FACIT-F).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (0 months), midpoint (3 months) and endpoint (6 months).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. No diagnosis of dementia or Mild Cognitive Impairment (MCI).
2. Evidence of SCCs as measured by:
        Answering yes to any of the following questions:
          -Do you feel your memory and thinking is getting worse?
	  -Do you feel your memory and thinking has become worse over the past 2-3 years?
          -Are you concerned about your decline in memory and thinking? 
3. Scoring (greater than or equal to) 23 on the Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA).   
4. Normal vision or corrected to normal.
5. Normal hearing or aided.
6. Provide informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Depression, as measured by the 30-item Geriatric Depression Scale (GDS); Participants scoring (greater than or equal to) 19 will be excluded.
2. Use of antidepressants/anxiolytics (if participants have been taking these, a 16-week washout is required, but only if this was the intended course of action from their usual care)
3. Use of psychoactive medications, alcohol intake (maximum of 14 standard drinks per week) as recommended by the Australian Department of Health.
4. No caffeine 6 hours prior to testing, and non-smokers.
5. No history of seizures or head injury (with loss of consciousness).
6. Allergy to study drug ingredients: ginseng, ginkgo, brahmi, or alpha-lipoic acid.
7. Participants taking the following ingredients: Bacopa monnieri (brahmi), Ginkgo biloba, Panax ginseng or alpha-lipoic acid (either separately or as a component of a supplement), are excluded from participation unless they have discontinued using these ingredients 8 weeks prior to testing.  
8. Left-handedness, only for EEG testing.
9. Type 2 diabetics with a high fasting glucose level at baseline (&gt;8 mmol/L, according to Diabetes Australia) or diabetics experiencing complications associated with their diabetes.
10. Diagnosed psychiatric disorders including: bipolar disorder, schizophrenia, personality disorders, drug and alcohol dependence or substance abuse disorders.
11. Presence or history of severe renal and hepatic disorders.
12. High dependence on medical care (including medications) due to past or current medical conditions (chronic illness), for example; cancer.  Participants using Cyclophosphamide and Levothyroxine will be excluded.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>An external staff member to the research team will send the random sequence directly to the trial drug manufacturer, with participant IDs and unique batch codes that will be used to conceal the sequence.  This is a double-blind trial, so both participants and the research team will be blinded to allocation until study completion.  </concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomly allocated at a 1:1 ratio to either the treatment or placebo group using a permuted block allocation strategy.  Computerised randomisation and allocation will be conducted using a unique random number generator in Microsoft Excel by a University staff member external to the research team.  After eligibility is confirmed, participants will then be allocated to the next participant ID/numbered box of product by a member of the research team. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The study will employ a mixed-model design with a between-subjects factor of group: (treatment vs. placebo), and within-subjects factor of time (baseline vs. midpoint vs. endpoint).  Mixed-model ANOVAs will be conducted to assess differences in continuous outcome measures, with simple planned contrasts conducted in order to assess all time points: baseline vs. midpoint, midpoint vs. endpoint and baseline vs. endpoint.  A significant group × time interaction will be required to determine treatment efficacy on the primary outcome measure.  Bonferroni corrections for multiple comparisons will be applied to any non-planned contrasts.  MANOVAs, Principal Components Analysis (PCA), and Pearsons correlations will also be utilised for psychophysiological data assessment.  The primary outcome measure to be assessed is the change in scores from each of the CogState® tasks, and the secondary outcomes are: the changes in DASS-42, SHAI and FACIT-F scores, and changes neuronal and physiological activity.  An alpha level of &lt; .05 will be used to determine statistical significance. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/07/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2500 - Wollongong</postcode>
    <postcode>2560 - Campbelltown</postcode>
    <postcode>2570 - Camden</postcode>
    <postcode>2567 - Narellan</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Mrs Adele Cave</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The National Institute of Complementary Medicine
Building 5,  Campbelltown Campus
Western Sydney University 
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith  NSW  2751
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>BioCeuticals pty ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Unit 1/ Level 1, 85 O'Riordan St
Alexandria 2015
New South Wales Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Western Sydney University (The National Institute of Complementary Medicine) </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The National Institute of Complementary Medicine
Building 5,  Campbelltown Campus
Western Sydney University 
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith  NSW  2751
Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of the proposed study is to test the efficacy of a herbal and nutritional supplement
(BioCeuticals Pty Ltd Cognition Support Formula) in a sample of older adults who report
Subjective Cognitive Complaints (SCCs). The proposed study is a 6 month randomised double blind placebo controlled trial which will test the effects of cognition support formula on cognition (CogState), mood, fatigue, electrophysiology and autonomic function in older adults with SCCs. Participants will undergo telephone and face to face screening in order to determine if they meet the criteria for participation. During the telephone screening, participants will respond to questions from a cognitive status questionnaire (TICS-M). General health and depression questionnaires will be administered during the face to face screening. At baseline (0 months), midpoint (3 months) and endpoint (6 months) participants will complete a series of mood, fatigue and cognitive tests (both computerised and pen and paper tests).Opportunities will be made available for participants to additionally take part in Electroencephalography (EEG) testing at baseline and endpoint.These measures will enable a greater capacity to determine the efficacy of cognition support formula on cognitive health in older adults with SCCs.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Western Sydney University Human Research Ethics Committee (EC00314)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Western Sydney University 
Research Engagement, Development and Innovation (REDI) 
Locked Bag 1797 
Penrith NSW 2751</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/02/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H11958</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Adele Cave</name>
      <address>The National Institute of Complementary Medicine
Building 5,  Campbelltown Campus
Western Sydney University 
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith  NSW  2751
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 487 472 273</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>A.Cave@westernsydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Adele Cave</name>
      <address>The National Institute of Complementary Medicine
Building 5,  Campbelltown Campus
Western Sydney University 
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith  NSW  2751
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 487 472 273</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>A.Cave@westernsydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Adele Cave</name>
      <address>The National Institute of Complementary Medicine
Building 5,  Campbelltown Campus
Western Sydney University 
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith  NSW  2751
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 487 472 273</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>A.Cave@westernsydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Adele Cave</name>
      <address>The National Institute of Complementary Medicine
Building 5,  Campbelltown Campus
Western Sydney University 
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith  NSW  2751
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 487 472 273</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>A.Cave@westernsydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>