<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367144">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/09/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/10/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001094662</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Glutamine kinetics in intensive care unit patients  relation between plasma concentration and endogenous production</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Observational study of the relation between plasma glutamine concentration and endogenous production in ICU patients. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1162-1906 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Low plasma glutamine and critical illness</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>High plasma glutamine and critical illness</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Liver failure</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>To measure endogenous glutamine production in ICU patients by a previously verified bolus injection  method (Mori et al. PLoS One 2014 8;9(5) e96601). Subjects will receive a bolus injection of both glutamine and phenylalanine labeled with a stable isotope (1-13C-glutamine 3 mg/kg; ring2H5-phenylalanine 0.3 mg/kg). Bolus will be given over 20 seconds followed by 60 blood samples over 90 min to get a decay curve. Initially 1 sample every 30 sec, then every 60 sec and finally every 3 min. Each blood sample is 0,5 mL. During the measurement nutrition should be constant; to achieve this nutrition will not be altered two hours prior to the measurement or during the 90 minutes that blood samples are collected.
Four different groups will be studied:
1. 20 patients with low plasma glutamine (&lt;420 umol/L)  at admission to the ICU.
2. 20 patients with high plasma glutamine (&gt;900 umol/L) at admission to the ICU.
3. 20 patients staying &gt;5 days in the ICU.
4. 20 patients with high plasma glutamine (&gt;900 umol/L) at admission to the ICU and liver failure.
Group 1 and 2 will be measured once in the first week of ICU stay. Group 3 will be measured several times with 3-5 days intervals. Group 4 will be measured several times with 2-3 days intervals. A subject may be included in more than one group.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control treatment.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Glutamine endogenous production or synthesis is assessed with injection of a small amount of labeled glutamine (labeled with a stable isotope; 13C). By taking frequent plasma samples and analyzing these for the decay of the labeled glutamine the endogenous production of glutamine can be analyzed by dividing the bolus dose of labeled glutamine by the area under the curve for the decay in plasma.</outcome>
      <timepoint>First week of ICU stay. Measured over 90 minutes on one occasion only in groups 1 and 2, on 1-2 occasions in Group 3, and on 2-3 occasions in Group 4.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in glutamine synthesis during ICU stay. Endogenous production is assessed with injection of a small amount of labeled glutamine (labeled with a stable isotope; 13C). By taking frequent plasma samples and analyzing these for the decay of the labeled glutamine the endogenous production of glutamine can be analyzed by dividing the bolus dose of labeled glutamine by the area under the curve for the decay in plasma.
Several measurements are made for groups 3+4. These will be compared to see if there is a change over time.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2-5 days after previous measurement as long as in the ICU (maximum 3 measurements/2 week period).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Glutamine de novo production and production from protein breakdown. 
Glutamine endogenous production is coming from 2 sources; de novo synthesis and from breakdown of protein. To distinguish between the two we will assess whole body protein breakdown using a labeled phenylalanine (2H5-phenylalanine) in the same way as for the labeled glutamine (phenylalanine endogenous production is calculated from bolus divided by area under the curve for plasma 2H25-phenyalanine). Since phenylalanine is an essential amino acid its endogenous production can only come from protein breakdown. By assuming a ratio of phenylalnine to glutamine content in whole body protein the amount of glutamine coming from protein breakdown can be estimated. By subtracting the glutamine coming from protein breakdown from the total glutamine endogenous production, de novo production of glutamine is calculated (as in Mori et al Crit Care 2014 14;18(2)R72).</outcome>
      <timepoint>First week of ICU stay and 2-5 days after previous measurement as long as in the ICU (maximum 3 measurements/2 week period).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Group 1: Plasma glutamine &lt;420 umol/l at admission to the ICU. 
Group 2: Plasma glutamine  &gt;900 umol/l at admission to the ICU. 
Group 3: Expected length of stay in ICU &gt;5 days.
Group 4: Plasma glutamine &gt;900umol/l at admissio to the ICu and liver failure.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Absence of informed consent.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>To detect a 25% difference in endogenous glutamine production rates between group 1 and 2 (primary outcome) with a 80% power, 19 patients are needed in each group based on variation in previous study in similar patients (Mori et al Crit Care 2014 14;18(2)R72).

Since repeated measures of glutamine endogenous production are not performed before we do not know the variation and will not be able to calculate power on the groups with repeated measures. The comparison between the low and the high glutamine production is the key question and therefore the study is powered to answer this question. The other groups are of the same size as an pragmatic approach and will give us data to in future studies calculate power also for repeated measurements. However since the repeated measurements will allow us to use paired analyses, the obtained higher power will most likely make this part of the study over powered rather than under powered.

Primary analysis: For comparison between group 1 and 2 using t-test or Mann-Whitney. 
For repeated measurements ANOVA.

Secondary analysis: Regression analysis</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>25/09/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Jan Wernerman</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Karolinska Institutet, Department of Clinical Science, Intervention and Technology (CLINTEC)
and
Dept. Anesthesiology and Intensive Care, B31
Karolinska University Hospital Huddinge
SE-141 86 Stockholm, Sweden</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Sweden</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Supported by grants provided by the Stockholm County Council (ALF project)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Stockholm County Council
Box 22550
SE-104 22 Stockholm
Sweden</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Sweden</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A low plasma concentration of glutamine at ICU admission is associated with an unfavorable outcome. A high glutamine concentration at ICU admission may also communicate a negative prediction. Exogenous glutamine supplementation normalizes plasma concentration and has been found to improve mortality outcome in the Scandinavian Glutamine Trial (Wernerman et al, Acta Anesth Scand 2011;55:812-18). However, the recent REDOX study showed a harmful effect of high doses of glutamine supplemented both parenteral and enteral (Heyland et al, NEJM 2013;368:1489-97). 
In an earlier study we have found that a small group of patients with high glutamine concentration at ICU admission had a higher 6-month mortality (Rodas Castillo et al, Clin Sci 2012;122:591-97). The group was too small to identify any other characteristics in the patients. However, acute liver failure was a diagnosis found within the subgroup. In another, still unpublished, study we have studied plasma glutamine concentration in patients with different kinds of hepatic insufficiency. The results show that both patients with acute fulminant liver failure and decompensated chronic liver failure have high glutamine concentrations. 
In order to be able to offer our ICU patients glutamine supplementation without risking an overdose by treating patients with normal plasma concentration,  we have a machine (BioProfile Analyser from Nova Biochemical) which can analyze glutamine concentration in blood and plasma within minutes. 
We have previously studied endogenous glutamine production in ICU patients given intravenous glutamine supplementation (Mori et al, Crit Care. 2014 14;18(2)R72). With this study we intend to use the same method to study specific groups of ICU patients to elucidate if the abnormal plasma glutamine concentrations are related to alterations in endogenous production.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Regional Ethical Board in Stockholm</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Regionala etikprovningsnamnden i Stockholm
FE 289
171 77 STOCKHOLM</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/02/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2014/68-31/2</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Sweden</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jan Wernerman</name>
      <address>Karolinska Institutet, Department of Clinical Science, Intervention and Technology (CLINTEC) and Dept. Anesthesiology and Intensive Care, B31 Karolinska University Hospital Huddinge SE-141 86 Stockholm, Sweden</address>
      <phone>+46 8 58 58 00 00</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jan.wernerman@karolinska.se</email>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Marie Smedberg</name>
      <address>Dept. Anesthesiology and Intensive Care, B31 Karolinska University Hospital Huddinge SE-141 86 Stockholm, Sweden</address>
      <phone>+46 8 58 58 00 00</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>marie.smedberg@karolinska.se</email>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Marie Smedberg</name>
      <address>Dept. Anesthesiology and Intensive Care, B31 Karolinska University Hospital Huddinge SE-141 86 Stockholm, Sweden</address>
      <phone>+46 8 58 58 00 00</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>marie.smedberg@karolinska.se</email>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>