<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369502">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/01/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/01/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000040460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Concise Regular Assessment and Feedback for Teaching and learning (CRAFT): a pilot study to evaluate the effect of a deliberate teaching tool on the educational environment of vocational trainees in anaesthesiology</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Concise Regular Assessment and Feedback for Teaching and learning (CRAFT): a pilot study to evaluate the effect of a deliberate teaching tool on the educational environment of vocational trainees in anaesthesiology</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1175-6804</utrn>
    <trialacronym>CRAFT pilot</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Educational environment</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention: Concise Regular Assessment and Feedback for Teaching and learning (CRAFT) model

The CRAFT model has 3 phases:
i. Prebrief - A brief encounter at the start of the list to determine the trainees previous experience relevant to the list and mutually agreed learning goals for the session, led by
the trainee and guided by the supervising clinician.
ii. Teaching - Teaching during the list, guided by the mutually agreed learning objectives
iii. Debrief - Takes place at the end of a list, and is organised as follows: Reaction (allows trainee to express their initial emotional reaction), Analysis (framing of actions and use of the advocacy-inquiry approach),  Summary (distill lessons from debrief and provide suggestions for future learning).

This deliberate teaching tool is to be used for all in-theatre teaching encounters during normal working hours (Monday-Friday, 0700-1800) where both the supervisor and trainee are study participants, during a 4-week study period. The supervisor (specialist anaesthetist) leads the teaching encounter but may be prompted by the trainee. Material for pre-reading will be provided to the specialists prior to the 4-week intervention period. This will consist of a background summary and instruction and tips on how to use the intervention, with an emphasis on providing effective feedback using the advocacy-inquiry model. A brief description of the intervention will be provided to trainees. The Site Investigator will contact trainees at the end of each week to determine compliance with using the tool, and follow-up with specialists and trainees as required.

</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Educational environment, assessed by survey of trainees designed specifically for this study (modified Anaesthesia Trainee Educational Environment Measure or mATEEM).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Survey completed at end of 4 week intervention period.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility of study design with regards to quantitative (mATEEM) and qualitative (trainee focus group) measures, assessed based on results of both measures and feedback from Site Investigators.</outcome>
      <timepoint>mATEEM and trainee focus group completed at end of 4 week intervention period.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Levels of outcome variability, to calculate sample size for quantitative aspect of main study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At end of 4 week intervention period</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of specialists and trainees in departments consenting to participate in study</outcome>
      <timepoint>At end of recruitment period, just prior to 4 week intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compliance rate of CRAFT model use during teaching encounters, assessed using information from trainees obtained by Site Investigator</outcome>
      <timepoint>At end of each week of 4 week intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Delphi study phase: Experts identified through stated process. Expert = specialist anaesthetist registered in New Zealand or Australia with a formal medical education qualification.

Institution: Any hospital department of anaesthesia that is accredited for vocational training
with English as the main language of instruction, with consent from the Clinical Director and Supervisor of Training.

Specialists: Any specialist anaesthetist employed in a participating institution
who has not opted out of the study.

Trainees: Any trainee/resident/medical officer employed in a participating institution who
has not opted out of the study, with at least 8 weeks of clinical anaesthesia experience in that
department. Separate consent is obtained for trainee focus groups.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>All institutions/participants: Those who have declined to consent.

Institutions: &lt;30% of specialists or &lt;50% of trainees consenting to participate.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>None. </concealment>
    <sequence>None</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This is an interventional study with pre- and post-intervention measurement of the educational environment using a survey tool (mATEEM) and qualitative analysis using focus groups..</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Delphi phase (development and validation of survey): An item is deemed to be relevant to anaesthesia teaching encounters in the operating theatre if a mean of 5.0 or above is obtained and consensus is achieved (i.e. SD equal to or less than 1.0).

Statistician input to estimate the levels of outcome variability to determine samples sizes for main study, including power for any sub-analysis.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>75</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Department of Anaesthesia &amp; Perioperative Medicine, North Shore Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>North Shore Hospital, 124 Shakespeare Road, Takapuna, Auckland 0622</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Anaesthesia and Perioperative Medicine, North Shore Hospital, Waitemata District Health Board</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>North Shore Hospital, 124 Shakespeare Road, Takapuna, Auckland 0622</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to determine if the CRAFT tool, a tool developed to promote deliberate teaching in the operating theatre, can improve the educational environment of junior doctors training in anaesthesia. 

The educational environment will be assessed using a specific survey tool developed for this purpose, the modified Anaesthesia Theatre Educational Environment Measure (mATEEM). In addition, qualitative aspects of the CRAFT tool application will measure assessed using focus groups.

This pilot study aims to:
1.) Develop and validate the mATEEM survey items 
2) Determine the feasibility of the quantitative  and qualitative aspects of the study
3) Determine participation rates of specialists and trainees in each department, and subsequent compliance rates of utilising the CRAFT tool
4) Estimate the levels of outcome variability to determine samples sizes for a future definitive study</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not required</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Institutional locality approval has been obtained from Awhina Research and Knowledge, Waitemata District Health Board (Approval ID: RM13266), who have determined that formal ethics approval is not necessary.</publicnotes>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Navdeep Sidhu</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia and Perioperative Medicine
North Shore Hospital
Private Bag 93-503
Takapuna
Auckland 0740</address>
      <phone>+64 9 4868900</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 4423237</fax>
      <email>nav.sidhu@waitematadhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Navdeep Sidhu</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia and Perioperative Medicine
North Shore Hospital
Private Bag 93-503
Takapuna
Auckland 0740</address>
      <phone>+64 9 4868900</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 4423237</fax>
      <email>nav.sidhu@waitematadhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Navdeep Sidhu</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia and Perioperative Medicine
North Shore Hospital
Private Bag 93-503
Takapuna
Auckland 0740</address>
      <phone>+64 9 4868900</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 4423237</fax>
      <email>nav.sidhu@waitematadhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Navdeep Sidhu</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia and Perioperative Medicine
North Shore Hospital
Private Bag 93-503
Takapuna
Auckland 0740</address>
      <phone>+64 9 4868900</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 4423237</fax>
      <email>nav.sidhu@waitematadhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>