<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372503">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/03/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/03/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000361303</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of nutraceutical supplements (Thompsons Super Bioflavonoid Complex 'Registered Trademark' and Thompsons Cholesterol Manager 'Registered Trademark' on blood glucose levels in patients with type 2 diabetes- A pilot study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of nutraceutical supplements (Thompsons Super Bioflavonoid Complex 'Registered Trademark' and Thompsons Cholesterol Manager 'Registered Trademark' on blood glucose levels in patients with type 2 diabetes- A pilot study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 Diabetes mellitus</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study will investigate the potential of commercially available nutraceutical supplements (Thompsons Super Bioflavonoid Complex 'Registered Trademark' and Thompsons Cholesterol Manager 'Registered Trademark' similar to the dipeptidyl peptidase-4 (DPP-4) inhibitor group, also known as gliptins, which are second line anti-diabetic drugs after metformin and sulfonylureas.
This study has two interventions:
Intervention 1 (week zero to week 12): To use nutraceutical supplement (Thompsons Super Bioflavonoid Complex 'Registered Trademark') as natural DPP-4 inhibitor in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus.
A wash out period of 4 weeks.
Intervention 2 (week 16 to week 28): To use nutraceutical supplement (Thompsons Cholesterol Manager 'Registered Trademark') as natural DPP-4 inhibitor in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus.

A. Thompsons Super Bioflavonoid Complex 'Registered Trademark':
Active Compounds: Citrus bioflavonoid extract, ascorbic acid, rutin, sodium ascorbate.
Composition: Citrus Bioflavonoid Extract-500 mg; Ascorbic Acid- 390 mg; Rutin- 100 mg; Sodium ascorbate- 125.3 mg.
Number of Tablets in each pack: 120
Mode of Administration: Two tablets per day before/with meal (NOT AFTER MEAL) 

B. Thompsons Cholesterol Manager 'Registered Trademark':
Active Compounds: Beta-sitosterol, stigmasterol, campesterol.
Composition: Phytosterol Complex- 450 mg.
Number of Tablets in each pack: 120
Mode of Administration: Four tablets per day before/with meal (NOT AFTER MEAL) for the first 4 weeks, then continue on 2 tablets per day for the remaining 8 weeks.

Strategies used to monitor adherence to the intervention: Participants will be asked to complete a logbook to record the day and time they take the tablets. 

</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will use placebo. The placebo tablets will contain the same excipients as the active tablets, but the active herbal extract would be replaced by excipients.
The excipients in the Thompson's Super Bioflavonoid Complex are microcrystalline cellulose (BP), calcium hydrogen phosphate dehydrate (USP), silica  colloidal anhydrous (BP), crospovidone (BP) and magnesium stearate (BP).
The excipients in the Cholesterol Manager are hydromellose (BP), microcrystalline cellulose (BP), croscarmellose sodium (BP), maize starch (BP), silicon dioxide (BP), stearic acid (BP) and magnesium stearate (BP).
Placebo will be sourced from the Integria Healthcare Pty Limited (the same company who produce Thompson's supplements). All their products are manufactured under pharmaceutical GMP by facilities licensed by the TGA (as required by law).</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in blood glucose levels: This can be measured using glucometers and HbA1c measuring devices.</outcome>
      <timepoint>after 12 weeks of the use of the supplements</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in levels of oxidative stress: Oxidative stress can be chemically measured using 8-Hydroxy deoxyguanosine ELISA kit and Human resistin ELISA kit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 12 weeks of the supplement intake</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in the levels of serum lipids: Serum lipids can be measured chemically using ELISA kits.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 12 weeks of taking each supplement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in the levels of Dipeptidyl Peptidase 4 (DPP-4) enzyme activity: Using DPP-4 ELISA kit. </outcome>
      <timepoint>After 12 weeks of taking each supplement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>For all participants
1.	Have been clinically diagnosed with type 2 diabetes.
2.	Aged between (25 and 75) years.
3.	Lean, overweight or obese (BMI 19 to 35 kg/m2).
4.	Have normal or controlled blood pressure. 
5.	Normotensive (seated brachial blood pressure less than 140/90 mmHg).
6.	Have given signed informed consent to participate in the study.
7.	Clinically diagnosed T2D on diet and lifestyle intervention or metformin only treatment (e.g. fasting plasma glucose equal or more than 7.0mM, HbA1c).
8.	Willing to take nutraceutical supplements (Thompsons Super Bioflavonoid Complex 'Registered Trademark' and Thompsons Cholesterol Manager 'Registered Trademark'), for 12 weeks.
9.	Negative pregnancy test for the woman during their reproductive life.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>25</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>For all participants
1. Age less than 25 yrs or more than 75 yrs
2. Morbidly obese with a BMI equal or more than 35 kg/m2
3. Not on diet and lifestyle or metformin only treatment for their diabetes (e.g. insulin injections, sulphonylureas, GLP-1 receptor agonists).
4. History of myocardial infarction or stroke
5. History of malignancy within past 5 years (except for non-melanoma skin cancers)
6. Identification of any medical condition requiring immediate therapeutic intervention
7. Uncontrolled hypertension (resting brachial blood pressure equal or more than 160/100 mmHg)
8. History of severe liver disease
9. History of drug or alcohol abuse
10. Elective major surgery during the course of the study
11. Pregnancy and/ or lactation
12. Currently consuming nutraceutical supplements (especially vitamin C and D)
13. Participation or intention to participate in another clinical research study during the study period.
14. Not willing to take nutraceutical supplements (Thompsons Super Bioflavonoid Complex 'Registered Trademark' and Thompsons Cholesterol Manager 'Registered Trademark'), for 12 weeks.
15. Positive pregnancy test for the woman during their reproductive life.
16. Participants with impaired renal function.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>numbered containers</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Our previous data shows that we had statistical significant changes in the levels of 8-OHdG and antioxidants using 40 T2DM patients. Based on these data and assuming 20-25% withdrawal rate from the study, for a two-sample test (t-test) with a Type I error of 5% (a = 0.05) and 80% power, we will require 50 participants in each group (both for aims 1 and aim 2)</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1 / Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>23/04/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>29/10/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>TAS</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Hobart Hospital - Hobart</hospital>
    <postcode>7000 - Hobart</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Tasmania</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Medicine, 
Domain Campus, 
Medical Science (Hollydene House - 310), 
University of Tasmania
17 Liverpool Street, Private Bag 34
Hobart, TAS, 7001</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Tasmanian Community Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Tasmanian Community Fund
GPO Box 1350
HOBART TASMANIA 7001

Suite 1A, Tech 4
Tasmanian Technopark
Innovation Drive
DOWSING POINT
Hobart, TAS, 7001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will investigate the potential of commercially available nutraceutical supplements (Thompsons Super Bioflavonoid Complex 'Registered Trademark' and Thompsons Cholesterol Manager 'Registered Trademark' similar to the dipeptidyl  peptidase-4 (DPP-4) inhibitor group, also known as gliptins, which are second line anti-diabetic drugs after metformin and sulfonylureas. The gliptins block the action of DPP-4, an enzyme which inhibits a group of gastrointestinal hormones called incretins which stimulate the production of insulin post meal and reduce the production of glucagon by the liver during digestion. DPP-4 inhibitors help regulate blood glucose levels by inhibiting incretins reducing the financial burden for antidiabetic medicine equivalent to AU$193.8 million per year.
This study has two main aims-:
Aim 1-: To determine the effect of nutraceutical supplement (Thompsons Super Bioflavonoid Complex 'Registered Trademark') as natural DPP-4 inhibitor on glycemic control in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus.
Aim 2-: To determine the effect of nutraceutical supplement (Thompsons Cholesterol Manager 'Registered Trademark') as natural DPP-4 inhibitor on glycemic control in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus.
The study will include a total of 100 T2D participants recruited from the community. After an overnight fast (12-hr), participants will attend the clinical areas of the Medical Science Precinct, University of Tasmania
(UTAS) to undergo the following:
1) Medical &amp; lifestyle questionnaires
2) Anthropometrics
3) Blood tests to measure blood glucose, HbA1c, serum lipids, insulin, &amp; oxidative markers.
4) Glucose metabolism (2hr oral glucose tolerance test).
5) Hemodynamic measures (blood pressure, heart rate &amp; ECG).
6) Urinary electrolytes &amp; kidney function.
7) Pregnancy test for woman during their reproductive life.

This is a randomised single-blinded placebo-controlled parallel study consisting of two phases, with a 4-week wash out period. The total duration of the recruitment process is 28 weeks.
(Phase 1 starts from week zero till week 12, followed by a 4-weeks wash out period, then phase 2 to starts at week 16 and ends at week 28).
Venous blood &amp; urine samples will be collected at the start and end of the two phases of the study. Nutraceutical supplements will be provided to the participants for 12 weeks. These natural products possess anti-diabetic activities &amp; the suggested course of supplements will maintain a constant level of dosage of these nutraceutical supplements to improve the overall metabolic functions in T2D cohort.

Biomarkers of metabolic response included in this study include measuring 8-hydroxy deoxyguanosine (8-OHdG) (oxidative DNA damage), total lipid peroxidation (lipid peroxidation) &amp; resistin (adipocytokine response).</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Tasmanian Health and Medical Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Research Services
University of Tasmania
Private Bag 1
Hobart, TAS, 7001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/02/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H0015762</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/09/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372503-TSRAC V5.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372503-CBBS Participant Information Sheet- V5 with Changes.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372503-H15762 approval letter 170220.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hayder Al-Aubaidy</name>
      <address>University of Tasmania
School of Medicine
17 Liverpool Street
Hobart, TAS 7001</address>
      <phone>+61362266975</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>H.Alaubaidy@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hayder Al-Aubaidy</name>
      <address>University of Tasmania
School of Medicine
17 Liverpool Street
Hobart, TAS 7001</address>
      <phone>+61362266975</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>H.Alaubaidy@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hayder Al-Aubaidy</name>
      <address>University of Tasmania
School of Medicine
17 Liverpool Street
Hobart, TAS 7001</address>
      <phone>+61362266975</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>H.Alaubaidy@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hayder Al-Aubaidy</name>
      <address>University of Tasmania
School of Medicine
17 Liverpool Street
Hobart, TAS 7001</address>
      <phone>+61362266975</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>H.Alaubaidy@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>