<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="1167">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/03/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/03/2006</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000101583</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The DEPTH Project: Detection, Evaluation, and Psychological Therapy for Health</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised controlled trial of cognitive behaviour therapy to prevent psychosis among people with at-risk mental states</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>DEPTH</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Ultra-high risk for the development of a psychotic disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Psychosis and personality disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study intervention is Cognitive Behaviour Therapy. This treatment will follow that employed by Morrison and colleagues in the EDIE trial, as described in the manual for that trial. Interventions are tailored to address the problems identified by the patients and are based on shared formulations. Therapists encourage collaborative empiricism, use guided discovery and recommend homework. However, this form of CBT differs somewhat from other forms in that it is designed specifically for preventing transition to psychosis among young high-risk individuals. Problems of substance use and dependence will be addressed with the techniques of motivational interviewing and CBT developed by Baker and Bucci for substance problems among people with psychoses. 

Duration of treatments: 26 therapy (weekly) sessions</interventions>
    <comparator>The control intervention is Non-Directive Reflective Listening: this is a form of person-centred counselling in which, within a therapeutic setting, the therapist offers empathic reflections while adopting a stance of genuineness or congruence and unconditional positive regard. Patients will be invited to discuss any topics they wish, not necessarily issues related to at-risk mental states, and the direction of content throughout the treatment will be for the patients to determine. 
Duration of treatments: 26 therapy (weekly) sessions</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome will be length of survival without the development of levels of positive psychotic symptoms of such severity that they mark a threshold at which anti-psychotic medication would normally be commenced. This severity threshold is defined as ratings in the psychotic range on the Comprehensive Assessment of At-Risk Mental States (CAARMS) positive items with frequencies of 3 to 6 times a week, plus the symptoms have persisted for more than one week. The development of mania, dangerous behaviour, or suicidality, defined as ratings of 5 or more on the corresponding scales of the CAARMS, will also be regarded as a transition and will also constitute a cue for the commencement of appropriate medication (Transition to psychosis).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Formally assessed once a month for the first 6 months and once every 2 months for the next 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Group differences in rates of change of symptoms assessed by the CAARMS.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Formally assessed once a month for the first month and once every two months for the next 6 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Group differences in rates of change of substance use assessed by the OTI.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Formally assessed once a month for the first month and once every two months for the next 6 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Group differences in rates of change of social functioning assessed by the Quality of Life Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Formally assessed once a month for the first month and once every two months for the next 6 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>reside within the boundaries of the Hunter New England Health Area or the former Mid-Western region of the Greater Western Area Health Service, meet criteria for one or more of 3 at-risk mental states (ARMS). These three groups are operationally defined as follows: Group A (state and trait risk factors): A combination of a first-degree relative with a history of any psychotic disorder, or the patient meets DSM-IV criteria for a diagnosis of schizotypal personality disorder, and any change in mental state or functioning which has resulted in a loss of at least 30% on the Global Assessment of Functioning scale for at least one month. Group B (attenuated psychotic symptoms): The person has developed one or more prodromal symptoms which represent a change in their functioning, different from their normal personality, and which occur with a frequency of at least several times a week and have been occurring for at least one week. The symptoms include ideas of reference, odd beliefs or magical thinking, perceptual disturbance, suspiciousness or paranoid thinking, and behaviour that is odd, eccentric or peculiar. The symptoms must deviate significantly from normal, as defined by ratings in the prodromal range on the Comprehensive Assessment of At Risk Mental States (CAARMS). Group C (transient psychotic symptoms): The person has a history during the previous year of brief limited intermittent psychotic symptoms (BLIPS) lasting less than one week before resolving spontaneously. The symptoms are defined by the presence of one or more ratings in the psychotic range on the CAARMS positive items: disorders of thought content, perceptual abnormalities, disorganised speech.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>12</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>30</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Meet criteria for a past or current DSM-IV psychotic disorder, have previously been prescribed anti-psychotic medication, have an organic mental disorder or intellectual disabilities, are at serious suicidal or homicidal risk (they will be eligible for inclusion once this risk has resolved), have an inadequate command of the English language.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by phone/email</concealment>
    <sequence>Stratified by gender, site, and receipt of antidepressant medication, using a system of central and external randomisation.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>18/04/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>78</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Prof. Mike Startup, University of Newcastle</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Psychology, University of Newcastle, NSW 2308</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health &amp; Medical Research Council Project Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 5, 20 Allara Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Prof. Vaughan Carr</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Centre for Brain and Mental Health Research, University of Newcastle, 2300</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>A/Prof Amanda Baker</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Centre for Brain and Mental Health Research, University of Newcastle, 2300</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>A/Prof Ulrich Schall</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Centre for Brain and Mental Health Research, University of Newcastle, 2300</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Helen Stain</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Centre for Rural and Remote Mental Health, Broomfield Hospital, Orange, NSW</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study will compare the effectiveness of cognitive behaviour therapy (CBT) and a non-directive psychotherapy matched for therapist input in delaying or preventing transition to psychosis among young people at high risk for psychosis. It is expected that patients assigned to CBT will: (1) show lower rates of transition to psychosis during the 12-month follow-up period; (2) survive longer without becoming psychotic even if they do make a transition during the 12-month follow-up period; (3) show better outcomes at 6 and 12 months in terms of psychotic and non-psychotic symptoms, quality of life and social functioning, whether or not they become psychotic.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Locked Bag No 1, New Lambton, NSW 2305</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/02/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>05/12/07/3.23</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee of the University of Newcastle</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/02/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H-183-0206</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/12/2005</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee of the Greater Western Area Health Service</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 143, The Lodge, Gorman's Hill Road, Bathurst, NSW 2795</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/07/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>GW2006/04</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/03/2006</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Mike Startup</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
University of Newcastle
Callaghan NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 49215979</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 49216980</fax>
      <email>Mike.startup@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mr Sean Halpin</name>
      <address>Psychological Assistance Service
Hunter Health Service
43 Brunker Road
Broadmeadow NSW 2292</address>
      <phone>+61 2 49610431</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 49610435</fax>
      <email>Sean.Halpin@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>