<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366385">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/05/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/05/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000571673</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Word retrieval in primary progressive aphasia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Is a structured therapy programme aimed at improving word retrieval for people with primary progressive aphasia successful in improving naming of treated items and do gains generalize to untreated items?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Primary progressive aphasia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dementias</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Speech therapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The treatment period for each participant will span 4 weeks, in addition to two weeks of initial baseline assessment, involving two 90 minute therapy sessions per week, delivered on an individual basis. The self-cueing approach will consist of a hierarchy of semantic, phonological and orthographic cues intended to train lexical retrieval strategies and will be administered by the student researcher. 120 treatment items will be trained across the intervention period. The stimuli will consist of 10 nouns, 10 verbs and 10 adjectives. Items will be controlled across categories for frequency, length and imageability. 

In addition to two weekly sessions, each participant will be assigned home practice to compliment learning in therapy. This will increase the repetition of lexical retrieval, consistent with the intensity of practice principle of neural plasticity (Kleim &amp; Jones, 2008). Homework will include picture naming of the target items in the category for that particular week. Participants will be required to complete homework for 30 minutes on the days without therapy.  Each participant will be required to document on a form their completion of the homework, including details of the time, support required and number of attempts. A spouse/significant other will assist the participant during these sessions to support word retrieval and motivation.
</interventions>
    <comparator>A multiple baseline design will be used with each participant acting as their own control. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The 120 items will be re-assessed post treatment using a naming battery of black and white line drawings (nouns, verbs &amp; adjectives)</outcome>
      <timepoint>One week immediately post the 4-week treatment  (single time point)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Mini Mental State Examination will be repeated post treatment to assess cognitive function
</outcome>
      <timepoint>One week immediately post the 4-week treatment </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A word finding self-assessment questionnaire will be administered post treatment. This has been developed for the study and is not a validated tool.</outcome>
      <timepoint>One week immediately post the 4-week treatment </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Curtin University Discourse Profile </outcome>
      <timepoint>One week immediately post the 4-week treatment </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Individuals are required to have a working diagnosis of Primary Progressive Aphasia (PPA) or progressive language impairment, established from previous diagnostic evaluation by a neurologist. All variants of PPA and language profiles will be accepted into the study. Participants are required to have English as their first language and no significant hearing problems that may impact their participation in the intervention. Participants will be in the early to mid-stages of PPA, as determined by a mild-moderate score on the Mini Mental State Examination (MMSE, Folstein, Folstein, &amp; McHugh, 1975). Participants and their spouse/carer will be required to have capacity to consent themselves to their involvement in the study. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Unable to give informed consent to participate</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Seven adults with a history of progressive language impairment / diagnosis of PPA will be recruited to the study via private neurologists working in Perth, Western Australia and the Curtin Adult Speech Pathology Clinic. 
Participants will be assigned to one of two treatment blocks, consisting of the same intervention but at different times.</concealment>
    <sequence>N/A</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Multiple baseline case study design</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Changes in accuracy of lexical retrieval of treated items, pre-treatment, post treatment and four weeks maintenance, will be determined for each participant using Cochrans Q test, with follow up comparisons between particular conditions using the McNemar test. Changes in accuracy of lexical retrieval of control items, pre-treatment, post treatment and four weeks maintenance, will be determined for each participant using Cochrans Q test, with follow up comparisons between particular conditions using the McNemar test. Outcomes for different participant profiles will be analysed descriptively.

Given that PPA is a relatively rare clinical syndrome, the sample size was selected based on typical presentation / referral patterns in Western Australia. Given the case series design a sample of 7 participants was deemed appropriate. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>19/05/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>21/05/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>7</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Curtin University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>GPO Box U1987
Perth, WA, 6845
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Curtin University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box U1987
Perth, WA
6845</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Neurodegenerative Disorders Research Pty Ltd</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>4 Lawrence Avenue, West Perth WA 6005</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The proposed research aims to investigate the effects of a self-cueing lexical retrieval therapy on seven individuals with varying language profiles, consistent with the diverse presentation of PPA. All participants will engage in an intervention designed to improve the retrieval of nouns, verbs and adjectives through the incorporation of semantic, phonological and orthographic levels of language production. Changes in accuracy of lexical retrieval of treated and control items, pre-treatment, post treatment and four weeks maintenance, will be determined for each participant. The findings will help Speech Pathologists understand the impact this type of therapy can have on the communication you need in day-to-day life. With this knowledge it is hoped that Speech Pathologists will be better equipped to help people with Primary Progressive Aphasia.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin University HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>GPO Box U1987
Perth, WA, 6845</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/04/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HR60/2014</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jade Cartwright</name>
      <address>Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth, WA, 6000</address>
      <phone>+61892663039</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.cartwright@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jade Cartwright</name>
      <address>Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth, WA, 6000</address>
      <phone>+61892663039</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.cartwright@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Anne Whitworth</name>
      <address>Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth, WA, 6000</address>
      <phone>Tel: +61892663498</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>anne.whitworth@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jade Cartwright</name>
      <address>Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth, WA, 6000</address>
      <phone>+61892663039</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.cartwright@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>