<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367102">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/09/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/05/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000606482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Tranexamic acid use in Total Hip Replacement - beyond blood loss: a randomised clinical trial of efficacy of tranexamic acid in improving postoperative inpatient functional outcomes following anterior total hip replacement.
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparing functional measures and blood loss with the of tranexamic acid in patients undergoing elective anterior total hip arthroplasty. A Randomized controlled trial. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1161-7799</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hip Osteoarthrtitis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients will be randomly assigned to the control or experiment arm of the study by the pharmacist who will have a random sequence to dictate arm allocation. Those in the intervention arm will receive one 15mg per Kg intraoperative bolus of tranexamic acid intravenously at the time of induction of anaesthesia. With a further 15mg / kg bolus at 8hrs and 16 hours post procedure. The procedure duration is approximately 1 hour. This is the current protocol being employed by Orthopaedic surgeons and reflects the Australian Medical Handbook guidelines for dosing of tranexamic acid. The brand of tranexamic acid to be used will be Cyklokapron, currently the only product available in the Australian market. </interventions>
    <comparator>Those in the control arm will receive an injection of an equal volume of normal saline at induction of anesthesia. Patients in the control arm will receive a further  bolus of normal saline at 8 hours and 16 hours after the initial normal saline bolus.
</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome: Thigh swelling. Thigh swelling is assessed using the frustum method of volumetric measurement. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured day 1, day 3 and 2 weeks post operatively. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional measure - timed up and go test. Measured by recording the time taken to complete the test. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured day 1, day 3 and 2 weeks post operatively. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcome: blood loss. This will be measured using observed blood loss intra-operatively as well as post operative haemoglobin levels. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured intra-operatively, day 1, day 3 post op. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Analgesia will be recorded using a visual analogue pain score.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured pre-operatively, day 1, day 3 and 2 weeks post op. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Eligible participants will be adults aged 40 or above undergoing a total hip replacement in the private practice of Mr Phong Tran. 


</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria are:
Contraindication to tranexamic acid use:
- Allergies or previously known drug reaction to tranexamic acid, 
- Active intravascular clotting  DVT, PE or cerebral thrombosis
- Predisposition to thrombosis  previous documented DVT or PE
- Subarachnoid hemorrhage

Rheumatoid arthritis</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients will be recruited from the private rooms of Mr Phong Tran. Patients undergoing a primary total hip replacement will be invited to participate in the study. The parameters of the trial will be explained verbally and a consent form will be provided which will document the proposed aims, importance, risks and details of the intervention being studied. It will be re-enforced that the patient’s choice to participate in the trial will in no way affect their ability to receive the medical treatment which they are seeking. Allocation concealment will be carried out by the pharmacist preparing the medication. They will have a random number sequence which will be allocated to the patient's data sheet. They will allocate the patients to the arm of the trial. The randomisation sequence will not be available to the participating surgeon or anaesthetist. The patients will be correlated to the sequence at the time of completion of the trial for data analysis. </concealment>
    <sequence>A random number sequence with an allocation of 1:1 will be generated using the STATA software package. 
</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/02/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>31/03/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>105</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>30/04/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St Vincents &amp; Mercy Private Hospital - Mercy campus - East Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3002 - East Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Andrew Fraval</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>St Vincent's Private Hospital 
East Melbourne
159 Grey Street, East Melbourne VIC 3002
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Does tranexamic acid use in the perioperative period reduce post operative thigh swelling, improve short term functional outcomes and reduce analgesia use following total hip replacement?

The secondary question of whether tranexamic acid use decreases blood loss in the anterior approach to total hip replacements will also be addressed.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>J Arthroplasty. 2017 May;32(5):1516-1519. doi: 10.1016/j.arth.2016.11.045. Epub 2016 Dec 8.
OBTAIN A: Outcome Benefits of Tranexamic Acid in Hip Arthroplasty. A Randomized Double-Blinded Controlled Trial.
Fraval A, Effeney P, Fiddelaers L, Smith B, Towell B, Tran P.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent’s HREC-D</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>41 Victoria Parade, Fitzroy VIC 3065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/09/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HRECD - 107/13</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/08/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrew Fraval</name>
      <address>St Vincent's Private Hospital 
East Melbourne
159 Grey Street, East Melbourne VIC 3002</address>
      <phone>+ 61 423 155 386</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>afraval@mac.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrew Fraval</name>
      <address>St Vincent's Private Hospital 
East Melbourne
159 Grey Street, East Melbourne VIC 3002</address>
      <phone>+ 61 423 155 386</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>afraval@mac.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrew Fraval</name>
      <address>St Vincent's Private Hospital 
East Melbourne
159 Grey Street, East Melbourne VIC 3002</address>
      <phone>+ 61 423 155 386</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>afraval@mac.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrew Fraval</name>
      <address>St Vincent's Private Hospital 
East Melbourne
159 Grey Street, East Melbourne VIC 3002</address>
      <phone>+ 61 423 155 386</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>afraval@mac.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>