<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369907">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/01/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/01/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000093482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A single dose, randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled, dose escalation study to evaluate the safety, pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of M012 administered by subcutaneous injection to healthy male volunteers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A single dose, randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled, dose escalation study to evaluate the safety, pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of M012 administered by subcutaneous injection to healthy male volunteers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Beta Thalassemia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haematological diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>M012 (and matching placebo) will be administered at 7 dose levels. Single doses 0.2mg, 0.6mg, 2mg, up to 5mg (exact dose to be decided based on pharmacokinetic information obtained from previous doses), up to 10mg (exact dose to be decided based on pharmacokinetic information obtained from previous doses) , up to 20mg (exact dose to be decided based on pharmacokinetic information obtained from previous doses) and up to 40mg (exact dose to be decided based on pharmacokinetic information obtained from previous doses), will be administered subcutaneously. All doses will be administered on-site by study staff.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo-controlled.  Placebo will be administered via subcutaneous injection into the abdomen.  Placebo contains 190 mM trehalose and 50 mM sodium acetate adjusted to pH 5.5 +/- 0.5.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the safety and tolerability of a single subcutaneous dose of M012 by monitoring of ECGs, vital signs, physical exams and safety lab results</outcome>
      <timepoint>ECG performed at screening, 2 hours and 4 hours post-dose, on Day 1, Day 2, Day 3, Day 4 and as needed on Day 8, Day 15 and Day 29 based on ongoing assessment of adverse events.  Vital sign check performed at screening, on Day -1, Day 1, Day 2, Day 3, Day 4, and Day 8.  Physical exams will be performed at screening, on Day -1, Day 8, Day 15 and Day 29.  Safety labs (Chemistry/Haematology) will be performed at screening, on Day -1, Day 4 and Day 8. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetic profile of a single subcutaneous dose of M012, assessed by Cmax, Tmax and AUC determined by blood sample

</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-dose,at 5,10, 15,30, 45 minutes and at 1, 1..5, 2, 4, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 30, 36, 48, 60, 72, and 168 hours post-dose  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacodynamic effect of M012 on serum iron and transferrin saturation (TSAT) after a single dose of M012</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 min pre-dose,at 4,12, 24,36, 48, 60 and 72 hours post-dose as inpatient and on Day 8 </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Immunogenicity of a single subcutaneous dose of M012 assessed by anti-drug antibody testing via a blood sample.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-dose on Day 1, Day 8, Day 15 and Day 29</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Be a healthy male volunteer age 18-60.
2.	Have a body mass index (BMI) between 18.5 and 30 kg/m2 (inclusive).
3.	Have laboratory values within the reference range unless deemed not clinically significant by the Investigator.
4.	Be surgically sterile, using barrier method of contraception or abstain from sexual intercourse from inpatient admission to one month after dosing. 
5.	Agree to adhere to the protocol-defined schedule of assessments and procedures.
6.	Be informed of the nature of the study and provide written informed consent before any study-specific procedures are performed.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Have iron deficiency, iron overload, liver disease, renal disease, chronic inflammatory disease, haemochromatosis, beta thalassemia, glucose 6 phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency or hemolytic anaemia. 
2.	Be a current smoker.
3.	Have alcohol intake outside normal limits (&gt; an average of 3 standard drinks per day). 
4.	Have received a blood transfusion within the last 3 months.
5.	Have positive test result for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV).
6.	Have positive test result for hepatitis B surface antigen, or hepatitis C antibody. 
7.	Have donated blood within 4 weeks of screening.
8.	Have had recent (within 4 weeks of screening) significant (greater than or equal to 1 unit) blood loss for any reason.
9.	Have any evidence of abnormal iron metabolism.  During screening, the following indicators must all be within normal limits: Hb, RBC, reticulocyte count, RDW, haematocrit, TSAT, serum ferritin, serum iron and TIBC. 
10.	Have participated in an investigational drug trial within 30 days prior to first dose of study drug on Day 1.
11.	Have a known hypersensitivity to any ingredient in the study formulation.
12.	Have, as determined by the Investigator and/or medical monitor, any clinically relevant medical or surgical condition that could interfere with the administration of study drug, interpretation of study results, or compromise the safety or well-being of the subject.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/02/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>15/02/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>23/05/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>56</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Merganser Biotech Australia Pty Ltd.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Floor 19, HWT Tower
40 City Road
Southbank, Victoria, 3006
Australia
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Merganser Biotech Australia Pty Ltd.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Floor 19, HWT Tower
40 City Road
Southbank, Victoria, 3006
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Clinical Network Services (CNS)</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Level 4, 88 Jephson Street
Toowong, QLD 4066
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Nucleus Network (NN)</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>5th Floor Burnet Tower
89 Commercial Road
Melbourne VIC 3004</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This research project is testing the safety, tolerability and pharmacokinetics (looking at the amount of drug in your blood to evaluate the way the body processes the drug), pharmacodynamics (the response of your body to the drug) and immunogenicity (your immune response to the drug) of a new drug called M012 when it is given as a single dose.
M012 is an injection into the skin of your abdomen to be administered by a trained professional. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Alfred Hospital Commercial Road MELBOURNE VIC 3004 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/02/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/01/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jason Lickliter</name>
      <address>Nucleus Network
Level 5 Burnet Institute
AMREP Precinct
89 Commercial Road
Melbourne, Victoria 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 8960</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.lickliter@nucleusnetwork.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Elaine Wong</name>
      <address>Nucleus Network
Level 5 Burnet Institute
AMREP Precinct
89 Commercial Road
Melbourne, Victoria 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 8958</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.wong@nucleusnetwork.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Mark Falone</name>
      <address>Merganser Biotech
1004 W. 9th Avenue
Suite 115
King of Prussia, PA 19406</address>
      <phone>+1 484 753 2408</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mfalone@merganserbiotech.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>