<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366115">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/04/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/11/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001213639</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Internet treatment for Posttraumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial comparing the impact of internet-based cognitive behavioural therapy (iCBT) for posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD) to waitlist control on PTSD symptoms</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The internet PTSD program comprises 6 lessons completed over 10 weeks. It includes all treatment components 
typically seen in face­-to­-face cognitive behavioural therapy (CBT) (the first­-line treatment for PTSD). One lesson will be completed every 7 to 14 days (it will become available after the preceding lesson has been completed, with a minimum of 5 days between lessons and a maximum of 14 days). Each lesson will take approximately 20-30 minutes to complete. Participants will have access to summaries of each lesson, homework exercises, extra resources, email contact from the clinician (registered clinical psychologist) after completion of the first two lessons, then as required. The participant is also able to email or phone the clinician at any point during the trial as required. The participant completes a measure of psychological distress before each lesson and if their scores increase by one or more standard deviations the clinician is automatically alerted and initiates contact with the participant by phone or email.

Strategies used to improved adherence to intervention protocols and procedures for monitoring adherence include: automated email reminders, monitoring the downloading of homework, collection of data on how long participants spent reading lessons and practicing skills.</interventions>
    <comparator>Waitlist control group. These participants remain on the waitlist until the immediate treatment group has completed their treatment and post-treatment assessment (11 weeks). At that time (11 weeks) the waitlist control group will be offered the same internet treatment program for PTSD.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reductions in the PTSD Checklist - Civilian Version (PCL-C)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, before each lesson, 1 week post-treatment (week 11), 3 months after post-treatment (week 24), and 6 months after treatment (week 36).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reductions in the Patient Health Questionnaire  9-Item (PHQ-9)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, mid-treatment (week 4), 1 week post-treatment (week 11), 3 months after post-treatment (week 24)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reductions in psychological distress according to the Kessler-10 (K10).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, before each lesson, 1 week post-treatment (week 11), 3 months after post-treatment (week 24)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Treatment Credibility/Expectancy Questionnaire (CEQ).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reductions in self-reported patient disability (Sheehan Disability Scale)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, mid-treatment (week 4), 1 week post-treatment (week 11), 3 months after post-treatment (week 24)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reductions in Intolerance of Uncertainty Scale Score (IUS-12)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, mid-treatment (week 4), 1 week post-treatment (week 11), 3 months after post-treatment (week 24).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reductions in Emotion Regulation Questionnaire Score (ERQ)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, mid-treatment (week 4), 1 week post-treatment (week 11), 3 months after post-treatment (week 24).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction in WHODAS-II score</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, mid-treatment (week 4), 1 week post-treatment (week 11), 3 months after post-treatment (week 24).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Self-identified as suffering from PTSD/experienced a major trauma
- Meet criteria for PTSD as determined by the Mini International Neuropsychiatric Interview Version 5.0.0 (MINI; Sheehan et al., 1998)
- Australian residential status
- At least 18 years of age
- Access to a computer, internet and printer
- If taking medication, must have been taking the same dose for at least 1 month and not intend to change that dose during the course of the program
- Prepared to provide name, phone number and address, and to provide the name and address of a local general practitioner
- Willing to provide written informed consent
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Does not meet PTSD diagnostic criteria
- Trauma occurrence within the past 4 weeks
- Currently participating in CBT or other treatment for trauma or PTSD
- Currently highly dissociative (indicated by score greater than or equal to 40 on the Dissociative Experiences Scale)
- Current or pending medicolegal proceedings associated with the reported trauma
- Applying for or receiving Workers Compensation associated with their trauma or PTSD
- Regularly using illicit drugs or regularly consuming more than three standard drinks per day
- Current regular use of benzodiazepines
- Currently experiencing a psychotic mental illness or bipolar disorder
- Severe symptoms of depression (defined as a total score of at least 22 or responding at least 2 to Question 9 (suicidal ideation) on the Patient Health Questionnaire_9 Item (PHQ-9) will require risk assessment with the responsible clinician before being admitted into the study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants apply online, followed by a telephone interview to confirm diagnosis via the Mini-International Neuropsychiatric Interview (MINI), a structured clinical interview.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomized using a list generated prior to the study. Allocation concealment will occur in the following way: A staff member not involved in the clinical trial will generate the sequence using computer software and place each choice in a sequentially numbered, opaque sealed and stapled envelope.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A pre-to-post-treatment improvement of effect size (ES) 1.0 is expected for the active treatment group on the primary PTSD measure (the PCL-C). This group is also expected to improve more than the waitlist control group by an ES of 0.47. Sample size is powered to have an 80% chance of detecting differences at p&lt;.05. This will require n=72 per group.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/03/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>14/09/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>2/01/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>2/01/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>144</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>49</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>16/06/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The project aims to evaluate the acceptability and clinical efficacy of the online PTSD program; and to examine the role of intolerance of uncertainty and emotion regulation in PTSD symptom change following the PTSD Program. 

Up to 144 people with PTSD will be randomly assigned to either the active treatment group or a waitlist 
control group. The treatment group will commence the PTSD program immediately, whereas the waitlist control group will commence once the treatment group has completed. 

PTSD program efficacy will be determined by comparing the PTSD symptom levels of each group at the time the treatment group completes treatment. The role of intolerance of uncertainty and emotion regulation in PTSD symptom change will be examined using mediation analysis.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>St Vincent's Hospital
390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>31/03/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/SVH/28</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/02/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Gavin Andrews</name>
      <address>Clinical Research Unit for Anxiety and Depression
390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8382 1405</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gavina@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Adrian Allen</name>
      <address>Clinical Research Unit for Anxiety and Depression
390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8382 1428</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>aallen@stvincents.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Adrian Allen</name>
      <address>Clinical Research Unit for Anxiety and Depression
390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8382 1428</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>aallen@stvincents.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Adrian Allen</name>
      <address>Clinical Research Unit for Anxiety and Depression
390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8382 1428</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>aallen@stvincents.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>