<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362452">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/05/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/05/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000487819</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of Topaz investigational multi-purpose solution when used with two types of contact lenses</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A prospective, bilateral, open-label, parallel group, randomised clinical trial to compare Topaz investigational multi-purpose solution and two commercially available solutions for subjective response, lens deposition and ocular surface effects when used in conjunction with two types of contact lenses in experienced wearers.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Subjective response to different types of contact lens solutions</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Lens deposition</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Ocular surface effects</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal eye development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a prospective, open label clinical trial with two parallel groups of 40 participants each, randomised to ACUVUE [Registered trade mark] OASYS [Trademark] or ACUVUE [Registered trade mark]  2 lenses worn bilaterally for one month on a daily-wear basis (n=80 in total). Each lens-group will be, randomised to COMPLETE [Registered trade mark]  Multi-Purpose Solution Easy Rub [Trademark] Formula or renu [Registered trade mark]  fresh [Trademark] for the first month of the trial only (n=20 in each solution / lens combination). After the first month of lens wear, all participants will be crossed over into Topaz multipurpose solution, whilst continuing wear of the same lens type. Lenses will be worn on a daily-wear basis for a further three months. There will be four scheduled visits: baseline, 1-month visit, 2-month visit, 4-month visit. 
These visits will involve assessment of visual acuity, assessment of ocular comfort using questionnaires employing a 1-10 numeric rating scale and ocular response by examination with a slit-lamp biomicroscope (a specialised microscope for viewing the eye) . Lenses will be worn
a minimum of 5 days per week, 6 hours per day.
All solutions will be used after lens removal and as per manufacturers recommendation: Rub lenses with solution (5 seconds), rinse lenses with solution (5seconds) and store in solutionfor at least 6 hours. Solution is not to be reused.
Contact lenses will be replaced 2x/month.</interventions>
    <comparator>The two commercially available solutions will serve as controls and Topaz will be the test.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ocular comfort as measured with 1-10 numeric rating scales</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and after 1 month, 2 months and 4 months of wear</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ocular surface effetcs as assessed with a slit lamp biomicroscope, which is a specialised microscope to view the eye</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and after 1 month, 2 months and 4 months of wear</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lens deposition as assessed ex vivo with a microscope</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 1 month and 2 months of wear</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Able to read and comprehend English and give informed consent as demonstrated by signing a record of informed consent.
Be at least 18 years old, male or female.
Willing to comply with the wearing and clinical trial visit schedule as directed by the Investigator.
Have ocular health findings considered to be normal and which would not prevent the Participant from safely wearing contact lenses.
Is correctable to at least 6/12 (20/40) or better in each eye with contact lenses.
Be an experienced contact lens wearer
Be able to insert and remove contact lenses.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any pre-existing ocular irritation, injury or condition (including infection or disease) of the cornea, conjunctiva or eyelids that would preclude contact lens fitting and safe wearing of contact lenses.
Any systemic disease that adversely affects ocular health e.g. diabetes, Graves disease, and auto immune diseases such as ankylosing spondylitis, multiple sclerosis, Sjögrens syndrome and systemic lupus erythematosus.  Conditions such as systemic hypertension and arthritis do not automatically exclude prospective Participants.
Use of or a need for concurrent category S3 and above ocular medication at enrolment and/or during the clinical trial.
Use of or a need for any systemic medication or topical medications which may alter normal ocular findings / are known to affect a Participants ocular health / physiology or contact lens performance either in an adverse or beneficial manner at enrolment and/or during the clinical trial. 
NB: Systemic antihistamines are allowed on an as needed basis, provided they are not used prophylactically during the trial and at least 24 hours before the clinical trial product is used.
Eye surgery within 12 weeks immediately prior to enrolment for this trial.
Previous corneal refractive surgery.
Contraindications to contact lens wear.
Known allergy or intolerance to ingredients in any of the clinical trial products.
Currently enrolled in another clinical trial.
Neophytes (potential Participants who have not previously worn contact lenses).
Participation in a clinical trial within the previous 2 weeks for dispensing studies and 48 hours between in-house studies.
Pregnancy*.
The Investigator may, at his / her discretion, exclude anyone who they believe may not be able to fulfil the clinical trial requirements or it is believed to be in the Participants best interests.
*Formal testing of pregnancy is not required. A Participants verbal report is sufficient.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants who satisfy the inclusion/exclusion criteria are enrolled in the trial and are given a sequential participant number. A randomisation plan (see below) is used to allocate contact lens type (and solution) to each participant, based on their unique participant number. A randomisation list will be generated by the biostatistician and applied through the Clinic Data Management system.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation plan will be generated from http://www.randomization.com/.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>4/07/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>18/12/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Abbott Medical Optics, Inc</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>1700 East St. Andrew Place
PO Box 25162 Santa Ana, CA 92799-5162</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Brien Holden Vision Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 5, Rupert Myers Building Gate 14, Barker
Street University of New South Wales, NSW
2052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This trial will examine the effect of a new
solution on subjective response, the ocular surface, and lens deposition. The hypotheses are these outcomes will be similar for each lens type and similar for control solutions</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Limited</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>229 Greenhill Road
Dulwich
South Australia 5065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/06/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/05/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Daniel Tilia</name>
      <address>Level 5, North Wing, RMB, Gate 14, Barker Street,
The University of New South Wales
SYDNEY NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61293857516</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.tilia@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Daniel Tilia</name>
      <address>Level 5, North Wing, RMB, Gate 14, Barker Street,
The University of New South Wales
SYDNEY NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61293857516</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.tilia@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Daniel Tilia</name>
      <address>Level 5, North Wing, RMB, Gate 14, Barker Street,
The University of New South Wales
SYDNEY NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61293857516</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.tilia@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Daniel Tilia</name>
      <address>Level 5, North Wing, RMB, Gate 14, Barker Street, The University of New South Wales SYDNEY NSW 2052  </address>
      <phone>+61293857516</phone>
      <fax />
      <email> d.tilia@brienholdenvision.org  </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>