<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82425">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/07/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/11/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000573358</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Individualised versus conventional enoxaparin dosing: a randomised controlled trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial to investigate whether an individualised dosage of enoxaparin reduces the incidence of minor and major bleeding when compared to conventional dosing in patients receiving treatment doses of enoxaparin for cardiovascular disease</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>PK-Enox</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute Coronary Syndrome</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Deep Vein Thrombosis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Atrial Fibrillation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Pulmonary Embolism</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients will be randomly assigned to either a conventional dosing regimen or a pharmacokinetically-guided dosing regimen. 
The amount of the first dose will be at the discretion of the prescribing doctor. 
Patients will be enrolled by an investigator at the start of their enoxaparin treatment. 

The pharmacokinetically-guided dosing regimen involves the following:
1. Initial dose as normal (please see below)
2. A blood sample will be collected 2-6 hours after the dose
3. enoxaparin concentration determined by measuring anti-factor Xa concentration in the sample
4. a pharmacokinetic (PK) analysis, based on enoxaparin concentration, will be carried out to estimate concentration-time profile
5. a subsequent dose will be recommended based on the PK analysis such that peak concentrations are over 500 IU/L and trough concentrations are below 500 IU/L.

Current criteria for initial dose are:
1. Venous thromboembolism (VTE)	1 mg/kg twice a day or 1.5 mg/kg daily based on total body weight (TBW)
2. Non-ST-elevation acute coronary syndrome	1 mg/kg twice a day based on TBW
3. Severe renal impairment	CLCR &lt; 30 ml/min* = 1 mg/kg daily based on TBW

The range of dosage for each regimen is:
In a conventional dosing regimen, enoxaparin dose is based on total body weight. That is, a 40 kg patient without severe renal impairment would receive 40 mg twice daily; a 40 kg patient with severe renal impairment would receive 40 mg once daily; a 140 kg patient without severe renal impairment would receive 140 mg twice daily; and a 140 kg patient with severe renal impairment would receive 140 mg once daily.

In a pharmacokinetically-guided dosing regimen, enoxaparin dose is based on patient demographics and enoxaparin concentration. The dose is unlikely to fall outside the range above (40-140 mg) but details are patient-specific and unavailable at this stage.

For both regimens enoxaparin is administered subcutaneously

Duration of intervention:
While on enoxaparin treatment (usually 2-8 days)

Duration of the overall intervention:
While on enoxaparin treatment (2-8 days). Patients will be followed up for up to 30 days after the commencement of treatment in order to monitor evidence of therapeutic outcomes and events such as revascularisation, re-thrombosis, or repeat emboli.</interventions>
    <comparator>The conventional dosing regimen for all patients will be that determined by the prescribing doctor (and as recommended by the manufacture and approved by Medsafe).</comparator>
    <control>Dose comparison</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary endpoint of this study will be the total number of patients with a bleeding event. A bleeding event incorporates any major or minor bleed. A major bleed is defined by a decrease in hemoglobin greater than 30 g/L or evidence of an internal anatomical bleed such as retroperitoneal, intracranial or intraocular (as used in the TIMI 11B trial, Antman et al. Circulation 1999; 100(15):1593-601). 
Minor bleed is defined as a bleed other than a major bleed, e.g. epistaxis, haematuria, an injection or venepuncture site bleeding, and haematemesis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All patients will be inspected daily for signs of bleeding by an investigator who is blinded to treatment.
This will take a few minutes each occasion and the investigator will be using a Clinical Report Form to record findings. 
Each patient will be monitored for a period of 2-8 days of treatment and for as many days as the patient remains in hospital as per usual care (expected 24-48 hours). Each assessment will take approximately 10 minutes.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary endpoint is defined as a composite of any primary endpoint and any single major bruise that has a surface area of greater than 20 cm2 and is distal to the site of injection and venipuncture sites for blood draws (as used in a post hoc analysis of the ESSENCE study, Berkowitz et al. Am J Cardiol. 2001; 88(11):1230-4)</outcome>
      <timepoint>All patients will be inspected daily for signs of bleeding by an investigator who is blinded to treatment.
This will take a few minutes each occasion and the investigator will be using a Clinical Report Form to record findings.
Each patient will be monitored for a period of 2-8 days of treatment and for as many days as the patient remains in hospital as per usual care (expected 24-48 hours). Each assessment will take approximately 10 minutes.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All patients admitted for treatment with enoxaparin who are likely to require treatment for at least 48 hours are eligible for inclusion into the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients who are pregnant; less than 18 years old; have received warfarin in the past 7 days or heparin therapy (unfractionated heparin 'UFH' or low-molecular weight heparin 'LMWH') in the last day; have an international normalised ratio 'INR' &gt; 1.2 or an Activated Partial Thromboplastin Time 'APTT' &gt; 60 seconds at the time of recruitment; or an estimated creatinine clearance less than 10 ml/min (using the Cockcroft and Gault equation calculated based on lean body weight).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>1.	block randomisation (block of 10) to be undertaken by HA who is blinded
2.	consenting patients to be undertaken by HA or JS
3.	randomisation of patient to be undertaken by HA. Allocation is concealed and allocation schedule is off-site to be held by SD
4.	collecting blood samples from all patients to be undertaken by HA, L, JS, or FV
5.	assaying blood samples from all patients to be undertaken by HA 
6.	analysing blood sample and using TCIWorks to estimate a dose for every patient to be undertaken by HA. HA will then print out a pharmacokinetic profile (including time for next sample) and hand this to JS or RW 
7.	JS or RW will check with SD (who has possession of the allocation schedule) whether the patient is in individualised or controlled group (unconcealment) and heed dose recommendation only if patient is in the individualised group
8.	bleeding and bruising assessment to be undertaken by L (by using lab results recorded in the programme iSOFT, by performing a physical assessment, and by checking the clinical notes) or by HA (by using lab results recorded in the programme iSOFT and by performing a physical assessment).
9.	the 30-day follow up to be undertaken by HA by accessing the programme ORACARE.
10.	the final analysis to be undertake by HA</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer-generated randomisation table.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/11/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>140</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Dunedin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Otago</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>School of Pharmacy</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Pharmacy
University of Otago
PO Box 913
Dunedin 9054</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Otago Medical Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Otago Medical Research Foundation
PO BOx 1245
Dunedin 9054</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr John Schollum</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of Nephrology
Dunedin Hospital
Private Bag 1921
Dunedin 9054</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Enoxaparin is a low molecular weight heparin (LMWH) widely used in clinical practice (e.g. heart attacks, and clots in the lungs. It has been proven to be a safe and effective alternative to the traditional unfractionated heparin (UFH). Unlike UFH where dose is monitored, enoxaparin is given on a weight-based regime, without any monitoring. The safety of this dosing regimen of enoxaparin is not well established particularly in patients who are obese or have kidney disease. The effect of enoxaparin can be monitored by measuring a serum protein (anti-Xa). It is known that there is an increased rate of bleeding complications if the anti-Xa concentration is higher than 1000 IU/L.

We wish to undertake a randomised controlled trial of patients admitted to Dunedin Hospital who are treated with enoxaparin. Patients will be randomly assigned to either a conventional dosing regimen or a pharmacokinetically-guided dosing regimen. The main endpoints are minor and major bleeding events as defined in the literature (Antman et al. Circulation 1999; 100(15):1593-601).

The conventional dosing regimen for all patients will be that determined by the prescribing doctor (as per the products license).  For the pharmacokinetically-guided dosing regimen, the initial dosing regimen is one chosen by the prescribing doctor. Subsequent doses will be calculated using the anti-Xa concentration obtained from blood samples.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Lower South Regional Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Administrator: Riria Tautau-Grant

Postal address:
229 Moray Place
PO Box 5849
Dunedin 9054</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/01/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Project Key: LRS/07/11/041 Lower South Regional Ethics Committee</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Hesham Al-Sallami</name>
      <address>School of Pharmacy
University of Otago
PO Box 913
Dunedin 9054, New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+6434797295</phone>
      <fax>+6434797034</fax>
      <email>hesham.al-sallami@stonebow.otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Hesham Al-Sallami</name>
      <address>School of Pharmacy
University of Otago
PO Box 913
Dunedin 9054, New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+6434797295</phone>
      <fax>+6434797034</fax>
      <email>hesham.al-sallami@stonebow.otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Hesham Al-Sallami</name>
      <address>School of Pharmacy
University of Otago
PO Box 913
Dunedin 9054, New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+6434797295</phone>
      <fax>+6434797034</fax>
      <email>hesham.al-sallami@stonebow.otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>