<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369240">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/09/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/10/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001040550</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of the impact of surgical repair of rib fractures compared to non surgical management of rib fractures on pain and quality of life.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle> Evaluation of the impact of operative fixation of displaced rib fractures compared to non surgical management of rib fractures on pain and quality of life.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>fractured ribs</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fractures</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study will look specifically at patients with multiple painful broken ribs and surgical fixation of displaced ribs using plates and screws as required to hold fractured ribs in the correct position to allow healing - these plates and screws remain in  situ after healing.  The duration of the surgery to repair the fractured ribs will depend upon the individual injury and be performed by a qualified cardiothoracic surgeon. We will compare a group treated with an operation to fix the broken ribs with plates and screws to a group treated with pain control and full supportive measures that are currently our standard of care. Study Participant's Quality of life and recovery from injury will be followed up in the months after treatment for the rib fractures.</interventions>
    <comparator>Non surgical medical management of rib fractures.
This may include pain relief medications, oxygen support and mechanical ventilation</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain and disability at 3 months post injury (composite endpoint assessed using McGill Pain Questionnaire and SF12 Questionnaire)

</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post injury</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>*Pain control / analgesic requirements  (Assessed by auditing the use of narcotic drugs and other analgesics)





</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months post injury</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>*(Composite endpoint) Non-invasive ventilator requirements / respiratory complications during hospital stay (eg. pneumonia, pneumothorax (barotrauma), tracheostomy insertion, intercostal catheter usage and duration, readmission to ICU)   (assessed by review of hospital records)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 &amp; 12 months post injury</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>*Incidence of wound complications related to the rib fixation
 (assessment by review of patient medical records)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 &amp; 12 months post injury</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>*Hospital length of stay (assessment by review of patient medical records)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 &amp; 12 months post injury</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>*Mortality  (assessment by review of patient medical records)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 &amp; 12 months post injury</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>*Discharge destination  (assessment by review of patient medical records)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 &amp; 12 months post injury</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>*Work or usual activity days lost - Patients will be questioned about their return to work and the type of work activity they are performing. (i.e. full time, part time, manual labour, desk duties etc) Assessed during Patient clinical review at 6 &amp; 12 months </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 &amp; 12 months post injury</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>*Pain and quality of life at 6 and 12 months (composite endpoint)
Quality of Life is Assessed using the SF12 Questionnaire
Pain is assessed using the McGill Pain Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 &amp; 12 months post injury</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>*Previously functionally independent patients with multiple, closed fractured ribs  between the level of ribs 3 to 10 confirmed on CXR and CT chest. 
*Uncontrolled pain from fractured ribs and/ or displaced fractured ribs
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>*Pre-injury dependency requiring ADL support
*Invasive ventilator support at the time of referral (patients will not be excluded if they deteriorate and require invasive ventilator support after initial referral)
*Spinal injuries which would preclude placement of the patient in a lateral decubitus position
*Open rib fractures with soiling or infection
*Severe head injury
*Uncorrected coagulopathy
*Adult respiratory distress syndrome
*Uncorrected Sepsis
*Pregnancy
*Immunocompromised patients including  those who are steroid dependent
*Known opiate dependency
*Age&lt; 18 years or &gt;85 years
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients will be recruited from the Alfred Trauma Service. Any patients with rib fractures, admitted under the trauma unit will be referred to the cardiothoracic surgery unit for screening. Patients who fulfill the entry criteria for this study will be enrolled. Patients will be randomised via selection of a sealed opaque envelope to operative or non operative arms.
</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer program will be used to generate the Randomisation sequence.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Pain and disability at three months post injury is the primary endpoint therefore sample size calculation will be based on that.
Using results of the relevant study by Fabricant (2013),  sample size calculation has been completed using MPQ-PRI index scores for patients with rib fracture treated conservatively, population mean 28 + 16 during index admission, reducing to mean 10.6 +- 10.9 sd @ 60 days (n=187) CI 95% = 1.56. In that study, Fabricant assumed a reduction in MPQ-PRI score to less than 8 correlated with a good reduction in pain to allow return to normal duties. Using that data, and assuming an a of 0.05 and power of 0.8 to detect a difference in MPQ-PPI, MPQ-PRI index scores, 21 patients per group will be needed. To allow for drop out in the follow up phase of the study, 25 participants per group will be recruited to ensure adequate sample size for analysis at study completion.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/04/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>24/04/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
    <postcode>3181 - Prahran</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Alfred Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>55 Commercial Road
Melbourne 3004
Victoria</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The optimal management of patients with fractured ribs who are not ventilator dependent has still not been determined.  Although various studies suggest improvements in both short and long term function in patients who are treated by operative stabilization, there is not enough good evidence to advise management practices.  However, the evidence available suggests that significant improvements in patient management and long term outcomes could be achieved by surgical fixation of ribs in these patients.  A definitive answer will only be achieved by a prospective trial examining the short-term and longer term outcomes for patients treated by operative stabilization of their rib fractures
This study aims to assess early and late outcomes in patients with multiple painful displaced fractured ribs with and without operative fixation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Alfred Human Research Ethics Committee (EC00315)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Alfred Hospital
55 Commercial Road
Melbourne 3004
Victoria</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/03/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>510/14</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Silvana Marasco</name>
      <address>The Alfred Department of Cardiothoracic Surgery
55 Commercial road
Melbourne 3004
Victoria </address>
      <phone>+61390763313</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.marasco@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Silvana Marasco</name>
      <address>The Alfred Department of Cardiothoracic Surgery
55 Commercial road
Melbourne 3004
Victoria </address>
      <phone>+61390763313</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.marasco@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Silvana Marasco</name>
      <address>The Alfred Department of Cardiothoracic Surgery
55 Commercial road
Melbourne 3004
Victoria </address>
      <phone>+61390763313</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.marasco@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Robyn Summerhayes</name>
      <address>The Alfred Department of Cardiothoracic Surgery
55 Commercial road
Melbourne 3004
Victoria </address>
      <phone>+61390763313</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.summerhayes@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>