<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369439">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/10/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/10/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001123538</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The analgesic effectiveness of an Ilioinguinal-Transversus Abdominis Plane (iTAP) injection technique nerve block in addition to opioid plus NSAID analgesia for elective Caesarean Sections.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The efficacy of an Ilioinguinal-Transversus Abdominis Plane (iTAP) injection technique nerve block in addition to opioid plus NSAID post-operative analgesia for elective Caesarean Sections under spinal anaesthetic block with intrathecal morphine in reducing the opioid usage in the first 24 hours post-operatively compared to opioid plus NSAID post-operative analgesia alone.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1175-2460</utrn>
    <trialacronym>iTAPIT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pain following caesarean section</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Childbirth and postnatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A single shot bilateral iTAP nerve block using total of 60mls of 0.33% (i.e. 200mg) ropivacaine post-caesarean section in the Post-Operative Recovery Unit (PARU) before spinal anaesthetic has worn off

iTAP - TECHNIQUE
Single shot nerve block which combines a traditional TAP block and a traditional ilioinguinal-iliohypogastric nerve block.

Landmarks: 2cm medial and superior to the ASIS. Sonoplex short bevel needle inserted perpendicular to skin until "1st pop" is felt and 10mls ropivacaine injected. Needle advanced until "2nd pop" felt and 20mls of ropivacaine is injected. Nerve block repeated on the other side. </interventions>
    <comparator>Control group will receive a simulated block. This includes skin preparation, needle sensation simulation using a blunt needle without skin puncture and identical dressings to the intervention group. Patients will be blinded through the use of a screen during block performance.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total PCA opioid (fentanyl) usage by review of medical records (PCA chart)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 4, 8, 16 and 24 hours post iTAP/simulated nerve block</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain assessed using a VAS (visual analogue scale) (mm) on movement and at rest.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 4, 8, 16 and 24 hours post iTAP/simulated nerve block</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Opioid adverse effects 
- Sedation score as reviews in medical records from nursing / APS observation
- Nausea and/or vomiting requiring treatment as expressed by participant / medical records
- Pruritus requiring treatment as reviewed in medical records from nursing / APS observation</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 4, 8, 16 and 24 hours post iTAP/simulated nerve block</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Additional analgesia required by review of medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours post iTAP/simulated nerve block</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>iTAP nerve block complications. Assessed by review of medical records and as expressed by participant. Potential complications include bleeding, infection, peritoneal puncture, LA toxicity, femoral nerve palsy and LA allergy </outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours post iTAP/simulated nerve block</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Score of maternal satisfaction with post-operative analgesia (excellent, satisfactory, neutral,  unsatisfactory, no benefit) as assessed by brief questionnaire designed for this study given to participant 24 hours post nerve block</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours post iTAP/simulated nerve block</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of potentially confounding variables as obtained from participant and medical records.
Information includes: 
- Age (years)
- Gravidity and Parity
- ASA (1-4)
- Weight at time of booking (kg)
- Height at time of booking (cm)
- BMI at time of booking
- Previous LSCS (yes or no)
- Previous abdominal surgeries (yes or no)
- Time of spinal 
- Duration of surgery (min)
- Regular paracetamol received post-operatively (yes or no)
- Regular NSAID received post-operatively (yes or no)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>No specific time point. Information will be collected during participation in trial.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Competent to sign consent
Elective Caesarean Section</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Emergency surgery
Age &lt; 18 years
&lt; 65kg
Inability to consent, lack of written consent or speak English fluently
Contraindication to spinal anaesthetic or block
Allergy to local anaesthetics or morphine
Pre-operative chronic opioid use or chronic pain syndrome
Progressive neurological disease
Patients in EREC (enhanced recovery after elective Caesarean Section) protocol</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed opaque envelopes opened by block proceduralist just prior to performance of block</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>We aim to recruit 100 participants in total (50 participants per group). This is consistent with a similar previous study that calculated a sample size of 90 participants in total (not accounting for dropouts) for total opioid usage at 24 hours based on a minimum detectable difference between means of 20 mg, alpha=0.05, power=0.9, and standard deviation of 25 / 30 mg with a two sample, two-tailed Students t-test. Our study includes repeated measures of total opioid usage at 0, 4, 8, 16, and 24 hours and will likely have greater statistical power, but no pilot data is available for formal power analysis. 

Statisitcal analyses will be performed using Stata/IC 14.0 (StataCorp, Texas, USA) using an intention-to-treat approach. The statistician will be blinded to the coding of analgesia type in the data. Continuous variables (total opioid usage, visual analogue scale) will be analysed with a two-way repeated measures ANOVA with a between-subjects factor of analgesia type and a within-subjects factor of time, and assumptions checked using residuals diagnostics. Binary outcomes (presence of nausea/vomiting, pruritus requiring treatment, additional analgesia at 24 hours, iTAP block complications at 24 hours) will be analysed with Fishers Exact Test. Ordinal variables (sedation score, maternal satisfaction) will be analysed using ordinal logistic regression with one predictor variable, analgesia type. All analyses will use alpha=0.05 with no family-wise corrections. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>4/02/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/06/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>29/06/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>100</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>30/06/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Lyell McEwin Hospital - Elizabeth Vale</hospital>
    <postcode>5112 - Elizabeth Vale</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Jessica Staker</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Lyell McEwin Hospital
Haydown Road
Elizabeth Vale
SA 5112</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Dr Jessica Staker</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Lyell McEwin Hospital
Haydown Road
Elizabeth Vale
SA 5112</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Thien LeCong</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Lyell McEwin Hospital
Haydown Road
Elizabeth Vale
Sa 5112</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Richard Church</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Lyell McEwin Hospital
Haydown Road
Elizabeth Vale
SA 5112</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>PURPOSE
One of the methods of providing pain relief after a Caesarean Section involves the injection of local anaesthetic into the muscle layers to surround the nerves that supply pain sensation to the lower abdomen. These blocks are called Ilioinguinal / Iliohypogastric nerve blocks and Transversus Abdominis Plane (TAP) blocks and have been used for a range of surgeries. This helps to reduce pain over the surgical wound where the Caesarean Section is performed.

The purpose of this study is to determine if combining these blocks in addition to opioid and anti-inflammatory pain management will improve pain relief in the first 24 hours for women who have an elective Caesarean Section. This block will be performed at the end of the Caesarean section before the spinal anaesthetic has worn off.

HYPOTHESIS
Our primary aim is to determine whether administering the modified Ilioinguinal-Transversus Abdominis Plane (iTAP) nerve block in addition to opioid plus NSAID analgesia is superior to opioid plus NSAID analgesia alone following caesarean section with a Pfannenstiel incision.

STUDY DESIGN AND INTERVENTION
Approximately 100 volunteers will participate in this study and the study will be conducted at the Lyell McEwin Hospital. You will be enrolled in this study on the day of your Caesarean Section and randomly allocated to one of two groups. One group will receive pain medication with the iTAP block in the Post Anaesthetic Recovery Unit (PARU) as well as opioid medication (Fentanyl) through a Patient Controlled Analgesia (PCA) device. The second group will receive pain medication with the PCA but will receive a placebo block. A placebo is a medication with no active ingredients or a procedure without any medical benefit. It will feel like the real thing but it is not. Your participation in the study will continue until 24 hours after the iTAP block / placebo block.

OUTCOMES
We will be measuring total pain medication usage (opioids) and pain levels (VAS) over a 24 hour period. We will also measure adverse side effects of pain medication and the block, as well as the satisfaction of our participants. Hopefully there will be less pain and pain medication usage in our interventional group.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>N/A</trialwebsite>
    <publication>N/A</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>N/A</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital/Lyell McEwin Hospital/Modbury Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Basil Hetzel Institute
28 Woodville Road
Woodville South
SA 5011
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/12/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/TQEH/196</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/09/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Site specific ethics - Northern Adelaide Local Health Network</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research governance office
Level 2, clinical trials unit 
Lyell McEwin hospital 
Haydown road
Elizabeth vale 
SA
5112</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/12/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>SSA/15/NALHN/102</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/11/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jessica Staker</name>
      <address>Lyell McEwin Hospital
Haydown road
Elizabeth Vale
SA 5112</address>
      <phone>+618 81829000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jjstaker@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jessica Staker</name>
      <address>Lyell McEwin Hospital
Haydown Road
Elizabeth Vale
SA 5112</address>
      <phone>+6181829000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jjstaker@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jessica Staker</name>
      <address>Lyell McEwin Hospital
Haydown Road
Elizabeth Vale
SA 5112</address>
      <phone>+618 81829000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jjstaker@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jessica Staker</name>
      <address>Lyell McEwin Hospital
Haydown Road 
Elizabeth Vale
SA 5112</address>
      <phone>+618 81829000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jjstaker@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>