<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370475">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/04/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/04/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000489493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Parkinson's and Memory: The Effect of Brain Stimulation</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Parkinsons disease and Working Memory: The Effect of Transcranial Direct Current Stimulation</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Parkinson's disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Parkinson's disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Transcranial direct current stimulation is a technique that non-invasively stimulates the brain by applying electrical currents to a small region of the scalp, which transmit into the brain.  For the current project, the current strength will be 2 milliamperes (mA). Two milliamps is low strength stimulation and you may feel some tingling sensations from the stimulation. 

The tDCS session involves continuous stimulation at a fixed current of 2 milliamperes (mA) that is applied to the scalp, which will be delivered for 20 minutes. The intervention group will only receive a single 20 minute session of tDCS. The student researcher, Ms. Johanna Stephens, will be administering the treatment. Ms Stephens has received training in administering tDCS. In most cases tDCS poses a negligible risk. Mild tingling sensations under the electrodes during tDCS and minor headaches have been reported after stimulation and the electrodes can cause some redness on the scalp that typically last up to an hour. However, no serious adverse events have been reported. Participants will be instructed to report any discomfort they experience during the stimulation and that the stimulation will be terminated immediately if this should occur. At the completion of the tDCS, participants will be asked to complete a questionnaire regarding any side-effects they had. This will provide a record for the researcher and results are typically reported in the manuscript. Testing will be conducted at Swinburne University of Technology (Hawthorn campus). 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Half of the participants will randomly receive active stimulation and half will receive sham stimulation. Sham stimulation emits a brief current but then remains off for the remainder of the stimulation time. The stimulation session will last approximately 20 minutes. Testing will be conducted at Swinburne University of Technology (Hawthorn campus). </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome of the study is memory. This will be assessed using an n-back task, which is a standard research tool used to assess working memory. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Memory will be assessed at baseline and immediately post-stimulation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>NA</outcome>
      <timepoint>NA</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Have a diagnosis of Parkinsons disease
2.	Those aged between 18 and 80 years of age
3.	Have normal or corrected-to-normal vision
4.	Have normal or corrected-to-normal hearing
5.	Speak and understand English fluently

Normal or corrected-to-normal vision and hearing will be assessed informally by the researcher, Ms. Johanna Stephens. Participants will be asked if they need glasses/hearing aid or assistance. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Currently involved in any therapeutic trial
2.	Previously experienced moderate or severe head injury/stroke/other neurological impairment
3.	Had neurosurgery
4.	Major medical illness (cardiovascular; diabetes requiring insulin; severe migraine)
5.	Previous diagnosis of PTSD, personality disorder, schizophrenia and/or psychosis. 
6.	Anxiety disorder in the last 6 months
7.	Significant psychiatric illness requiring hospitalisation
8.	Major depression in the last 6 months
9.	Dementia/hallucinations
10.	Indication of excess alcohol abuse
11.	Currently taking medications known to have a significant effect on CNS other than anti-PD medication
12.	Diagnosis or special education for learning disability
13.	History of epilepsy or seizure disorders
14.	Metal implant in their head or body (including surgical implants, pace-makers, orthodontic braces). 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Parkville
Victoria 3052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Melbourne</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Parkville
Victoria 3052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of the study is to investigate the effect of brain stimulation on memory in those with Parkinsons disease. The investigation will use a type of transcranial current stimulation (TCS) called transcranial direct current stimulation (tDCS) to examine the effect of stimulation on memory. Some of the difficulties that individuals with Parkinsons disease often experience are problems with their memory. Research has found marked impairment in the accuracy of memory tasks when compared to those without the disease. 
Transcranial direct current stimulation is a technique that non-invasively stimulates the brain by applying electrical currents to a small region of the scalp, which transmit into the brain. The currents are usually in the order of a few milliamps and stimulation lasts for several minutes. For the current project, the strength will be 2 milliamperes (mA) and delivered for 20 minutes to test the impact this has on memory performance. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>55 Commercial Rd, Melbourne VIC 3004</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/12/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>484/15</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>21/09/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Melbourne</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Parkville
Victoria 3052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/04/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Swinburne University of Technology</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>John Street
Hawthorn
P.O. Box 218
Victoria 3122</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/04/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>SHR Project 2016/082</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/04/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Audrey McKinlay</name>
      <address>The University of Melbourne
Parkville
Victoria 3052</address>
      <phone>+613 9035 5180</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>audrey.mckinlay@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Johanna Stephens</name>
      <address>University of Melbourne
Parkville
Victoria 3052</address>
      <phone>+613 9035 5180</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tdcsparkinsonsdiseasestudy@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Audrey McKinlay</name>
      <address>University of Melbourne
Parkville
Victoria 3052</address>
      <phone>+613 9035 5180</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>audrey.mckinlay@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Johanna Stephens</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>