<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365212">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/10/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/11/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001251718</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Indacaterol in Lymphangioleiomymotosis (LAM) Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A double blind, randomised placebo controlled within patient cross-over study to assess the efficacy and safety of indacaterol (150 micrograms once daily) in the symptomatic treatment of pulmonary lymphangioleiomyomatosis (LAM)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>TILT </trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Lymphangioleiomyomatosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Double blind placebo controlled cross-over trial, studying efficacy and safety of inhaled indacaterol 150 micrograms daily in women with lymphangioleiomyomatosis. Treatment duration 2 weeks for active drug and placebo; washout period 2-6 weeks according to patient convenience. Inhaled medication will be returned at end of treatment periods to monitor adherence.</interventions>
    <comparator>Identical placebo (glucose)</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1.	To evaluate the efficacy of indacaterol in terms of change in trough forced expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV1) versus baseline in women with lymphangioleiomyomatosis (LAM).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 week treatment period for both active drug and placebo; assessments at baseline and end of treatment periods in each case. Symptom score monitoring during treatment periods.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary
1. To examine the effect of indacaterol on quality of life measurements (QoL as measured by SF-36 and other measures) in women with LAM.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 week treatment with drug and placebo; QoL and lung function measured at baseline and after treatment periods.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2. To examine the effect of indacaterol on airway inflammation in LAM using non-invasive exhaled breath monitoring (fractional exhaled nitric oxide assessment, electronic nose analysis (ENA)) and some blood based biomarkers including  VEGF-D, HGF, ACE, MMP 2 and 9.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurements: FeNO, ENA, blood based biomarkers at baseline and after treatment periods.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Women:

1.	Age: 18-80 inclusive.
1.2.	Diagnosed with LAM and classified into possible, probable and definite according to ERS criteria (1).
1.3.	Willingness and ability to participate in the study after fully informed consent.
1.4.	Both sporadic LAM (sLAM) and TSC-LAM (tuberous sclerosis-related LAM) to be included.
1.5.	Women with all severity categories of LAM are eligible to participate in the study but those on continuous home oxygen will be excluded, as well as those not sufficiently well to participate in the requisite tests.


</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria: 
1. Known sensitivity to indacaterol or the class of long acting beta agonists
2. Patients with severe medical condition(s) which in the view of the investigator prohibit participation in the study (e.g. uncontrolled diabetes, uncontrolled heart failure, severe renal or liver disease, high blood pressure, coronary artery disease, cardiac arrhythmias, thyroid disorders, or lactose intolerance).
3. Use of any other investigational agent within the last 30 days
4. Current smoking or smoking within 6 months of study start.
5. Concurrent respiratory disease including a diagnosis of asthma (provided LAM has not been misdiagnosed as asthma prior to the diagnosis of LAM). Pleural pathology from previous pleurodeses and disease related to LAM are not included in this category.
6. Respiratory tract infection of exacerbation within the previous 4 weeks. Patients can be re-entered into the trial after a 4 week recovery period, provided baseline FEV1 is within 10% of first study period.
7. Treatment with oral glucocorticosteroids within the previous 4 weeks.
8. Women of childbearing potential not using adequate contraceptive method(s) including the oral contraceptive pill, barrier contraception, IUD, as well as women who are breastfeeding.
9.  Patients on continuous oxygen therapy.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomization will be performed by the investigator according to a randomization study code. An unblinded pharmacist will dispense the study drug to ensure double blinding. The randomization code may be broken by the investigator only in a medical emergency. The reasons for this must be documented carefully.”

</concealment>
    <sequence>Random computerised sequence generation - small number of subjects only</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Washout period of 2-6 weeks according to patient convenience.

Pre-study power calculation yields a sample size of 13 patients, to have 90% power (at alpha equals 0.05, two sided test) to detect a 10% difference, assuming a minimum difference of 100 mls between treatment groups. To be conservative, 15 patients will be included. FEV1 and FVC are highly reproducible in most patients, with differences between highest and lowest values of less than 6%, and these data are applicable to LAM patients. The advantage of a double blind crossover design is that variation is minimized. When considering the degree of change in FEV1 that is considered clinically meaningful by the regulators, a change of 510% from baseline values is usually considered to be clinically important, or an increase of FEV1 of greater than 12% or 200 mls. However, in this trial we are selecting for subjects who do not have bronchodilator reversibility so only a small lung function change is anticipated. In LAM, both FEV1 and DLCO have been reported as predictors of progression but a change in DLCO is not expected to change in this short-term trial, so this measurement is a secondary rather than a primary outcome variable).</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Analyses will be performed according to the intention-to-treat principle. The primary outcome, the FEV1 response measured in milliliters per week over the course of 2 weeks (the FEV1 change), will be analyzed as the difference in the FEV1 slope between the placebo group and the indacterol group. Differences in FEV1 will be analysed by a students matched pair t-test.
For categorical outcomes, the data will be compared using Fisher's exact test or the chi-square test, as appropriate. For continuous variables, the medians will be compared with the use of the Wilcoxon rank-sum test. p values of less than 0.05  will be considered to indicate statistical significance. All reported p values will be two-sided, and unadjusted for multiple testing. All analyses will be performed with the use of SPSS software, version 4.0. .Data will be presented for the complete intent-to-treat population (all patients having taken at least one dose of study medication) as well as the per-protocol population (all patients who completed the study without major protocol deviations). 

FeNO values will be log transformed and analysed using paired t-tests. ENA analysis will take place using appropriate statistics. Smellprints using the Cyranose 320 will be analysed using on-board learning software. SavitzkyGolay filtering (which performs a local polynomial regression (of degree k) on a series of values) will be utilised to process the sensor response data and baseline corrections will be applied to improve signal-to-noise ratio. To reduce the data from 32 individual sensors to a set of principal components, principal component analysis (PCA) will be used. This determines factors that capture the largest variance in the data. PCA factors will be then used to perform a linear canonical discrimination analysis for the construction of a pattern recognition algorithm. This will be achieved by enhancing the ratio of pooled within-class scatter to between-group distance. A cross validation value (CVV%) will be calculated, to give an estimate of error, or in other words, the accuracy in distinction between the smellprints from different subject groups. The Mahalanobis distance (M-distance) between group means, in units of standard deviation, will be calculated. This will be used to quantify the discrimination between sample groups, providing a measure of dissimilarity between two samples. Thus, M-distance and the ability to discriminate are directly related, so that values greater than 3 will be indicative of a high probability of discrimination (p less than 0.01).

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/11/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>14/12/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>15</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Darlinghurst) - Darlinghurst</hospital>
    <postcode>2010 - Darlinghurst</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Deborah H Yates</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Dept Thoracic Medicine
St Vincent's Hospital
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Novartis 
(Investigator initiated study)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Novartis Pharmaceuticals Australia Pty Limited 54 Waterloo Road North Ryde NSW 2113</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Holdsworth House Medical Practice (HHMP),</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>32A Oxford St
Darlinghurst
NSW 2010</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Lymphangioleiomyomatosis (LAM) is a rare lung disease restricted to adult women. This may occur either sporadically (s-LAM) or in association with tuberous sclerosis (TSC-LAM). The lungs of patients with LAM are infiltrated by smooth muscle cells (LAM cells).There is a very limited evidence base for treatment of LAM and it is only recently that the first randomised trials have been initiated. The LAM clinic at St Vincents follows the largest number of women with LAM in Australia, currently approximately 40 patients. The first ever trial into the efficacy of doxycycline in LAM was completed at St Vincents LAM clinic, and this new study aims to assist the breathlessness associated with this disease and evaluate the mechanisms underlying this.
Indacaterol is a novel, inhaled, once-daily, ultra-long-acting beta 2-agonist for the treatment of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD). Bronchodilator agents are frequently prescribed in LAM but have never been the subject of a clinical trial. Long acting beta2-agonists have been described as having anti-proliferative effects on smooth muscle in vitro as well as in vitro, but these agents have not yet been investigated in LAM. It is theoretically possible that women with LAM will respond clinically, and it is also possible that indacaterol might have a beneficial effect within the airway. This trial will evaluate indacaterol in LAM using a classical study design ie. a double blind placebo controlled trial, in 15 women with LAM.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.holdsworthhouse.com.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of New South Wales HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>High St, Kensington NSW 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>31/07/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC Ref: # HC13202</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Deborah Yates</name>
      <address>Dept Thoracic Medicine, St Vincent's Hospital, Victoria St, Darlinghurst, NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>61-2-8382-2330</phone>
      <fax>61-2-83822359</fax>
      <email>deborahy88@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Trina Vincent</name>
      <address>Holdsworth House Medical Practice
Suite 1, Level 2, 32A Oxford St, Darlinghurst NSW 2010 </address>
      <phone>61-2- 8032- 1044</phone>
      <fax>61-2- 9331-5705 </fax>
      <email>Trina.Vincent@holdsworthhouse.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Deborah H Yates</name>
      <address>Dept Thoracic Medicine, St Vincent's Hospital, Victoria St, Darlinghurst, NSw 2010</address>
      <phone>61-2-8382-2330</phone>
      <fax>61-2-8382-2359</fax>
      <email>Deborahy88@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Trina Vincent</name>
      <address>Holdsworth House Medical Practice
Suite 1, Level 2, 32A Oxford St, Darlinghurst NSW 2010 </address>
      <phone>61-2- 8032- 1044</phone>
      <fax>61-2- 9331-5705 </fax>
      <email>Trina.Vincent@holdsworthhouse.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>