<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370347">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/03/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/03/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000387426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Central Venous Access Device (CVAD) Registry - an electronic database to monitor the outcomes of patients with CVADs</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Central Venous Access Device (CVAD) Registry - an electronic database to monitor the outcomes of patients with CVADs at the Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>CVAD failure (infective and mechanical complications)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The CVAD Registry is designed to capture information relevant to CVAD insertion, management and outcomes for patients receiving in-patient and out-patient treatment at the Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital (RBWH). The Registry will collate data that is currently collected within multiple departments at the RBWH and store it in a single database. It will enable researchers and clinicians to explore CVAD trends and examine device-related complications, as well as increase their understanding of device failure, therefore improving clinical outcomes for patients with CVADs.

The CVAD Registry will prospectively collect clinical data on CVAD characteristics, adverse outcomes and risk factors. Clinical data will be collected on all patients at the RBWH requiring a CVAD.on or after the Registry commencement date. Patient outcomes will be monitored through electronic medical records until the final CVAD is removed or the patient dies.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To measure the CVAD outcomes (annual CVAD failure rate per 1000-CVAD-days; annual CVAD failure rate per 1000-patient-days) for patients receiving treatment at RBWH. This will be assessed by reviewing electronic medical records and recording the number of days each patient has a CVAD; the number of days each patient is in hospital with a CVAD and recording the outcome (device still in place; reason for device removal) for each CVAD the patient receives at RBWH. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of CVAD removal or after the patient has deceased. Initial findings of CVAD Registry will be analysed after twelve months of data collection.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To identify the cause of CVAD failure per patient and rate of each CVAD Failure subtype within patient population. CVAD failure will be classified into the following subtypes - catheter occlusion; catheter-related thrombosis; migration; dislodgement; CVAD rupture; catheter-related bloodstream infection (CRBSI); central line associated bloodstream infection (CLABSI); catheter-related infection (CRI). This outcome will be assessed by reviewing electronic medical records and pathology records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of CVAD removal or after the patient has deceased. Initial findings of CVAD Registry will be analysed after twelve months of data collection.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To measure characteristics about patient population with CVADs at RBWH (e.g. CVAD utilisation ratio; dwell time; number of CVADs required to complete treatment; number of CVAD days; number of in-patient days; patient demographics).. This outcome will be assessed by reviewing electronic medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of final CVAD removal or after patient has deceased. Initial findings of CVAD Registry will be analysed after twelve months of data collection.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All patients who have a CVAD inserted at the RBWH on or after the Registry commencement date.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>There are no exclusion criteria for the Registry.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Approximately 900 CVADs are inserted into patients receiving cancer care services (CCS) per annum. To date, there is no data source available that records the number of CVADs inserted across RBWH. No sample size calculation was required, as the entire cohort of patients who have a CVAD inserted at the RBWH during the pilot registry period will be included, Continuous data will be presented with medians, interquartile ranges or means and standard deviations, as appropriate and categorical data as rates and percentages. CVAD failure will be calculated by dividing CVAD failure (infective or mechanical) in patients with a CVAD by the number of CVAD days and multiplying by 1000. Survival analysis will be used to evaluate time-to-event data (e.g. time to catheter failure). Additionally, clinicians and researchers interested in CVADs and CVAD failure will be able to request permission to access de-identified data held on CVAD Registry if they have successfully gained ethical approval. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>True</patientregistry>
    <followup>12</followup>
    <followuptype>Months</followuptype>
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/04/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/03/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>2000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>257</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/03/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <postcode>4029 - Royal Brisbane Hospital</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Nicole Gavin</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Cancer Care Services
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Building 34, Level 2
Butterfield St
Herston
QLD 4029</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Metro North Hospital and Health Service (MNHHS)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>MNHHS Support, Explore, Excel, Deliver (SEED) Innovation Program
Clinical Operations Strategy Implementation (COSI)
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Block 7, Level 13
Butterfield St
Herston
Queensland 4029</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Sarah Northfield</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Cancer Care Services
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Building 34, Level 2
Butterfield St
Herston
QLD 4029</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Treatment today is unthinkable without vascular access devices for the management of patients. CVADs are essential for the administration of intravenous medications and blood sampling. This registry will collect information about the patients requiring CVADs, the type of CVADs being inserted, any complications experienced and the reasons for removal. The registry will provide clinicians and researchers with first-hand information about CVADs for patients receiving treatment and over time will increase our understanding of the complications associated with CVADs. The CVAD Registry will provide clinicians and researchers with an increased understanding of device failure, therefore improving clinical outcomes for patients with CVADs. The CVAD Registry will prospectively collect clinical data on device characteristics, adverse outcomes and risk factors. The Registry will:
1.	Store existing clinical data pertaining to patients with CVADs in one database.
2.	Facilitate quality improvement and research projects about patients with CVADs. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>The pilot CVAD Registry will first be implemented in Cancer Care Services stream of the Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital and will slowly be rolled out to other service lines, after initial feasibility assessments have been completed.</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics Office
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Level 7, Block 7
Butterfield St
Herston
Queensland 4029</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/01/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/QRBW/643</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>17/12/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Nicole Gavin</name>
      <address>Cancer Care Services
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Building 34, Level 2
Butterfield St
Herston 
QLD 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 36465833</phone>
      <fax>N/A</fax>
      <email>nicole.gavin@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Sarah Northfield</name>
      <address>Cancer Care Services
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Building 34, Level 2
Butterfield St
Herston
QLD 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 36462182</phone>
      <fax>N/A</fax>
      <email>sarah.northfield@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Nicole Gavin</name>
      <address>Cancer Care Services
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Building 34, Level 2
Butterfield St
Herston
QLD 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 36465833</phone>
      <fax>N/A</fax>
      <email>nicole.gavin@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Sarah Northfield</name>
      <address>Cancer Care Services
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Building 34, Level 2
Butterfield St
Herston
QLD 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 36462182</phone>
      <fax>N/A</fax>
      <email>sarah.northfield@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>