<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369938">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/01/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/02/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000154404</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparison of C-MAC D-blade video laryngoscope with C-MAC and Macintosh laryngoscope: A randomised, controlled trial in patients with normal airways</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Clinical evaluation of C-MAC D-blade videolaryngoscope. Randomised comparison to C-MAC and direct laryngoscopy in patients with normal airways</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1144-6475</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Videolaryngoscopy during endotracheal intubation in patients with normal airways.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other anaesthesiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>We recruited 180 patients of ASA physical status 1-3 who were scheduled for elective surgery under general anaesthesia requiring endotracheal intubation.
After obtaining written informed consent, patients were assigned, by using a computer-generated randomisation code, to laryngoscopy with either C-MAC D-blade, C-MAC with Macintosh blade or Macintosh laryngoscope. All tracheal intubations were performed by  anesthesiologists who had used all the devices more than 60 times in practice.
Standard monitoring devices were attached before induction of anaesthesia (pulse oximeter, 3-lead ECG and a non-invasive blood pressure cuff). After the pre-oxygenation with 100% oxygen in order to achieve end-tidal oxygen &gt;80%,anesthesia was induced with intravenous sufentanil 0.2-0.3 µg.kg-1 and propofol 2-3 mg.kg-1. Rocuronium 0.6-0.9 mg.kg-1 was administered for neuromuscular blockade after confirmation of successful manual bag-mask ventilation with patients placed in sniffing head position. A size 7.0 mm tracheal tube was used to intubate the trachea in female patients, and a size 7.5 mm tube was used for all male patients.
If more than one intubation attempt was required, the patient received bag-and mask ventilation between attempts and various manoeuvres were employed, including external laryngeal pressure, readjustment of the stylet and use of a bougie. Failure of the procedure was declared if intubation was not achieved within 120s, if more than three intubation attempts were required or if oxygen saturation dropped below 95%.. Intubation attempt was defined as commencing with placement of the device past the level of upper incisors (or upper lip if patient had no teeth) and similarly ending with removal of the device past the level of upper incisors(or upper lip if patient had no teeth). The failed attempt was subsequently managed at the discretion of the attending anaesthesiologist and the chosen technique was recorded.  Correct placement of the tracheal tube was confirmed by capnography and bilateral chest auscultation.
Data were collected by one independent observer. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Endotracheal intubation with Macintosh laryngoscope.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total time to successful intubation. Intubation attempt is defined as commencing with placement of the device past the level of upper incisors (or upper lip if patient had no teeth) and similarly ending with removal of the device past the level of upper incisors (or upper lip if patient had no teeth) using end-tidal carbon dioxide (CO2) detected by capnography as confirmation of successful intubation.. Failure of the procedure is declared if intubation was not achieved within 120s, if more than three intubation attempts were required or if oxygen saturation dropped below 95%. </outcome>
      <timepoint>During intubation - From insertion of the allocated videolaryngoscope into the participants mouth until end-tidal carbon dioxide (CO2) detected by capnography.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total time to optimal laryngeal view. Defined as commencing with placement of the device past the level of upper incisors (or upper lip if patient had no teeth) and ending when optimal laryngeal view obtained to start the intubation. Optimal laryngeal view is assessed using POGO score (percentage of glottic opening).</outcome>
      <timepoint>During intubation - From insertion of the allocated videolaryngoscope into the participants mouth until optimal laryngeal view obtained for starting the intubation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total time to tracheal tube insertion. Defined from the point when optimal laryngeal view is obtained to start the intubation and ending with removal of the device past the level of upper incisors (or upper lip if patient had no teeth) with confirmation of successful intubation using capnography.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During intubation - From point when optimal laryngeal view obtained for starting the intubation until removal of the device past the level of upper incisors (or upper lip if patient had no teeth) with confirmation of successful intubation using capnography.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Difficulty of intubation assessed using 100 mm visual analogue scale (VAS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>After completion of endo tracheal intubation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Difficulty of intubation assessed using intubation difficulty score (IDS), a seven point scoring system and Fremantle score</outcome>
      <timepoint>After completion of endo tracheal intubation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hemodynamic effect assessed using non-invasive blood pressure monitoring and pulse oximetry</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 min before, during and 5 min after commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of laryngeal view assessed using Cormack and Lehane classification and POGO score (percentage of glottic opening)</outcome>
      <timepoint>After completion of endo tracheal intubation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>patients with normal airway set for general anaesthesia with endotracheal intubation needed</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>history of known difficult airway, non-fasting, ASA status IV and above, known airway pathology</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>sealed opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>computerised sequence generation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The primary endpoint of the study is time to successful tracheal intubation. A power analysis in order to determine sample size needed was conducted. Based on standard deviation of time to successful intubation of 17.6 s, analysis indicated a sample size of 56 patients in each group would provide 80% power and 5% level of significance to detect 30% difference between devices using one-way ANOVA. A decision was made to recruit 60 patients per group to allow dropouts. This is a parallel way three group study. SPSS v20 is going to be used to analyse the data: Kruskal-Wallis test for ordinal data, Chi-square test for nominal data and one-way ANOVA for continuous data. When significant differences will be encountered, post hoc pair-wise comparison will be performed. A value of p&lt;0.05 is considered significant.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>16/07/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>19/05/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>180</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>180</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Croatia</country>
      <state>The city of Zagreb</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University Clinical Hospital Sestre milosrdnice</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Vinogradska cesta 29
10000 Zagreb
Croatia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Croatia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University Clinical Hospital Sestre milosrdnice</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Vinogradska cesta 29
10000 Zagreb
Croatia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Croatia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>none</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>none</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The major goal of endotracheal intubation is to secure the airway during reanimation and anaesthesia. To ensure adequate laryngeal view during intubation we use devices called laryngoscopes. Many conditions in medical practice complicate that process and produce conditions known as difficult airway which can have severe consequences if intubation is not possible. Because of the problems that can arise from difficult airway, new technologies were developed and video laryngoscopy has a major role in it. The main objective of this research is to compare intubation characteristics of the C-MAC D-Blade video laryngoscope with C-MAC video laryngoscope and direct laryngoscopy. The hypothesis of our research is that more curved design of D-blade will assure better laryngeal view compared to other devices and consequently intubation would be less difficult and total time to successful intubation would be comparable.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>V. Hostic, B. Maldini, Z. Novotny, I. Hodzovic. Clinical evaluation of C-Mac D-Blade video laryngoscope: randomized comparison with C-Mac Blade and direct laryngoscopy. Br. J. Anaesth. first published online November 17, 2015 doi:10.1093/bja/aev258</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University Clinical Hospital Sestre milosrdnice ethical board</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Vinogradska cesta 29
10000 Zagreb
Croatia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/07/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EP-11810/13-4</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/07/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Croatia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Vedran Hostic</name>
      <address>KBC Sestre milosrdnice, Vinogradska cesta 29,  10000 Zagreb, Croatia</address>
      <phone>+385912554054</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vedran.hostic@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Croatia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Vedran Hostic</name>
      <address>KBC Sestre milosrdnice, Vinogradska cesta 29,  10000 Zagreb</address>
      <phone>+385912554054</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vedran.hostic@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Croatia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Vedran Hostic</name>
      <address>KBC Sestre milosrdnice, Vinogradska cesta 29,  10000 Zagreb</address>
      <phone>+385912554054</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vedran.hostic@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Croatia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>