<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370307">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/03/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/03/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000356460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparing the Old with the New: Randomised controlled trial of three different treatments for mild to moderate impetigo in children</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised controlled trial assessing the efficacy of topical fusidic acid and topical hydrogen peroxide cream for mild impetigo in school children.
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Impetigo</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dermatological conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention will be randomised between 3 possible interventions described below; children with 3 or less impetigo lesions will be enrolled and all lesions will be managed
 
1. Topical fusidic acid ointment 2% twice a day for 5 days  - Fusidic acid 2% ointment (15g tube supplied) with single occasion wound cleaning by a nurse and topical fusidic acid ointment applied to each lesion then covered with occlusive dressing. Ongoing twice daily ointment and dressings twice daily will be done by parent/carer with instructions supplied with no adherence monitoring other than verbal review with nurse on Day 2 and day 7

Intervention 2.  Topical hydrogen peroxide 1% (10g tube) applied twice a day for 5 days. Initial wound cleaning by nurse and H2O2 cream applied to each lesion then covered with an occlusive dressing. The topical antiseptic and sufficient dressings will be supplied to the family along with instructions with no adherence monitoring other than verbal review with nurse on Day 2 and day 7 

Intervention 3: Wound care: the wound will be cleansed, scab softened and removed where possible, then covered with an occlusive dressing. Sufficient dressings will be supplied to the family along with instructions to cleanse and reapply dressing twice a day for 5 days with no adherence monitoring other than verbal review with nurse on Day 2 and day 7. 

Assessment of lesions will be done ongoing at day 2 and day 7 after enrollment  </interventions>
    <comparator>Simple wound care: the wound will be cleansed, scab softened and removed where possible, then covered with an occlusive dressing. Sufficient dressings will be supplied to the family along with instructions to cleanse and reapply dressing twice a day for 5 days. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome is treatment success as evaluated by review of digital images on day 0-7. 
Independent reviewers (clinician including paediatrician x4, dermatologist x2) masked to treatment allocation will compare digital images of skin lesions from days 0 and 7. The order of the images when reviewed will be randomly assigned to ensure further blinding. Outcomes will be scored as success if they have healed or improved and failure if same or worse, or if the reviewer was unable to determine success or failure compared to day 0. Assessment criteria will be adapted from trial and methodology published by Bowen et al. Lancet ID 2014 Dec 13;384(9960):2132-40. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Primary time endpoint is outcome at Day 7 
Digital images of skin lesions will be taken on Days 0 and 7</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcome
Number of treatment failures on both Day 2 and Day 7 
This includes children assessed as needing change management of lesions such as escalation to oral antibiotics, visiting their general practitioner for concerns over the skin infection, or admission to hospital or medical review.

.   

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Treatment failures will be assessed by clinical review at day 2 and day 7 post treatment commencement by school/study nurse. 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical success at Day 7 based on nurse assessment using clinical notes, lesion size, patient report and clinical nursing assessment</outcome>
      <timepoint>Clinical success will be assessed by clinical review (at day 2) and day 7 post treatment commencement by school/study nurse. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcome microbiologic based on detection of skin pathogens at Day 0 and Day 7 and comparison of antibiograms of isolated S.aureus and S.pyogenes from skin swabs</outcome>
      <timepoint>Swabs and cultured Day 0 and Day 7 of a single lesion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Consented children aged 5-13 years presenting with primary non-bullous impetigo  in participating schools who currently are part of sore throat national programme to prevent rheumatic fever and have on site school nurses for this programme.  </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>5</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>13</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Immunocompromised, extensive lesions (&gt;3) requiring oral antibiotics at presentation, known allergy to study drugs, cellulitis, temperature &gt;38.5 C, patients who had used topical or oral antibiotics in the previous 5 days, and patients for whom informed consent is not obtained. T</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>central randomisation by phone and computer</concealment>
    <sequence>simple randomisation using computer generation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>non inferiority</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>To show no difference between treatment regimens and a predicted fusidic acid efficacy of 75% (as per previous published trials)we calculated that 160  participants per group are required: 480 children in total 
This would provide 80% power and a one-sided a=0.05 to show non-inferiority (10% margin) between the groups</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/03/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>10/12/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>480</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Alison Leversha</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Community Child Health and Disability Services
Starship Childrens Health
2 Park Road
Grafton
Auckland 1023
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cure Kids</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 90 907
Victoria Street West
Auckland 1142</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>NZ Wound Care Society</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Contact via Administrator 
74 Fergusson Road, RD9
Fielding
4779
New Zealand</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Skin sepsis is a common problem among children and severe skin infections are the most common reason for hospitalisation in NZ children. Pacific and Maori children are  more likely to develop cellulitis than their NZ European counterparts and hospital admissions for skin sepsis occur at more than twice the rate in NZ compared with other developed countries.  Evidence-based clinical guidelines for the treatment of mild to moderate impetigo recommend the use of fusidic acid cream, currently funded topical antimicrobial in NZ. Recent data, however, have identified a high rate of community resistance to this medication amongst Staphylococcus aureus (SA) ; resistance &gt;30%. This is linked to widespread community use of this topical antibiotic. The evidence base for alternative treatment strategies for mild impetigo is limited and judicious use of topical antibacterials is needed. Alternative therapies must be urgently found to prevent increasing resistance.
The overall aim of the research is to compare two alternative treatments with the current standard of care treatment for mild-to-moderate impetigo among school children.
Aims To undertake a non-inferiority trial comparing topical fusidic acid with (i) topical hydrogen peroxide, and (ii) with simple wound care in a community with both high rates of impetigo and increasing fusidic acid resistance.
The results of this trial will inform evidence-based skin infection guidelines locally, nationally, and internationally including funding of best treatments. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>none</trialwebsite>
    <publication>None</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Ethics Department
Freyberg Building
Reception  Ground Floor
20 Aitken Street
Wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/10/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>16/NTA/113</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>21/03/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alison Leversha</name>
      <address>Community Child Health and Disability Services
Starship Childrens Health
Park Road Grafton
Auckland 1023


</address>
      <phone>+64 9 307 4949</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>aleversha@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alison Leversha</name>
      <address>Community Child Health and Disability Services
Starship Childrens Health
Park Road Grafton
Auckland 1023</address>
      <phone>+64 9 307 4949</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>aleversha@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alison Leversha</name>
      <address>Community Child Health and Disability Services
Starship Childrens Health
Park Road Grafton
Auckland 1023</address>
      <phone>+ 64 9 3074949</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>aleversha@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>alison leversha</name>
      <address>Community Child Health and Disability Services
Starship Childrens Health
Park Road Grafton
Auckland 1023</address>
      <phone>+64 9 3074949</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>aleversha@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>