<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371238">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/06/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/06/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000840381</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Enhancing decision-making about treatment in bipolar II disorder: Evaluation of a treatment decision-aid for patients and their family. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Phase II randomised controlled trial evaluation of treatment decision-aid for patients with bipolar II disorder and their family considering treatment options for relapse prevention. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1186-0652</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Bipolar II disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment decision-aid intervention: This decision-aid website for bipolar II disorder, developed by PI Juraskova, CIs and professional web designers/developers, has been informed by: best available clinical evidence; extensive qualitative interviews with key stakeholders (patients [n=28], family [n=13], and clinicians [n=20]) (Fisher et al., 2017a; 2017b; 2017c); iterative review by an expert advisory group (decision-aid experts, patients with bipolar II disorder, their family and treating clinicians); and International Patient Decision Aid Standards (IPDAS). It provides evidence-based, non-directional information, which has been professionally-copy edited for low health literacy levels. The decision-aid explains main available medication and psychological treatment options for relapse prevention in bipolar II disorder, based on available guidelines; with specific sections for patients family. Lay information is presented using text and graphics on the rationale for, efficacy and known benefits/costs of each treatment option. Interactive values clarification exercises are included to assist patients/family to consider their preferences and deliberate on the benefits/costs of the different treatment options. The decision-aid website can be accessed by the patient participant and/or family member at any frequency and duration in the period following diagnosis and leading up to follow-up consultation/s with their managing psychiatrist, GP and/or clinical psychologist. The website will be used for informed treatment decisions insofar as it is designed to increase patients' knowledge about their main available treatment options and guide them through a deliberate process of weighing up the "pros" and the "cons" of options in line with their personal values and preferences (via the interactive, values, clarification exercises). Patients (and their families) will have the option to save/print their values clarification responses and take these along to follow-up consultations with clinicians to serve as a "conversation starter". Adherence to the intervention will be tracked via Analytics software (e.g., page views, time spent on page, downloads etc.). Moreover adherence/fidelty will be maintained via "essential reading sections"; these are information sections of the website that will need to be consulted before the participant can proceed to the values clarification exercises and completion of the questionnaires.

Fisher A et al. (2017a). A qualitative exploration of patient and family views and experiences of treatment decision-making in bipolar II disorder. Journal of Mental Health (Epub:13 January 2017). doi: http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/09638237.2016.1276533

Fisher et al. (2017b). A qualitative exploration of clinician views and experiences of treatment decision-making in bipolar II disorder. Community Mental Health Journal (Epub: 19 January 2017). doi: 10.1007/s10597-016-0077-4 

Fisher A et al., (2017c) Identifying and addressing barriers to treatment decision-making in bipolar II disorder: Clinicians perspective. Australian Psychologist (Epub: 14 February 2017) doi:10.1111/ap.12264.



</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care/attention control will comprise: any information materials (e.g., factsheets) that patients are already routinely provided with, or advised to consult during their appointment at the Black Dog Institute (recruitment site); and the existing Black Dog Institute webpages on treatments for bipolar disorder: (www.blackdoginstitute.org.au/public/bipolardisorder/treatments/). </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Decisional conflict (i.e., feeling certain/confident about decided-on course of action, feeling well informed, well supported and clear about values). 

This composite primary outcome measure will be assessed via the validated self-report questionnaire: The Decisional Conflict Scale (O'Connor, 1995). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately post-treatment decision (T1)
3 months' post-treatment decision follow-up (T2)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Knowledge about treatment options and outcomes 

Composite secondary outcome measure assessed via a questionnaire designed specifically for this study. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately post-treatment decision (T1)
3 months' post-treatment decision follow-up (T2)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Concordance between preferred/actual levels of decision-making involvement

This secondary outcome will be assessed via the agreement between patient ratings of their preferred and  actual levels of decision-making involvement on the validated self-report questionnaire: The Control Preferences Scale (Degner, 1997). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately post-treatment decision (T1)
3 months' post-treatment decision follow-up (T2)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Informed, values-based treatment choices.

This secondary outcome measure will be assessed via an adapted version of Marteau et al's (2001) self-report Measure of Informed Choice, designed specifically for this study. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately post-treatment decision (T1)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Preparation for decision-making

This secondary outcome measure will be assessed via the validated self-report questionnaire: The Preparation for Decision-making Scale (Bennett et al., 2010).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately post-treatment decision (T1)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Decisional regret 

This secondary outcome measure will be assessed via the validated self-reported questionnaire: The Decision Regret Scale (Brehaut et al., 2003).</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months' post-treatment decision follow-up (T2)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Uptake of effective treatment options

This secondary outcome measure will be assessed via self-report on a questionnaire specifically designed for this study. Participants who indicate uptake of one or more of the medication and psychological treatment options indicated in the decision-aid will be said to have taken up effective treatment options.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately post-treatment decision (T1)
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Understanding of treatment options and outcomes

This secondary outcome measure will be assessed via a questionnaire designed specifically for this study. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately post-treatment decision (T1)
3 months' follow-up (T2)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptom Severity (used as an index of safety).

This secondary outcome will be assessed via a validated self-report questionnaire: The Internal States Scale (Bauer et al., 1991).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately post-treatment decision (T1)
3 months' follow-up (T2).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Medication Adherence (used as an index of safety).

This secondary outcome will be assessed via validated self-report questionnaire: The Morisky Medication Adherence Scale (MMAS-8).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately post-treatment decision (T1)
3 months' follow-up (T2).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>i)   Confirmed clinical diagnosis of bipolar II disorder;
ii)  Out of acute episode of depression and/or hypomania (i.e., subsyndromal or euthymic);
iii) Actively considering treatment options for relapse prevention in bipolar II disorder with a clinician (e.g., GP, psychiatrist or clinical psychologist).
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>i)  Lacks English proficiency to read the decision-aid and/or complete questionnaires;
ii) Lacks capacity to provide informed consent to research;
iii) Comorbid substance abuse disorder;
iv) Comorbid neurological or major psychiatric condition.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation</concealment>
    <sequence> Computer generated (https://www.randomizer.org/)</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Pre-/post-design with 1:1 randomisation of individual patients.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Planned statistical analyses will follow the intention-to-treat principle. Descriptive statistics will assess sample characteristics, decision-aid perceptions and any potential decision-aid differences on symptom severity and medication adherence at T1/T2 (safety). Linear and logistic regressions will determine DA effects at T1/T2 on continuous and binary outcomes, respectively. Adjusted models will control for baseline (T0) variables identified a-priori as potential covariates (e.g., medical training, time-since-diagnosis). </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/09/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/12/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Black Dog Institute - Randwick</hospital>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>A/Prof Ilona Juraskova</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Psychology, 
Brennan MacCallum Building (A18), 
University of Sydney, 
Camperdown, NSW, 2006. </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Sydney </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>School of Psychology
Brennan MacCallum Building (A18)
University of Sydney, 
Camperdown, NSW, 2006.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Rotary Health </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Address:
2nd Floor, 43 Hunter Street,
Parramatta NSW 2150

Postal Address:
PO Box 3455,
Parramatta NSW 2124</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Sydney</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Psychology
Brennan MacCallum Building (A18)
University of Sydney, 
Camperdown, NSW, 2006</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other Collaborative groups</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Black Dog Institute</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Hospital Road, 
Randwick, NSW, 2052.</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A diagnosis of bipolar II disorder is commonly accompanied by a need to make complex treatment decisions about medications and adjunctive psychological therapies, often for lifetime prophylactic (preventative) use. However, people with bipolar II disorder are often reluctant to commence and adhere to effective medications long-term, mostly due to lack of knowledge, less-than-desired involvement and preference for treatments other than those prescribed, which can worsen the course of their illness. Research shows that many people with bipolar II disorder, especially those with a recent diagnosis, prefer a more active role in their treatment decisions than they currently have, and may have greater unmet decision-making needs than those with a longer-standing diagnosis. Yet, there is currently no resource that might facilitate this involvement. This project aims to build on our comprehensive research program targeting bipolar II disorder treatment decision-making by evaluating the worlds first, evidence-based online decision-support resource, a decision-aid website, for patients with bipolar II disorder and their family who are deciding on treatment options for relapse prevention. In this Phase II randomised control trial, a consecutive patient sample (n=60) aged 18+ and with a confirmed clinical diagnosis of bipolar II disorder will be recruited through the Black Dog Institute and randomised (1:1) to receive either usual care with or without the decision-aid. At baseline, immediately post-treatment decision and at 3 months' follow-up, we will assess, via validated and purpose-designed questionnaires, the decision-aid's potential efficacy at improving key aspects of decision-making quality. We expect that the DA will: i) reduce patients' uncertainty and regret in decision-making, ii) empower them to feel more informed and supported in decision-making, iii) help clarify their values regarding for treatment for bipolar II disorder, iv) improve their knowledge about treatment options/outcomes, v) help them to be involved in treatment decision-making to the extent desired, and vi) improve their uptake of effective medication and psychological treatments.   </summary>
    <trialwebsite>N/A</trialwebsite>
    <publication>N/A</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>N/A</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The University of Sydney, 
NSW, 2006 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/09/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016/763</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/09/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Black Dog Institute Research Advisory Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Hospital Road, 
Randwick, NSW, 2031</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/08/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016011 Fisher</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/08/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Ilona Juraskova</name>
      <address>School of Psychology, 
Brennan MacCallum Building (A18), 
University of Sydney, 
Camperdown, NSW, 2006.</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 6811</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9036 5292</fax>
      <email>ilona.juraskova@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Alana Fisher</name>
      <address>School of Psychology, 
Brennan MacCallum Building (A18), 
University of Sydney, NSW, 2006.</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9036 9258</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9036 5292</fax>
      <email>a.fisher@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Ilona Juraskova</name>
      <address>School of Psychology, 
Brennan MacCallum Building (A18), 
University of Sydney, NSW, 2006.</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 6811</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9036 5292</fax>
      <email>ilona.juraskova@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Alana Fisher</name>
      <address>School of Psychology, 
Brennan MacCallum Building (A18), 
University of Sydney, NSW, 2006.</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9036 9258</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9036 5292</fax>
      <email>a.fisher@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>