<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363536">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/01/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/02/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000221752</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Establishing an open access Biobank of human Fallopian tubes</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Open Access Biobank of Human Fallopian Tubes: A prospective biomedical study of archived tissue samples to elucidate mechanisms of abnormal implantation including a molecular make-up of early maternal-embryonic interface, trophoblast proliferation and its paracrine/autocrine regulation in tubal ectopic pregnancy.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1138-7484</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Infertility
 </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Tubal ectopic pregnancy</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Pathogenesis of abnormal implantation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Carcinogenesis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fetal medicine and complications of pregnancy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fertility including in vitro fertilisation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ovarian and primary peritoneal</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The project is a prospective biomedical study of archived specimens of Fallopian tube tissue and peripheral venous blood obtained from consented women age group from 21 to 50 years old who had salpingectomy for tubal ectopic pregnancy. A comparison group will include intact Fallopian tubes and peripheral blood samples from consented women of the same age group who underwent hysterectomy for non-malignant disease or tubal ligation for permanent contraception. All biological samples will be coupled to a detailed, anonymised medical history of each participant. 

This project aims to address the lack of human samples for research in the areas of embryonic implantation and implantation failure, pathogenesis of ectopic pregnancy and understanding of malignant tissue invasion using trophoblast as a model system by establishing a collection of Fallopian tubes samples from patients undergoing surgical treatment of ectopic tubal pregnancy. This library of tissue and matched blood samples can then be interrogated using a variety of molecular techniques to improve understanding of regulation mechanisms of tissue receptivity to trophoblast invasion.    
Protein and RNA analysis will be carried out on microdissected epithelial cells collected from the stored tubal specimens using laser capture microscopy (LCM). 
The expression of the molecules of interest will be measured at the protein level by immunohistochemistry, Western blot and confocal microscopy. The gene expression of candidate molecules will be measured by RNA microarray and quantitative RT-PCR. Collected blood samples will be centrifuged 20 minutes following collection and the serum will be stored in aliquots (100 micro litres) at -20 degree Celsius till processed for ELISA to measure the concentrations of the molecules of interest.
</interventions>
    <comparator>The study group will include women diagnosed with tubal ectopic pregnancy and undergoing surgical treatment. 
The comparison group will include women with healthy Fallopian tubes obtained at tubal ligation in the absence of a pregnancy or women with healthy Fallopian tubes undergoing a hysterectomy for other non-malignant diseases.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>to create a bank of appropriately stored human Fallopian tube (FT) tissue from women with an unruptured ectopic pregnancy and from a healthy comparison group
</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>to reduce reliance on animal models which do not accurately mimic the human cellular phenotype and genotype, are  costly and difficult to manage due to ethical dilemmas involved in animal research
</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>a.   to study the molecular basis of human embryonic implantation
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point will be  determined by utilization of the Biobank and tissue availability.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>b.   to elucidate the pathogenesis of infertility and implantation failure</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point will be  determined by utilization of the Biobank and tissue availability.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>c.   to investigate trophoblast invasion and a model for carcinogenesis</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point will be  determined by utilization of the Biobank and tissue availability.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>d.   to develop novel methods for early diagnosis and non-invasive treatment of ectopic pregnancy</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point will be  determined by utilization of the Biobank and tissue availability.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>e.   to investigate abnormal placentation leading to placental disorders(pre-eclampsia, placenta accrete later in a pregnancy) 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point will be  determined by utilization of the Biobank and tissue availability.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria for study group:
Sex: female 
Age range: 21- 50 
Disease status:  unruptured ectopic pregnancy with stable vital signs
Concomitant disease status: 
Laboratory parameters: positive bHCG
Others:  ultrasound        
Willingness to give written or oral informed consent and willingness to participate to and comply with the study.
Ability to understand spoken and written English, able to consent for research.
 
The comparison group will include women having hysterectomy for benign disease
or a sterilization procedure
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>21</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria for participants in study group:

Patients with a significant degree of pain due to ectopic pregnancy
Patients with unstable vital signs
Patients who expressed desire not to participate in research
Patients who unable to understand the requirements of the study
 
Exclusion criteria for participants in comparison group:

Patients who are not willing to participate in research 
Patients who are not able to give written informed consent. 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>26/02/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Hospital for Women - Randwick</hospital>
    <hospital>Wollongong Hospital - Wollongong</hospital>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
    <postcode>2500 - Wollongong</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>NHMRC</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
Level 1; 16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601

Postal address: GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Royal Hospital for Women Foundation</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>RHW Foundation
Locked Bag 2000
Randwick NSW 2031</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>MAWA trust</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The MAWA Trust 
PO Box 4203
Weston Creek 
ACT 2611</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Ectopic pregnancy is an unpredictable, non-viable and potentially life-threatening condition caused by ectopic (abnormal) implantation of an early embryo into the Fallopian tube instead of the uterus (womb). Ectopic pregnancy occurs in about 2% of pregnancies in Australia.
Recent research by our group and others has suggested possible reasons for the embryo failing to implant in the correct place in ectopic pregnancy. To allow us to study this further, we are setting up a bank of stored Fallopian tube tissue collected from women who are having the tube removed as treatment for an ectopic pregnancy. To study possible causes of miscarriage and infertility we will compare affected Fallopian tubes to healthy Fallopian tubes obtained from women who are having operation for non-malignant disease or tubal ligation. A Fallopian tube removed during surgery is not usually kept once it has been examined for diagnosis.
We have set up a process by which we can collect and appropriately store the tissue after it is examined by the pathologist. 

The Biobank of human Fallopian tubes, a repository of disease-specific human samples will promote cutting edge biomedical research in the area of fertility, early embryogenesis and implantation, human reproduction, and carcinogenesis by decreasing reliance on animal models and allowing open access to human samples for scientists. The open access Biobank of human Fallopian tubes will facilitate data dissemination and will help to generate more studies refining methodologies in human research.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Presentations:
November 2012  Presentation at 10th Australasian Biobanking Network Association (ABNA) meeting, Hobart, Tasmania
"Exploring an opportunity of establishing a biobank in Australia" 
September 2012    Poster presentation at the Annual Scientific Meeting 2012, RANZCOG, Canberra  "Capital Gains in Women Health"

Publications:
November 2012  Abstract of presentation "Exploring an opportunity of establishing a Biobank in Australia" in a Conference Handbook at 10th Australasian Biobanking Network Association (ABNA) meeting, Hobart, Tasmania

September 2012       Abstract of poster presentation in a "Capital Gains in Women Health"  Conference Handbook at the Annual Scientific Meeting 2012, RANZCOG.

Refaat B, Ledger WL. The expression of activins, their type II receptors and follistatin in human Fallopian tube during the menstrual cycle and in pseudo-pregnancy. Human Reproduction, Vol 26, No 12 pp 3346-3354,2011

Al-Azemi M, Refaat B, Alpin J, Ledger W. The expression of MUCI in human Fallopian tube during the menstrual cycle and in ectopic pregnancy. Human Reproduction 2009;24:2582-2587

Al-Azemi M, Refaat B, Amer S, Ola B, Chapman N, Ledger W. The expression of inducible nitric oxide synthase in human Fallopian tube during the menstrual cycle and in ectopic pregnancy. Fertility and Sterility 2010;94:833-840

Bahathiq AO, Stewart RL, Wells M, Moore HD, Pacey AA, Ledger WL. Production of activins by the human endosalpinx. J Clin Endocriol Metab 2002;87:5283-5289

Bahathiq AO, Stewart RL, Baxter L, Wells M, Moore HD, Ledger WL. Tissue immunoexpression and messenger ribonucleic acid localization of inhibin/activin subunit in human epididymis. Fertility and Sterility 2005;83:78-85 

Refaat BA, Bahathiq AO, Sockanathan S, Stewart RL, Wells M, Ledger WL. Production and localization of activins and activin type IIA and IIB receptors by the human endosalpinx. Reproduction 2004;128:249-255

Refaat B, Amer S, Ola B, Chapman N, Ledger W. The expression of activin-beta A and betaB-subunits, follistatin and active type II receptors in Fallopian tubes bearing an ectopic pregnancy. J Clin Endocrinol Metab 2008;93:293-299.

Refaat B, Al-Azemi M, Geary I, Eley A, Ledger W. Role of activins and inducible nitric oxide in the pathogenesis of ectopic pregnancy in patients with or without Chlamidia trachomatis infection. Clin Vaccine Immunol 2009;16:1493-1503
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>SESIAHS LHD HREC- Northern Sector </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Prince of Wales Hospital
G71, East Wing, Edmund Blacket Building
Cnr High &amp; Avoca Streets
Randwick NSW 2031</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/09/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>12/055 (HREC/12/POWH/105)</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/03/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>William L. Ledger</name>
      <address>Level 1, Royal Hospital for Women, Barker Street (Locked Bag 2000), RANDWICK  NSW  2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9382 6515 </phone>
      <fax> +61 2 9382 6444 </fax>
      <email>w.ledger@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tatiana Zandanova</name>
      <address>Level 1, Royal Hospital for Women, Barker Street (Locked Bag 2000), RANDWICK  NSW  2031</address>
      <phone>+61 422447270</phone>
      <fax> +61 2 9382 6444 </fax>
      <email>tatianazandanova@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tatiana Zandanova</name>
      <address>Level 1, Royal Hospital for Women, Barker Street (Locked Bag 2000), RANDWICK  NSW  2031</address>
      <phone>+61 422447270</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9382 6444 </fax>
      <email>tatianazandanova@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tatiana Zandanova</name>
      <address>27 Linthorpe Street, Newtown, NSW 2042</address>
      <phone>+61 422447270</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9382 6444</fax>
      <email>tatianazandanova@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>