<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366403">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/05/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/06/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000606684</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparison between the outcomes of adherent placenta  encountered during emergencies and adherent placenta managed electively</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparison between the outcomes of placenta accreta encountered during emergencies and placenta accreta managed electively</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Placenta accreta</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fetal medicine and complications of pregnancy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>20 women with placenta accreta presenting to the labour ward in an emergency (Group1) will be compared to 20 women having elective Cesarean section (CS) for placenta accreta (Group2).
Both groups will be compared regarding their base line criteria, their sonographic and Doppler findings, the management, operation time, whether the CS was upper segment or lower segment and if removal of the placenta was attempted.
Each participant is expected to be observed 4 times during the study and the overall duration of observation is expected to be one week. 
All women will be subjected to full history taking, abdominal examination, ultrasound examination to confirm fetal number, viability, gestational age, exclusion of congenital anomalies and assessment of the amniotic fluid index and localization of the placenta
All women with Placenta previa and women with previous CS who have anterior placentas covering the CS scar are at increased risk of having placenta accreta. 
Placenta accreta will be suspected using a grey scale ultrasound when there is loss of the retroplacental sonolucent zone, irregular retroplacental sonolucent zone, thinning or disruption of the hyperechoic serosabladder interface, presence of focal exophytic masses invading the urinary bladder or the presence of abnormal placental lacunae.
In the presence of any of the previous criteria colour Doppler will be applied and the following criteria will support the diagnosis of placenta accreta: diffuse or focal lacunar flow, vascular lakes with turbulent flow (peak systolic velocity over 15 cm/s), hypervascularity of serosabladder interface, or markedly dilated vessels over peripheral subplacental zone.
3D ultrasound and MRI facilities are not available in the labour ward, but women presenting electively can have 3D ultrasound, MRI scan or both if necessary for further confirmation of placenta accreta. placenta accreta will be confirmed clinically and histopathologically.
Women presenting to the labour ward will have a CS if they have regular uterine contractions, excessive bleeding indicating delivery or if their gestational age is greater than or equal to 38 weeks.
All women will have CS and placenta accreta will be confirmed clinically and histopathologically.

</interventions>
    <comparator>20 women with placenta accreta presenting to the labour ward in an emergency (Group1) will be compared to 20 women having elective CS for placenta accreta (Group2)</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Eestimated blood loss during surgery.
 The amount of blood in the suction container (which represents the amount of blood sucked from the surgical field) will be added to that staining the surgical towels and the sum will represent the estimated blood loss during surgery. </outcome>
      <timepoint>5 minutes after the Cesarean section  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Need for hysterectomy</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 minutes after surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Need for blood transfusion</outcome>
      <timepoint> 1 hour after surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>surgical complications like injury to the bowel, bladder or ureters</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 minutes after completion of surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>the need for admission to the intensive care unit</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours after surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postoperative hospital stay</outcome>
      <timepoint>one week after the surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-Suspected placenta accreta (In the labour ward placenta accrete will be suspected by the grey scale ultrasound and colour Doppler. In women presenting electively, 3D ultrasound or MRI may be used for further confirmation)
-consent to participate in the study </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-Intra uterine fetal death.
-Preeclampsia, Diabetes Mellitus or other medical disorders.
- Boby mass index (BMI)&gt;35
-Known coagulation defects
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods> This is a pilot study with no available data on management of suspected placenta accreta during emergencies. We have planned to enrol 40 patients in the study; at the end of the study we may recommend doing further studies with a larger sample size.  


Quantitative data will be statistically represented in terms of mean +/- standard deviation (+/- SD) while categorical data will be represented as frequency and percentage. Comparison of quantitative data will be done using Mann Whitney U test for independent samples while categorical data will be compared using Chi squared test or Fisher exact test when appropriate. A probability value (p value) less than 0.05 will be considered significant. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/06/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>12/06/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/11/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <state>Cairo </state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Cairo University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Kasr Al-Ainy,
1 Al-Saray Street,
Al-Manial, Cairo
Postal Code 11559
EGYPT 
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Egypt</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cairo University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Kasr Al-Ainy,
1 Al-Saray Street,
Al-Manial, Cairo
Postal Code 11559
EGYPT 
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Egypt</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Cairo University hospitals </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Cairo university hospitals
Kasr Al-Ainy,
1 Al-Saray Street,
Al-Manial, Cairo
Postal Code 11559
EGYPT 
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Egypt</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>20 women with adherent placenta presenting during an emergency will be compared to 20 women with adherent placenta presenting electively.
Both groups will be compared regarding their base line criteria, their sonographic and Doppler findings, the operation time, whether the CS was upper segment or lower segment and if removal of the placenta was attempted</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Research ethics committee, Department of Gynecology and Obstetrics </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Department of Gynecology and Obstetrics
Kasr Al-Ainy,
1 Al-Saray Street,
Al-Manial, Cairo
Postal Code 11559
EGYPT 
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/05/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Egypt</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>AbdelGany Hassan</name>
      <address>Work address:
Department of Gynecology and Obstetrics,
Cairo University hospitals
Kasr Al-Ainy,
1 Al-Saray Street,
Al-Manial, Cairo
Postal Code 11559
EGYPT 

 </address>
      <phone>+20 010 17801604</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>abdelgany2@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>AbdelGany Hassan</name>
      <address>Work address:
Department of Gynecology and Obstetrics,
Cairo University hospitals
Kasr Al-Ainy,
1 Al-Saray Street,
Al-Manial, Cairo
Postal Code 11559
EGYPT 
</address>
      <phone>+20 010 17801604</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>abdelgany2@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>AbdelGany Hassan</name>
      <address>Work address:
Department of Gynecology and Obstetrics,
Cairo University hospitals
Kasr Al-Ainy,
1 Al-Saray Street,
Al-Manial, Cairo
Postal Code 11559
EGYPT 
</address>
      <phone>+20 010 17801604</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>abdelgany2@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>AbdelGany Hassan</name>
      <address>Work address:
Department of Gynecology and Obstetrics,
Cairo University hospitals
Kasr Al-Ainy,
1 Al-Saray Street,
Al-Manial, Cairo
Postal Code 11559
EGYPT 
</address>
      <phone>+20 010 17801604</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>abdelgany2@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>