<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366410">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/05/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/06/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000623695</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>WorkplaceAid - A trial on improving mental health and physical first aid skills in the workplace</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effects of eLearning or blended (eLearning plus face-to-face training) mental health first aid training on public servants' knowledge, attitudes, confidence in providing support and actual supportive behaviours towards others in the workplace, as well as personal help-seeking and their own mental health. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1157-3138 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>WorkplaceAid</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>mental health first aid knowledge</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>stigmatizing attitudes toward people with mental health problems</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>confidence in supporting someone who has a mental health problem</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>actual supportive behaviours toward someone who has a mental health problem</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>personal help-seeking for a mental health problem</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>participants' own mental health</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>first aid knowledge</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>actual supportive behaviours toward someone who has a physical health problem</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>confidence in supporting someone who has a physical health problem</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Group 1: a 6-hour eLearning Mental Health First Aid course via online portal, which teaches an action plan for responding to disorders such as depression, anxiety, psychosis and substance misuse. The crises covered include suicidal thoughts and behaviours, non-suicidal self-injury, panic attacks, traumatic events, severe psychotic states, severe effects from alcohol misuse, severe effects from drug misuse, and aggressive behaviours. It has been tailored to incorporate information on policies, resources and help-seeking pathways of specific relevance to the Victorian public service. Participants will receive weekly emails for 6 weeks to pace them through the material. Weekly reports will be extracted to monitor course progress and flag completers. 

Group 2: as per 6-hour eLearning course above plus a 3.5 hour face-to-face session, which reviews the contents of the online course through quizzes, discussion, case studies and includes a manual. It also uses role plays to give participants more concrete experience in applying the MHFA Action Plan in different situations and settings. Group training will be delivered between week 7 to 10 (minimum of 12 participants per group to a maximum of 24).</interventions>
    <comparator>Group 3: a 4-hour eLearning Apply First Aid course via online portal, which teaches the fundamental principles, knowledge and skills to provide emergency care for injuries and illnesses in the home or the workplace. Participants will receive weekly emails for 6 weeks to pace them through the material. Weekly reports will be extracted to monitor course progress and flag completers. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>16-item true/false quiz based on the content of the Mental Health First Aid Manual (Kitchener et al., 2013).
Frequencies of correct responses converted to percentages. </outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 2-months post training, one year post-training, two-years post training</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported supportive behaviours if someone at work develops a mental health problem. "Describe all the things you did to help." (open-ended). Scoring based on MHFA Action Plan (Yap &amp; Jorm, 2012). </outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, one-year post training, two-years post training</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stigmatizing attitudes of participants in relation to vignettes depicting i) depression and ii) PTSD, measured by Social Distance Scale (Link et al., 1999). 

"Would you be happy: 
a) To move next door to John/Paula? 
b) To spend an evening socializing with John/Paula? 
c) To make friends with John/Paula? 
d) To work closely with John/Paula on a project at work? 
e) To have John/Paula marry into your family?" 

Response frame: 1 = Yes definitely (low social distance) to 4 = Definitely not (high social distance).</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, two-months post training, one-year post training, two-years post training</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Recognition of mental health problems in vignettes. "What, if anything do you think is wrong with John/Paula?" (open-ended response). Scoring based on DSM-5 classification for Major Depressive Disorder and PTSD. </outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, two-months post training, one-year post training, two-years post training</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Supportive behaviours to assist characters in vignettes depicting depression and PTSD. 
"If John/Paula was a co-worker, I would help him/her." 7-point scale ranging from 1 = Strongly Disagree to 7 = Strongly Agree. 

"Describe all the things you would do to help John/Paula." (open-ended response) Scoring based on MHFA Action Plan (Yap &amp; Jorm, 2012). </outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, two-months post training, one-year post training, two-years post training</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Confidence in providing help to someone at work with depression or PTSD. 
"How confident do you feel in helping someone at work with a problem like John/Paula?" 5-point scale ranging from 1 = Not at all to 5 = Extremely. </outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, two-months post training, one-year post training- two-years post training</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>16-item scale on mental health literacy about depression with suicidal thoughts and PTSD. Scoring based on 2011 National Survey of Mental Health Literacy and Stigma (Reavley &amp; Jorm, 2011).  5-point scale: 1 = Helpful, 2 = Neither, 3 = Harmful, 4 = Depends, 5 = Don't know.</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, two-month post training, one-year post training, two-year post training</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants' personal stigma in relation to characters depicted in depression and PTSD vignettes, measured by Personal Stigma Scale, 9 items. Scored using 5-point scale ranging from 1 = Strongly Agree to 5 = Strongly Disagree. (Griffiths et al., 2004). </outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, two-months post training, one-year post training, two-years post training</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants' self-reported supportive behaviours over the last 12 months towards people outside of their work with a mental health problem. "Describe all the things you did to help." (open-ended response)</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, one-year post training, two-years post training</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Recognition of a mental health problem in someone outside of work, over the last 12 months. "What do you think the problem was?" (open-ended response)</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, one-year post training, two-years post training</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Help seeking of participants for own mental health problem. If think they had a problem, "What do you think the problem was? Over the last 12 months, have you done anything to deal with this mental health problem? Describe all the things you did." (open-ended responses)</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, one-year post training, two-years post training</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mental health of participant measured by K6 12-month version (Kessler et al., 2003). It contains 6 items with responses ranging from 1 = All of the time to 5 = None of the time. The resulting score range is between 6 to 30, with a cut-off point of equal to or more than 19 indicating a high level of psychological distress in the anxiety and depression spectrum. </outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, one-year post training, two-years post training</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Recognition of a physical health problem which requires first aid using a vignette depicting a seizure. "What do you think is wrong with Rob?" (open-ended response)</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, two-months post training, one-year post training, two-years post training</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Supportive behaviours toward a character in a vignette depicting a seizure. 

"If Rob was a co-worker, I would help him." 
Scoring based on a 7-point scale ranging from 1 = Strongly Disagree to 7 = Strongly Agree. 

"Describe all the things you would do to help Rob." (open-ended response)</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, two-months post training, one-year post training, two-years post training</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Confidence in providing support to someone at work who has a seizure. "How confident do you feel in helping someone at work with a problem like Rob's?" Scoring based on 5-point scale ranging from 1 = Not at all to 5 = Extremely. </outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, two-months post training, one-year post training, two-years post training</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>10-item first aid quiz based on Red Cross eLearning Apply First Aid course. Response frame: Agree, Disagree, Don't know. 

Frequencies of correct responses converted to percentages. </outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, two-months post training, one-year post training, two-years post training</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Course satisfaction: 

1. How much of the training did you complete? (1 = none of it, 2 = part of it, 3 = most of it, 4 = all of it). 

2. How easy was the material to understand? (1 = very easy, 2 = easy, 3 = neither easy nor difficult, 4 = difficult, 5 = very difficult). 

3.  How much did you learn from the course? (1 = a great deal, 2 = a fair bit, 3 = not very much, 4 = almost nothing). 

4. How useful was the course? (1 = very useful, 2 = useful, 3 = not very useful, 4 = not at all useful). 

5. Do you think you will use the training material in the future? (1 = yes, 2 = no, 3 = not sure). 

6.  Would you recommend the course to others? (1 = yes definitely, 2 = probably, 3 = probably not, 4 = definitely not). 

7 What did you like about the training materials?

8. What did you dislike about the training materials?
</outcome>
      <timepoint>at two-month post training only</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Employees from the Victorian Public Service.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any Victorian Public Servant who has undertaken the Mental Health First Aid course or the Apply First Aid course in the previous three years. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subjects will enrol online via the WorkplaceAid trial website. Allocation will be concealed as randomization will occur via computer, at the end of baseline survey completion. </concealment>
    <sequence>Randomization will be carried out by a random integer generator programmed on the trial website to give values of 1 = eLearning MHFA; 2 = Blended eLearning MHFA and 3 = eLearning Apply First Aid (see http://php.net/manual/en/function.rand.php).</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The data for this study will be analysed using mixed-effects models for continuous and binary outcome variables, with group-by-measurement-occasion interactions. This method of analysis is well suited to the data that will be collected for this study as it takes into account the hierarchical structure of the data in the analysis of differences between the groups, i.e. the correlation of measurement occasions within participants. 

For the purpose of sample size calculation, the main hypothesis of interest is that MHFA training delivered in blended mode will be superior to MHFA training delivered in online mode in achieving the outcomes of interest. This hypothesis is of main interest because the sample size required to detect differences between these two modes of training will be larger than that required to detect differences between these modes and first aid training. Consequently, we chose a small effect size to evaluate the difference between the two modes of MHFA training. We believe that an effect size smaller than this may not be practically meaningful in terms of participant outcomes. According to Stata Release12, for a repeated measures design, with 1 pre-training measure and 3 post-training measures, using the change method of sample size calculation and assuming a conservative 0.70 correlation between pre-post measurements (see Means et al., 2010), to detect an effect size of Cohens d=0.20 (or h=0.20), with a power=0.80 and an alpha=0.05, 165 participants will be required per group. Increasing the sample size by 20% to account for attrition, the total sample size required is 594 (198 participants per group).
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>27/06/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>600</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3000 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3051 - North Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3032 - Ascot Vale</postcode>
    <postcode>3053 - Carlton</postcode>
    <postcode>3058 - Coburg</postcode>
    <postcode>3068 - Clifton Hill</postcode>
    <postcode>3066 - Collingwood</postcode>
    <postcode>3175 - Dandenong</postcode>
    <postcode>3108 - Doncaster</postcode>
    <postcode>3040 - Essendon</postcode>
    <postcode>3002 - East Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3199 - Frankston</postcode>
    <postcode>3065 - Fitzroy</postcode>
    <postcode>3220 - Geelong</postcode>
    <postcode>3011 - Footscray</postcode>
    <postcode>3046 - Glenroy</postcode>
    <postcode>3029 - Hoppers Crossing</postcode>
    <postcode>3122 - Hawthorn</postcode>
    <postcode>3081 - Heidelberg Heights</postcode>
    <postcode>3036 - Keilor</postcode>
    <postcode>3079 - Ivanhoe</postcode>
    <postcode>3031 - Kensington</postcode>
    <postcode>3028 - Laverton</postcode>
    <postcode>3032 - Maribyrnong</postcode>
    <postcode>3337 - Melton</postcode>
    <postcode>3194 - Mentone</postcode>
    <postcode>3039 - Moonee Ponds</postcode>
    <postcode>3015 - Newport</postcode>
    <postcode>3174 - Noble Park</postcode>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
    <postcode>3044 - Pascoe Vale</postcode>
    <postcode>3070 - Northcote</postcode>
    <postcode>3131 - Nunawading</postcode>
    <postcode>3181 - Prahran</postcode>
    <postcode>3072 - Preston</postcode>
    <postcode>3207 - Port Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3121 - Richmond</postcode>
    <postcode>3101 - Kew</postcode>
    <postcode>3134 - Ringwood</postcode>
    <postcode>3141 - South Yarra</postcode>
    <postcode>3011 - Seddon</postcode>
    <postcode>3021 - St Albans</postcode>
    <postcode>3171 - Springvale</postcode>
    <postcode>3205 - South Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3182 - St Kilda</postcode>
    <postcode>3020 - Sunshine</postcode>
    <postcode>3016 - Williamstown</postcode>
    <postcode>3125 - Burwood</postcode>
    <postcode>3124 - Camberwell</postcode>
    <postcode>3056 - Brunswick</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Melbourne School of Population and Global Health
Centre for Mental Health 
Level 4, 207 Bouverie Street 
CARLTON  VIC   3010 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
Marcus Clarke Street 
CANBERRA  ACT   2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Mental Health First Aid (MHFA) Australia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Level 6, 369 Royal Parade 
PARKVILLE  VIC   3052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Australian Red Cross</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>23-47 Villiers Street 
NORTH MELBOURNE  VIC   3051</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to evaluate whether Mental Health First Aid (MHFA) training, delivered in eLearning or Blended learning (eLearning plus face-to-face) modes, leads to improvements in mental health first aid knowledge, stigmatizing attitudes, confidence in supporting a person in the social network with a mental health problem, and self-reported supportive behaviours if someone in their social network develops a mental health problem. It will also evaluate the effects of the training on the participants personal help-seeking if they have a mental health problem and on their own mental health. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>workplaceaid.net.au </trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Melbourne School of Population and Global Health (MSPGH) Human Ethics Advisory Group</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The University of Melbourne
Melbourne School of Population and Global Health 
Level 3, 207 Bouverie Street 
CARLTON  VIC   3010 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/05/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1341345.1</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/04/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/366410(v11-06-2014-16-32-29)-WorkplaceAid_advertising_flyer_FINAL.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nicola Reavley</name>
      <address>Senior Research Fellow 
WorkplaceAid Project 
The University of Melbourne 
Melbourne School of Population and Global Health 
Centre for Mental Health 
Level 4, 207 Bouverie Street 
CARLTON  VIC   3010 </address>
      <phone>+61 3 9035 7628</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nreavley@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Julie-Anne Fischer</name>
      <address>Trial Manager, WorkplaceAid Project 
The University of Melbourne 
Melbourne School of Population and Global Health 
Centre for Mental Health 
Level 4, 207 Bouverie Street 
CARLTON  VIC   3010 </address>
      <phone>+ 61 3 9036 6770</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jfischer@unimelb.edu.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nicola Reavley</name>
      <address>Senior Research Fellow 
WorkplaceAid Project 
The University of Melbourne 
Melbourne School of Population and Global Health 
Centre for Mental Health 
Level 4, 207 Bouverie Street 
CARLTON  VIC   3010 </address>
      <phone>+61 3 9035 7628</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nreavley@unimelb.edu.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Julie-Anne Fischer </name>
      <address>Trial Manager, WorkplaceAid Project 
The University of Melbourne 
Melbourne School of Population and Global Health 
Centre for Mental Health 
Level 4, 207 Bouverie Street 
CARLTON  VIC   3010 </address>
      <phone>+61 3 9035 6770</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jfischer@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>