<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336676">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/03/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/03/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000295943</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Lifestyle Intervention for early diabetes: A randomised controlled trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect on patients with newly diagnosed diabetes of a lifestyle intervention + standard care or standard care alone on HbA1c levels.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1120-0845</utrn>
    <trialacronym>LIFEDIAB</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cardiovascular disease risk</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>health service utilisation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Psychological distress</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Standard care (i.e, standard diabetes management by a healthcare provider) plus a 1-week intensive residential lifestyle program with booster sessions held over 14 weeks. The multimodal lifestyle intervention will be held at The Gawler Foundation. This intervention will be delivered by a team of multidisciplinary health professionals and will consist of daily group sessions educating participants about diabetes pathophysiology, risks, stress management, and lifestyle factors (diet and exercise) and behaviour likely to better control T2DM. The minimum dietary change advocated to participants will be in line with recommendations of the American Diabetes Association. During the residential program a plant-based high-fibre wholefood diet will be available to participants and healthy eating behaviour will be encouraged. This will encompass the use of mindfulness when eating, awareness of hunger and satiety signals, and enjoyment of food through paced food consumption. Participants in the lifestyle group will also receive counselling and group interaction designed to improve their compliance with lifestyle change. The intervention will draw upon the ESSENCE framework for health. This is a model of wellbeing suitable for the layperson and is taught to medical graduates of Monash University. It is based on the tenet that there are seven factors that are essential to well being: Education, Stress management, Spirituality, Exercise, Nutrition, Connectedness, and Environment.

The duration of standard care will be variable for each patient. It will be determined by their usual general practitioner or endocrinologist as would normally occur in the context of usual care.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard care only (i.e, standard diabetes management by a healthcare provider)</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>For all patients the primary outcome will be glycaemic control operationalised as HbA1c level.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (study entry) and 12 months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The percentage of patients achieving normal glycaemic control as assessed using fasting BSL (using WHO definition) and HbA1c (defined as a haemoglobin A1c &lt;8%).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (study entry) and 12 months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cholesterol (Fasting LDL//HDL, total cholesterol)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (study entry) and 12 months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lipids:	Fasting Serum triglyceride levels</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (study entry) and 12 months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma Vitamin D (25-hydroxyvitamin D)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (study entry) and 12 months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>body mass index :	Calculated from Height, weight</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (study entry) and 12 months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>waist girth measured in centimetres by tape measure at the level of the naval while in the standing position.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (study entry) and 12 months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>blood pressure measured using a digital sphygmomanometer. The average of three measurements will be used.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (study entry) and 12 months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>pulse measured using a digital pulse oximeter.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (study entry) and 12 months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of co-morbidities measured by patient self-report using a researcher devised survey</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (study entry) and 12 months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diabetes symptoms (Type 2 diabetes Symptom Checklist)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (study entry) and 12 months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychological Distress (Kessler Psychological Distress Scale (k-10))</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (study entry) and 12 months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lifestyle indicators:	
Diet, Exercise, Smoking, Alcohol intake, 
Meditation, (via researcher designed survey)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (study entry) and 12 months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number and dose of hypoglycaemic drugs being taken for glycaemic control.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (study entry) and 12 months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number type and dose of other medications measured by patient self report and verified by medical records data.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (study entry) and 12 months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health service utilisation measured by (1) self report (and valdated by medical records data) for the number of general practitioner visits and (2) self-report for the number of unplanned hospital attendances.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (study entry) and 12 months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Aged 18 years or more
With newly identified (within 24 months at the time of intervention) T2DM
Able to attend a 1-week residential program in and 4 X 3 hour booster sessions held over the subsequent 14 week period. 
Willing to undertake significant lifestyle change</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients who are unable to provide informed consent
Patients who are unable to communicate adequately in English
Patients who are cognitively impaired or in an altered conscious state
Patients that are receiving palliative care
Patients who have commenced sulfonylreas as an adjunct to metformin to treat their diabetes</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A computer generated randomisation sequence will be created by a researcher independent to the study. After assessing study eligibility and obtaining participant consent the site investigator will call the research office (or officer if after hours) who holds the allocation schedule to determine the group to which the patient is randomly allocated. The study will be unblinded upon allocation and the patient will be allocated to one of two groups: lifestyle intervention (LI) + standard care group or a control group who will receive standard therapy (ST) alone.

Allocation will be concealed from the researcher determining eligibility; upon determining eligibility of a patient, the recruiting researcher will contact the holder of the allocation schedule (held at a centre administration site), at which time the allocation will be revealed to the recruiting researcher and participant.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer generated randomisation sequence will be created by a researcher independent to the study. After assessing study eligibility and obtaining participant consent the site investigator will call the research office (or officer if after hours) to determine the group to which the patient is randomly allocated. The study will be unblinded upon allocation and the patient will be allocated to one of two groups: lifestyle intervention (LI) + standard care group or a control group who will receive standard therapy (ST) alone.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>84</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Monash University Human Research Ethics Committee (MUHREC)
Building 3e  Room 111
Research Office
Monash University VIC 3800</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Walter Pisciotta Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>45 Hepner Road
Emerald VIC 3782</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>St. Vincent's Hospital Melbourne</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Emergency Practice Innovation Centre
PO Box 2900
Fitzroy VIC 3065</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>By 2010 T2DM is expected to affect in excess of 1.1 million Australians. This is clearly an epidemic that threatens to overwhelm the resources of our health system. Evidence-based strategies that engage patients to make lifestyle choices that result in better glucose control are urgently needed. Better glucose control has the potential to significantly decrease complications and health care costs, and halt or reverse disease progression. The proposed research offers an opportunity to manage chronic illness through sustained lifestyle change facilitated by delivery in a residential setting. The research aims to determine the feasibility and efficacy of a residential lifestyle intervention plus standard care compared to standard care alone in patients with newly established type 2 diabetes in (1) stabilising average blood glucose (as assessed using HbA1c); and (2) achieving normal glucose control assessed by fasting blood sugar level. A randomised controlled trial will be conducted for adult patients with newly diagnosed diabetes. Patients will be allocated to receive either standard care only (i.e, standard diabetes management by a healthcare provider) or standard care plus a 1-week intensive residential lifestyle program with booster sessions held over 14 weeks. The multimodal lifestyle intervention will be held at The Gawler Foundation. This intervention will be delivered by a team of multidisciplinary health professionals and will consist of daily group sessions educating participants about diabetes pathophysiology, risks, stress management, and lifestyle factors (diet and exercise) and behaviour likely to better control T2DM. The minimum dietary change advocated to participants will be in line with recommendations of the American Diabetes Association. During the residential program a plant-based high-fibre wholefood diet will be available to participants and healthy eating behaviour will be encouraged. This will encompass the use of mindfulness when eating, awareness of hunger and satiety signals, and enjoyment of food through paced food consumption. Participants in the lifestyle group will also receive counselling and group interaction designed to improve their compliance with lifestyle change. The intervention will draw upon the ESSENCE framework for health. This is a model of wellbeing suitable for the layperson and is taught to medical graduates of Monash University. It is based on the tenet that there are seven factors that are essential to well being: Education, Stress management, Spirituality, Exercise, Nutrition, Connectedness, and Environment. Patients will be followed up at 12 months. Outcome measures will include glycaemic control as measured using glycated haemoglobin A1c (HbA1c; primary outcome) and fasting capillary blood sugar. Secondary outcome measure will include lipid status (low density and high density lipoprotein, triglyceride levels), Vitamin D, bodyweight, body mass index, waist girth, waist-to-hip ratio, blood pressure, pulse, number of co-morbidities, diabetes symptoms and diabetes specific health-related quality of life, and compliance with lifestyle change.  An economic analysis will be undertaken at the conclusion of the study to determine the cost-benefit of the program. Among other endpoints this will consider costs associated with medication use and health service utilisation.This research will add to the literature regarding strategies for controlling the diabetes epidemic by assessing whether intensive lifestyle interventions prevent the progression to diabetes in patients with pre-diabetes, or improved glycemic control in patients with diabetes. This may ultimately revolutionise treatment approaches to pre-diabetes and diabetes and decrease the costs borne by individuals and the health system. This research investigates an inexpensive approach with the capacity for widespread adoption that is likely to be highly cost-effective and sustainable.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>CF10/3563-2010 001887</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/12/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Prof George Jelinek</name>
      <address>Emergency Practice Innovation Centre
PO Box 2900
Fitzroy VIC 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 3 92882734</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>george.jelinek@svhm.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Prof George Jelinek</name>
      <address>Emergency Practice Innovation Centre
PO Box 2900
Fitzroy VIC 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 3 92882734</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>george.jelinek@svhm.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>