<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372982">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/06/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/06/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000923369p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The impact of different proline and glycine containing test foods and supplements on serum amino acid and peptide availability</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The impact of different proline and glycine containing test foods and supplements on serum amino acid and peptide availability in healthy active males
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Connective tissue health</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Collagen synthesis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal musculoskeletal and cartilage development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The amino acid bio-availability of proline and glycine containing foods will be measured in 16 participants (part a) as per the protocol outlined below. These 16 participants will be separated further into 2 sub-groups of 8 for the assessment of urinary hydroxyproline (HYP) - (part b) and the assessment of food sources on In vitro collagen synthesis and ligament mechanical properties (part c).  The second group of 8 participants included in part c will undertake the research protocol once the timing of appearance and peaks of amino acids are determined: derived from the 1st group and will inform the timing of part 3: serum sample collection for the engineered ligament and cell-cultures.  

Research protocol:
Part a: Healthy male participants will complete a single-blinded cross-over design. A total of 7 trials will be undertaken in fasted, rested conditions with a 72 hour wash-out period between trials. Participants will arrive on testing days in a 8 hour fasted state after standardised pre fast meal and fluid intake Participants will be cannulated by a trained phlebotomist and a baseline (BL) blood sample collected (2 ml) for analysis of amino acids. The participants will then consume the test food (as described below) and blood samples (2ml) will be obtained every 20 minutes over the proceeding 3 hours for plasma amino acid assessment. 
Participants will ingest  7 different proline and glycine containing test foods (specifically whey protein powder, skim milk powder, casein protein powder, hydrolysed collagen powder, liquid gelatin, solid gelatin powder and a bone broth). Foods will be sent to an external lab for analysis of food amino acid concentrations (Australian Proteome Analysis Facilty). Participants will ingest an amount of product equivalent to 0.3 grams/kg BM protein. Where food protein concentrations are small and doses required to provide 0.3 g/kg BM are impractical to consume within 10 minutes, an amount to an acceptable/ practical volume (i.e. 500ml) will be prescribed. Commencement of intake of test food will be considered t = 0 and encouragement will be provided to finish consumption of test food within 10 min. Fluid volume associated with product intake will be standardised to 500ml. (this will consist of either the test food being used  if applicable i.e. bone broth or a matched amount of fluid will be given in the form of water). No further food/fluid intake will be allowed for 60 min after ingestion of test food to standardise gastric emptying rates.
Once the final blood sample is collected, the cannula will then be removed and pressure applied to the insertion site, after which participants will then be provided with a meal. The participant will be free to go and will return to the lab for subsequent testing after 72 hrs washout

Part b: For the first 8 participants completing the study, participants will attend the lab the day prior to day 1 testing, and provide a urine samples for assessment of baseline HYP assessment (first morning, 12 hours after first morning (i.e. before bed) and 24h excretion) and 24 hour food/fluid intake records. On arrival to the lab of the 1st testing day, these 8 participants will be required to give a first morning urine sample and will then undergo testing as per part a. To assess for hydration status (USG) and urinary excretion of hydroxyproline (HYP), first morning urine will be collected on each trial day (BL) (USG), 12 hours after 1st morning urine (i.e. before bed) and for the 24 hour period following the ingestion of the test food. A 24hr food diary will also be required to be completed by participants to assess dietary intake of HYP containing foods.

Part c: For the second 8 participants completing the trials, an additional 55ml of blood will be collected at BL and at the time point associated with the proline and glycine plasma peak post ingestion. This blood collection will occur for 3 of the 7 foods described above. Two collagenous protein sources (hydrolysed collagen, Gelatin) and one non collagenous protein source (casein powder).   The serum obtained from this blood pull (~ 24ml) will be utilised for the treated constructs and cell lines, serum will be sent to the University of California, Davis Proteomics Core facility and the Collagen Research Institute, Kiel, Germany, respectively

The second 8 participants will complete the trials after amino acid analysis has occured (~3 months post part a, to ensure timing of blood pulls correspond to measured amino acid peaks. 
Once collected the 55ml blood will be allowed to clot and spun at 1, 500 x g for 10 min with the resultant serum separated into 2 x ~12ml samples and stored at -80C for further analysis.
NB. . The research protocol, standardised diet preceding data collection and any relevant information on dietary intake (i.e. 24 food diaries) will be completed by an Accredited Practicing Dietitian with a minimum of 3 years  experience.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Cross-comparison study between different collagen containing and non-collagen containing foods. Matched to amount of protein and volume. All subjects will complete identical consumption protocols, with the only difference being the type of food consumed.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in plasma amino acid after ingestion of treatment food - assessed within all participants
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre - treatment (baseline), and then every 20 minutes for a total of 3 hours post ingestion of treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in plasma peptide availability after ingestion of treatment food - assessed within all participants</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre - treatment (baseline), and then every 20 minutes for a total of 3 hours post ingestion of treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Urinary hydroxyproline excretion - this outcome is assessed in part b only.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (1 day before testing commences)
After the intake of 2 collagen containing and 2 non-collagen containing food sources/supplements
Both of the above at the following time points:
First morning (upon waking)
12 hours after first morning urine (before bed)
24 hours </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Active individuals exercising at least 2-3 times per week</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Females: Variations in serum estrogen concentrations associated with female reproductive function has been shown to influence the mechanical properties of engineered ligaments via its action on lysyl oxidase. This would add confounding to the study and therefore we have decided to control for this by excluding female subjects. 
2. Individuals with allergy/intolerance to porcine and/or bovine gelatin, milk and/or milk products and/or chicken/beef/seafood 
3. Individuals with diabetes: Increase blood glucose has been shown to influence non-enzymatic cross linking in collagen.
4. Individuals with a history of recent (&lt; 1 month) or current tendinopathies: Inflammatory cytokines have been shown to influence fibroblast activity and collagen synthesis and subsequent cross-linking.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation will be controlled by a primary researcher. Samples will be coded so as to ensure blinding from assessors.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Bio-availability</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size calculations
Part a. A power estimation for detecting differences in AUC of blood amino acid concentrations following intake of protein-rich food has previously been undertaken by Van Loon et al. 2000.  The suitability of the derived sample size (n = 15) was further confirmed by other research undertaken by our team in which clear differences in post-meal concentrations of blood amino acid were detected in a cohort of athletes of this size (Burke et al. 2012).  
Part b. The suitability of a sample size of 8 for detecting changes in urinary HYP was confirmed by a power calculation using a 5mg change assuming a SD of 2.5mg providing an estimation of 80% power at the 0.05 level of significance.
Part c. According to calculations undertaken in a similar study by our group (Shaw et al. 2016), a 2.4 ug change in engineered ligament collagen content, assuming a SD of 1 ug with 80% power at the 0.05 level of significance, will be detected with a sample size of 8 subjects.

Statistics
Descriptive statistics will be used to summarise amino acid content within each food sample, serum levels of amino acids and differences in engineered ligament properties between and within groups. The differences between amino acid data and engineered ligament properties between and within groups will be analysed using a repeated measures two way ANOVA with either LSD or Tukey HSD post hoc analysis. To determine the association between urine Hyp and intake of Hyp, Pearsons correlation will be used. Statistical significance will be set at p &lt;0.05. Statistical analysis will be undertaken using SPSS (Version 15 for Windows, SPSS Inc, Chicago, IL).</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/07/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/01/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>16</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>28/03/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2617 - Bruce</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australian Institute of Sport</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Leverrier street, Bruce, Canberra ACT 2616</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Catholic University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>115 Victoria Parade
Fitzroy, Victoria 3065</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>ACT Brumbies</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Building 29, University Dr, Bruce ACT 2617</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of California Davis</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Hutchison Dr. 
Davis, CA, United States 95616</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>United States of America</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Maastricht University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Minderbroedersberg 4-6, 6211 LK Maastricht, Netherlands</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Netherlands</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Collagen Research Institute </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Schauenburgerstraße 116, 24118 Kiel</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Germany</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Specific amino acids (i.e. proline and glycine) and/or sequences of these amino acids (i.e. peptides) play a supportive role in the synthesis of collagen, the predominant protein found within connective tissues. Recent work by our team has shown a dose response relationship between amino acid availability and collagen content, and tissue mechanics in engineered ligaments following the ingestion of gelatin (a food form of collagen). However, it is not currently known whether other foods/supplements containing relevant amino acids/ peptides have the potential to support collagen synthesis. Furthermore, the bioavailability (i.e. timing and peaks of appearance within the blood) of varying collagen and non-collagen containing food sources is currently unknown. Therefore the goal of this study is twofold;
Part a) Determination of the plasma amino acid response to dietary and supplemental sources of non- collagen and collagen containing foods while measuring potential biomarkers of collagen intake urinary HYP. 
Part b) Investigation of the effect of dietary and supplemental sources of non-collagen and collagen containing proteins on in-vitro collagen synthesis in engineered ligaments and cultured fibroblast cell lines.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Australian Institute of Sport ethics committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Leverrier St, Bruce ACT 2617</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>22/05/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Rebekah Alcock</name>
      <address>Australian Institute of Sport
Leverrier St, Bruce ACT 2617
</address>
      <phone>+61476291511</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Rebekah.Alcock@ausport.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Rebekah Alcock</name>
      <address>Australian Institute of Sport
Leverrier St, Bruce ACT 2617</address>
      <phone>+61476291511</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Rebekah.Alcock@ausport.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Rebekah Alcock</name>
      <address>Australian Institute of Sport
Leverrier St, Bruce ACT 2617</address>
      <phone>+61476291511</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Rebekah.Alcock@ausport.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Rebekah Alcock</name>
      <address>Australian Institute of Sport
Leverrier St, Bruce ACT 2617</address>
      <phone>+61476291511</phone>
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>