<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372267">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/02/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/03/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000449336</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Outcomes of early auditory, tactile, visual and vestibular (ATVV) stimulation in the adaptation to birth of the mother and child dyad</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of multisensory stimulation auditory, tactile, visual and vestibular (ATVV) in the adaptation to the birth of the mother and child dyad</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1192-3774</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>'Nil known' </secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>postpartum depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Ineffective breastfeeding</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast feeding</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Childbirth and postnatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>1. Early stimulation of the newborn. The technique of auditory, tactile, visual and vestibular multi-sensory stimulation (VCTA) is used.
2. This therapy performs the hearing of the stimulus with the voice of the mother, the touch of the stimulus with the realization of an ordered and sequential massage; Visual stimulation with visual contact with his mother and vestibular stimulation with slow movements in the arms of the mother
3. ATVV therapy is performed according to the Rice Protocol modified by White-Traut and Contributors and lasts for 15 minutes.
4. Mothers received training in therapy by a nurse. A video was used to do the demonstration of each stimulation and neonatal behavioral responses showing pleasure with the stimulus. The video lasted 6 minutes. Then a recording gives continuous instructions to the mother step by step during the performance of the stimulation therapy
5. During the first application an understanding checklist is made
6. To promote adhesion, the mother is given a headset set with recorded instructions
7. At home, mothers performed therapy by listening to recorded instructions, twice a day for 7 days</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group
The standard of care involves advice from nurses on doubts that the mother in the first 24 to 36 hours of hospital stay. A medical assessment by the gynecologist in the first 10 days postpartum and an assessment made of Pediatrics between 30 and 40 of the life of the newborn</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>depression postpartum whith EPDS scale or Edinburg Postpartum Depression Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint> Six weeks post birth.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>stress for motherhood 
Measured with Being to Mother BaM-13 version in Spanish</outcome>
      <timepoint> Six weeks post birth.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Effective neonatal suckling
The footage in the video of a moment of breastfeeding were observed. They are used to construct the indicator the following criteria: the amount of milk obtained by the method of double heavy. The time of suction effective, the number of suctions made and the construction of the saved</outcome>
      <timepoint>two weeks post birth</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dyadic mutuality whith Code Mutuallity Dyadic</outcome>
      <timepoint>six weeeks post birth</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>quality of life using SF-12</outcome>
      <timepoint>six weeks post birth</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neonatal growth Using anthropometric measurements: weight, height and cephalometric perimeter</outcome>
      <timepoint>six weeks post birth</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Development Measured observing the evolution of the characteristics of the oral suction</outcome>
      <timepoint>six weeks post birth</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>New mothers
Newborns full term
Healthy dyads
Newborns without congenital diseases
Mothers who can read and write
Dyadic without contraindications to breastfeeding
Mothers with breastfeeding intentions at least the first month</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Mothers with cognitive impairments or diagnosed mental illness
Mother or child hospitalization during follow-up time
Breastfeeding suspension</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>"Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer softwar</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size: Was calculated to establish differences between and within groups with repeated measurements.  alpha: probability of incurring type I error Beta: probability of incurring type II error Delta: upper bound of the standard deviation from the valuesproduced by the total variable of the scale used deviation standard: Minimum difference between the means of the groups to establish the value of beta K: number of groups
 Values established for the sample of the sample. alpha = 0.04 beta= 0.01 Delta = 0.8s K = 2 Taking into account these precisions of the required size is 60 dyads.  The size of the global sample previously identified by 120 dyads, ie 60 dyads per group.


Inferential Statistics:
To test the hypotheses raised, a normality test will be performed first to determine the distribution of each of the variables. Once established, a path of analysis with parametric tests will be considered according to the normal distribution and for the non-normal distribution, a path of analysis with non-parametric tests. The significance of the tests is set at p: &lt;0.05. The analyzes follow two different ways, one to compare two groups (the experimental and the control); And the other to compare the group with itself at two different time points, in the first 14 days and 4 to 6 weeks
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>19/07/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>30/10/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>107</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>27/11/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Colombia</country>
      <state>Bogota D.C</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Universidad Nacional de Colombia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Carrera 30 #43-06 Edificio 228</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Colombia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Universidad Nacional de Colombia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Carrera 30 #43-06 Edificio 228</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Colombia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Colciencias</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Avenida Calle 26 # 57-41 Torre 8 - Pisos del 2 al 6</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Colombia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Colciencias</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Avenida Calle 26 # 57-41 Torre 8 - Pisos del 2 al 6</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Colombia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Contrary to popular conceptions, mothers and newborns do not spend the best time of their lives once birth occurs. Both go through a period of physiological adjustments , emotional and behavioral, which are reflected in the affectation of physical and emotional well-being. This adaptation is influenced by contextual factors peculiar to a developing country such as poverty or low level of schooling; Which can lead to consequences such as postpartum depression in the mother and delayed growth and development in children (12,17-19). In Colombia, no support or rigorous follow-up strategies are available during this sensitive period for mother and child dyads (20,21). The multimodal auditory, tactile, vestibular and visual stimulation (VCTA) has been studied since 1980 and is known to favor the premature newborn and its growth has ended; Decreases stress; Favors the organization of neonatal behavior and improves mother-child interaction. When the mother offers it, there has been a decrease in depressive symptoms. Objective: To measure the results of the multisensory stimulation ATVV performed by the mother to her newborn, in the adaptation to the birth of the mother and child dyad. Method: A quasi-experimental, blind study using the design of equivalent materials, with repeated post-test measurements. Expected Results: Performing the stimulation (VCTA) by the mother to her newborn will generate positive results in: 1. The synchrony of mother and child interaction. 2. Decreased depressive symptoms in the mother. 3. Health and maternal energy level. 4. Effective neonatal suction. 5. Neonatal growth and development. In this way, adaptation to the birth of the mother and child dyad will be favored.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Comite de Etica de la facultad de  Enfermeria de la Universidad Nacional.</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Carrera 30 No.45 - 03, TORRE DE ENFERMERIA, Edificio 228, piso 8, Oficina 403 Conmutador: </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/04/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Acta N06 de 2016</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/02/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Colombia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372267-AVAL-016-2016 LUCY MARCELA VESGA.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372267-Aval san Jose.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Lucy Marcela Vesga Gualdron</name>
      <address>Universidad Nacional de Colombia Carrera 30 #45-06 Edificio 228 Bogota D.C. America del sur.</address>
      <phone>+54 3006071569</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lmvesgag@unal.edu.co</email>
      <country>Colombia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Lucy Marcela Vesga Gualdron</name>
      <address>Universidad Nacional de Colombia Carrera 30 #43-06 Edificio 228 Bogota D.C. America del sur.</address>
      <phone>3006071569</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lmvesgag@unal.edu.co</email>
      <country>Colombia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Lucy Marcela Vesga Gualdron</name>
      <address>Universidad Nacional de Colombia Carrera 30 #43-06 Edificio 228 Bogota D.C. America del sur.</address>
      <phone>3006071569</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lmvesgag@unal.edu.co</email>
      <country>Colombia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Lucy Marcela Vesga Gualdron</name>
      <address>Carrera 30 #43-06 Edificio 228 Bogota D.C. America del sur.</address>
      <phone>+54 3006071569</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lmvesgag@unal.edu.co</email>
      <country>Colombia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>