<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366305">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/05/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/05/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000565640</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Enhancing neuroplasticity in the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex using non-invasive brain stimulation: Investigating the effects of repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS) and theta burst stimulation (TBS) on working memory and neuroplasticity in healthy volunteers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Enhancing neuroplasticity in the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex using non-invasive brain stimulation: Investigating the effects of repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS) and theta burst stimulation (TBS) on working memory and neuroplasticity in healthy volunteers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Neuroplasticity in healthy volunteers</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of the normal brain and nervous system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Both repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS) and theta burst stimulation (TBS) are non-invasive brain stimulation techniques which, when applied over the scalp, may be used to alter the excitability of underlying neural tissue. 

This study employs a randomised, crossover design where participants take part in three separate treatment sessions at least 72 hours apart. Each session involves administration of either active TMS (rTMS or TBS) or sham TMS. Specifically, rTMS will involve the application of TMS pulses delivered over the left dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (DLPFC) at a rate of 10 Hz at 120% of resting motor threshold (RMT). A total of 60 five-second stimulation trains will be delivered, each with a 15 second inter-stimulus interval (total 3000 pulses). TBS will be delivered over the left DLPFC at 80% of RMT. Two-second stimulation trains will be repeated every 10 seconds for a total of 190 seconds. Within each train, 3 pulses will be delivered at 50 Hz every 200 milliseconds (total of 600 pulses).
</interventions>
    <comparator>Sham TMS (TMS coil placed over the scalp at a 90 degree angle which mimics the sensation of active TMS, but does not alter cortical activity). </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>N-back task accuracy and reaction time</outcome>
      <timepoint>Two separate time-points for each session: 
a) directly after TMS treatment
b) 30 minutes after TMS treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>TMS-EEG evoked potential amplitudes</outcome>
      <timepoint>a) Immediately after TMS treatment
b) 30 minutes following TMS treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>EEG oscillations</outcome>
      <timepoint>Two timepoints for each session. EEG oscilations recorded during n-back task:
a) Immediately after TMS treatment
b) 30 minutes following TMS treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) Right-handed adults who have the capacity to provide informed consent. 
2) Have no personal history of psychiatric or neurological illness.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) Anyone suffering from an unstable medical condition, neurological or psychiatric disorder or any history of a seizure disorder or who are currently pregnant or breastfeeding.

2) Anyone with any metallic implants in the head, a pacemaker, cochlear implant medication pump or other electronic device.

3) Anyone currently taking any psychoactive medications.

4) Professional drivers are not able to participate due to the, albeit relatively low, risk of seizure as this could affect their employment.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Participants will receive both active and sham stimulation in a cross-over design employing a 72 hour wash out period.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>As there is limited data on which to base meaningful power analyses we will aim to recruit 30 participants. However, we will conduct interim analyses at N=20. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash Univeristy</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Wellington Road, Clayton, VIC 3168</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Monash University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Wellington Road, Clayton, VIC 3168</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Repetitive TMS protocols are emerging as promising therapeutic tools for the treatment of a number of psychiatric and neurological conditions. The clinical efficacy of these protocols is likely due in part to their ability to promote lasting neuroplastic changes within the brain. 

rTMS and TBS are two commonly used protocols which have shown some success in transiently altering cortical excitability and treating a number of brain-related disorders. To date, however, the comparative effectiveness of these two techniques remains to be thoroughly investigated. 

This study will apply rTMS, TBS and sham stimulation over the left dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (DLPFC) in normal healthy participants. Behavioural (n-back task) and neurophysiological (TMS-EEG, EEG oscillations) data will be collected both before and after stimulation, which will provide insight into the effects that each of these stimulation protocols has on both cognitive function and underlying cortical neurophysiology. We anticipate that, compared to sham stimulation, both rTMS and TBS will significantly improve n-back task performance and induce lasting changes in brain activity as measured with combined  TMS-EEG and EEG. In addition, we anticipate that these effects will be the strongest following the TBS protocol.   
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Health Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Alfred Hospital, 
Commercial Rd, 
Prahran
3181 VIC</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>193/14</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/05/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Aron Hill</name>
      <address>MAPrc, 
Level 4, 607 St Kilda Rd, 
Melbourne, VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)3 9076 6564</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>aron.hill@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Aron Hill</name>
      <address>MAPrc, 
Level 4, 607 St Kilda Rd, 
Melbourne, VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)3 9076 6564</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>aron.hill@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Aron Hill</name>
      <address>MAPrc, 
Level 4, 607 St Kilda Rd, 
Melbourne, VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)3 9076 6564</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>aron.hill@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>