<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371394">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/09/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001225404</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A validation study to investigate the role of Central Hypertension in Atrial Fibrillation Outcome</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A prospective validation study to Investigate the role of Multi-modality central PULSE wave evaluation and its impact on atrial fibrillation (AF) outcome. (IMPULSE AF)- Validation Study
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1186-9931</utrn>
    <trialacronym>IMPULSE AF-Validation Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Atrial Fibrillation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Hypertension</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Hypertension</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>IMPULSE AF is a pilot study to validate our non-invasive central pressure assessment against invasive aortic pressure.
Central Hypertension will be validated in AF by comparing invasive assessment during AF ablation with non-invasive appraisal of central pressure indices during AF ablation.
Invasive central BP waveform will be recorded for 5-10 mins with pig tail catheter in aorta at the time of into-atrial septal puncture. 
Non-invasive assessment of central pressure wave morphology and pulse wave velocity (PWV) appraisal between descending and abdominal aorta by echocardiography and carotid 
femoral PWV by Sphygmocor (cuff based device over the thigh) will be done at the same time. 
Invasive BP monitoring will be performed by anaesthetics as usual in AF after that.
The validation of the non-invasive assessment of central pressure indices (morphology and PWV) will be performed in AF and sinus rhythm during AF ablation. 
In the next step, We will take this opportunity to look at the earliest change in central pressure wave form with reversion in sinus rhythm. </interventions>
    <comparator>Non-invasively CMR, echo and Sphygmocor are validated means of looking at central pressure wave in sinus rhythm but not in AF. 
In the validation step we will like to validate the non-invasive method by comparing it with invasive assessment in AF.
In next step the validated non-invasive method or methods will be employed to look into central pressure wave change with change in rhythm from sinus to AF or vice versa.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early Detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Validation of non-invasive central pressure indices appraisal method in AF by comparing it with invasive assessment during AF ablation.
Invasive assessment will be performed by the pig tail catheter placed in the aorta at the time of intra-atrial septal puncture.
Non invasive assessment will be done by echocardiography and cuff based device (Sphygmocor) applied at thigh. Central Pressure wave morphology and velocity will be computed by these techniques. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of ablation
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To record and review earliest marker of change in central pressure wave morphology or velocity with change in rhythm i.e; AF or sinus rhythm. During AF ablation the transformation in central pressure with change in rhythm will be studied with invasive (via pig tail) and non-invasive methods (echo, Sphygmocor). 
In the validation phase we are not planning to follow up our patients for the study purpose. during follow up appointments. </outcome>
      <timepoint>For validation study, we are only collecting data at the time of validation and 4-6 weeks post ablation re CMR study. Further follow ups will be organised as a protocol for our next study. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Validation of invasive central pressure recorded during AF ablation with non-invasive central pressure assessment by echocardiography and Sphygmocor device during sinus rhythm</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of ablation
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients undergoing AF ablation for symptomatic PAF
Age range 18-80 yrs
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Patients contraindicated for exercise testing according to American Heart
Association (AHA) guidelines.
2. Acute decompensated heart failure
3. Unstable angina or recent MI (less than 4 weeks)
4. Hemodynamic instability 
5. Connective tissue disorders involving aortic root. 
6. Moderate to severe aortic valve insufficiency
7. Advanced valvular heart disease
8. Constrictive or restrictive cardiomyopathy
9. Pregnancy 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Sample Size Calculation:
ARTERY society guidelines recommend enrolment of 30 patients in validation study. For our pilot study we will recruit 30 patients to allow normal distribution of data as well as addressing the Std. deviation of Sphygmocor device (0.5m/s). A sample size of 30 will give us a beat of 0.8 to correlate invasive and non-invasive evaluation of central pressure with alpha of 0.05. 
Statistical Analysis: 
Continuous variables will be reported as mean with standard deviation (SD). Results will be expressed as mean +/- SEM with p value of &lt;0.05 considered statistically significant. Intra-class correlation analysis, Students t-test and Bland Altman plots will be used to assess the agreement between the invasive and non-invasive central pressure measurements. Pearsons method will be used for correlation analysis for the differences between the mean values of the non-invasive and invasive measurements. 
Other ad hoc summary or analysis may be performed as necessary. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>True</patientregistry>
    <followup>9</followup>
    <followuptype>Months</followuptype>
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>19/09/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>20/09/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>20</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>28/02/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>CHRD, Royal Adelaide Hospital,</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Centre of Heart Rhythm Disorders (CHRD), Level 5 Royal Adelaide Hospital, Adelaide SA 5000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Adelaide Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>North Terrace Adelaide, SA 5000, Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Prash Sanders </othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>CVC, 62 Beulah Road Norwood, Adelaide SA 5067</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Central hypertension leading to early vascular remodelling is an independent predictor of major cardiovascular events. Aorta is not only a conduit artery but also act as a vascular buffer to each ventricle contraction. Overtime, this stretch leads to decrease aortic compliance resulting in aortic stiffness. Ageing and HTN are the predominant attributable risk factors leading to premature aortic stiffness. 
Central HTN can be computed by pulse wave morphology or velocity assessment. Central pressure indices including systolic, diastolic, pulse and augmented pressure along with augmentation index can be derived by central pulse wave morphology. Although evaluation of central haemodynamics can potentially flag the early phase of vascular remodelling but the precise component of central pressure indices predicting risk as per age is under considerable debate. Aortic stiffness is recognised as a surrogate for central arterial hypertension and its non-invasive estimation by pulse wave velocity (PWV) is considered gold standard by European Society of Cardiology (ESC) 2013 guidelines. Non-invasive central pulse wave morphology and velocity assessment is not being validated during atrial fibrillation (AF) . In addition, there is paucity of data revealing central pressure indices, including PWV appraisal as an independent predictor of outcome in AF. 
1	Purpose of the study
Raised central pressure is more closely associated with cardiovascular outcome as compare to peripheral HTN. There is evolving evidence that central HTN is underdiagnosed leading to inadequate treatment resulting in early vascular ageing. We propose a staged prospective investigation by designing two perspective studies to validate and incorporate central pressure indices (central systolic, diastolic and pulse pressure with augmentation index and PWV) respectively in AF risk stratification with a view to titrate treatment as per central pressure to study clinical outcome in AF. 

2	Aims
In this validation study we will compare invasive versus non-invasive central pressure indices appraisal including pulse wave morphology and velocity assessment in AF.   
Through this study we seek:
I. To validate widely used non-invasive methods to assess local, regional and systemic central pressure indices while the subjects are in atrial fibrillation (AF). We will compare the non-invasive appraisal of central pressure with an invasive enumeration in our paroxysmal/persistent atrial fibrillation (PAF) cohort  in atrial fibrillation and post restoration of sinus rhythm during elective pulmonary vein isolation (PVI).
II. We will review the shift in central pressure profile with rhythm control in our PAF cohort to identify the early changes in central pulsatile load as well as conduit artery compliance with restoration of sinus rhythm. and will draw a comparison between invasive and non-invasive evaluation</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>CALHN Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>CALHN HUMAN RESEARCH ETHICS
Royal Adelaide Hospital  Level 4 Womens Health Centre
North Terrace, Adelaide, SA 5000
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/08/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CALHN Ref R20160712, HREC Ref: HREC/16/RAH/269</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/08/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Prashanthan Sanders</name>
      <address>CHRD, Dept. of Cardiology, Level 5, Royal Adelaide Hospital, North Terrace, Adelaide, SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61882222723</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>prash.sanders@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Prashanthan Sanders</name>
      <address>CHRD, Dept. of Cardiology, Level 5, Royal Adelaide Hospital, North Terrace, Adelaide, SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61882222723</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>prash.sanders@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Prashanthan Sanders</name>
      <address>CHRD, Dept. of Cardiology, Level 5, Royal Adelaide Hospital, North Terrace, Adelaide, SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61882222723</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>prash.sanders@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>