<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368096">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/03/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/03/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000274572</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Using a Stool Colour Chart in the care of the new-born - A qualitative study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Stool Colour Chart - a qualitative study on its use to improve passive screening for neonatal cholestasis in 0-6 week olds in New Zealand</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1165-5111</utrn>
    <trialacronym>SCC</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Neonatal cholestasis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Biliary Atresia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Complications of newborn</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>After informed consent, the Lead Maternity Carer (LMC) will undertake an initial questionnaire with families will take place, and then a visual reference card with six colour palettes, three normal stool colours and three abnormal acholic stool colours would be given to families of new-borns and the LMC.  The LMC would discuss with the families using the Stool Colour Chart (SCC) as a reminder of normal stool colour at the initial visit at home in the first week of life, then again at the check between 2-6 weeks of life.  As a final screen, there will be another chance for intervention at the Six Week Check, either with the LMC or Well Child Provider, with direct questioning using the SCC regarding stool colour.  The head investigator will undertake a final exit interview with the families and the health professionals will take place inquiring about the usefulness and ease of use of the SCC and education process.  If at any stage there is an abnormally coloured stool, the Protocol for Further Testing if SCC Screen Positive will be instigated.

Data Collection Process:
1)	Anonymised data collection will take place at time of consent, including demographics of the family, the gravidity and parity of the mother, name of LMC and the likely WCP that will perform the Six Week Check.  
2)	A questionnaire asking consented caregivers their perception of normal neonatal stool colour will be performed at the start of the intervention. 
3)	SCC with instructions will be distributed to the families along with their WCTO - My Health Book.  The LMC will also have a copy of the SCC for reference.  The family will notify the LMC at any stage if the stool colour is abnormal and Protocol for Further Testing will be implemented.  
4)	First conversation utilising the SCC between the LMC and family will take place within the first week of life to reinforce the normal stool colour and the sign of acholic stools.
5)	At the scheduled WCTO assessment by the LMC between 2-6 weeks of age, there is already a list of suggested topics of conversation which include stool colour.  At this point the family and LMC should refer to the SCC and ensure there have not been any abnormal stool colours. 
a.	If this is the final LMC visit, an exit interview with the LMC will be performed seeking qualitative data regarding the utility of the SCC in helping with the education and dialogue with families on normal neonatal stool colours.  
6)	There will be a Six Week Check by WCP. A final interaction using the SCC will take place between families and the health professional.  
a.	Practitioners performing the Six Week Check will be interviewed. The Investigator will coordinate with families to ensure the Six Week Check takes place in a timely manner as the window for effective HPE closes rapidly beyond this point.  
7)	The families will then be interviewed regarding their experiences with the SCC, compliance with SCC led discussions during WCTO interactions and whether this aided or changed their perceptions of normal and abnormal neonatal stool colour.  A repeat question regarding the colour or normal neonatal stool will be asked again of all caregivers.  
8)	Analysis of pre-intervention perceptions of normal stool colour and the post-intervention understanding of acholic stools will be performed.  Satisfaction with the SCC as a screening and educational tool will be assessed with interview results with health professionals and families.</interventions>
    <comparator>There is no control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1) Feasibility of SCC to be incorporated into Well Child Tamariki Ora framework - Proportion of Families and LMC that have used the SCC as part of usual practice during the 1st week check, 2-6 week check and at the 6 week check
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 weeks after birth.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2) Post-intervention perceptions of normal stool colour compared to the pre-intervention perceptions. At enrolment prior to birth then at 6 weeks after birth using a questionnaire asking what normal infant stool colour is at birth, at 1st week of life, between 2-6 weeks of life. 
The questionnaire has seven colour palettes, the six colours used in the SCC (3 normal, 3 acholic) but also one black palette to resemble meconium or melaena.  Caregivers are to choose all the colours they believe resemble normal infant stool colour at those 3 ages. Questionnaire is specifically designed for this trial by the Investigator. The colours used from the SCC are validated as representative of normal stool and acholic stool colours, from the Johns Hopkins Stool Color Card. The addition of black is taken from Pantone colour chart to represent meconium or melaena as chosen by the Investigator.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Questionnaire at enrolment (before infant's birth) then repeated at 6 weeks of infant's life.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3) Families and health professional review of the SCC and its use for education and passive screening, assessed by  interview.  Interviews will consist of open-ended questions and answers transcribed and coded for qualitative and thematic data.  Data will be analysed using interpretative phenomenological analysis (IPA).  IPA is utilised as part of the recognition that having a new-born is already an event of great adjustment and emotional impact.  Adding the SCC into the large amount of information afforded to parents as well as possible adding to exisiting anxieties will need to be analysed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 weeks after birth</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of acholic stool is identified by the family or midwife with the SCC.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From birth until 6 weeks of life.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Maori, Pacific Island, European/Pakeha, South Easth Asian families with infants born between March 2015-May 2015.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>1</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Days</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>If pre-term (&lt;36 weeks gestation), any major existing medical conditions eg congenital anomlies or genetic abnormalities.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>10-15 term new-borns and their families from the Wellington and Hutt Valley regions, between 01 March 2015 and 30 May 2015 will be selected using a convenience sampling method.  The New Zealand College of Midwives has provided a list of LMC midwives who indicated interest in participating in the study and were willing to enrol families under their care.  Ideally, the cohort of 10-15 families will be made up evenly in four groups of families identifying as New Zealand European/Pakeha, Maori, South East Asian and Pacific Islander. The ethnic proportionality acknowledges the fact that Biliary Atresia has increased incidence amongst South East Asians and Pacific Islanders and the need to ensure the SCC would be an acceptable intervention to these families in particular.</concealment>
    <sequence>Convenience sampling/enrolment.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/03/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>13/03/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>29/05/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>15</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Stanley Ng</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Ministry of Health
PO Box 5013
No. 1 The Terrace
Level 1 - CLPR
Wellington 6145</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ministry of Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Ministry of Health
PO Box 5013
No. 1 The Terrace
Level 1 - CLPR
Wellington 6145</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Capital &amp; Coast District Health Board</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Riddiford Street
Newtown
Wellington 6021</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To conduct a qualitative study on the implementation of a home-based Stool Colour Chart (SCC) to improve the current opportunistic screening for neonatal cholestasis.  Better awareness of acholic stools by families and health professionals is expected to lead to earlier diagnosis and intervention for time-urgent neonatal liver diseases such as Biliary Atresia.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health &amp; Disability Ethics Committees</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Freyberg Building
20 Aitken Street
PO BOX 5013
Wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/02/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/02/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368096-Stool Colour Chart Study Proposal v4.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Stanley Ng</name>
      <address>Ministry of Health
PO Box 5013
No. 1 The Terrace
Level 1 - CLPR
Wellington 6145</address>
      <phone>+64 4 816 2046</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>stanley_ng@moh.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Stanley Ng</name>
      <address>Ministry of Health
PO Box 5013
No. 1 The Terrace
Level 1 - CLPR
Wellington 6145</address>
      <phone>+64 4 816 2046</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>stanley_ng@moh.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Stanley Ng</name>
      <address>Ministry of Health
PO Box 5013
No. 1 The Terrace
Level 1 - CLPR
Wellington 6145</address>
      <phone>+64 4 816 2046</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>stanley_ng@moh.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Stanley Ng</name>
      <address>Ministry of Health
PO Box 5013
No. 1 The Terrace
Level 1 - CLPR
Wellington 6145</address>
      <phone>+64 4 816 2046</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>stanley_ng@moh.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>