<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372342">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/02/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/03/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000412336</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial to assess the impact of compression therapy to manage chronic oedema on recurrence of cellulitis.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial to assess the impact of compression therapy to manage chronic oedema on recurrence of cellulitis.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Lower Limb Recurrent Cellulitis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Lower limb Chronic Oedema</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants in the control and intervention groups will receive education regarding the benefits of skin care and how to prevent cellulitis at an initial appointment. The initial appointment will take approximately 60-90minutes and will conducted in individual format. Education will involve a handout (created for the study) and verbal education regarding how to maintain good skin integrity and prevent infection through moisturising regularly, minimising trauma to skin (long pants, closed shoes, insect repellent, sunscreen etc), managing minor wounds/abrasions/bites (using antiseptic creams and covering with dressings), minimising risk of tinea/fungal infections between toes (dry between toes, thongs in public pools/showers) and managing inflammatory skin conditions.
The intervention group will be provided with skin care education but the initial appointment will also be used to plan appropriate compression therapy, which will then be provided in subsequent additional appointments. The treatment plan will be developed by a qualified level 1 lymphoedema physiotherapist (or physiotherapist supervised by a level 1 lymphoedema therapist) based on the participants requirements (e.g severity of swelling, functional capacity, and ability to do/doff compression garments). Compression therapy  will consist of prescription of appropriate compression garments and where indicated provision of a period of compression bandaging to minimise swelling prior to measure for and fit of compression garments). The number of appointments necessary for provision of compression therapy will vary based on patient requirements. Patients may require between 1-6 appointments per episode of care and appointments may range from 30-90 minutes. Time per appointment and number of appointments will vary based on severity of oedema (patients with more severe oedema will require more compression bandages to reduce oedema), patient function and comorbidities, and number of legs affected). Compression garments will be selected from the current range available on the Australian market and may include ready to wear or custom made garments, including wrap systems. The initial garments provided to the patient free of charge will be from Haddenham Health Care, who have a range of ready to wear and custom made garments which are available on the Australian market.  
Following this, participants in both groups will be followed for up to three years at regular intervals (6 monthly) to have outcomes measures taken and to continue to receive the allocated treatment (skin care education with or without compression therapy). Compression garments with or without bandaging will be renewed regularly (every 6-12 months).

- Clinicians who providing chronic oedema management and education to prevent cellulitis will be qualified level 1 Lymphoedema physiotherapists or be supervised by qualified level 1 lymphoedema physiotherapists. 

- Participants will be seen at Calvary Public Hospital Bruce outpatient physiotherapy department

Assessments will be done face to face where possible. Phone contact will be made at times to collect certain data for participants who cannot attend scheduled appointments

-Compliance with treatment will be monitored at regular assessments
</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants in the control group will receive only education (regarding the benefits of skin care and how to prevent cellulitis through prevention of tinea/fungal infections between toes) compared to the intervention group who will receive both education and compression.

Note: For patients in the control group, once an episode of cellulitis has occurred, they will cross-over into the intervention group to receive compression therapy.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to first episode of recurrent cellulitis (days)

Diagnosis of cellulitis will be confirmed through patient report. Diagnosis may be confirmed through medical record review or from General practitioner report when deemed necessary by the clinician. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Time (in days) to cellulitis recurrence. 


Diagnosis of cellulitis will be confirmed through patient report. Diagnosis may be confirmed through medical record review or from General practitioner report when deemed necessary by the clinician. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percent change in volume of leg circumferences (cm) and oedema (ml). Perometer will be used to assess leg volume. Tape measure will be used to measure leg circumferences.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Volume assessed at initial assessment, post initial treatment and then 6monthly from initial assessment for three years. 

Assessment of volume post initial treatment will occur when compression garments are initially fitted. Fitting of garments may or may not be preceded by a period of compression bandaging to decrease oedema. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life using LYMQOL questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>LYMQOL will be completed at initial assessment and then 6, 12, 24 and 36 months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>If participant was hospitalised for episode of cellulitis recurrence

Hospitalisation will be based on patient self report and may be confirmed through medical record review or from General practitioner report when deemed necessary by the clinician. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed 6 monthly for three years from initial assessment. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. The patients is over 18 years of age
2. The patient is identified as having chronic oedema (oedema persisting more than 3 months) in one or both legs 
3. The patient has a history of 2 or more episodes of cellulitis in the past 2 years
4. The patient is able to understand their involvement in the study, as per the information sheet
5.The patient is able to give informed consent
6. The patient has a valid Medicare card
7. The patient is able to attend regular scheduled appointments
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. The patient is currently receiving chronic oedema management that involves compression
2. The patient declines to participate or is unable to participate for whatever reason
3. The patient is receiving end of life care
4. The patient is medically unstable
5.The patient has wounds requiring treatment that prevents use of compression garments
6. The patient is unable to wear compression (unable to don/doff garments or has a medical condition that contraindicates use of compression)
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>sealed opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation using a randomisation table created by
computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)

 As prophylactic antibiotics may strongly influence recurrence of cellulitis (Morton &amp; Swartz, 2004), randomisation of participants will be stratified by prophylactic antibiotic use</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>For patients in the control group, once an episode of cellulitis has occurred, they will cross-over into the intervention group to receive compression therapy. Follow up will continue according to the original specified plan (6 monthly from initial assessment)</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Based on the assumptions that compression therapy will reduce incidence of recurrent cellulitis by 50% (Arsenault, Rielly, &amp; Wise, 2011; Ko, Lerner, Klose, &amp; Cosimi, 1998), and that the cellulitis recurrence rate is approximately 40% (Cox, 2006; Jorup-Ronstrom &amp; Britton, 1987), in order to achieve a statistically significant effect (P=0.05) we plan to admit 152 participants (76 per arm) into the study for a follow up of three years or until 45 events of recurrent cellulitis occur. This sample size has been calculated for the primary objective (time to cellulitis recurrence)

For the main outcome measure of time to first episode of recurrent cellulitis, survival analysis will be undertaken. Kaplan-Meier plots will be used to compare the time to first recurrence between the groups, with a log rank test being used to determine if there is a statistically significant difference between the groups. Cox proportional hazards regression may also be used to adjust for important risk factors. Right censoring will be used for patients who are lost to follow up. 

For the secondary outcomes of percent change in limb volume and QOL, measures will be at multiple time points. Therefore groups may be compared using a linear mixed model or using a repeated measures analysis. Intention to treat analysis will be used. 

. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>2/06/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/04/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>152</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>14</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/04/2022</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Calvary Public Hospital ACT - Bruce</hospital>
    <hospital>The Canberra Hospital - Garran</hospital>
    <postcode>2617 - Bruce</postcode>
    <postcode>2605 - Garran</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Calvary Public Hospital Bruce</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Calvary Public Hospital Bruce,
Haydon Drive,
Bruce 
ACT 2617</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Calvary Public Hopsital Bruce</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Calvary Public Hospital Bruce,
Haydon Drive,
Bruce 
ACT 2617
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Haddenham Healthcare</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>30/170 Forster Rd, 
Mount Waverley 
VIC 3149</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this research is to investigate the functional impact of compression therapy (to manage chronic oedema) for adults who have chronic oedema and a history of recurrent cellulitis in a lower limb or limbs who access health services within the ACT. Reducing cellulitis recurrence could decrease the burden on the healthcare system and may positively influence the quality of life (QOL) of individuals experiencing recurrent episodes of cellulitis. Whilst this study will be performed in adults receiving healthcare services in the ACT, it is hoped the results may provide insight for cellulitis management within Australia.

Research Objectives
For adults with a history of chronic oedema and recurrent cellulitis who are accessing healthcare services within the ACT, we plan to investigate:
1.If use of compression therapy delays the incidence of recurrent cellulitis in the affected limb/s (primary objective),
2. If use of compression therapy decreases affected limb volume, 
3. If use of compression therapy improves quality of life, and
4. If use of compression therapy delays incidence of hospitalisation for cellulitis in the affected limb/s.

Research Hypothesis:
Addition of compression therapy to manage chronic oedema will delay recurrence of cellulitis
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Calvary Public Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Calvary Public Hospital
Haydon Drive,
Bruce
ACT 2617</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/01/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>ACT Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 11
Woden
ACT 2606</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/05/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>ETH.4.17.092</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>13/04/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Elizabeth Webb</name>
      <address>Calvary Public Hospital
Haydon Drive
Bruce
ACT 2617</address>
      <phone>+61 412 959 294 and +61 2 6201 6190</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>elizabeth.webb@calvary-act.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Elizabeth Webb</name>
      <address>Calvary Public Hospital
Haydon Drive
Bruce
ACT 2617</address>
      <phone>+61 412 959 294 and +61 2 6201 6190</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>elizabeth.webb@calvary-act.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Elizabeth Webb</name>
      <address>Calvary Public Hospital
Haydon Drive
Bruce
ACT 2617</address>
      <phone>+61 412 959 294 and +61 2 6201 6190</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>elizabeth.webb@calvary-act.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Elizabeth Webb</name>
      <address>Calvary Public Hospital
Haydon Drive
Bruce
ACT 2617</address>
      <phone>+61 412 959 294 and +61 2 6201 6190</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>elizabeth.webb@calvary-act.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>