<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367428">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/11/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/12/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001253695</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Randomised Placebo Controlled Study of Superior Hypogastric Nerve Blockade (SHNB) for Post-Operative Pain Management in Patients Undergoing Uterine Artery Embolisation for Symptomatic Uterine Fibroids.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomised Placebo Controlled Study of Superior Hypogastric Nerve Blockade (SHNB) for Post-Operative Pain Management in Patients Undergoing Uterine Artery Embolisation for Symptomatic Uterine Fibroids.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1164-0753</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Uterine fibroids</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other reproductive health and childbirth disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Post recruitment, patients will be streamed into one of two treatment arms prior to uterine artery embolisation; superior hypogastric nerve block (SHNB) using bupivacaine 0.5% plus adrenaline at a dose rate of 0.5mg per kilogram body weight, or placebo retroperitoneal injection (normal saline). 

Local anaesthetic will be infiltrated to a subumbilical site and either bupivacaine 0.5% plus adrenaline or a placebo (normal saline) will then be injected into the retroperitoneum using a 22g Chiba needle. X-ray confirmation of the landmarks (junction of L5 and S1) will be obtained prior to injection and aspiration through the Chiba needle will be performed to confirm extravascular placement of the needle. Technical success of SHNB will be defined as spread of contrast plus local anaesthetic anterior to the vertebral body of L5. </interventions>
    <comparator>All patients will receive a retroperitoneal injection of either bupivicaine 0.5% + adrenaline (treatment group) or normal saline (placebo). The group receiving placebo retroperitoneal injection of normal saline will act as the control group.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean postoperative pain intensity measured with a 10 point Visual Analogue Scale (VAS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at 0, 2, 4, 6, 8 and 24 hours post procedure </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to suitability for discharge, measured by a Modified Post-anaesthetic discharge scoring system (MPADSS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at at 10 hours post procedure</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient satisfaction with analgesia, procedure and quality of recovery at 6 weeks post procedure  measured with a 10 point VAS</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks post procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cumulative opioid requirement (measured via reference to Abbot (Trademark) Gemstar (Trademark) PCA machine).</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 hours post procedure (at time of PCA removal)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Opioid related side effects (including pruritis, nausea and vomiting) measured with 10 point VAS and the total amount of administered anti-emetic medication</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours post procedure (at time of discharge)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient experience and symptom burden measured by validated tools including:
* Modified Post-Anaesthetic Discharge Scoring System (MPADSS)
* Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) for pain and nausea assessment
* Patient Satisfaction Survey (also using VAS)
* Edmonton Symptom Assessment Scale (ESAS)
* Decision Regret Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours post procedure (at time of discharge)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>* Diagnosis of symptomatic leiomyomata and referred for UAE; 
* Normal renal function or pre-hydration;
* No allergy to contrast media or pre-treatment.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>* Viable pregnancy;
* Active infection;
* Known or suspected pelvic malignancy;
* Previous UAE (as increased uterine ischaemia);
* Contrast allergy;
* Allergy/intolerance to one or more of the treatment drugs;
* Allergy to cephalosporins;
* History of alcoholism/Intravenous drug use;
* Diagnosed hepatic disease;
* Renal insufficiency;
* Acute pelvic infection/ Pelvic inflammatory disease;
* Endometriosis;
* Adenomyosis.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients referred for UAE to Prof Ken Thomson, A/Prof Stuart Lyon or Dr Jim Koukounaras, the study investigators, will be considered for the study. 

Patients fulfilling the study criteria will be informed about the study during their initial consultation and will be given a Participant Information and Consent Form to take with them. The potential participants will be told to discuss the study with their referring GP/Gynaecologist and their family and to contact the study coordinators if they decide to volunteer for the study.  Consent will be obtained by the study coordinators.
If patients choose to participate, they will be required to sign a consent form. 

The placebo (normal saline only) and bupivacaine + adrenaline injections will be pre-randomised by The Alfred’s clinical trials pharmacy. The randomisation code will only be revealed by the clinical trial pharmacy to the investigators after the last patient has been recruited and their procedure completed .</concealment>
    <sequence>Pre-randomisation of placebo and bupivicaine + adrenaline for retroperitoneal injection will be performed by pharmacy prior to SHNB being performed.
Sequence will be generated by simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation).
Investigators will be unaware of the treatment group allocation until the conclusion of the trial.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Data from a previous UAE pain management study conducted at the Alfred Hospital was used to estimate the sample size. In a randomised controlled study of pre-emptive oxycodone with PCA for pain management post UAE we found that in the control group the mean pain VAS at 6 hours and at discharge (24 hours) was 3.2 mm and 1.3 mm respectively (20% effective difference). 
With 180 subjects per group this study should have an 80% power to detect a difference in a continuously normally distributed outcome equivalent to 1/2 standard deviation with a two-sided p-value of 0.05.

Data analysis will involve confirmation of data characteristic followed by appropriate testing. Parametric data will be analysed with student t-testing, while non-parametric variables will be analysed using Wilcoxon Rank Sum testing. Binomial data will be analysed using Chi Squared or Fishers Exact testing as appropriate. P &lt;0.05 will be considered significant.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/12/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>360</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3181 - Windsor</postcode>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Ken Thomson</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Alfred Hospital
55 Commercial Rd Prahran 
Victoria 3004</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Alfred Hospital Research Trusts Small Projects Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Alfred Hospital
55 Commercial Rd Prahran 
Victoria 3004</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>A/Prof Stuart Lyon</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The Avenue Hospital
40 The Avenue, Windsor 
Victoria 3181</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To determine if injection of local anaesthesia into the area surrounding the pelvic nerves (superior hypogastric nerve block, or SHNB) is useful in reducing pain in patients who have undergone uterine artery embolisation (UAE).

Patients will receive an injection into the retroperitoneal space (which contains the nerves supplying the pelvic organs) immediately before the UAE. It may contain either local anaesthetic or a placebo (normal saline).

After the procedure the amount of pain relief needed by the patient and any associated side effects (e.g. nausea, vomiting) will be recorded throughout the patient's stay.

At outpatient follow up in 6 weeks, overall satisfaction with both the UAE and the pain relief obtained will be recorded.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Alfred Hospital
55 Commercial Rd Prahran 
Victoria 3004</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/07/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>389/13</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/09/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Kenneth Thomson</name>
      <address>Alfred Hospital
55 Commercial Rd Prahran 
Victoria 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 03 9076 2536</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.thomson@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Helen Kavnoudias</name>
      <address>Alfred Hospital
55 Commercial Rd Prahran 
Victoria 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 0413027175</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>h.kavnoudias@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Helen Kavnoudias</name>
      <address>Alfred Hospital
55 Commercial Rd Prahran 
Victoria 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 0413027175</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>h.kavnoudias@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Su-Ling Lai</name>
      <address>Alfred Hospital
55 Commercial Rd Prahran 
Victoria 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 0417533986</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sllai03@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>