<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373449">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/08/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/08/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001222336p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Validating the impact of an alternative, shared-care pathway on waiting times for patients referred for eye examination to a public ophthalmology clinic</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of a Collaborative Ophthalmic System for Effective Triage (COSET) for patients referred to a public ophthalmology clinic on waiting times </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1200-4657 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>COSET</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>eye health</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients on the waiting list for "next available" appointment at the Prince of Wales Hospital (POWH) Eye Clinic associated with a current wait time of over 12 months, will be offered an alternative appointment at the Centre for Eye Health (CFEH) as part of an optometry-ophthalmology shared-care arrangement within 4-6 weeks.

The intervention will be delivered face to face in the form of a single clinical appointment at CFEH. Appointments will be delivered by specially trained, therapeutically endorsed optometrists and clinical data will be reviewed by an ophthalmologist from the POWH prior to completion of a clinical report and patient management recommendation. Duration most commonly will cover 1-2 hours, but exact time frame and procedures are personalised depending on the reason for referral for eye examination by the primary care provider.

All examinations will include physical inspection of the eye by an optometrist, visual acuity testing, and slit lamp examination. Other tests will be specific to the specific reason for referral and may include gonioscopy, measurement of the intraocular pressure, central corneal thickness, or visual function. Individual structures of the eye may be imaged using fundus photography, corneal topography, scheinpflug imaging, optical coherence tomography, autofluorescence imaging or ultrasound biomicroscopy.</interventions>
    <comparator>Patients on the waiting list for "next available" appointment at the Prince of Wales Hospital (POWH) Eye Clinic associated with a current wait time of over 12 months, will be enrolled in the clinical trial as control group.

The intervention will be delivered face to face in the form of a single clinical appointment delivered by ophthalmologists at the POWH Eye Clinic. Duration most commonly will cover 1-2 hours, but exact time frame and procedures are personalised depending on the reason for referral for eye examination by the primary care provider.

All examinations will include physical inspection of the eye by an ophthalmologist, visual acuity testing, and slit lamp examination. Other tests will be specific to the specific reason for referral and may include gonioscopy, measurement of the intraocular pressure, central corneal thickness, or visual function. Individual structures of the eye may be imaged using fundus photography, corneal topography, scheinpflug imaging, optical coherence tomography, autofluorescence imaging or ultrasound biomicroscopy.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>T-test analysis of wait times, defined as difference between receipt of patient referral and eye examination appointment date) for patients referred for eye examination to the Prince of Wales Hospital Eye Clinic or the Centre for Eye Health obtained from medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>two year after trial commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>T-test analysis to assess changes in the lead time between referrals received for eye examinations at the Prince of Wales Hospital Eye Clinic to establishing a patient care plan obtained from clinical records 6, 12, 18, and 24 months after trial commencement in comparison to baseline</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6, 12, 18, and 24 months after trial commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mann-Whitney U-test to assess proportion of appointments at the Prince of Wales Hospital Eye Clinic that do not require ophthalmology care obtained from clinical triage outcomes 6, 12, 18, and 24 months after trial commencement in comparison to baseline</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 6, 12, 18, and 24 months after trial commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) Valid referral for eye examination to the Prince of Wales Hospital Eye Clinic
2) Waiting for a "next available" appointment associated with current wait time of over 12 months in response to the referral
3) Suitable for a potential shared-care appointment as assessed by a senior ophthalmology trainee
4) Written, informed consent provided </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) Insufficient information on the patient referral for appropriate triage
2) Patients with significant neurological or systemic co-morbidities that constitute an immediate medical or ophthalmic emergency, or need to be referred to other specialties or immediately admitted to hospital
3) Patients triaged for an appointment at the Prince of Wales Hospital Eye Clinic other than "next available"
4) No written, informed consent provided</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using coin tossing</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Less than 10% of patients on the waiting list for "next available" appointment at the Prince of Wales Hospital Eye Clinic are seen within 12 months of receiving their referral. A decrease in wait time (and subsequently lead time to the patient care plan) from 90% to 50% would require 52 patients in each arm at a 99% confidence level at 99% power.

Increasing the sample size to 100 patients in each arm will allow us to calculate false positive and negative rates for potentially vision threatening or severe conditions that require ophthalmological review either immediately or within up to one week at 99% specificity and sensitivity with a confidence interval of 94.55% to 99.97.

Paired t-test will be applied to calculate the correlation between patient management initiated based on the initial referral and recommended based on patient outcome. Descriptive statistics will be applied to investigate patient satisfaction at either side using results from obtained survey data. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/09/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/09/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Prince of Wales Private Hospital - Randwick</hospital>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Centre for Eye Health, Unversity of New South Wales</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of New South Wales
Rupert Myers Building (south wing)
Barker Street, Gate 14
Kensington NSW 2052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Centre for Eye Health, Unversity of New South Wales</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The University of New South Wales
Rupert Myers Building (south wing)
Barker Street, Gate 14
Kensington NSW 2052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Prince of Wales Hospital Eye Clinic</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 4, High Street Building,
The Prince of Wales Hospital,
High Street, Randwick,
Sydney, NSW 2031 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Prince of Wales Hospital Eye Clinic</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Level 4, High Street Building,
The Prince of Wales Hospital,
High Street, Randwick,
Sydney, NSW 2031 </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In the face of the progressive disease burden associated with an ageing population, public hospitals must face the challenge of providing cost-effective, accessible, and timely care for patients with chronic disorders, especially so that the need for inpatient care is reduced. Within the eye health care sector, shared care models are increasingly utilized to facilitate comprehensive care for all patients. These models integrate optometrists in the care of patients with chronic stable conditions, or in need of long-term at-risk disease monitoring, thus effectively focusing specialist and hospital care for patients with urgent or complicated conditions. Establishing effective triage and collaborative care schemes, however, requires careful validation to ensure that implemented alternative care pathways improve patient management.

The Centre for Eye Health (CFEH) in Sydney has already established active collaboration with the Prince of Wales Hospital (PoWH) eye clinic resulting in a shared-care glaucoma management clinic. The knowledge and expertise gained from this collaboration provide the foundation to initiate the current project aiming at an expansion of the current eye health care model to patients waiting for over 12 months to be seen at the PoWH eye clinic. Successful outcomes will result in significantly reduced wait times for patients leading to timely implementation of patient care plans and improved efficiency with regard to eye health care specialist appointments within the public health system.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>SESLHD Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Support Office
G71, East Wing
Edmund Blacket Building
Prince of Wales Hospital
Randwick NSW 2031 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/08/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Barbara Zangerl</name>
      <address>Centre for Eye Health
The University of New South Wales
Rupert Myers Building (south wing)
Barker St, Gate 14
Kensington NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8115 0793</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 8115 0799</fax>
      <email>bzangerl@cfeh.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Barbara Zangerl</name>
      <address>Centre for Eye Health
The University of New South Wales
Rupert Myers Building (south wing)
Barker St, Gate 14
Kensington NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8115 0793</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 8115 0799</fax>
      <email>bzangerl@cfeh.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Barbara Zangerl</name>
      <address>Centre for Eye Health
The University of New South Wales
Rupert Myers Building (south wing)
Barker St, Gate 14
Kensington NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8115 0793</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 8115 0799</fax>
      <email>bzangerl@cfeh.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Barbara Zangerl</name>
      <address>Centre for Eye Health
The University of New South Wales
Rupert Myers Building (south wing)
Barker St, Gate 14
Kensington NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8115 0793</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 8115 0799</fax>
      <email>bzangerl@cfeh.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>