<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336465">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/01/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/02/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000120976</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparison of myofascial trigger point therapy to stretching and strengthening for maintaining or increasing muscle length in muscles with spasticity.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The application of Myofascial Trigger Point therapy in maintaining or increasing muscle length in muscles with spasticity, influencing the need for Botox and functional ability in School Aged Children with Spastic Cerebral Palsy (GMFCS level I-III).</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1119-2475</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Spastic Cerebral Palsy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The research project will be divided into the application of two therapy blocks of 12 weeks, allowing the study to be a cross-over study. Participants will not have a break between blocks. One block will consist of stretching, strengthening and massage. The other block will consist of stretching, strengthening, massage and the application of myofascial trigger point therapy. Myofascial trigger points will be applied once a week by a qualified Physiotherapist and daily by the parents/carer for approximately 15minutes. Stretching, strengthening and massage will be carried out daily for a further 15 minutes. Measurements will be taken pre and post each block and will include, muscle length, quality of life survey, functional tests (ie hopping, single leg stand and heel-toe walk) and the need for botox. A follow up assessment will also be carried out 6 weeks later.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control treatment will consist of a routine therapy block - stretching, strengthening and soft tissue massage. Each participant will undergo this control treatment for 12 weeks either prior or after the application of myofascial trigger points.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The need for botox application. This will be measured by the consulting physician who regularly measures muscle length and function and decides upon the need for this form of treatment. The measure of this outcome will be based on the incidence for botox prescription.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post each block of treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Muscle length of gastroc and soleus. These measurements will be based on goniometer measurements taken by a blinded therapist pre and post each block of treatment. Photos will also be taken of standing muscle length pre and post each block of treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre and Post each block of treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life surveys will be taken pre and post each block of treatment. These will be completed by the parent/carer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre and post each block of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional tests using part of the Movement ABC. Tests will include hopping, single leg stand and heel-toe walking.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre and Post each block of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Children aged between 5 and 12 years
Cerebral Palsy GMFCS level I and III with muscle spasticity
Parent and Doctor consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>12</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>None required.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>We can identify potential participants from the pool of clients at Therapy ACT and approach them to consider participation in the project at the end of their therapy sessions. If they are interested we will send a letter describing the project and invite them to apply. Most of the screening can be done before approaching the clients. Those that respond will then be considered for the project. Following this, names of all potential candidates will be placed in bag and 20 names will be pulled out for participation. Following selection of the 20 candidates, participants will be randomized into groups using permuted block randomization from a computer random number generator, with the randomization result sealed in an envelope. Once a participant has arrived for the pre assessment the envelope will be opened to determine which group they are selected into.</concealment>
    <sequence>To divide the 20 participants into 2 groups will use a permuted block randomization on a computer to generate a number. This will be sealed in an envelope and the envelope opened at the participants pre-assessment.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Therapy ACT</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Cnr Weingarth and Blackwood Terrace Holder 2611 ACT</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The main aims of this research project are to compare the effects of routine therapy, considered as the combination of stretching, strengthening, casting and the application of botox, to the proposed therapy consisting only of stretching, strengthening and myofascial trigger point therapy. The effects of weekly myofascial trigger point therapy alongside stretching and strengthening will be measured in a group of children aged between 4 and 12 years with muscle spasticity. It is proposed that the study will be small due to limited resources, but the intention is to publish the results for further research in this area.

We hypothesise that myofascial trigger point therapy when applied to spastic muscles is successful at maintaining or increasing muscle length.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>NEAF</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra  ACT  2601</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/07/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/02/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Michelle Elmitt</name>
      <address>Cnr of Weingarth and Blackwood Terrace Holder 2611 ACT</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 6205 1275</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michelle.elmitt@act.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Michelle Elmitt</name>
      <address>Cnr of Weingarth and Blackwood Terrace Holder 2611 ACT</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6105 1275</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michelle.elmitt@act.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Nikki Mitchell</name>
      <address>Cnr of Weingarth and Blackwood Terrace Holder 2611 ACT</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6205 1275</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nicola.mitchell@act.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>