<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365210">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/10/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/10/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001191785</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Pilot, Randomised, Blinded, Feasibility, Safety and Biochemical and Physiological Efficacy Study of Terlipressin versus Placebo in Hypotensive Sepsis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Pilot, Randomised, Blinded, Feasibility, Safety and Biochemical and Physiological Efficacy Study of Terlipressin versus Placebo in Hypotensive Sepsis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Sepsis STEP</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hospitalised patients with sepsis-associated hypotension</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study will recruit patients in the Emergency Department (ED), in the Intensive care unit (ICU) and in the wards after a Medical Emergency Team (MET) review.  Eligible patients will be randomised to receive either:
- Terlipressin at 0.85 mg IV push, OR
- Placebo (Normal Saline 0.9%)

The study treatments will be macroscopically identical and will be supplied in identical 5 ml syringes prepared by ICU research.

The initial treatment dose will be 0.425 mg (half dose).  If haemodynamic goals are achieved after one hour the participant will only receive the study drug at half dose.  However, if the haemodynamic goals are not met after one hour the remaining half dose will be administered and the participant will receive the full-dose (0.85 mg) of the study drug.

In all instances treatment will be given every six hours until resolution of hypotension or to a maximum of 24 hours using the individualised patient-responsive dose.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Normal saline 0.9% (as placebo)</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean arterial blood pressure via continuous invasive monitoring (arterial line)</outcome>
      <timepoint>one hour after intravenous drug administration</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The amount of intravenous fluid given in the first hour after after intravenous drug administration as per fluid balance chart</outcome>
      <timepoint>In the first hour after intravenous drug administration</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The amount of intravenous fluid given in the 6 hours after intravenous drug administration as per fluid balance chart</outcome>
      <timepoint>in the first 6 hours after intravenous drug administration</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The amount of intravenous fluid given in the 24 hours after intravenous drug administration as per fluid balance chart</outcome>
      <timepoint>in the first 24 hours after intravenous drug administration</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood creatinine levels as per hospital pathology analysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>assessed daily in the first 3 days after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of acute kidney injury based on creatinine according to risk, injury, failure, loss, end-stage (RIFLE) classification as per changes in blood creatinine levels as per hospital pathology level</outcome>
      <timepoint>assessed daily in the first 3 days after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The amount of vasopressor drug given in the first hour after intravenous drug administration as per fluid balance chart</outcome>
      <timepoint>In the first hour after intravenous drug administration</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The amount of vasopressor drug given in the 6 hours after intravenous drug administration as per fluid balance chart</outcome>
      <timepoint>In the first 6 hours after intravenous drug administration</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The amount of vasopressor drug given in the24 hours after intravenous drug administration as per fluid balance chart</outcome>
      <timepoint>In the first 24 hours after intravenous drug administration</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Patients aged 18 years or older
- Confirmed or suspected sepsis
presentation to the emergency department (ED) or activation of an urgent medical emergency team review or admission to the intensive care unit
Hypotension</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Pregnancy
- Death is considered imminent (within 24 hours)
- Known contraindications to terlipressin such as: severe peripheral vascular disease, Raynaud's phenomenon, Known allergy to terlipressin, Unstable angina, Recent myocardial infarction, Asthma.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The study will recruit such patients in the Emergency Department (ED), in the ICU and in the wards after a Medical Emergency Team review.  Eligible patients will be randomised to receive either:
- Terlipressin at 0.85 mg IV push, OR
- Placebo (Normal Saline 0.9%)

The study treatments will be macroscopically identical and will be supplied in identical 5 ml syringes prepared by ICU research.

The initial treatment dose will be 0.425 mg (half dose).  If haemodynamic goals are achieved after one hour the participant will only receive the study drug at half dose.  However, if the haemodynamic goals are not met after one hour the remaining half dose will be administered and the participant will receive the full-dose (0.85 mg) of the study drug.

In all instances treatment will be given every six hours until resolution of hypotension or to a maximum of 24 hours using the individualised patient-responsive dose.
</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomization will be by means of sealed envelopes with permuted blocks of variable size. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Outcomes will be compared after log transformation where appropriate. Comparisons will be made using t-test and ANOVA for repeated-measures or Wilcoxon rank-signed test and Kruskall-Wallis according to the underlying distribution for continuous data and Chi-square for categorical data. A Kaplan-Meier curve with log-rank test will be performed to further compare in-hospital mortality and rate of discharge home. Logistic regression analysis will also be performed to adjust for baseline imbalances.  Analysis will be on intention-to-treat.

Using data from previous studies, we estimate that a sample size of 18 patients in each group, will have a &gt;90% statistical power at an alpha of 0.05, to detect a clinically significant increase in mean arterial pressure of 10 mmHg to 70 mmHg at one hour after injection assuming a standard deviation of 10 mmHg. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>25/08/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <postcode>3084 - Banyule</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Anaesthesia Intensive Care Trust Fund</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>c/o Department of Intensive Care
Austin Hospital
145 Studley Road
Heidelberg, VIC, 3084</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Anaesthesia Intensive Care Trust Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>c/o Department of Intensive Care
Austin Hospital
145 Studley Road
Heidelberg, VIC, 3084</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The management of patients who have serious infection and a low blood pressure is complex and includes making sure that the circulation is stable, safe and optimal in terms of blood flow to vital organs. This is called resuscitation. The best way to deliver resuscitation is uncertain. However, it typically includes the use of fluids given though a vein and drugs to help increase blood pressure. 

Drugs to increase blood pressure can be useful but those available either have a short duration of action (minutes) or can only be given though a large vein.  As the need for drugs to increase blood pressure can last for hours or even days, this means that a special catheter needs to be inserted for such treatment into a large central vein like the jugular (neck) vein. This carries risks, requires special expertise and takes time. Thus, potentially helpful treatment is often delayed. As a consequence, blood pressure may remain undesirably low for more than an hour and/or the patient may be given large amounts of fluids instead, which can be undesirable. More recently, however, a medication called terlipressin has been developed to help liver patients with low blood pressure and worsening kidney function. Terlipressin can be given as a single dose injection through any hand or arm vein and can increase blood pressure for up to 6 hours. 

Terlipressin offers the opportunity to improve blood pressure management in patients with serious infection. However, because terlipressin has only been used to support blood pressure in this way in liver patients, we do not know how effective it would be in patients with infection. In this study we aim to test whether, in patients with infection and low blood pressure, terlipressin is more effective than placebo (dummy injection) at restoring blood pressure and whether such treatment changes the amount of fluid given and kidney function.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office for Research
Austin Hospital
145 Studley Road
Heidelberg VIC 3084</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/03/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/11/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/365210-HREC13Austin258(Prot and PICF's)OOS - Amendment Single Site  - ethics &amp; ....pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Rinaldo Bellomo</name>
      <address>Department of Intensive Care
Austin Hospital
145 Studley Road
Heidelberg VIC 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9494 5992</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9496 3932</fax>
      <email>rinaldo.bellomo@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Rinaldo Bellomo</name>
      <address>Department of Intensive Care
Austin Hospital
145 Studley Road
Heidelberg VIC 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 5992</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9496 3932</fax>
      <email>rinaldo.bellomo@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Rinaldo Bellomo</name>
      <address>Department of Intensive Care
Austin Hospital
145 Studley Road
Heidelberg VIC 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 5992</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9496 3932</fax>
      <email>rinaldo.bellomo@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Glenn Eastwood</name>
      <address>Department of Intensive Care
Austin Hospital
145 Studley Road
Heidelberg VIC 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 4835</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9496 3932</fax>
      <email>glenn.eastwood@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>