<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369007">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/07/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/08/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000847516</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An investigation of the relationships between pain, physical activity, sleep and mood in people with Parkinson's disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Do people with Parkinson's disease respond to exercise with the same exercise-induced analgesia response as the general older population?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Parkinson's disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Parkinson's disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All participants will be asked to perform one short bout of isometric upper limb exercise, in order to assess exercise induced analgesia/hyperalgesia. First, the participants maximal voluntary force will be determined by asking them to maximally contract their muscles against a force transducer. This procedure will be repeated two more times with the participants maximal voluntary contraction (i.e. 1RM) being the greatest force produced during the 3 trials. Following a short rest, participants will be asked to sustain an isometric contraction at a moderate intensity (i.e. 40% 1RM) for as long as possible with a maximum time of 3 minutes.

Following the assessment session, participants with PD will be asked to wear an activity and sleep monitoring device on their wrist and their waist for 7 consecutive days.</interventions>
    <comparator>The exercise-induced analgesia/hyperalgesia response (i.e. any change in pressure pain threshold following exercise) of the participant's with Parkinson's disease will be compared to that of healthy age and gender-matched participants.

The healthy age and gender-matched participants will not be required to wear the activity and sleep monitors.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pressure pain threshold measured with a pressure algometer will be collected for all participants.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Collected immediately before and after performing isometric exercise, at the assessment session.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain will be assessed using the Brief Pain Inventory, which assesses pain severity and the impact of pain on daily activities in the past week. This will be collected for people with PD who experience pain.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Collected once - at the assessment session before performing the isometric exercise.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Pain Self-Efficacy Questionnaire assesses how confident people are that they can do their daily activities despite any pain they have and will be collected for people with PD who experience pain.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Collected once - at the assessment session before performing the isometric exercise.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Incidental and Planned Exercise Questionnaire will be used to measure physical activity. It is a self-report questionnaire that covers the frequency and duration of several levels of planned and incidental physical activity in the previous 3 months in older people. It assesses the level of physical activity relating to both basic and more demanding activities. This will be collected for all participants with PD.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Once - at the assessment session</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index will be used to assess sleep quality for the previous month, and will be collected for all participants with PD.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Once - at the assessment session</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Epworth Sleepiness Scale will be used to assess day time sleepiness and will be collected for all participants with PD.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Once - at the assessment session</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The REM Sleep Behaviour Disorder Questionnaire will be used to screen for REM sleep behaviour disorder and will be collected for all participants with PD.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Once - at the assessment session</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale is a self-report questionnaire for measuring anxiety and depression in the past 7 days and will be collected for all participants with PD.</outcome>
      <timepoint> Collected at the assessment session and at the conclusion of the 7 days of activity and sleep monitoring.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Actigraphy measures of physical activity intensity will be collected for all participants with PD.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured for 7 days while wearing the activity and sleep monitor.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Actigraphy measures of the percentage of time asleep while in bed from lights off to lights on (i.e. sleep efficiency) will be collected for all participants with PD.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured for 7 days while wearing the activity and sleep monitor</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Daily measure of pain severity (score out of 10) will be collected for all participants with PD.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured for 7 days while wearing the activity and sleep monitor.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Daily measures of physical activity recorded as a summary of activities undertaken through the day will be collected for all participants with PD.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured for 7 days while wearing the activity and sleep monitor, in order to verify activity monitor data.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Daily measures of sleep recorded as a description of the previous night's sleep will be collected for all participants with PD.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured for 7 days while wearing the activity and sleep monitor, to verify sleep monitor data.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Actigraphy measures of the number of steps taken will be collected for all participants with PD.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured for 7 days while wearing the activity and sleep monitor.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Actigraphy measures of the minutes of sleep between sleep onset and wake time (i.e. total sleep time) will be collected for all participants with PD.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured for 7 days while wearing the activity and sleep monitor.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Actigraphy measures of the minutes between lights off and first sleep episode (i.e. sleep latency) will be collected for all participants with PD.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured for 7 days while wearing the activity and sleep monitor.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Actigraphy measures of the minutes awake between sleep onset and wake time (wake after sleep onset) will be collected for all participants with PD.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured for 7 days while wearing the activity and sleep monitor.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Daily measure of pain interference with activity - score out of 10.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured for 7 days while wearing the activity and sleep monitor.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parkinson's disease severity will be measured with the Movement Disorders Society-sponsored Unified Parkinson's Disease Rating Scale for all participants with PD.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured once at the assessment session.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parkinson's disease -related quality of life will be measured with the PDQ-39 for all participants with PD.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured once at the assessment session.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Central Sensitisation Inventory (a screening instrument to identify people who may have central sensitivity syndrome) will be collected for all participants with PD.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured once at the assessment session.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The King's Pain Scale will be measured to collect background information about pain in participant's with PD. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured once at the assessment session before performing the isometric exercise.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Aged 40 years or over, living in the community.
Participants with Parkinson's disease will be required to have had no changes to their usual Parkinson's disease medications in the prior 2 weeks.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>People with neurological impairments other than those due to Parkinson's disease. 
People with substantial cognitive impairment (i.e. mini-mental state examination below 24)
People with pain due to a known radiculopathy (i.e. a compressed nerve of the spine) or another diagnosed chronic pain condition (e.g. fibromyalgia) that is likely to interfere with the evaluation of the persons safety and of the study outcome.
People with an upper limb problem which would preclude the upper limb isometric exercise.
People without Parkinson's disease who experience significant pain (i.e. pain of &gt;3/10 intensity for at least 2 days per week in the prior 3 months)
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Case control</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/08/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>28/08/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>5/12/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>4/07/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>85</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>50</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>11/07/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Sydney,
Parramatta Rd, NSW, Australia
2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The University of Sydney,
Parramatta Rd, NSW, Australia
2006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of this study is to investigate if people with Parkinson's disease have the usual reduction in pain threshold following exercise (i.e. exercise induced analgesia). We hypothesize that people with Parkinson's disease will have the usual exercise-induced analgesia response to exercise.

The secondary purpose is to investigate the relationships between measures of exercise-induced analgesia with pain, physical activity levels, sleep quality and mood in people with Parkinsons disease and the relationships between physical activity levels, sleep quality, mood and pain in people with Parkinsons disease. We hypothesize that increased physical activity, better sleep and better mood will be associated with a better exercise-induced analgesia response and with less pain in people with Parkinson's disease.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The University of Sydney,
Parramatta Rd,
NSW, Australia, 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/08/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2015/574</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/07/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Natalie Allen</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences,
The University of Sydney,
PO Box 170,
Lidcombe, NSW, 1825.</address>
      <phone>+61293519016</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>natalie.allen@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Natalie Allen</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences,
The University of Sydney,
PO Box 170,
Lidcombe, NSW, 1825.</address>
      <phone>+61293519016</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>natalie.allen@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Natalie Allen</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences,
The University of Sydney,
PO Box 170,
Lidcombe, NSW, 1825.</address>
      <phone>+61293519016</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>natalie.allen@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Natalie Allen</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences,
The University of Sydney,
PO Box 170,
Lidcombe, NSW, 1825.</address>
      <phone>+61293519016</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>natalie.allen@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>