<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373184">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/07/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001009303</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Action: PACT. Be Active. Online. A trial to promote physical activity in young people with cystic fibrosis. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial of a novel web-based intervention to promote physical activity participation in young people with cystic fibrosis. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Action: PACT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cystic Fibrosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human Genetics and Inherited Disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Cystic fibrosis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The aim of this project is to determine whether the use of an online program (ActivOnline  www.activonline.com.au) is more effective than usual care at improving physical activity participation in young people with Cystic Fibrosis (CF) after an inpatient admission to hospital. People who agree to take part in the study will be randomly allocated to one of two groups. The intervention group will use the ActivOnline program, via the internet, as well as receive usual care. Usual care will comprise provision of details for an online information source regarding physical activity participation and physical activity targets for children and young adults (http://www.nhs.uk/Livewell/fitness/Pages/physical-activity-guidelines-for-young-people.aspx) as well as activity and exercise guidance, as indicated, as part of their routine clinical care on hospital discharge. ActivOnline was developed in accordance of the principles of motivational interviewing and has been used to promote physical activity participation in older adults with chronic respiratory disease. Those allocated to the ActivOnline group will be provided with a unique logon and password to access the ActivOnline program and will be asked to record their daily physical activity and exercise using the secure portal. When logging onto ActivOnline they will be prompted to set goals, will record their PA or exercise using a pedometer or other device of their choice and will regularly enter data about that will be displayed graphically so they can see their progress.. The messaging tab on the Home screen is there for communication between researchers and participants. For example participants will be able to send to questions at any time and clinicians will be able to remind participants to review their goals each week.  The intervention phase will last for 12 weeks during which time participants will have access to the ActivOnline program to facilitate their participation in exercise and seek support in reaching their activity goal. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants randomised to the usual care group will be provided with details for an online information source regarding physical activity participation and physical activity targets for children and young adults (http://www.nhs.uk/Livewell/fitness/Pages/physical-activity-guidelines-for-young-people.aspx). These guidelines are consistent with Australian Department of Health recommendations for daily physical activity participation. Participants in the control group will receive activity and exercise guidance, as indicated, as part of their routine clinical care on hospital discharge.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in physical activity participation objectively measured via accelerometry
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline
At the end of the intervention phase
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in exercise capacity as measured by the Modified Shuttle Test (MST)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline
At the end of the intervention phase
3 months post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in lung function as measured by Forced Expiratory Volume in one second (FEV1)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline
At the end of the intervention phase
3 months post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in health related quality of life as assessed by the Cystic Fibrosis Questionnaire (CFQ-R)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline
At the end of the intervention phase
3 months post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline
At the end of the intervention phase
3 months post intervention
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline
At the end of the intervention phase
3 months post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to first hospital admission, by medical record review</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months post end of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in the Centre for Epidemiological Studies - Depression (CES-D) scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline
At the end of the intervention phase
3 months post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in physical activity participation self reported by the Habitual Activity Estimation Scale (HAES)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline
At the end of the intervention phase
3 months post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in physical activity participation objectively measured via accelerometry</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline 
3 months post intervention </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of hospital inpatient days by medical record review</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months post end of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Confirmed diagnosis of cystic fibrosis
Hospital inpatient admission (including hospital in the home) for intravenous antibiotic therapy for a respiratory cause
Able to provide informed consent
Able to access the internet via computer or mobile device</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>12</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>24</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Presence of severe co-morbidity limiting mobilisation or physical activity participation
Previous lung transplantation
Pregnancy</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by computer</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated, block randomisation with stratification for:
1) site 
2) whether or not the participant is enrolled in fulltime schooling (primary or secondary) </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Not applicable</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A mixed model within (time) and between (group) ANOVA will be conducted to investigate change across all outcome measures. Linear regression modelling will be used to investigate impact of demographic and baseline measures on the change in physical activity (PA). Sample size was based on physical activity PA participation measured post hospitalisation in our population of young adults with CF. A difference of 20 mins/day between groups in PA would correspond to achievement of accepted activity targets (&gt; or = 150 mins/week). This assumes a standard deviation of 26 mins/week with a power of 80% and a significance level of p&lt;0.05. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/09/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/02/2020</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/05/2021</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>TAS,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
    <hospital>The Royal Childrens Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Clayton campus - Clayton</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Hobart Hospital - Hobart</hospital>
    <postcode>3004 - Prahran </postcode>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
    <postcode>7000 - Hobart</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>La Trobe University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>La Trobe University 
c/- La Trobe/Alfred Clinical School
Level 4. The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Road
Melbourne 
Victoria 3004</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>United Kingdom CF Trust</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>2nd Floor
One Aldgate 
London EC3N 1RE</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United Kingdom</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Cystic Fibrosis (CF) is a complex, progressive, life-limiting disease that predominantly affects children and young adults. Flare-ups of CF lung disease are common in people with this condition and often lead to admission to hospital and decline in lung capacity, imposing considerable burden on patients, their families and the healthcare system.  
Physical activity (PA) participation is a low-cost, easily accessible treatment option that has the potential to reduce the impact and progression of chronic lung disease in CF and may help reduce flare ups of lung disease. However uptake and adherence to PA and exercise rehabilitation programs by young people with CF is poor. 
Advances in Internet technology and accessibility have made it possible for people to receive specialist medical care and rehabilitation therapy without attending the hospital. By using a secure website, readily accessible on any smartphone, tablet, laptop or computer it is possible for young people with CF to track their PA participation and receive feedback  at any time and place of their choosing. 
The aim of this project is to determine whether use of an online program to track PA participation and provide feedback, is more effective than usual care at improving PA participation, exercise capacity and quality of life, and prolonging the time to next hospital admission. People who agree to take part in the study will be randomly allocated to use the online program via the Internet, or to usual post-hospital care. 
At the beginning and end of the 12 weeks of the intervention phase, and at 3-months post completion of the intervention period, all participants will undergo measurements of PA participation, exercise capacity and health status. At 12 months- post completion of the intervention, hospital medical records will be reviewed to determine the frequency of hospital admission and number of hospital days. 
It is hypothesized that:
1.	The web-based intervention will improve uptake and participation in PA by young people with CF.
2.	The web-based intervention to increase PA will lead to improvements in exercise capacity, lung function, quality of life, anxiety and depression and sleep quality in young people with CF and reduced health care utilisation for this group in the 12 months post intervention. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Ethics and Research Governance
Old Baker Building, Level 1
The Alfred
55 Commercial Road
Melbourne 
Victoria 3004</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/02/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/Alfred/188(Alfred 7/17)</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/01/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Anne Holland</name>
      <address>La Trobe University/Alfred Health Clinical School
Level 4, The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Road
Melbourne 
Vic 3004</address>
      <phone>+61394796744</phone>
      <fax>+61395332104</fax>
      <email>a.holland@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Bev Eldridge</name>
      <address>La Trobe University/Alfred Health Clinical School
Level 4, The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Road
Melbourne 
Vic 3004</address>
      <phone>+61394791333</phone>
      <fax>+61395332104</fax>
      <email>b.eldridge@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Anne Holland</name>
      <address>La Trobe University/Alfred Health Clinical School
Level 4, The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Road
Melbourne 
Vic 3004</address>
      <phone>+61394796744</phone>
      <fax>+61395332104</fax>
      <email>a.holland@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Bev Eldridge</name>
      <address>La Trobe University/Alfred Health Clinical School
Level 4, The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Road
Melbourne 
Vic 3004</address>
      <phone>+61394791333</phone>
      <fax>+61395332104</fax>
      <email>b.eldridge@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>