<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83428">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/12/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/02/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000086268</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Single-Center, Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Dose-Escalating Study to Evaluate the Safety and Tolerability of KDF-07002 in Healthy, Adult Volunteers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Single-Center, Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Dose-Escalating Study to Evaluate the Safety and Tolerability of KDF-07002 in Healthy, Adult Volunteers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>This trial is to assess safety and tolerability of KDF-07002 in healthy adult males and dose not focus on any particular health condition or problem</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>KDF-07002 will be adminstered in the morning on day 1 of the study as a single intravenous infusion.  The doses in the study will be 0.013, 0.026, 0.053,
0.105, 0.158, 0.237, 0.356, 0.533, and 0.800 mL/kg of bodyweight.  Duration of infusion will be based on dose but should not exceed 1 hour.  Particiapnats will be observed for 48 hours in clinic, released with a followup visit ocurring on day 7.  Escalation of dose will proceed based on results of vital signs and clinical chemistry analyses.</interventions>
    <comparator>Single intravenous infusion of saline for injection based on the same volume as the active drug at the respective dose level (i.e. 0.013, 0.026, 0.053,
0.105, 0.158, 0.237, 0.356, 0.533, 0.800 mL/kg of bodyweight).</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and maximum tolerated dose of KDF 07002.  Safety assessments of participants will be performed by the Pricipal Investigators and Medical Monitors of the study based on vital signs, ECG, and clinical chemistry values.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants will be monitored in the clinical unit for 48 hours then released.  Particiapnts are requyired to return to the clinic on day 7 for follow-up assessment of ECG, vital signs, including blood pressure, heart rate, and respiratory rate measurements; a blood sample will be taken for clinical chemistry, hepatic profile, renal profile, hematology, and coagulation measures</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Whole blood samples will be taken for analysis of KDF-07002 to determine the Pharmacokinetic profile of KDF-07002.  Trained scientists will use special software to analyze the resutls to determine how quickly the KDF-07002 exits the bloodstream.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline, 5 minutes, 0.25, 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 8, 12, 24, and 48 hours after infusion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Be a male between the ages of 18 and 60 years, inclusive.
2. Be healthy and have an acceptable medical history (defined as individuals who in the view of the investigator are free from significant cardiac, pulmonary, gastrointestinal, hepatic, renal, hematological, neurological, infective, or psychiatric diseases and confirmed by medical history, physical examination, and laboratory tests).
3. Have readily accessible peripheral venous access sites for administration of clinical trial material and blood sampling.
4. Subjects who are sexually active must also agree to a reliable form of contraception during the study and for 30 days following administration of the study drug.
5. Have the ability to understand the requirements of the study, be willing to provide written informed consent as evidenced by signature on an informed consent document approved by the institutions Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC), and agree to abide by the study restrictions</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Have a known sensitivity to any imaging contrast agents
2. Be an intravenous drug user, user of any illicit drugs, or dependent on alcohol
3. Have participated in an investigational drug or device study within the past 30 days
4. Have donated blood or blood products within the past 30 days prior to pretreatment baseline
period.
5. Have had surgery or suffered injury involving significant blood loss within the past 45 days
prior to pretreatment baseline period.
6. Have any clinically significant abnormal laboratory test based on clinical chemistry, hepatic
profile, renal profile, hematology, or coagulation measures
7. Have epilepsy or a history of grand mal seizure
8. Have a red blood cell disorder such as hemoglobinopathies or anemia
9. Have asthma, Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease, Restrictive Pulmonary Disease or any
other allergic respiratory diseases
10. Have hepatic disease (liver function tests greater than 1.5 times the upper limit of normal)
11. Have renal impairment with serum creatinine &gt; 105 mmol/L and/or Glomerular Filtration Rate (GFR) &lt;60 mL/min.
12. Have splenic disorders such as hepatosplenomegally, splenomegally or splenectomy
13. Have a history of pancreatitis
14. Have thrombocytopenia (&lt;150,000 platelets/mm3)
15. Have a blood-clotting disease including hemophilia or von Willebrand disease
16. Be currently taking warfarin (Coumadin®)
17. Have a known allergy to eggs</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Upon confirmation of all entry criteria, subjects will be assigned a randomisation number.  At the site, the investigator will use the next available subject number and retrieve the envelope for that subject number.  The pharmacist at the Study site will be able to determine, from the assigned subject number and the randomisation schedule provided, the correct Clinical Trial Material (CTM) vial to be used (active or placebo).</concealment>
    <sequence>The independent statistician will generate the randomisation schedule with the statistical software SAS.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/12/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>54</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Nucleus Network, Ltd.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>5th Floor, Burnet Tower, The Alfred Medical Research and Education Precinct (AMREP)
89 Commercial Road
Melbourne, Victoria 3004</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Kereos, Inc.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>4041 Forest Park Avenue
St. Louis, MO 63108</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a Phase 1a, single-center, randomized, double blind, placebo controlled, dose escalating study to evaluate the safety, tolerability, and Pharmacokinetic (PK) profiles of a single, intravenous dose of KDF-07002 in healthy adults.    Up to 54 subjects will be sequentially enrolled into one of nine cohorts.  Each cohort will be randomised to receive KDF 07002 or placebo at a 2:1 ratio.  All eligible subjects will be assigned an enrollment number in sequential order beginning with 01.  After completion of screening, eligible subjects will be randomized to receive KDF-07002 or placebo at a ratio of 2:1.  

Each cohort will receive KDF-07002 in the following ascending dose order: 0.013, 0.026, 0.053, 0.105, 0.158, 0.237, 0.356, 0.533, 0.800 mL/kg of bodyweight.  Safety and tolerability will be assessed immediately after dosing until Day 7.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Alfred Hospital
55 Commercial Road
Melbourne  VIC  3004</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/11/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>121/08</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/04/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Peter Hodsman</name>
      <address>5th Floor, Burnet Tower, AMREP Precinct
89 Commercial Road
Melbourne, Victoria 3004</address>
      <phone>+61-(0)3-9076 8960</phone>
      <fax>+61-(0)3-9076 8940</fax>
      <email>p.hodsman@nucleusnetwork.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Peter Hodsman</name>
      <address>5th Floor, Burnet Tower, The Alfred Medical Research and Education Precinct (AMREP)
89 Commercial Road
Melbourne, Victoria 3004</address>
      <phone>+61-(0)3-9076 8960</phone>
      <fax>+61-(0)3-9076 8940</fax>
      <email>p.hodsman@nucleusnetwork.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Phillip M. Buckler</name>
      <address>4041 Forest Park Avenue
St. Louis, MO 63108</address>
      <phone>+(011) (1) (314) 633-1873</phone>
      <fax>+(011) (1) (314) 633-1878</fax>
      <email>pbuckler@kereos.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>