<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335900">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/09/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/09/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000775011</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Impact of routine screening and feedback on post-stroke depression</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In stroke patients with symptoms of depression, will automated feedback to clinicians from computerised depression screening, compared to no feedback, increase rates of identification and referral, and decrease depression at three month follow-up.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1116-7365</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>n/a</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All potentially eligible patients undergo computerised depression screening once.  Computerised screening involves administration of an individualised depression screen on a portable touchscreen computer, taking approximately 2-5 minutes, completed individually and in their own time in the presence of a research assistant.
  
Computerised screening begins with the Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ) 2 item version.  If scores on the PHQ2&gt;0, the person is asked the remaining 7 items of the PHQ9.  If total PHQ9 score &gt;4, the person is given a problem list adapted from the Distress Thermometer problem list, and is considered eligible for the randomised controlled trial (RCT; unless suicidal or severe symptoms are expressed - in this case their clinician is always informed about their symptoms).
All patients screened are provided with 1 page written feedback regarding the severity of depression symptoms, with contact details regarding relevant stroke and depression services.

If eligible for the RCT and allocated to the intervention condition, a written feedback sheet detailing severity of depression, endorsed items on the problem list, and follow up care options is automatically produced and given to the patient's treating clinician immediately following screening.</interventions>
    <comparator>Computerised screening of depression and feedback to patient alone (1 page written feedback regarding the severity of depression symptoms, with contact details regarding relevant stroke and depression services).  No written or verbal feedback is provided to the patient's treating clinician regarding results of the depression screening.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression identification, referral for mental health treatment or initiation of treatment (via file audit)</outcome>
      <timepoint>File audit of medical notes of the treating stroke/rehabilitation team between the depression screening appointment and 3 months post-screening follow-up.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression severity as measured by the Patient Health Questionnaire 9 (PHQ9)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 3 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diagnosis of Major Depressive Episode accoding to the Diagnositic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, 4th Edition (DSM-IV), using the Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-IV (SCID).</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Confirmed stroke (ischaemic, haemorraghic, other)
2. Current symptoms of depression (Patient Health Questionnaire 9 score of 5 or above)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Severe/suicidal symptoms (PHQ9 score of 20 or above, or a score of 1 or above on PHQ9 item 9, thoughts of self harm)
2. Unable to read English
3. Lacks capactity to provide informed consent (e.g. moderate-severe dementia or significant cognitive deficits)
4. Refusal
5. Unavailable for 3 month phone follow-up</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All consecutive potentially eligible patients attending the stroke and rehabilitation clinics will be invited to participate in computerised depression screening.  
Those with depression symptoms (not severe/suicidal) will be included in the intervention study and block randomised to the treatment or control condition. For patients in the treatment condition, the research assistant will provide the doctor feedback form to the clinicians.  Allocation will not be concealed from the research assistant.   
The Project Officer conducting the file audit and follow-up assessments will be blind to treatment allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>A block randomisation procedure will be used over a 6 month period.  Each month all patients seen will be allocated to either treatment or control conditions. Randomisation order will be computer generated and kept off site.  The research assistant will be informed of the randomisation allocation at the start of each month.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>13/09/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>156</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Newcastle</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University Drive
Callaghan, NSW, 2308</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Stroke Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 7, 461 Bourke Street
Melbourne VIC 3000
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Alyna Turner</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Heart Research Centre
Box 2137 Post Office
The Royal Melbourne Hospital
Victoria 3050</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The project will examine whether providing clinicians with feedback regarding depression symptoms, generated automatically following computerised depression screening, will result in higher rates of identification of depression, and treatment initation, and decrease rates of depression at 3 months post-screening.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Locked Bag No 1
New Lambton, NSW, 2305</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/06/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>10/05/19/5.06</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/04/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Alyna Turner</name>
      <address>Heart Research Centre
Box 2137 Post Office
The Royal Melbourne Hospital
Victoria 3050</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9326 8544</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 93265066</fax>
      <email>Alyna.turner@heartresearchcentre.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Alyna Turner</name>
      <address>Heart Research Centre
Box 2137 Post Office
The Royal Melbourne Hospital
Victoria 3050</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9326 8544</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 93265066</fax>
      <email>Alyna.turner@heartresearchcentre.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>