<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364100">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/04/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/04/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000465752</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Apolipoprotein E driven therapeutics for Alzheimers disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A study evaluating the effects of Apolipoprotein E driven therapeutics for Alzheimers disease</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1141-4103</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Alzheimer's Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Alzheimer's disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In brief the study is a 30 day bexarotene treatment  in very early Alzheimer's Disease (AD) and mild AD patients measuring;
1.brain beta-amyloid  burden using NAV4694-PET scans
2.cognition while on treatment and at 3 months post treatment.
Bexarotene is a US Government (FDA) approved anti-cancer drug, used to treat T-cell lymphoma. In Australia, bexarotene is not marketed or TGA approved.  Research studies using mice with AD have shown that bexarotene reduces amyloid plaque and improves mental function. 
For the study the visit schedule is 8 visits.   First visit is a screening visit and then Bexarotene is dispensed at the following baseline visit (one oral tablet of 150mg/m2 per day for 30 days). Whilst on the study drug there are 4 weekly visits then 2 follow-up visits; at 1 week and 3 months after treatment has ceased. Safety blood tests and cognition tests are performed at these visits and in total two PET scans. Participants will maintain a simple diary to indicate when the dose was taken and if there are any changes to other prescribed medications or condition. The diary is reviewed at each visit.</interventions>
    <comparator>NA- This is a single group study</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Brain ABeta burden as measured by NAV4694-PET scan</outcome>
      <timepoint>A baseline scan is taken and then at the completion of 30 days of treatment of bexarotene</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in cognition. 
Cognition is assessed through neuropsychological assessments where memory and attention tasks are completed. Assessments take 1-2 hours.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>The assessments will occur at screening, the last week of treatment then at 3 months post treatment. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Completion of the standard evaluation and fulfillment of the specific diagnostic criteria for very early Alzheimer's Disaease and mild Alzheimer's Disease. Also to be fluent in English; Age &gt;50; &gt;7 years of education; adequate visual and auditory acuity to complete neuropsychological testing;to have a reliable caregiver who is able to provide accurate information about the patients symptoms; 


</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>A negative brain PET scan;a lifetime history of schizophrenia, schizoaffective disorder, or treatment with ECT;recent history of drug or alcohol abuse/dependence; 
any significant disease or unstable medical condition that in the opinion of the investigators, could affect drug levels or neuropsychological testing. 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Twenty participants with very early AD or mild Alzheimers disease will be recruited from the Austin Health Memory Disorders Clinic and affiliated specialists with expertise in memory disorders. 
Very early AD and mild AD is defined for this study as subjective and objective evidence of cognitive decline with a composite episodic memory score more than 1 standard deviation below the age matched norm, minimental state examination (MMSE) score of greater than 22, Clinical Dementia Rating of 0.5 or 1, and a PET scan that is positive for brain amyloid.  
</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>20 participants are needed to achieve study objectives. This is a preliminary, exploratory study to determine if a larger and double blind, placebo controlled trial is warranted.
The hypotheses that bexarotene treatment reduces NAV retention over time will be tested by paired Students t-tests
The hypotheses that bexarotene treatment improves cognition will also be tested by paired Students t-tests.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Nuclear Medicine and Centre for PET Research Fund</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 1, Harold Stokes Building
Austin Hospital
Studley Rd
Heidelberg 3084</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Nuclear Medicine and Centre for Positron Emission Tomography (PET ) Research Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1, Harold Stokes Building
Austin Hospital
Studley Rd
Heidelberg VIC 3084</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The ApolipoproteinE-e4 allele is the most consistent genetic risk factor associated with sporadic Alzheimers Disease (AD). ApolipoproteinE has an important influence on beta-amyloid  clearance and recent studies have shown that while there are no differences in beta-amyloid production between healthy controls and sporadic AD patients, in the latter beta-amyloid clearance is reduced by 30%. Novel therapeutic approaches targeting beta-amyloid clearance are being tested. A single oral administration of bexarotene, an FDA approved anti-cancer drug, to a mouse model of AD resulted in enhanced clearance of soluble beta-amyloid in an ApoE-dependent manner and a &gt;50% reduction of beta-amyloid plaque area within just 72 hours. In vivo imaging of beta-amyloid pathology by positron emission tomography (PET) is facilitating research into causes, diagnosis and treatment of major dementias, such as Alzheimers disease (AD), where beta-amyloid plays a role. This project aims to use brain amyloid imaging NAV4694 PET scans, for the in vivo assessment of the effect of bexarotene treatment on beta-amyloid burden and its relation to cognition in very early AD and mild AD patients.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health, Heidelberg, Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 6 , Horold Stokes Building
Austin Hospital
studley Rd
Heidelberg, VIC 3084</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/05/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Christopher Rowe</name>
      <address>Level 1 Harold Stokes Building
Austin Hospital 
145 Studley Rd
Heidelberg VIC 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94965183</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christopher.rowe@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Robyn Veljanovski</name>
      <address>Level 1 Harold Stokes Building
Austin Hospital 
145 Studley Rd
Heidelberg VIC 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94963579</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>robyn.veljanovski@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Christopher Rowe</name>
      <address>Level 1 Harold Stokes Building
Austin Hospital 
145 Studley Rd
Heidelberg VIC 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94965183</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christopher.rowe@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Robyn Veljanovski</name>
      <address>Level 1 Harold Stokes Building
Austin Hospital 
145 Studley Rd
Heidelberg VIC 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94963579</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>robyn.veljanovski@austin.org.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>