<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83165">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/09/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/05/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000286246</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Weight Loss and Type 2 Diabetes: A prospective randomised controlled trial intervention study of best practice medical management versus the additional placement of the Lap-Band System in overweight patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Weight Loss and Type 2 Diabetes: A prospective randomised controlled trial intervention study of best practice medical management versus the additional placement of the Lap-Band System in overweight patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes Type 2</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Placement of the Lap-Band (Laparoscopic Adjustable Gastric Band) by surgery in overweight individuals in the Body Mass Index 25-30 range. This procedure is permanent and patients will be followed for two years after surgery.</interventions>
    <comparator>Best practice medical management (optimal standard therapy) is a program of optimal medical treatment. Advice from a diabetes educator and dietician regarding diet, weight loss, movement and exercise, and any behavioral changes will take place 3-monthly. A specialist endocrinologist will manage any medication necessary to control blood sugar levels, high blood pressure and other diabetes related conditions 3-monthly. This advice and education will take the form of one hour sessions 3-monthly for a total of 2 years. Patients with HbA1c&gt;7% at 9 months will be reviewed 6-weekly until 12 months</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Biochemical assessment of glycaemic control of type 2 diabetes (HbA1c, fasting glucose)</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 and 60 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of co-morbidity control including abnormalities of blood pressure, serum lipids and liver function (via measurement of liver enzymes concentrations)</outcome>
      <timepoint>months 3, 6, 9, 12 and 60</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resolution of diabetes (fasting and 2h glucose following 75g oral glucose &lt;7.1 and &lt;11.1 respectively)</outcome>
      <timepoint>months 12 and 60</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical measures related to metabolic syndrome (eg lipids, waist circumference, medication burden, BP)</outcome>
      <timepoint>months 3, 6, 9, 12 and 60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost effectiveness - via technical efficiency analysis, which will draw on both the primary data collections from the trial (costs of the intervention; change in weight; cases of diabetes resolved; change in functional status), as well as economic modelling.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 and 60 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weight loss will be measured by Excess weight lost in kilograms (EWL) or Body Mass Index (BMI) points lost</outcome>
      <timepoint>months 3, 6, 9, 12 and 60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>insulin and C-peptide response to 25g IV glucose</outcome>
      <timepoint>Months 12 and 60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Be between 18 and 65 years of age, 2. Have a body mass index greater than 25 and less than 30 kg/m2. 3. Have been diagnosed with type 2 diabetes in the last 5 years. 4. Be able to understand the options and study requirements and to comply with the requirements of each program. 5. Willing to be randomized.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	If there was lack of acceptance of the randomization process, 
2.	If there were a history of previous abdominal surgery which would potentially preclude laparoscopic placement of the band. 
3.	If there was a history of previous obesity surgery
4.	If there were any contraindication to LapBand (LAGB) placement.
5.	If there were medical issues which contra-indicated the application of either arm of the study.   These would include; acute myocardial infarction within the past 6 months, dementia, active psychosis, concurrent experimental drug use, pregnancy or intending to conceive in the next two years, lactation, illicit drug use, excessive alcohol intake, use of drugs known to affect body composition, cytotoxic drugs, internal malignancy, or major organ failure.
6.	Systemic lupus erythematosis or other auto-immune disease. 
7.	Direct hypothalamic damage as a cause of obesity.
8.	If they were unable to understand the risks, realistic benefits and compliance requirements of the Lap-Band intervention and conventional management of diabetes. 
9.	The patient had type 1 diabetes or diabetes was secondary to specific diseases such as haemachromatosis or chronic pancreatitis.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Initial recruitment into the study would be achieved by a general awareness campaign, which emphasized a study of weight loss on  type 2 diabetes in the overweight patient. Interested candidates would be provided with detailed information regarding the problems of diabetes and excess weight on at least two occasions along with detailed information of the two treatment arms of the study. 
The eligible patients will be randomly assigned to receive: 
(1) a continuing program of medical treatment which will have a conventional program of advice and education regarding eating and exercise and include conventional medical therapy for diabetes and associated conditions (Program 1) or: 
(2) the LAGB procedure as an additional intervention (Program 2).
Allocation was achieved via the use of sealed opaque envelopes with the letters A and B enclosed, which corresponded to either the treatment group or control group. This procedure was carried out by a data manager not involved with the study (in any other way)</concealment>
    <sequence>The random assignment will be computer generated</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>38</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Wellington Rd
Victoria 3800</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Monash University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Wellington Rd
Victoria 3800</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Centre for Obesity Research and Education</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Monash University Medical School
The Alfred Hospital
Commercial Rd
Melbourne, 3004
Victoria</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary aim of this proposal is to compare LAGB surgery with optimal medical therapy over the period of the 2-year trial. The hypothesis is LAGB provides better results.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Miss Kristine Egberts</name>
      <address>Centre for Obesity Research and Education (CORE)
School of Public Health &amp; Preventive Medicine
Monash University
The Alfred Hospital, Commercial Road
Melbourne Victoria 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9903 0686</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Kristine.Egberts@med.monash.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Miss Kristine Egberts</name>
      <address>Centre for Obesity Research and Education (CORE)
School of Public Health &amp; Preventive Medicine
Monash University
The Alfred Hospital, Commercial Road
Melbourne Victoria 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9903 0686</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Kristine.Egberts@med.monash.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Paul O'Brien</name>
      <address>Centre for Obesity Research and Education
Monash University
Level 6 The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Rd
Melbourne Vic 3004</address>
      <phone>+61422992891</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>paul.obrien@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>