<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365697">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/02/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/04/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000411640</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Post Anaesthesia N-Acetycysteine Cognitive Evaluation trial, investigating the potential for N-Acetylcysteine to reduce cognitive dysfunction following major elective non-cardiac surgery</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised controlled trial of N-Acetyl-Cysteine vs placebo for the prevention of Post Operative Cognitive Dysfunction in major elective non-cardiac surgery</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1152-5499 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>PANACEA</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Barwon Health HREC project number 13/111</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Post Operative Cognitive Dysfunction
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Surgical Stress Response</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Post Operative Mood Disorder</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Post surgical pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>N-Acetyl-Cysteine
600mg oral capsules
dosage regimen = 1200mg twice daily, commencing 1-2 hours prior to surgery, continuing for 4 days, with a resultant total dose of 9600mg
Adherence to be monitored by trial coordinators via daily patient visits, medication chart review, and clinical effect to be correlated with biomarker evidence of antioxidant action.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo
Oral starch capsules, matched in appearance
dosage regimen to match intervention group</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A between-groups difference in the severity of early Post-operative Cognitive Dysfunction (POCD) as measured by the psychomotor-attention composite score of the CogState Brief Battery, adjusted for baseline values. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Post Operative Day 7</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A between-groups difference on the individual tasks of the CogState Brief Battery</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post Operative Day 7</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A between-groups difference on the Repeatable Battery for the Assessment of Neuropsychological Status (RBANS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post Operative Day 7</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A between-groups difference on the Controlled Oral Word Association Test (COWAT)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post Operative Day 7</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A between-groups difference on Trail Making A &amp; B tasks</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post Operative Day 7</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A decrease in the severity of late POCD, as defined by between groups differences in scores within the neuropsychological test battery outlined above, adjusted for baseline values</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post operation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A decrease in the incidence of post-operative delirium, as measured by between groups differences in scores on the Confusion Assessment Method</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post Operative Days 2 and 7</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A decrease in mood disturbance, as measured by between groups differences in scores on the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale, adjusted for baseline values.</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days and 3 months post operation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>An improvement in function and quality of life, as measured by between groups differences in scores on the WHOQOL-BREF Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months and 12 months post operation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A between-groups difference in serum levels of Interleukin-1, as measured by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post operative day 2</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A between-groups difference in serum levels of Tumor Necrosis Factor alpha, as measured by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post operative day 2</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A between-groups difference in serum levels of Thiobarbituric acid reactive substances, as measured by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post operative day 2</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A between-groups difference in serum levels of Protein Carbonyls, as measured by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post operative day 2</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A between-groups difference in serum levels of 8-Hydroxydeoxyguanosine, as measured by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post operative day 2</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A between-groups difference in serum levels of Glutathione, as measured by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post operative day 2</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A between-groups difference in acute post surgical pain, as measured by the Numerical Rating Scale (NRS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post operative day 2 and 7</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A between-groups difference in persisting post surgical pain, as measured by the Modified Brief Pain Inventory</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post operation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A between-groups difference in persisting post surgical pain, as measured by the Neuropathic Pain Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months post operation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients above the age of 60 years undergoing major elective non cardiac surgery, defined as surgery expected to last at least 1 hour in duration and requiring admission to hospital.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants will be ineligible to take part if they;
* Have known contraindications to NAC including allergies and concomitant nitrate therapy
* Are unable to comply with the requirements of informed consent or the study protocol
* Are already taking NAC
* Require subsequent procedures necessitating general anaesthesia prior to completion of testing procedures
* Are undergoing carotid endarterectomy, due to the high incidence of perioperative cerebrovascular accidents
* Experience major perioperative morbidity, or mortality, that precludes them from completing post-operative cognitive testing within the prescribed time frame.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Recruitment

Research nurses will identify eligible participants at surgical outpatient clinics, and approach them to obtain written informed consent.

Allocation Concealment

Randomisation will be performed by contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who is at a central administration site, which will be the institution's pharmacy.
</concealment>
    <sequence>To be randomised to either the intervention or placebo group in 1:1 fashion, stratified by age (greater or less than 80 years) and surgery type (orthopaedic or non-orthopaedic surgery), via centralised computer sequence generation.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size calculations:
There is limited literature pertaining to the detection and quantification of POCD utilising the CogState Brief Battery. The few studies that are available suggest that the acute effect of POCD is likely to be small, somewhere in the region of d is equal to .2 to .4. The Pyschomotor-attention composite (detection and identification tasks) of the CogState Brief Battery has demonstrated sensitivity to differentiating between healthy controls, mild cognitive impairment (MCI), and Alzheimer's disease. MCI is the closest approximation for POCD currently available in the literature, and is comparable to POCD in the perioperative setting. Effect sizes and variance from Lim et al. (2012) suggest a a composite effect size of .96 and resultant post-operative effect size of .51. Given the likely strong correlation (r is likely to be greater than or equal to .5; Silbert et al. 2004) between pre- and post-operative scores, and with consultation with the trial statistician, a sample size of 370 participants is anticipated.


Data analysis:
Primary analyses will include analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) to examine post-surgical differences while controlling for pre-surgical scores. Cognitive outcomes, quality of life measurements, and serum levels of biomarkers will all be examined using a liner mixed effects models, and the magnitude of difference between treatment groups will be calculated at Cohen's d.
Mood and Delirium measurements will be treated as dichotomous variables, and analyzed using Chi-square tests.
Pearson's R will be used to examine correlations between biomarkers of oxidative stress and scores from the neuropsych battery. 

Exploratory analyses will be conducted to examine risk factors and latent variables (such as demographics, surgery type, other distinguishing factors) that may contribute to the incidence or severity of POCD. This will be examined using a multilevel modelling approach. This approach will also be used to examine the roles of other measures of participant experience, such as delirium, quality of life, or mood dysfunction. For dichotomous outcomes (such as delirium and mood dysfunction), McNamars test can be used to compare proportions across time points.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>29/04/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>25/04/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>370</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Barwon Health - Geelong Hospital campus - Geelong</hospital>
    <postcode>3220 - Geelong</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Geelong Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Ryrie Street
Geelong
Victoria 3220</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Geelong Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Ryrie Street
Geelong
Victoria 3220</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>CRC for Mental Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 2, 161 Barry Street, Carlton VIC 3053</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Sydney Parker Smith Scholarship</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Barwon Health
Ryrie Street Geelong Victoria 3220</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Aims:

* To examine the effectiveness of NAC in reducing POCD (primary aim)

* To investigate the effectiveness of NAC in reducing biomarkers of neuroinflammation and oxidative stress in the perioperative setting
* To examine the correlation between cognition and biomarkers
* To identify possible predictors of POCD

Hypotheses:

* The administration of NAC in a perioperative setting is more effective than placebo in reducing the severity of early POCD, as measured by performance changes on a neuropsychological battery (primary hypothesis)

* The administration of NAC in a perioperative setting is more effective than placebo in reducing the severity of long term POCD

* The administration of NAC in a perioperative setting is more effective than placebo in reducing the incidence of post operative delirium

* The administration of NAC in a perioperative setting is more effective than placebo in reducing the incidence of post operative mood disorders

* The administration of NAC in a perioperative setting is more effective than placebo in improving quality of life

* The administration of NAC in a perioperative setting is more effective than placebo in improving post surgical pain

* The administration of NAC in a perioperative setting is more effective than placebo in reducing serum levels of biomarkers of neuroinflammation and oxidative stress</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Barwon Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ryrie Street
Geelong 3220
Victoria</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/07/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>13/111</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/04/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Deakin University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Deakin University
Pigdon Road
Waurn Ponds
Victoria 3216</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/09/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2014-213</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/08/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrew John Marriott</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia, Perioperative Medicine and Pain Management
The Geelong Hospital
Ryrie Street
Geelong 3220
Victoria</address>
      <phone>+613 42151916</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amarri@barwonhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrew John Marriott</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia, Perioperative Medicine and Pain Management
The Geelong Hospital
Ryrie Street
Geelong 3220
Victoria</address>
      <phone>+613 42151916</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amarri@barwonhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrew John Marriott</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia, Perioperative Medicine and Pain Management
The Geelong Hospital
Ryrie Street
Geelong 3220
Victoria</address>
      <phone>+613 42151916</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amarri@barwonhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrew John Marriott</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia, Perioperative Medicine and Pain Management
The Geelong Hospital
Ryrie Street
Geelong 3220
Victoria</address>
      <phone>+613 42151916</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amarri@barwonhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>