<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365288">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/12/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/12/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001362785</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Do new blood-thinning treatments commenced after cardiac surgery keep By-Pass Grafts open longer ?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle> The effect of postoperative Aspirin and Clopidogrel versus Aspirin and Ticagrelor on coronary graft patency in patients undergoing primary isolated coronary artery bypass surgery (CABG) post acute coronary syndrome (ACS) presentation

</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>IMPACT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Coronary Artery Graft Patency following Coronary Artery Bypass Graft (CABG) post Acute Coronary Syndrome (ACS)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All patients who are undergoing isolated CABG following an ACS presentation at Waikato hospital Hamilton NZ and the Austin hospital Melbourne Australia will be eligible for randomisation and will be approached to consider participation
After CABG patients will be randomised to receive enteric coated Aspirin 100 mg orally daily and either Ticagrelor 90 mg orally twice daily or Clopidogrel 75 mg orally daily for 12 months post CABG. Post-operatively dual anti-platelet treatment will be commenced within 12 hours of the procedure, once the cardiac surgeon assessment indicates bleeding /drainage is less that 50 ml/hour
The study drug initial dose after surgery is going to be the maintenance dose, 75 mg orally daily for clopidogrel and 90 mg orally twice dailiy for ticagrelor. Compliance will be assessed by phone follow up
</interventions>
    <comparator>-	The control/comparator treatment arm is active treatment, clopidogrel and aspirin
 </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Coronary Graft patency 12 months following CABG as measured by multi slice computed tomography coronary angiography</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1.	Total Mortality

</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>bleeding 
Bleeding is the primary safety endpoint. Bleeding complications will be assessed using the TIMI Bleeding Criteria (15-18)
2.3.1    Non-CABG Related Bleeding:

1. Major
	Any intracranial bleeding (excluding microhemorrhages &lt;10 mm evident only on gradient-echo MRI) 
	Clinically overt signs of hemorrhage associated with a drop in hemoglobin of 50 g/L or greater or a 15% or more  absolute decrease in haematocrit 
Fatal bleeding (bleeding that directly results in death within 7 d) 

2. Minor
Clinically overt (including imaging), resulting in hemoglobin drop of 30 to &lt;50 g/L or 10% or greater decrease in haematocrit 
No observed blood loss: 40 g/L or greater decrease in the haemoglobin concentration or =12% decrease in haematocrit 
Any overt sign of hemorrhage that meets one of the following criteria and does not meet criteria for a major or minor bleeding event, as defined above 
Requiring intervention (medical practitioner-guided medical or surgical treatment to stop or treat bleeding, including temporarily or permanently discontinuing or changing the dose of a medication or study drug) 
Leading to or prolonging hospitalization 
Prompting evaluation (leading to an unscheduled visit to a healthcare professional and diagnostic testing, either laboratory or imaging) 
3. Minimal
Any overt bleeding event that does not meet the criteria above 
Any clinically overt sign of haemorrhage (including imaging) associated with a &lt;30 g/L decrease in haemoglobin concentration or &lt;9% decrease in haematocrit 

2.3.2     Bleeding in the Setting of CABG:
Fatal bleeding (bleeding that directly results in death) 
Perioperative intracranial bleeding 
Reoperation after closure of the sternotomy incision for the purpose of controlling bleeding 
Transfusion of 5 U or more PRBCs or whole blood within a 48-h period; cell saver transfusion will not be counted in calculations of blood products. 
Chest tube output &gt;2 L within a 24-h period 	
</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2.	Presentations with symptomatic graft failure (acute coronary syndrome or angina)

</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3  The occurrence of major adverse cardiac events (MACE), defined as follows:  
1.	Cardiovascular death  	
2.	Myocardial infarction  (Post operative incidence of myocardial infarction will be assessed by serial cardiac enzymes (High sensitive Troponin T) at day 1, 3, 5 and post discharge myocardial infarction will be assessed by either hospital visit for myocardial infarction reported by patient or hospital admission for myocardial infarction reported by cardiologist) . 
The 3rd universal definition of post CABG MI (Type 5) will be used for post CABG events . 
The 3rd universal definition of MI  (Type I) will be used outside of peri/post operative period .


</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3.	The need for revascularization (repeat operation or angioplasty reported by patient or cardiologist) through 12 months after CABG. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>4.	Combined MACE (CV death,MI,revascularization)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>5.	Assessment of platelet function with VERIFY-NOW assay at Day 5 post CABG and Pre CT Coronary angiography
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 5 post op and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients undergoing primary isolated CABG post ACS presentation</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Previous CABG
Platelet count &lt;100x 109/l
need for concomitant valve surgery or aneurysm resection
Need for post op warfarin
profuse post op bleeding
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Consent will be sought and obtained pre op.  Patient will be randomised post op using pre randomisation via sequentially numbered envelopes.  Treatment will not be blinded.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table from a statistics book.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>each participating centre will be supplied with 100 sealed envelopes in sequential order</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>According to previous studies, the combination of aspirin and clopidogrel has a graft occlusion rate of about 10% at 1 year after CABG. We estimate that a 5% difference between 2 arms can be reliably detected with a power of 80%, if we have 435 coronary grafts in each arm (2 sided T test with a p-value &lt;0.05). In addition, expecting a 10% drop out rates, we estimate 175 patients in each arm (average of three grafts per patient). 
The analysis will be based on an estimate of the proportion of failed grafts within each patient and compare these patient graft failure proportions between treatments using a non-parametric test like Wilcoxon. 
Analysis will be performed on an intention to treat AND treatment received at time CT 
The effect on power compared to a potentially biased Chi-square test is very limited. Based on simulations from the assumptions listed by Prof. Devlin in his proposal, would the power to detect a reduction from 10% graft failure to 5% with 165 patients per arm and 3 grafts / patient in mean, be over 80% with large probability and such a study would deliver a significant result at a 5% level with an observed absolute reduction of 2.5 percentage points.
One note is that for a study this large is probably a parametric approach like a t-test or z-test acceptable approximations, but picky statistical peer reviewers might frown upon such an approach.
Continuous variables will be expressed as mean (SD) or median (interquartile range [IQR]), and categorical variables reported as number (percentage). The significance of any difference between treatment groups in the proportion of patients with =1 occluded graft or with a secondary outcome will be assessed using Fisher exact test, and continuous variables (chest tube output, transfusion) assessed using 2-sample t tests. The significance of any differences between randomized treatment groups in the total numbers of occluded bypass grafts will be assessed by logistic regression using the generalized estimating equations method for non-independent outcomes. A 2-sided P value &lt; .05 will be considered statistically significant.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/02/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>20/11/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>400</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Waikato District Health Board</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Pembroke Street
Hamilton
3240</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>AstraZenica Limited
Global Commercial Organisation New Zealand</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 5, 15 Hopetoun Street, Freemans Bay, Auckland 1011
New Zealand
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>By pass grafts fail following cardiac surgery in nearly one in five people at 12 months .New blood thinning medicines may reduce the likelihood of this happening.In this trial we will look at these agents and whether or not they keep by pass grafts open with CT scan assessment of the by passes at 12 months </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>New Zealand Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
No 1 The Terrace
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6011
	

 
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/12/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Gerry Devlin</name>
      <address>Cardiology Department
Waikato Hospital
Private Bag 3200
Pembroke St
Hamilton 3240</address>
      <phone>+64 7 839 8899</phone>
      <fax>+64 7 839 7140</fax>
      <email>Gerard.Devlin@waikatodhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Gerry Devlin</name>
      <address>Cardiology Department
Waikato Hospital
Private Bag 3200
Pembroke St
Hamilton 3240</address>
      <phone>+64 7 839 8899</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Gerard.Devlin@waikatodhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Gerry Devlin</name>
      <address>Cardiology Department
Waikato Hospital
Private Bag 3200
Pembroke St
Hamilton 3240
</address>
      <phone>+64 7 839 8899</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Gerard.Devlin@waikatodhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Gerry Devlin</name>
      <address>Cardiology Department
Waikato Hospital
Private Bag 3200
Pembroke St
Hamilton 3240
</address>
      <phone>+64 7 839 8899</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Gerard.Devlin@waikatodhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>