<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371390">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001197426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Visual images to assist in positioning for spinal and epidural anaesthesia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Usefulness of visual aids in achieving optimal positioning for neuraxial anaesthesia: a randomised trial. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>None</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>neuraxial anaesthesia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The patients undergoing neuraxial anaesthesia for their hip and knee replacements, were randomised into two groups: The intervention group( Group 2) received standardised verbal instructions along with visual images to assist them to appropriate positioning to enable a spinal block. 
Following intravenous cannulation and application of standard monitoring, the participants were requested to sit in the upright position on the operating table with their feet resting on a stool, and shoulders gently supported by an assistant. No further assistance in positioning or any verbal prompting was provided by the theatre assistant. No sedative or anxiolytic premedication was administered to the participants, due to possible interference with their comprehension. Anaesthetists were allowed to choose the type, level, and approach of the block, as well as the needle and local anaesthetic used. 
	The anaesthetist prepared the spinal tray and drugs under aseptic conditions, and prepared and draped the patients back.   A second person started the timer and read out the standardised verbal instructions and showed the visual images (with a model demonstrating one correct and three incorrect positions).The patient then adopted the required position, and the anaesthetist immediately commenced the procedure. A trained independent observer recorded the relevant data.  </interventions>
    <comparator>The control group( Group 1) received standardised verbal instructions to assist them to appropriate positioning to enable a spinal block. These verbal instructions were drafted based on the common phrases used by anaesthetists to get their patients positioned for spinal anaesthesia.The patient then adopted the required position, and the anaesthetist immediately commenced the procedure. A trained independent observer recorded the relevant data.  </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time taken to achieve a successful dural puncture</outcome>
      <timepoint>The timer would start when the anaesthetist commences the spinal anaesthetic and would stop when there is free flow of CSF.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>  Secondary endpoints included number of skin punctures (not including local anaesthetic infiltration) until successful dural puncture</outcome>
      <timepoint>Total number of skin punctures until  there is free flow of CSF through the needle</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Success at the first attempted intervertebral space. Success is defined by the CSF flow through the needle.</outcome>
      <timepoint> The time point when there was CSF flow through the needle</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Satisfaction scores for anaesthetist from 1 to 5, 1 being very dissatisfied to 5 being completely satisfied</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after the procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Satisfaction scores for the patient from 1 to 5, 1 being very dissatisfied to 5 being completely satisfied</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after the procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adult patients undergoing elective hip and knee replacements under spinal anaesthesia were eligible for inclusion</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria were refusal to consent, inability to read or comprehend English, any contraindication to neuraxial anaesthesia, prior experience with neuraxial blocks, body mass index (BMI) greater than 45 kg/m2, anticipated positioning difficulties due to severe arthritis or major spinal deformities.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Random allocation was achieved by means of double opaque, sealed envelopes marked with trial identification numbers. </concealment>
    <sequence>Eligible participants were randomly allocated into two equal groups, based on computer generated random numbers.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Differences between continuous variables such as age, height, weight and body mass index will be by Students t-test or analysis of variance as appropriate. Comparison of categorical variables such as sex, number of skin punctures, number of spaces attempted, and level of experience will be done using Pearsons chi-squared test of independence. Comparison of ordinal variables such as satisfaction levels between groups will be done using appropriate non-parametric tests. Logistic regression will be used to assess association between continuous variables and binary outcomes such as success at first attempt. 
A sample size of approximately 43 patients per arm is proposed, based on obtaining 90% power to detect a difference 2.5 minutes between average times for the two treatment groups, using a 5% significance level and based on standard deviation of approximately 3.525  minutes. The level of significance will be set at p&lt;0.05.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/08/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>29/06/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>86</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>85</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>11/07/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Prince Charles Hospital - Chermside</hospital>
    <postcode>4032 - Chermside</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Usha Gurunathan</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Prince Charles Hospital,  Rode Road, Chermside, QLD 4032</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Prince Charles Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The Prince Charles Hospital, Rode Road, Chermside, Queensland 4032</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Nil</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Traditionally, anaesthetists have always been verbally instructing patients how to position themselves for spinal or epidural anaesthesia. This project is based on our hypothesis that if we use images in addition to verbal instructions, the patients could understand easily what is expected of them and therefore they can position themselves appropriately and quickly. We believe this will increase the satisfaction of both anaesthetists and patients with the whole procedure.

This project involves randomising patients into two groups, one group gets the standard verbal instructions and the other group gets to see images of the correct position as well. We note the time taken to do a successful procedure, the number of skin punctures made and the satisfaction scores of patients and anaesthetists. The two groups are compared and analysed if showing visual images is any beneficial as opposed to mere verbal instructions.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Prince Charles HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Rode Road, Chermside, QLD 4032</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/12/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/13/QPCH/335</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Usha Gurunathan</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia, The Prince Charles Hospital,  Rode Road, Chermside, QLD 4032</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3139 4000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>usha.gurunathan@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Usha Gurunathan</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia, The Prince Charles Hospital, Rode Road, Chermside, QLD- 4032</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3139 4000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>usha.gurunathan@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Usha Gurunathan</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia, The Prince Charles Hospital, Rode Road, Chermside, QLD- 4032</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3139 4000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>usha.gurunathan@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>