<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336763">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/04/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/04/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000356965</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Validating a Scored Salt Questionnaire against Urinary Sodium Excretion in Patients with Chronic Kidney Disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Validating a Scored Salt Questionnaire against Urinary Sodium Excretion in Patients with Chronic Kidney Disease</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1120-5489</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic kidney disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Cross-sectional validation study of a Scored Salt Questionnaire (SSQ). The SSQ is a self-administered and scored questionnaire consisting of 30 questions relating to common foods and sodium-related behaviour patterns identified from food records collected previously from the local renal population.  To validate this tool, assessment of agreement between sodium intake score from the SSQ and the gold-standard 24-hour urinary sodium excretion (mmol) will be undertaken using Bland-Altman plat and inter-class correlation.  It is anticipated this study will take 18months in total including data analysis and write-up.</interventions>
    <comparator>24 hour urinary sodium excretion - widely accepted as the preferred method of assessment of intake</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of agreement between sodium intake score from the Scored Salt Questionnaire and the gold-standard 24-hour urinary sodium excretion (mmol)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Scored Salt Questionnaire completed on the day participants finish the 24-hour urine collection. The assessment of agreement will occur at the end of the study once all data has been collected.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary aim is to describe the habitual sodium intake of a cohort of CKD patients attending hospital outreach clinics.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will occur at the end of the study once all data has been collected.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients with CKD stages 3, 4, or 5
Stable condition and medications</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with CKD stages 1 and 2
Primary language other than English (only if limits ability to carry out study requirements)
&lt;18 years of age
Women who are pregnant
Patients lacking the capacity to give consent for themselves or the cognitive ability to participate e.g. dementia
Patients who have recently commenced diuretic medications i.e. in the last week
Patients with known poor compliance
Patients with salt losing nephropathy</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>90</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>4029</postcode>
    <postcode>4012</postcode>
    <postcode>4509</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Queensland Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Nutrition and Dietetics, Level 2, Dr James Mayne Building, Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital, Butterfield St, Herston, QLD, 4029</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital Foundation and ANZSN-Amgen Quality Assurance Grants</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>RBWH, Butterfield St, Herston, QLD, 4029</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this research is to validate a Scored Sodium Questionnaire (SSQ) as a quick and easy clinical and research tool for assessing salt intake in renal patients. 

Evidence Based Practice Guidelines internationally recommend a low sodium diet for renal patients to assist in the management of and retard progression in chronic kidney disease (CKD) 1-9. While dietary counselling is effective in lowering dietary sodium, the prevalence of this disease is increasing rapidly, making it impossible to provide individualised dietary education to all patients. It is essential that finite dietetic resources are directed at those with the greatest need for dietary intervention. Therefore, it is important that clinicians and researchers have a reliable and convenient method of screening and assessing dietary sodium intake to assist in identifying patients who would benefit most from individualised dietetic education and counselling support. Current methods for assessing dietary sodium intake are time consuming, subject to inter-rater variability and are therefore rarely used in the clinical setting. In addition, the gold standard (24-hour urinary sodium) is time consuming, costly and intrusive.

A self-administered SSQ was recently developed by dietitians and researchers at the Royal Brisbane and Womens Hospital (RBWH) but has not yet been validated in the target population.

Research design: Cross-sectional validation study involving 90 consecutive patients with CKD visiting the Nundah or North Lakes Kidney Health Clinics. Consented participants will be asked to complete the SSQ and a 24-hour food record as well as provide 24-hour urine collections for estimating urinary sodium excretion (urine samples are collected as part of routine care). To validate the SSQ in this population, dietary sodium intake (grams) will be calculated using the tool, confirmed by comparing to 24-hour urinary sodium excretion (grams/day) (gold standard), and cross checked against sodium intake assessed by the 24-hour food record. Steps will also be taken to investigate which parts/questions in the SSQ are more strongly correlated to predict a higher sodium intake, so that clinical referral for dietetic resources can be directed accordingly (screening section of the tool).  

A valid tool will provide clinicians and researchers with a quick and efficient method of assessing patients sodium intakes without the need for intensive dietary interviewing and analysis. In addition, the screening section could be used by non-dietetic staff to identify patients with higher sodium intakes for dietetic referral.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>International Congress on Nutrition and Metabolism (2010):
Gill E, Marshall L, Ross L, Ash S. Development of the Scored Salt Questionnaire for the rapid assessment of dietary sodium intake in renal patients within the clinical setting (in press). 

Australia and New Zealand Society of Nephrology (2009):
Marshall L, Gill E, Ross L, Ash, S.  Identification of Foods Making a Significant Contribution to the Total Dietary Sodium Intakes of Brisbane Renal Patients.  Nephrology 2010; Vol 15 (s4) 1-101.
Gill E, Yang C, Gillen L, Lloyd L, Kark A, Healy H. Validating a Scored Salt Questionnaire against Qualitative Sat Assessment in Renal Patients. Nephrology 2009; Vol 14 (s1) A1-A61.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Butterfield St, Herston, QLD, 4029</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/03/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/10/QRBW/464</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Belinda Morey</name>
      <address>Department of Nutrition and Dietetics, Level 2, Dr James Mayne Building, Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital, Butterfield St, Herston, QLD, 4029</address>
      <phone>+61736367997</phone>
      <fax>+6136361874</fax>
      <email>Belinda_Morey@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Belinda Morey</name>
      <address>Department of Nutrition and Dietetics, Level 2, Dr James Mayne Building, Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital, Butterfield St, Herston, QLD, 4029</address>
      <phone>+61736367997</phone>
      <fax>+6136361874</fax>
      <email>Belinda_Morey@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Belinda Morey</name>
      <address>Department of Nutrition and Dietetics, Level 2, Dr James Mayne Building, Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital, Butterfield St, Herston, QLD, 4029</address>
      <phone>+61736367997</phone>
      <fax>+6136361874</fax>
      <email>Belinda_Morey@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>