<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373462">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/08/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/08/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001212347p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Ageing well: Effect of a social participation and engagement tool on community participation and quality of life among community aged care clients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Ageing well: Effect of a social participation and engagement tool on community participation and quality of life among community aged care clients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1200-5886</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Dementia and Aged Care Services Fund (DACS):
Schedule ID: 4-4ZO9T62
Agreement ID: 4-4ZO9T5A</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>social participation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>engagement</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions> The Australian Community Participation Questionnaire (ACPQ) and the ICEpop CAPability Measure for Older Adults (ICECAP-O) will be implemented by community aged care support workers from one of Australia's largest aged care providers as part of routine assessment with community aged care clients, The assessments will be conducted face-to-face across New South Wales and the Australian Capital Territory. The data collected from these tools, along with other key outcomes will be analysed at baseline and six month follow-up. 

Semi-structured interviews and focus groups with clients and community aged care staff will be conducted regarding their experiences of the social participation and quality of life tools.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Type, breath and level of social participation as determined by the Australian Community Participation Questionnaire (ACPQ).
- Type and level of social participation is determined by analysis of each category of social participation in the ACPQ
- Breath of social participation is determined by the total score obtained in the ACPQ</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and six-month follow-up post implementation of tool</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Level of quality of life as determined by the mean ICEpop CAPability Measure for Older Adults (ICECAP-O) total score.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and six-month follow-up post implementation of tool</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Community aged care client and support staff experiences of the two social engagement and participation tools using semi-structured interviews and focus groups. Interviews will be conducted face-to-face or via telephone, dependent on what is most suitable for each participant. Focus groups will be conducted face-to-face in a group setting.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Between baseline and six-month follow-up post implementation of tool</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Service use as assessed by data linkage to community aged care databases</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and on a monthly basis from implementation of tools for six months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse events (e.g. falls, medication errors, injuries) as assessed by data linkage to community aged care databases</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and on a monthly basis from implementation of tools for six months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospitalisation as assessed by data linkage to community aged care databases</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and on a monthly basis from implementation of tools for six months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to residential aged care as assessed by data linkage to community aged care databases</outcome>
      <timepoint>Six-month follow-up post implementation of tool</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to death as assessed by data linkage to community aged care databases</outcome>
      <timepoint>Six-month follow-up post implementation of tool</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ability to complete activities of daily living as assessed by data linkage to community aged care databases</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and on a monthly basis from implementation of tools for six months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Community aged care clients:
1.	Receiving community aged care services from Uniting
2.	Living within one of the NSW or ACT regions recruited for this study
3.	Completed the ACPQ and ICECAP-O with a community aged care support staff
Additional criteria for qualitative element of study (interviews and focus groups):
4.	Able to provide written consent, or has an appropriate person that can provide proxy consent on their behalf if required, e.g. due to cognitive impairment

Community aged care support staff:
1.	Permanent staff member with Uniting
2.	Aged 18 or older
3.	Experience using the ACPQ and ICECAP-O with a diverse range of clients (people with varying levels of independence, care needs, ability to communicate, and cultural and lingual diversity) between baseline and follow-up (six months)
4.	Able to provide written consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Community aged care consumers:
1.	Not receiving community aged care services from Uniting, or cease all services during the study period
2.	Did not complete the ACPQ and ICECAP-O with a community aged care support staff
Additional criteria for qualitative element of study (interviews and focus groups):
3.	Unable or declines to provide written consent themselves or from a proxy

Community aged care support staff:
1.	Casual staff member with Uniting
2.	Under the age of 18
3.	Has not used the ACPQ and ICECAP-O with a diverse range of consumers (people with varying levels of independence, care needs, ability to communicate, and cultural and lingual diversity)
4.	Unable or declines to provide written consent</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Quantitative data:
The proposed number of clients enrolled in the study is based on evaluating one of the primary quantitative outcome of interest, quality of life (ICECAP-O). A sample size of between 821 and 1,098 consumers is needed to detect a meaningful change in quality of life scores between baseline and six-month follow-up (with 80% power and 90% power, respectively). This sample size estimate assumes a moderate correlation between pre- and post-scores (r=0.5), and a meaningful change in mean ICECAP-O scores of 0.02.

Analysis of linked de-identified records of clients who are administered the social participation and engagement tools will be performed to quantitatively examine the associations between service provision, social participation and consumer outcomes over the six months following tool administration. 

Descriptive analyses will be used to quantify: (i) the types, breadth and level of social participation at baseline; (ii) level of quality of life of clients at baseline; (iii) changes in clients social participation and quality of life at six months; and (iv) community service utilisation and other client outcomes captured by the client management system over the six months following tool administration. 

Correlation and regression analyses will be used to determine associations between: i) social participation and quality of life; ii) social participation and community service utilisation; and iii) social participation and other consumer outcomes (e.g., time to residential aged care). Potential confounders, such as age and mobility, will be controlled for in these analyses .

Qualitative data:
The qualitative data will be analysed using a structured content analysis approach of client and staff experiences. A critical realist approach will be used. 

Data collection and analysis will be conducted in NVivo software. One researcher will perform the initial open coding of the data, which will then be reviewed and modified by the research team. Any discrepancies in coding will be discussed and used to modify the list of codes until all researchers agree on code application. The codes will then be sorted into preliminary domains and themes, which will be repeatedly reviewed and refined by all researchers to maximise homogeneity prior to developing an analytic narrative.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/11/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>3/12/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1098</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>7/01/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Macquarie University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Research office
Macquarie University
North Ryde
NSW
2109</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Dementia and Aged Care Services</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Aged Care Grants, Tasmania
GPO Box 9848
Melbourne
Victoria
3001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Uniting</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Level 4, 222 Pitt Street
Sydney
NSW
1155</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary objective of this study is to evaluate the impact of a social participation and engagement tool on community participation and quality of life of community aged care clients. It is hypothesised that the implementation of the ACPQ and ICECAP-O (social participation and engagement tools) as part of routine assessment for community aged care services will improve social engagement and quality of life for clients. The aims of this study are: (i) ascertain the levels of social participation and engagement, and quality of life for a sample of community aged care clients; (ii) measure the association between the delivery of community aged care services, social participation and engagement, and quality of life; (iii) utilise the findings to provide recommendations of potential strategies that could be implemented in the future to improve social participation and engagement. A mixed method design will be utilised for this study, involving the collection of both quantitative and qualitative data to achieve the study objectives. The study will be conducted over two years with one of Australia's largest aged care providers.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Macquarie University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research office
Macquarie University
North Ryde
NSW
2109</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/09/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Andrew Georgiou</name>
      <address>Centre for Health Systems and Safety Research
Australian Institute of Health Innovation
Macquarie University
Room L6 36
Level 6, 75 Talavera Road
Macquarie University
NSW
2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 2424</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9850 2499</fax>
      <email>andrew.georgiou@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Andrew Georgiou</name>
      <address>Centre for Health Systems and Safety Research
Australian Institute of Health Innovation
Macquarie University
Room L6 36
Level 6, 75 Talavera Road
Macquarie University
NSW
2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 2424</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9850 2499</fax>
      <email>andrew.georgiou@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Andrew Georgiou</name>
      <address>Centre for Health Systems and Safety Research
Australian Institute of Health Innovation
Macquarie University
Room L6 36
Level 6, 75 Talavera Road
Macquarie University
NSW
2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 2424</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9850 2499</fax>
      <email>andrew.georgiou@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lindsey Brett</name>
      <address>Centre for Health Systems and Safety Research
Australian Institute of Health Innovation
Macquarie University
Level 6, 75 Talavera Road
Macquarie University
NSW
2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 2487</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9850 2499</fax>
      <email>lindsey.brett@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>