<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368422">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/08/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/08/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000879561</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>CHERISH Collaborative for Hospitalised Elders: Reducing the Impact of Stays in Hospital</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Do older hospital inpatients admitted to acute care wards implementing the "Eat Walk Engage" quality improvement programme have reduced geriatric syndromes, shorter length of stay and greater likelihood of discharge home than older inpatients admitted to control wards?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1169-4943 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>CHERISH</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>delirium</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>functional decline</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>malnutrition</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>"Eat Walk Engage" is a quality improvement programme designed to enhance uptake of evidence-based processes of care for older inpatients. The target processes are early mobility; adequate oral nutritional intake; and meaningful, cognitively stimulating activities. The programme uses enabling facilitation based on the i-PARIHS implementation framework, and engages members of the multidisciplinary team on intervention wards to identify barriers to these processes, trial solutions, and embed successful solutions into practice. Solutions may entail both individual behaviour change and system redesign, and are individualised to the context. The facilitator supports change using methods such as marketing, team building, active reflection, process mapping, audit and feedback and education. 
The facilitator is recruited within the study hospital, but resourced, trained and supported by the project team which includes expert facilitators. This includes a 3 day formal training course; fortnightly in-person or telephone support by the expert facilitator team;  6 monthly forum for sharing skills and experiences between sites; and ad hoc telephone support as required. Facilitator contacts will be monitored by the project manager to measure fidelity. The intervention will take place over 12 months. Facilitator roles include monthly 1-hour group meetings between the site facilitator and the ward multidisciplinary team; identification of local barriers and enablers; facilitation of the planning and implementation of small scale improvement cycles as agreed by the team to support the programme aims; identification of delegation tasks suitable for an additional part time health care assistant resourced by the project; audit and feedback of structured process measures related to the improvement aims (patient interviews, activity audits and mealtime audits); and escalation of barriers and solutions if necessary to higher level decision makers. Meeting minutes and field notes by the novice and expert facilitators will be used to monitor intervention fidelity, and 6 monthly structured process audits will measure implementation effectiveness.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual ward care, including any facility based improvement programmes</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>length of hospital stay: number of days between inpatient admission and discharge from hospital based on hospital record</outcome>
      <timepoint>at discharge from hospital</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>any geriatric syndrome (composite of delirium, functional decline, in-hospital falls, in-hospital pressure injury and new incontinence) based on participant assessment at admission, day 5 and discharge (basic activities of daily living scale, short portable mental status questionnaire, 3D-CAM delirium assessment tool, and recall of incontinence, falls and skin injuries); as well as review of clinical documentation in hospital record</outcome>
      <timepoint>at admission, day 5 and at discharge</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>death or discharge to higher level of care based on hospital record</outcome>
      <timepoint>at hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>delirium (3D-CAM and chart review)</outcome>
      <timepoint>by day 5 of admission and by discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>functional decline (any increase in basic activities of daily living assistance compared to baseline) by patient (or proxy) self-report </outcome>
      <timepoint>by day 5, discharge, and 30 days after discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>hospital readmission based on state-wide hospital admissions information system</outcome>
      <timepoint>within 30 days of discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>mortality based on hospital records and telephone follow-up</outcome>
      <timepoint>in hospital or within 30 days of discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>cost-utility analysis based on EQ5D and hospital costing database</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days after discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Admitted to hospital for 3 or more days, with admission to nominated intervention or control ward</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Discharged from hospital within 2 days; palliative intent of care</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>As this is a system-level improvement intervention, the study is a cluster randomised controlled trial, comparing changes measured  before and after intervention on 4 randomly selected intervention wards with the changes occurring over the same time period in 4 hospital-matched control wards. Randomisation occurs at the level of ward (each hospital providing a control and intervention ward) and will be undertaken by the off-site study statistician using a random number generator i.e. allocation is concealed. Participant allocation to each ward (and therefore to treatment or control) will occur based on usual hospital processes (diagnosis, treating team on call schedules, and bed availability). </concealment>
    <sequence>Random number generation by off-site study statistician</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Detailed process of care measure will supplement the outcome measures to help determine the effectiveness of the implementation process at each site</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Outcomes will be measured and analysed at a patient level, allowing for clustering by ward. Patient, ward and group characteristics will be described using summary statistics. Change in average length of stay between baseline (pre-intervention) and post-intervention will be compared between the intervention and control group using time-to-event analysis. Competing outcomes will be included to explore the impact on acute length of stay and discharge destination from acute stay (death/home/subacute or residential care). Participants who are still in-hospital at the end of study will be censored. The primary outcomes will be presented as: i) the average difference in length of stay, ii) the percentage change in geriatric syndromes. Outcomes will be presented as means or proportions and 95% confidence intervals. Plots of the cumulative risks of discharge by length of hospital stay will be compared between groups to examine the differences between groups in detail and to show whether the intervention effect varies by time in hospital.
The estimated sample size will provide 90% power to detect a difference of 10% in acute length of stay and discharge home and 20% reduction in geriatric syndromes. Proportions of participants developing secondary outcomes will be compared between groups using chi-squared testing. Modelling approaches (such as multiple logistic regression) will be used if needed to adjust for intergroup baseline differences, however we anticipate that the randomised design will protect against any confounding. Planned subgroup analysis of outcomes will be undertaken to identify effect at different sites and in frail versus non-frail participants.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>28/08/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>5/10/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/03/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>15/06/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>Nambour General Hospital - Nambour</hospital>
    <hospital>The Prince Charles Hospital - Chermside</hospital>
    <hospital>Caboolture Hospital - Caboolture</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Alison Mudge</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Building C28 Level 1
Roal Brisbane and Women's Hospitals
Herston Queensland 4029</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Queensland Department of Science, Information Technology and Innovation (DSITIA)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 5078
Brisbane Qld 4001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Queensland University of Technology</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Institute of Health and Biomedical Innovation
Q Block
60 Musk Ave
Kelvin Grove Qld 4059</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Metro North Hospitals and Health Services</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 14, Block 7
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospitals
Herston Qld 4029</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Sunshine Coast Hospital and Health Service</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Nambour General Hospital Block 5 Executive
PO Box 547
Nambour Qld 4560</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Hornsby Ku-Ring-Gai Health Service</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Palmerston Rd
Hornsby NSW 2077</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Queensland University of Technology
Office of Research</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Level 4, 88 Musk Ave
Kelvin Grove Qld 4059</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of Queensland
Centre for Research in Geriatric Medicine</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Level 2, Building 33 Princess Alexandra Hospital
Ipswich Rd 
Woolloongabba Qld 4102</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of Adelaide
School of Nursing</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Level 3, Eleanor Harrald Bldg
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace, Adelaide 5000</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of Melbourne
Department of Medicine</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Clinical Sciences Building, Royal Melbourne Hospital
Royal Parade
Parkville Vic 3050</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of Sydney
Sydney Medical School</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Northern Clinical School
Kolling Building, Royal North Shore Hospital
St Leonards NSW 2065</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other Collaborative groups</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Hebrew Senior Life Centre
Institute for Ageing Research</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>1200 Centre St
Boston
Massachussets 02131</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>United States of America</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Older people (age 65 and older) account for more than half of hospital bed days, and have longer stays and more hospital adverse events that younger people. A hospital stay is often a decisive point in an older persons health, with hospitalisation accounting for half of newly acquired disability in elders. Geriatric syndromes (including delirium, functional decline, falls, incontinence and pressure injury) result in longer hospitalisations and greater risk of death and institutionalisation. Research clearly shows that simple strategies (early mobilisation, adequate oral nutrition, and meaningful cognitive activities) are effective to reduce geriatric syndromes, improve outcomes and reduce costs. While such strategies have been effectively incorporated in specialist acute care for elders wards, only a limited number of patients have access to these specialist services. In order to optimise care we need to embed these principles in all acute wards caring for older people. However, this requires systematic changes in acute care staff attitudes, practices and systems of care.

We have piloted a programme of enabling facilitation, based on the i-PARIHS implementation framework, to embed this evidence into practice. The Eat Walk Engage programme supports a ward-based multidisciplinary team to identify barriers, trial solutions and embed successful strategies into practice using evidence-based quality improvement methods. In two pilot wards at the Royal Brisbane and Womens Hospital we have shown promising reductions in length of stay, geriatric syndromes and adverse events accompanying process improvements. 

The CHERISH (Collaborative for Hospitalised Elders: Reducing the Impact of Stays in Hospital) study is a cluster randomised controlled trial of the Eat Walk Engage programme across 4 sites, and will provide robust evidence of the transferability, scalability, effectiveness and cost-effectiveness of the programme to inform further implementation. Comparing 4 intervention wards with  control wards in the same hospitals to account for other sources of variation, we aim to demonstrate a reduction in hospital stay, geriatric syndromes, and discharge to a higher level of care within 12 months of implementing the Eat Walk Engage programme. The project is supported by a Queensland Accelerate Partnership Grant from the Department of Science, Information Technology, Innovation and the Arts, administered by Queensland University of Technology.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Mudge A, McRae P, Cruickshank M. Eat Walk Engage: an interdisciplinary collaborative model to improve care of hospitalised elders. Am J Med Qual 2015; 30 (1):5-13</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>RBWH Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 7, Block 7
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospitals
Herston Qld 4029</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/04/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/QRBW/95</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>QUT University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Research Ethics and Integrity
Level 44, 88 Must Avenue
Kelvin Grove Qld 4059</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/05/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Queensland Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>17/08/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Alison Mudge</name>
      <address>Building C28 Level 1
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospitals
Herston Queensland 4029</address>
      <phone>61736460854</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Alison.Mudge@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Prue McRae</name>
      <address>Building C28 Level 1
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospitals
Herston Queensland 4029</address>
      <phone>61736460787</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Prue.McRae@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Alison Mudge</name>
      <address>Building C28 Level 1
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospitals
Herston Queensland 4029</address>
      <phone>61736460854</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Alison.Mudge@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Alison Mudge</name>
      <address>Building C28 Level 1
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospitals
Herston Queensland 4029</address>
      <phone>61736460854</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Alison.Mudge@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>