<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365473">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/12/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/12/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001375741</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Using a biodegradable polyurethane dermal matrix in the management of deep burn injury.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Biodegradable Temporising Matrix (BTM) in dermal replacement and wound temporisation prior to definitive split-skin grafting post-excision of full thickness burns affecting between 20% and 50% of the total body surface area (TBSA) to assess integration, delamination and ability to support subsequent graft take.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Australian Therapeutic Goods Administration (TGA) Clinical Trial Notification (CTN) Number - 343/2013.</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Deep-dermal and full thickness burn injury (ie burns which require surgical excision and repair) involving between 20% and 50% of the total body surface area (TBSA).</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other skin conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Burns</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Once the non-viable burned skin/tissue is excised surgically, the BTM will be surgically implanted into the healthy wound bed and held with surgical staples before being over-dressed. Dressing changes every three days will allow observaton and monitoring of the progress of integration of the dermal component (a biodegradable polyurethane foam). After 3 - 6 weeks, following complete integration of the permanent 'dermal' component of the material, its temporary 'epidermal component (a bonded, superficial, non-biodegradable polyurethane film) will be removed, the underlying 'neodermal' surface refreshed by dermabrasion and definitive closure afforded by the application of a thin, split-thickness skin graft. Graft take and subsequent quality will form long-term outcomes</interventions>
    <comparator>No comparator</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ability of the dermal component of the BTM to integrate into the wound. The BTM is a white foam bonded to a transparent seal, integration is obvious by observations of colour (red), texture (homogeneous and lacking the initial foam appearance through the seal) and opacity (bed structures such as tendons become completely obscured by the overlying integrated BTM).</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 - 6 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ease of delamination of the temporary epidermal seal from the integrated dermal matrix. At the time of delamination, ease will be determined by the removal of the lamina (seal) in one piece and in one action. Fragmentation and piecemeal removal would, for example, be seen as a failure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 - 6 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ability of the integrated dermal component to receive a split skin graft and to then support split skin graft take. Split skin grafts are usually vascularised by inosculation within 48 hours. Take in this context is defined as adhesion of the graft by scar tissue and revascularisation by inosculation by 72 hours and is assessed by colour, blanching and real-time video VivoScopy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 - 6 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Degree of wound contraction (function). In such large wounds, this can only be assessed in terms of major joint function (range of motion) and in the hand by the Michigan Hand Questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 - 18 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cosmetic appearance compared to historical experience. This will include patient rating of scars.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 - 18 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Deep (deep-dermal and full-thickness) burn injuries between 20 and 50% TBSA requiring burn excision and split skin grafting
Age between 18 and 70 years inclusive
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnancy
Unable to provide informed consent
Known allergy/previous reaction to polyurethane dressings
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All patients meeting inclusion and no exclusion criteria will be assessed for inclusion in the study. The nature of the trial will be discussed and signed consent obtained if the patient is willing to be involved.</concealment>
    <sequence>Not applicable</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>This is a pilot study designed to assess the properties of the BTM in a large burn model. As such, only 5 patients are to be recruited, since sufficient data will be generated to provide confidence to progress to multi-centre human trials. Most analysis will thus be based on clinical observation (material integration, graft take, etc). Some statistical analysis may be appropriate to compare the treatment group with historical controls in terms of certain outcomes (Michigan Hand Questionnaire, joint range of motion, etc).</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/05/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>2/12/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>5</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>5</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>2/12/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Royal Adelaide Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>North Terrace, Adelaide 5000, South Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>PolyNovo Biomaterials Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Unit 2, 320 Lorimer Street,
Port Melbourne 3207, Victoria, Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>PolyNovo Biomaterials Pty Ltd</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Unit 2, 320 Lorimer Street,
Port Melbourne 3207, Victoria, Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of the whole research program is to evaluate the feasibility of replacing several high cost materials currently in use for burn management at the RAH (Integra, Matriderm, Biobrane/cadaver allograft for burn wound temporisation after excision) with a cost-effective, synthetic alternative. This new material has demonstrated superior efficacy in large animal studies and two pilot human trials in non-burn wounds are currently ongoing. This will represent the first stage of a proposed two-stage strategy to abolish the need for split skin grafts in burn care. The second stage is already at an advanced stage of development in-vitro and has similarly proven effective in porcine wounds.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Papers
A Li, BL Dearman, KE Crompton, TG Moore, JE Greenwood
Evaluation of a novel biodegradable polymer for the generation of a dermal matrix
Journal of Burns Care and Research July/August 2009;30(4):717-728.

JE Greenwood, A Li, B Dearman, TG Moore
'Evaluation of NovoSorb novel biodegradable polymer for the generation of a dermal matrix. Part 1: In-vitro studies'
Wound Practice and Research Feb 2010;18(1):14-22.

JE Greenwood, A Li, B Dearman, TG Moore
'Evaluation of NovoSorb novel biodegradable polymer for the generation of a dermal matrix. Part 2: In-vivo studies'
Wound Practice and Research Feb 2010;18(1):24-34.

JE Greenwood, BL Dearman
Split-skin graft application over an integrating, biodegradable temporising polymer matrix: Immediate and delayed
Journal of Burn Care and Research Jan/Feb2012;33(1):7-19.

JE Greenwood, BL Dearman
Comparison of a sealed, polymer foam biodegradable temporising matrix against Integra dermal regeneration template in a porcine wound model
Journal of Burn Care and Research Jan/Feb2012;33(1):163-173.

BL Dearman, K Stefani, A Li, JE Greenwood
Take Of A Polymer-Based Autologous Cultured Composite Skin On An Integrated Temporising Dermal Matrix: Proof Of Concept.
Journal of Burn Care and Research 2012 (Accepted June 2012) 


Published Abstracts

JE Greenwood, IM Griffiths, T Moore, K Crompton, T Gunatillake, R Adhikari
Design and synthesis of biodegradable polymers to create dermal regeneration scaffolds (abstract)
ANZ Journal of Surgery May 2008:78 (supplement):A11 (BA20).

JE Greenwood, A Li, B Dearman, IM Griffiths 
Biodegradable polymers  (i) in-vitro evaluation as dermal matrices (abstract)
ANZ Journal of Surgery May 2008:78 (supplement):A12 (BA22).

JE Greenwood, A Li, B Dearman, IM Griffiths
Biodegradable polymers  (ii) in-vivo evaluation as dermal matrices (abstract)
ANZ Journal of Surgery May 2008:78 (supplement):A12 (BA23).

JE Greenwood
Biodegradable polyurethane as a dermal matrix
Journal of Burn Care and Research 2011;32(2) Suppl:S58.

JE Greenwood, B Dearman
Biodegradable polyurethane as a dermal matrix allowing immediate or delayed grafting (abstract)
ANZJS 2011;81 (Suppl. 1):A3.

JE Greenwood, BL Dearman
Wound closure over integrated polymer neo-dermes using cultured epithelial autograft and composite cultured skin equivalents (poster abstract)
Journal of Burn Care and Research 2012;33(2) Suppl:S173.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 3, Hanson Institute,
Royal Adelaide Hospital, North Terrace,
Adelaide 5000,
South Australia
Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/11/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec> Protocol Number - 121125.</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>John E Greenwood</name>
      <address>Adult Burn Centre,
Royal Adelaide Hopspital, North Terrace, Adelaide 5000, South Australia, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 2233</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8222 5676</fax>
      <email>john.greenwood@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>John E Greenwood</name>
      <address>Adult Burn Centre,
Royal Adelaide Hopspital, North Terrace, Adelaide 5000, South Australia, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 2233</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8222 5676</fax>
      <email>john.greenwood@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>John E Greenwood</name>
      <address>Adult Burn Centre,
Royal Adelaide Hopspital, North Terrace, Adelaide 5000, South Australia, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 2233</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8222 5676</fax>
      <email>john.greenwood@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>John E Greenwood</name>
      <address>Adult Burn Centre,
Royal Adelaide Hopspital, North Terrace, Adelaide 5000, South Australia, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 2233</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8222 5676</fax>
      <email>john.greenwood@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>