<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366858">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/08/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/09/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000987662</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of chiropractic care on upper limb function </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effects of chiropractic care on upper limb force production, proprioception and spinal stretch reflexes in adults with a history of recurring spinal dysfunction </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U111111512164</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>subclinical spinal pain </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Full spine adjustments will be carried out during the experimental sessions. The entire spine and sacroiliac joints will be assessed for vertebral subluxations and adjusted by hand where deemed necessary by a registered chiropractor with at least ten years clinical experience. The vertebral subluxation indicators that will be used to assess the function
of the spine prior to and after each spinal adjustment intervention include assessing for tenderness to palpation of the relevant joints, manually palpating for restricted intersegmental range of motion, assessing for palpable asymmetric intervertebral muscle tension, and
any abnormal or blocked joint play and end-feel of the joints. All of these biomechanical characteristics are known clinical indicators of spinal dysfunction (Fryer, Morris, &amp; Gibbons, 2004; Hestboek &amp; Leboeuf-Yde, 2000). These findings will be documented prior to and after each spinal adjustment intervention. The improvements in segmental function following spinal adjustments will also be recorded for each subject. The single spinal adjustment intervention session will take 10 minutes on average. </interventions>
    <comparator>The control intervention will consist of passive and active movements of the subjects head, spine and body that will be carried out by the same chiropractor who pre-checks the participants for vertebral subluxations and who performs the adjustments in the experimental intervention sessions. This control intervention will involve the participants being
moved into the adjustment setup positions where the chiropractor would normally apply a thrust to the spine to achieve the adjustments.
However, the experimenter will be particularly careful not to put pressure on any individual spinal segments. Loading a joint, as is done prior to spinal adjustments has been shown to alter paraspinal proprioceptive firing in anesthetised cats (Pickar &amp; Wheeler, 2001), and
will therefore be carefully avoided by ending the movement prior to endrange-of-motion when passively moving the participants. No spinal adjustments will be performed during any control intervention. This control intervention is not intended to act as a sham adjustment but to act as a physiological control for possible changes occurring due to the cutaneous, muscular or vestibular input that will occur with the type of passive and active movements involved in preparing a patient for an adjustment. It also acts as a control for the effects of the stimulation necessary to collect the dependent measures of the study, and acts as a
control for the time required to carry out the adjustment intervention. The single control intervention session will take 10 minutes on average. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>We will be measuring the following dependant measures from the deltoid muscle in the upper limb before and after
a single session of adjusting subluxations;

Maximum isometric force production using an isometric strain gauge.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre and Post of intervention or control session</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Spinal stretch reflex function will be assessed using electromyography</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre and Post of intervention or control session</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Median frequency data from surface electromyography
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre and Post of intervention or control session</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proprioception in the form of a position sense task
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre and Post of intervention or control session</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Subjects will be eligible for inclusion if they are English speaking, aged 18-40,and have previously sought
chiropractic care, and have some history of recurring spinal dysfunction such as mild pain, ache, and/or stiffness
with or without a history of known trauma.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Subjects will be ineligible to participate if they exhibit no evidence of
vertebral subluxations, have absolute contraindications to spinal
adjustments, have experienced previous
significant adverse reactions to chiropractic care, or they are suffering from a current lower limb disorder/dysfunction that would make them unable to carry out data recording sessions (e.g. sprain/strain/fracture),and if they have sought treatment for the subclinical pain symptoms.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>21/09/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/08/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>19/10/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>12</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>12</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>23/11/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>NewZealand College of chiropractic</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>6 Harrison road
Ellerslie
1060,Auckland</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NewZealand College of chiropractic</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>6 Harrison road
Ellerslie
1060,Auckland</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Over the past ten years a growing body of evidence has accumulated that suggests neural plastic changes occur following chiropractic adjustments (for recent review see Haavik &amp; Murphy, 2012). Recently, due to ASRF funding, we presented the findings from eight subjects that demonstrated that a full spine chiropractic adjustment session resulted in an increase in the subjects ability to maximally voluntarily contract their lower limb muscle by almost 73% (Niazi et al. 2013). There was also a 50% increase in cortical drive and a shift in the H reflex curve. These exciting findings were not observed following the control intervention and are similar to those reported in a study that investigated the effects of three weeks of strength training (Vila-Cha, Falla, Correia, &amp; Farina, 2012).
In this proposed study we plan to expand on these findings to investigate whether chiropractic care also influences upper limb muscle function and neurological control. This study could have significant implications for our understanding of the effects of chiropractic care on sports performance. If the findings corroborate our previous work it will add weight to the hypothesis that increased strength and the prevention of fatigue may occur following chiropractic adjustments, which will be an important consideration for athletes who are trying to achieve their optimum athletic performance. We will be measuring the following dependant measures from the deltoid muscle in the upper limb before and after a single session of adjusting subluxations;
Maximum isometric force production (to provide strength and fatigue measures)
Median frequency data from surface electromyography (another fatigue measure)
Proprioception in the form of a position sense task (functional performance measure)
Spinal stretch reflex function (for spinal cord excitability measure)
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern A Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Health and Disability Ethics Committees
Ministry of Health
C/- MEDSAFE, Level 6, Deloitte House
10 Brandon Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/03/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>13/NTA/236</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/12/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Imran Khan Niazi</name>
      <address>New Zealand College of Chiropractic 
6 Harrison Road, Ellerslie Auckland
1060</address>
      <phone>+6495266789</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>imran.niazi@nzchiro.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Heidi Haavik</name>
      <address>New Zealand College of Chiropractic 
6 Harrison Road, Ellerslie Auckland
1060</address>
      <phone>+6495266789</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>heidi.haavik@nzchiro.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Imran Khan Niazi</name>
      <address>New Zealand College of Chiropractic 
6 Harrison Road, Ellerslie Auckland
1060</address>
      <phone>+6495266789</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>imran.niazi@nzchiro.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kelly Holt</name>
      <address>New Zealand College of Chiropractic 
6 Harrison Road, Ellerslie Auckland
1060</address>
      <phone>+6495266789</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kelly.holt@nzchiro.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>