<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364979">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/09/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/09/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001081707</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Exploring the effects of different ways of communicating fracture risk and treatment benefits would influence patients' beliefs of risk of fracture and osteoporosis treatment to reduce their fracture risk.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of different approaches to communicating fracture risk to adults on their perceived risk of osteoporotic fracture and hip fracture at which treatment would be considered.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Osteoporosis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Fracture risk communication</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoporosis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fractures</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will complete a questionnaire regarding clinical history, have their bone density measured, and then complete a short questionnaire exploring their beliefs about their risk of fracture and the benefits they might obtain from treatment. Their absolute risk of osteoporotic fracture and hip fracture within the next 5 years will be calculated. Participants will then be randomised to receive one of four different presentations of their absolute risk, and the likely benefits they could expect from osteoporosis treatment (option 1: framed as the chance of having an event, option 2: the chance of not having an event, option 3: the number needed to treat to prevent an event, and option 4: the number needed to treat to prevent an event, with presentation of number treated without benefit).
Participants will then complete a short questionnaire (immediately and at 3 months) exploring whether the knowledge of their absolute risk of fracture has influenced their beliefs about their personal risk of fracture, their willingness to take treatment, and the benefits of treament.
All the questionnaires are administered as a written information.</interventions>
    <comparator>All 4 groups with 4 differents presentaions of fracture risk and treatment benefits are compared.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome> The primary outcome is the perceived risk of total fracture and hip fracture at which treatment would be considered. The primary outcome is assessed by administering questionnaires at the time of bone density scan, 3 months after their bone density scan and randomisation.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months after the bone density scan and randomisation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceived need for treatment, assessed by administering questionnaire at the time of bone density scan and 3 months after the bone density scan and randomisation. </outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months after bone density scan and randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceived threshold for fracture, assessed by administering questionnaire at the time of bone density scan and 3 months after the bone density scan and randomisation. </outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months after bone density scan and randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Age &gt;60y (because the Garvan absolute fracture risk calculator does not estimate fracture risk for younger participants).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>100</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients taking antiresorptive treatment for osteoporosis.
Unable to complete the questionnaires, for language or cognitive reasons
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>200 consecutive English speaking patients &gt; 60 years of age, attending the University of Auckland bone densitometry service will be recruited after written informed consent. Allocation is not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomised as per computer generated random numbers to one of the four different ways of presenting risk of fracture and treatment benefits.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>The primary analysis will be a comparison between the four randomised groups for the perceived risks of total fracture and hip fracture at which treatment would be considered. Secondary analyses will be comparisons between the four groups for the perceived risk of fracture, the perceived need for treatment, the perceived thresholds for risk of fracture, and comparisons between the baseline data and the data post provision of the participants risk of fracture will be undertaken for all of these variables. Differences in continuous variables will be tested with one way ANOVA or t-tests as appropriate, and differences in categorical tests tested using chi-square tests or McNemars test. 

This is a novel study and it is difficult to estimate what effect sizes we will observe. Therefore a power calculation is problematic. We estimate that recruiting 200 patients is feasible and can be achieved in a timely period (&lt; 3 months). With 50 patients per group, the largest confidence interval for a percentage result is 14% (when the result is 50%). Thus, a difference of approximately 20% could be detected in a pairwise comparison between 2 groups in this scenario. If the result was closer to 100% or 0%, the detectable difference becomes smaller.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/10/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Auckland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>85, Park Road
Grafton
Auckland 1023</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Auckland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>85, Park Road
Grafton
Auckland
New Zealand 1023</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Osteoporosis (thin bones) is a common disorder in New Zealand. Having thin bones increases the chance that a fracture (broken bone) will occur. Prevention of fracture is currently best achieved by identifying those people at higher risk of fracture and treating them with medications that are known to reduce fracture risk.
Effective communication of information about risk is therefore very important in managing bone health. There are different ways of presenting information about risk- for example, risk can be framed positively (you have a 5% chance of a particular outcome) or negatively (you have a 95% chance of NOT having that outcome), or can be presented using any of several numerical methods. Our study aims to explore the presenting risk in different ways on people's attitudes to, and beliefs about, bone health.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Diability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>1 The Terrace
C/- MEDSAFE, Level 6, Deloitte House
10 Brandon Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/09/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>13/CEN/127</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/09/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ramanamma Kalluru</name>
      <address>85, Park Road,
Bone and Joint Research group
Level 4, Building 502
University Auckland
Grafton
Auckland 1023
</address>
      <phone>+64 9 9234139</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.kalluru@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ramanamma Kalluru</name>
      <address>85, Park Road
Bone and Joint Research group
Level 4, Building 502
University Auckland
Grafton
Auckland 1023</address>
      <phone>+64 9 9234139</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.kalluru@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mark Bolland</name>
      <address>85, Park Road,
Bone and Joint Research group
Level 4, Building 502
University Auckland
Grafton
Auckland 1023</address>
      <phone>+64 9 9233004</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.bolland@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ramanamma Kalluru</name>
      <address>85, Park Road
Bone and Joint Research group
Level 4, Building 502
University Auckland
Grafton
Auckland 1023</address>
      <phone>+64 9 9234139</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.kalluru@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>