<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367562">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/12/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/12/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001313628</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of the Pharmacokinetics and Safety of Rivastigmine Intranasal Spray</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Sequential, Crossover, Pharmacokinetic and Safety Study of Single Dose Rivastigmine Intranasal Spray (3.126mg) and Single Dose Intravenous Solution (1mg) to Evaluate the Absolute Bioavailability of Rivastigmine Intranasal Spray in Healthy Elderly Volunteers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Alzheimer's disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Alzheimer's disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Arm 1: First day, Intravenous Rivastigmine 1mg (delivered by infusion pump over 30 minutes) followed by a 2-day washout

Arm 2: Fourth day, Rivastigmine Intranasal Spray 3.126mg as single dose (One spray each nostril)</interventions>
    <comparator>Arm 1: Intravenous Rivastigmine 1mg</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetics: F, Cmax, tmax, AUC0-infinity, t1/2, Cavg

Plasma assay for rivastigmine and its' primary metabolite (NAP 226-90) and pharmacokinetic parameters calculated using noncompartmental pharmacokinetic analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nasal: Pre-dose, 5, 10, 15, 30, 60, 90 mins; 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12 and 24 h
IV:  Pre-dose, 10, 20, 30, 45, 60, 75, 90 mins; 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 12 and 24 h</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety: Adverse events reporting, visual nasal mucosal examination and healthy screen pre- and post-study

Healthy screen includes: Physical examination, including vital signs (blood pressure, heart rate, respiratory rate and temperature) and ECG. Urinalysis for general health (urine pH, blood, protein, ketones, leukocyte elastase, nitrates, glucose, Specific gravity, urobilinogen and bilirubin) and any drugs of addiction*. Blood collected for clinical laboratory analysis (serum chemistry and haematology) and analysis for HIV*, hepatitis B*, and hepatitis C* analysis. Normal ranges for clinical laboratory parameters will be as per the local laboratory definitions.
*Pre-study</outcome>
      <timepoint>Visual nasal mucosal examination at screening, check-in, day 4 (pre-nasal-dose) and day 5 (24 hours post-nasal-dose).

Adverse events are monitored from Day 1 until Day 5 (24 hours post-nasal-dose) and at follow-up visit (Day 9 +/- 1).

Healthy screens are undertaken at screening, admission (Day -1) and on Day 5 (24 hours post-nasal-dose). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Healthy Caucasian males and females between 55 and 85 years (inclusive) of age.
- No known history of clinically significant neurological, renal, cardiovascular, respiratory (asthma), endocrinological, gastrointestinal, haematopoietic disease, neoplasm or any other clinically significant medical disorder, which in the Principal Investigator's judgment contraindicate administration of the study interventions.
- BMI 18-32 (inclusive) calculated as Weight (Kg)/Height (sq.m).
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>55</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Known hypersensitivity to the drug, components (benzyl alcohol, benzoates) or other carbamates.
- Current symptomatic allergic rhinitis
- History of or currently active asthma or chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, excluding childhood asthma.
- History of or currently active cardiac arrhythmias such as bradycardia and sick sinus syndrome. 
- History of urinary tract obstruction.
- History of or currently active GI diseases such as peptic ulcer, GERD, bleeding or history of any GI surgery other than appendectomy or herniotomy, or with any gastrointestinal disorder likely to influence drug absorption, or with any history of anorexia, frequent nausea or emesis, regardless of etiology.
- Use of any beta-blocker class prescription drug, cholinomimetic and anticholinergic drugs, including atropine, tricyclic antidepressants and anti-histamines.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Pharmacokinetics</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>10/03/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>20/03/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>8</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Lachesis Biosciences Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>24 Mickle Crescent, Warrnambool VIC 3280</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Lachesis Biosciences Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>24 Mickle Crescent, Warrnambool VIC 3280</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Rivastigmine (RIV) is an acetylcholine esterase inhibitor which prevents neurotransmitter breakdown. As such it is currently approved for the treatment of neurological disorders such as Alzheimer's and Parkinson's disease. RIV is available in two forms, oral (capsule and liquid) and as a transdermal (through the skin) patch. The latter was developed as a consequence of the oral forms causing nausea, vomiting and diarrhoea predominantly caused by the low oral bioavailability of this drug. Although the transdermal patch overcomes a lot of these side effects, a high percentage of people suffer from skin irritation and possible sleeplessness. This study will investigate whether delivering RIV intranasally (into the nose), results in lower side effects, while maintaining the desired therapeutic effect. As such this study will compare the bioavailability of intranasal delivery to intravenous delivery of RIV at a level that is reported to be therapeutically beneficial. Each intervention will be as a single dose with thorough blood sampling over 24 hours to assess drug levels; each intervention will be separated by a 2 day washout period. This is an exploratory phase 1 trial in 8 healthy elderly males and females aged 55 to 85 years. While comparing the two delivery methods, this study will also investigate the safety and tolerability of intranasal Rivastigmine.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.clinicalstudies.com.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Alfred Health Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Alfred Hospital, Commercial Road, Melbourne, Victoria, 3004</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/12/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>538/14</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/11/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Bob Soh</name>
      <address>Nucleus Network Ltd, 5th Floor, Burnet Tower, AMREP Precinct, 89 Commercial Road, Melbourne, Victoria, 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 8900</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>b.soh@nucleusnetwork.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Tristan Iseli, PhD</name>
      <address>Nucleus Network Ltd, 5th Floor, Burnet Tower, AMREP Precinct, 89 Commercial Road, Melbourne, Victoria, 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 8900</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>t.iseli@nucleusnetwork.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Timothy Morgan, PhD</name>
      <address>Lachesis Biosciences Pty Ltd, 24 Mickle Crescent, Warrnambool VIC 3280</address>
      <phone>+61 3 5561 7758</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tim.morgan@lachesisbio.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Timothy Morgan, PhD</name>
      <address>Lachesis Biosciences Pty Ltd, 24 Mickle Crescent, Warrnambool VIC 3280</address>
      <phone>+61 3 5561 7758</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tim.morgan@lachesisbio.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>