<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364237">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/05/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/07/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000781741</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle> A Post Recall Clinical Follow-up of patients previously treated with the DePuy Articular Surface Replacement Hip System.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Clinical Follow-up of ASR patients Post -Recall

A 5 year Post Recall Clinical Follow-up study to collect longitudinal data from patients previously treated with the DePuy Articular Surface Replacement Hip System</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition> Clinical outcomes post hip replacement</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal musculoskeletal and cartilage development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>For 5 years post hip replacement, each study participant will be observed and  monitored for the rate of revision, adverse events/complications (local tissue reaction and metal ion levels in serum or whole blood) and patient reported outcome measures (PROMs), to determine potential predictors for these outcomes. 
A web-based data entry system managed  will collect data from multiple sites internationally to document the radiographic and clinical outcomes of the DePuy Articular Surface Replacement Hip systems.  All enrolled patients will be monitored with annual clinical exams and serum or whole blood levels of cobalt and chromium.  All data will be uploaded to the central database when the exams are performed. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>No control</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To monitor the outcomes of standard clinical care in terms of rate of revision and complications.
A complication is any untoward medical occurrence in a participant who has received the Articular Surface Replacement (ASR) Hip System.   It does not necessarily have to have a causal relationship with the Articular Surface Replacement (ASR) Hip System and can therefore, be any unfavorable and unintended sign (including an abnormal laboratory finding), symptom, or disease temporally associated with the use of a device, whether or not considered related to this device. An example is the detection of increased level of cobalt and / or chromium ion levels measured in serum or whole blood
 </outcome>
      <timepoint>Annually for 5 years post hip replacement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determinmation of patient recorded Outcome Measures via the  Harris Hip Score, Case Mix Indicator, EQ-5D score and UCLA questionnaires.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the completion of data collection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determination of the acetabular cup position from radiographs.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the completion of data collection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine the incidence of radiolucencies</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the completion of data collection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure cobalt and chromium ion serum levels. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At the enroment in the study and each annual vist for 5 years post hip replacement surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Observe any adverse local tissue reaction that may be attributable to the Articular Surface Replacement (ASR) Hip System</outcome>
      <timepoint>Annually for 5 years post hip replacement surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.Any patient with on-label use of the ASR-XL or ASR component system currently implanted. Manual addition of antibiotics to cement during arthroplasty is not considered to be off-label use.
2.Able to provide informed consent at those sites where this is required by the institutions institutional review (IRB) or ethics committee (EC).
3.Able to return for follow-up annually for 5 years.
4.Able to complete the required patient reported outcome measures.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.Any patient with off-label use indications for the ASR-XL or ASR component system. 
2.Any patient who received the ASR-XL implant as a result of a hip resurfacing conversion or a revision THA. 
3.Patients with difficulty in comprehending the Informed Consent Form for any reason.
4.The patient refuses to allow their medical records to be inspected by the Sponsor, representatives of the Sponsor, or the medical office staff.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Primary Outcome 
The following Data Analyses will be completed on the Primary Outcome.

Implant Failure/Survival Rate (time-to-event, revision surgery, from date of surgery)
1.Revision rate estimates and survival curves will be estimated via Kaplan-Meier curves 
2.For comparison across groups: log-rank tests (ex: difference in survival between genders)
3.For comparison to quantitative covariates: Cox proportional hazard models (ex: association of survival to age of patient).

Secondary Outcomes
The following Data Analyses will be completed on the Secondary Outcomes.

Adverse Local Tissue Reaction (ALTR)
1.The following summary statistics will be provided for 3 groups of patients after each follow-up visit: 
a.Number and proportion of patients with follow-up for each annual visit or later
b.Cumulative number and proportion of patients with ALTR: those that experienced ALTR in this interval or any previous interval
c.Cumulative number and proportion of patients with no diagnosis of ALTR up to each annual visit
2.Logistic Regression Models will be used to estimate rates and the relationship to covariates after each annual follow-up visit
3.Generalized Linear Mixed Models for binary data will be used to estimate the change in rates over time and how this relates to possible covariates

Metal Ion Levels in Serum or Whole Blood: Cobalt and Chromium
1.Summary Statistics will be provided after each follow-up visit (sample size, means, medians, standard deviation, and range).
2.Linear Regression Models will be used to estimate means and the relationship to covariates after each annual follow-up visit.
3.Generalized Linear Mixed Models for quantitative data will be used to estimate the change in outcomes over time and how this relates to possible covariates

Note: measures are expected to be right-skewed, so a median or Wilcoxon-type regression methods may be used.

Incidence of Radiolucencies
1.Logistic Regression Models will be used to estimate rates and the relationship to covariates after each annual follow-up visit
2.Generalized Linear Mixed Models for binary data will be used to estimate the change in outcomes over time and how this relates to possible covariates.

Four Surveys: UCLA, Harris Hip Score, Case Mix Indicator, and EQ-5D score
1.Linear Regression Models will be used to estimate means and the relationship to covariates after each annual follow-up visit
2.Generalized Linear Mixed Models for binary data will be used to estimate the change in outcomes over time and how this relates to possible covariates.

Determination of cup position from AP and shoot through radiographs (Martell technique)
1.The incidence of migration will be provided, where migration is determined radiographically.
2.Logistic Regression will be used to estimate rates and the relationship to other covariates at each follow-up visit.
3.Changes in cup position will be monitored with Generalized Linear Mixed Models.


</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>True</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Both</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/05/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>5000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,SA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Sportsmed SA Hospital - Stepney</hospital>
    <postcode>5069 - Stepney</postcode>
    <postcode>2150 - Parramatta</postcode>
    <postcode>3107 - Templestowe Lower</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Massachusetts General Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress> 55 Fruit Street Boston Massachusetts MA 02114 
 United States of America</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname> DePuy Orthopaedics, Inc.
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>700 Orthopaedic Drive
Warsaw, IN 46582 
United States of America
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname> The International Muscukloskeletal Research Institute</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The General Repatriation Hospital
216 Daws Road
Daw Park 
 SA 5042</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Aims of the project

The aims of this research project are to:

Collect information to monitor the health and  progress of in study participants who have been treated with either the Depuy ASR Trademark XL Acetabular Hip System or DePuy ASR Trademark Hip Resurfacing Systems. 

This is a global research project, coordinated by Massachusetts General Hospital (MGH), Boston Massachusetts USA, to be conducted at multiple sites worldwide. The International Musculoskeletal Research Institute Inc. (IMRI) is the contracted research Organisation to conduct this study in Australia at number of sites including the site of SPORTSMED SA.

MGH has a contract with Depuy Orthopaedics to undertake the study as a global research project
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Belberry Limited</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>229 Greenhill Road 
Dulwich SA 5065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/04/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2012-09-1077-A-1</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Stephen Graves</name>
      <address>Director, Arthroplasty Service &amp; Research, Department of Orthopaedics, Repatriation General Hospital, Daws Road, Daw Park SA 5041

</address>
      <phone> +61 08 82769666</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>segraves@aoanjrr.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Slav Lerner</name>
      <address>Harris Orthopaedic Laboratory 
Massachusetts General Hospital 
Fruit St.,  Jackson 1126 
Boston, MA 02114 

</address>
      <phone>+1-617-726-3607</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>VLERNER@PARTNERS.ORG</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Slav Lerner</name>
      <address>Harris Orthopaedic Laboratory 
Massachusetts General Hospital 
Fruit St.,  Jackson 1126 
Boston, MA 02114 </address>
      <phone>+1-617-726-3607</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>VLERNER@PARTNERS.ORG</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Peter Walters</name>
      <address>The International Musculoskeletal Research Institute Inc.
B-Block
Repatriation General Hospital
Daws Road, Daw Park
South Australia, 5041

</address>
      <phone>+ 61 08 8275 1135</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter.walters@imri.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>