<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336002">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/09/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/09/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000812099</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Getting better at chronic care in North Queensland:  A cluster randomized trial of patient-centred care delivered by Indigenous health professionals to Indigenous clients.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Getting better at chronic care in North Queensland:  A cluster randomized trial of patient-centred care delivered by Indigenous health professionals to Indigenous clients.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Renal Disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Hypertension</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Coronary Heart Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Nutrition, lifestyle support, drug management, physical activity support to participants, workshops and focus groups for participants, care planning with each participant. The intervention will involve treatment intensification including with insulin, nutrition coaching with families, and upskilling of health workers in clinical management. The frequency and duration of these sessions will be tailored to the needs of the community and the participants. This will include engaging with families to discuss nutrition, lifestyle support, smoking cessation and physical exercise, self-monitoring of conditions, and appropriate drug management, and using local resources to support effective client self-management. The unit of intervention is the COMMUNITY, via a designated specialist health worker. This means that out of the 12 participating communities, 6 communities will be randomly selected to undertake the intervention in the first 2 years. The remaining 6 communities (the control communities) will not take part in the intervention. Control communities will participate in the intervention in year 3 of the study with one IHW FTE will be recruited for each intervention site, who is eligible at HW Level 004. An Indigenous clinical support team (ICST) will train and mentor community-based IHWs (and the rest of the PHC team) to deliver intensive management for 5 common chronic conditions, with clear clinical and service goals.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control communities receive usual care during the intervention phase.  They will receive a similar intervention, informed by the trial results and agreed upon by partner organisations,  in year 4.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 1: reduction in glycated haemoglobin (HbA1c) among adults with diabetes, assessed through blood analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 18 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 1: Clinic care processes are improved.  

Assessment of this outcome will include checking of weight, waist circumference, HbA1c, blood pressure (BP), lipids, urinary albumin creatinine ratio (UACR) according to care plans (6 monthly and annually) plus vaccinations.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months after commencement of intervention and 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 2: Intermediate condition specific outcomes (other than HbA1c) eg blood pressure control, avoidable hospitalisations.

Assessment of this outcome will include tests of HbA1c, 6 monthly, and blood pressure six monthly.  Hospitalisations 12 monthly.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months after commencement of intervention and 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 3: Changes in client Quality of Life indicators and service satisfaction from baseline.

Assessment of this outcome will be through the administration of questionnaires such as; assessment of quality of life questionnaires (AQoL) and the SF-36, a health survey questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months after commencement of intervention and 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Indigenous patients from clinics in rural north Queensland, in the communities listed below, diagnosed at least one year prior to recruitment with diabetes (with HbA1c&gt; 8.5%) and at least one of the four following conditions:

1. Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease
2. Renal disease
3. Hypertension
4. Coronary heart disease.
Communities in rural north Queensland: Bamaga Umagico Seisia New Mapoon Injinoo Badu Island Napranum Old Mapoon Kowanyama Mossman Gorge Yarrabah Mareeba</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Over 65 years of age 
Major mental illness 
Chronic Renal Failure Stages 4 &amp; 5
Pregnancy</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Enrolment is by the health service from the diabetes register. Randomisation is by community. Allocation is concealed because clusters are randomly selected to the intervention group after enrolment of participants.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation.  All 12 community (cluster) names are placed into a hat, and the first 6 names removed from the hat receive the intervention.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This is a cluster trial.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>10/12/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>11/07/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>360</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>213</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>4876</postcode>
    <postcode>4875</postcode>
    <postcode>4874</postcode>
    <postcode>4871</postcode>
    <postcode>4873</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Queensland Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>147-163 Charlotte Street
Brisbane Qld 4000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Queensland Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>147-163 Charlotte Street
Brisbane Qld 4000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Apunipima Cape York Health Council</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>186 McCoombe Street
Bungalow Qld 4870</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Queensland</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Research and Innovation Division
Cumbrae Stewart Building
Brisbane Qld 4072</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The life expectancy gap for Indigenous people in Australia is 13 years and most of this gap is due to preventable chronic disease (diabetes, heart, lung and renal problems) in adults. Once people have these conditions, many complications can be prevented with good primary-level chronic care.  This project aims to introduce and evaluate a new strategy for integrated community-based, intensive chronic condition management in rural and remote Indigenous primary care services:  Diabetes, hypertension, coronary heart disease (CHD), renal disease and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD).

Proposed strategy: An intervention in 3 phases over 5 years:

1.  A trial of intensive locally delivered chronic care in 6 out of 12 participating sites in FNQ with clear clinical and quality-of-life outcomes;
2.  Review of lessons learned in the first phase trial, modified as necessary to reflect findings, a discussion about generalisability to the control sites in the trial, with an implementation plan and the development of a curriculum package for the program and;
3.  In collaboration with the trial partners(QH, Apunipima CYHC and local AMS where relevant), a more general system rollout of lessons learned, with potential regional implications of a patient-centred service delivery model, including workforce and funding applications.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>None</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Publications
1. Schmidt B, Wenitong M, Esterman A, Hoy W, Segal L, Taylor S, et al. Getting better at chronic care in remote communities: study protocol for a pragmatic cluster randomised controlled of community based management. BMC Public Health. 2012;12(1):1017. 

2.Johnson J, McDermott R, Clifton P, DOnise K, Taylor S, Preece C, et al. Characteristics of Indigenous adults with poorly controlled diabetes in north Queensland: implications for services. . BMC Public Health. 2015.

3. McDermott R, Schmidt B, Preece C, Owens  V, Taylor  S, Li M, et al. Community health workers improve diabetes care in remote Australian Indigenous communities: results of a pragmatic cluster randomized controlled trial. BMC Health Serv Res. 2015;15(68).

4. Schmidt B, Campbell S, McDermott R. Community health workers as chronic care coordinators: evaluation of an Australian Indigenous primary health care program. Australian and New Zealand Journal of Public Health. 2015:n/a-n/a.

5. McDermott R, Schmidt B, Wenitong M, Sinha A, Hoy W, Owens V, et al. Do Indigenous Health Workers improve chronic care for high risk adults in remote communities: lessons from a cluster randomised and implications for service delivery. Australian Diabetes Educator. 2015;18(3).

Poster presentations
2013 	PHCRIS Conference
Integrated community based/family-centred management of chronic conditions by Indigenous Health Workers for Indigenous clients in rural and remote Queensland: a cluster randomised controlled trial

2014	NT Chronic Disease conference
Getting Better at Chronic Care in North Queensland: Improving Health literacy for high risk Aboriginal and Torres Strait clients: the answer is in the community

2014       AITHM Conference Cairns
Improving health literacy for high risk Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander clients: The answer is in the community. 

2015	PHCRIS Conference
Community Health Workers reduce avoidable acute hospitalisations for diabetes: a cluster randomised trial in far north Queensland Indigenous communities

2015	PHCRIS conference
Getting Better at Chronic Care in North Queensland Measuring implementation fidelity: Assessment of a chronic disease case management model delivered by Indigenous Health Workers in remote communities

Conference presentations
2013  PHA - Social determinants of Health - Canberra - Barbara Schmidt &amp; Frank Hollingsworth:  Chronic Care Coordination by Indigenous Health Workers  A solution for better care?

2014  PHCRIS conference - Canberra - Dr Robyn McDermott: Getting Better at Chronic Care (GBACC) in North Queensland: a cluster RCT of community health worker care co-ordination in remote FNQ settings

2014  PHCRIS conference - Barbara Schmidt: Community Health Workers as chronic care coordinators: A mixed methods evaluation of Indigenous primary health care services in far north Queensland

2015 AITHM Conference, Cairns - Barbara Schmidt-Improving health literacy for high risk Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander clients: The answer is in the community. 

2015 Queensland Health Chronic Disease conference - Dr Robyn McDermott






</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Cairns Base Health Service District Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 902
Cairns Qld 4870</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/04/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/10/QCH/30-654</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Queensland, Medical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research and Innovation Division
Cumbrae Stewart Building
Brisbane Qld 4072</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/08/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2010001007</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of South Australia Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/09/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>P091/10</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/336002-Getting better at chronic care in north queensland.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/336002-Do Indigenous Health Workers Improve Chronic Care for High Risk Adults in Remote Communities.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/336002-Johnson 2015 BMC.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/336002-Schmidt_et_al-Australian_and_New_Zealand_Journal_of_Public_Health.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Robyn McDermott</name>
      <address>University of South Australia
CEA-01, GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 2922</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8302 2794</fax>
      <email>robyn.mcdermott@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Robyn McDermott</name>
      <address>University of South Australia
CEA-01, GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 2922</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8302 2794</fax>
      <email>robyn.mcdermott@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Khloe Xu</name>
      <address>University of South Australia
CEA-01, GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 2405</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8302 2794</fax>
      <email>Khloe.xu@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Robyn McDermott</name>
      <address>University of South Australia CEA-01, GPO Box 2471 Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 2922 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>robyn.mcdermott@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>