<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335027">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/06/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/06/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000481077</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effectiveness of guideline driven antiemetic therapy versus single agent antiemetic therapy in patients with cancer and nausea not related to cancer therapy.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A two-stage trial of response to antiemetic therapy in patients with cancer and nausea not related to anticancer therapy.
 
Study 1: A randomised open label study of guideline driven targeted antiemetic therapy versus single agent antiemetic therapy.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Nausea in the setting of advanced cancer not related to anticancer therapy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cancer types</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a multi-centre, open label randomised parallel arm trial to determine whether guideline driven (targeted) aetiology based antiemetic therapy is more effective than single agent therapy with haloperidol in patients with cancer and nausea not related to anticancer therapy. 
Participants will be randomised to active treatment arms 1 or 2.

In each trial arm, the duration of each step is 24 hours and the overall duration of treatment is 72 hours (3 days) after administration of the first study antiemetic. The mode of administration will be a clinician decision based on patient characteristics.

Abbreviations: subcutaneous (sc), po (orally), bd (twice daily), iv (intravenously), tds (three dimes/day), qid (four times /day), Q4/6h (every 4/6 hours), prn (as required). 

Rescue medication for all patients will be metoclopramide (10mg po, sc, iv, prn q4h). If this dose is already delivered in the standard treatment (Arm 1), haloperidol (0.5mg po, sc, prn to q6h) will be administered. 

Patients will have access to laxatives according to clinician practice.

Arm 1 Clinical Practice Guideline (CPG) driven antiemetic therapy, given orally or parenterally (subcutaneous or intravenous), according to the presumed cause of nausea, using freely available Pharmaceutical Benefits Scheme (PBS) listed antiemetics, in a 3 step dose escalation schedule. The duration of each step is 24 hours. Overall duration of treatment is 72 hours.  

Treatment drugs are prochlorperazine, haloperidol, dexamethasone, promethazine, metoclopramide, hyoscine butylbromide, ranitidine.  

CPG dosing schedule and drug selection by cause: If there are multiple causes, the most likely cause is chosen from the following schedule. Note: sc drug delivery can be in a 24hr infusion, except for Dexamethasone which is not given as an infusion.

Dominant Cause A: Central/Chemoreceptive Trigger Zone (CTZ) stimulation
Step 1 Prochlorperazine 5mg tds po
           or 25mg PR followed by 5mg tds po 
           or 12.5mg bd iv
Step 2: Haloperidol 1.5mg/24hrs po or sc
Step 3: Haloperidol 3mg/24hrs po or sc

Dominant Cause B: Central Nervous System (CNS) disease 
Step 1 Dexamethasone 8mg/24hrs po/sc/iv
Step 2 Dexamethasone 12mg/24hrs po/sc/iv
Step 3 Dexamethasone 16mg/24hrs po/sc/iv

Dominant Cause C: Vestibular involvement (nausea related to abnormalities of the middle ear or motion and/or positional nausea)
Step 1 Prochlorperazine 5mg tds po 
           or 25mg per rectum (PR) followed by 5mg tds po 
           or 12.5mg bd iv
Step 2 Prochlorperazine 10mg tds po 
           or 25mg PR followed by 10mg tds po
           or 12.5mg tds iv 
Step 3 Promethazine 25 mg tds po 
           or 12.5mg sc followed by 10mg tds po

Dominant Cause D: Gastric stasis
Step 1 Metoclopramide 10mg qid po/sc/iv
Step 2 Metoclopramide 10mg Q4h po/sc/iv 
           (patients must receive at least 5 doses of 4 hourly metoclopramide/24hours)
Step 3 Metoclopramide 10mg Q4h po/sc/iv,  
           Dexamethasone 8mg/24hrs po/sc/iv

Dominant Cause E: Ileus	
Step 1 Metoclopramide 10mg qid po/sc/iv
Step 2 Metoclopramide 10mg Q4h po/sc/iv
Step 3 Metoclopramide 10mg Q4h po/sc/iv, 
           Dexamethasone 8mg/24hrs po/sc/iv

Dominant Cause F: Mechanical obstruction
Step 1 Haloperidol 1.5mg/24hrs po/sc,
           Dexamethasone 8mg/24hrs	
Step 2 Haloperidol 3mg/24hrs po/sc,
           Dexamethasone 8mg/24hrs	
Step 3 Haloperidol 3mg/24hrs po/sc,
           Dexamethasone 8mg/24hrs po/sc/iv, 
           Hyoscine butlybromide 80mg/24hrs sc or Ranitidine 200mg/24hrs sc (in patients where there is a realistic chance of bowel obstruction).

Dominant Cause G: Gastritis
Step 1 Metoclopramide10mg qid po/sc/iv, Proton Pump Inhibitors (PPI) min dose
Step 2 Metoclopramide 10mg qid po/sc/iv, PPI max dose
Step 3 Metoclopramide 10mg Q4h po/sc/iv, PPI max dose 
           (PPI choice according to local policy)

Dominant Cause H: Cause undetermined (or multifactorial)
Step 1 Metoclopramide 10mg qid po/sc/iv
Step 2 Metoclopramide 10mg qid po/sc/iv,
           Haloperidol 1.5mg/24hrs po/sc	
Step 3 Metoclopramide 10mg Q4h po/sc/iv,
           Haloperidol 3mg/24hrs sc

Arm 2 Haloperidol, in a 3 step dose escalation schedule from 1mg/24 hours to 3mg/24 hours orally or parenterally (subcutaneously).

Participants with intolerable nausea despite maximum breakthrough doses can proceed to Study 2 prior to the next 24 hour assessment. Participants already on Step 3 should be considered for Study 2.

Treatment after the 72 hour trial period should be at the clinicians discretion if the patient does not continue to study 2.

For all study participants, secondary outcomes and collection of data for safety will occur until the end of 4 weeks after the primary endpoint, unless consent is withdrawn.</interventions>
    <comparator>Antiemetic CPG driven (targeted) therapy according to the presumed cause of nausea, using freely available PBS listed antiemetics</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Response to treatment at 72 hours. Response is defined as an improvement of at least two points in average nausea score from baseline and final score less than 3, measured for the previous 24 hours on an 11-point (0-10) numeric rating scale (NRS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Average nausea: Baseline, 24, 48 and 72 hours after first study antiemetic administered
Response: At 24, 48 and 72 hours after first study antiemetic administered.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Best nausea score measured on an 11-point (0-10) NRS.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 24, 48 and 72 hours after first study antiemetic administered.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Worst nausea score measured on an 11-point (0-10) NRS.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 24, 48 and 72 hours after first study antiemetic administered.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of rescue doses delivered, obtained from medical records of drug and dose recorded by treating nurse.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At each 24 hour assessment after first study antiemetic administered until final assessment 24 hours after last antiemetic administered (i.e. 24, 48 and 72 hours after first antiemetic administered).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of patients treated at each dose level determined from medical records kept by treating nurse.</outcome>
      <timepoint>When drugs are administered: At baseline, 24 and 48 hours after first study antiemetic administered.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of patients with nausea who were not eligible for study 1 and proceeded to study 2, determined as those who have received appropriate antiemetics at sufficient dose (equivalent to step 3 in the antiemetic guidelines) and report refractory nausea (defined as an average nausea score greater than or equal to 3).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At recruitment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of participants with nausea refractory to either targeted or single agent therapy. Refractory nausea is defined as an average nausea score greater than or equal to 3, measured for the previous 24 hours on an 11-point (0-10) NRS.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 24, 48 and 72 hours after first study antiemetic administered.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of participants with refractory nausea (nausea score greater than or equal to 3) who proceeded to study 2 after completion of study 1, 72 hours after the first study antiemetic was administered.</outcome>
      <timepoint>On completion of study, 72 hours after first study antiemetic administered.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of episodes of vomiting experienced, patient self-reported on nurse-held records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At each 24 hour assessment after first antiemetic administered until final assessment 24 hours after last antimetic administered (i.e., 24, 48 and 72 hours after first antiemetic administered).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Toxicity identified by the National Cancer Institute Adverse Events Criteria (V4.0)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At each 24 hour assessment after first antiemetic administered until final assessment 24 hours after last antimetic administered (i.e., 24, 48 and 72 hours after first antiemetic administered).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of patients randomised to the guideline therapy arm who comply with the antiemetic guidelines, patient reported on nurse-held records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At each 24 hour assessment after first antiemetic administered until final assessment 24 hours after last antimetic administered (i.e., 24, 48 and 72 hours after first antiemetic administered).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients who: are 18 years or over, have a clinical diagnosis of cancer, 	have nausea with an average score over the last 24 hours of greater than or equal to 3 on an 11 point numerical rating scale (NRS) anchored at 0 (no nausea) and 10 (worst possible nausea), are not currently receiving antiemetics or are already receiving antiemetics but these are inappropriate as defined by the antiemetic guidelines or are at a suboptimal dose, are able to comply with all trial requirements, are able to provide fully informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients who: have nausea related to the treatment of cancer (i.e. surgery, chemotherapy, radiotherapy) where acute treatment with 5HT3 antagonists is indicated (i.e. within 5 days of anticancer therapy), have nausea for which a specific antiemetic is indicated and randomisation to haloperidol would not be appropriate (e.g. dexamethasone for acutely raised ICP), have undergone a procedure or intervention with the potential to affect nausea within 2 days prior to study or are likely to undergo a procedure or intervention with the potential to affect nausea during the 3 day study period, if on corticosteroids, the dose has changed within 48 hours prior to study, have a definite contraindication to any of the drugs listed in the guidelines (e.g. Parkinsons disease, QTc prolongation on most recent ECG (&gt;450msecs in men, &gt;470msecs in women), uncontrolled seizures), have had a prior serious adverse event following use of any of the drugs listed in the guidelines (e.g. dystonic reaction, neuroleptic malignant syndrome), are pregnant or breastfeeding </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All patients under the care or shared care of the palliative care team and all potential participants attending clinic will be screened by the study nurse for their suitability to enter the study in consultation with the treating clinician and nursing staff. The study nurse will ask the clinician in charge for permission to approach potentially eligible participants. This referral will be recorded within both the Case Report Form (CRF) and the participant clinical file. After checking with the clinical team to make sure the person meets the broad criteria for consideration of eligibility, that the person has given explicit permission to be seen by a researcher, and is well enough to be approached, the study nurse will introduce themself to the person and explain the study. If participants are suitable for entry and prepared to consent to the study, they will undergo baseline assessments and assessment of eligibility criteria. On notification of a participant, the site co-ordinator will consult the central registry to obtain the next code available. The Principal Investigator will then chart and order the allocated medication according to the code. A screening log will be kept of all potentially eligible participants including the reasons for non-entry.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation schedules will be developed for each site using random numbers generated by computer at an independent centre. Treatment for each patient will be allocated according to a block randomisation schedule held by the central registry at the Queensland University of Technology. Site coordinators will contact the central registry to obtain random allocation once consent has been obtained. Block randomisation within the centre will ensure even allocation to each code in each site. Sites will not be informed of the block size in order to minimise bias in patient allocation.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>None</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/06/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>19/10/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>29/04/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>216</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>185</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital Brisbane - Kangaroo Point</hospital>
    <hospital>Sacred Heart Hospice - Darlinghurst</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - City campus - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>3065</postcode>
    <postcode>2310</postcode>
    <postcode>2164</postcode>
    <postcode>2217</postcode>
    <postcode>5041</postcode>
    <postcode>3002</postcode>
    <postcode>4101</postcode>
    <postcode>3181</postcode>
    <postcode>3215</postcode>
    <postcode>4169 - Kangaroo Point</postcode>
    <postcode>2010 - Darlinghurst</postcode>
    <postcode>3050 - Royal Melbourne Hospital</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Patsy Yates</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Queensland University of Technology
School of Nursing and Midwifery
Victoria Park Road
Kelvin Grove QLD 4059</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Palliative Care Clinical Studies Collaborative</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Flinders University
700 Goodwood Rd
Daw Park SA 5041</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Nausea in advanced cancer is a multifaceted problem. Recent systematic reviews have concluded that aetiology based guidelines may be effective in reducing nausea, but no rigorously controlled studies have been undertaken to trial this approach. Moreover, evidence to support the implementation of guidelines in practice is limited and contradictory, and a number of barriers to the implementation of the guidelines have been identified. 

This is a randomised open label study to compare the effectiveness of aetiology based antiemetic guideline therapy (targeted) versus haloperidol (single agent therapy) in improving the management of nausea not related to anticancer therapy in patients with advanced cancer. The hypothesis is that for advanced cancer patients with nausea not related to treatment, there is no difference in response to targeted aetiology-based antiemetic guideline treatment compared to using haloperidol alone, after 72 hours of treatment. Response to treatment is defined as a minimum two point improvement from baseline and end score &lt;3 on an 11 point (0-10) numeric rating scale for average nausea for the previous 24 hours, measured 72 hours after the first study antiemetic administered
Participants will be randomised into one of two study arms. In Arm 1, guideline driven antiemetic therapy is given orally or parenterally (subcutaneous or intravenous) according to the presumed cause of nausea using freely available PBS listed antiemetics in a 3 step dose escalation schedule. In Arm 2, Haloperidol is administered in a 3 step dose escalation schedule from 1mg/24 hours to 3mg/24hours orally or parenterally (subcutaneously). The active comparator is standard guideline treatment.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>1. Hardy J, O'Shea A, Gilbert C, Norris R. Is levomepromazine stable over time? Palliat Medicine, 2010, 25 (3) 284-285.
2. Yates, P, (2012) Management of nausea. In OConnor, M., Lee, S. &amp; Aranda, S. Palliative Nursing: A Guide to Practice (3rd Ed). Ausmed: Melbourne.  
3. J Hardy. Symptom management in end-of-life care.  2011 RBWH Health Care Symposium, Brisbane, 13th October 2011.
4. Yates, P.  A randomised controlled trial of aetiology based guidelines for the management of nausea in advanced cancer: a work in progress.  11th Annual Palliative Care Research Conference, Royal Brisbane and Womens Hospital, 27th April 2012.
5. Hardy, J. &amp; Yates, P.  A two-stage trial of antiemetic therapy in patients with cancer and nausea not related to anticancer therapy. Palliative Care Clinical Studies Collaborative (PaCCSC) 3rd Research Forum, Sydney, 15th March 2012.
6. J Hardy, P Yates, P Martin, J Phillip, P Hudson, H Kerman, D Currow. Targeted versus single agent antiemetic therapy in patients with cancer and nausea not related to anticancer therapy The Australian and New Zealand Society of Palliative Medicine Inc. Conference. Queenstown, New Zealand, 4th  7th September 2012.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Mater Adult Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Raymond Terrace
South Brisbane QLD 4101</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/06/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1517A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/04/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Adelaide Palliative Services</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>700 Goodwood Road
Daw Park SA 5041</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/02/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>388.10</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>21/07/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>St Andrew's Place
East Melbourne VIC 3002</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/02/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/10/Alfred/22 SSA/10/PMCC/19 </hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/07/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 2900
Fitzroy VIC 3065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/11/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/10/Alfred/22 SSA/10/SVHM/33</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/07/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 315
Prahan VIC 3181</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/09/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/10/Alfred/22</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>21/06/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Barwon Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>45-95 Ballarat Rd
North Geelong VIC 3215</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/10/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/10/Alfred/22 AU/5/C12709</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/06/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Area Health Service</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Hunter Region Mail Centre
Warabrook NSW 2217</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/09/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/10/HNE/167 SSA/10/HNE/288</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/06/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Calvary Health Care</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>91-111 Rocky Point Road
Kogarah NSW 2217</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/02/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/10/HNE/167 2011.02.02</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/07/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Braeside Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Locked Bag 82
Wetherill Park NSW 2164</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/12/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/10/HNE/167 SSA/10/HOPE/13</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/07/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Health and Aged Care HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>48 Montpelier Road
Bowen Hills QLD 4004</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/03/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC #11/14</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/10/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital (Sydney) HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 6, deLacy Building
St Vincent's Hospital
390 Victoria St 
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/05/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Melbourne Health Human Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 6, Central Building
The Royal Melbourne Hospital
300 Gratten Street
Parkville VIC 3050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/05/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Patsy Yates</name>
      <address>Queensland University of Technology
School of Nursing and Midwifery
Victoria Park Road
Kelvin Grove QLD 4059</address>
      <phone>+ 61 7 3138 3835</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.yates@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Patsy Yates</name>
      <address>Queensland University of Technology
School of Nursing and Midwifery
Victoria Park Road
Kelvin Grove QLD 4059</address>
      <phone>+ 61 7 3138 3835</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.yates@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Helen Skerman</name>
      <address>Queensland University of Technology
Institute of Health and Biomedical Innovation
60 Musk Avenue
Kelvin Grove QLD 4059</address>
      <phone>+ 61 7 3138 6127</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>h.skerman@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Patsy Yates</name>
      <address>Queensland University of Technology School of Nursing  Victoria Park Road Kelvin Grove QLD 4059</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3138 3835</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.yates@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>