<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366914">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/08/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/09/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000939695</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>T3 Trial: Triage, Treatment and Transfer of Patients with Stroke in Emergency Departments</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A cluster randomised controlled trial to evaluate the effectiveness of a multidisciplinary organisational intervention to improve triage, treatment and transfer of acute stroke patients in Emergency Departments (EDs), relative to usual care, on death or dependency (defined as modified Rankin Scale [mRS] &gt;=2) 90-days post hospital admission. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1159-4170</utrn>
    <trialacronym>T3 Trial </trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>APP1024812</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Stroke</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Health services research</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>T3 Intervention
This organisational intervention will be implemented in Emergency Departments (EDs) and will target health care professional behaviour for acute stroke management. We will design evidence-based clinical protocols for triage, treatment and transfer following acute stroke. (Ai) routine assignment of stroke patients to triage Category 1 or 2; (Aii) time-sensitive trigger screening for tPA eligibility; (Aiii) instigation of protocols for prompt management of fever, hyperglycaemia and swallowing; (Aiv) rapid transfer of patients from ED to the stroke unit. These protocols will be implemented using an evidence-based implementation strategy consisting of: 
(Bi) workshops to identify local barriers and enablers and to identify clinical champions; (Bii) didactive and interactive education; (Biii) use of local clinical opinion leaders (site clinical champions); and (Biv) reminders in the form of email, telephone and site visits. The overall duration of the intervention period is anticipated to last for 12 to 18 months. Once we have recruited our required sample size the intervention period will cease.

For the duration of the trial, control group EDs will not receive any T3 Trial intervention elements.

As part of our intervention, site visits will be undertaken to discuss adherence to the intervention. This will be supported by email and telephone contact. Medical record audit will provide protocol adherence rates at the conclusion of the trial.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care

Usual care will be the current treatment that stroke patients receive when admitted to EDs randomised to the control group.  There will be no T3 trial intervention elements introduced at these sites.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Death or dependency (defined as modified Rankin Scale [mRS] &gt;= 2)


</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: 90-days post-hospital admission</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 1:
Barthel Index [BI]) &gt;= 95 (dependency score)

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: 90 days post hospital admission</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 2:
mean SF-36 Physical Component Score [PCS]

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: 90 days post hospital admission</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 3:
mean SF-36 Mental Component Score [MCS] 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: 90-days post-hospital admission</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Cluster level (ED): Hospitals with EDs located in the Australian states of New South Wales, Queensland, Victoria and Australian Capital Territory 

Patient level: English-speaking; admitted to the stroke unit via ED with a clinical diagnosis of ischaemic stroke or intracerebral haemorrhage; presented to hospital less than 48 hours from symptom onset; access to a telephone.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Presenting to hospital more than 48 hours from symptom onset; requiring palliative care only; identified non-cerebrovascular causes of acute focal neurological deficits (seizure, hypoglycaemia, toxic or metabolic encephalopathies); sub-arachnoid haemorrhage; and acute and chronic subdural haemorrhage.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Cluster level: Cluster guardians will provide written informed cluster consent, agreeing that their ED can be randomised to either the intervention or control arm of the trial. They will agree to the intervention becoming ‘business as usual’ should they be allocated to the intervention group. This is in contrast to Emergency departments randomised to the control arm who will just continue usual care.

Patient level: Clinical Research Assistants (CRAs) at each study site who will be masked to trial design will enrol eligible patients. All eligible patients will be given a Patient Information Statement (PIS) outlining the collection of data and the 90 days follow-up process. This PIS outlines the opt-out consent process, with contact details provided to the study team for further questions or to opt-out.

As this is a cluster randomised controlled trial, randomisation of EDs and allocation to either intervention or control group will be conducted simultaneously – see below.
</concealment>
    <sequence>Allocation will be based on clusters (EDs) rather than individuals. Each ED will be assigned a unique study number. EDs will be stratified by State and hospital baseline thrombolysis rates.

A list of participating EDs and stratification details will be provided in a de-identified format to an independent statistician not otherwise involved in the trial. Generation of the allocation sequence using random number generating software and assigning of EDs to either intervention or control group will be undertaken by this independent statistician.


</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>We plan to recruit 1160 patients from 26 clusters following implementation of the intervention and anticipate 9% loss to follow-up. With a 5% significance level and 80% power, assuming that 50% of patients in the usual care group will have mRS &gt;=2, 60% will have Barthel Index &gt;= 95, standard deviations for MCS and PCS of 11 and a design effect of 1.4 (the assumptions are based on our previous QASC Study), this will allow detection of a difference between intervention and control groups at 90 days post admission of: 

10% for mRS &gt;=2 (Primary outcome) 

10% for Barthel Index [BI]) &gt;= 95 (Secondary outcome 1);
0.2 standard deviations (~2.5 units) higher mean SF-36 Physical Component Score [PCS] (Secondary outcome 2); and
0.2 standard deviations (~2.5 units) higher mean SF-36 Mental Component Score [MCS] (Secondary outcome 3)

Analysis of outcomes will involve regression (logistic or linear as appropriate) with adjustment for clustering of patients within hospitals. We will undertake unadjusted analyses as well as analyses which adjust for baseline covariates. Primary analysis will be a complete case analysis with sensitivity analyses using multiple imputations to account for missing data.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>14/07/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/10/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1160</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,QLD,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Canberra Hospital - Garran</hospital>
    <hospital>Bankstown-Lidcombe Hospital - Bankstown</hospital>
    <hospital>Bathurst Base Hospital - Bathurst</hospital>
    <hospital>John Hunter Hospital Royal Newcastle Centre - New Lambton</hospital>
    <hospital>Liverpool Hospital - Liverpool</hospital>
    <hospital>Nepean Hospital - Kingswood</hospital>
    <hospital>Prince of Wales Hospital - Randwick</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>St George Hospital - Kogarah</hospital>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Darlinghurst) - Darlinghurst</hospital>
    <hospital>Westmead Hospital - Westmead</hospital>
    <hospital>Gold Coast Hospital - Southport</hospital>
    <hospital>Nambour General Hospital - Nambour</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>The Townsville Hospital - Douglas</hospital>
    <hospital>The Wesley Hospital - Auchenflower</hospital>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <hospital>Bendigo Health Care Group - Bendigo Hospital - Bendigo</hospital>
    <hospital>Box Hill Hospital - Box Hill</hospital>
    <hospital>Latrobe Regional Hospital - Traralgon</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - City campus - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Southwest Health Care - Warrnambool - Warrnambool</hospital>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne) Ltd - Fitzroy</hospital>
    <hospital>Geelong Private Hospital - Geelong</hospital>
    <hospital>Northeast Health Wangaratta - Wangaratta</hospital>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
    <postcode>2605 - Garran</postcode>
    <postcode>2200 - Bankstown</postcode>
    <postcode>2795 - Bathurst</postcode>
    <postcode>2305 - New Lambton</postcode>
    <postcode>2170 - Liverpool</postcode>
    <postcode>2750 - Penrith</postcode>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>2217 - Kogarah</postcode>
    <postcode>2010 - Darlinghurst</postcode>
    <postcode>2145 - Westmead</postcode>
    <postcode>4215 - Southport</postcode>
    <postcode>4810 - Townsville</postcode>
    <postcode>4066 - Auchenflower</postcode>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3550 - Bendigo</postcode>
    <postcode>3128 - Box Hill</postcode>
    <postcode>3050 - Royal Melbourne Hospital</postcode>
    <postcode>3280 - Warrnambool</postcode>
    <postcode>3065 - Fitzroy</postcode>
    <postcode>3220 - Geelong</postcode>
    <postcode>3677 - Wangaratta</postcode>
    <postcode>4560 - Nambour</postcode>
    <postcode>4006 - Herston</postcode>
    <postcode>3844 - Traralgon</postcode>
    <postcode>3181 - Prahran</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Prof Sandy Middleton</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Nursing Research Institute - SVHA (Syd) &amp; ACU
Executive Suite, Level 5, deLacy Building
St Vincent's Hospital, Victoria Street, Darlinghurst   NSW 2010
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (4PP1024812)



</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council, GPO Box 1421, Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Australian Catholic University


</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>PO Box 968, North Sydney, NSW, 2059</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In 2011, members of our research team published the results of the Quality in Acute Stroke Care (QASC) Trial.  This cluster randomised controlled trial evaluated the effectiveness of team-building workshops and education to introduce three clinical protocols to manage fever, sugar and swallowing (the FeSS protocols) in the acute stroke unit.  We found that patients cared for in stroke units who received our intervention were 16% more likely to be alive and independent 90 days following their stroke.  They also had fewer episodes of fever, lower mean temperatures, lower mean blood glucose levels, and better screening for swallowing difficulties.  This landmark trial demonstrated that teamwork and good nursing care can improve patient outcomes.  
Building on this previous work (1) we will evaluate using a cluster randomised controlled trial, an organisational intervention in EDs.  Our evidence-based T3 Trial intervention will comprise: A) evidence-based clinical protocols for triage, treatment and transfer in acute stroke comprised of: (Ai) routine assignment of stroke patients to triage Category 1 or 2; (Aii) time-sensitive trigger screening for tPA eligibility; (Aiii) instigation of protocols for prompt management of fever, hyperglycaemia and swallowing; (Aiv) rapid transfer of patients from ED to the stroke unit.  To support implementation of the protocols we will use: B) an evidence based implementation strategy consisting of: (Bi) workshops to identify local barriers and enablers and to identify clinical champions; (Bii) didactive and interactive education; (Biii) use of local clinical opinion leaders (site clinical champions); and (Biv) reminders in the form of email, telephone and site visits.
This trial will be conducted in the EDs of hospitals with pre-existing dedicated stroke units in NSW, Victoria, Queensland and the ACT. EDs will be randomised to receive either the T3 Trial intervention or no additional support.  At 90-days post-admission, we will measure death or dependency (mRS) (primary outcome); health status; and quality of life (secondary outcomes).  A separate process analysis will examine contextual factors that may influence successful intervention uptake.  Our novel and timely intervention will bridge the theory-practice gap aiming to deliver improvements in 90-day health outcomes for a group of patients currently underserved by evidence-based practice

Reference
1.	Middleton S, McElduff P, Ward J, Grimshaw J, Dale S, DEste C, Drury P, Griffiths R, Cheung NW, Quinn C, Evans M, Cadilhac D, Levi C. Implementation of evidence-based treatment protocols to manage fever, hyperglycaemia and swallowing dysfunction in acute stroke improves 90-day outcomes: QASC, a cluster randomised controlled trial. The Lancet 2011; 378 (9804): 1699-1706.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Published abstracts

Dale S, Martinez C, McInnes E and Middleton S. How ethical is the process of ethics and governance review for multi-site trials? Results from the T3 Trial. International Journal of Stroke. 2014; 9(S1) 13
S Middleton, CR Levi, C DEste, J Grimshaw, DA Cadilhac, J Considine, W Cheung, L McInnes. S Dale, RP Gerraty, M Fitzgerald. T3 Trial protocol: A CRCT evaluating an organisational intervention to improve triage, treatment and transfer of stroke patients in EDs. International Journal of Stroke. 2013;8(S1) 410
Middleton S, Levi C, DEste C, Grimshaw J, Cadilhac D, Considine J, Cheung W, McInnes L, Dale S, Gerraty R, Fitzgerald M, Cadigan G, Denisenko S, Longworth M, McElduff P, Quinn C. T3 stroke trial protocol: Triage, treatment and transfer of patients with stroke emergency departments. International Journal of Stroke. 2013;8(S2), 134

Conference Presentations

Dale S, Levi C, DEste C, Grimshaw J, Cadilhac D, Considine J, Cheung W,McInnes E, Gerraty R, Fitzgerald M, Middleton S, on behalf of the T3 Trialists. Translating evidence in stroke care: The T3 Trial Protocol. 2nd Annual NHMRC Symposium on Research Translation 2013. Sydney 2-3 October 2013

Middleton S. Levi C, DEste C, Cadilhac D, Considine J, Cheung W, McInnes E, Dale S, Quinn C on behalf of the T3 Trialists. Translating evidence in stroke care: The Triage, Treatment and Transfer Trial Study Protocol. 21st St Vincents &amp; Mater Health Sydney Research Symposium. Sydney: 6 September 2013. P.21.[Fast Forward Presentation &amp; poster]. 
** Winner Beckman Coulter Prize for Outstanding Poster Presentation**

Middleton S, Levi C, D'Este C, Grimshaw J, Cadilhac D, Considine J, Cheung W, McInnes E, Dale S &amp; Gerraty R.  T3 Stroke Trial Protocol: Triage, Treatment and Transfer of patients with stroke Emergency Departments.  Smart Stroke Conference 2013. Brisbane; 22-23 August 2013. 

Middleton S, Levi C, D'Este C, Grimshaw J, Cadilhac D, Considine J, Cheung W, McInnes E, Dale S &amp; Gerraty R.  T3 Trial Protocol: A CRCT evaluating an organisational intervention to improve Triage, Treatment and Transfer of stroke patients in ED's. Stroke Society of Australasia Annual Scientific Meeting 2013. Darwin, 31 July  1 August 2013. [Poster]

Middleton S, Levi C,DEste C, Grimshaw J, Cadilhac D, Considine J, Cheung W, McInnes E, Dale S, Gerraty R, &amp; Fitzgerald M, on behalf of the T3 Trialists. T3 Stroke Trial: Protocol for a Cluster Randomised Controlled Trial to evaluate an organisational intervention to improve Triage, Treatment and Transfer of stroke patients in Emergency Departments. European Stroke Conference 2013. London, 28-31 May 2013. [Poster]
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Our trial has a pre-intervention observational phase to inform trial recruitment methods and obtain baseline data to inform randomisation and sample size estimation. Recruitment has not yet commenced for the randomised (post-intervention) phase of the trial.</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Local Health District Ethics Review Committee (RPAH Zone)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>c/- Research Development Office
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
CAMPERDOWN NSW 2050 
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/04/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/12/RPAH/32</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Australian Catholic University Human Ethics Research Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Locked Bag 4115, Fitzroy, VIC, 3065



</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/03/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2012 16N</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Wangaratta Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 386 Wangaratta VIC 3676





</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/10/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>111</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South West Healthcare Multidisciplinary Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ryot Street, Warrnambool, Vic, 3280



</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/10/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>5/2012</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Uniting Care Health, Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Upper Floor Moorlands House, The Wesley Hospital, 451 Coronation Drive, Auchenflower, Qld, 4066



</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/12/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1231</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>ACT Government Health Directorate Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Building 10, Level 6, Canberra Hospital, PO Box 11, Woden, ACT, 2606

</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/02/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>ETH.1.13.009</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Sandy Middleton</name>
      <address>Nursing Research Institute St Vincents Health Australia (Sydney) &amp; Australian Catholic University, Executive Suite, Level 5, DeLacy Building, St Vincents Hospital, Victoria Road, Darlinghurst, NSW, 2010, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 2 83823790 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sandy.middleton@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Sandy Middleton</name>
      <address>Nursing Research Institute St Vincents Health Australia (Sydney) &amp; Australian Catholic University, Executive Suite, Level 5, DeLacy Building, St Vincents Hospital, Victoria Road, Darlinghurst, NSW, 2010, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 2 83823790 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sandy.middleton@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Sandy Middleton</name>
      <address>Nursing Research Institute St Vincents Health Australia (Sydney) &amp; Australian Catholic University, Executive Suite, Level 5, DeLacy Building, St Vincents Hospital, Victoria Road, Darlinghurst, NSW, 2010, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 2 83823790 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sandy.middleton@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Simeon Dale</name>
      <address>Nursing Research Institute St Vincents Health Australia (Sydney) &amp; Australian Catholic University, Executive Suite, Level 5, DeLacy Building, St Vincents Hospital, Victoria Road, Darlinghurst, NSW, 2010, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 2 83824027</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>simeon.dale@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>