<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347754">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/12/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/01/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000107820</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effects of Sterofundin versus Ringer's Lactate on Acid-base balance and electrolyte status in paediatric patients undergoing major urogenital surgery.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Sterofundin versus ringer's lactate on improvement of acid-base and electrolytes status in paediatric patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>1.	to determine any significant differences in acid base balance in paediatric patients undergoing major surgery .</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>2.	to determine any significant differences in electrolyte balance and haemodynamic stability in paediatric patients undergoing major surgery.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other anaesthesiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>administration of sterofundin as main intraoperative fluid in patients.
Sterofundin is used for maintenance of intra-operative fluid (amount according to 4:2:1 rule ie 4mls/kg for 1st 10kg, then 2mls/kg for next 10 kg and 1ml/kg for the remaining weight of the patient). It is also used for replacement of less than 10% plasma volume losses where replacement is given via intra venous route.</interventions>
    <comparator>administration of ringer's lactate as main intraoperative fluid in patients.
Ringers lactate is a balanced solution containing sodium (130mmol/l), potassium (5mmol/l), calcium and magnesium (both at 1mmol/l), chloride (112mmol/l) and lactate (27mmol/l) therefore it is actually slightly hypotonic. Its osmolarity is 276mOsm/l which renders it slightly hypo-osmolar to plasma.
Ringer's Lactate is used for maintenance of intra-operative fluid (amount according to 4:2:1 rule ie 4mls/kg for 1st 10kg, then 2mls/kg for next 10 kg and 1ml/kg for the remaining weight of the patient). It is also used for replacement of less than 10% plasma volume losses where replacement is given via intra venous route.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>pH via arterial blood gases measurements.
Arterial blood gases are taken at start (baseline) then hourly during the surgery and the last arterial blood gas is taken one hour postoperatively.
From the arterial blood gas results, pH, PCO2, PO2, bicarbonate, base excess, sodium, potassium, chloride, glucose and haemoglobin  levels were recorded. This will assess whether the ph is decreased or increased from patient's baseline.</outcome>
      <timepoint>A sample size calculation based on the expected 0.05 difference in pH in the mean population, and alpha of 0.05 and beta of 80%, leads to a minimum sample size of 15 in each side.
Arterial blood gases are taken at start (baseline) then hourly during the surgery and the last arterial blood gas are taken one hour postoperatively.
From the arterial blood gas results, pH, PCO2, PO2, bicarbonate, base excess, sodium, potassium, chloride, glucose and haemoglobin  levels were recorded.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>chloride.
Arterial blood gases are taken at start (baseline) then hourly during the surgery and the last arterial blood gas is taken one hour postoperatively.
From the arterial blood gas results, pH, PCO2, PO2, bicarbonate, base excess, sodium, potassium, chloride, glucose and haemoglobin  levels were recorded.</outcome>
      <timepoint>A sample size calculation based on the expected 5 mmol difference in chloride in the mean population, and alpha of 0.05 and beta of 80%, leads to a minimum sample size of 25 in each side</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The inclusion criteria for this study required the patients to be of paediatric age group (more than 1 year old to less than 13 years old), to be of ASA physical status I, II or III, undergoing major elective Urogenital surgery (duration of more than 2 hours)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>1</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>13</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with renal failure or renal impairment, cardiac or liver failure, anomalies of the heart, hypervolaemic states, severe generalised oedema, electrolyte imbalance, metabolic acidosis and known allergies to sterofundin .</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/03/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>university malaya</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>faculty of medicine,
Lembah pantai,
50603 kuala lumpur.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Malaysia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>university malaya</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>faculty of medicine,
Lembah pantai
50603 kuala lumpur</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Malaysia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Perioperative fluid comprises of basic maintenance requirement, replacement of fluid losses and fasting deficits. The aims of perioperative fluid therapy are to maintain correct fluid and electrolyte balance and adequate vascular volume which will ensure cardiovascular stability, organ perfusion and adequate tissue oxygenation .
Most of the fluids given perioperatively are used for replacing deficits and third space losses which consist mainly of extra cellular fluid . Therefore the hydrating solution should ideally have a composition of electrolytes as similar to plasma as possible. This favours crystalloids which are high in sodium and chloride concentration and have low concentrations of potassium, bicarbonate and calcium. Examples of crystalloids that approximate these ideals are ringers lactate and sterofundin. The two fluids used in this study, sterofundin and ringers lactate are balanced crystalloids. The composition of which is very similar to plasma composition. Sterofundin or ringerfundin is a balanced isotonic solution for intravenous infusion with electrolyte composition very similar to plasma (Na 140, k 4.0, Ca 2.5, Mg 1, Cl 127mmol/l. It also has a potential base excess of zero and contains acetate (24mmol/l) and malate(5mmol/l) which is widely metabolized in all organs and muscles, resulting in low oxygen consumption (1.4l oxygen per litre solution). 
Ringers lactate is a balanced solution containing sodium (130mmol/l), potassium (5mmol/l), calcium and magnesium (both at 1mmol/l), chloride (112mmol/l) and lactate (27mmol/l) therefore it is actually slightly hypotonic. Its osmolarity is 276mOsm/l which renders it slightly hypo-osmolar to plasma. Its potential base excess is 3 mmol/l and oxygen consumption is higher than that of sterofundin at 1.8l oxygen per litre solution. This minor difference in oxygen consumption would be actually significant in a perioperative paediatric patient who has to cope with other stresses of surgery and anaesthesia. The lactate in ringers lactate was added in order to reduce the chloride load and act as a bicarbonate precursor, therefore reducing likelihood of hyperchloraemic acidosis seen after large infusions of normal saline. However, the metabolism of lactate is dependent on the kidney and liver, and as such, when the functions of these organs are compromised, there will be lactate accumulation as well as reduction in production of bicarbonate resulting in lactic acidosis.Sterofundin has been compared with ringers lactate use for resuscitation in septic oncologic adult patients where it has been found to be associated with a better preservation of electrolyte and acid-base pattern . However, few data exist on perioperative use of sterofundin in children. This study aims to elicit any significant changes in sodium, chloride, pH and base excess levels when sterofundin is used in paediatric patients undergoing major surgery as compared to ringers lactate usage. Ideally, there should be minimal changes in these parameters as compared to the baseline levels as there are many undesirable and dangerous effects associated with moderate to severe derangement of acid base and electrolytes.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>university malaya medical centre ethics comittee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>lembah pantai,
50603 kuala lumpur</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Malaysia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ina Ismiarti Shariffuddin</name>
      <address>department of anaesthesia,
Faculty of medicine,
University malaya,
Jalan lembah pantai,
50603 kuala lumpur</address>
      <phone>60122353134</phone>
      <fax>60379556705</fax>
      <email>inashariffuddin@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ina Ismiarti Shariffuddin</name>
      <address>department of anaesthesia,
Faculty of medicine,
University malaya,
Jalan lembah pantai,
50603 kuala lumpur</address>
      <phone>60122353134</phone>
      <fax>60379556705</fax>
      <email>inashariffuddin@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ina Ismiarti Shariffuddin</name>
      <address />
      <phone>60122353134</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>inashariffuddin@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>