<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365706">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/01/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/02/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000134628</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>How Fit is the Stroke Survivor? Can community-dwelling stroke survivors undertaking an individualised program to increase activity levels improve their cardiorespiratory fitness? A pilot study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Can community-dwelling stroke survivors undertaking an individualised program to increase activity levels improve their cardiorespiratory fitness compared to waitlisted control participants? A pilot study </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>HowFITSS?</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is a 12 week program to increase levels of physical activity and reduce sedentary behaviour. After the completion of baseline measures a physiotherapist and an exercise scientist consults with the participant for approximately 1 hour to discuss their program and to demonstrate/practice activities. Thereafter, participants exercise on their own. The program is individualised based on each participant's age, exercise preferences and access to resources and is carried out in their local community or at home. They are provided with an exercise manual that includes tips on overcoming barriers and tips for staying motivated, an exercise diary and suggested activities that can be done at home. Participants who are interested in using a pedometer are provided with one to provide feedback and to set targets. Participants are encouraged to exercise/ be active for at least 30 minutes most days of the week. They are also encouraged to break up long periods of sitting with some standing and walking. Activities at an intensity to improve cardiorespiratory fitness are strongly encouraged. During the 12 week program support is provided weekly via emails and/or phone calls. After the 12 weeks support is provided monthly up until the 12 month review. Participants are encouraged to contact the research team if they have any queries or issues.</interventions>
    <comparator>No treatment during 12 week waitlist period then receive the 12 week intervention</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Peak oxygen consumption measured via a progressive exercise test with open circuit spirometry</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Peak oxygen consumption measured via a progressive exercise test with open circuit spirometry</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Walking ability using the 6 Minute Walk Test and 10m walk test (self selected and fast speeds)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, at the completion of a 12 week program, at 6 and 12 months after baseline measures</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of shuttles achieved during the Shuttle Walk Test</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, at the completion of a 12 week program, at 6 and 12 months after baseline measures</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Knee strength measured on the Humac Norm</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, at the completion of a 12 week program, at 6 and 12 months after baseline measures</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fatigue measured with the Fatigue Assessment Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, at the completion of a 12 week program, at 6 and 12 months after baseline measures</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health Related Quality of Life measured with the Stroke and Aphasia Quality of Life tool</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, at the completion of a 12 week program, at 6 and 12 months after baseline measures</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mood measured with the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, at the completion of a 12 week program, at 6 and 12 months after baseline measures</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body composition measured with the InBody</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, at the completion of a 12 week program, at 6 and 12 months after baseline measures</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Community dwelling, adult stroke survivor within 1 year of last stroke, able to follow basic commands</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnant, deemed medically unfit to participate as determined by a medical practitioner (ASCM Contraindications to Exercise Testing- absolute and relative- are provided on the Medical Clearance form), unable to attend the centre for testing</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Intervention participants commence their 12 week program after baseline measures are completed. Control participants undergo baseline testing then are waitlisted for 12 weeks. They will then undergo testing again after these 12 weeks before crossing over to receive the intervention. All participants will be re tested after the 12 week program and at 6 and 12 months</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A convenience sample of 20 will be recruited to this study. We aim to see if the intervention is safe and effective for adult males and females over a range of ages. The pilot trial will examine the feasibility of the testing protocols as well as providing data on the amount of change observed in cardiorespiratory fitness after the intervention. This will inform the design of a larger randomised controlled trial. 

Primary analysis: Intention to treat; Linear mixed model ANOVA will be used to compare treatment and control groups at 12 weeks. 
Secondary analysis: Repeated measures ANOVA will be used to investigate changes from baseline in treatment group at 3 time points: 12 weeks, 6 months and 12 months. 
Statistical significance will be set at p&lt; 0.05. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/12/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>12/12/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>28/02/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>John Hunter Hospital Royal Newcastle Centre - New Lambton</hospital>
    <hospital>The Maitland Hospital - Maitland</hospital>
    <hospital>Belmont Hospital - Belmont</hospital>
    <postcode>2305 - New Lambton Heights</postcode>
    <postcode>2320 - Maitland</postcode>
    <postcode>2280 - Belmont</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Newcastle</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University Drive, 
Callaghan,
NSW. 2308.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Stroke Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 7, 461 Bourke St
Melbourne. 
Victoria.3000.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>John Hunter Hospital Charitable Trust</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>John Hunter Hospital Research Committee
C/- Endocrine Unit, 
John Hunter Hospital
Level 3 John Hunter Hospital, 
Locked Bag 1, Hunter Region Mail Centre, 
NSW. 2310.
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Hunter Medical Research Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Lot 1 Kookaburra Circuit, 
New Lambton Heights, 
NSW. 2305</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>HNE Allied Health Research Committee Research Grant
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>c/o Speech Pathology
John Hunter Hospital,
Lookout Rd,
New Lambton Heights.
NSW. 2305.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Hunter New England Local Health District</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Lookout Rd,
New Lambton Heights,
NSW. 2305.</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Stroke is common in Australia and the number of people experiencing stroke will increase with the ageing population. Currently, rehabilitation therapy after stroke focusses on restoring functions such as walking, swallowing and speech, with a primary goal of enabling people to return home. Improving physical fitness, particularly cardiorespiratory fitness, receives very little or no attention; however, improving fitness has the potential to enhance recovery of function, prevent future stroke or other cardiovascular events such as heart attacks, and improve the quality of life of stroke survivors.
Low levels of fitness make everyday activities difficult and fatiguing to perform and may also put the person at greater risk of another stroke. Studies of stroke survivors suggest they are only about half as fit as non-stroke people of a similar age. Unlike heart attack survivors who commonly access cardiac rehabilitation, fitness-training programs are not routinely available for stroke survivors. There have only been a small number of fitness training trials in stroke and most required participants to undergo expensive testing in a large hospital or research centre. The majority used a "one-program-fits-all" training approach and required participants to train at a single centre. Therefore the purpose of this project is to trial a physical activity program that is individualised to the participants' interests, abilities and access to equipment in their home or local community, is low-cost, and could be implemented anywhere in Australia. Participants will be provided with encouragement and support by phone and email, not only for the 12 weeks of the program but for the 12 month study duration. This pilot is a small, controlled trial where 50% participants will commence the program immediately while the other 50% will undergo baseline testing then be retested 12 weeks later before they start the program. We will compare fitness levels between those undergoing immediate and delayed fitness training, and measure changes before and after training as well as at 6 and 12 months. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Ethics and Governance Unit
District Headquarters- Administration Building 
Lookout Road, 
New Lambton, 
NSW. 2305.

</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/05/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>11/04/20/4.04</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/04/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Newcastle Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Services, 
Research Integrity Unit, 
HA148, Hunter Building, 
The University of Newcastle, 
University Drive,
Callaghan, 
NSW. 2308.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/07/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H-2011-0172</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/06/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Neil Spratt</name>
      <address>Department of Neurology,
John Hunter Hospital,
Lookout Road, 
New Lambton Heights,
NSW. 2305.
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 49213491   </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Neil.Spratt@newcastle.edu.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Di Marsden</name>
      <address>Hunter Stroke Service, 
Level 2 The Lodge.
Rankin Park Campus
Lookout Road, 
New Lambton Heights,
NSW. 2305.
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 49223380</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Di.Marsden@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Di Marsden</name>
      <address>Hunter Stroke Service, 
Level 2 The Lodge.
Rankin Park Campus
Lookout Road, 
New Lambton Heights,
NSW. 2305.
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 49223380</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Di.Marsden@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Di Marsden</name>
      <address>Hunter Stroke Service, 
Level 2 The Lodge.
Rankin Park Campus
Lookout Road, 
New Lambton Heights,
NSW. 2305.
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 49223380</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Di.Marsden@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>