<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370773">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/05/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/05/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000692437</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of altering the proportions of meal components on subsequent energy intake: a randomised controlled trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of altering the proportions of meal components on subsequent energy intake of healthy young adults : a randomised controlled trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1183-1698</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Overweight</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study is a crossover trial in which participants are to consume a mid-day test meal consisting of a starchy food, non-starchy vegetables and mince in a bolognaise sauce. Pasta and rice will be used, such that half of the subjects will consume three pasta meals and the other half will consume three rice meals. Among the three meals, the amount of available carbohydrate in the starchy food will be 30, 45 or 60 g. The meal containing 45 g of available carbohydrate is the reference meal. The meals containing 30 or 60 g of available carbohydrate differ to the reference meal in that they contain one less or one additional serving of starchy food (15 g of available carbohydrate). The amount of rice and pasta on the plate corresponding to the 30, 45 and 60g available carbohydrate will be 100, 150 and 200g. The amount of vegetables on the plate will be 250, 200 and 150, respectively. The amount of mince with pasta sauce will be constant among the meals (200g). Overall, the total weight of food in all of the meals will be 550g. On each testing day, participants will record their food and beverage intake for the entire day (0000 to 2359 hrs) and subsequent energy intake will be measured following the consumption of the entire test meal. The washout period will be one week. The meals will be served hot (&gt;65 deg C) and consumed within the testing facility. Participants will be instructed to fast for 2 and a half hours before the lunch. They will be free to eat at their own pace meal consumption will be supervised to ensure that entire meal is consumed . </interventions>
    <comparator>Consumption of the meal containing 45 g of available carbohydrate is the control treatment. The amount of available carbohydrate contained within in this meal is based on a New Zealand healthy plate model. Many factors influence the amount of carbohydrates people consume, therefore 45 g may not be suitable for all.  </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Energy intake for the remainder of the day following a lunch meal. The energy intake will be assessed by having participants record all food and beverage consumption. The participants will be given electronic scales accutate to 1g and instruction on how to weigh their food items.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Dietary energy intake following a lunch meal up until 23:59 of the same day</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dietary energy intake preceding a lunch meal. The energy intake will be assessed by having participants record all food and beverage consumption. The participants will be given electronic scales accutate to 1g and instruction on how to weigh their food items.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Dietary energy intake over the portion of the day starting at 24:00 to the beginning of a lunch meal</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Daily dietary energy intake on the day of test. The energy intake will be assessed by having participants record all food and beverage consumption. The participants will be given electronic scales accutate to 1g and instruction on how to weigh their food items.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Dietary energy intake consumed over the period 24:00 to 23:59 on the test day</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>University students</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Food allergies or restrictions that cannot be catered for. We will be providing lunch meals and there will be no other exclusion criteria.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The person who will determine a persons eligiblity will be unaware, when this decision is made, to which group the person will be allocated.

Randomisation will be performed by the department statistician, the researchers will remain unaware of allocations until the laboratory phase. </concealment>
    <sequence>The method of sequence generation will be by permuted block randomisation. Block randomisation will be used to balance males and females into each of the intervention groups (rice or pasta). Computerised sequence generation will be used to randomise to order of treatment and week and time of laboratory sessions. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Washout of one week</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The sample size (n=80) allowing 39 in each intervention group will be sufficient to detect a 25% difference in energy intake post-test meal between meal size treatments with 80% power (using a mean energy intake of 4000 kJ, a standard deviation of the log of energy intake of 0.5 and a correlation of 0.55 between paired observations).
To analyse the percentage change in energy intake in response to test meal consumption, a mixed effects regression analysis will be undertaken.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>4/03/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>25/03/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>77</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Otago</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Otago</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Human Nutrition
PO Box 56
Dunedin
9054</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Otago</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Human Nutrition
PO Box 56
Dunedin
9054</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Obesity is a problem facing many countries including New Zealand. It would be helpful to develop dietary strategies to control overconsumption. Non-starchy vegetables have low energy density and their consumption is recommended widely by health organisations. We are interested in testing how manipulating the proportions of starchy and non-starchy vegetables on a plate affect ad libitum energy intake following lunch meals having different proportions of starchy and non-starchy vegetables. We aim to do this by providing lunch meals in a controlled setting and estimating the subsequent energy intake of participants over the rest of the day. Energy intake will be assessed via weighed food intake records.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Otago Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Department of Human Nutrition
PO Box 56
Dunedin
9054</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/02/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>14/204</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/02/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Bernard Venn</name>
      <address>University of Otago
Department of Human Nutrition
PO Box 56
Dunedin
9054</address>
      <phone>+6434795068</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bernard.venn@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Bernard Venn</name>
      <address>University of Otago
Department of Human Nutrition
PO Box 56
Dunedin
9054</address>
      <phone>+6434795068</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bernard.venn@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Bernard Venn</name>
      <address>University of Otago
Department of Human Nutrition
PO Box 56
Dunedin
9054</address>
      <phone>+6434795068</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bernard.venn@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>