<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363049">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/09/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/09/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001005842</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Does the drug Galvus enhance the effects of a protein preload to reduce blood glucose concentrations after a meal?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Does Galvus enhance the effects of a protein preload to reduce postprandial glycemia in patients with type 2 diabetes?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1134-8235</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>CLAF237AAU04T</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>22 males with type 2 diabetes, treated with metformin monotherapy, will be studied, each on 4 separate occasions in a randomized, double-blind crossover fashion to evaluate the effects of:
(1) A protein preload (25 g chocolate-flavoured whey protein dissolved in 250 mL water (89 kcal)) in combination with placebo
(2) A protein preload (25 g chocolate-flavoured whey protein dissolved in 250 mL water (89 kcal)) in combination with vildagliptin (50 mg)
(3) A control preload (250 ml water with chocolate flavouring (8 kcal)) in combination with placebo
(4) A control preload (250 ml water with chocolate flavouring (8 kcal)) in combination with vildagliptin (50 mg)
on blood glucose, insulin, glucagon and total and intact GLP-1 and GIP concentrations, and the gastric emptying of a carbohydrate-containing meal. The study days will be separated by at least 7 days.

On the evening before each of the study days (~1900 h), participants will be given a standardised evening meal (McCains frozen beef lasagne (McCain Foods Proprietary Ltd); 2472 kJ) to consume with water. With this meal, participants will be instructed to take their usual metformin dose, as well as 50 mg of vildagliptin, or matched placebo. Following this meal, participants will be asked to fast from solids and liquids (other than water) until the following morning. 

Participants will then attend the Discipline of Medicine at 0830 h on the following morning. On arrival, an intravenous cannula will be inserted into an antecubital vein for blood sampling. Following this (t = -90 min), a baseline blood sample will be taken, then participants will ingest either 50 mg of vildagliptin, or placebo, with 100 ml of water. One hour later (t = -30 min), they will consume a preload drink containing either 25 g chocolate-flavoured whey protein dissolved in 250 mL water (89 kcal), or control (250 ml water with chocolate flavouring (8 kcal)), within 2 minutes. Thirty minutes later (t = 0 min), participants will eat a meal consisting of 65 g powdered potato (Deb, Epping, NSW, Australia) and 20 g glucose, reconstituted with 200 mL water and 1 egg yolk containing 100 microlitres of 13C-octanoic acid. Participants will consume the meal within 5 minutes. Breath samples will be collected immediately before, and every 5 minutes after, meal ingestion in the first hour and every 15 minutes for a further 3 hours for the measurement of gastric emptying. Venous blood samples (~10 mL) will be taken immediately before the preload administration (t = -30 min), and at t = -15, 0, 15, 30, 60, 90, 120, 180 and 240 min for the measurements of blood glucose, insulin, GLP-1 and GIP (total and intact) and glucagon. At t = 240 minutes, the intravenous cannula will be removed, and participants will then be free to leave the laboratory. On each study day, a total of ~110 mL venous blood will be collected. At the same intervals used for blood sampling, appetite and gastrointestinal sensations will be assessed using 100 mm visual analogue scales. 

Gastric emptying of the carbohydrate meal, labelled with 13C octanoic acid, will be measured by excretion of 13CO2 in the breath by mass spectrometer. This technique has been validated against the gold-standard scintigraphy. Half-emptying time (t50) and gastric emptying coefficient (GEC) will be calculated.</interventions>
    <comparator>One tablet of Galvus (vildagliptin (50 mg)) will be taken on both the evening before, and the morning of the study. 
Matched placebo tablets.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood glucose levels</outcome>
      <timepoint>Venous blood samples (~10 mL) will be taken immediately before the preload administration (t = -30 min), and at t = -15, 0, 15, 30, 60, 90, 120, 180 and 240 min for the measurements of blood glucose.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Insulin</outcome>
      <timepoint>Venous blood samples (~10 mL) will be taken immediately before the preload administration (t = -30 min), and at t = -15, 0, 15, 30, 60, 90, 120, 180 and 240 min for the measurements of plasma insulin concentrations.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Glucagon</outcome>
      <timepoint>Venous blood samples (~10 mL) will be taken immediately before the preload administration (t = -30 min), and at t = -15, 0, 15, 30, 60, 90, 120, 180 and 240 min for the measurements of plasma glucagon concentrations.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Glucagon-like peptide-1 (GLP-1) (total and active)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Venous blood samples (~10 mL) will be taken immediately before the preload administration (t = -30 min), and at t = -15, 0, 15, 30, 60, 90, 120, 180 and 240 min for the measurements of plasma GLP-1 (total and active) concentrations.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Glucose-dependent insulinotropic polypeptide (GIP) (total and active)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Venous blood samples (~10 mL) will be taken immediately before the preload administration (t = -30 min), and at t = -15, 0, 15, 30, 60, 90, 120, 180 and 240 min for the measurements of plasma GIP concentrations.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gastric emptying rate</outcome>
      <timepoint>Breath samples will be collected immediately before, and every 5 minutes after, meal ingestion in the first hour and every 15 minutes for a further 3 hours for the measurement of gastric emptying.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Appetite perceptions and gastrointestinal symptoms</outcome>
      <timepoint>Visual analogue scale (VAS) questionnaires will be completed immediately before the preload administration (t = -30 min), and at t = -15, 0, 15, 30, 60, 90, 120, 180 and 240 min for the assessment of perceptions of appetite and gastrointestinal symptoms.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-Patients with type 2 diabetes (taking a stable dose of metformin, greater than or equal to 1500 mg/day for at least 3 months prior to the study)
-Body mass index of 25-35 kg/m2
Aged between 20-75 years, will be included in the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(1) significant gastrointestinal symptoms; disease or surgery
(2) inability to monitor blood glucose at home with a glucometer
(3) current use of any prescribed or non-prescribed medications, that may affect gastrointestinal function (except for metformin) within 48 hours of the study (e.g. domperidone and cisapride, anticholinergic drugs (e.g. atropine), metoclopramide, erythromycin, hyoscine, orlistat, green tea extracts, Astragalus, St John's Wort)
(4) current use of ACE inhibitors
(5) epilepsy
(6) cardiovascular (coronary heart disease, heart attack or failure, stroke) or respiratory disease (COPD, cystic fibrosis)
(7) any other significant illness as assessed by the investigator
(8) intake of &gt; 20 g alcohol on a daily basis 
(9) smokers (cigarettes, cigars, marijuana)
(10) donation of blood in the 12 weeks prior to enrolment in the study.  Participants will also be instructed to abstain from donating blood for 12 weeks after study completion. A screening blood sample will be taken to ensure that only individuals with normal haemoglobin and iron levels are included in the study. 
(11) consumption of a vegetarian diet 
(12) inability to comprehend study protocol
(13) known lactose intolerance, intolerance or allergy to whey, allergy to vildagliptin
(14) liver function tests and creatinine clearance outside the following ranges
*Alanine aminotransferase (ALT)	0 -55 U/l
*Alkaline phosphatase		30 - 110 U/l
*Aspartate transaminase		0 - 45 U/l
*Bilirubin			               6 - 24 mmol/l
Calculated creatinine clearance will be determined as follows:
Cr clearance = [140 - age (years) x weight (kg)] / serum creatinine (micromol/L)
with a creatinine clearance cut-off of &lt;50 ml/min AND/OR serum creatinine concentration &gt;0.12mmol/l will be excluded.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Pharmacy will randomise the patients to receive each of the four treatments in a double-blind fashion (i.e. the participants and the investigators responsible for data analysis) will be blinded to the treatment.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using a randomization table created by a computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Pharmacokinetics / pharmacodynamics</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/10/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>22</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Michael Horowitz</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Adelaide Discipline of Medicine
Level 6, Eleanor Harrald Building
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide, SA, 5000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Novartis Pharmaceuticals Australia Pty. Ltd.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>54 Waterloo Road, 
North Ryde, NSW, 2111</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Central Adelaide Local Health Network (ABN 96 269 526 412) (formerly Adelaide Health Service Inc) operating as  Royal Adelaide Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>North Terrace, 
Adelaide, South Australia, 5000</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To determine whether:
(i) A protein preload stimulates glucagon-like peptide-1 (GLP-1) and glucose-dependent insulinotropic polypeptide (GIP) secretion, and thereby reduces postprandial glycaemia following a carbohydrate-containing meal relative to a control condition.
(ii) Galvus (vildagliptin) enhances the effect of a protein preload to stimulate GLP-1 and GIP secretion, and thereby further reduces postprandial glycaemia following a carbohydrate-containing meal.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide, SA, 5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/07/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>120624</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Tanya Little</name>
      <address>University of Adelaide Discipline of Medicine
Level 6, Eleanor Harrald Building
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide, SA, 5000</address>
      <phone>+61882220724</phone>
      <fax>+61882233870</fax>
      <email>tanya.little@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Tanya Little</name>
      <address>University of Adelaide Discipline of Medicine
Level 6, Eleanor Harrald Building
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide, SA, 5000</address>
      <phone>+61882220724</phone>
      <fax>+61882233870</fax>
      <email>tanya.little@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Tanya Little</name>
      <address>University of Adelaide Discipline of Medicine
Level 6, Eleanor Harrald Building
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide, SA, 5000</address>
      <phone>+61882220724</phone>
      <fax>+61882233870</fax>
      <email>tanya.little@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>