<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83938">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/06/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/06/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000465257</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial examining the efficacy of a smoking cessation intervention initiated during psychiatric hospitalisation on post-discharge smoking reduction, nicotine dependence and abstinence. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of an integrated smoking care program on the reduction and abstinence of smoking in mental health inpatients following discharge from hospital.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>New secondary ID. Please modify.</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Smoking</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Mental health</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>*Provision of 3 quit smoking pamphlets upon recruitment to the intervention condition
*Active referral to the telephone support Quitline (occurring once at discharge from hospital)
*Up to 16 weeks provision of Nicotine Replacement Therapy (NRT), including patches, Gum, lozenges and Inhalers. 
* A weekly, one hour smoking support group (occurring for 4 weeks in total) 
* A one page referral to a general practitioner (GP) and other health professionals (for example psychologists, occupational therapists) to inform them of their clients participation in a smoking study. 
*Telephone support calls, made once every two weeks for up to 4 months.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group will receive standard hospital care for treatment of smoking. 
This care entails provision of nicotine replacement therapy (NRT), including gum, lozenges, inhalers and patches continuously for the duration of the hospital stay. 
Upon discharge, patients are given the option to receive an active referral to Quitline, and 3 days supply of 21mg/24 hour patches.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in smoking behaviour, including reduction in daily cigarette consumption and number and duration of quit attempts assessed by self-report and collaborative reports from smoking group facilitators. Detailed process data will also be collected, including uptake and use of smoking cessation supports, allowing researchers to determine the feasibility and acceptability of linking inpatient to community cessation support.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All participants will be followed up via telephone survey at 1 week, 2 months, 4 months and 6 months post discharge.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Abstinence from smoking, assessed by self-report and collaborative reports from smoking group facilitators. A small percentage (5%) of those who have indicated to be abstinent will be asked to complete a Carbon Monoxide (CO) test to confirm this.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All participants will be followed up via telephone survey at 1 week, 2 months, 4 months and 6 months post discharge.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inpatient at mental health hospital, smoker.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>non-smoker</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Prior to commencement of recruitment, a random allocation sequence will be generated using SPSS through consultation with an independent statistician not actively involved in the project. The random allocation sequence will be stored with a research assistant independent of the recruitment process, and all project officers involved in recruitment and follow-up data collection will be kept blind to the sequence. According to the order of the random allocation sequence, the research assistant will place small cards indicating the treatment condition (“Intervention” or “Control”) inside sealed, security envelopes, displaying the sequentially ordered participant identification code on the exterior. Following completion of the baseline interview, the project officer will provide the participant with the subsequent envelope in sequence, and the envelope will be opened by the participant at the conclusion of the baseline interview. </concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/06/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>30/10/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>30/05/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Newcastle</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University Drive, Callaghan 2308 NSW</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Rotary Health Research Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 3455
Paramatta NSW 2124</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to explore inpatient psychiatric settings as a platform for initiating smoking cessation treatment to patients smokers. We hypothesise that patients who commence smoking cessation treatment in hospital and receive ongoing support post-hospitalisation will be more likely to quit than smokers who receive standard hospital care only. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Newcastle Human research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University Drive, Callaghan 2308 NSW Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/07/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H-2008-0191</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>AProf Jenny Bowman</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
University of Newcastle, University Drive, Callaghan 2308 NSW</address>
      <phone>+61 2 49215958</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jenny.bowman@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>AProf Jenny Bowman</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
University of Newcastle, University Drive, Callaghan 2308 NSW</address>
      <phone>+61 2 49215958</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jenny.bowman@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Jenny Bowman</name>
      <address>School of Psychology, University of Newcastle, University Drive, Callaghan, NSW, 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 49215958</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jenny.bowman@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>