<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82051">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/05/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/06/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000296437</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>"A Randomised Controlled Trial on the Effectiveness of Synbiotics on the Frequency and Duration of Loose Bowel Movement in Acute Adult Diarrheal Disease.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomised Controlled Trial on the Effectiveness of Synbiotics, Lactobacillus acidophilus and Bifido bifidum in Soy Phytochemical Extract, on the Frequency and Duration of Loose Bowel Movement in Acute Adult Diarrheal Disease.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>loose bowel movement, acute adult diarrhea</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal oral and gastrointestinal development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Synbiotics- is a combination of probiotics and prebiotics.this is composed of live microbial supplements and non digestible sugars that stimulate the growth of those bacteria. The soy phytochemical extract contains Lactobacillus acidophilus and Bifido bifidum given to the randomize test group 1 casule  3 times a day for 4 days per orem. One capsule of the soy phytochemical extract contains 3.5 billion viable probiotic colony forming bacteria. 1.5 billion Bifido bifidum and 1.65 billion Lactobacillus acidophilus and 100mg prebiotic soluble oligosaccharides and soy phytochemical exract. All patient were put on low fat, lactose free diet, in the entire hospital stay. All results will be collected at the end of the 6 months study period, unmask, tabulated and analyze by the authors.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants in the control group will be given placebo capsule 3 times a day for 4 days per orem.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparing stool consistency and frequency</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 6 month of study duration, all collected forms with randomically allocated numbers provided to the patients to answer will be collected by the authors unmasked, tabulated and and entered into a computer using SPSS for windows version 14 software. Wilcoxon Signed Rank test will be utilized for comparing stool consistency and frequency.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparing the clinical improvement of symptoms</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 6 month of study duration, all collected forms with randomically allocated numbers provided to the patients to answer will be collected by the authors unmasked, tabulated and and entered into a computer using SPSS for windows version 14 software. Sign test is use for comparing the clinical improvement of symptoms. Level of significance is set at 0.05.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcomes were not included in this study</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Angeles University Foundation Medical Center (AUFMC) and Rafael Lazatin Memorial Medical Center (RLMMC) patients, admitted for acute diarrheal disease from September 2006 to March 2007.Acute Diarrhea is defined as loose, watery, bowel movement of more than 3x a day non-bloody; loose watery bowel movement of 2 episodes more than patients usual BM.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with co-morbidities, those who are diagnose with typhoid infections, amebiasis, no history or current antibiotics or antidiarrheal medication use, overflow diarrhea, antimotility intake, irritable bowel syndrome, history of diabetes mellitus, laxative abuse, malabsorption syndrome, thyroid pathology and those who are having diarrhea for more than a week.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>treatment allocation done by hospital pharmacy based on the generated randomized table by computer. intervention or controlled capsule issued by the pharmacy will be administered by the nurseon duty without knowing what type of medication is he/she administering.</concealment>
    <sequence>simple randomization using randomization table created by computer software</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>the subjects, investigators, clinician, and medication nurse are blinded.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>38</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Francel Villarin</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Angeles University Foundation Medical Center Department of Internal Medicine</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Philippines</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Precieze Pharma and Distribution, Philippines</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry>Philippines</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To determine if supplementation with the synbiotic would decrease the frequency of bowel movements of adult patients admitted for acute diarrheal disease.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>the ethics board of the department of internal medicine in Angeles University Foundation Medical Center a Philippine College of Physician</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Philippines</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Francel Villarin, M.D.</name>
      <address>Angeles University Foundation Medical Center
Mac artur Hi-way Angeles City Philippines (2009)
Mother of Perpetual Help Hospital
Sto. Entierro St.
Angeles City  (2009)</address>
      <phone>+63 9209540878</phone>
      <fax>+63 45 8881688</fax>
      <email>lecnarf@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Philippines</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Francel Villarin, M.D.</name>
      <address>Angeles University Foundation Medical Center, Mac Arthur Hi-way Angeles City Pampanga,  (2009)</address>
      <phone>+63 9209540878</phone>
      <fax>+63 45 8881688</fax>
      <email>lecnarf@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Philippines</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>