<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371266">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/10/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/10/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001491358</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The buccal administration of a Nanocelle cannabidiol (CBD) preparation to healthy volunteers: a safety, tolerability and pharmacokinetic exploratory pilot study. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The buccal administration of a Nanocelle CBD preparation to healthy volunteers: a safety, tolerability and pharmacokinetic exploratory pilot study. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>The Investigational Product may be indicated for anxiety</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>The Investigational Product may be indicated for mood symptoms</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>The Investigational Product may be indicated for insomnia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>The Investigational Product may be indicated for the treatment of inflammatory pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Herbal remedies</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>To evaluate the safety of a nanocelle cannabis extract (Cannabidiol 'CBD' primarily) from the whole plant (Cannabis sativa L.) as an administered oro-buccal (fine mist) spray (in a particle size of 0.050.2 microns) at a concentration of 15 milligram CBD / 900 microlitre / 6 x sprays to be administered within 5 minutes only on the first day post baseline blood sample. Participants are fasted for 8 hours prior to receiving treatment
Allocation: non-randomised. Treatment Endpoint classification: none. Intervention Model: oro-buccal administration. Masking: non-blinded. Primary Purpose: safety. </interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite outcome, safety and tolerability:
- BMI and BP
- Blood pathology (Northern Cancer Institute Laboratory): FBC, Urea, electrolytes and creatinine and LFTs, at baseline and 24 hours. Blood samples at baseline will determine suitability of participation in the study as well as values to be compared to the 24 hours collection to investigate drug safety.
- CBD metabolites (CRP in Adelaide)</outcome>
      <timepoint>- Blood draws: Baseline (0 [baseline]), 15, 30, 60, 90, 120, 180, 240, 360, and 420 min (7 hours) and 24 hours (via indwelling cannula or a venepuncture for the 24 hours blood draw)
On Day 1: 
- BP measured by sphygmomanometer and BMI by scales, tape measure at baseline. BP to be measured at 24 hours also.
- Blood pathology at baseline and 24 hours. 
- Blood samples at the above time points will be shipped to CRP in Adelaide for analysis of CBD metabolites
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetic properties of the Investigational Product:
- Drug absorption, distribution, metabolism and excretion time.
- Drug Half-life and peak concentration </outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood draws at baseline (0 [baseline]), 15, 30, 60, 90, 120, 180, 240, 360, and 420 min and 24 hours (via indwelling cannula inserted in a vein in the arm or a venepuncture for the 24 hour blood draw)
 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1)	Participants to be 18 years of age at time of entry on study 
2)	Cognitive ability to understand informed consent process and to give informed consent to the experimental treatment 
3)	Participants agree to undergo insertion of an indwelling tube (once with multiple blood draws) and venepuncture at a 24hour follow up period
4)	Participants agree to adhere to the study protocol 
5)	No history of illicit drug use (e.g., including but not limited to cannabis) 
6)	Have not been prescribed or have had administered any synthetic cannabinoids or any other natural cannabis compound
7)     No history of any chronic diseases </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1)	Any clinically relevant abnormal findings which, in the opinion of the investigators / clinicians, may put the participant at risk of adverse events because of participation in the clinical trial including: physical examination, clinical chemistry, haematology, urinalysis, vital signs
2)	Current or previous allergies or allergic responses to herbal medicines of any kind. 
3)	Active substance abuse (alcohol or drug dependency)
4)	The current use of any illicit drugs (e.g., cannabis in any form) 
5)	Pregnant or nursing an infant 
6)	Any psychiatric disorders by history or examination that would prevent completion of the study or result in possible adverse events for the participant 
7)	Elevated liver enzymes 2x normal limits 
The current use of any dietary and herbal supplements</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2018</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>16</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Northern Cancer Institute - St Leonards</hospital>
    <postcode>2065 - St Leonards</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Medlab Clinical </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>66 McCauley Street, Alexandria, New South Wales, 2015</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Medlab Clinical </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>66 McCauley Street, Alexandria, New South Wales 2015</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this project is to conduct a a safety, tolerability and pharmacokinetic exploratory pilot study assessing the buccal administration of a Nanocelle CBD (cannabidiol) preparation to healthy volunteers.

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to join this study if you are a healthy individual aged 18 years or over and have no history of illicit drug use (e.g., including but not limited to cannabis) 


Study details
Eligible participants will have a baseline pathology test for: Full Blood Counts (FBC), Electrolytes and Liver Function tests (ELFTs), Urea, blood lipids, Urine samples and appointments will be made for the participants at the Northern Cancer Institute Facility for dosing date. The clinical trial coordinator will document all demographic data, anthropometric measurements (Blood pressure, weight and height). The participants will be fasted 8 hours prior to dosing with the study medication. Cannabis extract containing 15 mg CBD/0.9 mL and &lt; 2% other cannabinoids (includes 0.02% THC) in 6 actuations of the pump to be administered post baseline blood draw on Day 1 ONLY. Blood tests will include FBC, ELFTs, Urea, blood lipids and will be performed at baseline and at the end of the study on at 24 hours of day 1. CBD cannabinoids will be assayed on all blood samples (see guidance document attached). Blood samples will be drawn at 0 (baseline) and at 15, 30, 60, 90, 120, 180, 240, 360, and 420 minutes (7 hours) and at 24 hours.  

Data derived from preliminary pharmacokinetic information gathered from this study will be used to design a subsequent Phase I further exploratory placebo controlled clinical trial (mood disorder / seizures) followed by a Phase IIa placebo controlled clinical study (mood disorder / seizures) for further IP development. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>National Institute of Integrative Medicine</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>11-23 Burwood Road, Hawthorn, Melbourne VIC 3122</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/02/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>0030E_2016</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Stephen Clarke</name>
      <address>Northern Cancer Institute
Level 1, 38 Pacific Highway, St Leonards NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8037 4100</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>stephen.clarke@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Serena Dal Forno</name>
      <address>Medlab Clinical. 66 McCauley Street, Alexandria, New South Wales 2015</address>
      <phone>1300 369 570 Ext. 120</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>serena_dalforno@medlab.co</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Luis Vitetta </name>
      <address>Medlab Clinical. 66 McCauley Street, Alexandria, New South Wales, 2015</address>
      <phone>1300 369 570 Ext. 106</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>luis_vitetta@medlab.co</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Serena Dal Forno</name>
      <address>Medlab Clinical. 66 McCauley Street, Alexandria, New South Wales, 2015</address>
      <phone>1300 369 570 Ext. 120</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>serena_dalforno@medlab.co</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>