<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362542">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/05/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/05/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000567820</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of exercise on balance in newly diagnosed Transient Ischaemic Attack patients?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of exercise on balance in newly diagnosed Transient Ischaemic Attack patients?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Balance of patients diagnosed with a transient ischaemic attack</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Exercise Programme: 
Participants randomized to the exercise programme will visit the Massey University recreation centre, twice a week, for 8 weeks to take part in a group focused exercise session. Each exercise session will last 90 mins, incorporating 30 mins of aerobic exercise (treadmill, cycle ergometer) and 60 mins of balance based exercises. The balance exercises will include resistance exercise, core-stability, control, postural exerices, flexibility etc. Participants progression will be monitored over the course of the programme. Heart rate, blood pressure and perceived exertion will be monitored at rest, during the session and following the session. The group exercises will be supervised by the principal investigator (lecturer in exercise prescription and 8 years expereince of working with patient populations) and postgraduate MSc research scholars who have more than three years of practical experience of working with patient populations.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control condition will complete identical assessment procedures as those randomized to the exercise programme. However, those randomized to the control condition at the completion of the baseline assessment will receive normal care  during the 8 week exercise programme. No additional supportive strategies are implemented in the 8 weeks following the TIA for those randomized to the normal care condition. As such, normal care enables patients to visit their general practitioner, physiotherapists and hospital (i.e., for check-ups) as and when the patient feels that it is needed or requested.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Balance (postural sway) as monitored by a force platform</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline + Post-intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Carotid Artery Stiffness - This will be obtained non-invasively using doppler ultrasound. The subject will be supine for 15 minutes prior to the assessment of carotid artery stiffness, and blood flow using ultrasound.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline + Post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Coronary artery disease risk factors  - Following the completion of a health history questionnaire, participants will have a finger-prick capillary sample to enable the assessment of total cholesterol (TC), high-density lipoproteins (HDL), TC: HDL ratio, using a cardiochek, and blood glucose (using a glucometer). Participats, seated, standing and supine blood pressure will be recorded, a long with height, weight, body mass index and hip and waist girth. Participants family history of coronary heart disease, smoking status and physical activity participation will also be noted.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline + Post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fitness as determined by a resting and exercise ECG</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline + Post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Those diagnosed with TIA after review by a specialist stroke physician</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Oxygen dependence, uncontrolled angina, unstable cardiac conditions, uncontrolled diabetes mellitus, major medical conditions, claudication, febrile illness, significant cognitive impairment, immobile

TIA patients who reside outside of the Wellington Region (i.e., further away than Porirua).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The Stroke Department at Wellington Hospital receives referrals for all those with possible TIA in the Region. Referrals are received via telephone, fax or e-mail from General Practitioners, the Emergency Department and Paramedics. All referrals are reviewed within 2 working days by a specialist physician and appropriate diagnostic tests undertaken, as per the NZ TIA guidelines. Between 6 and 10 referrals are seen each week. Those in whom a diagnosis of TIA/Non-disabling stroke is reached will be invited to participate. Following the baseline assessments participants will be randomized to the exercise programme or to the control group. Randomization will the occur via 'allocation concealment'. Allocation concealment will occur via sealed opaque envelopes which will be sequentially numbered.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerised sequence generation The randomization sequence will be generated using the following internet source (http://www.randomizer.org/form.htm). The randomization sequence (i.e. A = Exercise; B = Control) will be placed in a sequentially numbered envelope (from 1-30) based on the derived sequence generated by the website</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/05/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>75</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Massey University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>63 Wallace St,
Wellington, 6021</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Massey University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>63 Wallace St,
Wellington, 6021</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Wellington Regional Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Riddiford St, Wellington, 6021</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Kong Chung</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Wellington Regional Hospital, Riddiford Street, Wellington, 6021</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Mrs Lai-kin Wong</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Wellington Regional Hospital, Riddiford Street, Wellington, 6021</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Mr Brandon Woolley</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Massey University, 63 Wallace St, Wellington, 6021</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Lee Stoner</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Massey University, 63 Wallace St, Wellington, 6021</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Sally Lark</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Massey University, 63 Wallace St, Wellington, 6021</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Danielle Lambrick</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Massey University, 63 Wallace St, Wellington, 6021</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Recent research has demonstrated that balance and balance confidence is impaired after stroke, limiting independence in activities of daily living (i.e., cooking, shopping, walking, etc). When symptoms of stroke resolve within 24 hours it is known as a Transient Ischaemic Attack (TIA; mini stroke). To date, research is yet to identify whether balance and/or balance confidence is impaired in patients following a TIA. Anecdotal evidence from the study CEN/10/10/046 revealed that balance may be impaired in TIA patients. TIA patients mentioned that they received substantial functional benefits from exercises aimed at improving balance after completing an 8 week exercise intervention. However, the degree to which a balance-based exercise intervention positively influences balance performance and confidence has not been established. Therefore, the purpose of this investigation is to identify whether balance is actually impaired in TIA patients. Previous research has demonstrated that balance training exercises improves balance performance and confidence after stroke. Providing balance impairments are found in TIA patients, this investigation also aims to identify the effects of a balance-based exercise intervention on balance performance and confidence.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>N/A</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Regional Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Northern X Regional Ethics Committee
Private Bag 92522
Wellesley Street
Auckland 1141</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/04/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>NTX/12/02/009</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr James Faulkner</name>
      <address>Massey University
63 Wallace St
Wellington, 6021</address>
      <phone>+64 (0)4 801 5799 ext 62104</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>J.Faulkner@massey.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr James Faulkner</name>
      <address>Massey University
63 Wallace St
Wellington, 6021</address>
      <phone>+64 (0)4 801 5799 ext 62104</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>J.Faulkner@massey.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr James Faulkner</name>
      <address>Massey University
63 Wallace St
Wellington, 6021</address>
      <phone>+64 (0)4 801 5799 ext 62104</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>J.Faulkner@massey.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>