<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370907">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/06/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/06/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000822482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Examining the impact of targeting sleep on child physical activity levels</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot randomised controlled trial assessing the impact of targeting sleep on child physical activity.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>none</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>physical activity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>sleep</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Parents of children in the intervention group will receive a 3-month intervention supporting them to implement healthy sleep practices for their preschool aged child. The intervention will seek to educate parents about personal and environmental factors aimed to promote positive sleep for their child. The intervention will be developed and delivered by an established organisation who has over 20 years experience delivering evidence-based parenting programs.
The sleep support component will consist of a 15 minute online pre-recorded video module that will be sent via email to parents, one 30-minute telephone call and two text messages.  
The video resource will outline the importance of sleep generally and in children, good sleep habits, and how to establish them within their household. For example, parents are encouraged to create appropriate environments for bed (including reducing light and noise in the bed room where possible, removing all screens from the child's room, creating safe sleep associations that are independent of the parent).  Also included on the webpage will be links to other supporting web-based resources published by reputable organisations including the National Sleep Foundation (on bedroom environment) and Raising Children Network which provide tips on establishing healthy sleep. The link sent to the parents will enable the research team to monitor whether parents click on the resource and how much of the video was watched.

Approximately two weeks from being sent the web-link, parents will also receive one 30-minute telephone call by a trained psychologist to clarify the content of the video, problem solve any barriers to implementing suggested sleep routines and provide practical suggestions to support parents with implementing the practice. Approximately 2 and 4 weeks following the phone call, a text message will be sent to parents. The aim of the text messages will be to reinforce the level of engagement and implementation of strategies for improving child sleeping routines as identified in the phone call.  
Both the content of the telephone call and text messages will be tailored to parents level of engagement with the intervention and any reported barriers to implementing suggested changes. 
The content of the telephone call and text messages will be summarised on an excel spreadsheet by the personnel delivering the intervention.
</interventions>
    <comparator>No support will be provided to the control group.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Child moderate to vigorous physical activity: Total minutes that the child spends in moderate to vigorous physical activity will be assessed using an accelerometer. The child will be asked to wear the accelerometer for at least five days to provide three days of usable data.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 3-month follow up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Child Total Physical Activity: Total volume of activity (assessed via counts per 15 sec epoch) will be assessed using accelerometers. The child will be asked to wear the accelerometer for at least five days to provide three days of usable data.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 3-month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Child sleep duration - Child sleep duration will primarily be measured by parent self-report via telephone interview. This information will also be measured using parent reported daily logs</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 3-month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Child BMI-  Child BMI will be assessed using parent-reported weight and height </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 3-month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Parents will be recruited from childcare centres in the Hunter New England Area. To be eligible, each participant must be a parent of a child aged 3 to 5 years attending a participating preschool, must reside with that child for at least four days a week (in order to implement the suggested sleep strategies) and must be able to understand spoken and written English. 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Children with an intellectual or physical impairment that may impact on their physical activity capacity or prevent them from complying with data collection protocols will be excluded. 

Parents will be excluded from participation if they do not live with the child for four or more days as they will be unable to implement the recommended strategies.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Following baseline data collection, a statistician independent of the research team, will allocate parents to either the intervention or control condition in a 1:1 ratio, using a computerised random number generator. </concealment>
    <sequence>Following baseline data collection, a statistician independent of the research team, will allocate parents to either the intervention or control condition in a 1:1 ratio, using a computerised random number generator. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Time between baseline data collection and receipt of intervention may vary between 2- 6 weeks.
This is a pilot study designed to test the feasibility of research methods and procedures. While not primarily designed for hypothesis testing due to the potentially small sample size, the trial will provide important information about the direction and estimated treatment effect that can be used to inform sample size calculation for a larger trial.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Minutes of moderate-to-vigorous physical activity will be determined using age-specific child-validated equations. Linear mixed effects regression modelling will be undertaken including time (baseline vs 3 months), group (intervention vs control) and group X time interaction as fixed independent variables to assess the impact of the intervention on MVPA. Analysis will be done under an intention to treat framework.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/06/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>10/08/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>29/07/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>28/09/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>76</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>3/02/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Serene (Sze Lin) Yoong</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>c/o Hunter New England Population Health
Booth Building Longworth Avenue Wallsend 2287 NSW</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Hunter New England Population Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Booth Building Longworth Avenue Wallsend 2287 NSW</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Newcastle</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University Drive Callaghan 2308 NSW</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Previous research to improve physical activity in preschool aged children have resulted in only small improvements in child activity levels. Efforts to improve the impact of physical activity interventions may need to consider targeting other potential determinants of child activity. In the recent years, the relationship between sleep duration and obesity, as well as it's related modifiable risk factors (nutrition and physical activity) has received considerable attention. The current evidence examining the association between sleep duration and physical activity in children however have reported mixed findings and consists primarily  of cross-sectional studies.  Randomised trials provide an opportunity to explore the causal relationship between sleep and child physical activity. The proposed study therefore aims to examine the impact of an intervention targeting sleep duration on child activity levels. The research seeks to answer this question by supporting parents to modify sleep routines in their home and measures the potential impact of such an intervention on child PA and sleep. This study will use a randomised controlled trial study design with 150 children aged between 3-5 years old. Parents of 3- to 5-year-old children attending randomly selected childcare centres in the Hunter New England region of New South Wales, Australia will be approached to participate and randomised to receive an intervention targeting sleep practices and a no intervention control group. Parents in the intervention arm will receive a 3-month intervention consisting of a pre-recorded video module outlining practical tips for establishing and implementing strategies conducive to supporting sleep for their child, one follow up support call to support implementation of those strategies and two text messages to reinforce messages provided in the web link and video. The primary outcome of the trial will be the number of minutes the child spends in moderate to vigorous physical activity assessed using an accelerometer. Secondary outcomes include total time in physical activity, sleep duration and child BMI. All data collection will occur at baseline and approximately 3-months follow up.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Kookaburra Circuit, New Lambton Heights 2305 NSW</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/06/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/06/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sze Lin Yoong</name>
      <address>University of Newcastle.
c/o Hunter New England Population Health
Booth Building Longworth Avenue Wallsend 2287 NSW</address>
      <phone>+61433949140</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>serene.yoong@Hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Serene (Sze Lin) Yoong</name>
      <address>University of Newcastle.
c/o Hunter New England Population Health
Booth Building Longworth Avenue Wallsend 2287 NSW</address>
      <phone>+61433949140</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>serene.yoong@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Serene (Sze Lin) Yoong</name>
      <address>University of Newcastle.
c/o Hunter New England Population Health
Booth Building Longworth Avenue Wallsend 2287 NSW</address>
      <phone>+61433949140</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>serene.yoong@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Serene (Sze Lin) Yoong</name>
      <address>University of Newcastle.
c/o Hunter New England Population Health
Booth Building Longworth Avenue Wallsend 2287 NSW</address>
      <phone>+61433949140</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>serene.yoong@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>