<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362587">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/06/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/06/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000658819</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of foot massage on agitation in people with dementia living in residential care.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of foot massage on agitation in people with dementia living in residential care: a randomized control trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Agitated behaviours in people with dementia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dementias</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Foot massage involving long gliding, rhythmical strokes of the entire foot and ankle, and light pressure massage by a certified therapist in the privacy of the participant's bedroom. The intervention consists of 5 minutes massage for each foot, 5 times a week (Mon-Fri) from 1pm-4pm (at a standardized time for each individual) for a period of 3 weeks. After completion of the first treatment arm of the study and after a wash out period of three weeks, participants will then be exposed to the opposite treatment arm and the protocol repeated, that is, those in the first foot massage condition will then move to the quiet presence condition and vice versa.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants in the control arm (quiet presence) will not receive foot massage but will instead have an research assistant sit with them in quiet presence, i.e., close to the resident but not in direct skin to skin contact and no deliberate communication. This activity will also be conducted in participating residents bedrooms for 10-minutes, five times a week (Mon-Fri), from 1pm-4pm (at a standardized time for each individual), for a period of three weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure of Agitation using Pittsburgh Agitation Scale (PAS) and Cohen-Mansfield Agitation Inventory (CMAI).</outcome>
      <timepoint>a) Pre-massage/quiet presence intervention period (baseline)
b) Post-massage/quiet presence intervention period (before cross over/wash-out)
c) Post-cross over treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure of Depression using the Geriatric Depression Scale (GDS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>a) Pre-massage/quiet presence intervention period (baseline)
b) Post-massage/quiet presence intervention period (before cross over/wash-out)
c) Post-cross over treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure of Emotion and Discomfort using Observed Emotion Rating Scale (OERS) and Discomfort Scale for Dementia of the Alzheimer's Type (DSD).</outcome>
      <timepoint>a) Pre-massage/quiet presence intervention period (baseline)
b) Post-massage/quiet presence intervention period (before cross over/wash-out)
c) Post-cross over treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure of physiologic stress by monitoring blood pressure and heart rate using an Omron HEM-7070 electronic sphygmomanometer and body temperature using a No Touch Temporal Artery Thermometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre- and post- each massage intervention and quiet presence</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) informed consent (i.e., authority received from residents themselves and/or relatives and health attorneys to join the research)
2) permanent residence in one of the four chosen residential care facilities in the Brisbane area of South East Queensland for at least 2 months
3) two feet, excluding artificial legs
4) no specific medical-related contraindications (e.g., recent surgery to the area, vessel embolism, peripheral neuropathy, painful bunions or acute illness)
5) a diagnosis of dementia, or met the criteria for probable dementia of Alzheimers type as per DSM-IV
6) a Mini Mental State Exam (MMSE) score of &lt; 18 indicating moderate to severe dementia
7) a documented history of agitation on nursing or medical records within the previous two weeks
8) a score of &gt;3 points on the PAS 30 during each day over a period of one week. (the screening component of the PAS is used here and the full observation is used in the data collection)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) consent unobtainable
2) those that are not residents of the care facilities chosen for this trial
3) not having two feet
4) those that have specific medical-related contraindications (e.g., recent surgery to the area, vessel embolism, peripheral neuropathy, painful bunions or acute illness)
5) no diagnosis of dementia, or not met the criteria for probable dementia of Alzheimers type as per DSM-IV
6) a Mini Mental State Exam (MMSE) score of &gt; 18 
7) a score of &lt;3 points on the PAS 30 during each day over a period of one week.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Under the guidance of a biostatistician, an RA not associated with data collection will conduct the randomization process using a computer-generated program and prepare sequentially numbered sealed opaque envelopes that will outline the different ordering of treatments for each participant. Randomisation will be blocked to ensure that there are equal numbers of participants receiving the intervention and the control activities.</concealment>
    <sequence>Random order generation  using a computer generated program.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>For staff to remain blind to the participants group assignments all participants will have their feet exposed regardless of which the group they are allocated to.  Staff will be requested to refrain from attending participants rooms during the intervention, a do not disturb sign will be placed on the door and staff will be informed that the intervention requires participants to be given quiet, undisturbed time. 

Data collection research assistants will also be blinded to the purpose of the study and the type and timing of the intervention with data collection taking place outside of the time given to the intervention, i.e., before the intervention, end of intervention and post intervention.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Griffith University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>170 Kessels Road
Nathan
QLD 4111</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC) Dementia Research Grants Program</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra
ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Churches of Christ Residential Aged Care</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>41 Brookfield Road
Kenmore
QLD 4069</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Behavioural changes including agitation occur to a significant degree in up to 90% of people with dementia. This experimental, within-subjects, crossover design study with nursing home residents aims to compare the effects of foot massage and quiet presence on agitated behaviours in people living with moderate to severe dementia in residental care settings.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Griffith University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>170 Kessels Road,
Nathan
QLD 4111</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/04/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>NRS/08/08/HREC</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Wendy Moyle</name>
      <address>170 Kessels Road
Nathan, Brisbane,
QLD 4111</address>
      <phone>+61 (0) 7 3735 5526</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>w.moyle@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Wendy Moyle</name>
      <address>170 Kessels Road
Nathan, Brisbane,
QLD 4111</address>
      <phone>+61 (0) 7 3735 5526</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>w.moyle@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Shirley Wee</name>
      <address>Griffith Clinical Trial Coordinating Centre
Research Centre for Clinical &amp; Community Practice Innovation (RCCCPI)
Gold Coast campus, 
G16_2.64, 
Griffith University
Parklands, Southport, QLD 4222</address>
      <phone>+61 (0) 7 5552 9738</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.wee@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>