<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371052">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/11/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/12/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001671459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Personalised relaxation practice to improve sleep quality in patients with chronic fatigue syndrome and depression: A Randomised Control Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Personalised relaxation practice to improve sleep and functioning in patients with chronic fatigue syndrome and depression: A Randomised Control Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1189-5409 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Fatigue Syndrome</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Conditions of unknown or disputed aetiology (such as chronic fatigue syndrome/myalgic encephalomyelitis)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants randomly allocated to the intervention will be assigned to practise the relaxation method that optimizes de-arousal, determined from the results at the initial autonomic assessment. Laboratory-based autonomic measures include recordings of 3-channel electrocardiogram (ECG), respiration, sweat response and pulsatile skin blood volume. To obtain a baseline recording participants will rest in silence for 10 minutes. This is followed by the presentation of each of the three relaxation methods, order counter balanced across participants. The relaxation method which generates the greatest increase in heart rate variability (HRV), high frequency normalised units (HF nu) relative to resting baseline will be assigned to the participant for nightly practice. 

This trial will utilise three different relaxation methods: Guided Relaxation, Gentle Noise, and Instrumental Music, each consisting of pre-recorded 10 minute segments. The Guided Relaxation segments are a calming voice talking through body awareness and/or progressive relaxation.The Gentle noise segments are soft, undulating white noise which sound similar to the ocean or rain. The Instrumental Music segments are calming musical pieces such as Mozart's Flute and Harp Concerto in C, K.299 2nd Movement.

Participants will have free online access to their assigned method and will be able to download the recordings to their smartphone or media device, or if preferred an MP3 player will be provided. Each participant will be provided with seven variations of their assigned method to maximise enjoyment and prevent negative effects of frequent repetition. Participants will be instructed to practice their assigned method at a minimum before bedtime every evening for 4 weeks, and may use at other times if they feel comfortable. 

Participants will also keep a brief log of their sleep, activity, symptoms, and time spent practising their assigned method during this period. Weekly phone contact will be made to enhance engagement and compliance, </interventions>
    <comparator>Participants in the monitoring only control group will complete the same assessments as the intervention group at baseline and the 4 week follow up. Control participants will be informed that they will be monitored for four weeks before receiving the intervention. They will be asked to keep a brief  log of sleep, activity, and symptoms. Weekly phone contact will be made to control for placebo and Hawthorne effects.  During this period they will be asked not to practise mindfulness or meditation activities. At the completion of the second laboratory assessment session (i.e. 4 weeks post randomisation)  participants in the control group will be offered their personalised intervention.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in self-reported sleep quality as assessed by the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI); and daily sleep log</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks after randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in self-reported physical and psychological health as assessed by the Somatic and Psychological Health Report (SPHERE). This questionnaire contains two validated sub-scales for somatic and psychological symptoms (the SOMA and PSYC) and also provides an overall composite score.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks after randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in daytime functioning  as assessed by the Medical Outcomes Survey Short Form (MOS SF-36)</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks after randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in nocturnal autonomic functioning as monitored via nocturnal electrocardiogram (ECG).</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in self-reported sleep quality as assessed by the PSQI</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 weeks after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in self-reported physical and psychological health as assessed by the Somatic and Psychological Health Report (SPHERE). This questionnaire contains two validated sub-scales for somatic and psychological symptoms (the SOMA and PSYC) and also provides an overall composite score.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 weeks after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in daytime functioning  as assessed by the Medical Outcomes Survey Short Form (MOS SF-36)</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 weeks after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intervention Acceptability assessed using a 3-point Likert Scale from 'not at all' to 'completely'.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Change in self-reported psychological distress as assessed by the K-10</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 and 8 weeks after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported change in stress as assessed by the Perceived Stress Questionnaire (PSQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 and 8 weeks after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Meet international diagnostic criteria for chronic fatigue syndrome; or DSM-V diagnostic criteria for depression; Normal or corrected to normal hearing; Sufficient English to complete the questionnaires and follow the guided relaxation tasks;	Willingness and ability to give written informed consent and willingness to participate and comply with the longitudinal nature study.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnant; Other significant illness or major diagnoses such as primary sleep disorder, heart conditions, uncontrolled diabetes, chronic infections, or psychotic disorders; Taking regular medications that affect autonomic activity including beta-blockers/anti-hypertensives; concurrently engaged in other psycho-behavioural interventions. Use of anti-depressants or the oral-contraceptive pill will be recorded but not exclusionary.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>A computerised permuted block randomisation, stratified by clinical condition, will be undertaken by a biostatistician prior to the commencement of the trial.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A sample size of 128 participants (64 in each arm) will be sufficient to detect improvements in fatigue (a 3-point reduction in SOMA score), psychological distress (a 5-point reduction in K10 score), and sleep quality (reduction in PSQI of 2) in the intervention arm, with 80% power, and a Bonferroni-adjusted significance level of 0.013 allowing for multiple comparisons. This conservative estimate will allow for a drop-out rate of up to 10%. Estimates of effect size are based on preliminary data using this protocol, utilising standard deviations (SOMA SD = 2.7; PSQI SD = 3.2; K10 SD = 5.5) from published data in these patient group. The outcome variables will be analysed using regression modelling, with treatment arm (intervention / control)  included as a dichotomous between-subjects variable, and baseline values of the variable included as a within-subjects covariate (to control for chance differences between arms at baseline).   </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>16/05/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>128</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of New South Wales</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>UNSW Australia, High Street, Kensington, NSW, 2052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Judith Jane Mason &amp; Harold Stannett Williams Memorial Foundation </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Equity Trustees Wealth Services Limited
Level 2, 575 Bourke St, Melbourne, Vic, 3000
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Debilitating fatigue; unrefreshing sleep and poor daytime functioning are core features of many neuropsychiatric conditions including chronic fatigue syndrome (CFS) and major depression. Understanding of the aetiologies of these conditions is still incomplete and symptom management strategies have only limited efficacy. 
Accumulating evidence suggests that abnormalities in the function of the autonomic nervous system play a role in the sleep disturbance and chronic fatigue in these conditions. In particular, autonomic activity is characterized by neural hyper-vigilance and a marked loss of parasympathetic, vagus nerve activity that persist even during sleep. Measures of beat-to-beat heart rate variability (HRV) provide well-established, reliable indices of autonomic functioning, which consistently correlate with the severity and outcome of a spectrum of fatiguing disorders, including autoimmune and cardiovascular disease, chronic pain, depression, and CFS . For example, low HRV was repeatedly found to be a strong correlate of unrefreshing sleep, daytime fatigue and cognitive impairment in CFS.
Mindfulness-based stress reduction and relaxation methods are increasingly utilised with the aim to restore autonomic balance.  It is believed that the beneficial effects of these approaches are mediated via their impact on neural circuits involved in self-regulation, and on key stress-response pathways. However, individuals can have very different responses to different relaxations methods; and recent analyses revealed that some patients do not respond optimally to some. 
The main of the current study is to conduct a randomized control trial (RCT) to determine the efficacy and specific benefits of a 4 week personalised relaxation intervention, pre-tested to optimise the individuals' own HRV. Subjective health outcomes and parasympathetic autonomic activity (indexed by HRV) in patients with CFS and depression will be compared to a monitoring only control condition. We anticipate that daily practice of a personalised relaxation method before sleep will be substantively more effective in improving sleep quality, daytime fatigue and functioning in both patient groups compared to treatment as usual with symptom monitoring. We further anticipate that restoration of HRV will contribute to positive health outcomes. The findings from this research will facilitate a better understanding of the pathophysiological mechanisms operating in chronic fatigue conditions.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>UNSW Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>UNSW, Level 3 Rupert Myers Building (South Wing), Kensington, NSW, 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/12/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HC16953</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>22/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Ute Vollmer-Conna</name>
      <address>Level 1, 30 Botany Street,UNSW, Sydney, NSW, 2052</address>
      <phone>+610293852945</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ute@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Claire Macnamara</name>
      <address>Level 1, 30 Botany Street,UNSW, Sydney, NSW, 2052</address>
      <phone>+610293852942</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c.macnamara@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Ute Vollmer-Conna</name>
      <address>Level 1, 30 Botany Street,UNSW, Sydney, NSW, 2052</address>
      <phone>+610293852945</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ute@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Claire Macnamara</name>
      <address>Level 1, 30 Botany Street,UNSW, Sydney, NSW, 2052</address>
      <phone>+610293852942</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c.macnamara@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>