<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362084">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/02/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/02/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000189820</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A crossover, placebo-controlled trial to determine the impact of independent and combined alcohol and energy drink consumption on risky and impulsive behaviour</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>For healthy human volunteers, does combined consumption of alcohol and energy drinks compared to independent consumption increase engagement in risky and/or impulsive behaviour</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1126-1583</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Alcohol-related harms</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Using a crossover placebo-controlled design the two investigational products under examination will include 0.50g/kg alcohol (vodka; 37.5% alcohol by volume Smirnoff Red Label No. 21) and 3.5ml/kg Red Bull Energy Drink (Red Bull GmBH, Austria). The alcohol dose will be decreased to 85% for females due to their decreased body water to fat ratio. The alcohol dose was selected to achieve an average peak blood alcohol concentration of 0.05% and the energy drink dose is equivalent to one standard 250ml energy drink serving per 70kg person. A 250ml serving of Red Bull Energy Drink contains 21g sucrose, 5g glucose, 1g taurine, 80mg caffeine, 60mg glucuronolactone, 50mg inositol, and B vitamins (niacin, pantothetic acid, vitamin B6 and vitamin B12).

Participants will receive a different treatment condition in each of the four experimental sessions: placebo/placebo, alcohol placebo/energy drink, alcohol/energy drink placebo, and alcohol/energy drink. The two constituents will be mixed together, split into two portions, and served via an opaque lidded cup and straw. Participants will have five minutes to orally consume each portion, resulting in a total beverage consumption time of 10 minutes. Administration of treatment conditions including an alcohol and/or energy drink placebo will be identical to active treatment conditions. 

Experimental sessions will be conducted at the same time of day and separated by 7-10 days to ensure complete washout.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo alcohol will be achieved by floating 10ml alcohol on top of the energy drink constituent and spraying the opaque lidded cup with a fine alcohol mist.

Placebo energy drink will be achieved via administration of a Red Bull Energy Drink minus the active ingredients (excluding glucose and sucrose). Those active ingredients removed will include caffeine, taurine, glucuronolactone, inositol,and vitamin B complex.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Objective measure of behavioural risk-taking, assessed via mean number of adjusted pumps in a laboratory-based computerised Balloon Analogue Risk Task (Lejeuz et al., 2001).</outcome>
      <timepoint>115 minutes post-treatment administration</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Objective measure of behavioural inattention impulsivity, assessed via the proportion of commission errors in a laboratory-based computerised Immediate Memory/Delayed Memory Task (Doughtery et al., 2002)</outcome>
      <timepoint>40 minutes post-treatment ingestion</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Objective measure of behavioural inhibition impulsivity and decision-making impulsivity, assessed via the proportion of commission errors in a laboratory-based computerised Cued Go/No-Go Task and Experiential Discounting Task respectively (Marczinski et al., 2011; Reynolds &amp; Schiffbauer, 2004).</outcome>
      <timepoint>60 minutes and 90 minutes post-treatment ingestion respectively</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perception of sedation and stimulation, as assessed using the Biphasic Alcohol Effects Scale (Martin et al., 1993), a self-report unipolar adjective rating scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 30 minutes and 130 minutes post-treatment administration</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perception of general mood state, as assessed using the Profile of Mood States (Loor &amp; McNair, 1971), a self-report adjective rating scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 30 minutes and 130 minutes post-treatment administration</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perception of 20 somatic symptoms (e.g., increase in sweating, dizziness), as assessed using Visual Analogue Scales</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 30 minutes and 130 minutes post-treatment administration</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perception of the treatment and general abilities (e.g., general impairment, driving ability), as assessed using Visual Analogue Scales (Beirness, 1987; Fillmore, 2001)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Perception of treatment: 30 minutes and 130 minutes post-treatment administration

Perception of general abilities: Baseline, 30 minutes and 130 minutes post-treatment administration</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perception of alcohol and energy drink intoxication, as assessed using a Beverage Rating Scale (Fillmore &amp; Vogel-Sprott, 2000)</outcome>
      <timepoint>130 minutes post-treatment administration</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in blood alcohol concentration, as assessed using a Lion Alcometer Breathalyser</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 30, 40, 60, 90, 115, 130 and 140 minutes post-treatment administration</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Male or female

Aged 18 to 35

English as a first language

Right-handed (laterality quotient between +40 and +100 on the Edinburgh Handedness Index (Oldfield, 1971)

Regular energy drink consumer (minimum consumption of one energy drink in the preceding six months and maximum consumption of one energy drink per day on average in the preceding six months)

Regular caffeine consumer (minimum consumption of two caffeinated beverages in the preceding week).

Regular alcohol consumer (minimum consumption of two standard alcoholic beverages in the preceding month)

Normal or corrected-to-normal vision

Normal sleep patterns

Normal Body Mass Index (BMI; between 18.50 and 24.99)

Colour vision acuity (score of 9 or higher on Ishihara's (1936) Test for Colour-Blindness</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>35</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Regular tobacco smoker (typical daily use of one or more cigarettes)

Recent (i.e., preceding two weeks) illicit drug use

Current medicinal or recreational prescription medication use (excluding the contraceptive pill)

Participation in a drug study in the preceding three months

Currently pregnant or breastfeeding

History of any significant neurological condition

Current diagnosis of any significant physical condition

Current diagnosis of a significant psychiatric condition or score of 30 or higher on the Kessler Psychological Distress Scale (Kessler et al., 2002).

Current diagnosis of a significant intellectual disability or an age-normed quotient lower than 71 on the Wechsler Test of Adult Reading (Wechsler, 2001)

History of alcohol or drug abuse or dependence disorder or use of alcohol at hazardous or harmful levels, evident via a score of 10 or higher on the Alcohol Disorders Identification Test (Babor et al., 2001)

Extremely sensitive skin</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participant eligibility will be ascertained via telephone screening and attendance at a familiarisation session. Treatment order allocation will occur following confirmation of eligibility and will be achieved by contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who will be at a central administration site.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomised to the treatment condition order via permuted block randomisation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The four experimental sessions will be separated by a minimum of 2 and a maximum of 7 days to ensure complete washout. Sessions will be conducted between 10am and 7pm. Electroencephalographic activity will be collected during the Immediate Memory/Delayed Memory Task and Cued Go/No-Go Task via placement of a non-invasive electrode cap on the scalp.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>23/02/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>24</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>School of Psychology, University of Tasmania</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Psychology
University of Tasmania
Private Bag 30
Hobart
Tasmania
Australia 7001</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Alcohol Tobacco and other Drugs Council of Tasmania</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>6/81 Salamanca Place
Battery Point
Hobart
Tasmania
Australia 7004</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Alcohol Tobacco and other Drugs Council of Tasmania</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>6/81 Salamanca Place
Battery Point
Hobart
Tasmania
Australia 7004</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The limited existing empirical evidence has generally pointed towards a discrepancy between objective and subjective outcomes following AmED consumption. This discrepancy has been argued to result in increased alcohol consumption and/or risk-taking post-consumption. However, there is a dearth of research (i) supporting this proposed increase in risk-taking, and (ii) attempting to explain the potential mechanisms underlying any changes in risk-taking post-consumption. Consequently, the aim of the current study will be to examine the subjective physiological and psychological outcomes and objective risk and impulsive behavioural outcomes of independent and combined alcohol and energy drink consumption.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee (Tasmania) Network</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Research Services
University of Tasmania
Private Bag 1
Hobart
Tasmania
Australia 7001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/09/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H12010</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Amy Peacock</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
University of Tasmania
Private Bag 30
Hobart
Tasmania
Australia 7001</address>
      <phone>+61 3 62267458</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Amy.Peacock@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Amy Peacock</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
University of Tasmania
Private Bag 30
Hobart
Tasmania
Australia 7001</address>
      <phone>+61 3 62267458</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Amy.Peacock@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Amy Peacock</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
University of Tasmania
Private Bag 30
Hobart
Tasmania
Australia 7001</address>
      <phone>+61 3 62267458</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Amy.Peacock@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>