<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370008">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/01/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/02/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000137493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of the Rugby Fans in Training (RuFIT) study, a healthy lifestyle programme run through professional New Zealand rugby clubs, on bodyweight in men aged 25-65 years.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Rugby Fans in Training (RuFIT) feasibility study: a two-arm, multicentre, randomised control study to investigate the effects of a healthy lifestyle programme delivered through professional New Zealand rugby clubs on bodyweight in overweight men aged 25-65 years.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1178-9454 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>RuFIT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Overweight</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study will investigate the feasibility of implementing the RuFIT programme in overweight New Zealand males. RuFIT has been modified from the Scottish Football Fans in Training (FFIT) programme, and is a healthy lifestyle programme delivered through professional rugby clubs and designed to help men make healthier lifestyle choices to reduce their bodyweight  and improve their health. The 12-week intervention consists of twice weekly sessions which will be run at the rugby club (The Blues in Auckland and the Highlanders in Otago). Participants will receive training and fitness advice from the club trainers, in addition to education sessions on goal setting, lifestyle medicine, nutrition, physical activity, sleep, sedentary behaviour, and long-term maintenance of sustaining a healthier lifestyle. Participants will attend two 75-mintue sessions per week (one during the weekend and one during the working week). The weekend session will consist of an education session followed by a physical activity session, while the session during the working week will consist of a physical activity session only. 

The education sessions will be run in an informal setting, where the participants will sit in a circle and have the opportunity to discuss the content of the presentation as a group. At the end of each education session, participants will make a goal that is relevant to the content that was delivered during the session. All the education sessions will be run by either the club trainer, club doctor, or club nutritionist, except three nutrition sessions which will be run by a community nutrition group (e.g. Pacific Heartbeat). 

The physical activity program will be designed to progressively increase in difficulty over 12 weeks. The first 4 weeks will predominantly consist of aerobic off-feet conditioning (rower and bike) and body weight exercises (squats, push ups, body weight rows, lunges and core work). The second 4 weeks will consist of the same exercises as above but will also introduce external loads (e.g. Kettle bells, Dumbbells, barbells etc.) Running volume will also increased. The last 4 weeks will combine all of the above and involve strength, aerobic, and anaerobic conditioning. In addition, there will also be a number of small-sided games sessions. 

All participants will also receive a pedometer to monitor their step count. Roll calls will be taken at the beginning of each session to assess adherence to the programme. </interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will receive a condensed version of the RuFIT physical activity programme, which will include discussion of the top-line physical activity messages delivered during the original programme (e.g. importance of stretching, warm-up, and the benefits of different exercise types), in addition to an introduction to the exercises performed during the RuFIT programme. This will be delivered during a 1-day training from the club trainer. All control participants will also be given a pedometer to monitor their step count. The 1-day training will occur the week after the final follow-up (i.e. both intervention and control participants will be followed up at the end of week 12, and then the 1-day training day will occur at the end of week 13).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess the feasibility of the programme, including acceptability of randomisation, the proposed measurements, study retention, and acceptability of the adapted programme. These measures will be assessed by self-report using questionnaires designed specifically for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Height will be measured using a stadiometer at the baseline and final follow-up visits.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Heart rate will be assessed using an automated sphygmomanometry. </outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Seated blood pressure will be assessed using an automated sphygmomanometry. </outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bioelectrical impedance will be used to assess body fat.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Shuttle run test will be used to assess cardiovascular fitness.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hip circumference will be assessed using a tape measure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Waist circumference will be assessed using a tape measure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Alcohol consumption will be assessed by self-report using a survey designed specifically for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fruit and vegetable consumption will be assessed by self-report using a survey designed specifically for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body mass index will be measured using the following equation: weight (as assessed by digital scales) in kg / height squared (as assessed by stadiometer).</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Waist-to-hip ratio will be assessed by the ratio of the circumference of the waist (as measured by tape measure in cm) to that of the hips (as measured by tape measure in cm).</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bodyweight will be measured using digital scales at the baseline and final follow-up visits.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Overweight males (with a BMI of 25 kg/m2 or over) aged 25-65 years who are wanting to improve their physical fitness and diet; Are able to safely undertake physical activity; Can understand and read English; Are able to provide written consent to take part in the study.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>25</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Has been told by their doctor that they have a heart condition and that they should only do physical activity recommended by a doctor; Has pain in chest when doing physical activity; Has had pain in chest when not doing physical activity during the last month; Lose their balance because of dizziness or if they ever lose consciousness; Has a bone or joint problem (for example, back, knee, or hip) that could be made worse by a change in physical activity; Their doctor is currently prescribing drugs (for example, water pills) for blood pressure or a heart condition; Any other reason why they should not do physical activity.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Yes, using sealed opaque envelopes. </concealment>
    <sequence>Men will be randomised in a 1:1 ratio to the intervention or control group using a randomisation table created by computer software. The randomisation process will be stratified (1:1) according to study centre.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Baseline characteristics (age, ethnicity, BMI) will be summarised using descriptive statistics. Continuous variables will be presented as mean and standard deviation (SD). Categorical variables will be presented as frequency and percentage. Treatment evaluation will be performed on the principle of intention to treat. All statistical tests will be two-sided and maintained at a 5% significance level. Multiple regression analysis will be used to evaluate the main treatment effect, adjusting for important confounding factors at baseline. Categorical variables will be reported as n and %. Simple chi-squared analyses will be used to evaluate the treatment effect on the proportions adherent to health behaviours at end of the programme period, with estimation of relative risks, 95% confidence intervals and two-sided p-values.
As this is a feasibility study, no power calculation will be performed to assess participant numbers.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>13/02/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>13/02/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>17/02/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>2/04/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>90</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>90</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>25/06/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Dunedin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Auckland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Auckland, Private Bag 92019, Auckland 1142.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Health Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 3 - ProCARE Building, Grafton Mews, at 110 Stanley Street, Auckland 1010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Otago</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>362 Leith St, North Dunedin, Dunedin 9016</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will investigate the feasibility of implementing the RuFIT programme
in overweight New Zealand (NZ) males, a notoriously difficult-to-engage and
under-researched group. The programme will be modified from the Scottish
Football Fans in Training (FFIT) programme, which has been shown to be highly
effective. The RuFIT programme (the first of its kind in NZ) aims to address
underlying barriers to male participation in healthy lifestyle programmes,
harnessing the psychology of sports fandom, and appealing to deeply rooted
values in NZ culture about rugby being a manly exercise. Findings from the
feasibility study will inform a large effectiveness trial of the RuFIT programme.
The feasibility study follows on from the pilot study, which was conducted earlier
in 2015. The pilot study was undertaken in 20 men and was
designed to assess the components of the RuFIT programme in NZ men. Based
on the feedback provided by the participants, the programme delivered in the
RuFIT feasibility study will be better tailored to address the needs of Pacific men.
In particular, more focus will be placed on the role of family members supporting
the men, and healthy eating for different groups. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Auckland Human Participants Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Integrity Unit Level 10, Building 620 49 Symonds Street Auckland 1010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/08/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>015069</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/07/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ralph Maddison</name>
      <address>The University of Auckland, Private Bag 92019, Auckland 1142.</address>
      <phone>+64 9 3737 999 x 87863</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.maddison@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Samantha Marsh</name>
      <address>The University of Auckland, Private Bag 92019, Auckland 1142.</address>
      <phone>+64 9 3737 999 x 87863</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sam.marsh@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Samantha Marsh</name>
      <address>The University of Auckland, Private Bag 92019, Auckland 1142.</address>
      <phone>+64 9 3737 999 x 87863</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sam.marsh@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Samantha Marsh</name>
      <address>The University of Auckland, Private Bag 92019, Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 9 3737 999 x 87863</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sam.marsh@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>