<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371090">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/07/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000951459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Feasibility and effects of inorganic nitrate in acute decompensated heart failure</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Feasibility and effects of inorganic nitrate in acute decompensated heart failure</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>FINO-ADHF</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute decompensated heart failure</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention in this study is inorganic sodium nitrate which is commonly used as a food preservative: E251. 5 doses of 8.4mmol sodium nitrate will be given via oral tablets in 12 hour intervals. Doses will therefore be given at: 0, 12, 24, 36 and 48 hours. The duration of treatment is 48 hours. Doses will be given on the ward as prescribed on the medication chart. Nursing staff will sign against an administered dose and document/report any omission of dose and/or possible adverse effects experienced. Nursing staff will be briefed prior to the commencement of the study. A logbook of study drug/placebo will be kept on the ward alongside coded and labelled bottles of pre-prepared courses of study drug/placebo.</interventions>
    <comparator>This is a placebo controlled trial. Participants in the control group will receive microcrystalline cellulose (Avicel 'Registered Trademark') through the same dosing intervals as the intervention group.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A change in systemic nitrite blood plasma levels.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>At any time point of testing during the treatment phase and immediately following the treatment period. i.e Hours 1, 2, 3, 6, 12, 24, 27, 48, 51. Compared to baseline values obtained at hour zero.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A change in systemic nitrate blood plasma levels.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At any time point of testing during the treatment phase and immediately following the treatment period. i.e Hours 1, 2, 3, 6, 24, 27, 48, 51. Compared to baseline values obtained at hour zero.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in arterial stiffness, assessed via SphygmoCor (Registered Trademark); in particular, augmentation pressure (AP) and augmentation index (AI).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At points of testing during the treatment phase and immediately following the treatment period. i.e Hours 24, 48. Compared to baseline values obtained at hour zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A change in renal function, as assessed by serial plasma cystatin C levels.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At points of testing during the treatment phase and immediately following the treatment period. i.e Hours 24, 48 and pre-discharge. Compared to baseline values obtained at hour zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dyspnoea relief as per Likert scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At points of testing during the treatment phase and immediately following the treatment period. i.e Hours 12, 24, 48 and pre-discharge. Compared to baseline values obtained at hour zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Systemic oxygenation as determined by Sp02 assessed by pulse oximetry.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At points of testing during the treatment phase and immediately following the treatment period. i.e Hours 6, 12, 18, 24, 30, 36, 42, 48, 54, 60, 72 and pre-discharge. Compared to baseline values obtained at hour zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in serum troponin levels. Using serum samples taken at interval periods. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At points of testing during the treatment phase and following the treatment period. i.e Hours 0, 48 and pre-discharge. Compared to baseline values obtained at hour zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A change natriuresis, observable by serial urinary sodium concentrations. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At points of testing during the treatment phase and following the treatment period. i.e Hours 0, 48 and pre-discharge. Compared to baseline values obtained at hour zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A change in the incidence of deterioration and complications of treatment, including acute kidney injury, progression to respiratory failure/ventilatory support, hemodynamic compromise, stroke, and death.
This is a composite outcome. Data for this outcome will be collected from hospital medical records at the time of participant discharge from hospital.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This outcome will be measured at the time of patient discharge from hospital.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A change in the measures of cardiac function and cardiopulmonary congestion as assessed by serial point-of-care chest ultrasonography. 
This is a composite outcome. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At points of testing during the treatment phase and following the treatment period. i.e Hours 0, 6, 48. Compared to baseline values obtained at hour zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A change in blood viscosity assessed through a composite of blood fibrinogen levels</outcome>
      <timepoint>At points of testing during the treatment phase and following the treatment period. i.e Hours 0, 3, 24 and 48. Compared to baseline values obtained at hour zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in serum B-type natriuretic peptide (BNP) levels. Using serum samples taken at interval periods. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At points of testing during the treatment phase and following the treatment period. i.e Hours 0, 48 and pre-discharge. Compared to baseline values obtained at hour zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in serum lactate levels. Using serum samples taken at interval periods. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At points of testing during the treatment phase and following the treatment period. i.e Hours 0 and 48. Compared to baseline values obtained at hour zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in serum ADMA  levels. Using serum samples taken at interval periods.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At points of testing during the treatment phase and following the treatment period. i.e Hours 0 and 48 . Compared to baseline values obtained at hour zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A change in vasorelaxation as assessed by systemic vascular resistance index using the Physioflow (Registered Trademark) device .

NB:This is a primary outcome.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At hours 3, 24, 27, 48 and 51 as compared to baseline measures.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of participants exhibiting significant methaemoglobinaemia ( &gt; or = 5%) assessed using blood samples, at 0, 3, 27, 51 hours.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At timepoints 0, 3, 27, 51 hours. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients presenting to the emergency department within the previous 24 hours, with a provisonal diagnosis with ADHF. Diagnosis is based on at least one of: dyspnoea, orthopnoea or oedema, and one sign of: chest crackles, peripheral oedema or ascites, and/or radiological confirmation of pulmonary vascular congestion on chest radiography. BNP and the boston criteria will also be used to refute and affirm true heart failure status.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients will be excluded if they have a pre-existing need for inotrope therapy; an eGFR &lt;20 mL/min/1.73m2 or on renal replacement therapy (i.e. dialysis); a baseline systolic blood pressure of &lt; 110mmHg; relevant concomitant condition [haemoglobin of less than 10.0 gm/dL, critical aortic stenosis, isolated severe right sided heart failure, respiratory failure, cirrhosis of the liver (Child Pugh class C), advanced malignancy or advanced dementia]; women of child-bearing potential or nursing mothers, recent Sildenafil use (&lt;24 hours on specific enquiry) or a history of Glucose-6-phosphate deficiency elicited on history or medical record search.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>REDCap will be used for electronic data collection and case report forms.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Descriptive statistics will be presented as mean and standard deviation or median and range, as appropriate to the distribution. Comparisons will utilize t-tests or ANOVA (two way with repeated measures) for normally distributed data. Where appropriate, non-normally distributed data will be logarithmically transformed to achieve a normal distribution, or the Wilcoxon rank sum will be utilized for comparisons. 

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1 / Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>8/08/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Footscray Hospital - Footscray</hospital>
    <hospital>Sunshine Hospital - St Albans</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Western Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Western Health Cardiology, Footscray Hospital, Gordon St, 160 Footscray VIC   3011
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Melbourne</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of Melbourne, Parkville, VIC, 3010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Acute decompensated heart failure (ADHF) is the most frequent reason for hospital admission in Australia, requiring improved treatment strategies. Inorganic sodium nitrate (NaNO3) is an indirect dietary means of delivering nitric oxide (NO), which is deficient in ADHF. It is proposed that NaNO3 will improve circulation via vasodilation, without significant hypotension, whilst improving renal blood flow and preserving renal filtration, in ADHF. The aim of this pilot is to evaluate the feasibility and effectiveness of sodium nitrate (NaNO3 8.4mmol administered in 12- hour intervals) over 48 hours as a treatment for ADHF, correlating systemic levels of NO precursors (Nitrate and Nitrite), with measures of cardiovascular and renal function, in 40 patients.
We propose a single centre randomized, double-blind, placebo controlled trial, specifically testing the primary hypothesis that supplemental NaNO3 will result in increased systemic nitrate (NO3-) and nitrite (NO2-) levels, in parallel with improved vasorelaxation, as assessed by systemic vascular resistance index (SVRI). Additional surrogate measures relevant to the known pathophysiology of ADHF will be obtained in order to assess clinical effect on dyspnoea, diuretic efficiency and renal function. 
The results of this novel strategy will be of significant interest to the heart failure community and may help inform a future, larger study.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Melbourne Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Royal Melbourne Hospital - City Campus, 6 East
Grattan Street, Parkville Victoria 3050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/04/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/MH/402</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/03/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Christopher Neil</name>
      <address>Western Health Cardiology, Footscray Hospital, Gordon St, Footscray VIC 
Locked Bag 2, Footscray VIC 3011
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8345 6666</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christopher.neil@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michael Seman</name>
      <address>Western Health Cardiology, Footscray Hospital, Gordon St, Footscray VIC 
Locked Bag 2, Footscray VIC 3011</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8345 6666</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michael.seman@wh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michael Seman</name>
      <address>Western Health Cardiology, Footscray Hospital, Gordon St, Footscray VIC 
Locked Bag 2, Footscray VIC 3011</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8345 6666</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michael.seman@wh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Roman Falls</name>
      <address>Western Health Cardiology, Footscray Hospital, Gordon St, Footscray VIC 
Locked Bag 2, Footscray VIC 3011</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>roman.falls@wh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>