<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343049">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/06/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/06/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000614998</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Does acupuncture/dry needling applied as a sensory discrimination training tool decrease pain in chronic low back pain patients more than acupuncture alone?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Does acupuncture/dry needling applied as a sensory discrimination training tool decrease pain in chronic low back pain patients more than acupuncture alone?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic nonspecific lower back pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Acupuncture of lumbar spine (same points as the control) with sensory discrimination (subjects watch the acupuncture point via a mirror)
Detail: 
All the chosen points are designed to represent the most common and practical local acupuncture points for the treatment of low back pain. A total of 14 points will be inserted for each intervention. 
Considering subjects will be in different sizes and shapes, instead of using metric system to standardise points their thumb width (cun, unit of measuring points in acupuncture) will be measured by using a cunometer (a measuring instrument similar to a clipper that is used to find thumb width/cun). The spinous processes of lumbar spine will be used as the point of reference and the cunometer will be employed to find the acupuncture 
points. The points will be marked on the subjects lumbar region with skin safe pen and left for the duration of both intervention. 
The points are mostly traditional points thus they run over a meridian (Urinary Bladder). Four of the points do not run over the meridian and they are common Trigger or Ah Shi points.All these points have been used in numerous large trials of acupuncture for low back pain. The Depth of penetration will be standardised to only 15mm and insertion will be directed obliquely towards the spinous process. To standardise the depth all needles will be exactly 15mm in length and they are completely inserted in both interventions.
In the experimental intervention arm subjects will participate in a sensory discrimination training programme similar to that used by Moseley et al. (2008b) in the management of CRPS. Subjects will be shown a picture of the back with the position of each needle numbered. The clinician will manipulate a single needle for a few seconds in random order and the subject will be required to nominate which needle is being stimulated. This will be performed with visualisation of the back via a mirror in the first 10 minutes and progressed to without a mirror in the last 10 minutes.

Each intervention sesssion is 20 minutes in duration with a 10 minutes wash out periods between each intervention. Subjects will have to attend one appointment. During the appointment they will recieve the two interventions.</interventions>
    <comparator>Acupuncture of Lumbar spine without any sensory discrimination.  ISQ points as experimental group.

Detail:
In the control intervention arm subjects will be asked to lay comfortably and relaxed and not attend to the needles and there will be minimal interaction with the treating therapist while the needles are in and while the therapist manipulates the needles for 20 minutes.

Each intervention sesssion is 20 minutes in duration with a 10 minutes wash out periods between each intervention. Subjects will only have to attend one appointment. During the appointment they will recieve the two interventions.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lower Back Pain assessed using a Visual Analogue Scale after 10 most provocative active movement.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcme is assessed immediately before and after treatment and control.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>None</outcome>
      <timepoint>None</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Subjects with Nonspecific Lower Back Pain
Inclusion Criteria
Low back pain as the predominant problem
At least 6 months duration of current episode
Non-specific in nature
A score of 4 or more on the SF36 bodily pain scale (modified to read LBP)
18 years or older
Adequate knowledge of English to complete the forms
Ability to provide written informed consent
Otherwise well</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion Criteria
Specific low back pain (infection, malignancy, inflammatory disease, etc)
Nerve root pain 
Pregnant or less than 6 months post partum
Unstable psychiatric condition
Recent back surgery (within previous 12 months)
Judged by treating clinician to be unsuitable for acupuncture treatment</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subjects will be randomised by concealed randomisation.A random sequence of 25 numbers will be generated by an independent person not involved in the study, with each number in the sequence sealed in consecutively numbered opaque envelopes and an odd/even allocation to group used to randomise subjects to either experimental arm then contorl or’ or ‘control arm then experimental arm’.</concealment>
    <sequence>To generate the sequence for treatment a computer software will be used. The mothod will be computerised sequence generation.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/07/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>25</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>M Sadegh Sam Abbaszadeh</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Curtin University
Kent Street, Bentley, Perth 
Western Australia. 6102</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Curtin University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Curtin University
Kent Street, Bentley, Perth 
Western Australia. 6102</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Anne Smith</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Curtin University
Kent Street, Bentley, Perth 
Western Australia. 6102</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Ben Wand</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>University of Notre Dame
13-19 Mouat Street
Fremantle WA 6160</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Evidence obtained from this study may further increase our understanding of the CLBP experience and may potentially help us to develop a more effective treatment for management of this problem. Furthermore, it may also give us a new insight about the mechanism of acupuncture/dry needling. 
We hypothesis that CLBP patients will derive greater benefit from acupuncture when it is used as a sensory discrimination training tool</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin Human Ethic Commitee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Curtin University
Kent Street
Bentley WA 6102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/06/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sam Abbaszadeh</name>
      <address>328 Warwick Road Warwick WA 6023</address>
      <phone>+61 402842712</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sam.abbazadeh@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sam Abbaszadeh</name>
      <address>328 Warwick Road Warwick WA 6023</address>
      <phone>+61 402842712</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sam.abbaszadeh@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sam Abbaszadeh</name>
      <address>328 Warwick Road Warwick WA 6023</address>
      <phone>+61 402842712</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sam.abbazadeh@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>