<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343111">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/06/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/06/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000651987</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Platelet rich plasma injection for treatment of osteoarthritis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effects of intra-articular injection of platelet rich plasma on pain and function in patients with knee osteoarthritis: A randomised controlled trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1122-4264</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>osteoarthritis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>osteochondral defect</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>To make the platelet rich plasma (PRP), 20 ml of the patients blood will be collected and centrifuged at 100g for 5 minutes. The plasma and buffy coat will be drawn from the top, placed in a sterile tube and activated using low-level light irradiation. The activated PRP will then be injected into the patient's symptomatic knee under ultrasound guidance.

Patients will receive three injections each of 5ml platelet-rich plasma one week apart. Time-points for injections: 1) initial injection, 2) one week following initial injection and 3) two weeks following initial injection. This results in a total treatment duration of two weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>Three injections each of 2ml (16 mg) of Hylan G-F 20 one week apart. Time-points for injections: 1) initial injection, 2) one week following initial injection and 3) two weeks following initial injection. This results in a total treatment duration of two weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain measured using 100mm Visual Analogue Score (VAS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, daily for the first two weeks, weekly for the subsequent two weeks and four and eight weeks, and six and 12 months, following the final injection</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Knee Injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, four and eight weeks, and six and 12 months, following the final injection</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximum single leg hop for distance. Participant hops as far as possible and the distance (in cm) from the toe in starting position to heel in landing position is measured by the researcher using a tape measure. The best of three hops is recorded.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, four and eight weeks, and six and 12 months, following the final injection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximum number of knee bends performed in 30 seconds. Participant bends the knee without bending forward from the hip (until they cannot see a line along the toes, equivalent to about 30 degrees of knee flexion) as many times as possible in 30 seconds. Time is recorded using a stopwatch and number of bends are counted by the researcher.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, four and eight weeks, and six and 12 months, following the final injection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>A diagnosis of OA assessed via the International Cartilage Repair Society guidelines and a visual analogue pain score of greater than 50 out of 100</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>No systemic or inflammatory joint disease, no history of crystalline or neuropathic arthropathy, no cancer or other tumour-like lesions, not pregnant or lactating, not drug abusing, no other intra articular lesion in the previous six months, no allergy to any test substance and not immunosuppressed</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Recruited via a sports medicine clinic and provided with a full medical examination and assessment of the affected knee joint to determine study eligibility. Eligible participants will be allocated to either the control or intervention group by an independent clinic staff member using a central concealed computer randomisation process.</concealment>
    <sequence>Random order concealed allocation of participants into either the control or intervention group will be performed by simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e., computerised sequence generation). There will be no stratified allocation.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>22/06/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>28/07/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>5/08/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Kade Paterson</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Australian Catholic University, 115 Victoria Pde, Fitzroy VIC 3095</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dan Bates</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Lakeside Sports Medicine Centre, Melbourne Sports and Aquatic Centre, Aughtie Drive, Albert Park, VIC 3206</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Osteoarthritis (OA) is a progressive degenerative disease characterised by loss or damage of the cartilage surface of joints, resulting in pain and disability. Unitl recently, management of mild to moderate OA has been limited to symptomatic relief with analgesia or anti-inflammatory medications, viscosupplementation and exercise therapy, and in extreme cases joint replacement surgery. 

An emerging treatment for soft tissue healing and bone mineralisation is platelet rich plasma (PRP) injection. In addition to clotting functions, activated platelets have been found to contain growth factors, cytokines and protiens responsible for promotion of tissue regeneration and healing. Injection of PRP solution to joints during surgical procedures have demonstrated positive effects on healing, pain and function post-operatively. However, to our knowledge, there are limited ramdomised controlled studies evaluating the effect of a less invasive technique of intra-articular injection of PRP. Therefore, this double blinded study aims to assess the changes in pain, activity levels and lower extremity functional ability of patients with mild to moderate OA following intra-articular PRP injection compared to usual treatment of Hylan G-F 20 (SYNVISC).</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Australian Catholic University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Australian Catholic University, Level 5, 250 Victoria Parade, Fitzroy VIC 3065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>31/05/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>V2011 09</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/02/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kade Paterson</name>
      <address>Centre for Health, Exercise and Sports Medicine
Department of Physiotherapy, Melbourne School of Health Sciences
The University of Melbourne, Victoria, 3010
AUSTRALIA 
</address>
      <phone>+61 3  8344 0425 </phone>
      <fax>+61 3 8344 3771 </fax>
      <email>kade.paterson@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kade Paterson</name>
      <address>Centre for Health, Exercise and Sports Medicine
Department of Physiotherapy, Melbourne School of Health Sciences
The University of Melbourne, Victoria, 3010
AUSTRALIA 
</address>
      <phone>+61 3  8344 0425 </phone>
      <fax>+61 3 8344 3771 </fax>
      <email>kade.paterson@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kade Paterson</name>
      <address>Centre for Health, Exercise and Sports Medicine
Department of Physiotherapy, Melbourne School of Health Sciences
The University of Melbourne, Victoria, 3010
AUSTRALIA 
</address>
      <phone>+61 3  8344 0425 </phone>
      <fax>+61 3 8344 3771 </fax>
      <email>kade.paterson@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kade Paterson</name>
      <address>Centre for Health, Exercise and Sports Medicine
Department of Physiotherapy, Melbourne School of Health Sciences
The University of Melbourne, Victoria, 3010
AUSTRALIA 
</address>
      <phone>+61 3  8344 0425 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kade.paterson@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>