<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366280">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/05/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/05/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000517673</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of progressive resistance training in women with polycystic ovary syndrome. A feasibility study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised control trial comparing the benefits of progressive resistance training and/or usual care on health status in women with polycystic ovary syndrome</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>PCOSPRT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>polycystic ovary syndrome

</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>insulin resistance</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>obesity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>menstrual disturbance</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>anxiety</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Polycystic Ovary Syndrome health related quality of life</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>exercise self efficacy</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>health related quality of life</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>perceived stress scale</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other reproductive health and childbirth disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Women will be randomised into either the progressive resistance training group or usual care group. The trial will run for 12 weeks. Both groups will need to attend two baseline and two follow up session for 1-2 hours. Both groups will be assessed weekly to document for adverse changes or events 
Exercise intervention
PRT- Participants randomised to the progressive resistance training (PRT) will be required to undertake every week for 12 weeks: two supervised exercise sessions on non consecutive days for 1 hour at the University of Western Sydney Campbelltown or Penrith campus as well as perform two unsupervised sessions for 30 minutes at home. The exercises will consist of muscles involving the arms, back, legs and core. the basis of the intervention is to train to neuromuscular fatigue (for instance training at an RM of 8-12 repetitions. for the supervised sessions, exercises will consist of mainly machines and free weight activities. for the first two weeks each exercise will be performed at 2 sets of 8-12 RM. on the third week most exercises will be progressed to 3 sets of 8-12 RM until study completion. Exercise sessions will be progressed and adjusted to account for individuals exercise capacity and training adaptations.
The home based exercises will consist of six different body callisthenics (such as body weight exercises) without the use of machines/free weights and each exercise will be performed with 3 sets of 10 repetitions. the home based exercises will be modified every four weeks to different and challenging exercises.  adherence for the home based sessions will be measured via determine the number of sessions done for both supervised and unsupervised (home based). Participants are required to maintain a diary to record the number of sessions done for the home based sessions.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care group- participants randomised to the usual care group will be required to continue with their usual care (from physicians, practitioners etc). Upon completion participants will be evaluated and will be provided with an exercise program to incorporate as part of their lifestyle program</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome: Feasibility of prescribing PRT. This will be done by evaluating:
*	recruitment strategies and rate
*	adherence and compliance rates
*	retention rates for PRT and usual care
*	suitability of outcome measures
</outcome>
      <timepoint>February to November, Before and 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcome: menstrual regularity via self-care diaries</outcome>
      <timepoint>before and after 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body composition changes by DEXA scans, waist circumference, hip circumference</outcome>
      <timepoint>before and after 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>haematological outcomes (i.e. insulin, glucose, SHBG, FAI, Testosterone, Hs-CRP, HbA1c)</outcome>
      <timepoint>before and after 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximal isometric voluntary contractions for the upper and lower body - using an isokinetic machine such as the biodex. </outcome>
      <timepoint>before and after 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>psychological status: using validated questionnaires which include:
*	Polycystic ovary syndrome quality of life
*	Short-form 36
*	Depression Anxiety stress scale
*	Exercise self efficacy
*	Perceived stress scale
</outcome>
      <timepoint>before and after 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Must be diagnosed with polycystic ovary syndrome by Rotterdam Criteria, which includes two of the following: (i) irregular menstrual cycles (&lt;21 or &gt;35 days), (ii) clinical (hirsutism, acne) or biochemical (elevation of at least one circulating ovarian androgen) and (iii) polycystic ovaries on untrasound along with the exclusion of other etiologies such as cushings syndrome, congenital adrenal hyperplasia and androgen secreting tumours.  Must have BMI &gt; 25 m/kg2 and not on any fertility treatments. Not currently engaged in a high training resistance program, willingness to be randomised and to undergo study protocols</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>42</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Not pregnant or breastfeeding, no use of cigarettes greater than 6 months, no history of cardiovascular, liver, kidney, respiratory disease, uncontrolled hypertension or cancer, no acute or chronic medical conditions that would make assessment and interventions potentially hazardous or impossible to assess.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be recruited by means of flyer advertisement posted on bulletin boards, and delivered by online social media (e.g Facebook), mail drops and newspaper.  Participants will also be recruited via direct referral by local physicians and clinicians. All potential participants will be pre-screened via telephone or in-person, according to individual preference, for medical and study eligibility using a standardised eligibility checklist, detailed medical history questionnaire, and Physical Activity Readiness Questionnaire (PAR-Q).  Participants will be required to attend a baseline testing session for 1-2 hours for the assessment of body composition, isometric strength, menstrual cyclicity and psychological status. Upon completion of baseline testing participants will be given a sealed envelope detailing the allocation to either the PRT or usual care group.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation procedures used will be a simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation). This will be done by an investigator not involved in testing or training</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Secondary analysis will be analysed via intention-to-treat with all patients included regardless of dropout or level of adherence.  Missing data will be imputed according to the maximum likelihood expectation algorithm via the Statistical Package for the Social Sciences (SPSS Version 20.0).  Data will be presented as the mean or median, with ranges, SD, and confidence intervals to express group differences as appropriate.  Baseline characteristics will be compared using t-tests and Mann-Whitney U-tests for continuous parametric and non-parametric variables, respectively.  Chi square tests will be used for all non-continuous, descriptive variables.  Changes over time (group x time) in all continuous outcome variables and covariates will be determined by repeated measures analysis of variance (ANOVA) in unadjusted models, and analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) when appropriate.  Effect sizes and 95% confidence intervals will be calculated.  Categorical variables will be analyzed using logistic regression models.  Linear and multivariate regression analyses will be used to analyze associations between variables of interest.  A p value of &lt;0.05 will be considered indicative of statistical significance; clinical significance will be interpreted in light of the meaningfulness and magnitude of the adaptations observed.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Miss Lisa Vizza</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Science and Health
University of Western Sydney
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith South NSW 2751</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Western Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>School of Science and Health
University of Western Sydney
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith South NSW 2751</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Western Sydney</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Science and Health
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith South NSW 2751</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Douglas Hanly Moir</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>14 Giffnock Avenue
Macquarie Park NSW
2113 </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to investigate the feasibility of a 12 week progressive resistance training program versus usual care in overweight women with polycystic ovary syndrome. Participants will be required to attend two baseline and two follow up session for 1-2 hours at the University of Western Sydney Campbelltown for the assessment of body composition, isometric strength, menstrual cycle and psychological status.  On separate days participants will also be asked to undertake fasting blood samples first thing in the morning at Douglas Hanly Moir pathology. Upon completion of baseline testing participants will be randomised to either the PRT or usual care group and will be given to participants in a sealed envelope. Participants randomised to the PRT group will be required to exercise four sessions per week, where two sessions will be supervised at the University Western Sydney Campbelltown campus while the other two sessions will be unsupervised (i.e. home based). . If you are allocated to the usual care group, you will be required to continue with your usual care management for the duration of the trial. The researcher will contact you weekly to document for any adverse events or reactions. Participants will also be required to maintain a diary to record their  menstrual cycle details such as cycle length (i.e. day one of period  and day one of next period), signs and symptoms etc. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human research Ethics committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Locked bag 1797 Penrith NSW 2751 Australia 
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/12/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H10448</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Lisa Vizza</name>
      <address>School of Science and Health
University of Western Sydney Locked Bag 1797 Penrith South NSW 2751</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4620 3397</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4620 3792</fax>
      <email>16310852@student.uws.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Lisa Vizza</name>
      <address>School of Science and Health
University of Western Sydney Locked Bag 1797 Penrith South NSW 2751</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4620 3397</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4620 3792</fax>
      <email>16310852@student.uws.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Lisa Vizza</name>
      <address>School of Science and Health
University of Western Sydney Locked Bag 1797 Penrith South NSW 2751</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4620 3397</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4620 3792</fax>
      <email>16310852@student.uws.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Lisa Vizza</name>
      <address>School of Science and Health
University of Western Sydney Locked Bag 1797 Penrith South NSW 2751 </address>
      <phone>02 46203397</phone>
      <fax>02 46203792</fax>
      <email>16310852@student.uws.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>