<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82546">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/01/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/01/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000040369</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Balance dysfunction and falls risk in early dementia-Magnitude of the problem, and effectiveness of balance training program.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In people with early diagnosed Alzheimer's disease, will a home based balance exercise programme be effective in improving balance performance and quality of life of the patients and their caregivers.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Dementia (mild to moderate)</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Balance dysfunction</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dementias</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention group will participate in a home based balance exercise programme, provided at home by an experienced physiotherapist. This exercise programme is modified from an existing home exercise programme Otaogo programme to suit people with memory difficulties, and will be tailored to the results of the balance and mobility assessments. The Otago programme has been shown in a number of studies of older people to reduce falls. The exercise programme will be structured to be performed at least 5 times each week, and will have a focus on standing balance and strengthening exercise, as well as a graduated walking programme. The physiotherapist will provide six home visits over the six month period, to monitor, advise, and modify the programme as required. The frequency of home visits in this study is slightly increased on the successful Otago programme (4 visits), aiming to maximise safety with increased visits particularly in the first 6-8 weeks of the programme. An exercise booklet will be provided by the physiotherapist to each pariticipant to give illustrations and instructions for the participant to continue the exercise programme at home. In between visit, the physiotherapist will contact participant by telephone.</interventions>
    <comparator>There will be 3 sub-groups of participants. One intervention group (107 patients with recently diagnosed Alzheimer's dementia) will be provided with a home based balance exercise program. A futher 107 patients with recently diagnosed Alzheimer's dementia will receive a home occupational therapy programme involving six home visits for the six month duration by an experienced Occupational Therapist, to provide an information / education programme focusing on a mixture of social activities, psychological support, and maintenance of Activities of Daily Living advice. This programme will be based on a programme for people with dementia by Graff et al (2007). These Occupational Therapy (OT) home visit sessions will avoid any messages encouraging change in activity.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Laboratory measures of balance (NeuroCom Balance Master: long plate). e.g. Modified Clinical Test of Sensory Interaction on Balance, composite score.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 6, 12, 24 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical measures of balance and mobility, e.g. Step Test, number of steps in 15 seconds (worst leg).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 6, 12, 24 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Falls and falls risk measure by FROP-community assessment and the Lord's abbreviated Physiological Profile Assesment</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 6, 12, 24 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Carer burden measured by the Zarit Carer Burden Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 6, 12, 24 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life measured by the Assessment of Quality of Life (AQoL)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 6, 12, 24 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Older people with recent diagnosis of Alzheimer's disease, of mild to moderate severity, independent mobility, no other serious neurological or othopaedic history that impacts on balance and mobility performance.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Non-dementia diagnosis or dementia diagnosis other than Alzheimer's disease, Alzheimer's disease more than 12 months or severe dementia, limited mobility.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be informed about the study by a geriatrician at the CDAMS Clinic at the time or shortly after the time a patient is diagnosed with Alzheimer's disease. They will obtain permission from the participant or the person responsible for the research team to contact them about the research project. Following contact by the research team, and agreement to participate,  participants who finish the baseline assessment will be allocated to one of the two intervention groups by a research assistant who is independent of the assessors. She will communicate with the participants and their caregivers and advise them which group they are in and the next phases of the project. Allocation was concealed by using numbered opaque envelopes, the next consecutive one opened for each consecutive participant.</concealment>
    <sequence>Random numbers table generated by a computer software to determine group allocation for each participant ID number.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>28/08/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>264</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>3021</postcode>
    <postcode>3052</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>National Ageing Research Institute (NARI)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>34-54 Poplar Road, PO Box 31
Parkville,  Victoria, 3052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Ageing Research Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>34-54 Poplar Rd, Parkville, Victoria, 3052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Royal Melbourne Hospital (Royal Park Campus)</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>34-54 Poplar Road, Parkville, Victoria 3052</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>The Sunshine Hospital (Western Health)</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Furlong Road, St Albans, Victoria 3021</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Two hundred and fourteen participants with mild to moderate severity of Alzheimers disease will be recruited for the randomised controlled trial. Sixty-four age and gender matched (to first 64 people with Alzheimers dementia in the control group) healthy participants will be recruited for the longitudinal study. A series of laboratory and clinical measures will be used to investigate balance and mobility performances. All participants will undergo a full assessment process as the baseline, and will then be randomized to a control or an intervention group. The participants in the intervention group will undertake an individually tailored balance training at home programme of 6 months duration. This exercise programme will be based on the results of the balance assessment and conducted under the guidelines which is modified from the established Otago programme by a physiotherapist. For the control group, the participants will be provided six home visits by an occupational therapist. Both intervention group and control group will continue with their usual care programme as recommended by the Cognitive, Dementia and Memory Services (CDAMS). All participants will be re-assessed at the completion of the programme (after 6 months), and again in a further six months. Additionally, the first 64 participants of the control group with mild to moderate severity Alzheimers disease, and 64 age and gender matched healthy controls will be re-assessed on all measures again after 24 months to determine the longitudinal changes in balance performance and magnitude of balance dysfunction. This study will give improved understanding of the changes in balance performance associated with the progression of dementia and the degree of effectiveness of home based balance training in early stages of the disease on balance performance, risks of falls and quality of life in people with Alzheimers disease and their families.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Melbourne Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Royal Melbourne Hospital, Parkville, VIC, 3050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/04/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC 2008.004</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/01/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Keith Hill</name>
      <address>Preventive and public health division, National Ageing Research Institute (NARI), 34-54 Poplar Rd, PO Box 31, Parkville Victoria 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8387 2626</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 8387 2153</fax>
      <email>k.hill@nari.unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Plaiwan  Suttanon</name>
      <address>Preventive and public health division, National Ageing Research Institute (NARI), 34-54 Poplar Rd, PO Box 31, Parkville Victoria 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8387 2383</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 8387 2153</fax>
      <email>p.suttanon@nari.unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Plaiwan  Suttanon</name>
      <address>Preventive and public health division, National Ageing Research Institute (NARI), 34-54 Poplar Rd, PO Box 31, Parkville Victoria 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8387 2383</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 8387 2153</fax>
      <email>p.suttanon@nari.unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>