<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371282">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001102460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Changes in Pain Sensitivity Following Cervical or Lumbar Spinal Manipulative Therapy in Spinal Pain Patients: A Randomised Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Changes in Pressure Pain Threshold Following Cervical or Lumbar Spinal Manipulative Therapy in Spinal Pain Patients: A Randomised Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Spinal Pain</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Spinal Manipulative Therapy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>On a single occasion, each participant will be randomised to receive one of the following two interventions:
A) a single cervical high-velocity low-amplitude spinal manipulation technique known as the index pillar push, targeted at the C5-C6 facet joint on the most symptomatic side.
B) a single lumbar high-velocity low-amplitude spinal manipulation technique known as the hypothenar mamillary push, targeted at the L5-S1 facet joint on the most symptomatic side.
Each intervention will take approximately 1 minute to complete. Interventions will be performed in a private research room, on a chiropractic examination table, by a chiropractor with a minimum of 3 years clinical experience.
Multiple registered chiropractors will provide the interventions. They will receive training to standardise the techniques and participant interaction. Training will be in the form of a single 30 minute small group workshop. Topics will include a refresher on the specific manipulation techniques being used (the chiropractors will already be at least well familiar with the techniques), how to interact with participants in a reassuring but neutral manner. This will be run by a researcher with clinical experience as a chiropractor.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants will be randomised to either the cervical or lumbar manipulation group</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pressure pain threshold will be measured using a digital pressure algometer with a 1cm2 rubber probe (Wagner FPIX 50, USA),  bilaterally at the medial gastrocnemius muscle, L5 paraspinal musculature, deltoid muscle, and C5 paraspinal musculature. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pressure pain threshold will be measured at each site immediately following intervention, and again 15 minutes, 30 minutes, 45 minutes, and 60 minutes after intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>None</outcome>
      <timepoint>None</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>a) Current, episodic, or chronic spinal pain in both the neck and low back. Episodic is defined as at least 3 episodes of pain in the last 12 months, and chronic is defined as at least 3 months of ongoing pain in the last 12 months.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>a) Any contraindications to cervical or lumbar SMT
b) Have had spinal manipulative therapy within the previous week
c) Have cervical or lumbar radiculopathy, neurological symptoms, or a neurological condition
d) Have fibromyalgia or chronic widespread pain
e) Have an inflammatory joint condition (e.g. rheumatoid arthritis)
f) Have a bleeding disorder or take anticoagulant medication (e.g. warfarin)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The clinician providing the intervention will randomise the participant to one of two groups with the use of sequentially numbered, sealed, opaque envelopes containing randomised ones or twos. Group one will receive a cervical spinal manipulation and group two will receive a lumbar spinal manipulation.</concealment>
    <sequence>The ones and twos will be generated and placed into the sequential envelopes using an online random number generator with 1:1 allocation, by a researcher not involved in data collection (http://www.graphpad.com/quickcalcs/).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Based on the study by Waller et al. 2015, to see a 15% change (effect size 0.64) in pressure pain threshold at the lumbar spine, based on 80% power and with alpha at 5%, a sample size of 40 per group (80 total) will be required.
Repeated measures ANCOVAs will be run with factors of time and group to investigate within- and between-group change. Covariates for the ANCOVA will include two psychosocial questionnaires.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>24/02/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>17/06/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>20</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Stopped early</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/12/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>17/06/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis>Data collected is being analysed</dataanalysis>
    <withdrawnreason>Participant recruitment difficulties</withdrawnreason>
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>School of Health Professions, Murdoch University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>90 South St
Murdoch WA
6150</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Murdoch University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>90 South St
Murdoch WA
6150</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will be a randomised trial investigating whether changes in sensitivity to pressure pain are different when comparing spinal manipulation (a manual therapy technique) of the neck and the low back. It will measure any changes in pain sensitivity over 1 hour, and will measure pain sensitivity in 4 different areas of the body to study how widespread any changes are.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Murdoch University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Murdoch University
90 South St
Murdoch WA
6150</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/10/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016/178</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/09/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Bruce F Walker</name>
      <address>Murdoch University
90 South St
Murdoch WA
6150</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9360 1297</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bruce.walker@murdoch.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sasha L Dorron</name>
      <address>Murdoch University
90 South St
Murdoch WA
6150</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9360 2114</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.dorron@murdoch.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sasha L Dorron</name>
      <address>Murdoch University
90 South St
Murdoch WA
6150</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9360 2114</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.dorron@murdoch.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sasha L Dorron</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>