<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="81852">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/02/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/03/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000170426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Safety and Efficacy Study of Ambrisentan in Subjects with Pulmonary Hypertension</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>ARIES-3: A Phase 3, Long-term, Open-label, Multicenter Study of the Safety and Efficacy of Ambrisentan in Subjects with Pulmonary Hypertension</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ARIES-3</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Gilead Sciences Inc: AMB-323</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pulmonary Hypertension</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Hypertension</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a long-term, open-label study of a new experimental drug called ambrisentan. The purpose of this study is to evaluate the safety and efficacy of ambrisentan in a broad population of subjects with pulmonary arterial hypertension (PAH). Secondarily, this study will evaluate the effects of ambrisentan on other clinical measures of PAH, long-term treatment success, and survival. Subjects will receive 5 mg ambrisentan each day by mouth for the first 24 weeks. Then, subjects may receive 2.5, 5, or 10 mg each day by mouth, based on investigator discretion as clinically indicated. Each day of study participation subjects will receive ambrisentan until the study is ended or the subject discontinues study participation. Subjects may continue to receive ambrisentan until such time as the investigator or subject chooses to stop ambrisentan treatment, the cumulative adverse event profile does not warrant continuation of the study, ambrisentan becomes commercially available, or Gilead Sciences, Inc., stops the study.</interventions>
    <comparator>No comparator.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in the 6-minute walk distance (6MWD).  The 6MWD is the longest possible distance that a subject can walk in a timed 6-minute interval.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The 6MWD will be assessed at baseline, weeks 4, 12 and 24.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1) Clinical worsening of PAH</outcome>
      <timepoint>Events that mark the natural history of disease progression. These events will be assessed when or if they occur for each subject, and the event outcome will be recorded at the time of occurence. The occurrence of these events will be monitored for the duration of subject participation, until the study is ended or the subject discontinues study participation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2) Change from baseline in (i) World Health Organisation (WHO) functional class, (ii) SF-36 heath survey, (iii) Borg dyspnea index, (iv) B-type natriuretic peptide</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, again at Weeks 4, 12, and 24, and every 6 month thereafter from Week 24 until the end of the study or the subject discontinues study participation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3) Monotherapy treatment status</outcome>
      <timepoint>Events that mark the natural history of disease progression. These events will be assessed when or if they occur for each subject, and the event outcome will be recorded at the time of occurence. The occurrence of these events will be monitored for the duration of subject participation, until the study is ended or the subject discontinues study participation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>4) Failure-free treatment status</outcome>
      <timepoint>Events that mark the natural history of disease progression. These events will be assessed when or if they occur for each subject, and the event outcome will be recorded at the time of occurence. The occurrence of these events will be monitored for the duration of subject participation, until the study is ended or the subject discontinues study participation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>5) Long-term survival. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Events that mark the natural history of disease progression. These events will be assessed when or if they occur for each subject, and the event outcome will be recorded at the time of occurence. The occurrence of these events will be monitored for the duration of subject participation, until the study is ended or the subject discontinues study participation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) Current diagnosis of PAH associated with an acceptable etiology as outlined in the protocol (i.e., idiopathic pulmonary arterial hypertension, familial pulmonary hypertension, PAH associated with interstitial lung disease, PAH due to chronic thromboembolic disease or sickle cell disease, PAH associated with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, and associated PAH secondary to the scleroderma spectrum of disease, systemic lupus, erythematosus, anorexigen use, congenital heart defects, or human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection); 2) Receiving stable, chronic prostanoid treatment or oral phosphodiesterase type 5 (PDE-5) inhibitors for 4 weeks prior to the Screening Visit; 3) Receiving stable calcium channel blocker treatment or 3-hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl-coenzyme A (HMG-CoA) reductase inhibitors for 4 weeks prior to the Screening Visit; 4) Right heart catheterization completed within 1 year prior to the Screening Visit and fulfilling all pre-specified criteria; 5) Pulmonary function tests fulfilling all pre-specified criteria; 6) Aminotransferase concentrations less than 1.5x the Upper Limit of Normal (ULN) at the Screening Visit; 7) Male and female subjects may be eligible for study participation; however, female subjects of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test and must agree to use a reliable double method of contraception until study completion and for at least 4 weeks following their final study visit; 8) Male subjects must be informed of the potential risks of testicular tubular atrophy and infertility associated with taking ambrisentan and queried regarding his understanding of the potential risks as described in the Informed Consent Form.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) Participation in a previous clinical study with ambrisentan;2) Treatment with bosentan or sitaxsentan within four weeks prior to the Screening Visit;3) Contraindication to treatment with endothelin receptor antagonists (ERAs);4) History of malignancies within 5 years prior to the Screening Visit, with the exception of basal cell carcinoma of the skin or in situ carcinoma of the cervix;5) Female subject who is pregnant or breastfeeding.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/12/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Gilead Sciences, Inc.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Gilead Science, Inc.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a long-term, open-label study of a new experimental drug called ambrisentan. The purpose of this study is to evaluate the safety and efficacy of ambrisentan in a broad population of subjects with pulmonary arterial hypertension (PAH). Secondarily, this study will evaluate the effects of ambrisentan on other clinical measures of PAH, long-term treatment success, and survival.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent’s Hospital-St. Vincent's Hospital HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>St. Vincent's Hospital Limited, Victoria Street  Darlinghurst NSW 2010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/11/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Perth Hospital-Royal Perth Hospital EC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Royal Perth Hospital, Wellington Street Perth WA 6000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/09/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kathleen DeHaven</name>
      <address>Gilead Colorado, Inc.
7575 West 103rd Ave.
#102
Westminster CO 80021-5426</address>
      <phone>0011 303-410-6666</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kathleen.dehaven@gilead.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kathleen DeHaven</name>
      <address>Gilead Colorado, Inc.
7575 West 103rd Ave., #102
Westminster CO, 80021-5426</address>
      <phone>0011 303-410-6666</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kathleen.dehaven@gilead.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>