<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371277">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/11/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/12/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001679471p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A cross-sectional study to evaluate the ability to detect retinal amyloid-beta plaques utilizing the EidonTM (RetiaTM) retinal imaging system with and without curcumin labeling in participants with Mild Cognitive Impairment (MCI), and healthy controls


</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Cross-Sectional study to explore the correlation between PET SUVR and amyloid-beta plaques in the retina, identified by fluorescence imaging using the EidonTM (RetiaTM) retinal imaging system with and without curcumin labeling.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NVI0007</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Mild cognitive impairment</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dementias</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Alzheimer's disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>1. Tropicamide (0.5ml at 1%w/v), eye drops will be administered to each eye on Day 0 (visit one) and visit two of the study  (day 3 of dosing). One drop in each eye is administered by the study staff/doctors). Tropicamide is a mydriatic agent that induces dilation of the pupil to facilitate taking images of the retina. 

2. Vitamin E oral supplement equal to 500 IU daily in a tablet form to be taken for 3 days coinciding with the dosing of Longvida., It is administered in this study to improve the bioavailability of curcumin from the Longvida supplement. The empty bottle of Vitamin E or any used tablets will be returned to the study site at the second study visit.

3. Curcumin will be supplied in the form of Longvida (Registered Trademark) a formulation designed to improve uptake of curcumin into the body. Each Longvida packet is 20 grams and contains 4 grams of curcumin. Participants are required to take one packet each day for 3 days.  Longvida curcumin is granular in consistency and not water soluble.  For palatability, participants will be provided with a choice of non-dairy low-lactose shake in which to mix their daily dose of Longvida curcumin.  One option will be a special formulated shake for people with diabetes.  Longvida (Registered Trademark) is considered an investigational or experimental product.  Participants will be advised when to start the Longvida.. For some participants this will be the day after visit 1, for others, it will be at another time point as advised by the study staff to ensure 3 consecutive days of dosing prior to second imaging session.  The empty or any unused packets of Lonvida will need to be returned to the study staff at the second visit.

Imaging of the retinas will be done at the screening visit (Visit 1) and at the Day 3 visit (Visit 2) after Curcumin and Vitamin E dosing. The participants pupils will be dilated with eye drops prior to each imaging session. Photos will then be taken of the participants pupils by a trained operator using the retinal imaging camera RetisTM. </interventions>
    <comparator>The objective of this study is to explore the correlation between amyloid-beta plaques identified by fluorescence in the retina with PET SUVR and/or CSF amyloid-beta 42 testing in participants at risk for Alzheimers dementia previously enrolled in the AIBL Study. The AIBL study participants will be invited into the study. The AIBL study is an observational study and is unregistered. These participants have been classified as
1. "healthy controls" or
2.  having mild cognitive impairment.
The data from this study (retinal images) will be compared with the participants' de-identified PET and CSF data. 

PET-SUVR is gold-standard biomarker for detection of prodromal Alzheimer's Disease (AD). PET will be utilised to stratify participants into prodromal AD and control groups, for group comparison with respect to retinal plaques and also ROC analysis. PET-SUVR will also be utilised as a continuous parameter to compare brain and retinal plaque burden measures. 
CSF (AB42/tau) is an alternative gold-standard biomarker for detection of prodromal AD. CSF will be utilised to stratify participants into prodromal AD and control groups, for group comparison with respect to retinal plaques and also ROC analysis. CSF will also be utilised as a continuous parameter to perform regression analysis between CSF concentrations and retinal plaque burden measures. 
RetiaTM (with curcumin) is being used to identify amyloid-beta plaques in the retina. The retina has endogenous fluorophores which will be present in the day0 RetiaTM imaging (without curcumin). Curcumin dosing will allow curcumin to bind to amyloid-beta plaques, producing increased fluorescence. Comparison between pre-dosing and post-dosing RetiaTM imaging is therefore required to detect increased fluorescence due to curcumin binding. Images taken prior to dosing will be compared to those taken after dosing 
PET imaging and CSF samples have been collected in the AIBL study (an observational study). The time frame of sample collection was between January 2014 to December 2016.</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The objective of this study is to explore the correlation between amyloid-beta (AB) plaques identified by fluorescence in the retina with PET SUVR and/or CSF AB42 testing in participants at risk for Alzheimers dementia previously enrolled in the AIBL Study.

The primary outcome measure will be the retinal images obtained at day 0 (visit 1) and day 3 of dosing (visit 2) (RetiaTM images)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Visit 1 and Visit 2 (day 3 of dosing)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety outcomes will be evaluated by measuring:
a) the incidence of adverse events 
b) the incidence of serious adverse events

Assessment will be based on participant reports, either at the study visits or other contact with the site (eg phone call).

Common side effects (1% to 10% chance of occurring) from taking curcumin include
Diarrhoea
Nausea 
Bloated feeling
Reflux 
Anorexia

Participants may experience slight stinging and reddening of the eyes when the Tropicamide eyedrops are instilled.  These are temporary side effects usually lasting less than 5 minutes.
Other very common side effects  (greater than 10% chance of occurring) from eye drops may include
Intolerance to bright light.
Blurred vision 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Adverse events will be tracked until the final follow up safety phone call (30-35 days after visit 2).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.      Enrolled in the AIBL study with a A Ddiagnosis of MCI, or healthy controls within 36 months as per the AIBL criteria at the screening visit .
2. 	PET amyloid brain scan within 36 months of baseline visit
3.	Participant must be able to provide written informed consent in English.
4. 	Male or Female age 60 years or older at the screening visit 
5. 	In the opinion of the retinal photographer, clear ocular media and pupillary dilation to allow for ocular imaging
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	The participant has advanced retinal disease, advanced cataracts or other advanced ocular conditions that in the opinion of the investigator are likely to affect obtaining clear images of the retina. 
2. 	Participant has had prior ocular surgery within 2 months of planned retinal imaging, or is still taking post-operative ocular medications at first day of retinal imaging.
3. 	Participants with known current gallstone. 
4. 	Participants who have undergone angioplasty in the last 3 months. 
5	Participants who have had major surgery within 4 weeks of trial inclusion or planned surgical procedure during the trial period.
6. 	Significant haemorrhagic event (in past 12 months) or cardiovascular disease ( ie, history of myocardial infarction within past 6 months of trial inclusion, congestive cardiac failure NYHA grade II ). 
7.	Participant with retinitis pigmentosa. 
8. 	Participants with current bile duct obstruction (participants who have undergone a cholecystectomy will be considered eligible).
9. 	Participants with significant uncontrolled gastrointestinal disorders (including stomach ulcers and uncontrolled hyperacidity disorders) which in the opinion of the investigator will be aggravated by the intake of curcumin. 
10. 	Participants with known allergy to Tropicamide eye drops, Vitamin E or turmeric. 
11.	Participation in another clinical trial within 30 days prior to visit one (with the exception of the AIBL trial)	. 
12. 	In the opinion of the investigator, the participants cognitive function is no longer consistent with the AIBL diagnosis.  
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>16/01/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>284</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Australian Alzheimer’s Research Foundation - Nedlands</hospital>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>NeuroVision Imaging LLC</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>NeuroVision Imaging, LLC
1395 Garden Highway
Suite 250
Sacramento, CA 95833
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NeuroVision Imaging, LLC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1395 Garden Highway
Suite 250
Sacramento, CA 95833
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Australian Alzheimer's Research Foundation</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Australian Alzheimer Research Foundation 
Hollywood Hospital Consulting Suites, 
 85 Monash Avenue,
Nedlands, WA, 6009.
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In Alzheimers disease, a peptide called amyloid-beta is elevated and aggregate forms amyloid-beta (senile) plaques/ deposits in the brain and potentially in the retina. Curcumin  (an ingredient of turmeric) may increase the ability to detect the plaques in the retina.

Participants will be recruited from the existing AIBL study. Images will be taken of the participants retina using a camera, Participants will then be asked to take 3 days of Vitamin E supplements and 3 days of Curcumin powder. At visit 2 (after the curcumin dosing), images will be again taken of the participant's retinas. 
A comparison will be made of the participants retinas pre and curcumin post dosing to determine if it is possible to detect the presence of plaques. These results will be compared to the participant's PET scan conducted during the course of the AIBL study. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>129 Glen Osmond Rd, Eastwood SA 5063</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>13/12/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Roger Clarnette</name>
      <address>McCusker Alzheimer Research Foundation 
Unit 2 / 142 Stirling Highway
Nedlands, WA, 6009
</address>
      <phone>+61 8 6304 3966</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 6389 2033</fax>
      <email>Roger.Clarnette@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Shaun Frost</name>
      <address>C/-CSIRO
Private Bag 5
WEMBLEY WA 6913</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9333 6137</phone>
      <fax>not available</fax>
      <email>Shaun.Frost@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Shaun Frost</name>
      <address>C/-CSIRO
Private Bag 5
WEMBLEY WA 6913</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9333 6137</phone>
      <fax>none </fax>
      <email>Shaun.Frost@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Shaun Frost</name>
      <address>C/-CSIRO
Private Bag 5
WEMBLEY WA 6913</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9333 6137</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Shaun.Frost@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>