<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372031">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/01/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/01/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000140358</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A study to compare a two novel ketamine wafer formulations to intravenous ketamine in healthy adult volunteers.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An open label, three-way crossover study to evaluate the absolute bioavailability of two formulations of Wafermine Trademark, a novel sublingual wafer formulation of ketamine, in healthy volunteers under fasted conditions.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will complete three inpatient periods, each period separated by a minimum of 3 days.  Participants will be admitted the afternoon before and will remain inpatient until 24 hours after each study medication dose. Two formulations of Wafermine Trademark sublingual ketamine wafers will be tested, Formulation A and Formulation B.  The wafers contain identical pharmaceutical contents.  The difference between the wafers is the freeze-drying method of manufacture.  During one session, a single dose of Wafermine Trademark (ketamine wafer) Formulation A 25 mg will be administered under the tongue.  During another session, a single dose of Wafermine Trademark (ketamine wafer) Formulation B 25 mg will be administered under the tongue. During another session, Ketalar Registered Trademark (intravenous ketamine) 10 mg will be administered over 5 minutes.  No food or drink except water is allowed for at least 10 hours before the study medication dose.  Water is restricted 1 hour before and after dosing. </interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator is a single intravenous dose of United States Ketalar Registered Trademark 10 mg.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the absolute bioavailability of two formulations of Wafermine Trademark versus intravenous Ketalar Registered Trademark (US).  The bioavailability after sublingual dosing will be estimated by the ratio of dose adjusted Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time zero to infinity and observed maximum plasma concentration. The pharmacokinetic analysis will be based on plasma concentrations of racemic ketamine and norketamine.</outcome>
      <timepoint>A total of 17 blood samples will be collected per participant per occasion (pre-dose and at 5, 10, 20, 30, 40, 50 mins and 1, 1.25, 1.5, 2, 3, 4, 6, 10, 14 and 24 hours post dose).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine safety and tolerability of a single dose of two formulations of Wafermine Trademark (ketamine wafer) administered via sublingual route. The most common adverse effects of ketamine are nausea and dizziness.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Safety and tolerability assessments include:
1. Adverse event probes at 30 minutes, 1, 2, 4, 10 and 24 hours, and in a follow-up phone call 3 days after the last dose of study medication.
2. Vital signs collected pre-dose and at 15 and 30 minutes, then at 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 6, 10 and 24 hours.
3. Continuous oxygen saturation monitoring starting prior to dosing and for the first two hours after dosing (oxygen saturation readings recorded at 30, 60, 90 and 120 minutes).
4. Modified Wilson Sedation Score pre-dose and at 15 and 30 minutes, then at 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 6, 10 and 24 hours;
5. Oral Symptom Questionnaire at pre-dose, 20 minutes, 1 and 24 hours.
6. Sublingual assessments at pre-dose, 20 minutes, 1 and 24 hours. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Good general health without clinically significant renal, hepatic, cardiac or respiratory disease, as determined by the Principal Investigator. 
2.	Have suitable venous access for blood sampling. 
3.	Females must be non-pregnant, non-lactating, and using an acceptable form of birth control.
4.	BMI within the range of 19.0-30.0 kg/m2 (inclusive).
5.	Deemed able to read and understand English in order to communicate with research staff and complete protocol required questionnaires and forms.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Has abnormal, clinically significant laboratory value at the Screening Visit (including positive serology results for Hepatitis B or C or HIV). . 
2.	Any gastrointestinal condition, which could affect drug absorption.
3.	History of clinically significant condition involving the bladder or urinary tract, including frequent urinary tract infections (e.g. greater than 2 per year), or current symptoms of bladder irritation such as frequent or urgent need to urinate or burning with urination.  
4.	History (within the last six months) of or current clinically significant psychiatric disorder including anxiety, psychosis or depression.
5.	Current inflammatory or ulcerative disease of the oral cavity that could impair the absorption of sublingual medication.
6.	History of severe allergic or anaphylactic drug-related reactions.
7.	History of hypersensitivity to ketamine or any of the excipients of Wafermine Trademark.
8.	Intake of any Over-The-Counter (OTC)/non-prescribed drugs including vitamins, minerals, supplements or herbal medicines within 1 week of Period 1 study drug administration, or intake of prescribed drugs within 2 weeks of Period 1 study drug administration.  Use of drugs with enzyme-inducing properties (such as rifampicin and St Johns Wort) within 3 weeks or 5 half-lives, whichever is greater, or any drug known to be a strong inhibitor of CYP3A4 within 5 half-lives of treatment period 1 and throughout the study.
9.	Participation in another clinical trial of an investigational agent within 30 days of study entry.
10.	Clinically significant, as determined by the Investigator, abnormal ECG (12-lead) or vital signs at the screening visit or pre-dose (Day 1). 
11.	Drug (including analgesic drugs or tranquilizers) or alcohol abuse or dependence.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>13/02/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>24/02/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>4/03/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>12</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>12</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>22/03/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>iX Biopharma Ltd.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>24 Augusta Street
Willetton, WA 6155 

</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>iX Biopharma Ltd.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>24 Augusta Street
Willetton, WA 6155 
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil known</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Nil known</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Participants will be admitted to the research clinical for three separate inpatient periods, each period separated by a minimum of 3 days.  Participants will check in the afternoon before planned dosing and will stay inpatient for 24 hours after study medication for each inpatient period.  In one period, a single dose of intravenous ketamine 10 mg will be administered and in the two other periods a single 25 mg ketamine wafer (two different formulations) will be administered under the tongue.  No food or drink except water is allowed starting 10 hours before each study medication dose and for 4 hours after dosing.  Water is restricted 1 hour before and after dosing.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Limited</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>129 Glen Osmond Rd.
Eastwood, SA 5063</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/02/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2017-01-047</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/01/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Stephan A. Schug</name>
      <address>Linear Clinical Research Ltd
1st Floor, B Block, QEII Medical Centre
Hospital Avenue, Nedlands
WA 6009 
</address>
      <phone>+61 (08) 6382 5100</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>enquiries@linear.org.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Simon Scott</name>
      <address>Linear Clinical Research Ltd
1st Floor, B Block, QEII Medical Centre
Hospital Avenue, Nedlands
WA 6009 </address>
      <phone>+61 (08) 6382 5100</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>enquiries@linear.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Janakan Krishnarajah</name>
      <address>iX Biopharma Pty Ltd
24 Augusta Street
Willetton, WA 6155 


</address>
      <phone>+61 412 999 004</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.krishnarajah@ixbiopharma.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Georgia Simmons</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>georgia.simmons@ixbiopharma.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>