<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308392">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/08/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/08/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000734268</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Melbourne Atopy Cohort Study (MACS): A Randomised controlled trial of a partially hydrolysed whey and a soy formula for the prevention of allergic disease.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In children with a family history of allergic disease does consumption of a partially hydrolysed whey or a soy formula at the cessation or partial cessation of breastfeeding, when compared to conventional cows milk formula reduce the incidence of allergic disease</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>MACS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Allergic manifestations
Eczema
Asthma
Allergic rhinitis
Atopy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Allergies</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Arm 1: Partially hydrolysed whey formula (Nan HA) given as required, at the cessation, or partial cessation of breastfeeding, up to 12 months of age.  Administered orally after mixing 4.4g of powdered formula to every 30 ml of warm water.
Arm2: Soy formula (Prosobee) given as required, at the cessation, or partial cessation of breastfeeding, up to 12 months of age.  Administered orally after mixing 4.4g of powdered formula to every 30 ml of warm water</interventions>
    <comparator>Conventional cows' milk formula (NAN) given as required, at the cessation, or partial cessation of breastfeeding, up to 12 months of age.  Administered orally after mixing 4.3g of powdered formula to every 30 ml of warm water</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Allergic manifestations (eczema, food reactions, urticaria) assessed by telephone interview of parent</outcome>
      <timepoint>up to 2 years age.  Telephone interviews were undertaken 18 times during the first two years of life (every 4 weeks until 64 weeks, then at 78 and 104 weeks)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>eczema (assessed by telephone interview of parent)</outcome>
      <timepoint>up to 2 years age.  Telephone interviews were undertaken 18 times during the first two years of life (every 4 weeks until 64 weeks, then at 78 and 104 weeks)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>atopy (positive skin prick test)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6, 12, and 24 months of age</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>eczema assessed by telephone interview of parent</outcome>
      <timepoint>5-7 years of age.  Telephone interviews were conducted when the child was six and then seven years of age, asking if the child had had any episodesof eczema in the previous 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>asthma assessed by telephone interview of parent</outcome>
      <timepoint>5-7 years of age.  Telephone interviews were conducted when the child was six and then seven years of age, asking if the child had had any episodes of asthma in the previous 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>allergic rhinitis assessed by telephone interview of parent</outcome>
      <timepoint>5-7 years of age.  Telephone interviews were conducted when the child was six and then seven years of age, asking if the child had had any episodes of allergic rhinitis in the previous 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Family history of allergic disease (asthma, eczema, allergic rhinitis or severe food allergy)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Nil</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Mother-baby pairs were allocated to the next sequential number on the allocation list as they were enrolled in the study, and were assigned to the formula code allocated to that number.  The tins of formula were labeled at an independent location with a code number.  Neither the study staff or particpants knew which formula was assigned to each tin code number.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using a randomisation table created by a computer program</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/1990</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>8/01/1990</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/11/1994</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>15/07/1994</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>620</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Nestec Ltd,</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Avenue Nestle 55 CH - 180-0 Vevey</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Switzerland</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Nestec Ltd,</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Avenue Nestle 55 CH - 180-0 Vevey</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Switzerland</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Victorian Asthma Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>491-495 King Street, West Melbourne  
Victoria, 3003</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Despite a lack of clear evidence, partially hydrolysed whey formula has been recommended at the cessation of exclusive breast-feeding in infants at high risk of developing allergic disease.  It is thought that partially hydrolysed whey formula may promote oral tolerance and prevent allergic diseases. Similarly, soy formula has previously been recommended for allergy prevention.  The primary aim of this study was to determine if the use of a partially hydrolysed formula, or a soy formula, at the cessation, or partial cessation of breastfeeding, reduced the incidence of allergic manifestations (eczema, urticaria and food reactions), in high-risk infants when compared with a conventional cows milk formula.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>1. Tang MLK, Kemp AS, Thorburn J, Hill DJ. Reduced IFNy secretion in neonates and subsequent atopy. Lancet 1994;344:983-5. 
2. Hill DJ, Hosking CS, Yu Zhie C, Leung R, Baratwidjaja K, Iikura Y, et al. The frequency of food allergy in Australia and Asia. Environ Toxicol and Pharma 1997;4:101-10. 
3. Hill DJ, Sporik RS, Thorburn J, Hosking CS. The Association of Atopic Dermatitis in Infancy with Immunoglobulin E Food Sensitization. J Pediatr 2000;137:475-9. 
4. Stoney RM, Woods RK, Hosking CS, Hill DJ, Abramson MJ, Thien FC. Maternal breast milk long-chain n-3 fatty acids are associated with increased risk of atopy in breastfed infants. Clin Exp Allergy 2004;34:194-200. 
5. Hill DJ, Hosking CS. Food Allergy and Atopic Dermatitis in Infancy: an epidemiological study. Pediatr Allergy Immunol 2004;15:421-7. 
6. Lowe AJ, Carlin JB, Bennett CM, Abramson MJ, Hosking CS, Hill DJ, et al. Atopic disease and breastfeeding - cause or consequence? J Allergy Clin Immunol 2006;117:682-7. 
7. Lowe AJ, Abramson MJ, Hosking CS, Carlin JB, Bennett CM, Dharmage SC, Hill DJ. The temporal sequence of allergic sensitization and onset of infantile eczema. Clin Exp Allergy 2007;37:536-42. 
8. A.J. Lowe, C.S. Hosking, C.M. Bennett, J.B. Carlin, M.J. Abramson, D.J. Hill, S.C. Dharmage Skin prick test can identify eczematous infants at risk of asthma and allergic rhinitis. 2007 Clin Exp Allergy 
9. Hosking CS, Hill DJ, Thorburn J. Dharmage S. Does infection enhance or suppress the development of the atopic status? - a study of rhinitis in atopy-prone infants. Pediatric Asthma Allergy and Immunology 2007; 20(4): 223-228 
10. Koplin J, Dharmage SC, Gurrin L, Osborne N, Tang ML, Lowe AJ, Hosking C, Hill D, Allen KJ. Soy consumption is not a risk factor for peanut sensitization. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2008; 121:1455-9. 
11. Lowe AJ, Carlin JB, Bennett CM, Hosking CS, Abramson MJ, Hill DJ, Dharmage SC. Do boys do the atopic march while girls dawdle? J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2008;121: 1190-5. 
12. Lowe AJ, Thien FCK, Stoney RM, Bennett CM, Hosking CS, Hill DJ, Carlin JB, Abramson MJ, Dharmage SC. Associations between fatty-acids in colostrum and breast-milk and risk of allergic disease. Clinical and Experimental Allergy. 2008; 38:1745-1751.
13.	Lodge CJ, Lowe AJ, Gurrin LC, Matheson MC, Balloch A, Axelrad C, et al. Pets at birth do not increase allergic disease in at-risk children. Clin Exp Allergy 2012; 42:1377-85.
14.	Lowe AJ, Hosking CS, Bennett CM, Allen KJ, Axelrad C, Carlin JB, et al. Effect of a partially hydrolyzed whey infant formula at weaning on risk of allergic disease in high-risk children: A randomized controlled trial. J Allergy Clin Immunol 2011; 128:360-5.
15.	Lodge CJ, Lowe AJ, Gurrin LC, Hill DJ, Hosking CS, Khalafzai RU, et al. House dust mite sensitization in toddlers predicts current wheeze at age 12 years. J Allergy Clin Immunol 2011; 128:782-8 e9.
16.	Seach KA, Dharmage SC, Lowe AJ, Dixon JB. Delayed introduction of solid feeding reduces child overweight and obesity at 10 years. Int J Obes (Lond) 2010; 34:1475-9.
17.	Lowe AJ, Carlin JB, Bennett CM, Hosking CS, Allen KJ, Robertson CF, et al. Paracetamol use in early life and asthma: prospective birth cohort study. BMJ 2010; 341:c4616.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Mercy Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Mercy Hospital for Women 163 Studley Road HEIDELBERG VIC 3084</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/01/1989</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr David Hill</name>
      <address>Senior Consultant Allergist
Murdoch Children's Research Institute
The Royal Childrens Hospital
Flemington Road Parkville Victoria 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 0878</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>davidjlhill@bigpond.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr David Hill</name>
      <address>Senior Consultant Allergist
Murdoch Children's Research Institute
The Royal Childrens Hospital
Flemington Road Parkville Victoria 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 0878</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>davidjlhill@bigpond.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Adrian Lowe</name>
      <address>NHMRC Research Fellow
Respiratory Diseases, Infection, Immunity &amp; Envrionment 
Murdoch Childrens Research Institute
The Royal Childrens Hospital
Flemington Road Parkville Victoria 3052</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>lowea@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Shyamali Dharmage</name>
      <address>Centre for Epidemiology and Biostatistics
Melbourne School of Population and Global Health
L3, 207 Bouverie Street
University of Melbourne VIC 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 83440737 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.dharmage@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>