<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362931">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/09/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/09/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001015831</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effects of acupuncture and instruction on post-exercise recovery in healthy adults</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effects of acupuncture and instruction on cardiovascular recovery from maximal exercise in healthy adults: An investigation using the balanced placebo design</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1133-7700</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cardiovascular recovery from exercise</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the cardiovascular system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will attend a single 2hr session before which they will be required to abstain from alcohol and moderate-to-intense exercise for 24hrs and cigarettes and caffeine for 4hrs. 

Upon screening participants will have their height and weight taken for further analysis including calculating Body mass index (BMI). Participants will be instructed to lie in a supine position on a plinth for 15 min, prior to the performing of the exercise protocol, to evaluate resting metabolic parameters, and to establish a standardised baseline condition.  

Following 15 min of supine rest, participants will perform a graded exercise test to volitional fatigue on an electronically braked cycle ergometer (Velotron, Racermate, Boulder, CO, USA) using a ramped protocol to be consistent with previous similar research. The cycle ergometer is initially set to 0 Watts (W), with increments thereafter set at 15 W/min. The participant will also be required to maintain their pedal rate at 60 revolutions per min (RPM). The exercise test will be terminated if : (1) The participant can  no longer maintain a minimum cadence of 60 revolutions per min (RPM) or if the subject requests to terminate the testing. Upon completion of exercise, the participant will be told which treatment they have been allocated to receive (real acupuncture, placebo acupuncture or control).

An experienced acupuncturist trained in Traditional Chinese Medicine delivered the traditional acupuncture treatment.  The primary acupuncture points included PC6, ST36, LU7, and REN17. PC6 is located on the anterior aspect of the forearm, between the tendons of the palmaris longus and the flexor carpi radialis, 2 cun proximal to the palmar wrist crease. ST36 is on the anterior aspect of the leg, on the line connecting. LU7 is on the radial aspect of the forearm, between the tendons of the abductor pollicis longus and the extensor pollicis brevis muscle, in the groove for the abductor pollicis longus tendon, 1.5B-cun superior to the palmar wrist crease. REN17 is located on the anterior thoracic region, at the same level as the fourth intercostal space, on the anterior median line.   PC6 and ST6 both appear to have consistent regulatory effects on cardiovascular function.  LU7 is a classic point for promoting lung function. REN17 is indicated for regulating Qi in the chest and treating breathlessness. PC6, ST36, and LU7 have been used in previous research showing effects of acupuncture on exercise recovery and exercise capacity. Single-use disposable stainless steel needles (0.25 x 40mm for body acupuncture) were used. Acupuncture needles were inserted to tissue level and stimulated manually (3x180  rotations of approximately 3Hz) when the participant assumed the supine recovery position. The needles were stimulated after 10 min of needle retention and upon removal at 20 min of total needle retention, the participant will then rest for a further 40 mins (resting for a total of 60mins).  

While the participant may be told they are recieveing real acupuncture expectancy is being controlled by being randomised into;
1.Acupuncture with high expectancy (AH). Participants randomised to this group received traditional acupuncture treatment and were informed that they were receiving traditional acupuncture treatment. 
2.Acupuncture with low expectancy (AL). Participants randomised to this group received traditional acupuncture treatment but were informed that they were receiving placebo acupuncture.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo acupuncture was delivered using the Park device.  The placebo needle itself is able to slide into the handle, which increases the appearance that the skin is being penetrated, although there is no actual penetration. The placebo needle is placed 1-2cm away from acupuncture points used in the acupuncture method. The protocol in terms of frequency and intensity of needle stimulation and resting time is identical to that of the real acupuncture protocol. 

While the participant may be told they are recieveing placebo acupuncture expectancy is being controlled by being randomised into
3.Placebo acupuncture with high expectancy (PH). Participants randomised to this group received placebo acupuncture and were informed that they were receiving placebo acupuncture.
4.Placebo acupuncture with low expectancy (PL). Participants randomised to this group received placebo acupuncture but were informed that they were receiving traditional acupuncture treatment. 
5.Control (i.e. no treatment) (C). Participants allocated to this condition received no treatment and were informed that they were receiving no treatment.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Heart rate will be measures via telemetry (Polar XL, Stamford, CT).</outcome>
      <timepoint>- Every 5 Mins pre-exercise for 15 minutes
- Every 3 minutes during exercise until volitional fatigue
- At fatigue
- Every 5 minutes post-exercise for 60 minutes</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure will measured via auscultation and recorded as two components; systolic blood pressure and diastolic blood pressure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>- Every 5 Mins pre-exercise for 15 minutes
- Every 3 minutes during exercise until volitional fatigue
- At fatigue
- Every 5 minutes post-exercise for 60 minutes</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Oxygen consumption data, including, respiratory exchange ratio (RER), volume of oxygen consumed per minute (VO2), volume of carbon dioxide (VCO2) expired per minute, and respiratory exchange ratio (RER), will be monitored continuously using a Masterscreen CPX metabolic cart (Jaeger, Wurzburg, Germany) using breath-by-breath analysis protocol with the sampling frequency set at 15 seconds. Before each test O2 and CO2 sensors were calibrated using high-grade calibration gas with certified gas concentrations (O2 = 16%, CO2 = 5% and N2 = balance). Ventilation volume was measured using a Triple V digital flow meter and calibrated using a 3L calibration syringe (Hans Rudolph, Kansas, MO, USA).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured continuously throughout the session including; pre-exercise resting period, during exercise and post-exercise resting period at 15 second intervals</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood lactate</outcome>
      <timepoint>- 10 minutes into 15 minutes of the pre-exercise resting period 
- 5 minutes post exercise
- 10 minute intervals thereafter for 60 minutes</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rating of perceived exertion (RPE) according to Borg's scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>- Every 3 minutes during exercise</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Aged between 18-30 years old
- Engage in exercise a minimum of 3 times per week (30 minute sessions) at a moderate to high intensity</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>30</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Previous use of acupuncture as those who have had acupuncture could not be adequately blinded
- A phobia of needles
- Taking medication other than the contraceptive pill as this may affect the response to the acupuncture
- Any acute or chronic medical condition(s) that would make participation in the experimental conditions potentially hazardous or outcomes measures impossible to assess.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>1. Participants were recruited by means of convenience sampling via advertisements posted on notice boards throughout UWS Campbelltown Campus and on the UWS website. 
2. The principal investigator met with potentially eligible participants prior to performance of the experimental protocol.  Individuals were pre-screened for eligibility using a standardised checklist.  If eligible, the individual was presented with a detailed Participant Information Sheet, which detailed the study procedure and potential risks.  The principal investigator responded to all queries related to participation prior to the solicitation of written informed consent. The participant was then pre-screened for exercise participation using a standardised pre-exercise screening questionnaire.  General demographic data were also collected at this time.
3. The treatment allocated to each participant is concealed in a sealed envelop which are numbered from 1 to 75.
4. The participant is then allocated to their corresponding numbered envelop (e.g. the first participant will recieve envelop number 1) at the commencement of the rest/treatment period. The participant is told which treatment (real, placebo or no treatment) they will be recieving.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation was done via a computer randomisation program.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Factorial</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This study employed a 2 x 2 between-subjects balanced placebo design with an additional no-treatment control group</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>21/12/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>75</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr. Birinder SinghD Cheema</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Biomeducal and Health Sciences
University of Western Sydney
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith NSW 2751</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Western Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of Western Sydney
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith NSW 2751</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr. Ben Colagiuri</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Psychology (A18)
University of Sydney
Sydney NSW 2006</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr. Caroline A. Smith</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Centre for Complementary Medicine Research
University of Western Sydney
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith NSW 2751</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The objective of the study is to determine if acupuncture is effective for improving recovery from maximal exercise, and whether instruction about the treatment influences the treatment effect. The current study employs a balanced placebo design consisting of a 2x2 factorial design with treatment allocation and expected allocation as factors. A total of 75 participants are expected to be recruited from the University of Western Sydney, Campbelltown and the general public.  Participants are allocated to one of five groups; acupuncture with high expectancy, acupuncture with low expectancy, placebo with high expectancy, placebo with low expectancy, and a control no treatment group. All participants will attended a single testing session consisting of 15 minutes of supine rest (baseline), a maximal exercise test to volitional fatigue, and one hour of supine recovery with or without the treatment allocated.  Oxygen consumption, heart rate, blood pressure, blood lactate, respiratory exchange ratio, and respiratory rate will be monitored throughout the session.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Urroz. P, Colagiuri. B, Smith. C. A &amp; Cheema. B. S. (2012) The effect of acute acupuncture treatment on exercise performance and postexercise recovery: A systematic review. Journal of alternative and complementary medicine. In press.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>UWS Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Research Services
University of Western Sydney
Kingswood Campus, Building K
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith NSW 2751</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/08/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H8366</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/04/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Bobby Cheema</name>
      <address>School of Science and Health 
University of Western Sydney
Locked Bag 1797, Penrith South DC, NSW 2751</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4620 3795</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4620 3792</fax>
      <email>B.Cheema@uws.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Bobby Cheema</name>
      <address>School of Science and Health 
University of Western Sydney
Locked Bag 1797, Penrith South DC, NSW 2751</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4620 3795</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4620 3792</fax>
      <email>B.Cheema@uws.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Paola Urroz</name>
      <address>8 Mullenderree st,
Prestons, NSW, 2170</address>
      <phone>+61 4 2448 3558</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>16513251@student.uws.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>