<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335815">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/08/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/08/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000657022</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Accumulative Benefit of Light Exercise breaks for reducing diabetes risk</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The cumulative effects of repeated bouts of prolonged sitting with and without intermittent short-term physical activity on postprandial glucose and lipid metabolism, in overweight middle-aged adults.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ABLE (Accumulative Benefit of Light Exercise) breaks study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 diabetes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Overweight and obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This randomised crossover trial involves three consecutive days (total duration=21 hours) of prolonged sitting with intermittent light-intensity activity breaks. Participants will remain seated for the initial 80mins (steady-state) period, after which they will complete a 2 min bout of light-intensity walking activity on a treadmill (level, firm surface, slow pace - 3.2km/hr). Participants will then return to the seated position. The light-intensity walking breaks will be repeated on another 16 occasions every 20 mins during a 7 hour period (total walking time=34mins).
There is a 7 day 'wash-out' period between the intervention and comparator condition.</interventions>
    <comparator>Three consecutive days of prolonged sitting without activity breaks: Participants will sit quietly in a comfortable chair for three 7 hour periods.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome 1: Postprandial plasma glucose levels (mean area under the curve [AUC]). Plasma glucose concentrations will be assessed using standard testing equipment at an outsourced medical laboratory.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: Blood glucose levels will be measured every hour for determination of the mean area under the curve (AUC) for each experimental condition. The mean AUC will be determined at day 1 &amp; day 3. Change in mean AUC will be determined by subtracting mean AUC day 1 from mean AUC day 3.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome 2: Postprandial plasma insulin levels (mean area under the curve [AUC]). Plasma insulin concentrations will be assessed using standard testing equipment at an outsourced medical laboratory.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: Blood insulin levels will be measured every hour for determination of the mean area under the curve (AUC) for each experimental condition. The mean AUC will be determined at day 1 &amp; day 3. Change in mean AUC will be determined by subtracting mean AUC day 1 from mean AUC day 3.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome 3: Postprandial serum triglycerides levels (mean area under the curve [AUC]). Plasma triglyceride concentrations will be assessed using standard testing equipment at an outsourced medical laboratory.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: Serum triglycerides levels will be measured every hour for determination of the mean area under the curve (AUC) for each experimental condition. The mean AUC will be determined at day 1 &amp; day 3. Change in mean AUC will be determined by subtracting mean AUC day 1 from mean AUC day 3.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postprandial plasma free fatty acid levels (mean area under the curve [AUC]). Plasma free fatty acid concentrations will be assessed using standard testing equipment at a medical laboratory.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Plasma free fatty levels will be measured every hour for determination of the mean area under the curve (AUC) for each experimental condition. The mean AUC will be determined at day 1 &amp; day 3. Change in mean AUC will be determined by subtracting mean AUC day 1 from mean AUC day 3.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria includes: overweight or obesity (body mass index (BMI) greater than or equal to 25 kg/m2 but less than or equal to 45 kg/m2).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>45</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion is based on: pregnancy; employment in a non-sedentary occupation (&lt; 5 hours total sitting during the typical workday); currently watching &lt; 2 hours of total screen (including television, computer or electronic games) time per day; use of carbohydrate or lipid-lowering medication; greater than or equal to 5 previous vasovagal syncope episodes or epilepsy; known physical activity contraindications; major illness/injury (acute or chronic), smokers; or physical or medical problems that may limit the ability to perform the necessary light-intensity walking, and the use of aspirin or other anticoagulants.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Interested volunteers will receive written information about the study in lay terms and a full description of the inclusion/exclusion criteria. After obtaining informed consent and background information, the potential participants will be screened to confirm eligibility. Once a potential subject has been deemed eligible, the subject will be randomised to the order of experimental conditions. The method for allocation concealment is closed envelopes. The allocation information will be placed in numbered envelopes (1 allocation per envelope) by an independent researcher. After a subject has been enrolled in the study, the study co-ordinators will contact an independent staff member to ask for the sequence of experimental conditions. The independent staff member will keep a log of the date and time the envelope was opened, the envelope number, the initials and gender of the participant and the order of experimental conditions. The study co-ordinator will also keep a record of this information.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation allocation sequence will be generated using computer –generated random numbers in a Latin-square experimental design.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>19/08/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>8/11/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>7/06/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>24</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>24</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Baker IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>75 Commercial Road, Melbourne, Victoria 3004 (Postal address: PO Box 6492, St Kilda Road Central, Victoria 8008)</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 5, 20 Allara Street, Canberra ACT 2601 (Postal address: GPO Box 1421 Canberra ACT 2601)</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There is emerging evidence that people who break up their sitting time with activity breaks (such as light walking) may have better blood glucose and blood fat levels than people who sit for prolonged periods without activity breaks. This study aims to test the cumulative effects of three consecutive seven hour days of prolonged sitting on blood glucose and blood fat levels with and without intermittent breaks of light-intensity activity.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Larsen, Robyn N., Kingwell, Bronwyn A., Robinson, Carol, Hammond, Louise, Cerin, Ester, Shaw, Jonathan E., Healy, Genevieve N., Hamilton, Marc T., Owen, Neville and Dunstan, David W. 2015, Breaking up of prolonged sitting over three days sustains, but does not enhance, lowering of postprandial plasma glucose and insulin in overweight and obese adults, Clinical science, vol. 129, no. 2, pp. 117-127.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Alfred Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ground Floor, Linay Pavilion, The Alfred Hospital, 55 Commercial Road, Melbourne, Victoria 3004</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/08/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>22/07/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David Dunstan</name>
      <address>Baker IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute, Level 4, 99 Commercial Road, Melbourne, Victoria, 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8532 1873</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 8532 1100</fax>
      <email>David.Dunstan@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David Dunstan</name>
      <address>Baker IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute, Level 4, 99 Commercial Road, Melbourne, Victoria, 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8532 1873</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 8532 1100</fax>
      <email>David.Dunstan@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Robyn Larsen</name>
      <address>Baker IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute, Level 4, 99 Commercial Road, Melbourne, Victoria, 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8532 1872</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 8532 1100</fax>
      <email>robyn.larsen@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David Dunstan</name>
      <address>Baker IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute
Level 4, 99 Commercial Rd
Melbourne VIC 3004
</address>
      <phone>+613 8532 1873</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>david.dunstan@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>