<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336113">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/10/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/10/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000903088</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparison of Static Stretching techniques and Hold- Relax on flexibility, mobility, balance and cadence healthy elderly.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>To evaluate the effect of a stretching program for four weeks, with the techniques of Static Stretching  and Hold- Relax on the range of motion, mobility, balance and cadence of healthy elderly.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1117-4301</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Retraction of the hamstrings</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Balance</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Mobility</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cadence</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal musculoskeletal and cartilage development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Twenty-nine healthy sedentary elderly completed the study protocol: Control Group (GC) (64 + / - 5 years, n = 8) performed the tests and participated in lectures and cultural and recreational activities, (n 66 + / - 8 years, n = 10), Static Stretching  Group (SSG) and Hold- Relax Group (HRG) (69 + / - 5 years, n = 11) were tested and stretching exercises and performed by a physical educator. The elderly woman was positioned lying supine with the spine aligned horizontally and one set of legs lying on the extension of the body, with 0o of hip flexion by a band of tissue, 2) to the Static Stretching (SS) the other leg held a flexion hip and knee extension, the ceiling for each participant until a restriction point but not in pain, then, the physical educator passively maintain the position from the point mentioned, during 60 seconds.
In the Proprioceptive Neuromuscular Facilitation (PNF) technique was used to hold-relax (HR). This technique is similar to the Contract-Relax technique (CR), except that the antagonistic muscle pattern resists enough to cause an isotonic contraction and not, as in Contract- Relax (CR). In HRG, the participant was supine and the therapist positioned the leg to be stretched in flexion, adduction and external rotation of the hip, extended knee, dorsiflexion with inversion of the foot to reach the restriction point. Once reached the restriction point, the senior was asked to perform an isometric contraction matching in the sense of extension, abduction and internal rotation of the thigh, knee extended, plantar flexion with eversion for 10 s.
Immediately after, we asked the research subjects, the relaxation of the limb, followed by 20 s of passive stretching in the direction of flexion, adduction and external rotation of thigh, knee extended, dorsiflexion with foot inversion. And from this new range of motion possible, repeat the procedure a total of 60 S. The interventions were performed for 60 seconds in both lower limbs, once a day, twice a week for four consecutive weeks.
 	Both HRG and SSG performed ten minutes of warm-up before stretching exercises.The following tests were performed before and after the program of stretching exercises: photogrammetry to assess range of motion of the hamstring muscles, Berg Balance Scale (BBS) to assess balance, Timed up and go for mobility and step counts per minute to assess the cadence.</interventions>
    <comparator>Twenty-nine elderly healthy sedentary completed the study protocol: GC (64 +/-5 years, n = 8) performed the tests and participated in lectures and recreational and cultural activity, SSG (66 +/-8 years, n = 10) underwent testing and static stretching exercises and HRG (69 +/- 5 years, n = 11) performed the tests and hold-relax stretching exercises, both SSG and HRG performed warm-up ten minutes prior to stretching exercises.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Flexibility was measured using photogrammetry, which assessed the range of motion of the hamstrings.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The variable flexibility was measured before and after four weeks of training with static stretching exercises and hold-relax.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mobility was assessed using the Timed up and go.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The mobility was assessed before and after four weeks of training with static stretching exercises and hold-relax.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Balance was assessed by the Berg Balance Scale (BBS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>The balance was evaluated before and after four weeks of training with static stretching exercises and hold-relax.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cadence was assessed by count the number of steps per minute.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cadence was evaluated before and after four weeks of training with static stretching exercises and hold-relax.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Included were women aged 57 to 80 years and in stable health conditions, with the physical ability to perform the exercises and had not performed regular exercise in the last eight weeks.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>57</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria were: secondary joint damage, heart disease, cancer, neurological disorders, prosthetic use, systolic blood pressure above 200mmHg and diastolic blood pressure above 110 mmHg, regular exercise participation over the last eight weeks, anti-indication for exercise, severe functional limitations or cognitive dysfunction.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>This study is experimental, with random assignment and control groups. The subjects were selected by random assignment. He was given a number to each individual sample. The numbers were placed in numbered containers.</concealment>
    <sequence>The subjects were selected by random assignment. He was given a number to each individual sample. The numbers were placed in numbered containers. Three groups were formed, the control group (CG), static stretching (SSG) and hold-relax stretching (HRG). From the table of random numbers, the first number found from 00 to 37 (effectively started the study 38 women), went to SSG, the second for the HRG and the third for the GC and so on, until you find all numbers from 00 to 37. Where n = 13 for the SSG, n = 13 for  HRG and n = 12 for the GC. Even with these exclusions, 29 elderly completed the study. Groups were divided as follows: SSG, n = 10, HRG, n = 11 and CG, n = 8.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>26/04/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Universidade Federal do Parana- UFPR</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>R, Jaguariaiva, 512 Matinhos, Parana Brasil 83260-000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Brazil</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Universidade Federal do Parana (UFPR)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>R. Jaguariaiva, 512 Matinhos, Parana Brasil 83260-000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Brazil</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Universidade Paranaense  UNIPAR</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Mascarenhas de Moraes, 4282 Zona III Umuarama -Parana Brasil 87502-210</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Brazil</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Universidade Paranaense  UNIPAR</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Mascarenhas de Moraes, 4282 Zona III Umuarama -Parana Brasil 87502-210</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Brazil</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To evaluate the effect of static stretching techniques (SS) and hold-relax (HR) on the range of motion (ROM), balance, mobility, and cadence of healthy elderly. Methods: We selected 29 women aged 68 +/- 11 years. The participants were divided randomly into three groups: control group (CG) (n = 8), group SS (SSG) (n = 10) and group HR (HRG) (n = 11). CG performed the tests and attended lectures. The SSG conducted a session of 60 seconds of SS passive and HRG, a 60-second session of stretching HR. Stretching exercises were performed in the hamstring muscles of both legs, after 10 min of warm-up, twice a week for four consecutive weeks. Evaluations were performed before and after intervention of ROM through photogrammetry, balance, through the Berg Balance Scale (BBS), the mobility using the Timed up and go and cadence by count the steps per minute. Results: An increase in ROM for SSG and increase in HRG and scores of BBS Timed up and go and cadence only to the HRG. Conclusion: The techniques of stretching SS and HR promoted increased ROM of the hamstrings and HR technique was more effective than SS in improving balance, mobility, and cadence of elderly.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Part of this study was presented at the XIII Conference Trans Learning (2010).</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee of the University of Parana-UNIPAR</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Universidade Paranaense  UNIPAR

 Mascarenhas de Moraes, 4282 Zona III 
Umuarama -Parana Brasil 87502-210</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/04/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CAAE: 0008.0.375.000-10</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Brazil</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Anna Raquel Silveira Gomes</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health | AUSTRALIA
Level 7, 341 George St | Sydney NSW 2000 Australia</address>
      <phone>T +61 2 9657 0397</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>annaraquelsg@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Claudinara Botton Dal Paz</name>
      <address>Av Correa Lima, 666, Centro. Vicente Dutra - RS CEP 98450.000</address>
      <phone>(55) 3737 1155 (55) 9658 7769</phone>
      <fax>5537371073</fax>
      <email>narabotton@yahoo.com.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Clynton Lourenco Correa</name>
      <address>Rua Jaguariaiva, 512 
Caioba - Matinhos
PR /Brasil
83260-000</address>
      <phone>55 41- 3511-8323</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cyntoncorrea@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>