<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366953">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/08/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/08/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000928617</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Role of Imdur in Cortisol-Induced Hypertension in Humans</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect oral isosorbide mononitrate on blood pressure in healthy human subjects treated with oral hydrocortisone.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1160-7918 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hypertension</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Hypertension</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Healthy human subjects will be treated with oral hydrocortisone 200mg per day for 5 days. Blood pressure and metabolic parameters will be measured regularly. On the last day of hydrocortisone treatment, a single dose of oral isosorbide mononitrate will be given and the effect of this dose on blood pressure will be measured.Hydrocortisone will be administered at a dose of 50mg four times per day to provide a total daily dose of 200mg hydrocortisone per day.  Isosorbide mononitrate will be administered as a single oral dose of 60mg. It will be administered on the morning to the 5th hydrocortisone treatment day prior to the 17th dose of oral hydrocortisone (out of a total of 20 doses of hydrocortisone administered over the whole treatment phase).
Oral hydrocortisone administration at a dose of 200mg per day is expected to result in a number of metabolic changes including weight gain, elevation of white cell count, plasma glucose and cortisol concentrations, and reductions in plasma potassium and haematocrit.  Compliance with therapy will be assessed by a pill count on each attendance at the clinical study centre, Additionally at the beginning and end of each treatment phase measurement of body weight, plasma electrolytes, glucose and cortisol concentrations and measurement of haematocrit and white cell count will be undertaken,
There will be a minimum two week wash out period between each treatment phase.
</interventions>
    <comparator>The study is a double blind placebo control cross-over design.  The comparator is a single dose of placebo given on the last day of oral hydrocortisone treatment. In the control phase of the study subjects will receive hydrocortisone at a dose of 50mg four times per day to provide a total daily dose of 200mg hydrocortisone per day.  Placebo will be administered as a single oral dose. It will be administered on the morning to the 5th hydrocortisone treatment day prior to the 17th dose of oral hydrocortisone (out of a total of 20 doses of hydrocortisone administered over the whole treatment phase). The placebo will be a methyl-cellulose tablet.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome is the change in blood pressure on the last day of hydrocortisone treatment after isosorbide mononitrate (or placebo) is co-administered. Blood pressure is measured by standard cuff measurement, and ambulatory blood pressure monitoring.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The primary timepoint is the fifth day of hydrocortisone treatment with ambulatory monitoring extending for a further 24 hours after the oral isosorbide mononitrate or placebo is co-administered on day five of oral hydrocortisone treatment,</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Central pressure measurements will be assessed non-invasively by applanation tonometery of the radial artery.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day five or oral hydrocortisone treatment after co-administration of isosorbide mononitrate or placebo</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma nitrate / nitrite activity</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured on blood samples taken prior to the administration of oral hydrocortisone and the last day of treatment and two days after treatment is completed</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy male volunteers on no regular medications</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Prior history of high blood pressure or diabetes.
History of allergy to oral compounds in the study protocol.
Any comorbid medical conditions that may be exacerbated by oral hydrocortisone e,g gastro-oesophageal reflux, anxienty, sleep disorder, mood disorder.
Requirment for any regular medication.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All subjects undergo a standardised screening medical questionnaire and physical examination.  If there are no contraindications detected to enrolment, the study protocol is explained to the subjects and written informed consent is obtained. A study number which corresponds to the study code held in the dispensing hospital pharmacy is allocated.</concealment>
    <sequence>The key aspect of randomisation is the co-administration of isosorbide mononitrate or placebo on the last day of oral hydrocortisone therapy.  The allocation to co-administration of these compounds is done by the hospital pharmacy using a random number assignment from a random number table. In the second phase of the study the subjects are crossed to the alternate intervention.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The study is a two phase double-blind placebo controlled cross-over study. Each treatment phase lasts for a total of eight days including a day of pre-treatment observation 5 days of oral hydrocortisone, 24 hours on BP monitoring after co-administration of isosorbide or placebo and two post-treatment assessment days.  Each treatment phase is separated by a minimum of a two week wash-out period.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Data analysed using the Systat statistical programme (SYSTAT Version 10, SPSS Inc, 2000) as previously reported. Distribution of data was assessed using the Lilliefors test, and reported as the mean +/- SEM or median, interquartile range. Changes in parameters where more than two measurements were taken tested by repeated-measures analysis of variance (ANOVA). If ANOVA positive, further comparison between groups conducted with t-tests or Wilcoxon techniques as dictated by the distribution of data. Paired data were compared using a paired Students t-test if parametric or Wilcoxon sign rank test if non-parametric. Results were corrected for the effects of multiple comparisons using the Hochberg technique. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>13/06/2007</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2009</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>30/06/2008</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>8</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr John Kelly</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Renal Medicine
St George Hospital Clinical School
University of New South Wales
50 Montgomery Street
Kogarah. Sydney. NSW. 2217</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>John Curtin School of Medical Research, Australian National University, with funding for infrastructure and salary support primary derived from JCSMR.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The John Curtin School of Medical Research
 The Australian National University
 GPO Box 334
 Canberra City ACT 2600</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Medicine, St George Hospital Clinical School, University of New South Wales.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1 Belgrave Street, Kogarah, Sydney, NSW. 2217.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Judith Whitworth</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>The John Curtin School of Medical Research
 The Australian National University
 GPO Box 334
 Canberra City ACT 2600</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of the study is to investigate possible mechanisms by which glucocorticoids raise blood pressure.  The hypothesis is that glucocorticoids raise blood pressure by suppression of nitric oxide activity. The study tests this hypothesis by examining whether oral administration of isosorbide mononitrate, which is a nitric oxide donor, changes blood pressure in patients whose blood pressure has gone up after 5 days of treatment with oral hydrocortisone.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>In preparation</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of New South Wales Human Ethics Commitee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of New South Wales Human Research Ethics Committee
UNSW
High Street
Kensington
NSW 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/03/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>070503</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>John Kelly</name>
      <address>Department of Renal Medicine
St George Hospital
50 Montgomery Street.
Kogarah, Sydney.
NSW. 2217</address>
      <phone>61 2 9350 2622</phone>
      <fax>61 2 9531 0699</fax>
      <email>john.kelly@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>John Kelly</name>
      <address>Department of Renal Medicine
St George Hospital
50 Montgomery Street.
Kogarah, Sydney.
NSW. 2217</address>
      <phone>61 2 9350 2622</phone>
      <fax>61 2 9531 0699</fax>
      <email>john.kelly@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>John Kelly</name>
      <address>Department of Renal Medicine
St George Hospital
50 Montgomery Street.
Kogarah, Sydney.
NSW. 2217</address>
      <phone>61 2 9350 2622</phone>
      <fax>61 2 9531 0699</fax>
      <email>john.kelly@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>John Kelly</name>
      <address>Department of Renal Medicine
St George Hospital
50 Montgomery Street.
Kogarah, Sydney.
NSW. 2217</address>
      <phone>61 2 9350 2622</phone>
      <fax>61 2 9531 0699</fax>
      <email>john.kelly@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>