<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363749">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/02/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/02/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000231741</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Effects of
Normoxic and Hyperoxic Cardiopulmonary Bypass on Oxidative Stress in
Cyanotic Pediatric Patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Effects of
Normoxic and Hyperoxic Cardiopulmonary Bypass on Oxidative Stress in
Cyanotic Pediatric Patients:A Randomized Controlled Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Normoxic ,
Hyperoxic,
Cyanotic Pediatric Patients </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Thirty pediatric patients scheduled to undergo elective repair of cyanotic congenital heart diseases. Patients room air saturation is lower than %85.  Patients ages differed from 6 months to 5 years (average 24, 22+/-17, 42 months). All patients were in stable condition. The study was approved by the Research Ethics Committee of institution. Patients with genetic syndromes, preoperative inotropic support and reoperative procedures were excluded from the study. The patients who were taken into the study were divided into two groups as controlled normoxic (n=15) (pO2:80-150 mmHg) (Group I), and hyperoxic (n=15) (pO2: 150-250 mmHg) (Group II). All operations were performed under CPB. The same anesthesia technique was used in both groups. CPB was initiated using standard Aortabicaval cannulation. Isothermic blood cardioplegia was administrated every 20 minutes during aortic cross clamping. Equal perfusion pressure was applied in operations. After anesthesia induction, FiO2 rate was applied as 21% in Group I, and it was applied as 50% in Group II. Arterial blood gas was seen every 15 min. intervals after CPB started. In Group I, PO2 rate in arterial blood gas was about 80-150 mmHg; and in Group II, it was about 150-250 mmHg. After the patients were taken into intensive care, ventilator settings were calibrated as Fi02 21% in Group I, and Fi02 50% in Group II; and routine intensive care protocols were applied. Patients MDA (Malondialdehit), GSH-Px (Glutathione Peroxidase), Glutathione reductase (GSH-R) rates were looked from the blood, which were drawn from the patients pre-operation (T1), during operation after CC in the 30th minute (T2), 10 minutes after aortic clamp was removed (T3) and 12th hours (T4). Also, measured values correlation with reference periods, pump duration, CC duration, extubation period and mortality rates was examined.

       
</interventions>
    <comparator>Fifteen pediatric patients scheduled to undergo elective repair of cyanotic congenital heart diseases. Patients room air saturation is lower than %85.  Patients ages differed from 6 months to 5 years (average 24, 22+/-17, 42 months). All patients were in stable condition. The study was approved by the Research Ethics Committee of institution. Patients with genetic syndromes, preoperative inotropic support and reoperative procedures were excluded from the study. Controlled normoxic (n=15) (pO2:80-150 mmHg) (Group I),All operations were performed under CPB. CPB was initiated using standard Aortabicaval cannulation. Isothermic blood cardioplegia was administrated every 20 minutes during aortic cross clamping. Equal perfusion pressure was applied in operations. After anesthesia induction, FiO2 rate was applied as 21% in Group I. Arterial blood gas was seen every 15 min. intervals after CPB started. In Group I, PO2 rate in arterial blood gas was about 80-150 mmHg. After the patients were taken into intensive care, ventilator settings were calibrated as Fi02 21% in Group I; and routine intensive care protocols were applied. Patients MDA (Malondialdehit), GSH-Px (Glutathione Peroxidase), Glutathione reductase (GSH-R) rates were looked from the blood, which were drawn from the patients pre-operation (T1), during operation after CC in the 30th minute (T2), 10 minutes after aortic clamp was removed (T3) and 12th hours (T4). Also, measured values correlation with reference periods, pump duration, CC duration, extubation period and mortality rates was examined.

       
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patients MDA (Malondialdehyde), GSH-Px (Glutathione Peroxidase), Glutathione reductase (GSH-R) rates were looked from the blood.</outcome>
      <timepoint>the patients pre-operation (T1), during operation after CC in the 30th minute (T2), 10 minutes after aortic clamp was removed (T3) and 12th hours (T4). Also, measured values correlation with reference periods, CPB time, ACC(aortic cross clamp) time. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>extubation time assessed medical record data.</outcome>
      <timepoint>postoperative period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>mortality rates assessed  with medical records data</outcome>
      <timepoint>postoperative period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Elective total correction of cyanotic congenital heart diseases</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Months</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>5</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Acyanotic congenital heart diseases</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/09/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>Saricam</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Cukurova University </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Cukurova, Faculty of Medical,Department of Cardiovascular Surgery,
01330-Saricam-Adana</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Turkey</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>cukurova university</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of Cukurova,Faculty of Medical,department of cardiovascular surgery,
01330-Adana</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Turkey</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>balcali hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University of Cukurova,Faculty of Medical, Department of Cardiovascular Surgery, Saricam-01330/Adana</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Turkey</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Study Aim: Cardiopulmonary Bypass with high oxygen levels may expose cyanotic children to reoxygenation injury. The superoxide radicals that are formed as a result of molecular oxygen and inflammatory response on cardiopulmonary bypass can cause a decrease in the highenergy phosphates, structural and functional changes in biomolecules.  Antioxidant defense mechanism is inadequate in the children that have chronic hypoxia. Therefore, to avoid  damage reoxygenation, various methods have  been  developed  to  reduce  the  formation  of  free  oxygen  radicals.  Our study tested the hypothesis of oxidant damage via free radical generation during cardiopulmonary bypass on cyanotic pediatric patients. Materials and Methods: Cyanotic pediatric Patients (Fallot tetralogy)(n=30) were randomized to two treatment arms of the study. Cardiopulmonary bypass was performed as normoxic (pO2: 80-150mmHg) in Group I (n=15) and hyperoxic (pO2:150-250 mmHg) in Group II(n=15). Malondialdehyde, Glutathione  peroxidase,  Glutathione reductase were measured. Results: This study demonstrates that Malondialdehyde  and antioxidant   enzyme levels are higher in   cyanotic   infants   with   hyperoxic cardiopulmonary bypass. Conclusion: Routine clinical methods of cardiopulmonary bypass with a hyperoxemic may increase the reoxygenation injury in cyanotic children. The reoxygenation injury can be reduced by using a novel and simple Cardiopulmonary bypass strategy of controlled reoxygenation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Cukurova,Faculty of Medical Local Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Cukurova,Faculty of Medical,Department of Cardiovascular Surgery,
Saricam-01330/Adana</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/06/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Turkey</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Atakan Atalay</name>
      <address>University of Cukurova,Faculty of Medical, Department of Cardiovascular Surgery,Saricam-01330/Adana</address>
      <phone>+90 322 3386815</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>atakan1973@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Hafize Yaliniz</name>
      <address>University of Cukurova,Faculty of Medical, Department of Cardiovascular Surgery,01330Saricam / Adana</address>
      <phone>+ 90 322 3386815</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hafize101@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hafize  Yaliniz</name>
      <address>University of Cukurova,Faculty of Medical, Department of Cardiovascular Surgery,01330-Saricam/Adana</address>
      <phone>+90 322 3386815</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hafize101@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Hafize  Yaliniz</name>
      <address>University of Cukurova,Faculty of Medical, Department of Cardiovascular Surgery,01330-Saricam/Adana</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>hafize101@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>