<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371285">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/07/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001013358</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>TARGET study: Exercise for people with knee osteoarthritis and obesity</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Target study: Comparison of weight bearing functional exercise and non-weight bearing quadriceps strengthening exercise on pain and function for people with knee osteoarthritis and obesity.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1186-3614 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>TARGET</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Osteoarthritis </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Description of intervention(s) / exposure: This randomised controlled trial will compare two exercise interventions. 

Both interventions will comprise of 5 individual, in clinic physiotherapist-supervised exercise sessions (30-40-minute) and a 4 x weekly home exercise program over the same 12 week period.

In clinic physiotherapy sessions will occur at weeks 1, 2, 4, 7 and 10. 

Home exercise sessions will be approximately 20-30 minutes in duration and occur at the participants chosen time 4 times each week.  

The two exercise interventions are;
i) weight bearing functional exercise which includes 5 weight bearing exercises with progressions performed using body weight resistance, elastic bands, foam mats and a small step; and, 
ii) non-weight bearing quadriceps strengthening which includes 5 non-weight bearing exercises, with resistance provided by ankle weights or elastic bands.

The intensity and progressions of the exercise programs will be determined by the physiotherapist in discussion with the participant. Participants will be provided exercise equipment required. 

Adherence to the exercise program will be captured via questionnaire at the 12 week time point. Adherence to the 5 clinic physiotherapy sessions will be recorded by the physiotherapists in their study case notes.  Treatment fidelity will be scored by an assessment of the physiotherapist treatment notes, and fidelity will be maintained through regular tele-conferences between physiotherapists and the research team. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>We are comparing the effects of the two exercise groups described under intervention.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall average pain in the past week on an 11-pont numeric rating scale </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 weeks after baseline </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical function sub-scale of the Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Osteoarthritis Index (WOMAC)
(scores will be extracted from the Knee Injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS)questionnaire which contains the WOMAC questions.)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 weeks after baseline </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Average pain on walking in the past week on an 11-point numeric rating scale </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 weeks after baseline </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Knee Injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS)
This includes subscales
i) pain
ii) other symptoms
iii) function in sport and recreation
iv) knee related quality of life 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 weeks after baseline </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health related quality of life  - AQoL2</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 weeks after baseline </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional test 1.
30 second chair sit to stand 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 weeks after baseline </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional test 2.
40m fast paced walk </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 weeks after baseline </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional test 3.
6-step stair climb </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 weeks after baseline </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional test 4.
Timed single leg stance</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 weeks after baseline </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional test 5.
Four square test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 weeks after baseline </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Global change overall rated on a 7 point numeric scale from much worse to much better.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks after baseline </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Global change in pain rated on a 7 point numeric scale from much worse to much better.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks after baseline </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Global change in function rated on a 7 point numeric scale from much worse to much better.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks after baseline </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quadriceps muscle strength Maximum voluntary isometric strength of the knee extensors will be assessed on an isokinetic dynamometer (HUMAC) with the knee at 90 degrees of knee flexion. Maximum torque reached over 3 repetitions of 3 seconds each is recorded and normalised to body weight (Nm/kg), with higher scores indicating greater strength. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 weeks after baseline </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Abductor muscle strength 
Maximum voluntary isometric strength of the hip abductors will be assessed using a handheld dynamometer (Lafayette Manual Muscle Test System) with the hip in neutral abduction. Average force from 2 repetitions of 3 seconds each is recorded, converted to torque and normalised to body weight (Nm/kg), with higher scores indicating greater strength.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 weeks after baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>I.	aged 50 years and above;
II.	report knee pain on most days of the past month;
III.	suffered knee pain for 3 months or more;
IV.	report a minimum average overall pain score of 4 on an 11-point numeric rating scale over the previous week;
V.	demonstrate tibiofemoral osteophytes on x-ray;
VI.	obesity (BMI of 30 kg/m2 and over);
VII.	have a mobile phone that has text messaging functionality and be happy to receive text message reminders if required during the study.

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>I.	Lateral joint space narrowing greater than medial joint space narrowing on x-ray;
II.	knee surgery/joint injection in past 6 months or planned surgery in the next 9 months;
III.	current or past (4 weeks) oral corticosteroids;
IV.	systemic arthritic conditions;
V.	past knee fracture or malignancy;
VI.	past hip/knee joint replacement/tibial osteotomy;
VII.	other condition currently affecting lower limb function;
VIII.	participation in knee strengthening or neuromuscular exercise in past 6 months or planning to start exercise in next 9 months;
IX.	unable to walk unaided;
X.	unable to commit to study requirements (Unable to attend study appointments or complete study outcomes) </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The person who will determine if a potential participant is eligible for inclusion in the trial will be unaware, when this decision is made, to which group the participant will be allocated. Another researcher will access the randomisation schedule via computer, concealed in a password protected database.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomization will occur according to a 1: 1 allocation and be stratified by physiotherapist and physiotherapy clinic. The randomisation schedule will be computer generated, using random permuted blocks of varying sizes. To conceal allocation, the randomisation schedule will be accessed via a password-protected, computer program by a researcher not involved in participant recruitment scheduling or assessment.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample Size calculation: For an effect size of 0.5, power 80% and two-sided significance level 0.05, with a correlation between pre- and post-measurements of 0.45 for pain, 51 participants per arm will be required (using ANCOVA for analysis including baseline pain measurement as a covariate). To account for 20% loss to follow up, sample size will be increased to 64 per arm, for a total of 128. This gives power of 83% to detect an effect size of 0.5 for function with a correlation between pre- and post-measurements of 0.49 and a two-sided significance level of 0.05.
128 participants will be recruited and randomised.

Statistical Analysis Plan: Analyses comparing the two treatment groups will be performed by the statistician in a blinded fashion using all available data from all participants randomised to an exercise group. Demographic and baseline characteristics of participants will be summarised as appropriate (means and standard deviations for continuous variables that appear to be approximately normally distributed, medians and interquartile ranges for other continuous variables, counts and percentages for categorical variables) and will be inspected to assess baseline comparability of treatment groups. For continuous outcomes, differences in change will be compared between groups using linear regression models adjusted for baseline levels of these outcomes, including random effects for treating physiotherapist to account for clustering by physiotherapist. Model assumptions will be assessed using standard diagnostic plots. For binary outcomes, differences between groups will be compared using relative risks, calculated from logistic regression models with random effects for treating physiotherapist.  Should the amount of missing data for an outcome be such that imputation is required, multiple imputation will be conducted and the method reported. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/07/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>12/07/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>128</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>0</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>12/10/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Melbourne </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>1-100 Grattan Street, Melbourne, Victoria, 3010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>L 1 16 MARCUS CLARKE Street, Canberra Australian Capital Territory 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Knee osteoarthritis (OA) is a major public health problem with significant personal, social and economic burden.  Being overweight is a known risk factor for the development and progression of symptomatic knee OA. One potential reason may be due to the increased forces placed on the knee joint during weight bearing activities in people that are overweight. The development of targeted treatments for people at high risk of disease progression, such as those who are overweight, is a research priority. Our primary aim will therefore be to evaluate whether people with knee OA and obesity respond differently to two different types of exercise; 1) weight bearing functional exercise and ii) non-weight bearing quadriceps strengthening exercise.
Participants will be randomly allocated to one of the two exercise groups. Over 12 weeks participants will attend 5 in clinic physiotherapist appointments. The physiotherapist will prescribe a home based exercise program following the exercise protocol assigned to the participant. The home based exercise program will be completed 4 times a week, in addition to the physiotherapy sessions. Primary outcomes are overall knee pain and physical function measured at 12 weeks. 

As body mass index is easily measured our findings will potentially provide clinicians with a simple and effective means to tailor their exercise prescription and optimise outcomes for their patients with knee osteoarthritis.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Melbourne Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC), reference number 1544919</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Melbourne, Victoria, 3010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/03/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1544919</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/06/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Kim L Bennell</name>
      <address>L7 161 Barry Street, The University of Melbourne, Victoria, Australia, 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 4135 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.bennell@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Alexander J Kimp</name>
      <address>L7 161 Barry Street, The University of Melbourne, Victoria, Australia, 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 3109</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alexander.kimp@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Kim L Bennell</name>
      <address>L7 161 Barry Street, The University of Melbourne, Victoria, Australia,3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 4135 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.bennell@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Alexander J Kimp</name>
      <address>L7 161 Barry Street, The University of Melbourne, Victoria, Australia, 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 3109</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alexander.kimp@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>