<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367588">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/12/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/01/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000015549</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Prescribing the maximum tolerated dose of walking for people with severe knee osteoarthritis: A Phase II, Randomised Controlled Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>What are the effects of a prescribed walking program of 70 minutes per week for 12 weeks versus standard care only for pain, cardiovascular risk, function and quality of life for people with severe knee osteoarthritis and at least moderate risk of cardiovascular disease - a randomised controlled trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1165-0716 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>Nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Osteoarthritis of the knee</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cardiovascular disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In addition to standard care, participants in the intervention group will be prescribed a walking dose of 70 minutes per week, of at least moderate intensity using the rate of perceived exertion scale with a a score of at least 3/10, in bouts of at least 10 minutes. The weekly dose will be completed for 12 weeks in the community. The walking doses will be completed in the community using normal assistive devices, such as a walking stick if required. Participants will continue taking their usual medications and other normal strategies to manage their knee osteoarthritis. 

To increase the likelihood of adherence to the intervention and maximise the effectiveness of the intervention, we will use the following behavioural change techniques and strategies: Single planning session of up to 30 minutes with goal setting - a physiotherapist will assist the participant to determine when and where to complete the dose of walking; Supervision - physiotherapist supervision of one session of walking weekly; Monitoring - each participant will wear a pedometer to self monitor the number of steps each week. They will also complete a logbook to record number of steps and time spent walking each week. A physiotherapist will monitor their progress with a weekly phone call or send weekly SMS reminders; Engaging social supports - each participant will be encouraged to walk with a friend, or family member or other research participant. </interventions>
    <comparator>Standard care is non-operative management to manage pain and symptoms and may include pharmacological or non-pharmacological interventions providing these do not include prescription of physical activity. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome is average knee pain over the previous week measured by a 0-10 Numerical Pain Rating Scale. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post intervention (Week 12)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity level measured by activity monitor worn continuously for 7-days

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post intervention (week 12)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resting blood pressure - systolic and diastolic (mm Hg) using a blood pressure monitor</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post intervention (week 12)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body mass index (kg/m2) using scales for weight and tape measure for height</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post intervention (week 12)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Waist circumference (cm) using a tape measure
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post intervention (week 12)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total cholesterol (mmol/L), low-density lipoprotein (mmol/L), high-density lipoprotein (mmol/L), triglycerides (mmol/L), and fasting glucose level (mmol/L) using single blood test via local pathology department.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post intervention (week 12)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain, stiffness and activity limitation using the Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Osteoarthritis Index (WOMAC)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post intervention (week 12)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>40 metre (4 x 10 metres) fast paced walk test as per OARSI functional performance measure guidelines</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post intervention (week 12)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>30-second chair stand test as per OARSI fucntional performance measure guidelines </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post intervention (week 12)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health-related quality of life using the EuroQol (EQ-5D and EQ-VAS) questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post intervention (week 12)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(1) Adult aged at least 50 years and living independently in the community.
(2) Diagnosed with severe knee osteoarthritis rated as grade III or IV determined radiogaphically.
(3) Have a cardiovascular risk profile with at least 2 total risk factors using stage 2 of the Adult Exercise Screening Tool.
(4) Able to participate safely in the moderate-intensity physical activity trial using stage 1 of the Adult Exercise Screening Tool.
(5) Able to understand English.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(1) Live in supported accommodation such as a nursing home. 
(2) Report daily resting level of pain to be 9 or 10 on a 0 (no pain) to 10 (worst possible pain) Numerical Pain Rating Scale. 
(3) Have very high levels of psychological distress as measured by the Kessler 10 questionnaire with a K10 score &gt; 29. 
(4) Have an intellectual impairment as measured by the Short Portable Mental Status Questionnaire with a score of 7 or less. 
(5) Have a systemic arthritic condition such as rheumatoid arthritis.
(6) Have a neurological condition that affects walking.
(7) Had knee surgery or intra-articular corticosteroid injection within past six months. 
(8) Using oral corticosteroids within four weeks. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be randomly assigned using sealed opaque envelopes prepared by an independent researcher with no role in recruitment or assessment. </concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted block design with a computer random number generator </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>We aim to recruit 44 participants (22 in each group allowing for 10% loss to follow up) providing 80% power of detecting a difference of 2.8 units for the primary outcome of pain, assuming SD of 3.0 units, at a 5% significance level using a two tailed test. 

Intention to treat analysis will be performed including all available data regardless of adherence to protocol. 

Data analysis will use ANCOVA to compare the two groups using post intervention (week 12) data for all the primary and secondary outcome measures. Baseline measures will be used as the covariate. 

Adherence will be reported using the percentage of scheduled sessions completed and percentage of the prescribed walking dosage completed each week. Any adverse events will be reported in the manuscript.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>15/04/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>15/09/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>44</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>46</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>29/01/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Box Hill Hospital - Box Hill</hospital>
    <hospital>Maroondah Hospital - Ringwood East</hospital>
    <postcode>3128 - Box Hill</postcode>
    <postcode>3135 - Ringwood East</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Jason Wallis</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Box Hill Hospital
Building B - Level 3
8 Nelson Rd
Box Hill VIC 3128</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>La Trobe University
Rehabilitation Research Focus Area 
Sport, Exercise and Rehabilitation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>La Trobe University
Bundoora VIC 3086</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nicholas Taylor</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>La Trobe University and Eastern Health 
Level 2, 5 Arnold Street
Box Hill VIC 3128</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Low physical activity levels and poor cardiovascular health are big problems for people with severe knee osteoarthritis. This study is the first in the world to find out if a walking program can make a difference to their knee pain and cardiovascular health.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Eastern Health Research and Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 2, 5 Arnold Street
Box Hill VIC 3128</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/03/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>E11-2014 </hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/11/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Jason Wallis</name>
      <address>Box Hill Hospital
Building B, Level 3
8 Arnold Street 
Box Hill VIC 3128</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9895 3715</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jason.wallis@easternhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Jason Wallis</name>
      <address>Box Hill Hospital
Building B, Level 3
8 Arnold Street 
Box Hill VIC 3128</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9895 3715</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jason.wallis@easternhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Jason Wallis</name>
      <address>Box Hill Hospital
Building B, Level 3
8 Arnold Street 
Box Hill VIC 3128</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9895 3715</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jason.wallis@easternhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Jason Wallis</name>
      <address>Box Hill Hospital
Building B, Level 3
8 Arnold Street 
Box Hill VIC 3128</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9895 3715</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jason.wallis@easternhealth.org.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>