<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371892">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/11/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/11/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001631493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Warm humidification for prevention of hypothermia during liver transplantation</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Use Of Fisher &amp; Paykel Humigard (Registered Trademark) Open Surgery Humidification System in The Prevention of Hypothermia in Patients Undergoing Orthotropic Liver Transplantation: A Prospective Randomized Pilot Clinical Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn> U1111-1190-1169</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Not applicable</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>liver transplantation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Intraoperative hypothermia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other anaesthesiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention for this study is the Humigard (Registered Trademark) system (Fisher and Paykel Healthcare, Auckland, New Zealand), which is a heat delivery system that allows insufflation of warm humidified CO2 into the open wound cavity. 

The device works by delivering dry medical CO2 is at a flow rate of 10 L/min and a pressure of 4.5 bar from a medical pressurized gas cylinder (AGA gas AB, Stockholm, Sweden) via a polyvinyl chloride tube into an open surgery humidification system. It consists of a bacterial filter, and a humidification chamber filled with sterile water, positioned on a humidifier controller that includes an integrated temperature and flow sensor. The outlet of the humidification chamber is connected to a thermally insulated heated insufflation tube that maintains temperature and humidity of the gas to its outlet. The humidified and warm CO2 enters a gas diffuser (VITA-diffuser (Registered Trademark), Cardia Innovation AB, Stockholm, Sweden) consisting of a polyvinyl chloride tube with polyurethane foam at its end. The cylindrical polyurethane foam tip diverts the gas jet into multiple directions via the many small paths inside the foam. The gas is thus uniformly distributed and the large diffuser surface area greatly reduces the velocity of the outflow. The humidified gas is delivered directly into the surgical wound. The final temperature of the humidified CO2 is 37 degrees Celcius, with a 100% relative humidity. 

Patients that will be receiving this intervention are adult patients undergoing liver transplantation in  university teaching hospital. 

The sterile device is placed into the open abdominal cavity by the surgeon at commencement of the transplant. The device remains in situ until closure of the surgical wound at completion of surgery. The device settings do not change at any point and the humidification is delivered continuously. 

In addition to this device, all patients will also receive standard temperature homeostasis. 
This will include:
1.  Pre-warming with a full body warming blanket (Bair Hugger 3M 'Trademark', Model 315) set at 43oC one hour prior to surgery.
2. Ambient operating room temperature set at 21oC
3. Underbody warming blanket (Bair Hugger 3M, Model 637) set at 43oC, placed over a standard operating table. These warming blanket devices will be continued during induction of anaesthesia and during insertion of all invasive monitoring lines, after which the full body warming blanket will be replaced with an intraoperative upper body warming device that covers both upper limbs and face (Bair Hugger 3M 'Trademark', Model 523XL) for the remainder of the case. 
4. During the anhepatic phase, ambient operating temperature will be increased to 23oC, with no further adjustments for the remainder of the case.
5. Temperature of all fluids delivered will be via a Belmont (Registered Trademark) Rapid Infuser RI-2 system that will deliver preheated fluids at 42oC.
</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will have the Humigard (Registered Trademark) system (Fisher and Paykel Healthcare, Auckland, New Zealand) placed in to the abdominal cavity as for the Intervention group, however the device will not be turned on. 

All patients will also receive standard temperature homeostasis as the Interventional group. This will include:
1.  Pre-warming with a full body warming blanket (Bair Hugger 3M 'Trademark', Model 315) set at 43oC one hour prior to surgery.
2. Ambient operating room temperature set at 21oC
3. Underbody warming blanket (Bair Hugger 3M 'Trademark', Model 637) set at 43oC, placed over a standard operating table. These warming blanket devices will be continued during induction of anaesthesia and during insertion of all invasive monitoring lines, after which the full body warming blanket will be replaced with an intraoperative upper body warming device that covers both upper limbs and face (Bair Hugger 3M 'Trademark', Model 523XL) for the remainder of the case. 
4. During the anhepatic phase, ambient operating temperature will be increased to 23oC, with no further adjustments for the remainder of the case.
5. Temperature of all fluids delivered will be via a Belmont (Registered Trademark) Rapid Infuser RI-2 system that will deliver preheated fluids at 42oC.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Core temperature prior to reperfusion of the donor liver</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be measured five minutes immediately prior to reperfusion of the donor liver (Stage 3-5min). Measurement of core temperature will be measured using a nasopharyngeal temperature probe (CareFusion Incorporation, Australia) inserted between 9 and 11 cm from the nares to maximize the likelihood of positioning in the upper third of the nasopharynx. As the insertion of a continuous Cardiac Output Swan-Ganz pulmonary artery catheter (Edward Lifesciences CCO-Combo, IL, USA) is part of our standard anaesthesia technique for all patients undergoing OLT, we will also use temperature measurements from the Pulmonary artery catheter. 

</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Core temperature at Stage 1+60min</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be measured at Stage 1+60min: (recorded 60 min after start of the dissection phase.

Measurement of core temperature will be measured using a nasopharyngeal temperature probe (CareFusion Incorporation, Australia) inserted between 9 and 11 cm from the nares to maximize the likelihood of positioning in the upper third of the nasopharynx. As the insertion of a continuous Cardiac Output Swan-Ganz pulmonary artery catheter (Edward Lifesciences CCO-Combo, IL, USA) is part of our standard anaesthesia technique for all patients undergoing OLT, we will also use temperature measurements from the Pulmonary artery catheter. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Core temperature at Stage 2+30 min </outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be measured at Stage 2+30 min (recorded 30 min after start of the anhepatic phase)

Measurement of core temperature will be measured using a nasopharyngeal temperature probe (CareFusion Incorporation, Australia) inserted between 9 and 11 cm from the nares to maximize the likelihood of positioning in the upper third of the nasopharynx. As the insertion of a continuous Cardiac Output Swan-Ganz pulmonary artery catheter (Edward Lifesciences CCO-Combo, IL, USA) is part of our standard anaesthesia technique for all patients undergoing OLT, we will also use temperature measurements from the Pulmonary artery catheter. 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Core temperature at Stage 3+5min</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be measured at Stage 3+5min: (recorded 5 min post reperfusion)

Measurement of core temperature will be measured using a nasopharyngeal temperature probe (CareFusion Incorporation, Australia) inserted between 9 and 11 cm from the nares to maximize the likelihood of positioning in the upper third of the nasopharynx. As the insertion of a continuous Cardiac Output Swan-Ganz pulmonary artery catheter (Edward Lifesciences CCO-Combo, IL, USA) is part of our standard anaesthesia technique for all patients undergoing OLT, we will also use temperature measurements from the Pulmonary artery catheter. 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Core temperature at Stage 3+60min</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be measured at Stage 3+60min: (recorded 60 min post reperfusion)

Measurement of core temperature will be measured using a nasopharyngeal temperature probe (CareFusion Incorporation, Australia) inserted between 9 and 11 cm from the nares to maximize the likelihood of positioning in the upper third of the nasopharynx. As the insertion of a continuous Cardiac Output Swan-Ganz pulmonary artery catheter (Edward Lifesciences CCO-Combo, IL, USA) is part of our standard anaesthesia technique for all patients undergoing OLT, we will also use temperature measurements from the Pulmonary artery catheter. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Core temperature at surgical closure of the wound</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be measured during closure of the surgical wound

Measurement of core temperature will be measured using a nasopharyngeal temperature probe (CareFusion Incorporation, Australia) inserted between 9 and 11 cm from the nares to maximize the likelihood of positioning in the upper third of the nasopharynx. As the insertion of a continuous Cardiac Output Swan-Ganz pulmonary artery catheter (Edward Lifesciences CCO-Combo, IL, USA) is part of our standard anaesthesia technique for all patients undergoing OLT, We will also use temperature measurements from the Pulmonary artery catheter. 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria will include:
1. adult patients (age greater than 18 years) 
2. undergoing primary orthotopic liver transplantation (OLT)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria includes:
1.  pregnancy
2. fulminant hepatic failure
3. redo-OLT
4. requirements for continuous vena-venous bypass
5. requirements for haemofiltration
6. multivisceral transplantation</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All adult patients scheduled to be undergoing liver transplantation in the operating suite of the Austin Hospital will be screened for eligibility. Once informed consent has been obtained, randomisation will be by means of sealed opaque envelopes with permuted blocks of variable size. Each envelope will contain a study arm allocation with the Active device or placebo device. 
</concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted block randomisation will be used using computer generated software.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Not applicable</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Samples size calculations will be performed using inferences for means comparing two independent samples. This was established with an internal audit of 60 anaesthesia charts of patients undergoing OLT in our institution over the previous 2 years, which demonstrated a mean (standard deviation) temperature prior to reperfusion of 35.4oC (0.8). Nominating a clinically important difference of 1oC in the intervention group, using a two-sided test, with an alpha value of 0.05 and a desired power of 0.80, the sample size required for each group was 11 participants. 

Continuous data will be tested for normality using the DAgnostino-Pearson omnibus test.  For the primary end point between groups, comparisons for continuous data will be performed with the use of Studentss t-test.  All test will be considered two-tailed and a p-value &lt;0.05 will  indicate statistical significance. Values will be reported as mean and standard deviation (SD) or medians and interquartile range (IQR).  Changes in NPP and PAC temperatures over the given time points will be measured with repeated measures ANOVA. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>1/01/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>22</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>22</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/02/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Austin Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>152 Studley Road, Heidelberg, Victoria, 3084, Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Austin Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>152 Studley Road, Heidelberg, Victoria, 3084, Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The Victorian Liver Transplantation Unit at Austin Hospital is a collaborative service providing liver transplant services to residents in Victoria, Australia. Retrospective intra-operative data collection from our institution shows that 72% of patients undergoing liver transplantation are hypothermic prior to reperfusion of the donor liver, despite intense and standardised measures taken to maintain temperature homeostasis.  This study is a prospective, single centre, blinded, randomised pilot trial to test the feasibility and efficacy of whether, in addition to the standard temperature measure undertaken to prevent intra-opeartive hypothermia, the additional use of the Fisher &amp; Paykel Humigard (Registered Trademark) Open Surgery Humidification System will prevent hypothermia in adult patients undergoing orthotopic liver transplantation. Adult patients undergoing orthotopic liver transplantation will be included. The primary end point will be core temperature measured five minutes immediately prior to reperfusion of the donor liver.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Not applicable</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Not applicable</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Not applicable</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>152 Studley Road, Heidelberg, Victoria, 3084, Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/07/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC no: 2012/04674</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/05/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Laurence Weinberg</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia, Austin Hospital
152 Studley Road, Heidelberg, 3084, Victoria
</address>
      <phone>+61394965000</phone>
      <fax>+61394966421</fax>
      <email>laurence.weinberg@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Laurence Weinberg</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia, Austin Hospital
152 Studley Road, Heidelberg, 3084, Victoria
</address>
      <phone>+61394965000</phone>
      <fax>+61394966421</fax>
      <email>laurence.weinberg@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Laurence Weinberg</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia, Austin Hospital
152 Studley Road, Heidelberg, 3084, Victoria
</address>
      <phone>+61394965000</phone>
      <fax>+61394966421</fax>
      <email>laurence.weinberg@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Laurence Weinberg</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia, Austin Hospital
152 Studley Road, Heidelberg, 3084, Victoria
</address>
      <phone>+61394965000</phone>
      <fax>+61394966421</fax>
      <email>laurence.weinberg@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>