<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369884">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/01/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/02/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000105448</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Fatigue resistance index of inspiratory muscles  what is normal in a healthy population?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Fatigue resistance index of inspiratory muscles  what is normal in a healthy population?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Inspiratory muscle endurance in healthy adults</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the respiratory system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>To quantify inspiratory muscle endurance, through the Fatigue Resistance Index method, in healthy people in a one off session. The procedure is identical to that performed in the previous studies in intensive care at Canberra Hospital. To perform the testing, participants will need to empty their lungs, then inhale maximally through a hand-held device (MircoRPM Respiratory Pressure Metre) for 1 to 2 seconds. This will be repeated 3 times to ensure reliability. The participant will then breathe through an inspiratory muscle trainer (Threshold IMT) for 2 minutes at a resistance equivalent to 30% of their maximum effort. The participant will then repeat the 3 maximum inhalations through the hand-held MicroRPM machine. Thus a total of 6 maximal breaths is required for testing, i.e. 3 breaths either side of the 2 minute resistance challenge. Participants will be monitored closely and testing ceased if not tolerated at any point. Total testing time should take less than 15 minutes allowing for explanation and rest time. 

</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To quantify inspiratory muscle endurance, through the Fatigue Resistance Index method, in healthy people.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>In a one off session. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Borg Rate of Perceived Exertion whilst undertaking the Fatigue Resistance Index</outcome>
      <timepoint>Taken during the one off session; immediately before the first measure of Maximal Inspiratory Pressure, immediately after the completion of the 2 minute breathing challenge and at cessation of testing immediately after the final measure for Maximal Inspiratory Pressure is taken. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy adults, with no known respiratory disease, who have not undertaken any form of inspiratory muscle training. Healthy adults who are able to communicate and provide consent to perform testing. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants will be excluded it they already suffer from lung disease (eg Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease, Asthma or Cystic Fibrosis). These pathologies are likely to affect the strength and endurance of inspiratory muscles, and would therefore contaminate the sample of healthy participants.

Participants will also be excluded if they already participate in any form of inspiratory muscle training as this is likely to affect the Maximal Inspiratory Pressure manoeuvre used in the FRI test, and would not represent usual respiratory muscle activity for a healthy person  (i.e. they are likely to have supra-normal results).

Participants will be excluded if they cannot communicate sufficiently to provide consent or perform testing. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Descriptive analysis will be used for all data using Statistical Package for Social Sciences (SPSS) version 22. Correlation between FRI scores of healthy participants and ICU patients will be described using intra-class correlation coefficients and Pearsons correlation as appropriate. Significance level will be set at p &lt; 0.05. Analysis will be performed in collaboration with Dr Teresa Neeman at the ANU. 
To allow comparison with our sample from ICU patients, we will aim to recruit 45 participants aged 20  90, recruiting both males and females to allow age and gender matching to our intensive care patients as much as possible.
The ICU sample that we shall be comparing it to is detailed in the attached reference. In this study the sample size was calculated to be 16 to detect a change of 10% MIP when measuring FRI (correlation co-efficient of &gt;0.06). This study took FRI measures from 43 patients in an ICU setting. The aim of the proposed study is to compare the data between the ICU patients and the FRI scores of health adults.  
Reference: 	Bissett B, Ledtischke IA, Boots R &amp; Paratz J. Weaned but weary: one third of adult intensive care patients mechanically ventilated for 7 days or more have impaired inspiratory muscle endurance after successful weaning. Heart and Lung. 2015; 44: 15  20.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/02/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/03/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>45</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Elizabeth Kilpatrick</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Faculty of Health 
University of Canberra
University Drive 
Bruce 
ACT 
2601</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Canberra</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of Canberra
University Drive
Bruce
ACT
2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Bernie Bissett</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Faculty of Health 
University of Canberra
University Drive 
Bruce 
ACT 
2601</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Nicole Freene</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Faculty of Health 
University of Canberra
University Drive 
Bruce 
ACT 
2601</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Teresa Neeman</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>The Australian National University 
Acton 
Canberra 
ACT 
2601</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To quantify inspiratory muscle endurance, through the Fatigue Resistance Index method, in healthy people. 
Poor respiratory muscle endurance is a consequence of invasive mechanical ventilation for patients in intensive care (1,2). Over the past 10 years, researchers including ourselves (2,3) have used the Fatigue Resistance Index (FRI) method to quantify the endurance of the respiratory muscles of intensive care patients. This involves inhaling through a hand-held device for 2 seconds, then breathing against resistance for 2 minutes, and then inhaling maximally through the hand-held device again. The FRI is a feasible alternative to more complex invasive methods of analysing diaphragmatic endurance. 
However, to our knowledge, this method of quantifying endurance has not been tested in a normal population. Following our publication in 2015 (1), we wish to measure FRI in normal healthy subjects to allow us to compare our data from intensive care patients with age and gender matched healthy participants. 

REFERENCES:
1. Bissett B, Ledtischke IA, Boots R &amp; Paratz J. Weaned but weary: one third of adult intensive care patients mechanically ventilated for 7 days or more have impaired inspiratory muscle endurance after successful weaning. Heart and Lung. 2015; 44: 15  20.
2. Chang AT, Boots RJ, Brown MG, Paratz J, Hodges PW. Reduced inspiratory muscle endurance following successful weaning from prolonged mechanical ventilation. Chest. 2005; 128: 553  559.
3. Bissett BM, Leditschke IA, Paratz JD, Boots RJ. Protocol: inspiratory muscle training for promoting recovery and outcomes in ventilated patients (IMPROVe): a randomised controlled trial. BMJ Open. 2012:2e000813.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Canberra
University Drive
Bruce 
ACT 
2617</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/10/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>15-203</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/09/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/369884-FRI in Normals UC Ethics September 2015.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/369884-Faculty of Health Research Support Application 1 2015_FRI validity testing.doc</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/369884-15-203_Bissett_Approved_Letter.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Elizabeth Kilpatrick</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health 
University of Canberra
University Drive 
Bruce 
ACT 
2601</address>
      <phone>+61448682080</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>u3070332@uni.canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Elizabeth Kilpatrick</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health 
University of Canberra
University Drive 
Bruce 
ACT 
2601</address>
      <phone>+61448682080</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>u3070332@uni.canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Elizabeth Kilpatrick</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health 
University of Canberra
University Drive 
Bruce 
ACT 
2601</address>
      <phone>+61448682080</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>u3070332@uni.canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Elizabeth Kilpatrick</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health 
University of Canberra
University Drive 
Bruce 
ACT 
2601</address>
      <phone>+61448682080</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>u3070332@uni.canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>