<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367762">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/01/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/02/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000137594</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of the Impact of Exercise on the Performance of an Artificial Pancreas</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of the Impact of Exercise on the Performance of an Artificial Pancreas in Adults with Type 1 Diabetes.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1166-1659</utrn>
    <trialacronym>None</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 1 Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This two staged randomised crossover study involves people with type 1 diabetes who are established on insulin pump therapy and have glucose sensing experience. The study aims to examine the performance of an integrated "artificial pancreas" challenged by aerobic and anaerobic exercise in people with type 1 diabetes therapy and with glucose sensor experience. 

All participants will undertake the aerobic and anaerobic exercise stages in random order. Following clinical assessment, each participant will undergo cardiopulmonary testing to determine their maximal amount of oxygen consumed during exercise (VO2 max as ml/kg/min), maximal exercise capacity (Watts) and anaerobic threshold. Subsequently there will be a ~6 day run-in period when participants wear glucose sensors and the study pump (without insulin delivery from this pump), while continuing their usual insulin regimen via their own insulin pump. The aerobic exercise protocol will be conducted on a stationary bicycle with 5 minutes of warm-up, followed by 40 minutes of steady-state exercise at 20% below anaerobic threshold. The anaerobic exercise protocol is high intensity interval training with 5 minutes of warm-up, then 6 repetitions of 4 minutes of exercise at an intensity halfway between their anaerobic threshold and maximal intensity, followed by 2 minutes of rest (an additional 4 minutes rest will be provided between the 3rd and 4th repetitions).

On the morning of the exercise study days, participants will have an early morning light breakfast (40g of carbohydrate), preceded by an insulin bolus via their own pump to account for the carbohydrate of the meal. The participants will commence their exercise program ~3 hours after arrival at the Clinical Trial Centre, and venous blood samples will be collected at 15 minute intervals from 1 hour prior to exercise until 2 hours after exercise completion to assess insulin and counter-regulatory hormones. Participants will resume their usual insulin regimen via their own insulin pump at the conclusion of each stage. 

Participants will return to the Clinical Trial Centre approximately 2 weeks later to undertake the alternate exercise regimen, preceded by the run-in period.</interventions>
    <comparator>We are comparing the effectiveness of an "Artificial Pancreas" in both aerobic and anaerobic exercise. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety: Episodes of hypoglycaemia (blood glucose &lt; 4.0mmol/L for at least 15 minutes duration).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored every 5 minutes from 1 hour prior to exercise, until 2 hours post exercise in each study stage. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Efficacy: Continuous glucose monitoring % (CGM) time spent in target glycaemia (4.0-8.0 mmol/L and 4.0-10.0 mmol/L).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored every 5 minutes from 1 hour prior to exercise, until 2 hours post exercise in each study stage. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Episodes of major hypoglycaemia requiring third party assistance.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored every 5 minutes from 1 hour prior to exercise, until 2 hours post exercise in each study stage.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Episodes of hyperglycaemia (blood glucose &gt; 10.0mmol/L) with blood ketones &gt; 0.4 mmol/L.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored every 15 minutes from 1 hour prior to exercise, until 2 hours post exercise in each study stage.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Continuous glucose monitoring % (CGM) time spent in hyperglycaemia (&gt;10.0 mmol/L) and hypoglycaemia (&lt;4.0 mmol/L).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored every 5 minutes from 1 hour prior to exercise, until 2 hours post exercise in each study stage.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Continuous glucose monitoring (CGM) time and area under the curve (AUC) spent above target range (&gt; 10.0 mmol/L).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored every 5 minutes from 1 hour prior to exercise, until 2 hours post exercise in each study stage.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Continuous glucose monitoring (CGM) time and area under the curve (AUC) spent below target range (&lt; 4.0 mmol/L)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored every 5 minutes from 1 hour prior to exercise, until 2 hours post exercise in each study stage.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Glycaemic variability as determined by mean amplitude of glycaemic excursions (MAGE) and Standard deviations (SD).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored every 5 minutes from 1 hour prior to exercise, until 2 hours post exercise in each study stage.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Laboratory assay for counter-regulatory hormones (Free insulin, glucose, growth hormone, cortisol and catecholamines).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored every 15 minutes from 1 hour prior to exercise, until 2 hours post exercise in each study stage.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-Age &gt; 18 years
-Type 1 Diabetes (confirmed by fasting C-peptide level &lt; 50 pmol/L)
-Insulin pump therapy for at least 6 months
-HbA1c &lt; 9.0%
-Experience with a glucose sensor
-Established insulin pump therapy parameters
-Ability to insert/change sensor
-Ability to undertake exercise as per protocol</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-Requiring &gt; 150 units of insulin/day
-Diabetic ketoacidosis within the past 4 weeks 
-Hypoglycaemic unawareness (Gold score &gt;4) while on Sensor Augmented Pump Therapy (SAPT) or &gt; 2 severe hypoglycaemic episodes within the last 12 months
-Pregnancy
-Renal impairment (eGFR &lt; 60ml/min/1.73m2)
-Current or recent (&lt;4 weeks) oral or inhaled steroid therapy
-Dermatological conditions involving the region of device insertion
-Ischaemic heart disease or peripheral vascular disease precluding exercise
-Physical limitations (e.g. impaired vision) that would compromise operation of the Closed Loop system
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerised random allocation (i.e. equal numbers in both groups) </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>This is an exploratory study. There is an absence of available data allowing the calculation of statistical power. The data generated by this study will enable power calculations for future research.

Descriptive statistics will be used to describe safety and efficacy parameters. A formal statistical comparison will be used to compare time spent within target glucose range for each of the two exercise modalities. A qualitative analysis will be performed examining changes in circulating free insulin and counter-regulatory hormones in response to the two different forms of exercise. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/02/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>17/02/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>22/10/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>26/02/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>12</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>12</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>26/02/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne) Ltd - Fitzroy</hospital>
    <postcode>3065 - Fitzroy</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>St Vincents Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>41 Victoria Parade
Fitzroy VIC 3065  </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>St Vincent's Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>41 Victoria Parade
Fitzroy VIC 3065 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Medtronic Diabetes</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>18000 Devonshire Street
Northridge CA 91325 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Melbourne</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>29 Regent Street
Fitzroy VIC 3065 </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Insulin delivery via an insulin pump can mimic the normal action of the pancreas more closely than multiple daily injections of short and long acting insulin. With the development of continuous glucose monitoring devices, glucose levels can be measured continuously over 24 hours.   These two devices have now been linked by a computer to create an artificial pancreas or Closed Loop system. The computers function is to calculate accurately the amount of insulin to be delivered by the pump based on the sensor glucose readings.  Overnight Closed Loop systems have been tested in both children and adults with Type 1 diabetes. Overall, the results show that the systems are safe and effective.  However, important gaps in our knowledge remain to be explored. For example, while exercise is healthy for people with diabetes it can result in unpredictable changes in glucose levels that may challenge an artificial pancreas. In addition, different types of exercise have differing effects on glucose levels in people with Type 1 diabetes. Short intense bursts of exercise (anaerobic exercise) may initially increase glucose levels while less intense exercise (aerobic exercise) tends to reduce glucose levels.

This study aims to collect information about how well the Closed Loop system is able to control glucose levels of people with type 1 diabetes when they undertake aerobic and anaerobic exercise. Outcomes of interest will include the risk of hypoglycaemia and time in healthy glucose range. Insulin and counter-regulatory hormones will also be measured providing insights into changes in glucose levels with exercise in Type 1 diabetes patients. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital Melbourne</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Governance Unit
Level 5, Mary Aikenhead Building
27 Victoria Parade
Fitzroy VIC 3065 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/01/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC-D 152/14</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>David O'Neal </name>
      <address>Department of Endocrinology &amp; Diabetes, St Vincent's Hospital Melbourne, 35 Victoria Parade Fitzroy VIC 3065 </address>
      <phone>+61 3 9231 2211</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dno@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sybil McAuley</name>
      <address>Department of Endocrinology &amp; Diabetes, St Vincent's Hospital Melbourne, 35 Victoria Parade Fitzroy VIC 3065 </address>
      <phone>+61 3 9231 2211</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sybil.mcauley@svha.org.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sybil McAuley</name>
      <address>Department of Endocrinology &amp; Diabetes, St Vincent's Hospital Melbourne, 35 Victoria Parade Fitzroy VIC 3065 </address>
      <phone>+61 3 9231 2211</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sybil.mcauley@svha.org.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dilshani Jayawardene</name>
      <address>Department of Endocrinology &amp; Diabetes, St Vincent's Hospital Melbourne, 35 Victoria Parade Fitzroy VIC 3065 </address>
      <phone>+61 3 9231 2211</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dilshani_jay@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>