<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343375">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/08/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/08/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000900910</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Factors predicting therapy outcome in online cognitive behaviour therapy (with minimal therapist assistance) in the treatment of anxiety disorders among children and adolescents.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Factors predicting therapy outcome in online cognitive behaviour therapy (with minimal therapist assistance) in the treatment of anxiety disorders among children and adolescents.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>None</utrn>
    <trialacronym>None</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety disorders in children and adolescents</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The program comprised ten, one-hour online youth sessions and five, online one-hour parent sessions completed over a 12-week period. Booster sessions were completed at one- and three-months following treatment for both the young person and their parent(s). Standard CBT anxiety management strategies were used including: psychoeducation, relaxation training, recognition of the physiological symptoms of anxiety, cognitive strategies of coping self-talk and cognitive restructuring, graded exposure, problem solving, and self-reinforcement. Parent sessions also taught anxiety management skills, in addition to parenting strategies to empower parents to help their child implement anxiety management skills.  

The content, length and number of session activities in the Internet program replicate those of the clinic-based version. Sessions are designed to be engaging, interactive, and age-appropriate.  Eye-catching graphics, sounds, games and quizzes are used to maintain the youths level of interest.  Information is presented through interactive exercises and followed by quizzes that check for correct understanding and provide personalized corrective or positive feedback through pop up messages. The content of the intervention is designed to meet the developmental and cognitive level of youths, with age-appropriate scenarios, examples, and activities (example situations include school exams, job interviews, dating, and oral presentations).  
The program is (minimally) therapist-assisted, rather than self-help. Each family is assigned an online therapist (BRAVE Trainer) who monitors their progress through the program and provides brief email feedback following each session.  At no stage did any participants have face-to-face contact with their therapist and all other contact (i.e., email or phone) was minimal.  Clinician contact was restricted to brief, weekly emails and a short, 15-minute mid-program telephone call to assist in exposure hierarchy development.  Most other contact with the online therapist was computer generated. Client responses to all session and homework activities are stored in an administrator section of the program and can be viewed by the therapist to guide the content of the weekly email. In addition, automated computer-generated emails are sent on behalf of the online therapist to congratulate participants for completion of sessions and personalized emails are sent to provide feedback about responses to quiz tasks.  Personalized automated reminder emails are sent to advise when the next session is available for completion, or to provide prompts if not completed by the due date. The first session also includes a picture of the therapist, and some brief biographical information about them, to which the client responds by providing information about themselves.</interventions>
    <comparator>No comparison group 
This is a prediction of outcome study using a single intervention</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome measures is "blind", independent clinical diagnostic interview for anxiety disorders and clinician serverity rating of diagnosis using Anxiety Disorders Interview Schedule for DSM-IV: Child and Parent versions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment
12-weeks
6-month follow-up
12-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Children's Global Assessment Scale. (CGAS: Schaffer et al., 1983).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment
12-weeks
6-month follow-up
12-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parent and child survey of anxiety symptoms using Spence Children's Anxiety Scale (Spence, 1998)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment
12-weeks
6-month follow-up
12-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Internalizing problems using the Child Behaviour Checklist and Youth Self-Report form - Achenbach</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment
12-weeks
6-month follow-up
12-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Predictors of therapy outcome will include:
- working alliance (Working Alliance Inventory - Short Form)
- motivation (short rating scale developed by the researchers)
- types of anxiety disorders (from ADIS-C/P)
- compliance (operationalized for example as the percentage of therapy session and homework tasks completed by the participant by 6-month follow-up) 
- family factors including 
* parental relationship quality Quality of Marriage Index (Norton, 1983)
* parental anxiety and depression (DASS-21; Lovibond &amp; Lovibond, 1995) 
* family environment factors (Family Adaptability and Cohesion Evaluation Scale Version III (FACES-III; Olson et al., 1985).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Working alliance after session 3
Compliance with therapy tasks in each session
Family factors prior to commencement of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Primary diagnosis of Separation Anxiety disorder, social phobia, specific phobia or generalized anxiety disorder
be aged between 7 and 18 years, 
access to a computer and the internet at home, 
able to read and write English at an age-appropriate level.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>7</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>primary diagnosis of the following (ie. if greater severity than the presenting anxiety disorders)
- panic disorder (PD), 
- obsessive compulsive disorder (OCD) 
- post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) 
- depression
Or pervasive developmental disorder or specific learning disorder, self harm, severe conduct disorder</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants in this trial were recruited from across Australia and were referred by parents, mental health practitioners, GPs or teachers. 

As the study is a prospective one, examining predictors of outcome, there are no comparison conditions.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Clinical interviewers were independent of the intervention and were not aware of the type of therapy that participants had received, nor whether they had taken part in a therapy.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/05/2006</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2009</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>31/12/2009</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>170</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>120</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Griffith University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Griffith University 
Nathan Campus
Kessels Rd
Nathan
Brisbane
QLD 4111</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Queensland</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University of Queensland St Lucia
Brisbane
Queensland
QLD 4067</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study examines factors that predict treatment outcome in cognitive behaviour for child and adolescent anxiety disorders. In particular, it will examine the role of family factors (such as parental mental health problems, parent relationship problems, and family environment), and the role of compliance and the quality of the working alliance between the online therapist and family members, in predicting the impact of treatment. The study will have sufficient sample size to enable us to examine whether family factors and working alliance have their impact upon treatment outcome through their influence upon compliance with therapy tasks.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://brave.psy.uq.edu.au/</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Anderson, R.A., Spence, S.H., Donovan, C.L., March, S., Prosser, S., &amp; Kenardy, J. (2012). Working Alliance in Online Cognitive Behavior Therapy for Anxiety Disorders in Youth: Comparison with Clinic Delivery and its Role in Prediction of Outcome, Journal of Medical Internet Research, 14 (3): e88.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Macquarie University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Balaclava Rd
North Ryde
Sydney
New South Wales 2109</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/02/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HE24FEB2006-R04438</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/01/2006</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Griffith University Human Research Ethics committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Griffith University
Nathan Campus
Kessels Rd
Brisbane 
Queensland 4111</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/12/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>PSY-10-07-HREC</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/12/2007</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Queensland Behavioural and Social Sciences Ethical Review Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Queensland 
St Lucia Campus
St Lucia
Brisbane
QLD 4072</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/12/2004</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2004000768</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/12/2004</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Susan H Spence</name>
      <address>Griffith University
AISRAP, Mount Gravatt Campus
176 Messines Ridge Road
Mt Gravatt, Qld
4122</address>
      <phone>+ 61 07 373 53382</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 37357507</fax>
      <email>s.spence@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Susan H Spence</name>
      <address>Griffith University
AISRAP, Mount Gravatt Campus
176 Messines Ridge Road
Mt Gravatt, Qld
4122</address>
      <phone>+61 (07) 373 53382</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 37357507</fax>
      <email>s.spence@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Susan H Spence</name>
      <address>Griffith University
AISRAP, Mount Gravatt Campus
176 Messines Ridge Road
Mt Gravatt, Qld
4122</address>
      <phone>+ 61 07 373 53382</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 37357507</fax>
      <email>s.spence@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Susan H Spence</name>
      <address>Griffith University
AISRAP, Mount Gravatt Campus
176 Messines Ridge Road
Mt Gravatt, Qld
4122</address>
      <phone>+61 (07) 373 53382</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.spence@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>