<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366245">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/06/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/06/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000603617</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can a tailored exercise and home hazard reduction program reduce the rate of falls in community dwelling older people with cognitive impairment or dementia? A Randomised control Trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Can a tailored exercise and home hazard reduction program reduce the rate of falls in community dwelling older people with cognitive impairment or dementia? A Randomised control Trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn> U1111-1156-2215 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>i-FOCIS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>cognitive impairment or dementia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>falls prevention</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dementias</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention will consist of a 12 month home-based, individualised exercise and home hazard reduction program. There will be a combined total of 11 visits from the occupational therapist and physiotherapist, with the ratio of visits determined by the identified needs of participants. We anticipate the first 4 visits will occur on a weekly basis (Weeks 1-4) then the next 2 visits will occur (Weeks 7 and 9) to establish the intervention program. Following that the intervention visits will take place at the following intervals (Weeks 13, 17, 22, 36 and 48). 

This will be supplemented by regular phone calls in between visits to the participant / carer to encourage continued engagement and identify any problems with either the exercise or environmental recommendations. We anticipate phone calls to occur on weeks (6, 11, 15, 19, 24, 27, 30, 33, 40 and 44).

Both the physio and OT will follow up recommendations made and upgrade programs as this is an important part of the intervention.

All participants in the intervention group will undergo the Allen's Cognitive Assessment. The Allens model of functional cognition will be used to guide the therapists in tailoring the interventions to the skills and abilities of the participants. The functional cognition results of participants will be discussed with their carers to enhance their knowledge about optimal ways of communicating with the participant and skills with regard to assisting implement the intervention. This important aspect will facilitate active participation of carers without increasing carer burden. 

A home exercise program based on the Weight-bearing Exercise for Better Balance program will be established. The exercises will be individually prescribed by experienced physiotherapists and will target postural control (balance) and lower limb muscle strength. The participants will be asked to continue to exercises for the 12-month study period. The frequency and duration will be individually prescribed and will be up to 30 minutes 3-6 times a week. It is anticipated that the majority of the intervention group will be offered this intervention and tailored to the needs of the individual based on the results of the baseline physical and functional cognition assessments and in discussion with the participant and their carer. 

Participants will be provided with a folder outlining the exercises recommended. The format of the exercises will be adjusted to accommodate the cognitive abilities of the participant, with instructions adapted accordingly, i.e. written information, written and pictorial information etc. and the exercises will be progressed under instruction from the physiotherapist over the intervention period. 

The occupational therapist will undertake a detailed home safety assessment using the Westmead Home Safety Assessment and will provide advice and recommendations to optimise safety within the home. Recommendations following the assessment will be prioritised according to functional cognition of the participant, level of perceived risk and in negotiation with both the participant and carer. Typical recommendations will include removing/ securing loose mats, highlighting step edges with fluorescent tape, sensor lighting to illuminate walkways and bathrooms at night. Grab rails are commonly recommended and individuals will be referred to local home modifications services. Any recommendation for equipment will be done through the local hospital Equipment Lending Pool.

The carer education session is conducted by the occupational therapist (OT) in participants homes and provides support and education to carers. Some participants with dementia are present during the session, while other sessions are conducted with the carer only. These visits can also be conducted at the research office. These arrangements are determined by the carer prior to the session.

The session is informed by the functional cognition assessment and the falls behavioural risk factor assessment of the participant, and the Task Management Strategy Index (TMSI) completed by carers (which identifies strategies carers already use). This information is used to provide tailored strategies to help the carer engage with the exercise program. These include understanding participant cognitive abilities and implications for functional skills and behaviour in positive terms, as well as effective teaching and supervision skills according to the specific cognitive abilities of the participant. While these strategies are targeted to enhancing engagement with the program, they can often be generalised to other situations in everyday life. 

This visit is flexible in terms of timing within the program  it is usually the fourth OT visit, and occurs after the third or fourth physiotherapy visit (week 17). Depending on the needs of the participants. The carer visit is always within the first six months of the protocol. It usually has a duration of one hour.

In addition the intervention group will be required to fill out monthly falls calendars for 12 months and have a baseline, 6 month and 12 month re-assessment. </interventions>
    <comparator>Participants allocated to the control group will receive the usual care provided by their health service providers. In addition they will be required to fill out monthly falls calendars for 12 months. They will have no contact with the study physiotherapist or occupational therapists. They will also be required to have a baseline assessment, 6 month and 12 month re-assessment.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of falls in the control and intervention group over the 1 year follow up period.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 year follow-up using monthly falls calendars for all participants</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of fallers in the control and intervention group over the 1 year follow-up period</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 year follow-up period using monthly falls calendars</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Quality of life will be measured using the EQ5D-5L in both the participants and their carers at baseline, 6 months and 12 months reassessment and change compared in the control and intervention group overtime and their carers.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity level</outcome>
      <timepoint>Physical activity levels will be ascertained at baseline and at the 12 month reassessment using the Incidental and Planned Exercise Questionnaire (IPEQ) and will provide change compared in the control and intervention group over time.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disability assessment for everyday functioning</outcome>
      <timepoint>Disability Assessment for Dementia screen will be used to assess everyday functioning at baseline and at the 12 month reassessment in study participants and change compared in the control and intervention group overtime.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fear of falling </outcome>
      <timepoint>Fear of falling will be ascertained at baseline and at the 12 month reassessment using the Icon-FES and change compared in the control and intervention group over time.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression</outcome>
      <timepoint>The 15-item Geriatric Depression Scale will assess symptoms of depression at baseline and at the 12 month reassessment and compared in the control and intervention group over time. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety </outcome>
      <timepoint>The 9-item Goldberg Anxiety Scale will assess symptoms of generalized anxiety at baseline and at the 12 month reassessment and compared in the control and intervention group over time. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neuropsychological performance </outcome>
      <timepoint>Changes in cognition will be assessed using the 
*Frontal Assessment Battery, 
*Mini mental and 
*Addenbrooke's cognitive examination (ACER -R) 
at baseline and at the 12 month reassessment and compared in the control and intervention group over time. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical performance measures</outcome>
      <timepoint>Physical performance will be measure using the 
*Physiological Profile Assessment (measures visual contrast sensitivity, proprioception, quadriceps strength, simple reaction time, and postural sway while standing on a foam rubber mat with eyes open), 
*Short form physical performance battery (measures sit to stand, balance and walking speed),
*Maximal balance (measures maximum AP lean) and *Coordinated stability 

at baseline, 6 months and 12 months reassessment and compared in the control and intervention group over time. 

</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Carer burden</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured using the Zarit Burden of care Index at baseline and at the 12 month reassessment and compared in the control and intervention group over time. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Caregiver skill enhancement</outcome>
      <timepoint>Caregiver skill enhancement will be measured using the Task Management Strategy Index at baseline and at the 12 month reassessment and compared in the control and intervention group over time.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence to exercise </outcome>
      <timepoint>Adherence to exercise measure using monthly exercise diaries
within 12 months follow-up period for each participant in the intervention group </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Up take of home modifications</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up take of home modifications within 12 months follow-up period for each participant in the intervention group calculated as a percentage of recommendations. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Planned and unplanned use of health services</outcome>
      <timepoint>Health services measured using data collected from monthly diaries within 12 months follow-up period for each participant and compared in the control and intervention group over time.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>* Sex: Males &amp; Females
* 65 + years
* Living in the community
* MMSE&lt;24 or ACE-R &lt;83 or specialist clinical diagnosis of   cognitive impairment or dementia
* Must have an identifiable and consenting person responsible and a carer (likely to be the person responsible in many cases) who have a minimum of 3.5 hrs hours of face to face contact with the participant each week for the purposes of reporting of falls and supervising the exercise intervention (3 times per week).
* Willingness of participant and carer to give informed consent and to participate in and comply with the study protocol. Proxy consent and participant assent will be used where participants cannot give informed consent.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>* Participants with a MMSE &lt; 12/30, as it is considered unlikely such people will be able to engage with the intervention
* Participants with the following medical conditions: delirium, acute medical illnesses, severe psychiatric disorders, progressive neurological diseases other than dementia and blindness
* Residents of residential aged care facilities
* Non-english speaking and no readily available interpreter
* People in existing dependent or unequal relationships 
* People who are highly dependent on medical care
* People who may be involved in illegal activity
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Potential participants will be identified through a range of existing services including cognitive disorders and memory clinics. 

At the initial home visit, the researcher will explain the study and provide a chance for the participant and their carer to ask questions. If both the person with cognitive impairment or dementia and the carer are agreeable to participate, then both will be asked to sign the relevant consent forms.  If needed a person responsible may need to consent on behalf of the participant.
 
The participant and carer will be enrolled into the study after the informed consent process has been completed and the participant has met all inclusion criteria and none of the exclusion criteria.  The participant will receive a study enrollment number and this will be documented in the participant’s study record and on all study documents.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation to intervention or control groups will occur after completion of the baseline assessment and will be stratified by site. Concealed randomisation will be performed centrally using a web-based randomisation service.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Power analysis (with 5% significance levels, 80% power) has been undertaken using data from our previous work and similar studies. A total of 360 participants (180 per group) will provide 80% power to detect a significant 30% lower rate of falls for intervention participants than control participants (i.e. IRR = 0.70). We assumed alpha (measure of over-dispersion in negative binomial regression model) to be 0.8) and assumed the control group rate of falls would be 1.8 falls/person year over the 12-month follow-up period - based on our FOCIS cohort study. An average follow-up period of 11 months (rather than the planned 12 months) was used to account for loss to follow-up. A total of 360 participants will also allow us to detect a minimal increase of 5 points on the ADRQL (assuming control group mean of 79.7 and SD= 13.8) and provide us with over 90% power to detect between-group differences of the other measures.

An intention-to-treat approach will be used for all analyses. The number of falls per person-year in the intervention and control groups will be compared using negative binomial regression. This provides a more powerful analysis than a simple comparison of the proportion of fallers in the follow-up period, as it takes into account all falls during the trial, and also the distribution of falls, which is Poisson-like but has a fatter tail. General linear models will be used to assess the effect of group allocation on the continuously scored secondary outcome measures. Modified Poisson regression models will be used to compare groups on dichotomous outcome measures. Predictors of adoption and adherence will be analysed using multivariate modelling techniques such as multiple linear and logistic regression.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/06/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>24/06/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>2/07/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>360</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>2/07/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Hornsby Ku-ring-gai Hospital - Hornsby</hospital>
    <hospital>Prince of Wales Hospital - Randwick</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>The Sutherland Hospital - Caringbah</hospital>
    <hospital>St George Hospital - Kogarah</hospital>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
    <postcode>2077 - Hornsby</postcode>
    <postcode>2217 - Kogarah</postcode>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>2229 - Caringbah</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Jacqueline Close </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Neuroscience Research Australia, 
Barker Street, Randwick NSW 2031.

PO Box 1165, Randwick NSW 2031.

</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council, Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601  

Postal National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601 
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Lindy Clemson </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Discipline of Occupational Therapy, Faculty of Health Sciences, 
The University of Sydney; PO Box 170, Lidcombe, NSW 2141. 
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Cathie Sherrington </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The George Institute for Global Health, The University of Sydney, PO Box M201, Missenden Rd, Sydney, NSW 2050.</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Keith Hill </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Curtin University, Building 408 Business and Physiotherapy
Kent St Bentley WA 6102.

GPO Box U1987
Perth WA 6845
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Sue Kurrle </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Hornsby Hospital, 
Palmerston Rd
Department of Rehabilitation and aged care, 
Hornsby NSW 2077.</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Stephen Lord </othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Neuroscience Research Australia, 
Barker Street, Randwick NSW 2031.

PO Box 1165 Randwick Sydney NSW 2031.</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Henry Brodaty </othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Dementia Collaborative Research Centres (DCRC) 
Room 302, Level 3
AGSM Building (G27)
University of New South Wales (UNSW)
NSW 2052.

</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Laura Gitlin </othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Johns Hopkins University 
School of Nursing Center for Innovative Care in Aging 
525 North Wolfe Street, Suite 316
Baltimore, MD 21205</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>United States of America</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Kirsten Howard </othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Public Health, A27 Edward Ford Building, 
The University of Sydney, Sydney, NSW 2006.
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There is currently no evidence indicating that it is possible to prevent falls in community dwelling older people with dementia despite this group having a disproportionately higher rate of falls and fractures and poorer outcomes post event.

However, there is evidence that a dementia specific approach to care, in which interventions are based on the individuals preserved abilities and in which the caregiver is provided with the skills to work effectively with the person with dementia, can be effective in improving daily function for the person with dementia and sense of competence for the carer.


The purpose is to investigate whether a home-based exercise program and home hazard reduction program can: 
1) reduce the risk of falls in older people with cognitive impairment or dementia, and 
2) improve the quality of life of the person with cognitive impairment or dementia and their carer(s).
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Close JC, Wesson J, Sherrington C, Hill KD, Kurrle S, Lord SR, Brodaty H, Howard K, Gitlin LN, O'Rourke SD, Clemson L.

Can a tailored exercise and home hazard reduction program reduce the rate of falls in community dwelling older people with cognitive impairment: protocol paper for the i-FOCIS randomised controlled trial.
BMC Geriatr. 2014 Aug 15;14:89. 
doi: 10.1186/1471-2318-14-89.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Eastern Sydney Local Health District Human Research Ethics Committee. </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Support Office 
HUMAN RESEARCH ETHICS COMMITTEE
Room G71 East Wing
Edmund Blacket building
RANDWICK NSW 2031</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/05/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>14/046</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/03/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jacqueline Close </name>
      <address>Neuroscience Research Australia, 
Barker Street, Randwick NSW 2031.

PO Box 1165 
Randwick NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>(612) 9399 1055 </phone>
      <fax>(612) 9399 1204</fax>
      <email>j.close@neura.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Sandra O'Rourke</name>
      <address>Neuroscience Research Australia, 
Barker Street, Randwick NSW 2031.
PO Box 1165 
Randwick NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>(612) 9399 1851</phone>
      <fax>(612) 9399 1204</fax>
      <email>s.orourke@neura.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Sandra O'Rourke</name>
      <address>Neuroscience Research Australia, 
Barker Street, Randwick NSW 2031.

PO Box 1165 
Randwick NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>(612) 9399 1851</phone>
      <fax>(612) 9399 1204</fax>
      <email>s.orourke@neura.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Sandra O'Rourke</name>
      <address>Neuroscience Research Australia, 
Barker Street, Randwick NSW 2031.
PO Box 1165 
Randwick NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>(612) 9399 1851</phone>
      <fax>(612) 9399 1204</fax>
      <email>s.orourke@neura.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>