<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365338">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/11/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/11/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001278729</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A prospective randomised controlled trial investigating three dimensional knee joint kinematics in total knee replacement  a comparison of cruciate retaining, posterior cruciate sacrificing and medially stabilised designs.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A prospective randomised controlled trial investigating three dimensional knee joint kinematics in patients with osteoarthritis undergoing total knee replacement  a comparison of cruciate retaining, posterior cruciate sacrificing and medially stabilised designs.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Medacta knee kinematics</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Osteoarthritis
</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All participants in this trial will receive a total knee replacement.  The prosthesis used will be the GMK Total Prosthesis from Medacta International SA.
Randomisation will allocate patients to have one of three different types of prosthesis from this suite of prostheses.  
These are (1) posterior cruciate ligament retaining prosthesis, (2) a posterior cruciate ligament sacrificing/subsituting prosthesis and (3) a medially stabilised prosthesis - the GMK Sphere. 
The key differences between these prostheses is the level of antero-posterior constraint and the way in which the posterior cruciate ligament is handled.
The approximate duration for knee replacement surgery is 90 minutes, the standard operative time for all elective knee replacement surgery, regardless of the device being utilised. </interventions>
    <comparator>Group 1 will receive a Cruciate retaining prosthesis
Group 2 will receive a Posteriorly stabilising prosthesis
Group 3 will receive a Medially Stabilizing prosthesis 

Group 1 is the most commonly used technique in Australia and will thus be considered the control.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome will be to assess in vivo three dimensional knee kinematics for three different fixed-bearing total knee replacement prostheses.
Joint motion, ground reaction forces and muscle activity will be recorded simultaneously from each subject using an x-ray machine during four test conditions; level walking, stair ascent. stair decent and chair raise. </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post operatively </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Limb Alignment - x-ray and computed tomography imaging </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post-operatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Knee Pain and Function 
-will be measured using the New International Knee Society Score and the Oxford Knee Score Surveys plus a Six-minute-walk-test plus timed-up-go assessments </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-operatively, 6 and 12 months post-operatively </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>i) on the waiting list for primary total knee replacement due to osteoarthritis at St Vincent's Hospital, Melbourne 
ii) knee replacement performed by one of three joint replacement surgeons at St Vincent's Hospital whose prosthesis of choice is the Medacta GMK Knee System 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>i) Surgery for neoplastic disease
ii) Inability to provide informed consent</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>When a subject has fullfilled all study criteria allocation takes place. The patients assignment will be performed by the data manager who will have no direct contact with the subject either before or after assignment. The clinicians involved in the assessment of patients will have no role in the assignment process. The randomisation schedule will be revealed by telephone following informed consent. </concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation schedule will be generated and maintained centrally by one of the investigators who will not be involved in assessment of participants. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>No prior studies exist to base sample size calculation for 3-D fluoroscopic gait analysis. Therefore, our randomised control trial is powered (alpha value = 0.05 and power = 90%) to answer our secondary aim of determining whether a medially stabilised design will result in improved functional outcomes following knee replacement compared to a fixed-bearing cruciate retaining  design. Functional outcomes will be measured at 12 months post knee replacement using the Oxford Knee Score (OKS). To demonstrate a difference of 5.0 (SD 5.0) in OKS between groups, 25 participants in each arm will be required. We will recruit 30 per arm to account for an approximate drop out rate of 20%. 
Categorical variables will be analysed using chi-squared tests (or Fisher's Exact tests for small samples) while continuous variables will be apllied to (paramatric) t-tests and (non-parametric) Mann-Whitney tests for symetrically and asymmetrically distributted data, respectively. Multivariate analysis will be run to account for confounding variables. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>90</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne) Ltd - Fitzroy</hospital>
    <postcode>3065 - Fitzroy</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Peter Choong</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Orthopaedics
St Vincent's Hospital, Melbourne
Level 3 Daly Wing
35 Victoria Pde
Fitzroy Victoria 3065 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Medacta International SA</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Strada Regina
CH-6874 Castel San Pietro
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Switzerland</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Marcus Pandy</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of Biomechanical Engineering
University of Melbourne 
Level 5 
161 Barry Street
Parkville, 3010
Victoria</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is an investigator initiated study, aiming to assess the prosthetic performance of total knee replacements (TKR) and to determine whether abnormal movement of the replaced knee has an impact upon function and pain at one year post-operatively.
By using a prospective analysis of patients randomized to receive TKR of different designs, this study aims to determine the effect the type of prosthesis has on gait, three-dimensional joint movement plus both clinical and patient reported outcomes.
In order to achieve this, joint motion, ground reaction forces and muscle activity will be recorded simultaneously from each subject during four test conditions; level walking, stair ascent, stair descent and chair rise. Limb alignment, pain and functional assessments will also be evaluated, to assist in determining variables associated with improved functional outcomes following TKR.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne) Human Research Ethics Committee - D</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/11/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Choong</name>
      <address>Department of Orthopaedics
St Vincent's Hospital Melbourne
Level 3 Daly Wing
35 Victoria Parade
Fitzroy Victoria 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9288 3980</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sarcoma@bigpond.net.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Tony Young</name>
      <address>Department of Orthopaedics
St Vincent's Hospital Melbourne
Level 3 Daly Wing
35 Victoria Parade
Fitzroy Victoria 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9288 2364</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tony.young@svha.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tony Young</name>
      <address>Department of Orthopaedics
St Vincent's Hospital Melbourne
Level 3 Daly Wing
35 Victoria Parade
Fitzroy Victoria 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9288 2364</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tony.young@svha.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Sarah Anderson</name>
      <address>Department of Orthopaedics
St Vincent's Hospital Melbourne
Level 3 Daly Wing
35 Victoria Parade
Fitzroy Victoria 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9288 2364</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sarah.anderson@svhm.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>