<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371459">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/09/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/10/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001432404</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Community Intervention for Promoting Psychological Well-Being among Unemployed</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Development, implementation and evaluation of the impact of a mental health promotion intervention to build capacity and reduce inequalities for unemployed: A community controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1187-2096</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Healthy Search for Employment - HSE</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Addiction</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Healthy Search for Employment intervention focuses on the promotion of unemployed individuals social, emotional and interpersonal skills. It also targets the strengthening of resilience and the ability to overcome the adversity of unemployment. A strong focus will be given to mental health literacy strengthening. Health education sessions will be carried out by clinical psychologists with experience in prevention and treatment of depression and anxiety disorders (with more than five years of clinical practice). It is planned to be a short-term intervention adapted and delivered to groups. The intervention will be conducted on site (two public employment centres). The format, setting and contents of the intervention will be defined on basis of literature reviews and Delphi technique, assuring its adequacy as a short-term and sustainable community intervention. Still, the intervention is expected to include the following requirements:
-	Modules: Mental health literacy (depression, anxiety, burnout, emotions), work-life balance, mental health related stigma (personal and perceived stigma), assertiveness training, definition of individual plans of action (defining short, medium and long term goals) 
-	Materials: a standardized operating procedure manual (with training and implementation material for facilitators); each participant will get a booklet with mental health literacy contents and exercises for psychosocial and interpersonal skills self-training.
-	Procedures: roleplays, group discussion of vignettes, emotional and cognitive self-awareness individual tasks based on cognitive-behavioural intervention (e.g., ABC task for assessing emotions, behaviours and cognitions, Gallassis assertive behaviour grill, for assessing contexts of assertiveness-related difficulties, etc.
-	Intervention providers: psychologists with at least 5 years of training  
-	Mode of delivery: face-to-face, to groups (8-12 participants)
-	Number of sessions: 5 sessions, spread out into two- to three-weeks, 20 hours in total (four hours per session)
-	Location: two public employment centres
Intervention assessment will follow the RE-AIM (Reach, Effectiveness, Adoption, Implementation and Maintenance) framework dimensions: reach, effectiveness, implementation and maintenance of qualities/properties. 
The reach assessment will be evaluated by measuring the proportion of invited users from public employment centres that accepts to participate in the intervention. Effectiveness will be assessed through a randomized experimental field study with two arms (arm 1: intervention group ; arm 2: control group). Participants are unemployed people (18-65 years old, both genders, having at least nine years of formal education) registered at two public employment centres (from two different geographical regions) for less than 12 months, including first-job seekers. They will be recruited by intentional sampling and randomly allocated to arm 1 (intervention group) or arm 2 (control group) through a sequential match-to-case process, considering gender, age groups and educational level. The control group will receive the care-as-usual from public employment centres. 
The implementation assessment will be done by evaluating the extent to which the syllabus and training intervention is adequate and accomplished across the intervention (fidelity assessment). A specific fidelity assessment form will be filled in by trainers and co-trainers (based on already existent toolkit forms). Also, trainees satisfaction with practical exercises will be assessed. 
Finally, managers and supervisors willingness to replicate the intervention in other units of public employment centres will be assessed as a measure of the extent to which the intervention will be sustained over time (maintenance assessment).</interventions>
    <comparator>As mentioned, the intervention will be assessed through a randomized field study with two arms (arm 1: intervention group and arm 2: control group). Users from two public employment centres will be recruited with intentional sampling and randomly allocated to arm 1 or arm 2 groups. The arm 2 group (control group) will receive the care-as-usual from public employment centres (targeting only skills for job search) which includes training and practicing of job seeking skills (e.g., writing a CV or a job application, personal image care, interviewing tips).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mental health literacy, assessed by modified/shortened versions of  (a) Depression Literacy Questionnaire (D-Lit) and (b) Anxiety Literacy Questionnaire (A-Lit), developed by Griffiths et al (2008).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three moments of evaluation will occur: before intervention (baseline), immediately after its ending and three months later.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mental health-related personal and perceived stigma (composite primary outcome), assessed by a modified/shortened version of the Depression Stigma Scale (DSS), developed by Griffiths et al (2008).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three moments of evaluation will occur: before intervention (baseline), immediately after its ending and three months later.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychological well-being, assessed by the Brief Symptom Inventory (BSI), developed by Derogatis (1983).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three moments of evaluation will occur: before intervention (baseline), immediately after its ending and three months later.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Satisfaction with life, assessed by the Satisfaction with Life Scale (SWLS), developed by Diener (1985).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three moments of evaluation will occur: before intervention (baseline), immediately after its ending and three months later.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resilience, assessed by the Connor-Davidson Resilience Scale (CD-RISC) (2003).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three moments of evaluation will occur: before intervention (baseline), immediately after its ending and three months later.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Unemployed people (18-65 years old, both genders, having at least nine years of formal education) registered at public employment centres from different geographical regions for less than 12 months (including first-job seekers).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Public employment centres unemployed users already attending, at the moment of the recruitment, other public employment centres courses.
Users with a diagnosed mental or physical severe disorder or disability.
Chronic but not disabling diseases, such as depression, anxiety disorder, diabetes or hypertension, are not exclusion criteria.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Intention to treat analysis and per protocol analysis. Logistic regression analyses. Cohens' d and odds ratio for effect size estimation.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/04/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <state>Loures and Sines</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Faculdade de Medicina da Universidade de Lisboa</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Faculdade de Medicina da Universidade de Lisboa,
Av. Prof. Egas Moniz, 
1649  028, Lisboa
Portugal</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Portugal</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>European Economic Area (EEA) Grants (Public Health Initiatives Programme [PT06])</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Administracao Central do Sistema de Saude, IP
Unidade de Gestao do Programa  ACSS
Avenida do Brasil, 53
1700-063 Lisboa
Portugal</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Portugal</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Background: Unemployment rates have increased exponentially over the last 10 years in Portugal. These vulnerable populations have an increased risk of suffering from mood and somatoform disorders (e.g., depression, anxiety), as well as alcohol or drug abuse. Economic recession has also been highlighted as a risk factor for suicide ideation, suicide attempts and death by suicide. In Portugal, there has been limited support to the needs of socio-economic vulnerable groups and there is lack of evidence-based large-scale mental health promotion programs. There is a need for effective programs involving different sectors of the society, such as primary healthcare services, and family and social welfare support structures.
Project goals: Main community intervention goals of the project are: (a) to develop and implement a structured and standardized mental health promotion program, preventing negative psychological effects of unemployment, and (b) to empower unemployed and temporary-working people, in order to enhance mental health resilience and efficacious job search skills. Main research goals are: (a) to review evidence about efficacy of mental health promotion programs targeted to unemployed populations and temporary workers, (b) to create consensus regarding strategies, methods and priority areas of intervention to promote mental health, and (c) to assess effectiveness of a mental health promotion program, developed in the context of this project.
Methods: This is a mental health promotion community-based intervention program for unemployed, aiming to enhance resilience and personal skills to overcome the adversity of job-related socio-economic conditions. Main beneficiaries of the program will be unemployed people registered at employment centers. A systematic literature review (PRISMA guidelines) and a Delphi panel (consensus-building technique) with experts will be carried for supporting key-elements to include in the intervention program (formalized in an operating procedures manual). The intervention will comprise: socio-cognitive/emotional training, time and stress management, unemployment stigma-related coping strategies, assertiveness training, self-efficacy promotion, inoculation against setbacks and empowerment for job search/reintegration. Participants will be recruited by intentional sampling and will be randomly allocated on study or control conditions. The control group will receive a work-promoters intervention as usual. The project evaluation will run parallel to the process of developing, implementing and sustaining the program, in order to provide an ongoing feedback the different actors involved. The overall project assessment will follow the REAIM framework (assessing reach, effectiveness, adoption, implementation and maintenance qualities/properties of the program), which will be used for monitoring and evaluating outcome achievement.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.empregosaudavel.org</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Comissao de Etica do Centro Academico de Medicina de Lisboa</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Faculdade de Medicina da Universidade de Lisboa
Av. Professor Egas Moniz
1649-028 Lisboa</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/04/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>168/15</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/04/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Portugal</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Maria Joao Heitor dos Santos</name>
      <address>Faculdade de Medicina da Universidade de Lisboa, 
Av. Prof. Egas Moniz, 
1649  028 Lisboa</address>
      <phone>+351 217985148</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>eeagrants.he@medicina.ulisboa.pt</email>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ana Patricia Lopes Virgolino</name>
      <address>Faculdade de Medicina da Universidade de Lisboa, 
Av. Prof. Egas Moniz, 
1649  028 Lisboa</address>
      <phone>+351 217985148</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>avirgolino@medicina.ulisboa.pt</email>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ana Patricia Lopes Virgolino</name>
      <address>Faculdade de Medicina da Universidade de Lisboa, 
Av. Prof. Egas Moniz, 
1649  028 Lisboa</address>
      <phone>+351 217985148</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>avirgolino@medicina.ulisboa.pt</email>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>