<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372495">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/03/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/03/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000365369p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A prospective, multicentre, clinical study using Robotic-Assisted Total Knee Replacement, Mako and the Triathlon Total Knee System
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A prospective, multicentre, clinical study using Robotic-Assisted Total Knee Replacement, Mako and the Triathlon Total Knee System
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1193-8456</utrn>
    <trialacronym>MAKOTKR-17</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Non-inflammatory degenerative joint disease in the knee</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients will recieve a Triathlon Primary Total Knee implant. The Stryker Triathlon Primary Total Knee System is made up of various individual implants of different designs, sizes and thicknesses. The study devices include the following and will be used in combination based on the surgeon preference for the patient;
*Cruciate Retaining (CR) or Posterior Stabilizing (PS) Femoral Cementless Component  Beaded with Peri-Apatite
*CR or PS Femoral Cemented Component 
*CR, CS or PS Primary Tibial Baseplate  Cemented
*CR, CS or PS Primary Tibial Baseplate  Cementless
*CR or PS Tibial Insert  X3
*Triathlon X3 Patella (cemented asymmetric/symmetric)

Stryker's robotic-arm assisted surgery system Mako will be used in surgery.

Duration of surgery is approximately 1.5hours and will be conducted by a qualified Orthopaedic surgeon at a hospital. Patient pre-operative and post-operative follow up visits will be conducted at the surgeons clinic rooms by a surgeon and a physiotherapist.

1 x pre-operative study visit will take place prior to surgery, and 3 x post-operative visits will take place at 3 months, 12 months and 24 months at the surgeons clinic. These visits will be conducted face to face with the surgeon and/or physiotherapist and should take less than 30 minutes in duration.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To examine the clinical outcomes of Knee Replacement surgery using the Oxford Knee Score (OKS) at 24 months, in patients receiving Total Knee Replacement performed using Triathlon Total Knee System with Strykers robotic-arm assisted surgery system Mako.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months post-operative</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the functional and clinical outcomes of Total Knee Replacement (TKR) (including pain, function and health-related quality of life) with the Triathlon Primary Total Knee System at 24 months via EQ-5D</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months post-operative</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine patient satisfaction and frequency of recommendation via patient questionnaire designed for this study of the Triathlon Total Knee System using Strykers robotic-arm assisted surgery system Mako.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months post-operative</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite, To determine the implant location and limb alignment within 3 months pre-operatively, intra-operatively, and 3 months post operatively via surgical data and radiology results. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months pre-operatively, intra-operatively and 3 months post operatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite, To record the incidence of loosening, reoperation and revision in patients receiving the Triathlon Total Knee System using Strykers robotic-arm assisted surgery system Mako via radiology and adverse event data collected from the patient and medical records. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months, 12 months and 24 months post-operative</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the length of hospital stay in patients receiving the Triathlon Total Knee System using Strykers robotic-arm assisted surgery system Mako via review of medical records </outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post-operative</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the functional and clinical outcomes of Total Knee Replacement (TKR) (including pain, function and health-related quality of life) with the Triathlon Primary Total Knee System at 24 months via Knee Society Score</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months post-operative</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the functional and clinical outcomes of Total Knee Replacement (TKR) (including pain, function and health-related quality of life) with the Triathlon Primary Total Knee System at 24 months via Forgotten Joint Score.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months post-operative</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	The patient is a suitable candidate for a Primary Total Knee Replacement (based on the Investigators clinical judgement).
2.	The patient is a male or non-pregnant female. 
3.	The patient has signed the study specific, HREC-approved, Informed Consent document and is willing and able to comply with the specified pre-operative and post-operative clinical and radiographic evaluations.
4.	The patient is at least 18 years of age
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	The patient is undergoing revision surgery 
2.	The patient has active, local infection or previous intra-articular infection
3.	The patient has skeletal immaturity
4.	The patient is without sufficient bone stock to allow appropriate insertion and fixation of the prosthesis
5.	The patient has a blood supply limitation
6.	The patient has collateral ligament insufficiency 
7.	The patient had a prior High Tibial Osteotomy (HTO)
8.	The patients weight, age or activity level might cause extreme loads and early failure of the system (surgeons discretion).
9.	The patient has a systemic or local condition that would limit the ability to assess the performance of the device e.g. neuromuscular or neurosensory deficiency, disorder leading to progressive bone deterioration (including rheumatoid arthritis and osteoporosis), or patient is immunologically suppressed.
10.	Patient has a cognitive impairment, an intellectual disability or a mental illness that is considered by the investigator to inhibit the patients capacity to consent to research and the ability to participate in it
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/04/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Stryker Australia Pty Ltd.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>8 Herbert Street, St Leonards, NSW, 2065</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Stryker Australia Pty Ltd.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>8 Herbert Street, St Leonards, NSW, 2065</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will be a prospective, multicentre, clinical study examining clinical outcomes of Knee Replacement using the Oxford Knee Score (OKS), in patients receiving Total Knee Replacement using the Triathlon Total Knee System performed using Strykers robotic-arm assisted surgery system Mako.  Functional and radiographic outcomes will be additionally collected as part of this study. 

The study will be conducted in patients with non-inflammatory degenerative joint disease who require a primary Total Knee Replacement, with a minimum 2 year patient evaluation period.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St John of God Health Care Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 3, St John of God House
177-179 Cambridge Street
Wembley WA 6014</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/03/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Gavin Clark</name>
      <address>Perth Hip and Knee
Suite 1/1 Wexford Street
Subiaco WA 6008</address>
      <phone>+61 8 6489 1700</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Debbie@hipnknee.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Holly Solomon</name>
      <address>Stryker 
8 Herbert Street
St Leonards NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9467 1072</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>holly.solomon@stryker.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Holly Solomon</name>
      <address>Stryker 
8 Herbert Street
St Leonards NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9467 1072</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>holly.solomon@stryker.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>