<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336863">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/04/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/05/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000459921</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of pulmonary rehabilitation program on self-efficacy and severity of symptoms among patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of pulmonary rehabilitation program on self-efficacy and severity of symptoms among patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1120-9982</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>COPD</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>intervention group recieve pulmonary rehabilitation program.
One of the Researchers instructed the pulmonary rehabilitation program to the experimental group. Educational session was held in single day and 3 part of 30 minutes. One part abut self care education, second about breathing  techniques and last  was exercise. Each time, patients feel tired the researcher renews practices after a period of rest. Pulmonary rehabilitation program included self care and self management education, nutrition recommendations, stress reduction methods (deep breathing, exercises, visual imagery, and progressive muscle relaxation), effective cough, breathing exercises (deep breathing, pursed lip breathing and diaphragmatic breathing), control of breathing in crucial situations, and muscle stretching exercises. In order to develop opportunities for enactive vicarious experience, researcher had performed Breathing exercises and muscle stretching exercises as a successful model and then asked patient to perform in front of her.  Accuracy of learning checked and corrected by researcher in class.
Then patients were asked to perform exercise at home for 20 minutes 3 times a week for 7 week.  Stretch muscle exercise program consisted 3 parts of warming, exercise, and cooling that had been accomplished morning and 1.30 hour after breakfast. Time of exercise gradually increased from base of 5 minutes to 20 minutes by adding 3 minutes per week. Also, patients were asked to perform breathing exercises three to four times a day and along with exercises. The usage of Respiratory exercise, muscle stretching exercises, effective cough, stress reduction methods and nutritional recommendations was checked by phone and record on usage checklists by patients and researchers separately. All of educational components with instruction of pulmonary rehabilitation program gathered in booklets which content were validated by 3 nursing experts and delivered to patient after educational sessions.
We developed the pulmonary rehabilitation program base on Banduras theory of self efficacy. So the program included components to develop the four sources of self-efficacy: 1- Mastery experiences: pulmonary rehabilitation program was accessible. Main goal for all patients was successful performance of pulmonary rehabilitation program. We increased the intensity of program gradually and fallowed patients by phone and answered to their questions. Hence attainment to mastery experience was predictable), 2- Verbal persuasion (telephone follow up intervention was conducted by researcher to reinforcement and assure the patient that they can do activities successful gradually), 3-Vicarious experiences (researcher modeled breathing and Stretch muscle exercises), and 4- Emotional arousal (we instructed patients about stress reduction methods, dyspnea management strategy, effective cough and exercise).
Telephone follow-up program provided according to self efficacy Bandura's theory and performed weekly for 7 week. Each telephone call lasted an average 15 minutes and consisted 4 parts: health behaviors assessment, reinforcement of education, answers to the patient questions and encourage patients to continue the performance.  If there was non-adherence, the situation was analyzed and helps the patient to solve their problems.  
 Data were collected at baseline and after 7 week of intervention and analyzed.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group received only routine visits and telephone follow up weekly. Because results showed that pulmonary rehabilitation program is effective in reducing the severity of symptoms and improving self efficacy in the patients with COPD, one pulmonary rehabilitation program was held for control group and delivered educational booklet to patients. Educational booklet consisted all of educational components with instruction of pulmonary rehabilitation program.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self efficacy as assessed with COPD Self Efficacy Scale (CSES)</outcome>
      <timepoint>before and after intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>severity of fatigue as assessed with Fatigue Severity Scale (FSS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>before and after intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>severity of dyspnea as assessed with Dyspnea Severity Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>before and after intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>severity of cough as assessed with cough Severity Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>before and after intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>demographic and disease related information as assessed with demographic and disease related questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>before intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria included age lower than 65 years, verification of diagnosis of moderate to severe COPD that means Adherence to the ratio of FEV1 to FVC of less than 70 percent and FEV1 value greater than or equal to 80% of the predicted normal values criterion in GOLD stage I ; FEV1 value between 50% and 79% of the predicted normal values with ratio of FEV1 to FVC of less than 70 criterion in GOLD stage II , absence of formal exercise training or pulmonary rehabilitation for at least one year, absence of active symptomatic diseases (cardiac disease, musculoskeletal disease, mental disease) that would interfere with exercise, literate and able to speak Persian, possibility of contact by phone/mobile phone.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria included of recent exacerbation or change of medication, recent mobility limitation that interfere with exercise, not participate in educational session, and lack of employing nutritional recommendation or exercise and respiratory practice for at least a week.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using coin-tossing</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>23/09/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>70</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</country>
      <state>tehran</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Tehran University of Medical Science</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Tehran- Keshavarz boulevard-Ghods street
postcode:1417653761</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Tehran University of Medical Science</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Tehran- Keshavarz boulevard-Ghods street
postcode:1417653761</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Masih daneshvari</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Tehran- Darabad-Oshan boulevard
postcode: 1956944413</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study was to investigate the effect of pulmonary rehabilitation on self efficacy and severity of symptoms in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease patients. we hypothesised that the pulmonary rehabilitation programm can reduce severity of symptoms and improve self efficacy among patient with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics in Research Committee Tehran University of Medical Sciences</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Keshavarz boulevard -Ghods street
postcode:1417653761</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/05/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>89/130/189</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>sahar khoshkesht</name>
      <address>Tehran- Tohid Squre- Nosrat Steet- college of Nursing and Midwifery
postcode:1419733171</address>
      <phone>0982166943187</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>khoshkesht@razi.tums.ac.ir</email>
      <country>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>sahar khoshkesht</name>
      <address>Tehran- Tohid Squre- Nosrat Steet- college of Nursing and Midwifery
postcode:1419733171</address>
      <phone>0982166943187</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>khoshkesht@razi.tums.ac.ir</email>
      <country>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>sahar khoshkesht</name>
      <address>Tehran- Tohid Squre- Nosrat Steet- college of Nursing and Midwifery
postcode:1419733171</address>
      <phone>0982166943187</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>khoshkesht@razi.tums.ac.ir</email>
      <country>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>