<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82259">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/12/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/12/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000621415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A study to investigate the effect of an ergonomic seat on blood flow in the lower legs.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial to investigate the effect of an ergonomic seat on lower limb venous blood flow.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Deep vein thrombosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Venous blood flow will be measured after subjects have lain prone for 5 minutes (baseline; time (T) = 5).  They will then be randomly allocated to sit first in either the intervention chair (the ergoCentric ergonomic chair) or the control chair. Venous blood flow will be measured again after subjects have sat in the ergoCentric ergonomic chair with their legs at a 90 degree angle for 5 minutes and then when they have sat with their legs at a 120 degree angle for 5 minutes. (T = 10 and T =15 respectively).  The total time subjects will spend seated in the  ergoCentric ergonomic chair will be 10 minutes. The subjects will then lie prone for 5 minutes to re-establish the baseline blood flow rate which will be measured at T=20 and they will then cross over to the control treatment (i.e. there will be a 5 minute period during which time subjects will lie prone before they crossover to the control).  Blood flow measurement is not continuous but will occur after the subject has spent 5 minutes in each posture.</interventions>
    <comparator>Venous blood flow will be measured after subjects have lain prone for 5 minutes (baseline).  It will be measured again after subjects have sat in the Herman Miller Aeron chair (the control chair) with their legs at a 90 degree angle for 5 minutes and then when they have sat with their legs at a 120 degree angle for 5 minutes. The total time seated in the Herman Miller Aeron chair will be 10 minutes. Blood flow measurement is not continuous but will occur after the subject has spent 5 minutes in each posture.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Popliteal vein peak systolic velocity measured by Doppler Ultrasound</outcome>
      <timepoint>T = 5, 10, 15, 20, 25 and 30 min</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean popliteal vein flow velocity measured by Doppler Ultrasound</outcome>
      <timepoint>T = 5, 10, 15, 20, 25 and 30 min</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total popliteal vein volume flow measured by Doppler Ultrasound</outcome>
      <timepoint>T = 5, 10, 15, 20, 25 and 30 min</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Generally healthy adult volunteers with no known vascular history considered significant by the investigator; able to give informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Unable or unwilling to give informed consent; vascular history considered significant by the investigator; unable to comply with the study requirements; Under 18 years in age.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>After informed consent has been obtained subjects will undergo Doppler ultrasound scanning after lying, and sitting for 5 min (sitting with their legs at 2 different angles) in each of the test chairs.  The order subjects sit in each of the test seats is determined by random allocation using a computer generated randomisation schedule.  The randomisation schedule is generated as a list and is provided to the researcher conducting the subject visits in advance of the trial starting. As the 2 chairs being tested differ in appearance it is not possible to blind the trial hence allocation is not concealed; but the trial design is a crossover so that each subject acts as their own controls thereby reducing allocation bias.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer program will be used to generate random number sequences.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Pharmacodynamics</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/11/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>12</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>ErgoCentric Seating Systems</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>5616 McAdam Road
Mississauga
Ontario
L4Z1P1</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Canada</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>ErgoCentric Seating Systems</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>5616 McAdam Road
Mississauga
Ontario
L4Z1P1</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Canada</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to assess the effects of sitting compared with lying on lower limb venous blood flow and to assess whether the ErgoCentric seat results in a lesser reduction in lower limb venous blood flow than the Herman Miller Aeron chair (an office seat available internationally).</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Central Regional Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 5013
Wellington</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/09/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CEN/07/08/062</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/07/2007</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Richard Beasley</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand
PO Box 10055
Wellington</address>
      <phone>+64 4 472 9199</phone>
      <fax>+64 4 472 9224</fax>
      <email>richard.beasley@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Tanya Baker</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand
PO Box 10055
Wellington</address>
      <phone>+64 4 472 9636</phone>
      <fax>+64 4 472 9224</fax>
      <email>tanya.baker@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Tanya Baker</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand
PO Box 10055
Wellington</address>
      <phone>+64 4 472 9636</phone>
      <fax>+64 4 472 9224</fax>
      <email>tanya.baker@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>