<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365872">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/02/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/03/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000302651</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Improving the transition of care for people with diabetes</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparing people with type 2 diabetes who initiate insulin in the community to standard care (people initiating insulin in hospital) in hospital length of stay, HbA1c and Diabetes Treatment Satisfaction.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Transition Diabetes Team consisting of a community based credentialed diabetes educator working with a hospital based endocrinologist, to support the person with type 2 diabetes initiating insulin to self manage insulin therapy in their home.

Duration of visit likely 1.5 hours for the first visit, with subsequent contact being either home visits or phone contact, with the duration of contact dictated by the needs of the participant.  Part of this project is to collect information regarding the number and duration of contact required to have people with type 2 diabetes initiate insulin.

The home visits will include discussion of: 
1. Diabetes - physiology, signs and symptoms, reason/methods for management
2. Insulin - doses, administration, action, injection technique etc..
3. Self Blood Glucose Management - Meter/supplies, technique, testing times/frequency/records, factors affecting tests.
4. Hypoglycemia - causes, signs and symptoms, treatment and prevention, glucagon administration.
5. Exercise - rationale/effect on  blood glucose levels, pracautions, exercise plan.
6. Nutrition - general guidelines and referral to dietitian.
7. National Diabetes Services Scheme.
8. Driving
Written information will also be provided on the above.

Once credentialed diabetes educator confident that the participant is able to self-manage insulin, they will refer the participant to local community diabetes services and cease follow up - this can be up to 4 months post discharge.  Part of the project aims is to evaluate how long it takes for people starting insulin to be able to self manage.  Each participant will be given a follow up appointment with the Austin Health Endocrinologist at 4 months post discharge.</interventions>
    <comparator>Current care: hospital based diabetes educators to support the person with type 2 diabetes initiating insulin to self manage insulin therapy while in hospital.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of hospital stay</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data will be collected in the intervention group at 2-4 weeks discharge from hospital on hypo/hyperglycaemic events (this information will be readily available from the control group in the participant medical records).  

Final data collection will occur at 4 months post discharge from hospital for all groups.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Average blood glucose levels using HbA1c.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 4 months post discharge from hospital.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diabetes Treatment Satisfaction using the Diabetes Treatment Satisfaction Questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 4 months post discharge from hospital.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Review of hospital electronic records for hospital readmission rates.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 4 months post discharge from hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>a. Adults greater than 54 years of age
b. Admitted into Austin Health
c. HbA1c greater than 8.5%
d.  Insulin naïve, type 2 diabetes patients needing insulin post discharge
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>54</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Those who do not fit the inclusion criteria, and patients who are unable to give informed consent</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>This study is being undertaken with people who are admitted into Austin Health with the stipulated inclusion criteria. All patients with diabetes will be screened by the endocrinology registrar for their eligibility to participate in the trial and if fulfilling the criteria, will be asked to participate.

After consent, baseline data will be collected after which participants will be randomly allocated into the intervention or control group.  

Group allocations will be concealed by writing allocations on a card, and placing in a sealed envelope, with each consecutive participant being given their allocation by the Diabetes Registrar, once consent has been obtained. 
</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomized using block randomization, generated from a random number table using Excel, with consecutive recruited participants allocated the next number in the list.  Equal numbers of Standard Care and Diabetes Transition Group participants will be assigned to each group.
Group allocations will be concealed by writing allocations on a card, and placing in a sealed envelope, with each consecutive participant being given their allocation by the Diabetes Registrar, once consent has been obtained. 
Due to the obvious difference in treatment protocols, the study will be unblinded to the participants and the investigators.
</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>All statistical analyses will be based on the intent-to-treat population.

Data will be analysed using descriptive statistics and interpreted in an explorative manner.  Plausibility checks will be performed for demographic data, HbA1c and other medical values.  Absolute and relative frequencies will be calculated for qualitative variables, and adjusted relative frequencies will be calculated for variables with missing data points.  
 
Demographic, medical history, and baseline data will be summarised by treatment group and analysed for comparability across groups using a Wilcoxon rank sum test for pairwise comparisons.  A p-value of 0.05 or less will be considered statistically significant.  

For Diabetes Treatment Satisfaction Questionnaire, repeated-measures analysis of variance will be used, and treatment comparisons will be performed using Wilcoxon rank sum tests on change from baseline values.  

Quantitative data analysis will be performed using SPSS, (version 21, IBM Armonk, New York, USA). 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/03/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>250</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Heidelberg Repatriation Hospital - Heidelberg West</hospital>
    <postcode>3081 - Heidelberg West</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>RDNS, Royal District Nursing Service</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>31 Alma Road
St Kilda 
Victoria, 3182</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Lord Mayors Charitable Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 15, 1 Collins Street
Melbourne Victoria 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Estate of the Late GWA Griffiths</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>60 Hindmarsh Square,
Adelaide, South Australia 5000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Austin Health </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Endocrine Department
Level 2 Centaur Building Repatriation Campus
Heidelberg West 
Victoria, 3081
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Background:
Diabetes is on the rise, increasing the burden on our health system. Many people are admitted into hospital with poorly managed diabetes and require insulin initiation to improve their health outcomes. This project aims to improve the transition of care from hospital to the home, using an innovative new Transition Diabetes Team. If successful, it would improve the current care provision to this vulnerable population group, reducing costs and improving health outcomes. This model could be replicated at other Australian hospitals, improving health outcomes and reducing costs nation-wide.

Aims:
To trial the functionality and effectiveness of Transition Diabetes Team, comprising: a credentialed diabetes educator (CDE) and diabetes specialist in commencing insulin in the home versus in the hospital.

To compare hospital Length of Stay (LOS), blood-glucose control and patient satisfaction for patients with poorly managed Type 2 Diabetes between patients receiving Transition Diabetes Team care to people who receive Standard Care.

Methods:
All people with Type 2 diabetes admitted to Austin Health from March 2014 who have an HbA1c &gt;8.5%, are 54 years or older, are insulin naive and need to start insulin in order to improve blood glucose management will be invited to participate in the study.  All who consent will then be randomly allocated to either the standard care group or the Transition Diabetes Team group:
  
Standard care Group: inpatient diabetes educators providing insulin initiation education while the patient is admitted in hospital.  

Transition Diabetes Team Group: An RDNS credentialled diabetes educator working with an Austin Health Endocrinologist to provide insulin initiation education after the person is discharged from hospital  in their own homes.  

Data will be collected on demographics, medical history, medications, diabetes management, HbA1c, hospital length of stay and diabetes treatment satisfaction.  

 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>RDNS</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>31 Alma Road
St Kilda
Victoria 3182</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/02/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office for Research 
Level 8, Harold Stokes Building 
Austin Hospital
Heidelberg Vic 3084
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/02/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rajna Ogrin</name>
      <address>RDNS
31 Alma Road
St Kilda, Victoria 3182</address>
      <phone>613 9536 5245</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rogrin@rdns.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rajna Ogrin</name>
      <address>RDNS
31 Alma Road
St Kilda, Victoria 3182</address>
      <phone>613 9536 5245</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rogrin@rdns.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rajna Ogrin</name>
      <address>RDNS
31 Alma Road
St Kilda, Victoria 3182</address>
      <phone>613 9536 5245</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rogrin@rdns.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rajna Ogrin</name>
      <address>RDNS
31 Alma Road
St Kilda, Victoria 3182</address>
      <phone>613 536 5245</phone>
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>