<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362646">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/06/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/06/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000694819</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Does outpatient physical rehabilitation improve or maintain functional independence for people with Friedreich ataxia?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>What is the effect of an six-week outpatient rehabilitation program compared to a wait-list control on functional independence in people with Friedreich ataxia?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Friedreich ataxia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Neurodegenerative diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human genetics and inherited disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other human genetics and inherited disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>An individualised rehabilitation program, consisting of a minimum of 2 hours and 15 minutes of therapy (physiotherapy, exercise physiology and/or allied health assistant supervised exercise therapy and aquatic physiotherapy), 3 times per week as per usual clinical care.  In order to provide an individualised rehabilitation program, the treating physiotherapist will conduct a thorough assessment of the participants function and impairments.  The treating physiotherapist will get access to outome measures, including the Goal Attainment Scale from the first blinded-assessment in order to individualise the rehabilitation program to the participants specific goals.  rehabilitation will be broken down into domains in order to address the specific impairments which may contribute to functional decline.  Rehabilitation will be separated into seven domains: coordination and control exercises, functional mobility, strengthening, cardiovascular fitness and muscle endurance, core-stability, balance training, and stretching. Sessions may be one-on-one, in a group setting or a combination of both.  In addition, a home exercise program (HEP) will be given to the participant, to be commenced immediately after the period of intervention, as per standard practice.  The home exercise program will consist of any of/or a combination of aquatic exercises, home based exercises or a gym program.  This content will be determined by participant and rehabilitation/treating physiotherapist.  The HEP will be prescribed during the intervention </interventions>
    <comparator>Wait-list control: where participants are added to a wait-list to receive rehabilitation within the standard average time frame of six weeks. After the wait-list control period participants will receive the same intervention as per the intervention group. During the wait-list period participants will still have access to standard care, however participants will be asked not to increase their exercise/therapy over what they were completing on study entry.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional improvement as measured by the Functional Independence Measure (FIM).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, week 6, week 12, week 18 and week 24 after baseline. (Baseline is two weeks after randomisation.)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disease progression as measured by the Friedreich Ataxia Rating Scale (FARS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, week 6, week 12, week 18 and week 24 after baseline. (Baseline is two weeks after randomisation.)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life as measured by the Friedriech Ataxia Impact Scale (FAIS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, week 6, week 12, week 18 and week 24 after baseline. (Baseline is two weeks after randomisation.)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Foot posture as assessed by the Foot Posture Index (FPI).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, week 6, week 12, week 18 and week 24 after baseline. (Baseline is two weeks after randomisation.)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gastrocnemius, soleus and tibialis posterior spasticity as measured by the Modified Tardieu Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, week 6, week 12, week 18 and week 24 after baseline. (Baseline is two weeks after randomisation.)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Balance as assessed by the Berg Balance Score.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, week 6, week 12, week 18 and week 24 after baseline. (Baseline is two weeks after randomisation.)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gait velocity as measured by the Timed 25 Foot Walk (T25FW).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, week 6, week 12, week 18 and week 24 after baseline. (Baseline is two weeks after randomisation.)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient perceived benefit of intervention as assessed by the Patient's Global Impression of Change (PGIC).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, week 6, week 12, week 18 and week 24 after baseline. (Baseline is two weeks after randomisation.)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Confounding factors related to exercise out of the trial as assessed by the Phone-Fitt.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, week 6, week 12, week 18 and week 24 after baseline. (Baseline is two weeks after randomisation.)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Individual goal achievement as measured by the Goal Attainment Scale (GAS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, week 6, week 12, week 18 and week 24 after baseline. (Baseline is two weeks after randomisation.)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Spatio-temporal gait parameters as measured by the GAITRite mat.  Participants will be asked to walk down the mat six times at their preferred and fast speeds.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, week 6, week 12, week 18 and week 24 after baseline. (Baseline is two weeks after randomisation.)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Homozygosity for a GAA expansion in intron 1 of FXN 
2. Aged 15 years and over
3. Able to give informed consent
4. Understand written and verbal English
5. Reduction in functional capacity and/or need for physical rehabilitation intervention 
6. Able and willing to participate and attend a six-week outpatient rehabilitation program at the Kingston Centre
7. Have a FARS Functional Staging Score 2-5 (Symptoms present, recognized by patient, but still mild  Confined but can navigate a wheelchair and can perform some activities of daily living that do not require standing or walking)
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>15</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Compound heterozygotes for a GAA expansion in intron 1 and a point mutation/deletion in FXN 
2. Aged under 15 years
3. Acute orthopaedic injury limiting ability to weight-bear
4. Pregnancy
5. Living rurally or interstate with no other means of accommodation
6. Those unable to access the outpatient program due to transport issues
7. Need for immediate physiotherapy intervention for safety reasons (i.e. unable to be waitlisted)
8. Those requiring greater than three days per week of intervention (i.e. need for serial casting, multiple falls at home, pain) as assessed by the Friedreich ataxia Clinic multidisciplinary team
9. Other illness that has acutely reduced functional capacity	
10. Received botulinum injections or undergone major orthopaedic surgery in last 6 months
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The multidisciplinary team from the specialist multidisciplinary Friedreich ataxia clinic at Monash Medical Centre will complete a screening assessment as part of usual clinical practice. People with Friedreich ataxia identified as having the potential to benefit from rehabilitation will be considered for inclusion in the study.  People meeting the inclusion criteria will be invited to participate in the study, will receive comprehensive information about the study and will be asked to sign a written consent form. Once recruited to the study each participant will be randomly assigned to the immediate start ‘intervention’ group or the wait-list ‘control’ group. 
A study statistician, independent of the trial, will be responsible for generating (via computer) the allocation sequence and the block size-randomisation. Once the participant is enrolled, the chief investigator will inform the study statistician, of the participant’s name (and their ambulation status for stratification) via email.  The independent person will email the allocation, to immediate intervention or control group, to the investigator. The dates of recruitment and randomisation email correspondence will be kept to provide an audit trail of randomisation and allocation concealment.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be generated by a computer program using permuted blocks with stratification by ambulation status.

A set of random numbers will be used to create an allocation sequence for use by the chief investigator.  Potential selection bias will be reduced by using random block sizes, between 2 and 4, and the investigator will be blinded to the size of each block. A study statistician, independent of the trial, will be responsible for generating (via computer) the allocation sequence and the block size-randomisation.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Stepped wedge</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The primary outcome measure for the randomised controlled trial is the FIM total.  A mixed effects analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) will be conducted including the fixed effects factor variables Group (factor levels: intervention, control) and Time (factor levels: Assessment- baseline and Assessment- 6 weeks) and a random effect term (random intercept) for Study Individual. Participants baseline FIM scores will be used as the covariate in the analysis. The primary intervention effect will be estimated along with 95% confidence interval levels. The confidence interval limits will be utilised to draw inference concerning the average intervention effect in the underlying target population: confirmatory Interpretation of the study findings will be conducted with respect to clinical relevance of the range of possibly true mean effects (confidence interval limits) rather than based on p-values. The threshold for clinical relevance will be set at 3 points on the FIM total.   

The primary efficacy analysis will follow the intention-to-treat principle, utilising sensitivity analyses employing best and worst-case missing value imputation scenarios, to assess robustness of the study findings. 

Other outcome measures will be compared between groups using the same approach.  Further supportive analyses will include additional baseline covariates in the ANCOVA model to account for different routes of intervention assignment such as orthotic prescription and medical management. An exercise intensity-covariate (Phone FITT or number of HEP sessions) will be included in analyses to account for any varied exercise levels.

The mixed-effect ANCOVA models will be used to explore the relationships between the outcome measures at different time points and clinical parameters, in order to predict which clinical parameter may influence performance on outcome measures.

Significance will be recorded as p&lt;0.05. Statistical analysis will be performed using STATA (Version 13; Stata Corporation, College Station, Texas, USA).

An earlier study that investigated the effect of multidisciplinary inpatient rehabilitation compared to no intervention found a significant mean FIM total score change coefficient of 11.43 (SD=7.92) after a period of inpatient rehabilitation as compared to no intervention (Milne et al 2012). With the change coefficient of 11.43 and a standard deviation of 7.92, with use of a two-tailed alpha of 0.05 and power of 0.90 the sample size required is 12 people per group. To allow for dropout, 16 people will be recruited to each group. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>8/08/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>8/08/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>7/11/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>32</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Kingston Centre - Cheltenham</hospital>
    <postcode>3192 - Cheltenham</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Sarah Milne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Physiotherapy Department
Kingston Centre
Warrigal Road
Cheltenham VIC 3192</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Murdoch Childrens Research Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Bruce Lefroy Centre, Murdoch Childrens Research Institute, Flemington Road, Parkville, VIC 3052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Monash University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>School of Psychological Sciences, Monash University, Wellington Road, Clayton, VIC 3800</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Friedreich Ataxia is a degenerative disease impacting on the ability to mobilise and reducing independence in daily activities. This study aims to determine if outpatient rehabilitation improves or maintains functional ability and quality of life, as compared to a wait-list control. 

People attending a specialist multidisciplinary Friedreich ataxia clinic and who would benefit from rehabilitation, will be invited by the clinic to participate in this study. Consent will be gained at the Kingston Centre

Participants appropriate for outpatient rehabilitation will be randomised into an intervention group or a control group, using a computer program. Intervention will be accelerated standard-care, rehabilitation including physiotherapy, aquatic physiotherapy and exercises, and the wait-list period of the program will generate the control group. The duration of rehabilitation will be 6 weeks, and rehabilitation will be provided three times per week. A home exercise program will provided for participants in both groups to complete for six weeks following the rehabilitation program.

Outcome measures will examine quality of life, disease progression, performance of daily life activities, mobility and spasticity. These measures will be taken at baseline, pre and post-rehabilitation, and six weeks following rehabilitation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Health Human Research Ethics B</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Directorate
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Road
Clayton, VIC, 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/07/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>12134B</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/05/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sarah Milne</name>
      <address>Bruce Lefroy Centre, Murdoch Childrens Research Institute, Flemington Road, Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9265 7641</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sarah.milne@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sarah Milne</name>
      <address>Bruce Lefroy Centre, Murdoch Childrens Research Institute, Flemington Road, Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9265 7641</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sarah.milne@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sarah Milne</name>
      <address>Bruce Lefroy Centre, Murdoch Childrens Research Institute, Flemington Road, Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9265 7641</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sarah.milne@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sarah Milne</name>
      <address>Bruce Lefroy Centre, Murdoch Childrens Research Institute, Flemington Road, Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9265 7641</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9265 2378</fax>
      <email>sarah.milne@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>