<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368917">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/07/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/09/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000915550</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A study of peginterferon-alfa intervention to achieve hepatitis B surface antigen loss in chronic hepatitis B participants under long-term viral suppression with nucleoside analogues </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Peg-interferon-alfa to achieve HBsAg loss in chronic hepatitis B
under long-term viral suppression with nucleoside analogues</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>TRUST</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil Known
</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Hepatitis B</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is: Addition of peginterferon-alpha (pegIFNa)  to existing nucleos(t)ide analogues (NA) therapy in patients who are on long-term NA therapy and have achieved viral suppression but not clearance.
The dose of pegIFNa is 180mcg subcutaneously weekly. 

The patients recruited into the trial will already be on an antiviral , either entecavir or tenofovir. The usual doses of enetcavir and tenofovir in standard of care are  0.5-1 mg daily (oral tablet) for entercavir and  300 mg daily (oral tablet) for tenofovir. At the time of entry into the trial, patients are on either entecavir or tenofovir, not both oral agents at the same time. 

Duration of pegIFNa: 24 weeks or 48 weeks depending on stopping rules
Stopping rules :
There will be stopping rules at week 24. These are:
* HBV DNA detectable at week 24
* HBsAg &gt; 1000 IU/mL at week 24
* HBsAg decline &lt;0.1 Log IU/mL at week 24

The doses of entecavir or tenofovir will be the doses provided as part of standard of care which are the existing dose that the participants are already on. Patients will be on only one oral agent- either tenofovir or entecavir.
There will be no changes to NA doses from what the participant is already taking at the time of entry into the trial.
The dose of entecavir is 0.5 mg- 1 mg . this is determined by the treating clinician depending on renal function (patients with renal impairment are on a smaller dose). the dose of entecavir will not be changed for the purposes of the trial.

If  the pegIFNa intervention is futile (based on HBV viral load and HBsAg titres), treatment will be ceased. Patients who have responded will receive consolidation pegIFNa for up to 48 weeks
Mode of administration: subcutaneous injection of interferon, oral tablets for NA 
strategies used to monitor adherence to the intervention: counting drug tablets , history taking from the patient</interventions>
    <comparator>Patients not suitable or refusing pegIFNa will be our control group
Control group will consist on patients who are continuing existing NA therapy </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in HBsAg titre during antiviral therapy (pegIFNa plus NA therapy)
measured using the Roche Elecsys assay. This measures the quantitative
hepatitis B surface antigen (qHBsAg) titers expressed in international
units/mL (IU/mL).</outcome>
      <timepoint>48 weeks after commencement of treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean change in HBsAg titre over time, as estimated from the area
between the baseline value and the curve of HBsAg titre divided by the duration of treatment</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 24 weeks of treatment, 48 weeks of treatment and 24 weeks post treatment cessation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rates of HBsAg loss at 24 weeks and end of treatment (48 weeks)
This will be determined using the Roche Elecsys assay</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 24 and 48 weeks of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In patients who stop therapy, the rate of serological (serum HBsAg, HBeAg level) relapse will be evaluated
This will be determined using the Roche Elecsys assay</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 24 and 48 weeks after commencement of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Exploratory analysis of clinical / laboratory predictors for serological
responses will be performed (baseline and on-treatment factors will be considered). This will included performing bioplex assays which detects the phenotypic variation of the surface antigen.</outcome>
      <timepoint>48 weeks of treatment and 24 weeks post treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rates of HBsAg seroconversion at 24 weeks of treatment, 48 weeks of treatment and 24 weeks . This will be assessed using the Roche Elecsys assay</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 24 weeks of treatment, 48 weeks of treatment and 24 weeks post treatment cessation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In patients who stop therapy, the rate of  virological (serum HBV DNA level) relapse will be evaluated
This will be assessed using the Roche Elecsys assay
</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 24 and 48 weeks after commencement of treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>*Informed consent
*Age &gt; 18 years
*HBsAg-positive
*HBeAg negative
*On entecavir or tenofovir &gt; 18 months
*HBV DNA level undetectable for &gt; 18 months
*HBsAg &lt; 1000 IU/mL
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Severe liver disease which excludes them from peg-interferon</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients will be recruited from outpatients clinic</concealment>
    <sequence>NA</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>There will be clear stopping rules at week 24:
1.	HBV DNA detectable
2.	HBsAg &gt; 1000 IU/mL
3.	HBsAg decline &lt;0.1 Log IU/mL
4.	HBsAg seroconversion (stop after 8 weeks consolidation)


Those not suitable or unwilling to be treated will be recruited as the observational/control arm.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The sample size was determined using power calculation.
The mean change in HBsAg level and the standard deviation of HBsAg in patients on long term NA therapy (using previous clinical trials), was used to estimate parameters for power calculation. With 50 patients, we calculate &gt; 80% power to detect a 0.5 log10 IU/mL change in HBsAg level at 48 weeks, with a standard deviation of 1 log10 IU/mL. The level of significance was set to 0.05, with a 2-sided test.

The primary efficacy variable, change in log10 HBsAg, will be analysed with ANCOVA using the baseline log10 HBsAg as the covariate. Similarly for change in log10 HBsAg during follow-up. The mean change in log10 HBsAg with be analysed with ANOVA. HBsAg loss and HBsAg seroconversion will be analysed with logistic regression.

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/09/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne) Ltd - Fitzroy</hospital>
    <hospital>Box Hill Hospital - Box Hill</hospital>
    <hospital>Western Hospital - Footscray</hospital>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Clayton campus - Clayton</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - City campus - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
    <postcode>3181 - Prahran</postcode>
    <postcode>3065 - Fitzroy</postcode>
    <postcode>3128 - Box Hill</postcode>
    <postcode>3011 - Footscray</postcode>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
    <postcode>3050 - Royal Melbourne Hospital</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Peter Angus</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Liver Transplant and Gastroenterology
Austin Health
145 Studley Rd Heidelberg 3084 Victoria</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Gilead</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Gilead Sciences - Australia
Level 1, 128 Jolimont Road
East Melbourne 3002
Victoria Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Bristol-Myers Squibb</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Bristol-Myers Squibb
Level 2, 4 Nexus Court, Mulgrave, VIC, 3170</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Alex Thompson</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of Gastroenterology
Level 4 Daly Wing
St Vincent's Hospital
44 Victoria Parade
Fitzroy 3065</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a study to see if add-on peginterferon-alfa (pegIFNa) can help lose hepatitis B surface antigen in patients who have 
chronic hepatitis B and treated with longterm nucleotide analogue therapy.
We hypothesize that in participants under long term viral suppression with potent oral therapy nucleoside analogues, addon pegIFNa will reduce serum HBsAg levels and lead to HBsAg loss.
We propose an investigator initiated proof of concept study to evaluate
the efficacy of add-on pegIFNa therapy in patients who have been treated with tenofovir or entecavir for at least 18 months
Those suitable will be treated with a minimum 24 weeks of pegIFNa. Depending on their response, pegIFNa therapy may be extended for up to 48 weeks or ceased. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>NA</trialwebsite>
    <publication>NA</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>We have sought sponsorship of the study from Gilead and Bristol-Myer Squibb. The sponsorship will include providing medication only.  This is an investigator driven study.</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's ethics committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Governance Unit
Level 5, Mary Aikenhead Building
27 Victoria Parade
Fitzroy 
VIC 3065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/07/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Angus</name>
      <address>Liver Transplant Unit Austin Health 145 Studley Rd, 
Heidelberg 3084
Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94965353</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter.angus@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Zina Valaydon</name>
      <address>Department of Gastroenterology
Level 4 Daly Wing 
St Vincent's Hospital
44 Victoria parade, Fitzroy
VIC 3065</address>
      <phone>61431608006</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>zina.valaydon@svha.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Angus</name>
      <address>Austin Health 145 Studley Rd, Heidelberg 3084 Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94965353</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter.angus@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>