<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="456">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/09/2005</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/09/2005</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12605000403639</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Phase 1/2 Multicenter, Randomized, Placebo-Controlled Double-Blind, Parallel Group Study to Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of Two Regimens of a Candidate Topical NF kappaB Decoy in the Treatment of Adults with Mild to Moderate Atopic Dermatitis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 1/2 Multicenter, Randomized, Placebo-Controlled Double-Blind, Parallel Group Study to Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of Two Regimens of a Candidate Topical NF kappaB Decoy in the Treatment of Adults with Mild to Moderate Atopic Dermatitis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Atopic dermatitis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dermatological conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Eligible subjects will be randomized (flipping a coin) to either active treatment or placebo (placebo means the vehicle gel without the active ingredient), which will be applied per protocol either once or twice daily for a total of 4 weeks.  A 2 week follow-up period will follow the treatment period.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the safety of once-daily (qd) and twice-daily (bid) topical application of NF kappaB Decoy in adult patients with mild to moderate atopic dermatitis</outcome>
      <timepoint>Evaluated at each study visit.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the tolerability of once-daily (qd) and twice-daily (bid) topical application of NF kappaB Decoy in adult patients with mild to moderate atopic dermatitis</outcome>
      <timepoint>Evaluated at each study visit.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To maTo make a preliminary evaluation of the efficacy of qd and bid topical application of NF kappaB Decoy in adult patients with mild to moderate atopic dermatitis.ke a preliminary evaluation of the efficacy of qd and bid topical application of NF kappaB Decoy in adult patients with mild to moderate atopic dermatitis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Evaluated at each study visit.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Subjects in good health, who: 1. Sign an informed consent; 2. Have been given a diagnosis of atopic dermatitis as defined by: Pruritus, Eczematous dermatitis (acute, subacute, chronic) involving at least current or prior flexural lesions with chronic or relapsing course, Early age of onset (prior to 10 years of age, by history), Personal or family history of atopy; 3. If receiving antihistamines, are on a stabilized dose, and expect to maintain this dose throughout the study; 4. Are females or males of reproductive potential who are compliant in using adequate birth control or are females or males not of reproductive potential. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Have concomitant dermatologic or medical condition(s) which may interfere with the investigator⿿s ability to evaluate the subject⿿s response to the study drug; 2. Have immunocompromised status (such as known human immunodeficiency virus infection); 3. Have an active intercurrent infection, a clinically significant clinical laboratory test abnormality, or any poorly controlled medical condition; 4. Have applied any topical medication (including corticosteroid, calcineurin inhibitor, topical H1 and H2 antihistamines, topical antimicrobials, other medicated topical agents) or herbal preparation to the area selected for treatment within 1 week of the Day 1 visit, have used any systemic antibiotic within 1 week prior to the Day 1 visit; have used any systemic treatment for atopic dermatitis (including systemic corticosteroids, nonsteroidal immunosuppressants, or treatment with light) within 4 weeks prior to the Day 1 visit; have used an investigational drug for any reason within 4 weeks of the Day 1 visit; have used intranasal and/or inhaled corticosteroids at doses &gt; 2 mg prednisone equivalent per day within 4 weeks of the Day 1 visit; or have used immunosuppressive or immunomodulating drugs such as etanercept, alefacept, or infliximab within 16 weeks prior to Day 1; 5. Have a history of hypersensitivity or allergic reactions to parabens or any other ingredient in the vehicle formulation; 6. If female, are pregnant or lactating, or intend to become pregnant during the study period; 7. If male, have a female partner who is pregnant or lactating, or who intends to become pregnant during the study period.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation with numbered containers</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomization schedule was generated using SAS procedure PROC PLAN (SAS Version 8.2). To keep the balance of the treatment allocation, randomization list was generated using blocks to allocate active QD, active BID, placebo QD, and placebo BID groups.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1 / Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2005</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Corgentech Inc.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Corgentech Inc.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary />
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Julie Pompili</name>
      <address>Level 10
606 St Kilda Road
Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 95196852</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 95196888</fax>
      <email>julie.pompili@quintiles.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Julie Pompili</name>
      <address>Level 10
606 St Kilda Road
Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 95196852</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 95196888</fax>
      <email>julie.pompili@quintiles.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>