<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="1364">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/10/2002</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/10/2002</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000474550</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Skin exposure during conventional phototherapy in preterm infants: A Randomised Controlled Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of full body exposure compared to partial body exposure on total serum bilirubin (TSB) levels at 24-hours of treatment in preterm infants with physiological jaundice receiving phototherapy.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>None</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Perinatal Trials Registry: PTR395</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Preterm infants with physiological jaundice</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Complications of newborn</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Infants were randomised to either treatment (partial body exposure) or control groups. Infants in the treatment group were partially clothed wearing only disposable nappies and posturally supported in nested positions with boundary aids.
All infants wore eye protection whilst receiving phototherapy. Infants were nursed in double walled isolettes 35cm beneath Dulux L 36 W/12 Daylight Phototherapy Lamps, with a constant irradiance of 6uWcm-2/nm (4 white tubes) at a wavelength of 425nm-475nm. Phototherapy was delivered continuously except during infant hygiene and cares when lamps were temporarily switched off. Total serum billirubin levels were collected and measured at 24-hour intervals in infants until below treatment range using Cockington criteria. Lamps were checked prior to use and during the study and maintained at an irradiance of 6uWcm-2/nm using a standard photometer (Minolta/Air-Shields Fluoro-Lite meter 451). Infant axilla temperature was measured with infant hygiene 3-6 hourly, and the attending neonatologist managed fluids.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group (full body exposure) infants were nursed naked, posturally unsupported in prone and supine positions to maximise the surface area exposed to phototherapy.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome was mean total serum bilirubin  percentage change to the end of 24-hour treatment after trial entry. The mean total serum bilirubin percentage change was calculated for the 24-hour change from the baseline level at trial entry.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Total serum bilirubin levels were measured after the first 24-hours of treatment by direct spectrophotometry (Reichert Unistat-Bilirubinometer) by laboratory technicians blinded to the study group.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of rebound jaundice confirmed by total serum bilirubin and requiring an additional course of phototherapy treatment and number of infants continuing to receive phototherapy treatment based on total serum bilirubin levels.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at the end of each 24-hour period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parental stress and mother-infant interaction was assessed using the Parenting Stress Index-Short Form.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 24-hours of ceasing phototherapy. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The mean total serum bilirubin percentage change in infants who remained within phototherapy range.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After the first 24-hour period was also examined at 48 hours completed phototherapy treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Any episode of patent ductus arteriosus, skin rashes or dehydration (infant requiring intra-venous fluid resuscitation) was recorded.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Preterm infants in the special care nursery at the Royal Brisbane Womens Hospital with birthweight &gt;1500grams, gestation &gt;36 weeks and non-haemolytic hyperbilirubinemia (direct Coombs test negative, no blood group incompatibility) determined by total serum bilirubin levels to be within phototherapy range using Cockington criteria were considered for enrollment.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>36</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Weeks</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>37</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Weeks</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Infants with congenital abnormality or known coexisting pathologies or need for respiratory support.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>A scientist not otherwise involved in the trial computer-generated permuted block randomisation allocation to treatment groups. Infants were assigned to either group using sequentially numbered sealed opaque envelopes.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>none</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/1999</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Kimberly-Clark Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The Royal Brisbane Women's Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Phototherapy is effective in reducing total serum bilirubin (TSB) levels in preterm infants with physiologic hyperbilirubinemia. There is a clear relationship between the dose of phototherapy and the decline in the TSB level. To maximise the dose at a given irradiance, preterm infants are routinely nursed naked whilst receiving conventional overhead phototherapy. It is unclear if efforts to maximise the efficacy of phototherapy by increasing skin exposure achieve an optimal therapeutic response with a minimum of side effects. Conventional phototherapy lights are effective in reducing TSB but not without potential side-effects including increased insensible water loss, persistent patent ductus arteriosus, blunted post-prandial increase in mesenteric blood flow and the possibility of increased cerebral blood-flow velocity. Reports of poor infant regulation and disorganised behavior, early discontinuation of breastfeeding and parental anxiety may be more common side-effects with consequences extending beyond the neonatal period. 
	Such concerns have led clinicians to consider a "kinder, gentler" approach to managing physiologic hyperbilirubinemia in the preterm infant, which includes supporting early positive parent-infant interactions. Providing a supportive environment may facilitate well-regulated infant behavior and positive interactions with parents without prolonging physiologic hyperbilirubinemia and phototherapy treatment. We undertook this study to assess the effect of different skin surface area exposed to conventional overhead phototherapy on TSB levels at 24-hours of treatment. An additional purpose of the study was to obtain information on the incidence of episodes of rebound jaundice, duration of phototherapy, parent-infant interaction and parental stress as well as mean TSB percentage change of infants who continued to require phototherapy treatment after the initial 24-hour period.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Brisbane Women's Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>RWH99/06</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Margo Anne Pritchard</name>
      <address>Perinatal Research Centre. The University of Queensland.  Ned Hanlon Building Level 6. The Royal Brisbane Women's Hospital.Herston. 4209.</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3636 5172</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3636 1769</fax>
      <email>mpritchard@somc.uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Margo Anne Pritchard</name>
      <address>Perinatal Research Centre
Level 6
Ned Hanlon Building
The University of Queensland
The Royal Brisbane Women's Hospital
Herston QLD 4209</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3636 5172</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3636 1769</fax>
      <email>mpritchard@somc.uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>