<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343286">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/08/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/08/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000826943</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Long term follow up of patients with severe Systemic Sclerosis (SSc) and Rheumatoid Arthritis (RA) who have undergone Haematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation (HSCT).</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A retrospective review of patients with severe Systemic Sclerosis and Rheumatoid Arthritis who have had a Haematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant as a means of immunosuppression to achieve disease remission - assessment of safety and efficacy of response.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Systemic Sclerosis and Rheumatoid Arthritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Autoimmune diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Autologous stem cell transplantation (HSCT) is a procedure that is usually used to give high doses of chemotherapy to patients with blood cancers followed by stem cell infusion so that a new blood and immune system can regrow. Over the last 15 years, HSCT has become much safer. At the same time, numerous lines of evidence converged to suggest that a small number of patients with very severe immune conditions could also be treated by HSCT. The evidence came from patients who had chemotherapy for co-existant blood tumours and had an auto-immune disease (AID). Often these patients had prolonged remissions of their AID. In addition, there are animal models of HSCT in AID showing prolonged remissions with HSCT. AID patients suffer from an immune attack on their own body causing tightening of the skin (Systemic Sclerosis), spinal cord and brain problems (Multiple Sclerosis) and multiple other organs in the body (Systemic Lupus Erythromatosis, Crohn's disease and vasculitis). In some cases, people with auto-immune conditions can die from their condition, particularly when the disease has failed multiple treatments. It is possible to select the very sickest AID patients for more intensive therapy with HSCT and provide them with a lasting remission. 

The procedure requires a two step process. The first step requires chemotherapy with one dose of a drug called cyclophosphamide (2grams) intravenously along with GCSF 10ug/kg subcutaneously x 7 days (a hormone to stimulate the bone marrow) to help stem cells to be collected via a vein in your arm. Within 2 months, patients come into hospital for the second step. Here patients will have high doses of intravenous chemotherapy (cyclophosphamide 200mg/kg over 4 days along with Anti-thymocyte globulin 10mg/kg x 4 days) that also intensely suppresses the immune system. After these 4 days the patient's own stem cells are transfused so they can re-grow a new immune system and protect the patients from the toxic effects of the chemotherapy. It takes about 14 days for the new stem cells to grow and then we will follow patients carefully over the next 10 years (initially every 3-6 months but after 1 year just annually) to see if the immunosuppression controls your auto-immune disease and that there are no long term sequelae.</interventions>
    <comparator>There is no comparator arm.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and efficacy of HSCT. 

Initial contact of telephone advising patients of centre which will invite them into study followed by letter with consent form, health assessment questionnaire and visual analogue scales. 
The patients will be required to fill out a series of questionnaires to assess the impact of RA or SSc on their quality of life. 
 i. Health Assessment Questionnaire (HAQ)
 ii. Visual Analogue Scales (VAS)
 iii. Modified Rodnan Skin Score (For SSc patients only)
Subsequent to this, patients will be asked to come to Haematology outpatient to have their medical history taken and to answer questions related to the safety of past HSCT, particularly recurrence of their diseases, development of secondary tumour such as lymphoma, and risk of infection due to immunosuppressants.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Safety and efficacy of HSCT at 5 and 10 years post HSCT.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Immune reconstitution of T cell subsets post HSCT with a particular emphasis on thymic output.

The methods for this analysis include:
40mL of blood sample will be collected by venapuncture during the clinical session. The side effect of this procedure is minimal. However, there could be some bruising around the venapuncture site. Infection of the site is very rare. 
Aliquots of whole blood will be used for phenotypic analysis of lymphocytes subsets (CD4, CD8, CD45RA, CD45RO). In particular VBeta oligoclonal population will be assessed using anti-VB2, 3, 12, 13 monoclonal antibodies. 
PBMNC will be prepared using Ficoll density centrifugation. Normal stem cells will be compared for CLP phenotype with RA/SSc stem cell collections (Tissue Bank Consent H00/045). Antibodies used for CLP surface markers are CD7, CD34, Cd38, c-kit.
ELISA for inflammatory cytokines such as IL-7, TNF- alpha will be performed.
If time is permitting, TREC level in the blood samples will be measured using competitive PCR method to assess the thymic output. 
If time is permitting, culture of RA stem cells using OP-9 cell line comparing RA and normal common lymphoid progenitor populations (previously submitted under study H06/148).</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months, 1 year and 2 years post HSCT</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients who have undergone HSCT for severe Systemic Sclerosis and Rheumatoid Arthritis at St Vincents Hospital between 1996 and 2010.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients unwilling to sign consent forms and those who have a psychiatric condition preventing them from participating.
Severe end organ damage such as:
Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction &lt;50%
DLCO/VA &lt; 50%
Right Atrial pressure &gt; 45mm Hg</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients who have previously had a stem cell transplant at this hospital for Systemic sclerosis and Rheumatoid Arthritis are invited to participate by a letter. If they accept the invitiation they are then invited to attend the hospital to sign the informed consent form.</concealment>
    <sequence>No randomisation is required in this study.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>22/08/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>25</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>St Vincents Hospital, Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Victoria St,
Darlinghurst,
NSW 2010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>St. Vincents Hospital, Sydney.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Victoria St,
Darlinghurst,
NSW 2010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Haematology Department, St Vincents Hospital, Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Victoria St,
Darlinghurst,
NSW 2010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>St. Vincents Clinic Foundation</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Victoria St,
Darlinghurst,
NSW 2010</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This trial aims to assess the safety and efficacy of Haematopoietic stem cell transplant (HSCT) for severe systemic sclerosis (SSc) and rheumatoid arthritis (RA). HSCT is reserved for patients with severe disease who have failed multiple previous therapies. Numerous lines of evidence have suggested that HSCT may have a role to play in these autoimmune conditions as a way of suppressing the inflammatory condition but also by possibly re-educating the immune system, especially, the thymus. This study aims to assess if the HSCT has been successful ( as measured by standard response criteria) and safe in these patients. Secondly it aims to assess if the thymus has a role to play in those who respond. This will be assessed by flow cytometry on stored specimens (collected with informed consent via a tissue bank consent form) with a particular emphasis on oligoclonal T cell subsets.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Nil at present for this component of the study. The RA patient clinical data was published in 2002 as below:
Moore J, Brooks P, Milliken S, Biggs J, Ma D, Handel M et al. A prospective randomised trial comparing CD34 selected versus unmanipulated haemopoietic stem cell transplantation for severe resistant rheumatoid arthritis. Arthritis and Rheumatism, 46: 2301-2309, 2002.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincents Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>St Vincents Hospital
Victoria St,
Darlinghurst,
NSW 2010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/07/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1/08/0106</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/06/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>John Moore</name>
      <address>Haematology Department,
St. Vincents Hospital, 
NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>61 2 83822677</phone>
      <fax>61 2 83822645</fax>
      <email>jmoore@stvincents.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>John Moore</name>
      <address>Haematology Department,
St. Vincents Hospital, 
NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>61 2 83822677</phone>
      <fax>61 2 83822645</fax>
      <email>jmoore@stvincents.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>John Moore</name>
      <address>Haematology Department,
St. Vincents Hospital, 
NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>61 2 83822677</phone>
      <fax>61 2 83822645</fax>
      <email>jmoore@stvincents.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>