<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369533">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/10/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/11/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001174572</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Feasibility Study of a Brief Telephone-based Cannabis Intervention </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A brief telephone-based intervention for treatment seeking cannabis users with the primary outcome of cannabis use frequency</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1175-8732 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cannabis Use Disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Brief (60 minute) one session telephone-based intervention based on motivational interviewing and cognitive behavioural therapies. This call will be made by the counsellors working at the Cannabis Information Helpline who will receive intervention training. In addition to this training, adherence will be monitoring by the Helpline supervisors as well as by research staff who will listen to approximately 20% of the sessions. </interventions>
    <comparator>Do-It-Yourself workbooklet on reducing cannabis use</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Frequency of cannabis use assessed by telephone interview with research staff</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cannabis-related problems assessed by telephone interview with research staff</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severity of cannabis dependence assessed by telephone interview with research staff</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>18+ Years of age
Recent cannabis use
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Unable to give informed consent (no mental health concerns)
Dependence on other illicit substances
Recent cannabis use treatment</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The researcher who determined if a subject was eligible for inclusion in the trial was unaware, when this decision was made, to which group the subject would be allocated. Allocation assignment will be determined after screening for inclusion criteria and gaining consent through central randomisation by computer software which will present the outcome one at a time when activated.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>The quantitative and qualitative data in this study will be analyzed using IBM SPSS Statistics, Release Version 22. 
To address the study aim of determining whether intervention participants show a greater reduction in treatment outcome measures compared to the control group, an independent structure, linear model, Generalised Estimating Equation (GEE) approach to repeated measures analysis will be used to test between-group differences. GEE is appropriate for measuring the relationship between outcome variables and corresponding predictor variables over time. Prior to longitudinal modelling, two-tailed bivariate zero-order correlation analyses will be conducted between the treatment outcome variables and an indicator for the presence of any external cannabis treatment or pharmaceutical medication (dichotomous items that will be recorded at baseline and follow-up assessments). In the case of a statistically significant association, these indicator variables will be included into analyses as covariates. Similarly, to determine which baseline participant characteristics were associated with variance in cannabis-related treatment outcomes, a second series of two-tailed bivariate zero-order correlation analyses will be conducted. Due to an expected large number of comparisons for these analyses, Bonferroni corrections will be made to control for the probability of false positive findings. Finally, participant drop out in follow-up assessments will be tested prior to analysis to determine that the relevant data was missing completely at random (MCAR) using Littles MCAR test.

As this is a pilot feasibility trial, a power analysis was not performed to determine sample size. Instead, the expected number of participants (n=100) was determined (based on the call rate to the Helpline and the project timeline) to allow for an assumed uptake of approximately 15%.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/11/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>7/12/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/04/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>30/06/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>19</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Stopped early</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>30/09/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis>Data analysis is complete</dataanalysis>
    <withdrawnreason>Participant recruitment difficulties</withdrawnreason>
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Peter Gates</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>UNSW Randwick Campus NDARC
Building R1 Level 1, 22-32 King St
Randwick NSW 2031, Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Government Department of Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Health
GPO Box 9848,
Canberra ACT 2601, Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Cannabis use disorder is the most common illegal substance use disorder in the general population and demand for assistance from health professionals is increasing internationally (EMCDDA, 2014). Despite this, only a minority of individuals with the disorder seek treatment. Study on the barriers to cannabis treatment has highlighted the importance of providing additional outpatient treatments that are specific to cannabis (Treloar et al., 2007) and delivered to the individual in a way which unwanted contact with other illicit drug users can be avoided (Gates, Copeland, Swift and Martin, 2012). 

To date no Australian data exists on the efficacy of such a telephone-based intervention with a specific focus on an illicit drug. This study has been funded by the Australian Government Department of Health to examine whether a brief telephone-based counselling service can act as a feasible treatment option for people with problems with their cannabis use. The results from the randomised trial may validate decisions to support the funding of telephone based services or introduce similar services for other illicit drugs.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of NSW HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>UNSW, Kensington Campus, NSW, 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/12/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HC15744</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/12/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Peter Gates</name>
      <address>UNSW Randwick Campus NDARC
Building R1 Level 1, 22-32 King St
Randwick NSW 2031Australia </address>
      <phone>+61293850269</phone>
      <fax>+61293850201</fax>
      <email>p.gates@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Peter Gates</name>
      <address>UNSW Randwick Campus NDARC
Building R1 Level 1, 22-32 King St
Randwick NSW 2031Australia </address>
      <phone>+61293850269</phone>
      <fax>+61293850201</fax>
      <email>p.gates@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Peter Gates</name>
      <address>UNSW Randwick Campus NDARC
Building R1 Level 1, 22-32 King St
Randwick NSW 2031Australia </address>
      <phone>+61293850269</phone>
      <fax>+61293850201</fax>
      <email>p.gates@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Peter Gates</name>
      <address>UNSW Randwick Campus NDARC
Building R1 Level 1, 22-32 King St
Randwick NSW 2031Australia </address>
      <phone>+61293850269</phone>
      <fax>+61293850201</fax>
      <email>p.gates@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>