<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373536">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/08/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/09/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001285347p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomized controlled trial to determine the efficacy of Perx, an iPhone application for promoting medication adherence.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomized controlled trial to determine the efficacy of Perx, an iPhone application for promoting medication adherence among sufferers of chronic disease. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None.</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cardiovascular disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Chronic kidney disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Hypertension</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All participants will be educated on the importance of medication compliance as per standard care at baseline. Participants randomised to the 'Perx' intervention group will be asked to download the Perx iPhone application (app). They will be trained in its use during a 45 minute face-to-face session at baseline with the research nurse. The participants will enter their personal and medication information (name, dose, timing) into the app under the supervision of their physician or research nurse. Once this is completed, users will begin to receive reminders each time their medication is due based on the information they entered initially. If they verify they have taken their medication at the scheduled time they will be eligible to receive an opportunity to win an intermittent reward through a gamified interaction. Users get rewarded with a game every time they verify that they've taken their medication at the right time. To verify medication adherence, the app requests the user to take a real-time, in-app photo of their medication within plus/minus an hour of when their medication is due. This photo cannot be taken from their existing gallery. The photos are saved on the Perx server and checked by Perx app designers. 
The frequency of games is dependent on their schedule (typically 1-3 times per day). This game is a short mini-game on screen such as a virtual ring toss or a match-3 scratch card. They play by using their phone screen. 
Participants in the Perx group will use the Perx app for the 12 month duration of the study. </interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will receive education on medication compliance as per standard care at baseline.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine efficacy of Perx on medication adherence through manual pill counts (number of pills prescribed vs number of pills taken will be compared).</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months since baseline. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the acceptability of Perx to participants using a four item Perx Acceptability Questionnaire. This questionnaire has been designed specifically for use in this study. </outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 6, 9 and 12 months since baseline. 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the acceptability of Perx to participants' physicians using a two item Perx Physician Questionnaire. This questionnaire has been designed specifically for use in this study. </outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months since baseline. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the effect of using Perx on hospitalization rates. Hospitalisation data will be collected by study medical officers in consultation with the participant or through access to patient medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months since baseline.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the effect of using Perx on pathological measures of cardiovascular disease. A venous blood sample will be collected and analysed for blood lipid levels. </outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 6, 9 and 12 months since baseline. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the effect of using Perx on pathological measures of Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus. A venous blood sample will be collected and analysed for fasting blood glucose, HbA1c and lipid levels. </outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months since baseline. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the effect of using Perx on pathological measures of chronic kidney disease. A venous blood sample will be collected and analysed for blood microalbumin and serum creatinine. </outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 6, 9 and 12 months since baseline. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the effect of using Perx on pathological measures of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease by performing lung function tests. </outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 6, 9 and 12 months since baseline. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Diagnosed with at least one of the following chronic conditions: type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM), heart failure, hypertension (HT), chronic kidney disease (CKD), chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD)
- Taking a minimum of three different medications
- Able to visit the clinic monthly over a 12 month period.
- iPhone accessibility 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Absence of a chronic disease controlled with medication 
- Unable to correctly use the Perx app or an iPhone 
- Inability to read and write English
- Participants may also be excluded, if in the opinion of the study Investigators, they have some other condition or disorder that may adversely affect the outcome of the study or the safety of the Participant (e.g. psychiatric illness, substance abuse)
- Unable to commit to the appointment schedule or perform the tasks required in the study
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomisation will occur centrally using computer software. </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by FileMarker Pro computer software. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample Size Determination: At least 124 participants (62 in each group) will be required to detect a 20% difference in medication compliance between groups (assuming a 40% standard deviation and 20% drop-out).

Statistical Analyses: Data will be analysed for normality using the Shapiro-Wilk test. For analysis of differences between treatments, an analysis of co-variance (ANCOVA), or the non-parametric equivalent will be used. For within group changes, repeated measures ANOVA will be used. As well as an analysis of completers (those that attend the final visit), an intention to treat (ITT) analysis will also be included. For the ITT analysis, dropouts will be treated using a variety of sensitivity analyses.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/04/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>124</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/04/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>Concord Repatriation Hospital - Concord</hospital>
    <hospital>Liverpool Hospital - Liverpool</hospital>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>2139 - Concord</postcode>
    <postcode>2170 - Liverpool</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Sydney </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Sydney
Camperdown NSW 2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Sydney Local Health District </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 11, KGV Building
Missenden Road
CAMPERDOWN NSW 2050</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Liverpool Hospital </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Corner of Elizabeth and Goulburn Streets
Liverpool NSW 2170  </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Concord General Repatriation Hospital </othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Hospital Rd
Concord NSW 2139</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Previous research has shown that poor adherence to cardiovascular medications is associated with a 10-40% greater risk of related hospitalisations and a 50-80% greater risk of death. The World Health Organization has suggested that increasing medication adherence may actually have a far greater impact than any specific medical treatment.  

Tools for promoting medication adherence might improve the benefits of prescribed medications and management of chronic diseases. Meanwhile, medication adherence is difficult not only to measure precisely but also to improve with a tool that patients would like to engage and operate. The TEXTCARE program, recently initiative by The George Institute for Global Health, found that SMS reminders doubled the odds of patients with chronic illnesses taking their medications correctly. A lot of smartphone applications for increasing medication adherence have been developed, however, most of their functions were limited to reminding patients of their medication schedule and never tested properly in randomized clinical trials.

This study will investigate Perx, a newly developed iPhone application designed to encourage users to take their medications. Participants will be randomised to the Perx group or standard care group, who will receive education on medication compliance. Participants in the Perx group will be asked to download the app and will enter their personal and medication details under the supervision of their physician or research nurse. Once this is completed, users will receive regular reminders when their medication is due, and if they verify they have consumed their medication at the scheduled time they will be eligible to receive an opportunity to win an intermittent reward through a gamified interaction. The verification process can be useful to measure precise medication adherence rate and the instantaneous rewarding can help motivate and reinforce patients to adhere their medication. Participants in the Perx group will be encouraged to use the app for the 12 months duration of the study. 

We aim to determine the efficacy of Perx on medication adherence. We hypothesise that the Perx app will increase medication compliance among those suffering chronic disease/s and will improve clinical outcomes and hospitalisation rates.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Local Health District, RPA division</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Ethics and Governance Office (REGO)
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
Camperdown NSW 2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/07/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Mackenzie Fong</name>
      <address>The Boden Institute 
Level 2 Charles Perkins Centre D17
University of Sydney NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 86271931</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 86270141</fax>
      <email>mackenzie.fong@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Mackenzie Fong</name>
      <address>The Boden Institute 
Level 2 Charles Perkins Centre D17
University of Sydney NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 86271931</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 86270141</fax>
      <email>mackenzie.fong@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ian Caterson</name>
      <address>The Boden Institute 
Level 2 Charles Perkins Centre D17
University of Sydney NSW 2006</address>
      <phone> +61 2 8627 1944</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 86270141</fax>
      <email>ian.caterson@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Mackenzie Fong</name>
      <address>The Boden Institute 
Level 2 Charles Perkins Centre D17
University of Sydney NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 86271931</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 86270141</fax>
      <email>mackenzie.fong@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>