<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371203">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001159448p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of low glucose load diet on glycaemic control in patients with cystic fibrosis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of low glucose load diet on glycaemic control in patients with cystic fibrosis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cystic fibrosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other endocrine disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human Genetics and Inherited Disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Cystic fibrosis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Description: This study is a prospective, single arm pilot study. Patients with impaired glucose tolerance at the Royal Prince Alfred (RPA) Cystic Fibrosis (CF) Clinic will be eligible to participate in this study. Baseline measures relating to anthropometric measures, lung function, inflammatory status, quality of life (QOL) usual dietary intake via 3 day food record, oral glucose tolerance test (OGTT) and blood glucose levels (BGLs) via continuous glucose monitoring (CGM) or glucometer will be measured. Dietary education about low glucose load (GL) dietary modification will then be provided to the patient. 

There will be a one month follow up to review anthropometry, lung function, dietary intake, BGLs and food satisfaction survey. A three month follow up will review anthropometry, lung function, dietary intake, BGLs, QOL, inflammatory markers and food acceptability survey.  

Dietary prescription: Participants will be prescribed a diet based on current recommendations for CF energy and protein requirements. Education will be provided at the RPA CF clinic by the clinic dietitian. The baseline food record will be used to guide education of the participant about a low GL diet.  Sample meal plans will be provided demonstrating substitution of low GI dietary products and recommended meal and snack pattern, lists of low GI products will be provided and education about the GI tick for recognition of low GI products on food labels.. 

Measurement of subject compliance: This pilot study aims to assess feasibility of patient compliance with low GL dietary recommendation in this patient group.  Compliance will be assessed based on calculation of glycaemic index of diet based on 3 day food record.  </interventions>
    <comparator>Nil</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence to a low GL diet in CF measured by 3 day food records, QOL. questionnaire (CFQ-R) and patient food acceptability questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 day food records will be reviewed at baseline, 1 month and 3 months.
QOL and patient food acceptability questionnaires will be performed at baseline and 3 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Glycaemic control measured by 3 day glucometer or CGM readings, HbA1c and OGTT</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 day glucometer or CGM readings will be measured at baseline, 1 month, 3 months
HbA1c and OGTT will be performed at baseline and 3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lung function as measured by FEV1 and FVC</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1 month and 3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nutrition status as measured by weight, height and BMI</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1 month and 3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients with CF attending the RPA CF clinic with OGTT results within the previous 3 months of impaired glucose tolerance (IGT) i.e. 2-hour glucose of 7.8-11.1mmol/L. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants belonging to any of the following criteria will be excluded from the study:
Women who are pregnant or planning a pregnancy
Patients who have had a lung transplant because of prednisone effect
Patients who are identified to have cystic fibrosis related diabetes (CFRD), insulin and oral hypoglycaemic medications
Patients who have had a pulmonary exacerbation within one month of recruitment according to FUCHS criteria 
Patients requiring nutrition support via nasogastric tube or gastrostomy
People who do not have the level of English required to complete QOL questionnaires
People with significant cognitive impairment, mental illness, or involved in an illegal activity who are unfit for participation 
Patients who are on &gt;7.5mg daily doses of prednisone 
Patients with gastrointestinal dysfunction including DIOS and gastroparesis.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>10</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Academic Department of Adolescent Medicine</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Academic Department of Adolescent Medicine
Children's Hospital at Westmead
Cnr Hawkesbury Road and Hainsworth Street
Locked Bag 4001
Westmead NSW 2145</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Rd 
Camperdown NSW 2050</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Concentrated carbohydrate loads are often used in CF to help meet increased energy requirements and could have a role in the poor glycaemic control observed in CF. The aim of this project is therefore to establish the feasibility of implementing a low glycaemic load, high calorie dietary management plan for patients with CF and impaired glycaemic status (IGT). A secondary aim is to assess the effect of a low GL diet on clinical outcomes of glycaemic control, lung function and weight.

Patients with IGT at the RPA CF clinic will be eligible to participate in this study. Weight, glycaemic control, lung function, diet history and quality of life will be measured at baseline and also at 3 months, following dietary intervention of a low GL diet. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>SLHD Ethics Review Committee (RPAH Zone)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Ethics and Governance Office (REGO)
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
CAMPERDOWN NSW 2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/08/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Kate Steinbeck</name>
      <address>Academic Department of Adolescent Medicine 
Children's Hospital at Westmead
Cnr Hawkesbury Road and Hainsworth Street
Locked Bag 4001
Westmead NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9845 2517</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kate.steinbeck@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Natasha Armaghanian</name>
      <address>Academic Department of Adolescent Medicine 
Children's Hospital at Westmead
Cnr Hawkesbury Road and Hainsworth Street
Locked Bag 4001
Westmead NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9845 2517</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>natasha.armaghanian@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Natasha Armaghanian</name>
      <address>Academic Department of Adolescent Medicine 
Children's Hospital at Westmead
Cnr Hawkesbury Road and Hainsworth Street
Locked Bag 4001
Westmead NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9845 2517</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>natasha.armaghanian@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>