<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371575">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/11/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/11/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001593426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The determinants of corneal curvature in healthy participants and in cataract surgery patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Analysis of corneal refractive power changes associated with accommodation, corneal biomechanics and cataract surgery</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cornea after Cataract surgery</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All the investigations involved in this study are non-invasive and non-contact procedures that are routinely used in clinical ophthalmology. 

The first part of the study comparative diagnostic trial to compare clinical aberrometers. Participants will be examined on 4 different types of aberrometers (as described below) at a single half an hour long visit This part will commence in the first instance, approximately a month before the first cataract patient is assessed. 

The second is non randomized observational trial to examine changes in corneal curvature associated with ocular accommodation assessed with corneal tomography and aberrometry and the relative influence of corneal biomechanics. Healthy participants will undergo corneal tomography and aberrometry, (Galilei 2  and Orbscan) and corneal biomehanics (Corvis-ST), as described below. The assessments will only take up to half an hour at a single visit. The second part will run concurrently with the third part of the study.

The final and arguably the most important part, is observational cohort study  to characterise the relationship between corneal incision architecture and corneal biomechanics on two different incision sizes of surgically induced astigmatism following cataract surgery, using clinical aberrometry, corneal accommodation using tomography and corneal biomechanics. In this part, all the patients will be assessed at least a few hours once before the surgery, and 3 times after the surgery, which is standard of care for patients after cataract surgery. Assessments only take about 30 additional minutes more than their regular follow-up visit.

Visual acuity: Vision will be assessed using a letter chart. This is done as a standard of care for all the patients undergoing cataract surgery.

Slit-lamp biomicroscopy: Standard eye examination will be performed using a special microscope called a slit-lamp, which is used in every eye clinic room.

Aberrometry and tomography: The curvature of the front part of eye will be measured using special instruments known as the Orbscan II, Zywave, OPDIII, iDesign and Galilei 2 (only Galilei 2 for the third part). The instruments are used to assess the shape, refractive properties and thickness of cornea. 

Biomechanical properties of cornea: The biomechanics (rigidity and flexibility) of the front part of your eye will be measured with a special instrument called Corvis-ST. This instrument also uses a gentle air puff for measurement. It does not cause any discomfort or pain to the eyes.

Optical Coherence Tomography: The instrument produces high resolution images the front of the eye with a special laser camera called anterior segment - Optical Coherence Tomographer (AS-OCT).

Specular microscopy: This technique is used to evaluate the health of corneal endothelium. The endothelial cell density will be quantified after obtaining clinical images.

</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relationship between biomechanics of the cornea, using Corvis-ST, and surgically induced astigmatism, using tomographer (Galilei 2), following cataract surgery.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patients will be assessed at least a few hours before surgery, and, one day, one month and three months after the surgery. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relationship between biomechanics of the cornea and  wound architecture following cataract surgery. Biomechanics of the cornea will be measured by Corvis-ST and wound architecture by anterior segment optical coherence tomographer (AS-OCT) and Specular microscopy.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patients will be assessed at least a few hours before surgery, and, one day, one month and three months after surgery.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Topographical maps and corneal higher order aberrations obtained by 4 different aberrometers (Zywave, OPDIII, iTrace and Galilei 2) will be compared. This is a composite secondary outcome.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This is the first part of the study. Three months from the commencement of the project. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Part 1 and 2:  	Ametropia &lt;1D (defocus or astigmatism). Participants can be healthy volunteers.
Part 3:	Patients scheduled for routine cataract surgery.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Part 1:  	Ametropia &gt;1D (defocus or astigmatism)
Part 1, 2 and 3:	Pre-existing ocular pathology or previous ocular surgery, Contact lens use,
		Strabismus, Previous ocular trauma
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>All statistical analysis will be completed using the R statistical software package and Microsoft Excel.  
Part 1: The difference in total and individual HOA will be investigated using basic plots to visualise the raw data, investigate outliers and the spread of the data. Analysis of variance (ANOVA) and multivariate analysis of variance (MANOVA) and canonical discriminat analysis will be used to compare HOA with post hoc tests where required.  Non-normal data will be analysed using non-parametric tests.
Part 2: Statistical analysis will include analysis as described for Part 1 in addition to correlation and regression analysis to investigate the relationship between Corvis-ST data and accommodation induced corneal tomographic changes.
Part 3: Surgically induced astigmatism (SAI) will be calculated for all patients based on pre and post-operative tomography data using vector analysis.  The relationship between SIA magnitude, corneal biomechanics, and corneal wound architecture will be modelled using regression analysis.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection />
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>21/11/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/11/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>180</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/02/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Auckland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Ophthalmology
New Zealand National Eye Centre
Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences
The University of Auckland,
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Auckland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Ophthalmology
New Zealand National Eye Centre
Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences
The University of Auckland,
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Following removal of a cataract, an intraocular lens (IOL) is implanted during surgery to enable refractive correction of the eye to maximise vision following surgery. Selecting the correct model and refractive power of the IOL is critical to achieve the appropriate refractive target.  A sub-optimally selected IOL will typically result in post-operative residual refractive error, and decreased unaided vision that may be associated with falls and decreased quality of life in many cases. 

Refractive error is caused by the combined effect of the cornea and the lens and can be divided into lower order aberrations (LOA) and higher order aberrations (HOA).
To select an appropriate model IOL to minimise total spherical aberration and accurate assessment of corneal aberration is required prior to surgery. The first part of this study will compare four clinical aberrometers that use different optical principals to assess HOA in the eye.

Ocular accommodation is the process by which the crystalline lens adjusts the focus of the eye through conformational changes. A new strategy to accurately assess corneal curvature changes will be developed using 3D printed modifications to existing clinical tomographers and aberromters to allow corneal curvature assessment at near and distance fixation. Using this strategy even small changes in the corneal periphery should be quantifiable to definitively establish of the role of the cornea in accommodation. This is the second part  of the project.

Cataract surgery typically involves small incisions placed in the peripheral cornea to extract the cataract using phacoemulsification, and to enable implantation of an intraocular lens following cataract removal.  The size of the corneal incisions depends on the IOL that is selected and the lens cartridge that is required for insertion. 

The final part of this study will aim to characterise the relative contribution of wound architecture and corneal biomechanics on surgically induced astigmatism. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Health and Disability Ethics Committees
Ministry of Health
Freyberg Building
20 Aitken Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/09/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HDEC 16/CEN/132</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/09/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>James McKelvie</name>
      <address>Department of Ophthalmology
New Zealand National Eye Centre
Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences
The University of Auckland,
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142
</address>
      <phone>+64 9 923 6712</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>james@mckelvie.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>James McKelvie</name>
      <address>Department of Ophthalmology
New Zealand National Eye Centre
Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences
The University of Auckland,
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142
</address>
      <phone>+64 9 923 6712</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>james@mckelvie.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>James McKelvie</name>
      <address>Department of Ophthalmology
New Zealand National Eye Centre
Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences
The University of Auckland,
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 9 923 6712</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>james@mckelvie.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Stuti Misra</name>
      <address>Department of Ophthalmology
New Zealand National Eye Centre
Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences
The University of Auckland,
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 9 923 6582</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.misra@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>