<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363920">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/04/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/04/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000390785</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Telerehabilitation: A novel approach to the provision of Heart Failure Rehabilitation Programs</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>To determine the effects of telerehabilitation program on functional capacity, muscle strength, quality of life, balance and falls in people with chronic heart failure, compared with standard heart failure rehabilitation program.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic heart failure (CHF)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The telerehabilitation intervention will be delivered to participants in their own homes via a computer, broadband internet connection and DVD media. The program design will mirror the conventional heart failure rehabilitation program; comprising of education and exercise sessions.  Participants will be able to access the internet twice per week (for 60 minutes each time) over the 12-week duration to guide them through a combined aerobic and strength exercise program.  Adherence to the program will be monitored through number of attendance, exercise diary and web cam.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants in the conventional group will attend a centre-based heart failure rehabilitation program, comprising of education and exercise sessions.  Each 12-week program will consist of 60 minutes of aerobic and strength exercise, delivered twice per week.   The program is a group-based exercise class delivered by a physiotherapist and a nurse, designed specifically for people with heart failure.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The six minute walk test (6MWT) is a standardised submaximal measure of exercise capacity frequently used in people with CHF.   This is a self-paced walking test on a 30 metre track.  Two tests will be performed at baseline and the data from the best test will be used in analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, post-program and 3-month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Grip strength for each hand will be measured three times with a hand-held dynamometer.  The best measurement of the three tests will be used in the analysis.   Similarly, quadriceps muscle strength will be measured three times with a hand-held dynamometer and the best measurement will be used in the analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, post-program and 3-month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Balance Outcome Measure for Elder Rehabilitation (BOOMER) is a clinically applicable measure of standing balance.  This tool comprises of the following commonly used balance tests: timed up and go test, functional reach, static balance and step test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, post-program and 3-month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time taken to walk 10 metres will be recorded.  This test will be undertaken at usual and fast pace, and each will be performed twice to reduce a learning effect.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>This test will be administered at baseline, post-program and at 3-month follow-up visits.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life will be measured using the Minnesota Living with Heart Failure Questionnaire (MLWHFQ).  This disease-specific quality of life questionnaire contains 21 questions with scores ranging from 0 to 105, determining the key physical, emotional, social and mental dimensions of quality of life.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>The MLWHFQ will be provided to patients for completion at baseline, post-program and 3-month follow-up visits.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>EQ-5D is a standardised instrument for use as a measure of health outcome.  Applicable to a wide range of health conditions and treatments, it provides a simple descriptive profile and a single index value for health status that can be used in the clinical and economic evaluation of healthcare.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>The EQ-5D will be provided to patients for completion at baseline, post-program and 3-month follow-up visits.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Frequency and severity of urinary incontinence in people with CHF will be measured by the Revised Urinary Incontinence Scale (RUIS). </outcome>
      <timepoint>The RUIS will be provided to patients for completion at baseline, post-program and 3-month follow-up sessions.  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The experience of and satisfaction with the telerehabilitation program, will be measured using semi-structured interviews with participants. The Client Satisfaction Questionnaire 8 (CSQ-8) will be adapted to determine the level of satisfaction in the telerehabilitation group compared with the conventional group.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Interviews will only be conducted in the telerehabilitation group post-program.  CSQ-8 will be administered to both groups post-program.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A cost analysis of telerehabilitation compared with conventional care will be performed.  This consists of direct and indirect costs.</outcome>
      <timepoint>post-program.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Telerehabilitation assessment - Validity data will be established by comparing video-based telerehabilitation assessments with face-to-face assessments, in particular the 6MWT, the timed up and go test and grip strength.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Telerehabilitation assessment will be conducted in the telerehabilitation group post-program.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The system usability scale will also be used to rate a participants experience with the telerehabilitation assessment. </outcome>
      <timepoint>This survey will be given to the telerehabilitation group post-program, after the telerehabilitation assessment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients over the age of 18 previously admitted to hospital who:
- Have a primary diagnosis of 'chronic heart failure'.
- Have been started on medical therapy for heart failure.
- Have broadband internet access at home
- Are able to provide signed written informed consent.	
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Live in a nursing home or care facility
- Have limited written or verbal English language skills
- Are unable to secure a supervisor for exercise sessions
- Fail to satisfy the safety criteria 
- Poor cognition or reduced ability for self care
- Physical limitations that prevent participation in exercise
- Severe hypertrophic obstructive cardiomyopathy
- Any of the exclusion criteria listed by American College of Sport Medicine (ACSM) guidelines 2010 for exercise prescription in a cardiac population.
- Inability or refusal to sign informed consent
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All patients with a hospital admission for management of heart failure at The Prince Charles Hospital (Brisbane, Australia) and the Princess Alexandra Hospital (Brisbane, Australia) will be screened by heart failure physiotherapists and invited to participate in the study according to the inclusion and exclusion criteria.  Participants, who satisfy the inclusion criteria, provide written informed consent and complete the initial assessment will be randomly allocated to the telerehabilitation or conventional rehabilitation group.  Allocation will be concealed through the use of numbered, opaque, sealed envelopes and will be maintained at a central location in order to maintain independence of the randomisation process from project staff. </concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>A blinded assessor will undertake all pre- and post-program patient outcome measures.  Due to the nature of the interventions, neither subject nor treating therapist blinding will be possible.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>22/04/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>25/06/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>19/06/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>48</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>53</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>25/02/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Prince Charles Hospital - Chermside</hospital>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <postcode>4032 - Chermside</postcode>
    <postcode>4102 - Woolloongabba</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Prince Charles Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Rode Road, Chermside, QLD 4032</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Princess Alexandra Hospital Research Foundation and Private Practice Trust Fund </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Ipswich Road, Woolloongabba, Brisbane, QLD 4102.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Queensland Health Health Practitioner Research Scheme </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 6, Department of Health Building, 147 - 163 Charlotte Street, Brisbane, QLD 4000.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Prince Charles Hospital Foundation Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Rode Road, Chermside, QLD 4032</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Health Professional Scholarship, National Heart Foundation of Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Heart Foundation of Australia
Research Program
Level 12, 500 Collins Street,
Melbourne VIC 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Princess Alexandra Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Physiotherapy Department, Ipswich Road, Woolloongabba, QLD 4102</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The University of Queensland</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Physiotherapy Department, School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences, St Lucia, QLD 4072</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This randomised controlled trial will evaluate the effectiveness of a 12-week heart failure rehabilitation program that is delivered into the homes of patients via telerehabilitation (Telerehabilitation Group) compared to a 12-week program delivered in the face-to-face manner (Conventional Group).</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Prince Charles Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Prince Charles Hospital, Metro North Hospital and Health Services, Administration Building, Lower Ground, Rode Road, Chermside QLD 4032</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/07/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/12/QPCH/86</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/06/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Jared Bruning</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
The Prince Charles Hospital
Rode Road
Chermside
Brisbane QLD 4032</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3139 4443</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3139 4082</fax>
      <email>jared_bruning@health.qld .gov.au  </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Jared Bruning</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
The Prince Charles Hospital
Rode Road
Chermside
Brisbane QLD 4032</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3139 4443</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3139 4082</fax>
      <email>jared_bruning@health.qld .gov.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Rita Hwang</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
Princess Alexandra Hospital
Ipswich Road
Woolloongabba QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3176 2111 pager 1415</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3176 6495</fax>
      <email>Rita_Hwang@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Rita Hwang</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
Princess Alexandra Hospital
Ipswich Road
Woolloongabba QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3176 2111 pager 1415</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3176 6495</fax>
      <email>Rita_Hwang@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>