<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372684">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/04/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/04/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000568314</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effects of a brief reminiscence task on mood for older adults living in residential aged care. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effects of a brief reminiscence task on mood for older adults living in residential aged care. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Mood Disorders </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other public health</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study aims to investigate the impact that a brief instrumental reminiscence intervention has on mood, hopefulness and mastery for older adults living in residential aged care. Using a pre-test/post-test experimental design the study explores the impact that a reminiscence task has on mood, hopefulness and mastery using the following instruments: 
- The Positive and Negative Affect Scale (PANAS) (Watson, Clark &amp; Tellegan, 1988)
- Adult Hope Scale (AHS) (Snyder, et al. 1991)
- Pearlin Mastery Scale (Pearlin et al, 1981)
- Memories of Mastery Experiences Scale (Bhar, Brown &amp; Beck 2007) 

The research will be conducted face to face with individual participants using a standardise reminiscence script for the experimental condition and a current events script for the control condition. Both conditions will be conducted by the student investigators. Participants are asked general questions about their personal and family history. Such questions refer to participants work and schooling history, early family environment, and relationships with parents and siblings. The purpose of these questions is not to elicit comprehensive information about the participants history but rather to prime participants to think about their past, thus creating a psychological climate involving the recollection of memories. For participants in the intervention condition, these questions create a context for asking more specific questions about mastery related experiences (i.e., the mastery memory activation task). This discussion should take approximately 10 minutes. 

The research will be conducted in residential aged care facilities in Victoria and the Australian Capital Territory. </interventions>
    <comparator>The control condition involves talking about a current event and is delivered by the student investigators. Participants are asked general questions about current events, NOT related to their personal and family history. The questions will cover topics related to families, environment, education, work and children. The purpose of these questions is to provide an active control for the introductory questions in the reminiscence condition. This discussion should take approximately 10 minutes. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in mood as measured by the Positive and Negative Affect Scale (PANAS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change in mood after the intervention as compared to baseline.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in hopefulness as measured by the Adult Hope Scale (AHS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change in hopefulness after the intervention as compared to baseline.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in mastery as measured by the Pearlin Mastery Scale. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Change in mastery after the intervention as compared to baseline. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Memories of mastery experience as measured by the Memory of Mastery Experiences Scale (MOMS: Bhar, Brown, &amp; Beck, 2007).</outcome>
      <timepoint>directly after the intervention </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>To be eligible for the study, participants must (a) be living in a residential aged care facility, (b) be at least 65 years old, (c) demonstrate adequate cognitive functioning (as indicated by a score of 24 or more on the Mini Mental Status Examination). </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Potential participants who appear unable to participate in screening procedures, as assessed by the interviewer due to health, cognitive  or language related limitations will not be eligible for participation. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed envelopes </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomised table created by computer software </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/09/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/09/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Swinburne University of Technology </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>John Street, Hawthorn Victoria 3122</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Swinburne University of Technology </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Faculty of Health, Arts and Design, Swinburne University of Technology, Mail H24, Hawthorn VIC 3122</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The current study aims to explore the benefits of a brief reminiscence task on mood for older adults living in residential aged care. The reminiscence task involves remembering past positive memories and recalling past experiences where the participant had to solve a problem. Previous research with community samples suggests that thinking about these meaningful experiences leads to improved mood and feelings about the future and oneself. Research has not yet investigated if positive outcomes occur for older adults living in residential aged care.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Swinburne's Human Research Ethics Committee (SUHREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/01/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>SHR Project 2016/185</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Sunil Bhar</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health, Arts and Design, Swinburne University of Technology, Mail H24, Hawthorn VIC 3122</address>
      <phone>6139214 8371</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sbhar@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jencie Castles </name>
      <address>Faculty of Health, Arts and Design, Swinburne University of Technology, Mail H24, Hawthorn VIC 3122</address>
      <phone>61433474231</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jcastles@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jencie Castles </name>
      <address>John Street, Hawthorn Faculty of Health, Arts and Design, Swinburne University of Technology, Mail H24, Hawthorn VIC 3122</address>
      <phone>61433474231</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jcastles@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jencie Castles </name>
      <address>Faculty of Health, Arts and Design, Swinburne University of Technology, Mail H24, Hawthorn VIC 3122</address>
      <phone>61433474231</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>694941x@student.swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>