<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="485">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/09/2005</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/09/2005</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12605000447651</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparison between single dose oral prednisolone and oral dexamethasone in the treatment of croup: a randomised, double-blind clinical trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised, double-blind clinical trial comparing the
effectiveness of single dose oral prednisolone versus single dose oral 
dexamethasone in reducing the severity of croup in children presenting to 
the Emergency Department, as measured by changes in the Westley croup 
score.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Croup (laryngotracheobronchitis)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Three steroid preparations are being compared in a 
double-blinded, randomised trial. Children aged 6 months 
to 6 years presenting to Brisbane's Mater Childrens' Hospital Emergency 
Department (MCH ED) with moderate severity croup (defined in the study as 
Westley croup score 2-7) are randomised to one of three treatment groups: 
oral dexamethasone 0.6mg/kg, oral dexamethasone 0.15mg/kg, or prednisolone 
1mg/kg.  After administration of their oral dose of steroid treatment, the 
children are observed in the ED for up to 4 hours, with hourly measurement 
of their Westley croup score.  Subjects are able to be discharged from ED 
earlier than 4 hours if much improved; if they are still significantly 
symptomatic at 4hrs they may be admitted to the ward for observation.  
Salvage therapy such as nebulised adrenaline can be provided at the 
discretion of the treating doctor.  The subject's discharge or admission is 
at the discretion of the ED clinician looking after the patient.  If the 
child re-presented to a health care facility following the index 
presentation, additional treatment was at the discretion of the treating 
doctor.  A phone call was made to the parents of enrolled children 1-2weeks 
after their index presentation to discuss the duration of the child's croup 
symptoms, need for medical review with or without further steroids, and to 
discuss any noted side effects from the steroid preparation.</interventions>
    <comparator> Dexamethasone 0.6mg/kg was assigned as 
the standard to compare other treatment assignments. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>None</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Magnitude of reduction in Westley croup score, a derived cumulative severity-duration index using area under curve.  Enrolled children are randomly provided with one of three oral steroid preparations.  The Westley croup score is a validated observational score which scores for level of consciousness, cyanosis, stridor, air entry and retractions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The Westley croup scores are then recorded hourly for up to 4 hours on a standardised pro forma data collection sheet.  Scoring 
continues until the child is discharged from the ED due to clinical improvement or 4hours has elapsed.  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of reduction in Westley croup score, a derived cumulative severity-duration index using area under curve.  Enrolled children are randomly provided with one of three oral steroid 
preparations.  The Westley croup score is a validated observational score which scores for level of consciousness, cyanosis, stridor, air entry and retractions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The Westley croup scores are then recorded hourly for up to 4 hours on a standardised pro forma data collection sheet.  Scoring 
continues until the child is discharged from the ED due to clinical improvement or 4hours has elapsed.  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(1) Rate of return to medical care with ongoing croup and further treatment with steroids.</outcome>
      <timepoint>In the week following initial presentation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(2) Rate of hospitalisation and number of co-interventions (including salvage therapy with nebulised adrenaline)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Incurred during index presentation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(1) Children aged 6 months to 6 years presenting to the ED with a croup syndrome, clinically defined by hoarseness, barking cough and stridor.(2) Westley croup score of 2 or greater(3) Parents available for phone follow-up 1 week after study enrolment.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Months</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>6</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(1) Chronic respiratory disease (excluding asthma)(2) Severe croup (defined as Westley croup score of &gt;/= 8)(3) Nebulised adrenaline prior to or on arrival to the ED(4) Steroids within the preceding week(5) Known allergy to steroids(6) Varicella or exposure to varicella within the previous 3 weeks(7) Known immunodeficiency.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The 3 steroid preparations were prepared by MCH research pharmacists who were not involved in the design, conduct, analysis and write-up of the study. All study preparations were prepared as clear solutions in equivalent therapeutic concentrations per millilitre, such that each child would receive an identical volume of preparation regardless of treatment assignment allocated to the child.  Each treatment (designated A, B, and C) were placed in identical dispensing containers in the study centre. All recruiting and study staff were blinded to the treatment assignments. Codes were kept securely in Pharmacy and could only be revealed to manage adverse sequelae such as anaphylaxis resulting from study participation. Codes will only be revealed to the study investigators after data has been completely analysed to reduce interpretation bias.  Children are randomised to receive one of the 3 study preparations in a dose of 0.2ml/kg with 0.2ml containing either 1mg prednisolone, 0.15mg of dexamethasone or 0.6mg of dexamethasone.  The study agents were flavoured to standardise taste and palatability.</concealment>
    <sequence>A pre-specified sample size of 33 patients per treatment group was calculated prior to study commencement. Based on previous similar comparative studies, this sample size would power the study to detect the presence of a true difference (defined as 20% or greater) between treatment assignments, if it existed, to a probability of 80%. A randomised computer generated list of the numbers 1, 2 and 3 (representing treatment A, treatment B and treatment C respectively) provided treatment allocations to an equal proportion of subjects in each group.  Every</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3 / Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/07/2004</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Mater Childrens' Hospital Department of Paediatric Emergency Medicine</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Mater Childrens' Hospital Department of Paediatric Emergency Medicine</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary />
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Mater Childrens' Hospital ED</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr A Fifoot</name>
      <address>Department of Emergency Medicine
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Herston Rd
Herston QLD 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 36368111</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 36368732</fax>
      <email>fifoota@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr A Fifoot</name>
      <address>Department of Emergency Medicine
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Herston Rd
Herston QLD 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 36368111</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 36368732</fax>
      <email>fifoota@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>