<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365744">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/04/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/04/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000426684</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A pilot randomized clinical trial of physiotherapy intervention in early hip osteoarthritis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Is a physiotherapy intervention feasible for people with early hip osteoarthritis?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>HIPO</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Early hip osteoarthritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Interventions
Each participant will be treated by experienced physiotherapists who will be trained and proficient in both interventions (physiotherapy; education). 

Physiotherapy
The physiotherapy intervention will be delivered in 8 sessions each of 30 minutes duration over 3-months (1/week for 4 weeks, 1/fortnight for 8 weeks). This consists of (i) manual hip joint and soft tissue mobilisation and stretching; (ii) hip muscle retraining; (iii) trunk muscle retraining; (iv) functional, proprioceptive and sports- or activity- specific retraining; (v) enhancing physical activity; and (vi) education. Education will consist of topics including exercise, weight loss if appropriate, and appropriate stretching. This will be provided during thwe physiotherapy session. Based on our pilot data, the treatment will be tailored according to each patients clinical presentation (e.g. strength, pain severity, sporting and functional needs), presence of co-morbidities (e.g. back and other lower-limb pain or pathology) and progressed based on response to exercise load, thus maximising the training effects. The physiotherapist will supervise exercises during each visit for 15 minutes. A home exercise program will be performed independently at home 4 times per week for 60 minutes per session. An exercise manual will be produced and made accessible to each participant. Participants will complete a self report diary which will be checked at each visit and include adherence to home exercise program, use of medications and additional activity undertaken.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Education
In order to control for the psychosocial contact inherent with the physiotherapy treatment, the education group will encompass individualised health education sessions covering topics such as exercise, diet, weight loss and appropriate stretching, in a similar fashion to previously published clinical trials looking at physiotherapy management in older people with advanced hip OA. The information sheets will be modified to be appropriate for this younger age group. The control sessions will be provided with the same frequency and duration as the physiotherapy sessions. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome measure: Feasibility of full-scale RCT
Feasibility will be assessed by evaluating willingness of participants to enrol; number of eligible participants; recruitment rate; compliance with intervention, home exercises and log-book completion; and drop-out rate.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Treatment conclusion at 3 months post treatment commencement.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hip dysfunction and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (HOOS)-pain subscale.
This is a hip-specific patient reported outcome measure of pain.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 3 months from commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceived global change score 
This is a likert measure of patient reported perceived change between baseline and follow-up assessments.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 3 months from commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>International Hip Outcome Tool
This is a hip specific patient reported outcome measure which measures symptoms, job related activity, sporting activity and social activity.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 3 months from commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>HOOS-QoL subscale
This is a hip-specific patient reported outcome measure of quality of life.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 3 months from commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tampa Scale for Kinesiophobia. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 3 months from commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hip muscle strength and hip flexion and internal rotation range. This will be measured using methods which have been previously published and are reliable. Hip muscle strength will be measured using a hand held dynamometer. Hip flexion and internal range of motion will be an active measure measured with an inclinometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 3 months from commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>AQoL-4D. This is a generic questionnaire based measure of patient-reported quality of life.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 3 months from commencement of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion Criteria:
(i) aged 18-50 yr; (ii) arthroscopy for intra-articular hip pathology during the past 12 to 36 months; (iii) evidence of early-onset hip OA (defined as chondropathy greater than or equal to Outerbridge grade 1) at time of hip arthroscopy; (iv) hip-related pain &gt; 30 on a 100mm Visual Analogue Scale (VAS).
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion Criteria:
(i) pain that is not confirmed by physical examination of the hip; (ii) concurrent symptoms of hip bursitis or tendinitis; (iii) surgical complications including infection; (iv) planned lower limb surgery in the following 12 months (eg arthroplasty); (v) physical inability to weight-bear fully or undertake testing procedures; (vi) inability to understand written and spoken English. 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Potential participants will be identified by the surgeon, and invited to contact the Project co-ordinator. Volunteers will be screened via telephone interview, followed by a clinical examination to confirm eligibility. The randomisation schedule (permuted blocks of varying sizes), generated and maintained centrally by the University of Queensland, School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences, will be revealed via telephone following baseline assessment. The blinded researcher will perform outcome assessments at baseline and 3 months, and participants will be instructed not to divulge their group allocation to the assessor. The research group will access patient’s past medical and surgical records to obtain details of surgical intervention and pre-operative radiological findings.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation schedule (permuted blocks of varying sizes), will be generated and maintained centrally by the University of Queensland, School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>The primary outcomes measured at 3 months will include recruitment rate, compliance with all aspects of intervention and drop-out rate. Secondary outcomes will be analysed using linear mixed regression models, including their respective baseline scores as a covariate, subjects as a random effect, treatment condition as a fixed factor and the covariate by treatment interaction. Participant characteristics (e.g.; gender, age) will be included as covariates. We aim to detect the minimum clinically important improvement on this outcome as reported by Kemp et al.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/05/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>5/05/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>29/08/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>30/10/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>18</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>TAS</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>7000 - Hobart</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Health and Rehabiliation Sciences
St Lucia
QLD 4067</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Physiotherapy Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 437
Hawthorn BC
VIC 3122</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Bodysystem PL</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>38 Collins St
Hobart TAS 7000</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Hip osteoarthritis (OA) is associated with significant personal and societal burden, which is rising with increased life expectancy. Early hip OA is commonly seen during hip arthroscopic surgery, and can affect younger adults (age&lt;55 years) with peak work and family commitments. Whilst hip arthroscopy is commonly undertaken for pain associated with early hip OA, no studies have examined best practice for post-operative rehabilitation. An effective intervention for early-onset hip OA will potentially have great personal and societal impact. The primary aim of this study is to establish the feasibility of a randomised clinical trial (RCT) of physiotherapy, targeted to improve hip joint range and hip-related symptoms in early-onset hip OA. This study is a blinded pilot RCT conforming to CONSORT guidelines. Twenty people with early hip OA who had hip arthroscopy surgery six to 12 months previously will be recruited and randomized to the intervention group (individualized manual therapy, exercise therapy and education) or the control group (education only). Eight interventions will occur for both groups over three months, with outcomes collected at baseline and three months. Primary outcome measure - feasibility of a full scale RCT. Secondary outcome measures - symptoms, quality-of-life and range-of-motion. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Queensland Medical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Queensland
St Lucia
Queensland 4067</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/02/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>20130001553</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Kay Crossley</name>
      <address>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
University of Queensland
St Lucia
QLD 4067</address>
      <phone>+61733653008</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.crossley@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Joanne Kemp</name>
      <address>Bodysystem
38 Collins St
Hobart TAS 7000</address>
      <phone>+61362315991</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>joannekemp@bodysystem.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Kay Crossley</name>
      <address>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
University of Queensland
St Lucia
QLD 4067</address>
      <phone>+61733653008</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.crossley@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Joanne Kemp</name>
      <address>Bodysystem
38 Collins St
Hobart
TAS 7000</address>
      <phone>+61362315991</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>joannekemp@bodysystem.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>