<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362299">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/04/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/05/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000490875</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Is the healing rate in diabetes related foot ulcers improved with low frequency ultrasonic debridement versus non-surgical sharps debridement?  A randomised control trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of low frequency ultrasonic debridement therapy versus non-surgical sharps debridement on wound healing in diabetes related foot ulcers.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1129-4780</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes related foot ulceration.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other skin conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Low frequency ultrasonic debridement therapy. LFUD delivers a constant flow of saline through which low frequency ultrasound is delivered. The impact of the ultrasound in the saline close to the wound surface (either direct contact or held up to 1cm away) causes: 1. Acoustic streaming (steady current delivered in a fluid medium i.e. sterile saline) 2. Cavitation (imploding gaps in the fluid creating micro-shockwaves). In turn, these impacts result in three clinical effects: 1. Debridement 2. Bactericidal effects 3. Wound healing stimulatory effects Whilst low frequency ultrasonic debridement, can also be performed by podiatrists and wound clinical nurse consultants it differs from non-surgical sharps debridement as it is not dependent upon the clinicans skill to determine what tissue should be removed. Treatments are perfromed weekly until the wound is healed. The low frequency of the ultrasound transmitted through the liquid medium (sterile saline solution) selectively debrides the wound base, leaving healthy and viable tissue intact only removing infected and necrotic tissue thus making it safer for patients. Additionally, this treatment is less painful and has additional benefits when compared to non-surgical sharps debridement including that its action is also bactericidal and stimulates the phases of healing. This suggests an acceralated healing time for ulcers. Each treatment session take 60 minutes and includes assessment and treatment. LFUD is utilised for 30 seconds per centimetre square of the wound size, at its widest and longest points. This treatment will be utilised for the first 6 weeks from recruitment and then the ulcer will be reviewed to determine if there is a clinical indication to continue utilising the therapy.  If there is the indication to continue the therapy then no changes will be made.  If there is no clinical indication to continue the therapy then particpants will receive the control treatment, which is also standard practice, (Non-surgical sharps debridement) and will remain in the study.</interventions>
    <comparator>Non-surgical sharps debridement.

Standard practice for ulcer debridement by podiatrists and wound clinic nurse consultants is non-surgical sharps debridement.  Non-surgical sharps debridement depends upon the skill of the clinician and the ability for them to distinguish between healthy and necrotic tissue.  This treatment can often be painful and risks with treatment include bleeding, damage to healthy and vital tissue (e.g. nerves, tendon and ligaments) with a resultant loss in function.


Each treatment session take 60 minutes and includes assessment and treatment.  Sharps debridement is undertaken until as much necrotic and devitalised tissue has been removed from the wound bed, there is no time limit.  This treatment will be utilised until the wound has healed or is 100% epithelialised.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>This study aims to compare healing rates for diabetes related foot ulcers using non-surgical sharps debridement versus low frequency ultrasonic debridement.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Wounds will be measured following each treatment to determine total ulcer area in centimetres squared until the time of healing or completion of the study.  Percentage of necrotic tissue is no longer being included in this study.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Economic evaluation: cost effectiveness analysis of both direct and indirect health care costs will be determined at the completion of the study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week post final treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of complications that resulted from either method of ulcer debridement including: 
- Number of amputations required
- Number of surgical debridements required
- Number of infections developed</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week post final treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Wound pain assessment</outcome>
      <timepoint>All wounds will be assessed for pain using the visual analogue pain scale prior, during and after each treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost utility analysis using a quality of life tool EQ-5D-5L.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be conducted at the initial assessment, mid way through the study (at 3 months) and again at the end of the study (at 6 months or when healed, whichever occurs first) for each participant.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Equal to and greater that 30 years of age
- Able to provide informed consent
- Wounds greater than 1cm squared in total area
- Wounds present for greater than 1 month
- Vascular assessment: Palpable pedal pulses OR toe pressure equal to or greater than 45mmHg OR meeting stages 0 (asymptomatic), 1 (mild claudication) and 2 (moderate claudication at 200m) of the Rutherford Classification for peripheral arterial disease
- Infected ulcers being appropriately managed
- Ulcers meeting The University of Texas wound classification criteria: A1, A2, A3 (wounds of varying depth without infection or ischaemia) and B1, B2, B3 (wounds of varying depth with infection only)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>30</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Participants taking immunosuppressive medication 
- Known allergies to wound dressing products 
- Pre-existing ulcer pain preventing either type of debridement 
- Vascular assessment: meeting stages 3 (severe classification), 4 (rest pain), 5 (ischaemic ulceration not exceeding ulcer of the digits of the foot)  and 6 (severe ischaemic ulcers or frank gangrene) of the Rutherford Classification for peripheral arterial disease
- Dry gangrenous ulcers 
- Fungating ulcers 
- Malignant ulcers 
- Those meeting the University of Texas Wound Classification Criteria: A0, B0, C0, D0 (pre or post-ulcerative lesion with complete epithelialisation, with or without infection and ischaemia), C1, C2, C3 (wounds with varying depth and ischaemia only), D1, D2, D3, (wounds with varying depth with ischaemia and infection)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients with diabetes and foot ulcers that are referred to and treated by Podiatry at Southern Health will be recruited into this study. Only patients who meet the inclusion criteria will be invited to participate. These patients will be randomised into two groups. Group 1: Non-surgical sharps debridement and Group 2: LFUD. 

Standard initial podiatric assessment will occur including a neurovascular assessment, medical and surgical history, medications history, diabetes management and control history including Hba1c, footwear assessment, wound aetiology, duration and previous management. At this time, the patient will be informed about the research project and verbal and written consent will be obtained to participate in the study, if the patient meets the inclusion criteria.

Allocation will be concealed using opaque and sealed envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted block randomisation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The proportion of ulcers that are completed healed by the six month follow-up will be compared between groups using a logistic regression analysis approach with clustering of ulcer within participant.  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>26/06/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/12/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>4/06/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>108</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>13</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Stopped early</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/07/2015</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>8/08/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis>Data collected is being analysed</dataanalysis>
    <withdrawnreason>Participant recruitment difficulties</withdrawnreason>
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Clayton campus - Clayton</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Lucia Michailidis</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Podiatrist
Southern Health
Kingston Centre
Warrigal Rd
CHELTENHAM VIC 3192</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Lions John Cockayne Memorial Fellowship Trust Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Professor Barbara Workman 
Southern Health
Kingston Centre
Warrigal Rd
CHELTENHAM VIC 3192</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Ms Cylie Williams</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Allied Health Research Unit
Kingston Centre
Warrigal Rd
CHELTENHAM VIC 3192</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Associate Professor Terry Haines</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Allied Health Research Unit
Kingston Centre
Warrigal Rd
CHELTENHAM VIC 3192</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Shan Bergin </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Podiatry Department
Dandenong Hospital
135 David Street, Dandenong
VIC, 3175</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Jennifer Wong
Deputy Director of Diabetes Department</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Dandenong Hospital Diabetes Unit, 
Level 2, 105 David Street
Dandenong
VIC, 3175
Australia
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Low frequency ultrasonic debridement is a new treatment approved for use at Southern Health to treat diabetes related foot ulcers.
This project aims to assess if the use of low frequency ultrasonic debridement to treat diabetes related foot ulcers can achieve faster ulcer healing than standard non-surgical sharps debridement.
The current research around the use of low frequency ultrasonic debridement to treat diabetes related foot ulcers is positive and suggests that this therapy leads to faster healing and is potentially les painful that other therapies.  There is very little evidence comparing low frequency ultrasonic debridement with other ulcer debriding therapies for diabetes related foot ulcers.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>1. Michailidis L, Williams C, Bergin S, Haines T: Comparison of healing rate in diabetes-related foot ulcers with low frequency ultrasonic debridement versus non-surgical sharps debridement: a randomised trial protocol. Journal of Foot and Ankle Research 2014, 7.

2. Michailidis L, Kotsanas D, Orr E, Coombes G, Bergin S, Haines T, Williams C: Does the new low frequency ultrasonic debridement technology pose an infection control risk for clinicians, patients, and the clinic environment? Am J Infect Control 2016, 44:1656-1659.

</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Health HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Directorate 
Level 4, Main Block, 
Monash Medical Centre 
246 Clayton Road 
CLAYTON VIC 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/08/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>12101B</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/04/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Lucia Michailidis</name>
      <address>Podiatry Department
Southern Health
Kingston Centre
Warrigal Rd
CHELTENHAM VIC 3192
AUSTRALIA</address>
      <phone>+61 03 95942382</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lucia.michailidis@southernhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Lucia Michailidis</name>
      <address>Podiatry Department
Southern Health
Kingston Centre
Warrigal Rd
CHELTENHAM VIC 3192
AUSTRALIA</address>
      <phone>+61 03 95942382</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lucia.michailidis@southernhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Lucia Michailidis</name>
      <address>Podiatry Department Southern Health Kingston Centre Warrigal Rd CHELTENHAM VIC 3192 AUSTRALIA</address>
      <phone>+61 03 95942382</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lucia.michailidis@southernhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>