<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="81604">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/09/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/09/2006</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000411549</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Study of the effect of telmisartan on fibrosis in fatty liver disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A study of the safety and effects of  AT1 (angiotensin type 1) receptor blockade with the angiotensin receptor II antagonist, telmisartan, on hepatic fibrogenesis in patients  with non-alcoholic steatohepatitis (NASH).</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Non-alcoholic steatohepatitis (NASH)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Liver</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>12 months of oral telmisartan therapy (20-80mg per day). Participants will begin at 20mg and this dose will be increased in 20mg increments until the maximum tolerated dose is reached up to 80mg per day.</interventions>
    <comparator>No comparator.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary objective of this study is to assess the effects of blockade of the angiotensin type 1 (AT1) receptor with the angiotensin receptor II antagonist, telmisartan, on hepatic fibrogenesis in patients with non-alcoholic steatohepatitis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at 12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and tolerability of angiotensin type 1 (AT1) receptor antagonism in this patient group.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured during each study visit (initially weekly for the first month then 3 monthly) and at 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Effects of telmisartan on insulin resistance</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured during each study visit (initially weekly for the first month then 3 monthly) and at 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Stable body weight ( change of &lt; 3%) for the last 6 months Undergone 6 months of a diet and exercise regimen to help improve liver function tests Non diabetic or well controlled diabetes  Abnormal liver function tests in patients with fatty liver disease Haemaglobin &gt; 10g/dL Platelets &gt;70,000/mm3 Prothrombin time &lt; 2 sec prolonged  Serum creatinine &lt; .15 mmol/l</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Female patients of child bearing potential who are not using an accepted method of birth control (surgically sterile, intra-uterine device, oral contraceptives, hormone delivery systems, diaphragm or condom in combination with contraceptive cream or foam), or female patients who are pregnant or breastfeeding. A pre-enrolment serum or urinary HCG (human chorionic gonadotrophin) must be negative; Infection with Hepatitis B virus (HBV),  Hepatitis C virus (HCV) or Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) Other chronic liver diseases Significant weight gain or loss in the 3 months prior to study Unstable diabetes Patients with significant renal impairment (creatinine &gt; .15 mm/l) Patients with systolic BP &lt;110 mmHg Patients with decompensated liver disease ( Childs Pugh score &gt;6 ) Patients who have participated in a clinical trial for an investigational drug (a new chemical not registered for clinical use) within 30 days preceding entry into the       study, or who are due to enter such a trial during the treatment period Substance abuse such as alcohol (&gt;30g/day for males, &gt;20g/day for females), IV and inhaled drugs. If there has been a history of substance abuse, the subject must have abstained from using for at least 2 years.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Peter Angus</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC project grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Hepatic steatosis (fatty liver) is now the most common liver disease in western countries and NASH (fatty liver with inflammation) related cirrhosis and its complications is set to become one of the most important causes of liver related morbidity and mortality. It is clear that treatment and control of  predisposing factors such as  obesity and diabetes can lead to  improvement in liver fibrosis (scarring) in patients with NASH  however  this is not possible in many patients. At present there are no established drug treatments which have been able to prevent liver fibrosis due to NASH.
The renin-angiotensin sysytem (RAS) plays a central role in controlling blood pressure and sodium balance. Angiotensin II (the effector molecule) is a regarded as a key player in the general response to tissue injury in a number of organ systems, including the liver. A number of studies (experimental and human) have shown an improvement in fibrosis when the effects of AII are blocked.
This study will assess the ability of telmisartan therapy to decrease the formation of fat and scar tissue in the liver in patients with fatty liver disease. It will also study the effects of telmisartan on other factors commonly found in patients with fatty liver including obesity and insulin resistance. Telmisartan will be given for a period of 12 months. A liver biopsy will be performed prior to enrolment and then at 12 months. At each visit (3 monthly after the first month) a blood sample and medical consultation will be performed.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Westmead hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Peter Angus</name>
      <address>Department of Gastroenterology
Austin Health
PO BOX 5555
Heidelberg VIC 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94965582</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 94963487</fax>
      <email>Peter.Angus@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Steve Lontos</name>
      <address>Department of Gastroenterology
Austin Health
PO BOX 5555
Heidelberg VIC 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94963659</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 94963487</fax>
      <email>Steve.Lontos@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>