<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308235">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/07/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/07/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000601235</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The CONNECT Program Pilot Study: Evaluation of a nurse delivered telephone supportive care interventon for post-operative patients with colorectal cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The CONNECT Program Pilot Study: Evaluation of acceptance, feasibility and impact on supportive care needs of a nurse delivered supportive care intervention for post-operative patients with coloretcal cancer</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Colorectal cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Bowel - Back passage (rectum) or large bowel (colon)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A structured telephone intervention delivered by a cancer nurse. People diagnosed with colorectal cancer (colorectal Australian clinicopathological staging (ACPS) system A to D) will be asked to complete a baseline questionnaire during thier hospital admission. Patients will then be randomised into the intervention or control group. Patients in the intervention group will receive five telephone calls from the cancer nurse in the 6 months following their discharged from hospital (the first call is at Day 3 post-discharge and then the remaining four will be at Day 10 and then 1, 3 and 6 months post-discharge). Calls will vary in duration and be dependent on each individual patient's need. It is anticipated that calls will last about 20 minutes.</interventions>
    <comparator>Patients assigned to the control group will not receive any additional support and follow-up other than what has been provided or arranged for them by the treating medical team at Royal Prince Alfred Hospital in the six months following their discharge from hospital.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acceptability. Acceptability will be assessed by ascertaining the proportion of patients who complete each call at each time point. Demographic and clinical characteristics of patients allocated to the intervention group who did or did not accept or complete each call will be compared to assess the acceptability. Furthermore, a series of questions will be sent to patients at 6 months following the patient's hospital discharge and when the intervention is complete in order to gather detailed feedback of participant's views of the intervention.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 3 and 10 and 1, 3 and 6 months after the patient's hospital discharge.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility. Feasibility of the intervention will be determined by assessing the number of calls required to achieve a successful intervention call. Mean, standard devaitions, median and range of time taken for calls at each time point will also be calculated.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 3 and 10 and 1, 3 and 6 months after the patient's hospital discharge.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Unmet supportive care needs will be measured using the Supportive Care Needs Survey (SCNS). The SCNS is a 34-item questionnaire that determines participants level of unmet need for a range of items for five supportive care domains.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1, 3 and 6 months after the patient's hospital discharge.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life will be measured using the Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy - Colorectal (FACT-C), a 36-item colorectal quality of life questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1, 3 and 6 months after the patient's hospital discharge.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychological distress will be measured using the "Distress thermometer" where distress is rated using a sclae with scores ranging from 0 ("no distress") to 10 ("extreme distress")</outcome>
      <timepoint>1, 3 and 6 months after the patient's hospital discharge.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health Service Utlisation will be ascertained during telephone interviews with patients. During these interviews health service utilisation for a range of specialist and community based health professionals will be recorded.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1, 3 and 6 months after the patient's hospital discharge.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>To be eligible patients must be *over 18 years *diagnosed with primary colorectal cancer (ACPS A to D) * admitted for a surgical intervention with curative intent *have access to a telephone * have sufficient English skills (or have a person available to act as an interpreter) to participate *are able to give informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients will be ineligible to participate if they *do not have access to or are unable to use (eg due to deafness) a telephone *do not speak or read English (or have a person who can act as an interpreter) *plan to not reside in Australia for the next 6 months</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All patients who are admitted to Royal Prince Alfred Hospital (RPAH) for surgery for colorectal cancer (ACPS A to D) will be invited to participate by their surgeon who will provide them with written and verbal information about the study and obtain written consent. The surgeon will provide the details of consenting patients to the research coordinator [RC] who will then visit the patient prior to their discharge from hospital. The RC will explain the study processes in more detail and will obtain  written consent and ask them to complete a baseline self-administered questionnaire. Demographic information about the patient will be obtained during a short face-to-face interview with the RC. The details of consenting patients and baseline data will be forwarded by the RC to a second, independent researcher who will randomly allocate patients to the intervention or control groups using a computer-generated randomisation schedule. This will ensure allocation concealment in that the surgeons and RC who are actively involved in recruiting participants will be unaware of the group allocation sequence.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using a randomisation table created by a computer.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>19/06/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>75</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>A/Prof Jane Young</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Surgical Outcomes Research Centre (SOURCe), Royal Prince Alfred Hospital &amp; University of Sydney, PO BOX M157, Missenden Road, Camperdown, NSW, 2050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Surgical Outcomes Research Centre (SOURCe)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital &amp; University of Sydney, PO BOX M157, Missenden Road, Camperdown, NSW, 2050</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Prof Phyllis Butow</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Surgical Outcomes Research Centre (SOURCe), Royal Prince Alfred Hospital &amp; University of Sydney, PO BOX M157, Missenden Road, Camperdown, NSW, 2050</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Prof Michael Solomon</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Surgical Outcomes Research Centre (SOURCe), Royal Prince Alfred Hospital &amp; University of Sydney, PO BOX M157, Missenden Road, Camperdown, NSW, 2050</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Mr James Harrison</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Surgical Outcomes Research Centre (SOURCe), Royal Prince Alfred Hospital &amp; University of Sydney, PO BOX M157, Missenden Road, Camperdown, NSW, 2050</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This trial is the pilot randomised controlled trial to trial ACTRN12608000252314. The pilot randomised controlled trial (RCT) will test a novel telephone-based supportive care intervention for people with colorectal cancer. The intervention involves five structured calls from a nurse to the patients over the 6 month period after discharge from surgery. The intervention aims to improve psychosocial outcomes for patients. This pilot study aims to assess the feasibilty and acceptability of the intervention and determine any impact on patient outcomes. If the results are positive, this telephone intervention will be evaluated in a multi-centre randomised controlled trial (RCT) and could be implemented broadly in both metropolitan and rural areas, and could be adapted for other groups of carers.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.source.org.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney South West Area Health Service (RPAH Zone)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research &amp; Development Office, RPAH Medical Centre, 100 Carillon Avenue, Newtown, NSW, 2042</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/08/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>X06-0154</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/06/2006</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Prof Jane Young</name>
      <address>Surgical Outcomes Research Centre (SOuRCe), Royal Prince Alfred Hospital, PO BOX M157, Missenden Road, Camperdown, NSW, 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9515 3200</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9515 3222</fax>
      <email>jane.young@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>James Harrison</name>
      <address>Surgical Outcomes Research Centre (SOuRCe), Royal Prince Alfred Hospital, PO BOX M157, Missenden Road, Camperdown, NSW, 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9515 3200</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9515 3222</fax>
      <email>james.harrison@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>James Harrison</name>
      <address>Surgical Outcomes Research Centre (SOuRCe), Royal Prince Alfred Hospital, PO BOX M157, Missenden Road, Camperdown, NSW, 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9515 3200</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9515 3222</fax>
      <email>james.harrison@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>