<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366856">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/10/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/11/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001204639</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of kinesio taping on skill-related physical fitness and muscle activity following neuromuscular fatigue: A randomized-controlled trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of kinesio taping, versus no taping on skill-related physical fitness and muscle activity following neuromuscular fatigue in male recreational athletes: A randomized-controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Neuromuscular fatigue</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Kinesio taping will be used in this study. A physiotherapist that is specifically trained to apply kinesio taping for the purpose of this study. The type of kinesio tape that will be used is Kinesio Tex Gold with size of 5 cm and beige in colour. The tape will be applied to 3 muscles (rectus femoris of quadriceps, biceps femoris of hamstring and medial gastrocnemius) of the dominant leg of the participants. The tape will be applied during participants preparation atleast 30 minutes prior warm up and stretching at the High Performance Gym (study setting). Once the tape is applied, the tape will be used throughout the study (approximately 2 hours) as the tape is effective for 3-5 days. No replacement of tape will be required. Tape is applied to each participant on a single occasion only. The tape applied will be regularly checked throughout the study. If the edge of tape begun to lift, it will be trimmed. If the tape applied come off, new tape will be applied. 

After the warm up and stretching session, participants will be given a session to get familiarize with the test and protocol before the actual procedure. Then, participants will be asked to set a preferred jogging speed for dynamic postural control measurement. This will be achieved by participants jog on the treadmill with a fixed speed of 0.5 km/h to start. Next, the belt speed will be increased by 0.4 km/h every 15 seconds until participant found the preferred speed.

Next, participant will do the actual testing procedure.  
For the baseline test or pre-test, prior starting, participants maximum vertical jump will be recorded. Participant then will perform the T-Drill Test to assess the agility. After completing T-Drill Test, participant then will perform vertical jump test to assess leg power. Next, subject will perform Star Excursion Balance Test (SEBT) to assess balance. Next, subject will step on the treadmill to perform assessment of dynamic postural control. The washout period in between test will be 2-3 minutes. The test will be in a random order for each and every participant. The same procedure will be repeated for post test.

To induce neuromuscular fatigue, modified Functional Agility Short Term Fatigue Protocol (FAST-FP) will be used. This protocol consist of vertical jumping, stepping up and down, squatting and L-Drill. Firstly, participants will perform three consecutive vertical jump. Secondly, participants will perform a series of step up and down a 30 cm box for 20 seconds at 220 beats per minute (bpm). Thirdly, subjects will perform squatting to 90 degree knee flexion for 3 times. Finally, participants will perform a L-Drill (proagility shuttle run). For L-Drill, three cones will be set in the shape of an L with 4.05 meter apart. Participants will start at starting cone, sprint to the first cone and sprint back to the starting cone. Then participants will sprint to first cone, ran around it and cut inside to the second cone. Participants will ran in a circle around the second cone from the inside to the outside and sprint around the first cone before running to the starting cone. Completing the four tasks (vertical jumps, step-up and down, squatting and L-drill) will be counted as one set of the protocol. This will be repeated until maximal neuromuscular fatigue is achieved. Fatigue criteria will be manifested by the participants did not achieve 90% of the maximal jump on all 3 vertical jumps for 2 consecutive fatigue sets.

After maximal neuromuscular fatigue is achieved, participants will be test for post-test including  T-Drill Test, vertical jump test, Star Excursion Balance Test (SEBT) and postural control test on treadmill in random order. After completing one test, participant will be asked to perform again the fatigue protocol to ensure the maximal neuromuscular fatigue level is maintained. To minimize the recovery of neuromuscular fatigue, the manifestation of fatigue and the data collection will be less than 10-15 seconds.

There will be four groups. For Group A, tape will be applied to the participants and they will be exposed to neuromuscular fatigue. For Group B, no tape will be applied but participant will be exposed to neuromuscular fatigue. For Group C, tape will be applied but participant will not be exposed to neuromuscular fatigue. For Group D, no tape will be applied and participant will not be exposed to neuromuscular fatigue. For Group C and Group D where participants will not be exposed to neuromuscular fatigue, after completing the baseline test, participants will be given 15 minutes rest as washout period before proceeding to post-test. </interventions>
    <comparator>No taping</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composition score of Star Excursion Balance Test (SEBT)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post test. Baseline assessment is conducted after the tape is applied. Post test is within 15 seconds after manifestation neuromuscular fatigue</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Height of Vertical Jump Test </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post test. Baseline assessment is conducted after the tape is applied. Post test is within 15 seconds after manifestation neuromuscular fatigue</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time taken to complete T-Drill Test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post test. Baseline assessment is conducted after the tape is applied. Post test is within 15 seconds after manifestation neuromuscular fatigue</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parameters of Postural control. The postural control during running will be assessed using a pressure sensitive treadmill (Zebris FDM-T Treadmill System 'Registered Trademark', Isny, Germany). The treadmill will present a continuous trace of the Center of Pressure (CoP) trajectory for jogging/dynamic postural control. This is term as butterfly. This will provide the information on anterior/posterior variability, lateral symmetry and lateral variability.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post test. Baseline assessment is conducted after the tape is applied. Post test is within 15 seconds after manifestation neuromuscular fatigue</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Muscle activity will be assessed using electromyography (EMG) during performing skill related physical fitness tests such as Star Excursion Balance Test (SEBT) for balance, T-Drill Test for agility and using pressure sensitive treadmill for postural control.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post test. Baseline assessment is conducted after the tape is applied. Post test is within 15 seconds after manifestation neuromuscular fatigue</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.Male
2.Recreational athletes
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>25</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.History of sport injury to the lower limb</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subjects will be randomly assigned to one of the four groups using sequently numbered sealed opaque envelope.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomization will be generated using sequentially numbered, opaque, sealed envelopes. Each envelope contains a carbon paper and a paper with one of four group code label. After the envelope is sealed, the envelopes will be shuffled. Then only the envelope will only be sequentially numbered (1,2,3...100). Each participant will be given the envelope number-sequentially from 1 to 100. Participants’ information will be written on the envelopes prior to opening of the envelope. Audit trail will served with transferring the information to the assignment paper by the carbon paper. 
</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size calculation

The sample size is calculated using GPower 3.1 software. The statistical power will be set at 95% while effect size at 0.25 and p&lt;0.05. Ratio for every group is 1:1:1:1.

Analysis

Data will be analyzed using Statistical Package for Social Science (SPSS) version 20. Level of significant differences will be set at p &lt; 0.05. Descriptive statistics will be performed on demographic data and will be reported as means (M) +/- standard deviations (SD), range (minimum-maximum), median, frequency (%). Paired t-test will be performed to compare means between the dependent variables. ANOVA will be used to compare the means of groups in order to determine whether a significant difference exist between the groups.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/06/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>2/06/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <state>Selangor</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Muhamad Noh Zulfikri Mohd Jamali</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Universiti Teknologi MARA,
Puncak Alam Campus,
42300 Bandar Puncak Alam,
Selangor
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Malaysia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Universiti Teknologi MARA</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Universiti Teknologi MARA,
Puncak Alam Campus,
42300 Bandar Puncak Alam,
Selangor
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Malaysia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr. Maria Justine</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Universiti Teknologi MARA,
Puncak Alam Campus,
42300 Bandar Puncak Alam,
Selangor</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Malaysia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Saiful Adli Bukry</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Universiti Teknologi MARA,
Puncak Alam Campus,
42300 Bandar Puncak Alam,
Selangor</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Malaysia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To determine the effects of Kinesio Taping on dynamic balance following neuromuscular fatigue

We hypothesise that there will be a significant effect of Kinesio Taping on skill-related physical fitness and muscle activity following neuromuscular fatigue</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Research Ethic Comittee, Faculty of Health Sciences, UiTM</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Universiti Teknologi MARA,
Puncak Alam Campus,
42300 Bandar Puncak Alam,
Selangor</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/03/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Malaysia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Maria Justine</name>
      <address>Universiti Teknologi MARA,
Puncak Alam Campus,
42300 Bandar Puncak Alam,
Selangor</address>
      <phone>+60332584524</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>maria205@salam.uitm.edu.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Maria Justine</name>
      <address>Universiti Teknologi MARA,
Puncak Alam Campus,
42300 Bandar Puncak Alam,
Selangor</address>
      <phone>+60332584524</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>maria205@salam.uitm.edu.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Maria Justine</name>
      <address>Universiti Teknologi MARA,
Puncak Alam Campus,
42300 Bandar Puncak Alam,
Selangor</address>
      <phone>+60332584524</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>maria205@salam.uitm.edu.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Muhammad Noh Zulfikri Mohd Jamali</name>
      <address>Universiti Teknologi MARA,
Puncak Alam Campus,
42300 Bandar Puncak Alam,
Selangor</address>
      <phone>+60122672457</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nohzulfikri@ymail.com</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>