<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365561">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/01/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/03/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000283673</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Exercise positron emission technology (PET) imaging of the heart to predict cardiac complications after major cancer surgery
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Exercise Cardiac Positron Emission Technology Imaging in the Preoperative Assessment of Patients Undergoing Major Cancer Surgery: A Prospective Cohort Pilot Study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cardiac disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Any cancer</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is an observational study, investigating the feasibility and utility of preoperative exercise cardiac positron emission technology (PET) imaging in identifying patients with cardiac disease preoperatively.
Participants will undergo cardiopulmonary exercise testing (as per standard institutional protocol before major cancer surgery), which involves 10-12 minutes of cycling on a stationary bicycle. 
Endothelial function will be assessed non-invasively using a finger tonometry device (EndoPAT) before cardiopulmonary exercise testing. This involves application of a finger-probe on each hand which measures arterial pulse wave amplitude using plethysmographic technology. The testing process involves a resting measurement phase, forearm occlusion (using a blood pressure cuff inflated above systolic blood pressure on one arm for 5 minutes), and a final measurement of the magnitude of reactive hyperaemia after release of the forearm blood flow occlusion. 
Exercise PET imaging involves intravenous injection of radiolabelled glucose after peak exercise through an intravenous cannula. The radiolabelled glucose is taken up by ischaemic myocardium in the fasted state after a high fat and low carbohydrate meal. PET imaging then uses detection of emitted positrons to generate a tomographic image of the heart.
Patients must fast for 4-6 hours prior to the cardiopulmonary exercise test, and must consume a high fat, low carbohydrate meal for dinner the evening prior to the test and at 4-6 hours before the exercise test. A range on suggested high fat, low carbohydrate meals options will be provided to participants to choose from.
The total duration of cardiopulmonary exercise testing is approximately 60 minutes. Participants will undergo PET scans 1-2 hours after the cardiopulmonary exercise test. The cardiac PET scan duration is approximately 10 minutes.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility of performing cardiac PET (ability to recruit patients, ability of patients to follow fasting and dietary instructions, ability to complete PET testing, feasibility of blinded PET test reporting).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 0 (day of performing cardiac PET test).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ability of exercise cardiac PET imaging to identify exercise-induced myocardial ischaemia amongst patients at high risk for perioperative cardiac complications, compared to conventional SPECT MPI studies (and, if undertaken, echocardiography and coronary angiography).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 0-30 postoperatively (multiple assessments on days 0, 1, 2, 3, one week, two weeks, and at 30 days postoperatively).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of potential false-positive rates of exercise cardiac PET imaging (evidence of ischaemia in low risk patients without demonstrable myocardial ischaemia).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 0-30 postoperatively (multiple assessments on days 0, 1, 2, 3, one week, two weeks, and at 30 days postoperatively).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of semi-quantitative assessment of severity and distribution myocardial ischaemia using PET imaging vs. SPECT MPI.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 0 (after PET and MPI completed)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility of performing 'EndoPAT' testing of endothelial function and blood sampling for troponin and BNP at the time of exercise testing.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 0.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Greater than or equal to 18 years of age.
Informed consent.
Patients scheduled to attend pre-admission clinic review and cardiopulmonary exercise testing prior to major surgery at Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre, or patients with an indication for cardiac stress testing 
Are assessed as either high predicted risk or low predicted risk: High preoperative risk (Lee Revised Cardiac Risk Index greater than or equal to 2), OR Low preoperative risk (No risk factors other than high risk surgery, using the Lee Revised Cardiac Risk Index)
Participant assessed as being clinically suitable for CPET testing as per the American Thoracic Society guidelines</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Unable to provide informed consent
Unable to exercise
Intermediate risk (not meeting criteria for high or low risk groups).
Pregnancy or breastfeeding.
Insulin dependent diabetes mellitus.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>This study is a pilot study, and a sample size of 40 patients was chosen by the study investigators due to anticipated feasibility. As this is a pilot study, no formal sample size calculations were performed, due to the lack of data upon which to base any sample size calculation.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>10/07/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>28/02/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Peter MacCallum Cancer Institute - East Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3002 - East Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Marissa Ferguson</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
Lansdowne St, East Melbourne VIC 3002</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Lansdowne St, East Melbourne VIC 3002</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian and New Zealand College of Anaesthetists (ANZCA Novice Investigator Grant)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>630 St Kilda Road
MELBOURNE VIC 3004</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Alfred Hospital</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>55 Commercial Rd, Melbourne VIC 3004</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is evaluating the feasibility of exercise cardiac positron emission technology (PET) imaging to determine cardiac risk for patients undergoing major cancer surgery. Who is it for? You may be eligible to join this study if you greater than or equal to 18 years of age and are scheduled to attend pre-admission clinic review and cardiopulmonary exercise testing prior to major thoracic or abdominal surgery at Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre. Study details: All participants in this study will undergo cardiopulmonary exercise testing at the preadmission clinic to assess heart and lung function. You will be required to fast for 8 hours prior to arriving at the clinic, and you will be asked to consume a high fat and low carbohydrate meal 12 hours prior to the testing. Radiolabelled glucose will then be intravenously injected, i.e. administered directly into your vein. A positron emission technology (PET) scan of the heart will be performed 1-2 hours after the radiolabelled glucose injection. The diagnostic tests used in this study may have the potential to rapidly provide more specific information regarding myocardial metabolic function than CPET, and also enable anatomic localisation of areas of the myocardium which are susceptible to ischaemia under conditions of metabolic stress. We therefore hope to improve on the current tests available to identify patients at high risks of heart complications after surgery.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Lansdowne St, East Melbourne VIC 3002</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>31/03/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/02/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Marissa Ferguson</name>
      <address>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
Department of Anaesthesia and Perioperative Medicine
Division of Cancer Surgery
Locked Bag 1 ABeckett St
VIC 8006
</address>
      <phone>+613 9656 1111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>marissa.ferguson@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Marissa Ferguson</name>
      <address>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
Department of Anaesthesia and Perioperative Medicine
Division of Cancer Surgery
Locked Bag 1 ABeckett St
VIC 8006
</address>
      <phone>+613 9656 1111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>marissa.ferguson@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Marissa Ferguson</name>
      <address>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
Department of Anaesthesia and Perioperative Medicine
Division of Cancer Surgery
Locked Bag 1 ABeckett St
VIC 8006
</address>
      <phone>+613 9656 1111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>marissa.ferguson@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>