<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372036">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/12/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/01/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000147381</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Trans-nasal Humidified Rapid- Insufflation Ventilatory Exchange in Children Requiring Emergent Intubation  (Kids THRIVE): A Randomised Controlled Trial.
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Trans-nasal Humidified Rapid- Insufflation Ventilatory Exchange in Children Requiring Emergent Intubation  (Kids THRIVE): A Randomised Controlled Trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>KIDS THRIVE</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Airway Management</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Transnasal Humidified Rapid-Insufflation Ventilatory Exchange (THRIVE) used during induction of anaesthesia and prior to intubation in children during emergency intubations. THRIVE allows continued  oxygen delivery via high flow nasal cannual during intubation attempt; from the time the face mask is removed to successful intubation. Whereas after the traditional pre-oxygenation technique once the face mask is removed for intubation the oxygen reservoir is no longer renewed.  The rate of oxygen delivered will be dependant of weight with an FiO2 of 1.0 using Optiflo registered trademark device. These will be set up only to deliver an Fi02 of 1.0. 

HFNC Flow rates	Comments
0-12 kg	     2L/kg/min	(Max 25 L/min)
13-15kg	     30L/min	
15-30 kg	     35L/min	
30-50 kg     40L/min	
&gt;50 kg	     50L/min	


</interventions>
    <comparator>After induction of anaesthesia oxygen will be discontinued as per normal practice prior to intubation in children in emergency settings.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hypoxia defined as oxygen saturations using pulse oximetry less than 90% or a decrease of 10% from pre-intubation oxygen saturation where 100% oxygen saturation can not be clinically achieved during pre-oxygenation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After induction of anaesthesia and prior to intubation in children</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of successful first attempt intubations of success rate of intubation during emergency intubation. A single advanced airway manoeuvre beginning with the insertion of a device, such as a laryngoscope, into the patients mouth and ending when the device is removed from the patients mouth, or where there is a change in operator during the procedure even if the device is not removed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During emergency intubation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bradycardia -  Pulse rate decreasing 2 standard deviations below normal for age as defined by the American Heart Association in the Paediatric Advanced Life Support (PALS) Provider Manual using pulse oximetry and cardiac monitoring via ECG leads.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After induction of anaesthesia and prior to intubation in children</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hypotension - systolic BP falling below fifth centile for age, as defined by the American Heart Association in the Paediatric Advanced Life Support (PALS) Provider Manual using non invasive blood pressure monitoring and when available arterial blood pressure monitoring </outcome>
      <timepoint>After induction of anaesthesia and prior to intubation in children</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of mainstem bronchial intubations assessed by clinical  judgement or x-ray. This will be assessed using clinician reports and medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After intubation in children</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of oesophageal intubation (passage of endotracheal tube into the oesophagus) recognised immediately and with late recognition as defined below. This will be assessed using clinician reports and medical records.
-	Immediate Recognition:  recognised in the first 60 seconds after initiation of ventilation through endotracheal tube.
-	Late Recognition: recognised &gt;60s after initiation of ventilation through endotracheal tube.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>After intubation in children</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Laryngospasm - Partial or complete airway obstruction, with oxygen desaturation caused by involuntary and sustained closure of the vocal cords and is not relieved by routine airway re-positioning, suctioning or insertion or nasal or oral airway. This will be assessed using clinician reports and medical records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>During or post intubation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiac arrest with or without return of spontaneous circulation assessed using medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At any point during the emergency intubation process</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Emesis with or without aspiration assessed using medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At any point during the emergency intubation process</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Malignant hyperthermia assessed using medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At any point during the emergency intubation process</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pneumothorax or pneumomediastinum assessed using medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At any point during the emergency intubation process</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>* Is aged less than 16 years at the time of randomisation 
* Requires rapid sequence induction (RSI) or modified RSI* for emergency intubation and ventilation in either the emergency department or intensive care unit 

* Modified RSI is defined as the provision of ventilatory support by bag-mask ventilation, or other method, during the pre-oxygenation phase of induction of anaesthesia
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>16</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>* Planned endo-tracheal tube changes
* Requires immediate intubation for loss of cardiac output or respiratory arrest.
* Location of intubation is outside the Emergency Department or Intensive Care Unit.
* Blocked nasal airway due to anatomical abnormality (e.g. Choanal atresia)
* Blocked nasal airway due to acute injury, trauma or disease (e.g. Severe facial trauma)

</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Children requiring emergency intubation in the intensive care or emergency department
will be screened. Subjects that meet inclusion and exclusion criteria will be randomised by
sealed envelope allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Subjects that meet inclusion and exclusion criteria will be randomly
assigned 1:1 ratio to either high flow nasal cannula therapy or standard
care. Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by
computer software will be used (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>29/02/2020</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>820</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/02/2021</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Lady Cilento Children's Hospital - South Brisbane</hospital>
    <hospital>The Townsville Hospital - Douglas</hospital>
    <hospital>Gold Coast University Hospital - Southport</hospital>
    <postcode>4101 - South Brisbane</postcode>
    <postcode>4814 - Douglas</postcode>
    <postcode>4215 - Southport</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Lady Cilento Children's Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>501 Stanley Street
South Brisbane
Queensland, Australia 4101</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Emergency Medicine Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>2/15 Lang Parade Milton QLD 4064</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Paediatric Critical Care Research Group</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Paediatric Critical Care Research Group
Level 7, Centre for Childrens Health Research
Lady Cilento Children's Hospital Precinct
62 Graham Street, South Brisbane QLD 4101</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Children may present to an emergency department with life threatening conditions that require immediate treatment to support their breathing to allow enough oxygen to be supplied to the body. In these circumstances a child is anesthetized and intubated, this process is associated with a high risk for low oxygen levels (14%) in the body or low blood pressure or heart rate. Newer methods to avoid these risks and improve patient safety are important to investigate. In this  study we investigate a new approach called Transnasal Humidified Rapid-Insufflation Ventilatory Exchange (THRIVE);  to prevent a drop in oxygen levels during intubation using nasal high flow oxygen delivery.  This method allows continued post induction oxygen delivery during attempted intubation, whereas once the face mask is removed during traditional intubation the oxygen reservoir is no longer renewed and lower O2 levels can occur.  We have tested this method in children with healthy lungs undergoing anaesthesia for elective surgery, and we found that we can maintain oxygen levels more than twice as long as using standard intubation methods. These findings would allow the operator in emergency settings more time and a safer condition to secure the airway in a sick child. It is though that by providing oxygen throughout the intubation adverse events such as oxygen desaturation are reduced and he number of successful first intubation attempts increases. The high flow system used for the THRIVE method is not new and is often used in hospitals to treat children with respiratory illness such as bronchiolitis. 

Therefore we aim to compare the addition of the THRIVE method to standard intubation practice with the current standard practice to intubate a child in an emergency situation. We aim to demonstrate that the new THRIVE method will reduce the risk for low oxygen levels in the blood and prevents low blood pressure associated with intubation.

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Children’s Health Queensland Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 7, Centre for Childrens Health Research
Lady Cilento Children's Hospital Precinct
62 Graham Street, South Brisbane QLD 4101</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/12/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/12/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Andreas Schibler </name>
      <address>Level 7, Centre for Childrens Health Research
Lady Cilento Children's Hospital Precinct
Paediatric Critical Care Research Group
62 Graham Street, South Brisbane QLD 4101</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3068 1111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.schibler@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Andreas Schibler</name>
      <address>Level 7, Centre for Childrens Health Research
Lady Cilento Children's Hospital Precinct
Paediatric Critical Care Research Group
62 Graham Street, South Brisbane QLD 4101</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3068 1111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.schibler@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Andreas Schibler</name>
      <address>Level 7, Centre for Childrens Health Research
Lady Cilento Children's Hospital Precinct
Paediatric Critical Care Research Group
62 Graham Street, South Brisbane QLD 4101</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3068 1111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.schibler@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Andreas Schibler </name>
      <address>Level 7, Centre for Childrens Health Research
Lady Cilento Children's Hospital Precinct
Paediatric Critical Care Research Group
62 Graham Street, South Brisbane QLD 4101</address>
      <phone>07 3068 1111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.schibler@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>