<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367421">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/02/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/02/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000191493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Mindfulness-based Stress Release Program for university employees: a pilot, waitlist-controlled trial </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Mindfulness-based Stress Release Program for university employees: a pilot, waitlist-controlled trial and implementation replication</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Psychological distress</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Work engagement</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention period is six weeks, involving one half-day introductory session, followed by five weekly 60-minute face-to-face sessions with a trained instructor. The active intervention is based on an established Stress Release Program developed by staff at Monash University, Melbourne (Hassed &amp; Chambers, 2014). This program, delivered in the format of a small, interactive group, utilises cognitive strategies and reflective activities aimed to reduce stress, and improve wellbeing and resilience. Each session commences with a brief mindfulness practice, followed by an introduction to the session topic, an opportunity to reflect on the previous weeks practice, a theoretical component of the session. The main cognitive themes covered in the sessions include: perception and stress; reacting vs. responding to stress; presence of mind; the costs of automatic pilot and multitasking; listening; cultivating curiosity and openness; letting go and acceptance. Between sessions, participants are advised to practise formal mindfulness meditation at least 5 minutes per day and practise informal, mindfulness pauses (15-30 seconds) as needed. There is also a homework task related to each weekly topic, which involves identifying unhelpful cognitive patterns in real time as often as possible as they go about their usual daily life. One instructor who has received direct training from the original facilitators will deliver the intervention. Participant compliance is encouraged at each instructional session, and a register of attendees at each session noted.

Hassed C &amp; Chambers R (2014) Stress Release Program, accessed at http://www.monash.edu.au/counselling/stress-release-program.html on 30th May 2014 </interventions>
    <comparator>Waitlist control group over a 6 week period.

</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychological distress, as measured by a well validated and widely used self-report questionnaire, the Kessler Psychological Distress Scale (K10). This is a 10-item questionnaire intended to yield a global measure of distress based on questions about anxiety and depressive symptoms that a participant has experienced in the most recent 4 week period, and is the scale used by NSW Mental Health for standardized outcome measures. The K10 is scored using a five-level response scale based on the frequency of symptoms reported for each question. The maximum possible score of 50.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks after the commencement of the intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Work-specific measures of employee wellness and work-engagement. This will be measured by means of two questionnaires to evaluate a) University of Sydney specific workplace engagement and b) general engagement with the work content. The first questionnaire is adapted from a scale used by previous University of Sydney projects (The Voice Project, 2013). Only the relevant subscales will be used, the questions regarding Wellness and Work/life balance.  The second questionnaire is a previously validated tool for assessing work engagement, the Utrecht Work Engagement Scale (Schaufeli &amp; Bakker, 2003)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks after the commencement of the intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>N/A</outcome>
      <timepoint>N/A</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adult (&gt; 18 years old) employees at the University of Sydney willing to commit and consent to the full half day session and subsequent 5, weekly 60-minute sessions. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>As a naturalistic study there are no specific exclusion criteria</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>There is no allocation concealment to participants. Outcome measures are collected by self report and the investigators are blind to allocation</concealment>
    <sequence>Once the quota of 30 participants is enrolled in the program, the next 30 to register interest will then be invited to be placed on a waitlist to attend the next available mindfulness program in 3-4 months time. Whilst on the waitlist, participants in this group will be asked to fill out the same three short questionnaires regarding their level of stress, perceived wellbeing and workplace engagement, both at enrolment and then at 6 weeks follow-up. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The key analyses will involve a) a within group quantitative analysis of scores for each of the 3 scales at follow-up ( 6 weeks) compared to baseline (prior to commencing the study) and b) between group comparison of the scores of each of the 3 scales at baseline and follow-up</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>24/10/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>20/02/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>53</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2006 - The University Of Sydney</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Syndey</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Healthy Sydney University
Charles Perkins Centre
University of Sydney
NSW, 2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Healthy Sydney University
Charles Perkins Centre
University of Sydney
NSW, 2006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>na</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>NA</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Stress in the workplace is prevalent, with Australians reporting significantly lower overall workplace wellbeing in 2013 compared to previous years. Psychological injury is now the second most common cause of workplace compensation claims in Australia, and the direct cost to employers is estimated to be greater than $10 billion annual in terms of lost productivity. Thus, from an individual and public health perspective, there is an imperative to implement low risk, economically viable and effective programs to reduce workplace-stress and improve employee outcomes such as productivity, satisfaction and engagement.

Mindfulness-based programs have become increasingly popular as a means of targeting enhanced wellness at work as well as combatting negative consequences of excessive workplace stress. Mindfulness involves making a commitment to being fully conscious in the present moment without judgement, in an attitude of openness and acceptance. To date, reviews report a small to moderate effect for mindfulness in reducing multiple negative dimensions of psychological distress including anxiety, depression and appraised stress, although this is not specific for the workplace setting. Further research into the benefit of mindfulness programs in reducing workplace stress and quality of productivity is warranted.

This study aims to assess the effectiveness of structured, mindfulness-based program on decreasing work related stress and enhancing workplace wellbeing and engagement in fulltime university employees. Based on current available evidence, we hypothesise that mindfulness-based program participation will:
1. Improve employee work-related outcomes including workplace wellbeing and engagement
2. Reduce employee levels of stress, anxiety and improve mood</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee, University of Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Research Integrity Research Portfolio 
THE UNIVERSITY OF SYDNEY
Level 2, Margaret Telfer Building (K07)  
The University of Sydney, NSW  2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/09/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2014/649</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/367421-Ethics_approval.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/367421(v17-11-2014-21-37-49)-Utrecht Work Engagement Scale.docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/367421-K10.docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/367421-Usyd wellbeing &amp; engagement questionnaire.docx</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Nicholas Glozier</name>
      <address>Brain and Mind Centre
University of Sydney
94 Mallett Street
Camperdown 
NSW 2050
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9515 1596</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nick.glozier@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Fiona Wolfenden</name>
      <address>Safety, Health and Wellbeing, Human Resources
Level 5, School of Information Technologies Building (J12)
The University of Sydney, NSW 2006 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 4178</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>fiona.wolfenden@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Nicholas Glozier</name>
      <address>Brain and Mind Centre
University of Sydney
94 Mallett Street
Camperdown 
NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 95151596</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nick.glozier@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rebecca Koncz</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>rebecca.koncz@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>