<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364792">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/08/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/08/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000926730</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Augmenting internet-delivered cognitive behaviour therapy (iCBT) with daily SMS prompts for adults with chronic pain: an open trial to examine efficacy and acceptability.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Augmenting internet-delivered cognitive behaviour therapy (iCBT) with daily SMS prompts for adults with chronic pain: an open trial to examine efficacy and acceptability.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil.</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Pain
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All participants will complete 5 lessons of an iCBT treatment, the Pain Course (Dear et al., 2013) focusing on the management of pain, anxiety, depression and disability. All 5 Lessons will be administered online (via the internet) and one lesson will be completed every 7 to 10 days. Each lesson will take about 15 minutes to complete. Participants will also have access to summaries of each lesson, and will read anonymous stories about other people with chronic pain, taking a further 20 minutes per summary. All participants will also receive automatic email and weekly reminder phone calls by a clinical psychologist. The duration of the reminder emails and phone calls is expected to be 5-10 minutes per week. The duration of the program is 8 weeks. Study questionnaires will be administered at application, pre-treatment, post-treatment, and then 3, 12 and 24-months post-treatment. These questionnaires will take about 10 minutes to complete. Participants will be invited to receive generic SMS prompts and consenting participants will start receiving these prompts from week 3 of the course. The SMS prompts will be brief, limited to 1 a day on week days, and designed to remind participants to practice the skills during the day.</interventions>
    <comparator>N/A - This is a single group study.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Roland Morris Disability Questionnaire (RMDQ), which measures disability associated with pain.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Application, pre-treatment, post-treatment and 3, 12 and 24 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient Health Questionnaire 9-Item (PHQ9), which is a measure of depression.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Application, pre-treatment, post-treatment and 3, 12 and 24 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Generalized Anxiety Disorder 7-Item (GAD7), which is a measure of anxiety.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Application, pre-treatment, post-treatment and 3, 12 and 24 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Wisconsin Brief Pain Questionnaire (WBPQ), which is a general measure of the nature of participants pain including location, severity and duration.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Application, pre-treatment, post-treatment and 3, 12 and 24 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain Things You Do Questionnaire (PTYDQ), which is a measure of helpful cognitive and behavioural skill use.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment, post-treatment and 3, 12 and 24 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Employment and health service use will be measured by the Employment and Health Service Use Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment and 3, 12 and 24 month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Has experienced Chronic Pain (i.e. Pain &gt; 6 months)
- Internet access + Printer access
- Australian resident
- Has had their pain assessed by their GP or medical specialist.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Active psychosis
- Pain not assessed by GP
- Severe depression, suicidal intent or plan (PHQ-9 total score &gt; 22)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be the Waitlist-Control Group from another trial (ACTRN12613000252718). Participants receive access to the iCBT treatment once the Treatment Groups from the initial trial complete post-treatment and enter the follow-up phase.</concealment>
    <sequence>N/a.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Mixed linear models analyses will be conducted on the symptom outcome measures. With a alpha at 0.05 and power set at 80%, 27 participants are needed to detect a within-group effect size of .50, which is smaller than the smallest within-groups effect observed in a previous trial of the Pain Course. However, to hedge against attrition and to ensure the results are robust, more than 50 participants will be recruited. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>3/06/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>3/06/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Motor Accidents Authority of New South Wales</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Motor Accidents Authority of NSW
Address:	Motor Accidents Authority
Level 25, 580 George Street
Sydney NSW 2000, Australia
DX: DX 1517 SYDNEY</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Macquarie University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>eCentreClinic, The Centre For Emotional Health (CEH), Department of Psychology, Macquarie University, NSW, 2109, Australia.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project is part of a research program to develop and evaluate an Internet-based education and treatment program for people with chronic pain. This project extends an earlier trial (ACTRN12612000556842) to examine the efficacy and acceptability an iCBT program for people with chronic pain, when augmented with daily SMS prompts reminder participants to practice self-management skills. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.ecentreclinic.org</trialwebsite>
    <publication>- Dear, B. F., Titov, N., Nicholson Perry, K., Johnston, L., Wootton, B. M., Terides, M. D., Rapee, R. M., &amp; Hudson, J. L. (2013). The Pain Course: A randomised controlled trial of clinician-guided internet-delivered cognitive behaviour therapy program for managing chronic pain and emotional wellbeing. Pain, 154, 942-950.
- Johnston, L., Titov, N., Andrews, G., Dear, B. F., &amp; Spence, J. (submitted). Comorbidity and internet-delivered transdiagnostic cognitive behavioural therapy for anxiety disorders. Cognitive Behaviour Therapy. 
- Dear, B. F., Titov, N., Schwencke, G., Andews, G., Johnston, L., Craske, M. G., &amp; McEvoy, P. (2011). An open trial of a brief transdiagnostic treatment for anxiety and depression. Behaviour Research and Therapy, 49, 830-837. 
- Johnston, L., Titov, N., Andrews, G., Spence, J., &amp; Dear, B.F. (2011). A RCT of a transdiagnostic internet-delivered treatment for three anxiety disorders: Examination of support roles and disorder-specific outcomes. PLoS ONE 6(11): e28079. 
- Titov N., Dear B.F., Schwencke G., Andrews G., Johnston L., Craske M., &amp; McEvoy, P. (2011). Transdiagnostic Internet treatment of anxiety and depression: A randomised controlled trial. Behaviour Research and Therapy, 49, 441-452.
- Titov, N., Andrews, G., Johnston, L., Robinson, E., &amp; Spence, J. (2010). Transdiagnostic Internet treatment for anxiety disorders: A randomized controlled trial. Behaviour Research and Therapy, 48, 890-899.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Blake F. Dear</name>
      <address>eCentreClinic, The Centre for Emotional Health, Department of Psychology, Macquarie University, NSW, 2109.</address>
      <phone>61 2 9850 9979</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>blake.dear@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Blake F. Dear</name>
      <address>eCentreClinic, The Centre for Emotional Health, Department of Psychology, Macquarie University, NSW, 2109.</address>
      <phone>61 2 9850 9979</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>blake.dear@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Blake F. Dear</name>
      <address>eCentreClinic, The Centre for Emotional Health, Department of Psychology, Macquarie University, NSW, 2109.</address>
      <phone>61 2 9850 9979</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>blake.dear@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Blake F. Dear</name>
      <address>eCentreClinic, The Centre for Emotional Health, Department of Psychology, Macquarie University, NSW, 2109.</address>
      <phone>61 2 9850 9979</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>blake.dear@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>