<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="81711">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/11/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/12/2006</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000507583</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>ANZ 0601 / CIRG/TORI 010</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomized Phase 2 Trial of Double-Blind, Placebo Controlled AMG 706 in Combination with Paclitaxel, or Open-Label Bevacizumab in Combination with Paclitaxel, as First Line Therapy in Women with HER2 Negative Locally Recurrent or Metastatic Breast Cancer</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ANZ 0601 / CIRG/TORI 010</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Amgen Project Number: 20050225</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>NCT00356681</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>HER2 Negative Locally Recurrent or Metastatic Breast Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Eligible patients will be randomised in a 3-arm design to receive one of the following:

Arm B : Paclitaxel 90mg/m2 IV over 1 hour every week for 3 weeks (days 1, 8, 15, of each 28 day cycle) and blinded AMG 706 125mg orally every day.
Arm C : Paclitaxel 90mg/m2 IV over 1 hour every week for 3 weeks (days 1, 8, 15, of each 28 day cycle) and open label bevacizumab 10mg/kg IV following paclitaxel treatment on week 1 and week 3 of each cycle.

Treatment will be continued until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity or withdrawal of patient consent.</interventions>
    <comparator>Arm A : Paclitaxel 90mg/m2 IV over 1 hour every week for 3 weeks (days 1, 8, 15, of each 28 day cycle) and blinded AMG 706 placebo 125mg orally every day.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine if treatment with paclitaxel and AMG 706 is superior to paclitaxel plus AMG 706 placebo in subjects with HER2 negative locally recurrent or metastatic breast cancer, based on objective response rates.  Objective response rate is the percentage of patients assigned to a treatment arm with a confirmed best response of complete response or partial response as determined by an independent review committee.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>The primary analysis for the objective response rate will be performed when all patients who are receiving protocol therapy have at least their second radiological image.  An updated analysis will be performed when every patient on the study receiving protocol specified therapy have at least 10 months after first dose of study treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> To estimate the differences in progression-free survival time, clinical benefit, overall survival and duration of response between Arm A (paclitaxel plus AMG 706 placebo) and Arm B (paclitaxel plus AMG 706).</outcome>
      <timepoint>For Arm A and Arm B.
Progression Free Survival: the interval from the date of randomization to the first documented date of disease progression or death. Patients who have not progressed or died while on study will be censored at their last evaluable assessment date.
Duration of response: the interval from date of initial documented response (complete response or partial response) to the first
documented date of disease progression or death if due to disease progression. Patients who responded and have not progressed while on study or died for reasons other than disease
progression will be censored at the date of assessment of the last CT scan.
Clinical benefit rate: the percentage of patients with a complete response, partial responses or stable disease lasting &gt; 24 weeks.
Overall survival: the interval from the date of randomization and the date of death. Patients who have not died while on study drug will be censored at their last contact date.
Incidence of adverse events and laboratory abnormalities.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> To estimate the differences in objective response rate, progression-free survival time, clinical benefit, overall survival and duration of response between Arm B (paclitaxel plus AMG 706) and Arm C (paclitaxel plus bevacizumab).</outcome>
      <timepoint>For Arm B and Arm C.
Progression Free Survival: the interval from the date of randomization to the first documented date of disease progression or death. Patients who have not progressed or died while on study will be censored at their last evaluable assessment date.
Duration of response: the interval from date of initial documented response (complete response or partial response) to the first
documented date of disease progression or death if due to disease progression. Patients who responded and have not progressed while on study or died for reasons other than disease
progression will be censored at the date of assessment of the last CT scan.
Clinical benefit rate: the percentage of patients with a complete response, partial responses or stable disease lasting &gt; 24 weeks.
Overall survival: the interval from the date of randomization and the date of death. Patients who have not died while on study drug will be censored at their last contact date.
Incidence of adverse events and laboratory abnormalities.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> To evaluate safety and tolerability in the three treatment arms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The first Data Monitoring Committee review of safety data will occur no later than after the first 60 patients have been randomised and completed one cycle of therapy.  The safety analysis will be conducted on all patients who received at least one dose of study drug post protocol amendment 1. Patients will be included in the analysis according to the treatment received. Safety evaluations will consist of medical interviews,
recording of adverse events, physical examinations, blood pressure, and laboratory measurements. Patients will be evaluated for adverse events at each study visit for the duration of their participation in the study. Hypertension will be monitored through routine evaluation of blood pressure.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Confirmed HER2 negative locally recurrent or metastatic breast cancer (locally recurrent disease must not be amenable to resection with curative intent); measurable disease per RECIST (Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumor) guidelines; complete radiology and tumor measurement within 4 weeks (28 days) prior to randomization;  ECOG Performance Status of 0 or 1; adequate organ and hematological function; negative pregnancy test within 7 days prior registration for patients of child-bearing potential and sexually active; written informed consent signed prior to any study-related procedures.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Adjuvant or neoadjuvant taxane treatment within 12 months of randomization. Any other adjuvant chemotherapy regimen must be discontinued at least 3 weeks (21 days) prior to study randomisation.2. Prior chemotherapy for locally recurrent or metastatic breast cancer (prior endocrine therapyis permitted).3. Prior radiation therapy, radiofrequency ablation, percutaneous cryotherapy or hepaticchemoembolization on all sites of measurable disease unless disease progression was subsequently documented on at least one of these sites.4. Current or prior history of central nervous system metastasis.5. Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) v 3.0 peripheral neuropathy &gt; grade 2 at registration.6. Average systolic blood pressure &gt; 145 mm Hg or average diastolic blood pressure &gt; 85 mm Hg (average blood pressure of the 3 separate blood pressure values measured according to the Seventh Report of the Joint National Committee on Prevention, Detection, Evaluation, and Treatment of High Blood Pressure).7. History of arterial or venous thrombosis within 1 year prior to randomisation.8. History of bleeding diathesis or bleeding within 14 days of randomisation.9. Major surgical procedure within 4 weeks (28 days) prior to randomisation.10. Minor surgical procedure, placement of access device, or fine needle aspiration within 7 days of randomisation.11. Known positive test for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), hepatitis C, or malignancy (other than in situ cervical cancer, or basal cell cancer of the skin), unless treated with curative intent and without evidence of disease for = 3 years before study randomisation.12. Clinically significant cardiac disease within 12 months of study randomisation, including myocardial infarction, unstable angina, grade II or greater peripheral vascular disease, cerebrovascular accident, transient ischemic attack, congestive heart failure, or ongoing arrhythmias requiring medication or pacemaker.13. Non-healing wound, ulcer or fracture.14. Ongoing or active infection.15. Positive hepatitis B surface antigen.16. Known chronic hepatitis.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Australian and New Zealand institutions will register and randomise patients in liaison with the Cancer International Research Group (CIRG) Office in Paris.  At the time of study entry all participants will be allocated a treatment code via a web-based randomization system and blinded study drug (AMG 706) and open label study drugs will be supplied in accordance with the treatment code.</concealment>
    <sequence>Minimisation.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This is a double-blind study in which both the subjects and investigators (clinicians assessing the patients) are blinded to the treatment.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>11/09/2007</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>4/07/2008</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>273</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>282</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Amgen Inc.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Amen, Inc. One Amgen Centre Drive Thousand Oaks, CA 91320-1799 USA</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australia and New Zealand Breast Cancer Trials Group</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO BOX 155
HRMC NSW 2310</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Amgen Inc</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Amen, Inc. One Amgen Centre Drive Thousand Oaks, CA 91320-1799 USA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cancer International Research Group</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Cancer International Research Group
Suite 1100
9925-109 Street
Edmonton
Alberta T5K 2J8, Canada</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Canada</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Cancer International Research Group (CIRG)</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Cancer International Research Group
Suite 1100
9925-109 Street
Edmonton
Alberta T5K 2J8, Canada</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Canada</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to test a new anticancer drug, AMG 706, which targets the blood vessels of the tumour.  Evidence suggests that the formation of new blood vessels within the tumour is critical in the progression of solid tumours, including breast cancer.  Of the numerous factors that affect the growth of these blood vessels, vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) is likely one of the most, if not the most, important molecules regulating new blood vessel formation and subsequent invasion and metastasis.  As a result, agents that inhibit VEGF (such as those drugs being used in this trial) may prevent this tumour vascular invasion and thereby block the growth of the tumour.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>N/A</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Auckland Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Border Medical Oncology</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Christchurch Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Concord Repatriation General Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Mater Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Princess Alexandra Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Hobart Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/06/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital, Melbourne</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Tweed Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Waikato Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>John F Forbes</name>
      <address>ANZBCTG
PO BOX 155
HRMC NSW 2310</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4985 0113</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 49850141</fax>
      <email>enquiries@anzbctg.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Corinna Beckmore</name>
      <address>ANZBCTG
PO BOX 155
HRMC NSW 2310</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4985 0159</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 49850141</fax>
      <email>enquiries@anzbctg.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>John F Forbes</name>
      <address>ANZBCTG
PO BOX 155
HRMC NSW 2310</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4985 0113</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>enquiries@anzbctg.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>