<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367857">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/01/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/02/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000146594</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A pilot assessment of the feasibility of a notification system for patients with high-risk laboratory abnormalities in acute surgical wards</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot assessment of the feasibility of a notification system for patients with high-risk laboratory abnormalities in acute surgical wards</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Post-surgical adverse events</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Using data from the previous study (Loekito et al, Common laboratory tests predict imminent death in ward patients, Resuscitation, 2013;84(3):280-285) we have identified patterns and tests with given sensitivity and specificity that can be used to identify at risk patients. We plan to obtain raw level data generated by the Pathology Lab computers as they come on stream and, subsequent to their acquisition by the CERNER system, deliver them to a server where they can be analyzed by software designed to identify high-risk patterns. 

When such a pattern is identified in a patient who is electronically known to be located on the 8th floor, we plan to send an electronic message to a designated pager carried by the Medical Emergency Team (MET) registrar notifying her/him that patient X is at risk. 

As an example, if a patient was identified to be at risk of a Medical Emergecny Team (MET) call, the message might take this form MR John Citizen on ward 8N has major laboratory abnormalities. 

However, because of workload issues, only one in two alerts will be sent to the MET registrars pager (approximately 2 alerts/day).   Patient's whose alert is sent to the MET registrar's pager will form the intervention group.  The MET registrar will then review the participant at the next earliest opportunity.  At the review the MET registrar will assess the patient and assess the patient's pathology data.  The MET registrar will then make treatment decisions and contact the patient's primary team and modify treatment (if appropriate and agreed) following such discussion.  The duration of the intervention period is 12 months.

All data collections on treatment, characteristics and outcomes will be by means of review of scanned medical records after the patient has been discharged.

</interventions>
    <comparator>Using data from the previous study we have identified patterns and tests with given sensitivity and specificity that can be used to identify at risk patients. We plan to obtain raw level data generated by the Pathology Lab computers as they come on stream and, subsequent to their acquisition by the CERNER system, deliver them to a server where they can be analyzed by software designed to identify high-risk patterns. 
When such a pattern is identified in a patient who is electronically known to be located on the 8th floor, we plan to send an electronic message to a designated pager carried by the MET registrar notifying her/him that patient X is at risk. 

As an example, if a patient was identified to be at risk of a MET call, the message might take this form MR John Citizen on ward 8N has major laboratory abnormalities. 

However, because of workload issues, only one in two alerts will be sent to the MET registrars pager (approximately 2 alerts/day).  Patient's whose alert is not sent to the MET registrar's pager will form the control group.  Alerts that are not sent to the MET registrar will be stored in the CERNER database and the outcomes of patients identified by members of the research team.

All data collections on treatment, characteristics and outcomes will be by means of review of scanned medical records after the patient has been discharged.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mortality - 24 hours</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 24 hours after the biochemical alert.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mortality - 48 hours</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 48 hours after the biochemical alert.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mortality - Hospital</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at time when patient is discharged from hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of stay - hospital</outcome>
      <timepoint>Hospital admission duration in days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intensive Care Unit admission - 24 hours</outcome>
      <timepoint>The need for admission to the intensive care unit occuring within 24 hours following a biochemical alert.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Medical Emergency Team (MET) call - 24 hours</outcome>
      <timepoint>Occurence of a medical emergency team (MET) call within the first 24 hours following a biochemical alert.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Medical Emergency Team (MET) call - 48 hours</outcome>
      <timepoint>Occurence of a medical emergency team (MET) call within the first 48 hours following a biochemical alert.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intensive Care Unit admission - 48 hours</outcome>
      <timepoint>The need for admission to the intensive care unit occuring within 48 hours following a biochemical alert.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of identified alerts per day.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The number of alerts generated by the computer-based algorithm during the study period during the 12-month intervention period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of alerts received by the Medical Emergency Team registrar.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Number of alerts received by the Medical Emergency Team registrar during the 12-month intervention period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The number of patients seen by the Medical Emergency Team registrar.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The number of patients seen by the Medical Emergency Team registrar during the 12-month intervention period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All patients admitted to the acute surgical ward of the Austin Hospital.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Nil</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Identification of patients is achieved via central randomisation by a computer using a pre-specified algorithm of pathology data.  Allocation is concealed as the MET registrar who receives the alert will only know of the active alerts and not the control alerts.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a computerised sequence generation will ensure 1:1 randomisation.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Baseline and outcome variables will be compared using Chi-square tests for equal proportion, Students t-test for normally distributed outcomes and Wilcoxon rank-sum tests
otherwise. Multivariate models adjusting for baseline  imbalances and known covariates will be performed using logistic regression. A p-value of 0.05 will be considered to be statistically significant. Kaplan-Meier plot and and Cox-proportional hazards modelling will be performed as appropriate.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>23/07/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>23/07/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Austin Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Austin Health
145 Studley Road
Heidelberg VIC 3084</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Austin Health - Anaesthesia Intensive Care Trust Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Austin Hospital
Department of Intensive Care
145 Studley Road
Heidelberg VIC 3084</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Rinaldo Bellomo</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Austin Hospital
Department of Intensive Care
145 Studley Road
Heidelberg VIC 3084</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In a previous audit, we retrospectively studied 418,897 batches of tests in 42,701 patients for a total of 2.5 million individual measurements of nine laboratory results (Loekito et al, Common laboratory tests predict imminent death in ward patients, Resuscitation 2013; 84(3):280-285). We identified simple laboratory abnormalities (e.g. high plasma urea, low blood bicarbonate level, low albumin), which either alone, but even more so when clustered together in particular pattern were associated with a higher risk of poor outcome (MET call, ICU admission or death) by the following calendar day. This finding suggested that, using routinely measure laboratory results, we might be able to identify those patients, who are at high risk of such outcomes and that, we might, therefore, be in a position to notify the ward where these patients are located of such increased risk. In this pilot study, we plan to extend our assessment the feasibility of such a notification system following a pilot study approved by the Human Research Ethics Committee in 2011.
 
Specifically, we plan to continuously scan the raw data emerging form the pathology lab computers with focus on the 8th floor wards. Then, using a computerized risk identification system based on our retrospective analysis, we plan to identify patterns of laboratory data that identify patients at high risk of the above adverse outcomes by the next calendar day. 

Once such identification has been achieved, we plan to send every second notification to a dedicated pager carried by the Medical Emergency Team (MET) registrar, who will then visit the patient, review his/her laboratory results, contact the primary team to inform them of the laboratory concerns and modify treatment (if appropriate and agreed) following such discussion . Such notification will occur electronically by automated messages sent to the pager.

The purpose of the pilot study is to assess: 1. How many notifications such a system would generate per day for the 8th floor wards; 2. Whether such a system can reliably deliver such notifications; 3. How many at risk patients are identified by such a system and how many are missed per month; 4. The outcome of patients identified by such a system.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Austin Health
145 Studley Road
Heidelberg VIC 3084</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/06/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H2011/04296</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>8/02/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/367857(v29-01-2015-13-22-20)-20141208 - Austin Approval LNR14Austin407.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/367857-Austin_NDSAC_Activation of biochemical alerts_HREC approval letter_150611.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Rinaldo Bellomo</name>
      <address>Department of Intensive Care
Austin Hospital
145 Studley Road
Heidelberg VIC 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 5992</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 3 9496 3932</fax>
      <email>rinaldo.bellomo@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Glenn Eastwood</name>
      <address>Department of Intensive Care
Austin Hospital
145 Studley Road
Heidelberg VIC 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 4835</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9496 3932</fax>
      <email>glenn.eastwood@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Rinaldo Bellomo</name>
      <address>Department of Intensive Care
Austin Hospital
145 Studley Road
Heidelberg VIC 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 5992</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9496 3932</fax>
      <email>rinaldo.bellomo@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Glenn Eastwood</name>
      <address>Department of Intensive Care
Austin Hospital
145 Studley Road
Heidelberg VIC 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 4835</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9496 3932</fax>
      <email>glenn.eastwood@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>