<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370206">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/04/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/05/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000570482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Behavioural Balloon Dilatation in Upper Esophageal Sphincter (UES) Dysfunction</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of Behavioural Balloon Dilatation on UES opening diameter and duration and UES pressures during swallowing in participants with UES Dysfunction</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1180-0414</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Dysphagia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>UES dysfunction</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Speech therapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Each participant will undergo 6 assessments and 10 treatment sessions over a period of 4 months at the Rose Centre for Stroke Recovery and Research, University of Canterbury (see attachment Study procedures for a diagram detailing procedures that will occur at each session). Each session is expected to last approximately one hour. Some of the assessment and treatment sessions have been combined  these sessions will last approximately 1.5 hours. Each session will be an individual face-to-face session. They will be delivered by a speech language therapist with a minimum of 5 years experience.
Each participant will undergo two baseline assessments with the Timed Water Swallow Test (TWST), the Test of Mastication and Swallowing Solids (TOMASS). These are screening tests where the participant will be observed while drinking a fixed amount of water and when eating a cracker. The participant will then undergo High-Resolution Manometry (HRM) and Videofluoroscopic Swallowing Study (VFSS) to document UES function prior to therapy. At the second baseline assessment session, if measures on HRM and the screening tests remain similar, VFSS will be omitted to limit radiation exposure. After the two baseline assessment sessions, a two-week behavioural dilatation treatment program will then commence. 
The intervention under investigation is behavioural balloon dilatation. It involves oral insertion of a urethral balloon catheter without sedation to the upper esophageal sphincter (UES). Two balloon dilatation methods will be carried out for each participant:
a. the retrograde method  the balloon catheter is inserted to under the UES before the balloon is inflated with air and pulled through the UES in synchrony with swallowing (20 repetitions)
b. the anterograde method the balloon portion of the catheter is inflated with air before the participant swallows it down past the UES with the aid of a guidewire (10 repetitions).
The retrograde method will be implemented from the first week of treatment. The anterograde method will be added on only in the second week. Each time a new method of dilatation is taught, the first dilatation will be done with visualisation by VFSS to mark how far the balloon catheter needs to be inserted. This will hence occur twice: once in the first retrograde dilatation attempt in the first week; the other in the first anterograde dilatation attempt in the second week. In subsequent dilatation attempts without VFSS, insertions will follow the markings made and the participant will be instructed to phonate after swallowing the catheter to ensure the catheter has not been inserted into the trachea. 
The regimen will hence consist of a total of twenty repetitions of balloon dilatation at each session, two sessions per day, five times per week for the first week.  At the end of the first week, HRM will be carried out to chart progress before commencing the second week of treatment. It potentially may yield data that indicates which patients may or may not tolerate anterograde dilatation. The regimen then increases to thirty repetitions of balloon dilatation at each session, two sessions per day, five times per week for the second week. Patients are encouraged to perform self-dilatation of the UES. To rate the tolerability of the treatment program, participants will be asked to rate their comfort level on a visual analogue scale at one week into the treatment phase and again at immediately after treatment has ended.
Initial balloon sizes will be determined by VFSS opening diameters measured from the baseline VFSS sessions. Balloon size will then gradually be increased based on patient comfort levels and intra-balloon pressures generated when the balloon passes the UES. Intra-balloon pressures will be measured throughout the whole dilatation session with a manometer connected to a laptop which will display pressures within the balloon on screen. Dou and colleagues (2012) reported that small increments in balloon size will lead to fewer side effects like bleeding from mucosal trauma. Typically intra-balloon pressures will be monitored to remain less than 20% above baseline pressures. If pressures stay within 20% of baseline pressures, balloon size will be increased by 0.5mm. The maximum balloon diameter will correspond to normative data of maximum UES diameter during swallowing (normative data is available in Leonard and Kendall, 2013). Once this maximum diameter is achieved, therapy will continue at this balloon size until the end. This is to minimise the risk of bleeding from over-expansion.
At the end of the two-week of treatment, the TWST, TOMASS, HRM and VFSS will be repeated to document change in UES opening and manometric pressures from treatment. At two weeks and at three months after treatment has terminated, the TWST, TOMASS and HRM will be repeated to assess short and long-term effects of treatment. Once again, VFSS will be omitted if HRM measures remain stable to minimise radiation exposure.
Functional change in swallowing function will be monitored via scoring on the Functional Oral Intake Scale (FOIS), a 7-point scale based on details of a participants feeding status and amount of intake. The Eating Assessment Tool (EAT-10), a short questionnaire that assesses change in patient-reported dysphagia symptoms and severity, and quality of life, will also be administered at each session. Based on previous research indicating that reflux symptoms may increase after oesophageal dilatation, it would be of interest to investigate if laryngopharyngeal reflux, in particular, will be affected after behavioural dilatation. Change in symptoms will be tracked using the Reflux Symptom Index (RSI). 
</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite primary outcome: To determine if the behavioural balloon dilatation regimen is effective through assessing UES opening diameter and duration via videofluoroscopic swallowing study (VFSS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>i) Immediately after end of treatment (immediate outcome)
ii) 2 weeks after treatment (short-term outcome)
iii) 3 months after treatment (longer-term outcome)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite primary outcome: To determine if the behavioural balloon dilatation regimen is effective through assessing manometric measurements of the UES (UES resting pressure, nadir relaxation pressure and relaxation duration) on High-Resolution Manometry (HRM).</outcome>
      <timepoint>i) mid-treatment (1 week after treatment has commenced, mid-treatment outcome)
ii) Immediately after end of treatment (immediate outcome)
iii) 2 weeks after treatment (short-term outcome)
iv) 3 months after treatment (longer-term outcome</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite primary outcome: To investigate change in scores on functional swallowing scales - Functional Oral Intake Scale (FOIS) and Eating Assessment Tool (EAT-10)</outcome>
      <timepoint>i) Immediately after end of treatment (immediate outcome)
ii) 2 weeks after treatment (short-term outcome)
iii) 3 months after treatment (longer-term outcome)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite secondary outcome: To determine change in reflux symptoms due to behavioural balloon dilatation as assessed by Reflux Symptom Index (RSI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>i) Immediately after end of treatment (immediate outcome)
ii) 2 weeks after treatment (short-term outcome)
iii) 3 months after treatment (longer-term outcome)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess tolerability of behavioural balloon dilatation as a treatment program with 100mm visual analogue scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>i) After first week of treatment
ii) After second week of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine if UES manometric pressures, as measured on HRM, can indicate which participants can tolerate anterograde balloon dilatation  in the second week of treatment</outcome>
      <timepoint>one week after treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Able to give informed consent
- Diagnosis of UES dysfunction evidenced by reduced UES opening and pyriform residue post swallow on VFS and/ or
- Abnormal UES opening pressures on HRM</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Are medically unstable
- Have cognitive or language impairments
- Have abnormalities in the head and neck region
- Have undergone therapy for head and neck cancer including extirpative surgery, chemotherapy and radiation therapy
- Are currently on tracheostomy
- Have known upper oesophageal abnormalities e.g. active inflammation, tumours, perforation (not including reflux)
- Have known nasal abnormalities that precludes use of manometry
- Have known bleeding tendencies
- Are currently undergoing any other forms of swallowing management for UES dysfunction</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>N.A.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Multiple baseline cohort study</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The sample size was calculated using G*Power program based on published data from the study by Arenaz and colleagues (2015) which listed UES sagittal diameter 1 month pre- and post-intervention (intervention method was conventional balloon dilatation) in a sample size of 4:
Mean change in UES sagittal diameter (post- versus pre-treatment) = 1.48 mm
Standard deviation 			= 1.50 mm
Tails 					        = Two
Calculated effect size 			= 0.99
Alpha error probability 		= 0.05
Power (1- beta error probability) = 0.8
Calculated sample size 		= 11
A calculated sample size of 11 was obtained. However, given that the sample size was calculated from outcome data for medical UES dilatation and there is a lack of data from behavioural dilatation studies regarding exact change in UES opening size, a smaller effect size is expected for behavioural balloon dilatation. This is due to it being less intrusive as it is not expected to tear muscle. Hence, a more conservative sample size of 20 has been set.

Statistical data analysis of the treatment phase will be conducted using the Statistical Package for the Social Sciences (SPSS) program.

Independent variable: Time since intervention (balloon dilatation)
Dependent variables: UES opening diameter (ratio), UES opening duration (ratio), UES resting pressure (ratio), UES nadir relaxation pressure (ratio), UES relaxation duration (ratio), Timed Water Swallow Test times (ratio), Test of Masticating and Swallowing Solids times (ratio), Functional Oral Intake Scale (FOIS) score (ordinal), Reflux Symptom Index (RSI) score (ordinal), Eating Assessment Tool (EAT-10) score (ordinal)

Data screening for normal distribution and homogeneity of variance will first be carried out using various methods, including box plots, histograms, calculations of skewness and Levenes test . If the data do not meet the requirements for parametric testing, transformation of the data into a logarithm scale will be undertaken, or non-parametric tests will be used.

Descriptive statistics such as the mean, range and standard deviation of each measure will be listed. The alpha level will be set at 0.05 for this study.

There are six points in time when the dependent variables are measured:
1)	First baseline
2)	Second baseline
3)	Mid treatment (one week after treatment)  only for HRM measures of UES resting pressure, UES nadir relaxation pressure and UES relaxation duration
4)	Post treatment (immediate)
5)	Post treatment (two weeks after)
6)	Post-treatment (three months after)
To assess for changes in the dependent variables that are ratio data over these times, repeated measures ANOVA will be used. For ordinal data i.e. FOIS scores, RSI scores and EAT-10 scores, the mean of these scores will be reported.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>16/05/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>8/08/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/05/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Canterbury</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Seh Ling Kwong</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Rose Centre for Stroke Recovery and Research at St Georges Medical Centre
Leinster Chambers, Level 1, Private Bag 4737
249 Papanui Road
Christchurch 8140</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Canterbury</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Private Bag 4800, Christchurch 8140
New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Maggie-Lee Huckabee</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Rose Centre for Stroke Recovery and Research at St Georges Medical Centre
Leinster Chambers, Level 1, Private Bag 4737
249 Papanui Road
Christchurch 8140</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Phoebe Macrae</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Rose Centre for Stroke Recovery and Research at St Georges Medical Centre
Leinster Chambers, Level 1, Private Bag 4737
249 Papanui Road
Christchurch 8140</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Medical management of impairment in the UES has traditionally consisted of the surgical option of cricopharyngeal myotomy, with variable efficacy. More conservative options include medical dilatation, botulinum toxin injections and swallowing rehabilitation exercises carried out by the speech-language pathologist. Behavioural balloon dilatation, a conservative approach, was first documented in the 1990s by Japanese researchers. Frequently used in Asian countries as an adjunct to swallowing rehabilitation programs, the protocol for balloon rehabilitation has varied across studies, with a paucity of data available on long-term effects of UES dysfunction and UES dysfunction caused by disorders other than neurological diseases. 

This study will evaluate the short-term and longer-term efficacy, safety and tolerability of balloon dilatation as a behavioural treatment approach for patients with UES dysfunction. Twenty patients with UES dysfunction, demonstrated on videofluoroscopic swallowing study (VFSS) and high-resolution manometry (HRM), will be recruited to undergo a two-week intensive behavioural balloon dilatation protocol with a follow-up session at three months after therapy. The protocol is based on the concept of retraining the response of the UES via a series of behavioural therapy sessions, rather than just a single medical, mechanical expansion of the UES with the balloon. A combination of two main methods of self-administered balloon dilatation will be carried out with an inflated urethral balloon catheter: 1) anterograde method, where an inflated balloon is swallowed through the UES with aid of a guidewire; 2) retrograde method, where the catheter is inserted below the UES before inflating the balloon, then pulled up through the UES in synchrony with dry swallows. The retrograde method will be implemented from the first day of treatment and the anterograde method will only be added on in the second week of treatment. Dilatation will be performed 20 to 30 times in total within each session, two sessions a day, five days a week for two weeks, before re-evaluation of swallowing function. Initial balloon sizes will be determined based on UES opening size on VFSS. Subsequent increases in size will be guided by pressures that are generated when the balloon passes the UES, paired with patient comfort levels, to minimise the risk of mucosal trauma. Data analysis will compare pre and post- therapy UES opening diameter and duration during swallowing as well as UES resting pressure, nadir relaxation pressure and UES relaxation duration to determine the efficacy of behavioural balloon dilatation in treating UES dysfunction. Change in feeding status is also of interest, to determine if improvements in VFSS and HRM measures lead to functional changes in swallowing. Maintenance effects of therapy will also be examined with data provided at the three-month follow-up.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committees</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Ethics Department
Freyberg Building
Reception  Ground Floor
20 Aitken Street
Wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/06/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>16/NTA/63</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/04/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/370206-Study procedures.doc</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Seh Ling Kwong</name>
      <address>Rose Centre for Stroke Recovery and Research at St Georges Medical Centre 
Leinster Chambers, Level 1, Private Bag 4737 
249 Papanui Road
Christchurch 8140</address>
      <phone>+6433692385</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>seh.kwong@pg.canterbury.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Seh Ling Kwong</name>
      <address>Rose Centre for Stroke Recovery and Research at St Georges Medical Centre 
Leinster Chambers, Level 1, Private Bag 4737 
249 Papanui Road
Christchurch 8140</address>
      <phone>+6433692385</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>seh.kwong@pg.canterbury.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Seh Ling Kwong</name>
      <address>Rose Centre for Stroke Recovery and Research at St Georges Medical Centre 
Leinster Chambers, Level 1, Private Bag 4737 
249 Papanui Road
Christchurch 8140</address>
      <phone>+6433692385</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>seh.kwong@pg.canterbury.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Seh Ling Kwong</name>
      <address>Rose Centre for Stroke Recovery and Research at St Georges Medical Centre 
Leinster Chambers, Level 1, Private Bag 4737 
249 Papanui Road
Christchurch 8140</address>
      <phone>+6433692385</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>seh.kwong@pg.canterbury.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>