<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371234">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001077459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An Intralesional Injection Study of DUR-928 in Psoriasis Patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Proof of Concept Study to Assess The Efficacy and Safety of Single Intralesional Doses of DUR-928 in Psoriasis Patients.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Psoriasis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dermatological conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>DUR-928 solution: 30 mg/mL DUR-928 solution after constitution with sterile vehicle solution.
Placebo for solution: The sterile vehicle solution contains hydroxypropyl betadex in phosphate buffered water. 
DUR-928 suspension: 25 mg/mL DUR-928 suspension after constitution with sterile vehicle suspension.
Placebo for suspension: The sterile vehicle suspension contains polyethylene glycol  in phosphate buffered water.
Active Comparator: 2mg/mL Kenalog-10 (Triamcinolone Acetonide) after dilution with sterile sodium chloride.
Treatment Control: one site will contain no intervention. 
Each participant will be treated with 2 different formulations of study drug, 2 placebo (vehicle) formulations, one active comparator and one untreated area (6 treatments in total). Each treatment will be administered to every participant as three 100 microlitre intralesional injections, with the exception of the untreated area. All 5 treatments will be administered consecutively. Each treatment area is approximately 4cm^2. 
The planned study treatments are: 
A = DUR-928 Solution, 30 mg/mL (3 x 100 microlitre = 9 mg) 
B = DUR-928 Suspension, 25 mg/mL (3 x 100 microlitre = 7.5 mg) 
C = Vehicle for Solution, (3 x 100 microlitre = 0.3 mL) 
D = Vehicle for Suspension, (3 x 100 microlitre = 0.3 mL) 
E = Kenalog-10 (diluted) 2mg/mL (3 x 100 microlitre = 0.6 mg) 
F = Untreated area
Unblinded study staff will administer all doses. Adherence to the correct dosing procedure will be documented in source data and review by an unblinded monitor. This is a single dose trial. </interventions>
    <comparator>DUR-928 solution: 30 mg/mL DUR-928 solution after constitution with sterile vehicle solution.
Placebo for solution: The sterile vehicle solution contains hydroxypropyl betadex in phosphate buffered water. 
DUR-928 suspension: 25 mg/mL DUR-928 suspension after constitution with sterile vehicle suspension.
Placebo for suspension: The sterile vehicle suspension contains polyethylene glycol  in phosphate buffered water.
Active Comparator: 2mg/mL Kenalog-10 (Triamcinolone Acetonide) after dilution with sterile sodium chloride.
Treatment Control: one site will contain no intervention. 
Each participant will be treated with 2 different formulations of study drug, 2 placebo (vehicle) formulations, one active comparator and one untreated area (6 treatments in total). Each treatment will be administered to every participant as three 100 microlitre intralesional injections, with the exception of the untreated area. All 5 treatments will be administered consecutively. Each treatment area is approximately 4cm^2. 
The planned study treatments are: 
A = DUR-928 Solution, 30 mg/mL (3 x 100 microlitre = 9 mg) 
B = DUR-928 Suspension, 25 mg/mL (3 x 100 microlitre = 7.5 mg) 
C = Vehicle for Solution, (3 x 100 microlitre = 0.3 mL) 
D = Vehicle for Suspension, (3 x 100 microlitre = 0.3 mL) 
E = Kenalog-10 (diluted) 2mg/mL (3 x 100 microlitre = 0.6 mg) 
F = Untreated area
Unblinded study staff will administer all doses. Adherence to the correct dosing procedure will be documented in source data and review by an unblinded monitor. This is a single dose trial. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To establish preliminary evidence for the efficacy of intralesionally injected DUR-928 in patients with psoriasis, as assessed by microplaque assay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Local Psoriasis Severity Index (LPSI): LPSI assessments will be performed by the Principal Investigator or delegate at Screening, Baseline (Day 0, pre-dose), and at each outpatient visit at Day 1, Day 2, Day 7 and Day 14. The effect of DUR-928 in psoriasis will be assessed by the change of Local Plaque Severity Index (LPSI) score as compared to vehicle in this microplaque assay.
Photography: Digital photography of the application sites will be performed at Day 0 at Baseline (pre-dose) and 2 hours post-dose, and at each outpatient visit at Day 1, Day 2, Day 7 and Day 14. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the safety of DUR-928 in patients with psoriasis. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Routine vital sign measurements (blood pressure, heart rate, respiratory rate, temperature) will be measured at screening, pre-dose and 2 hours post-dose (Day 0), and at out-patient visits on Day 1, Day 2, Day 7 and Day 14. 
Physical examination will be performed at screening, pre-dose (Day 0), and at the out-patient visit on Day 14.
Safety Laboratory tests (Chemistry, Hematology and Urinalysis) will be drawn at screening, pre-dose (Day 0), and at out-patient visits on Day 2 and Day 14.
All adverse events will be collected from Screening and continues through to trial completion (Day 14).
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>None</outcome>
      <timepoint>None</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Moderate to severe chronic plaque-type psoriasis;
Duration of Psoriasis of at least 6 months;
Nominated total target plaque(s) must have a total approximate area of at least 562 cm to allow application of the study treatments, and must exclude the face, scalp, shin, genitals, and groin area The total area available for treatment may be split over a maximum of two contralateral plaques of equivalent LPSI, both of which meet the eligibility requirements.
Generally healthy as determined by medical history and physical exam;
BMI less than 35 kg/m2;
Male subjects must agree to use a medically acceptable method of contraception/birth control throughout the study duration and for 90 days after the study is completed; 
Female subjects must be of non-childbearing potential.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Presence of non-plaque psoriasis (ie pustular, erythrodermic).
Presence of other skin condition other than psoriasis, in particular eczema, skin infections or an inherited skin disorder (other than psoriasis) that would interfere with the ability to perform study assessments.
Participation in an investigational drug study within 30 days prior to dosing.
Treatment of target plaque body region with topical medications within 2 weeks prior to dosing and during the study period.  
Treatment with Vitimin A supplements within 2 weeks prior to dosing and during the study period.  
Treatment with any systemic immunosuppressant medication within 6 months  prior to dosing and during the study period.  
Positive tests for HIV, hepatitis B/C, drugs of abuse or alcohol breath-test. 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>10-12 participants will each be administered all 6 treatments: 2 different formulations of study drug, 2 vehicle formulations, one active comparator and one untreated area. The dose will be provided to blinded subjects by unblinded dosing staff. All other site staff will remain blinded to the treatment positions. 

A central randomization schedule will be generated by the INC Research Head of Biometrics personnel – who will have no further involvement in the study. The central Randomization schedule will be provided only to the site dosing administration staff (unblinded) who will be exclusively responsible for administering the doses. Subjects will be assigned a randomization number in sequential order, as their eligibility is confirmed, by blinded site staff (who have no access to the Randomization schedule).
</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table/schedule generated by computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Safety  Safety will be evaluated by assessment of clinical laboratory tests, physical examinations including vital signs, and ECGs, and by the documentation of all spontaneously reported adverse events (AEs). Treatment-emergent AEs will be tabulated by patient.

Efficacy - The effect of DUR-928 in psoriasis will be assessed by the change of LPSI score as compared to vehicle in this microplaque assay. The following evaluations will be made: 
Evaluation of the drug effect within the same formulation: For each formulation within a subjects target plaque, the comparison of drug vs the vehicle will be made by deriving the difference and its 95% Confidence Interval (CI) of the change in LPSI scores by study visit. 
Evaluation of formulation effect: The difference from DUR-928 solution formulation vs DUR-928 suspension formulation within a subjects target plaque(s) will be derived by study visit. 
Microplaque assay sensitivity of the active comparator: The positive effect of the active comparator, Kenalog 'Registered Trademark', on the plaque is expected. The active comparator treatment vs each vehicle treatment and the untreated site will be compared within a subjects target plaque(s).

No formal statistical assumptions or sample size calculations have been made for the study as this is a Proof of Concept study, wherein within each patient the vehicle treatment is compared to the active treatment (self-controlled study) to evaluate the signal of efficacy.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/08/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>31/08/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>21/09/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>9/11/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>12</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>10</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>14/10/2016</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>23/11/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>INC Research</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>159 Port Rd, Hindmarsh 
South Australia, 5007 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>DURECT Corporation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>10260 Bubb Road
Cupertino, CA  95014, USA
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This research project is being conducted to look at how safe, well tolerated and effective a new drug called DUR-928 is when given as an interlesional injection to participants with plaque-type psoriasis. The study will look at comparing the study drugs safety, tolerability and effectiveness as a treatment for psoriasis using 2 different formulations when compared against placebo vehicle formulations, an active comparator and no treatment at all. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Limited</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>129 Glen Osmond Rd
Eastwood SA 5063
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/07/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016-06-476</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>8/06/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Cathy Reid</name>
      <address>CMAX
Level 5, 18a North Terrace,
Adelaide SA 5000
AUSTRALIA
</address>
      <phone>+ 61 8 7088 7900</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 8 7088 7999</fax>
      <email>creid@internode.on.net</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Lucy Phillips</name>
      <address>CMAX
Level 5, 18a North Terrace,
Adelaide SA 5000
AUSTRALIA
</address>
      <phone>+ 61 8 7088 7900</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 8 7088 7999</fax>
      <email>lucy.phillips@cmax.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jemma Lawson</name>
      <address>INC Research
159 Port Road, 
Hindmarsh, SA 5007, Australia 
</address>
      <phone>+61 8 7202 1500</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 7202 1599</fax>
      <email>jemma.lawson@incresearch.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jemma Lawson</name>
      <address>INC Research
159 Port Road, 
Hindmarsh, SA 5007, Australia </address>
      <phone>+61 8 7202 1500</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 7202 1599</fax>
      <email>jemma.lawson@incresearch.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>