<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372535">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/03/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/05/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000796381</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of Adenomyosis on In Vitro Fertilisation - Embryo Transfer (IVF-ET) outcomes.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of sonographically diagnosed adenomyosis on the outcome of In Vitro Fertilisation-Embryo Transfer.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1194-0931 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Adenomyosis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Infertility</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fertility including in vitro fertilisation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Adenomyosis is a condition characterised by the presence of heterotopic endometrial glands and stroma in the myometrium with surrounding myometrial hyperplasia.  Patients undergoing fertility treatment at Monash IVF all have baseline pelvic ultrasound scan.  Patients with Adenomyosis will be identified by ultrasound criteria including a combination of: 
Uterine enlargement in the absence of leiomyomas.
Asymmetric enlargement of the anterior or posterior myometrial wall.
Lack of contour abnormality or mass effect.
Heterogeneous, poorly circumcised areas within the myometrium.
Hyperechoic islands or nodules, finger-like projections or linear striations.
Anechoic lacunae or cysts of varying size.
Increased echo texture of the myometrium.

All patients will undergo a stimulated fertility cycle and invitro-fertilisiation/embryo transfer (IVF ET) at Monash IVF.    The type of fertility cycle will be determined by the patients treating clinician and may be GnRH agonist or GnRH antagonist based, but all cycles must involve an embryo transfer.

Following each embryo transfer (ET), patients will be followed for a maximum of 9 months.  
</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group are those patients undergoing fertility treatment at Monash IVF who have a baseline pelvic ultrasound scan that does not have features to suggest the presence of Adenomyosis.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Live birth rate per IVF-ET cycle in adenomyosis versus no adenomyosis group.

Initial assessment is at 2 weeks folloeing ET with a serum bHCG test to determine whether a biochemical pregnancy exists.  An ultrasound at 6-7 weeks post ET will confirm a live pregnancy.  Live birth will be assessed as they occur or at 9 months.

The primary outcome data is routinely collected by our unit as part of mandatory self reporting of results to the Victorian Assisted Reproductive Treatment Authority (VARTA).  The initial blood test and US is usually done in house and is available from our pathology/radiology provider.  The other outcomes are followed up at the appropriate time by each patients nurse by contacting the patient directly. </outcome>
      <timepoint>9 months following embryo transfer.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Utilisation rate (Number of embryos transferred + Number Frozen/Total oocytes fertilised) per stimulation in adenomyosis versus no adenomyosis group.

The resulst used to assess this outcome are routinely collected by our unit as part of mandatory self-auditing to comply with  Victorian Assisted Reproductive Treatment Authority (VARTA).  The location, quality, quantity and outcome of every embryo and egg managed by our unit is strictly controlled.  All data exists on our patient management system.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month following stimulation cycle</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical pregnancy rate per IVF-ET cycle in adenomyosis versus no adenomyosis group.

A clinical pregnancy is defined as a pregnancy that is located within the intrauterine cavity and proven to have a fetal heart been as seen on US.  This US can occur at any time after 6 weeks gestation.  This data is routinely collected by our unit as part of mandatory self reporting of results to the Victorian Assisted Reproductive Treatment Authority (VARTA).  The other outcomes are followed up at the appropriate time by each patients nurse by contacting the patient directly. </outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months following embryo transfer.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Miscarriage rate per pregnancy in adenomyosis versus no adenomyosis group.

A miscarriage is any clinical pregnancy that is proven to have a fetal heart been as seen on US that does not continue on to a live birth.  This data is routinely collected by our unit.  The unit becomes aware of miscarriages by treating doctors informing the unit, by patients representing for further IVF treatment or by follow up by each patients nurse by contacting the patient directly. </outcome>
      <timepoint>9 months following embryo transfer.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ectopic pregnancy rate per pregnancy in adenomyosis versus no adenomyosis group.

An ectopic pregnancy is any clinical pregnancy that is not found to exist wholly within the uterine cavity.  This data is routinely collected by our unit.  The unit becomes aware of ectopics by treating doctors informing the unit, by patients representing for further IVF treatment or by follow up by each patients nurse by contacting the patient directly. </outcome>
      <timepoint>9 months following embryo transfer.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All women treated for infertility by Monash IVF over the next 2 years who:
1. Are aged 18  45
2. Are on their first egg collection cycle 
3. Have a fresh ET on Day 5 following a down regulation or antagonist cycle
4. Have an US study at Monash Ultrasound for Women within 6 months of IVF-ET (Baseline US)
5. Have any cause of infertility
6. Have complete study data on Monash IVF database (up to birth if pregnant)
7. Used their own eggs


Adenomyosis as diagnosed on ultrasound by a tertiary level COGU or board certified Obstetrician and Gynaecologist using their normal US technique and having findings of any of:
1.  Uterine enlargement in the absence of leiomyomas
2.  Asymmetric enlargement of the anterior or posterior myometrial wall
3.  Lack of contour abnormality or mass effect 
4.  Heterogeneous, poorly circumcised areas within the myometrium
5.  Hyperechoic islands or nodules, finger-like projections or linear striations
6.  Anechoic lacunae or cysts of varying size
7.  Increased echo texture of the myometrium


Cause of Infertility:
1.  Male factor
2.  Endometriosis
3.  Ovulation disorder
4.  Tubal factor
5.  Unexplained
5a.  All cases not able to be accommodated in other group.

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Not within the inclusion criteria.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>On average, IVF pregnancy rates for a day 5 fresh cycle is estimated at 30%.  Sample size calculation for a 10% reduction from a 30% clinical pregnancy rate (power 80% &amp; alpha 0.05) with a 3:1 patient ratio requires 640 patients with no adenomyosis and 220 with adenomyosis.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/01/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>860</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/09/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Monash IVF - Hawthorn - Hawthorn</hospital>
    <hospital>Monash IVF - Clayton - Clayton</hospital>
    <hospital>Monash IVF Geelong - Geelong</hospital>
    <postcode>3122 - Hawthorn</postcode>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
    <postcode>3220 - Geelong</postcode>
    <postcode>3121 - Richmond</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash IVF</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Pelaco Building 1
Level 1, 
21-31 Goodwood Street
Richmond VIC 3121</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Dr Hugo Fernandes</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Suite 9.4, Level 9
89 Bridge Road
Richmond VIC 3121</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Monash IVF</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Pelaco Building 1
Level 1, 
21-31 Goodwood Street
Richmond VIC 3121</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Adenomyosis is a condition characterised by the presence of endometrial lining/glands and stroma in the muscle wall of the uterus with surrounding swelling.   Typically patients present clinically with a combination of abnormal uterine bleeding, secondary period pain and a tender enlarged uterus in the fourth and fifth decades of life.   Infertility is a less common presentation, however as many women are delaying having children into their late thirties and fourties, adenomyosis is increasingly encountered during the clinical work up of infertile women.   A definitive link between adenomyosis and infertility has not been established, however several studies have demonstrated a strong association between the two.   A recent study looking at uterine wall thickness found that in vitro fertilisation and embryo transfer (IVF-ET) outcomes decreased with increasing uterine wall thickness and findings suggestive of adenomyosis, however two small trials of IVF-ET in patients with adenomyosis found no difference in pregnancy outcomes compared to matched cases. ,   There is therefore limited and conflicting evidence for the effectiveness of IVF-ET in patients with adenomyosis.

The aim of this trial is to evaluate the outcomes of IVF-ET (InVitro Fertilisation - Embryo Transfer)  in patients with an ultrasound diagnosis of adenomyosis.

The primary hypotheses are that:
1.  IVF-ET success rates (clinical pregnancy &amp; live-births) will be different in women with adenomyosis compared to those without adenomyosis based on ultrasound.
2.  That the above finding will be true regardless of whether adenomyosis is the only cause or one of multiple causes of infertility in the female.

The secondary hypotheses are that:
1.  The presence of adenomyosis will be associated with altered
1a.  Implantation rates.
1b.  Miscarriage rates per clinical pregnancy.
1c.  Ectopic pregnancy rates per clinical pregnancy.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not required</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>This study was presented to our relevant ethics committee for evaluation.  It was determined by them that as the data that is being used at all points within our study is already routinely collected from patients AND there was no intervention or alteration to the patients treatment, then this study was considered an audit of practice.  Further, when patients are treated by our unit, their signed contract states that treatment and outcome data is collected as part of a mandatory reporting requirement of VARTA, but also to be used in an unidentified manner for audit and research.</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hugo Fernandes</name>
      <address>Monash IVF
Suite 9.4, Level 9
Epworth Hospital
89 Bridge Road
Richmond VIC 3121</address>
      <phone>+61 03 9516 2895</phone>
      <fax>+61 03 9421 5932</fax>
      <email>research@drhugo.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hugo Fernandes</name>
      <address>Monash IVF
Suite 9.4, Level 9
Epworth Hospital
89 Bridge Road
Richmond VIC 3121</address>
      <phone>+61 03 9516 2895</phone>
      <fax>+61 03 9421 5932</fax>
      <email>research@drhugo.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hugo Fernandes</name>
      <address>Monash IVF
Suite 9.4, Level 9
Epworth Hospital
89 Bridge Road
Richmond VIC 3121</address>
      <phone>+61 03 9516 2895</phone>
      <fax>+61 03 9421 5932</fax>
      <email>research@drhugo.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hugo Fernandes</name>
      <address>Monash IVF
Suite 9.4, Level 9
Epworth Hospital
89 Bridge Road
Richmond VIC 3121</address>
      <phone>+61 03 9516 2895</phone>
      <fax>+61 03 9421 5932</fax>
      <email>research@drhugo.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>