<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369228">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/09/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/10/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001026516</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Provision of breathing support during delayed cord clamping in preterm infants.  </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In preterm infants &lt;31 weeks receiving delayed cord clamping (DCC) at birth but who do not concurrently establish spontaneous ventilation, does breathing support during DCC versus no breathing support during DCC effect the volume of placental transfusion and cardiovascular stabilisation. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>The ABC Study: 'Assisted breathing before cord clamping"</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Prematurity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anemia requiring red blood cell transfusion</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Intraventricular haemorrage</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Complications of newborn</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the cardiovascular system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In addition to standard treatment, breathing support in the form of positive pressure ventilation (PPV) and continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) delivered by mask and pressure controlled device. Infants will be randomised at 15 sec of age once their breathing has been assessed. Breathing support will begin at 20sec of age, will be continued for a duration of 30sec; the intervention will take place while 50 sec DCC is occuring (cord clamping to take place at 50sec of age). ILCOR and NZ resuscitation guidelines will be adhered to (initial positive pressure will be 20-25 cm water and CPAP 5-8cm water). 
The intervention received will be recorded on a data capture sheet including PPV time period in seconds received and or CPAP time period in seconds.  </interventions>
    <comparator>Standard treatment consists of: position (placed on back, head placed in neutral position) and thermal wrap during 50 sec delayed cord clamping</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Red blood transfusion rates
Assessed by reviewing hospital records of red blood cell transfusions received, number received, age of first transfusion in days. The study centre's red cell transfusion guideline will remain unchanged during the study and guideline adherance will be monitored. Infants transferred to other hospitals for surgery or ongoing care will be excluded from primary outcome analysis as so to avoid differing red cell transfusion guidelines.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From birth to time of discharge from neonatal admission</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Endotracheal intubation (ETT) and surfactant received.
Type and dose received will be recorded on designed data capture sheets at the bedside and verified from hospital records</outcome>
      <timepoint>First 24hours of life </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Temperature after the procedure measured by digital underarm thermometer and recorded on designed data capture sheet</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 5min of age </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Transitional circulation assessed by echocardiogram within first 24 hours of age, data collected from hospital records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>One echocardiogram assessment will be done at (6 to 12 hours of age if possibe) &lt; 24hours of age. Inotropic support (type, dose and length of treatment in hours) during the first 24hours after birth. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phototherapy received as recorded in hospital records and entered on designed data capture sheet</outcome>
      <timepoint>First week of life</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length and type of ventilation support as documented in hospital records and entered on designed data capture sheet</outcome>
      <timepoint>From birth to time of discharge from neonatal admission</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Chronic lung diease defined as respiratory support or oxygen at 36 week corrected gestational age as documented in hospital records and designed data capture sheets</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 36 week corrected gestational age</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intraventricular haemorrage grades 3 &amp; 4 as reported in hospital records and defined by ANZNN coding criteria</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 5 and day 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neurodevelopmental outcome as assessed at 2 year of age (Bayley III score) at Neonatal Clinic (current standard practice for infants born equal or &lt;29 weeks</outcome>
      <timepoint> 2 years of age</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Necrotising enterocolitis (NEC), defined by modified Bells stage 2 or higher as reported in hospital records 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Birth to discharge from neonatal admission</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Retinopathy of prematurity (ROP), requiring laser therapy as recorded in hospital records
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Birth to discharge from neonatal admission</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Late onset sepsis (LOS) defined by positive blood culture or CSF after 48hours as recorded in hospital records
</outcome>
      <timepoint>From 48hours of age to discharge from neonatal admission</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Death as recorded in hospital records
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Birth to discharge from neonatal admission</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of hospital stay in days as recorded in hospital records</outcome>
      <timepoint>Birth to discharge from neonatal admission</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Infants born &lt;31 week gestation and undergoing delayed cord clamping (DCC); born by vaginal or caeserean section and deemed not to have regular rhythmic breathing (chest wall movement) after 15sec of DCC.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Infants born equal or &gt; 31 week gestation, known congenital abnormality, twin-to-twin transfusion syndrome, severe antenatal intrauterine growth restriction (estimated fetal weight &lt;10th customised centile), placental abruption, delivery of placenta and infant simultaneously (en caul), short umbilical cord, obsterician refusal, declined antenatal consent.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Parents will be given a written information sheet about the study by a study member before labour where possible. In cases where active labour is in progress and consent before birth is not possible, deferred consent for study entry is proposed. Eligible infants that receive DCC will be randomised at 15 sec of age once the breathing has been assessed. 
Study groups and management: A standard treatment arm will be compared to an intervention arm. Standard treatment consists of: position (placed on their back, head in neutral position), and thermal wrap during 50sec delayed cord clamping.
Interventional treatment: In addition to the standard treatment above, breathing support in the form of intermittent positive pressure ventilation (PPV) and continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) delivered by mask and pressure controlled device.  
Randomisation: Randomisation will occur via sequentially numbered opaque sealed envelopes.  A card folded within the envelope will state whether the infant is to receive standard treatment (no breathing support) or breathing support (intervention) during delayed cord clamping. After delivery these cards will be attached to the data collection sheet. The infants study number will be documented in the clinical notes. Groups will be stratified into 24-25, equal/&gt; 26-27, equal/&gt;28 -29 and equal/&gt;29 week gestation.
Blinding:  The attending resuscitation team will not disclose to clinicians whether infants received respiratory support during DCC or not. 
</concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted block randomisation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Analysis will be carried out on an intention to treat basis. IBM statistics for data analysis version 22.0 will be used. Non-parametric data will be analysed using Mann-Whitney U while categorical variables will be compared using Pearson Chi-Square. Infants enrolled in the study will be stratified into groups [&lt;26, equal/&gt;26-27.6, equal/ &gt;28 -30.6]. 

Our observational data indicated that 60% of infants that received DCC and did not breathe received a RBC transfusion. Aiming for a 50% reduction in RBC transfusion, would require 100 infants whose primary outcome can be assessed. This would give the study 80% power at a significance level of 0.05. For a secondary composite outcome of death, CLD or severe IVH, the sample size would allow a 36% difference in outcome to be detected (80% power, significance 0.05). We plan to randomise 60 infants to each group. Based on mortality of 15% this will allow for the loss of 10 infants per group and result in 50 infants per group whose primary outcome can be determined. Our average admission rate is 70 &lt;31 week infants per year, and, estimating that 50% of infants do not breathe regularly by 15secs of age, the length of this study will be approximately  3 years.  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>17/03/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>17/03/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Middlemore Hospital </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Middlemore Hospital
Hospital Rd
Otahuhu, Auckland
New Zealand 1640</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ko Awatea Project Fund (called Tupu fund): awarded by Counties Manukau Health, Middlemore Hospital, Research Office</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Middlemore Hospital
Ko Awatea
Private Bag 93311 
Otahuhu
Auckland
New Zealand 1640</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The amount of placental transfusion (PLT) preterm infants receive at birth with the umbilical cord intact has been shown to have important effects on the transitional circulation in the first 24-48hrs of life. Not only does PLT effect the requirement for red blood cell (RBC) transfusions in the neonatal period but also alters important long-term neonatal outcomes such as intraventricular haemorrhage (IVH) and chronic lung disease (CLD). Observational work from Middlemore Neonatal Unit demonstrated that preterm infants that breathe during delayed cord clamping(DCC) receive a larger PLT and have significantly less CLD and less severe (grade 4) IVH than infants that did not breathe during the procedure. Similarly, a study in term infants showed lower mortality in infants that breathed during DCC. A preterm animal model showed improved cerebral circulation during transition in lambs that were ventilated during DCC. These studies suggest that establishing respiration during DCC could protect the most vulnerable preterm infants from the under perfusion-reperfusion cycle which leads to IVH. In addition, because respiration during DCC enhances PLT it is hypothesised that the requirement for blood transfusion will be reduced. Therefore, important health benefits and reduced costs together with improved long term outcomes could result and positively impact on the quality of life for the prematurely born infant and their families. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern A District Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
PO Box 5013
Wellington 
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/12/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>15/NTA/146</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/09/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Elizabeth Nevill</name>
      <address>Neonatal Care
Middlemore Hospital
Private Bag 93311
Otahuhu
Auckland 1640</address>
      <phone>+64 9 2760044 EXT 8365 / +64 21300877</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 2760091</fax>
      <email>elizabeth.nevill@cmdhb.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Elizabeth Nevill</name>
      <address>Neonatal Care
Middlemore Hospital
Private Bag 93311
Otahuhu
Auckland 1640</address>
      <phone>+64 9 2760044 EXT 8365 /+64 21300877</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 2760091</fax>
      <email>elizabeth.nevill@cmdhb.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Elizabeth Nevill</name>
      <address>Neonatal Care
Middlemore Hospital
Private Bag 93311
Otahuhu
Auckland 1640</address>
      <phone>+64 9 2760044 EXT 8365 / +64 21300877</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 2760091</fax>
      <email>elizabeth.nevill@cmdhb.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Elizabeth Nevill</name>
      <address>Neonatal Care
Middlemore Hospital
Private Bag 93311
Otahuhu
Auckland 1640</address>
      <phone>+64 9 2760044 EXT 8365 /+64 21300877</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 2760091</fax>
      <email>elizabeth.nevill@cmdhb.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>