<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365563">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/01/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/01/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000088640</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Spironolactone in myocardial dysfunction with reduced exercise capacity</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of spironolactone or control on LV filling pressure and exercise capacity in patients with myocardial dysfunction with reduced exercise capacity</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>STRUCTURE</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Heart Failure</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Oral spironolactone will be administered in a dose of 25 mg daily for 6 months. Patients will be reviewed and serum electrolytes will be performed after a week, then monthly for 3 months, then at the end of the study: study medication will be withheld in the presence of hyperkalemia (&gt;5.4 mmol/l), renal impairment (creatinine &gt;0.18 mmol/l) or unacceptable side-effects. Adherence will be monitored by tablet counts.</interventions>
    <comparator>Microcellulose 120 mg daily for 6 months</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Exercise capacity measured by peak oxygen uptake and metabolic equivalents (from treadmill exercise time) at incremental treadmill exercise test to exhaustion. </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after initiation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>LV filling pressure estimated from echo-Doppler assessment of E/e' </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after initiation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Avoidance of a hypertensive response to exercise measured by blood pressure assessed using a cuff sphygmomanometer during treadmill exercise test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after initiation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvements in myocardial deformation measure by echocardiography</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after initiation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients with exercise intolerance, who are found to demonstrate increased E/E at exercise echo with reduced exercise capacity. Exercise intolerance will be defined by exercise capacity reduced from published normal ranges. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(1) atrial fibrillation
(2) ischemia evidenced by angina or a positive diagnostic test (3) patients already on spironolactone
(4) patients with renal impairment (creatinine &gt; 1.5 mg/dl) or hyperkalaemia (&gt; 5.5 mmol/L).  </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sequentially-numbered, opaque, sealed envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerized </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>1. In patients with IFPE, treatment with spironolactone causes an improvement in exercise capacity. 
An improvement in exercise capacity will be identified in the treatment group shows significant improvement of exercise time compared with placebo at paired t-testing. The contribution of therapy to exercise time independent of other variables (including strain and backscatter indices, age and other drugs) will be examined by multiple linear regression. 
2. In patients with IFPE, treatment with spironolactone causes an improvement in post-exercise filling pressure. 
An improvement in exercise capacity will be identified in the treatment group shows significant improvement of E/e compared with placebo at paired t-testing. The contribution of therapy independent of other variables (including strain and backscatter indices, age and other drugs) will be examined by multiple linear regression. 
3. Reduction of IFPE is due to avoidance of a hypertensive response to exercise
This will be confirmed if exercise systolic BP is lower (t-test as continuous variable) or a hypertensive response to exercise (chi-square of a categorical variable, &gt;220/100 in men and 200/100 in women) is less frequent in patients showing reduced E/E by each intervention. A general linear model will be used to identify whether exercise systolic BP is an independent correlate of a reduction in IFPE.
4. Reduction of IFPE is due to improvements in myocardial deformation properties
This will be confirmed if average myocardial strain rate is greater (t-test as continuous variable) in patients showing reduced E/E by each intervention than those who do not. A general linear model will be used to identify whether a change in strain rate is independently associated with reduction in filling pressure, independent of other haemodynamic responses.

Sample size: Sample size calculations have been calculated (Sample Power, release 1.2, SPSS Inc) based on the primary hypotheses. To our knowledge, this will be the first intervention trial with spironolactone with an exercise endpoint in this population, so the effect sizes are obtained from a 1 minute (~15%) increment in treadmill time from ACE/ARB therapy in our recent experience and an 18% increment of myocardial strain in our previous spironolactone study in our recent experience. Assuming a 15% effect size, and a standard deviation of 30% of exercise capacity, we will need 65 patients/group to show a difference in exercise capacity. To allow for a dropout of 15%, we will recruit 150 patients. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/11/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/02/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>1/02/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>150</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>TAS</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Hobart Hospital - Hobart</hospital>
    <postcode>7000 - Hobart</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Menzies Research Institute Tasmania, University of Tasmania</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>17 Liverpool Street
Hobart, TAS 7000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Department of Cardiology
Wroclaw Medical University
</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Wybrzeze L. Pasteura 1, 
50-367 Wroclaw
Poland</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Poland</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The main aim of this study is to use aldosterone blockade for the treatment of exercise intolerance in the presence of diastolic dysfunction (DD) and preserved LV systolic function. The responses will be sought by measurement of: 1) exercise capacity, 2) techniques to quantify myocardial structure and function. 
Our primary hypotheses are that spironolactone therapy is associated with improved; 1. Exercise capacity by reduction of myocardial fibrosis and improvement in LV compliance with aldosterone blockade, 2. Post-exercise LV filling pressure. 
Our secondary hypotheses are that spironolactone therapy is associated with; 3. Avoidance of a hypertensive response to exercise, 4. Improvements in myocardial deformation properties.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Medical Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Research Services, University of Tasmania, Private Bag 1, Hobart, TAS, 7001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/01/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H0012926</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Thomas H Marwick</name>
      <address>Menzies Research Institute Tasmania
17 Liverpool St
Hobart, Tas 7000</address>
      <phone>+61 (0) 3 6226 7703</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tom.marwick@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Leah Wright</name>
      <address>Menzies Research Institute Tasmania
17 Liverpool St
Hobart, Tas 7000</address>
      <phone>+61 (0) 3 6226 7703</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>leah.wright@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Thomas H Marwick</name>
      <address>Menzies Research Institute Tasmania
17 Liverpool St
Hobart, Tas 7000</address>
      <phone>+61 (0) 3 6226 7703</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tom.marwick@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Leah Wright</name>
      <address>Menzies Research Institute Tasmania
17 Liverpool St
Hobart, Tas 7000</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)3 6226 7703</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>leah.wright@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>