<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370419">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/04/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/04/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000492459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The prophylactic potential of a Mediterranean dietary pattern enriched with oily fish  in improving respiratory function in asthmatic children.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The prophylactic potential of a Mediterranean dietary pattern enriched with oily fish  in improving respiratory function in asthmatic children: a randomized control trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1181-3989</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NONE</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>CHILDHOOD ASTHMA</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Asthma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the respiratory system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention group will be instructed to consume 2 fatty fish meals (150g cooked fish) per week over a period of 6 months. Prior to commencement participants will be provided with an information sheet and consent form. At baseline  and at 6 months during usual medical consultations, parents of participants will complete socio-demographics, Asthma Control Questionnaire, Quality of life and  food frequency questionnaires (requiring approximately 30 mins). During enrolment, a  telephone-interview  (lasting approximately 60 minutes) will be  conducted by the dietitian to collect medical, dietary and lifestyle information. Dietary advice based on the Greek Mediterranean dietary guidelines ( Greek Ministry of Health &amp; Welfare, 1999) including  instructions on the dietary intervention will be explained to parents. Participants will be monitored by fortnightly telephone calls and e-mails from the dietitian to address any problems relating to dietary adherence.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will continue with their usual dietary habits which are in accordance with the Traditional Greek Mediterranean diet. At baseline and at 6 months during usual medical consultations, parents will complete socio-demographic, Asthma Control Questionnaire, Quality of life and food frequency questionnaires. At both time-points, telephone-interviews will be conducted by the dietitian (lasting approximately 60 minutes) to collect medical and dietary information.  Patients will be monitored by fortnightly telephone calls and e-mails from the dietitian until the end of the study. At the end of 6 months, the child and their family will have a personalized consultation with the dietitian and will be provided with an information brochure on general healthy eating guidelines (Greek Mediterranean dietary guidelines (Greek Ministry of Health and Welfare, 1999) .</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Respiratory function as assessed by spirometry (FEV1, FVC, FEV1/FVC, predicted FEV1) and bronchial inflammation by exhaled Nitric Oxide (eNO) analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline and 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite outcome of the number of asthma episodes and severity of asthma as assessed by parent's and doctor's report. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Evaluated at baseline  and 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Asthma Control assessed by Asthma Control (ACQ) questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence to dietary intervention evaluated using multiple food recalls ( 3 recalls) administered via telephone.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, 3 months and at 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dietary habits evaluated using a Food Frequency Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline and at 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life using Paediatric Quality of Life questionnaire(PQOL)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline and at 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in plasma omega 3 fatty acid composition assessed by serum assay</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline and at 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in antioxidant level assessed by serum assay</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Physician-diagnosed asthma</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>5</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>12</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Children suffering from Cystic Fibrosis, Gerd, food allergies, or chronic illnesses requiring regular treatment with  medication which may affect participation, chronic use of anti-inflammatory medications, unable or unwilling to modify diet,   including psychiatric or behavioural disorders. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomization will be carried out by an independent private statistican and the participant's group allocation and number will be provided to the research dietitian on enrolment, who will provided participants with the appropriate dietary instructions.

</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomization will be conducted by an independent private statistitian using a computerised random number generator in variable block sizes, stratified by age group.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>G Power Analysis was used to determine sample size.  Sample size calculation was undertaken using a medium effect size of 0.40,  with 90% power and significance level of 0.05.  which produced a sample size of 52 participants. But allowing for  a 20% drop out rate gave  a final total sample size of 64 participants.
Data analysis will be performed using SPSS IBM Inc. Quantitative variables will be analyzed using Anova and qualitative variables by Chi square tests.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>11/11/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>64</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Attiki</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>La Trobe University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>La Trobe University
Department of Rehabilitation, Nutrition and Sport
School of Allied Health
Bundoora, 3086
Victoria Australia
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>La Trobe University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>La Trobe University
Department of Rehabilitation, Nutrition and Sport
School of Allied Health
Bundoora, 3086
Victoria Australia
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr.Charis Katsardis</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Private Pediatric Respiratory Allergy Clinic 
1 Pafou St
Marousi
Athens, 15125
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Greece</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Doctor Dimitris Tsoukalas</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Metabolomic Clinic
5 Koumbari Street
Kolonaki Square
Athens
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Greece</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Globally, asthma has become one of the most frequent chronic diseases in children during the past two to three decades. Furthermore, it is a debilitating disease and is one of the most common reasons for hospitalization and days absent from school. The change in dietary habits has been implicated in causing childhood asthma.  Observational studies revealed that adherence to a Mediterranean type diet by children was inversely associated with asthma symptoms. More specifically, some studies performed to date have reported that  fish in the childs diet was associated with reduced risk of  wheeze and asthma, whereas others not. However, clinical trials investigating the effect of fish consumption in asthmatic children are limited.  Therefore, there is a need for further investigation in order to clarify whether fish is a useful therapy for childhood asthma.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Latrobe University Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Latrobe University
Bundoora, 3086
Victoria
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/07/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HEC 16-035</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/04/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Catherine Itsiopoulos</name>
      <address>La Trobe University
Department of Rehabilitation, Nutrition and Sport
School of Allied Health
Bundoora, 3086
Victoria
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94791721</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 3 94792552</fax>
      <email>C.itsiopoulos@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Charis Katsardis</name>
      <address>Private Pediatric Respiratory Allergy Clinic
1 Pafou St
Marousi
Athens, 15125</address>
      <phone>+ 30-210-9322946</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>katsardis@yahoo.gr</email>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Charis Katsardis</name>
      <address>Private Pediatric Respiratory Allergy Clinic
1 Pafou Street
Marousi
Athens, 15125 
Greece</address>
      <phone>+30-210-9322946</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>katsardis@yahoo.gr</email>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Maria Papamichael</name>
      <address>La Trobe University
Department of Rehabilitation, Nutrition and Sport
School of Allied Health
Bundoora, 3086
Victoria
</address>
      <phone>+61 03 97875867</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sassipap@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>