<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366557">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/06/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/06/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000671662</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Conservative management of first carpometacarpal (CMC) joint osteoarthritis: a single blinded randomised controlled trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Clinical outcomes of adults with first carpometacarpal (CMC) joint osteoarthritis treated with either a push brace orthosis, corticosteroid injection, a basic hand therapy program or a combination of interventions</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Osteoarthritis of the first Carpometacarpal joint (of the thumb)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Occupational therapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention Group 1: Basic hand therapy program including a standardised exercise program (20 minutes once or twice daily for as long as found beneficial by the participant), advice on pain management including thermal modalities, joint protection and activity modification provided in a 45 minute one-off consultation with a qualified occupational therapist AND Push brace orthosis fitted by a qualified occupational therapist.

Intervention Group 2:  Basic hand therapy program (as above) AND Ultra-sound guided Corticosteriod injection (1mL of celestone chronodose and 1mL 0.5% marcaine) to the CMC joint (of the thumb) provided by a qualified radiologist

Intervention Group 3: Basic hand therapy program (as above) AND Push brace orthosis (as above) AND Ultra-sound guided Corticosteriod injection (as above)</interventions>
    <comparator>Control Group 1: Basic hand therapy program including a standardised exercise program (20 minutes once or twice daily for as long as found beneficial by the participant), advice on pain management including thermal modalities, joint protection and activity modification provided in a 45 minute one-off consultation with a qualified occupational therapist.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain measured using a 100 point (10 cm) visual analogue scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (pre-intervention); 3 months; 6 months; 12 months; 24 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Osteoarthritis Disease specific outcome Measure (AUSCAN Hand Osteoarthritis Index)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (pre-intervention); 3 months; 6 months; 12 months 24 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Function using Patient Rated Wrist and Hand Evaluation</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (pre-intervention); 3 months; 6 months; 12 months 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pinch Strength using a Pinch Gauge</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (pre-intervention); 3 months; 6 months; 12 months 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Global improvement measured using a Global Rating of Change Scale for symptoms and function</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (pre-intervention); 3 months; 6 months; 12 months 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health rated quality of life measured using the EQ-5D</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (pre-intervention); 3 months; 6 months; 12 months 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse events for the thumb orthosis which could include allergic dermatitis, skin maceration, pressure areas or heat rash.

Adverse events for the injection could include allergic reaction, abnormal systemic responses, dizziness, nausea, cognitive dysfunction.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (pre-intervention); 3 months; 6 months; 12 months 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1- 18 years and over
2- Clinical diagnosis of primary idiopathic 1st CMC joint osteoarthritis
3- Minimal level of symptoms either a pain score of at least 30 (out of 100) on VAS or 9 or higher (out of 40) on the AUSCAN function sub scale
 </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1- Inflammatory joint conditions including rheumatoid arthritis and gout
2- Significant untreated Dupuytren's Disease resulting in severely impaired function
3- History of previous conservative management of 1st CMC joint arthritis including use of a splint within the last 3 months
4- History of corticosteriod injection or Hyaluronate injection in either of the hands
5- Previous soft tissue injury or fracture of the thumb or wrist joints that has resulted in significant function limitation
6- Pregnancy
7- High medical dependency that may interfere with ability to return for assessments or compliance with interventions
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The study patient population will be recruited from the private consulting practices of the orthopaedic surgeons at the Brisbane Hand and Upper Limb Clinic at the Brisbane Private Hospital.  Once a participant has consented and completed their pre-treatment assessment, the patient will be randomised and allocated to an intervention group. This will be done by a research assistant who will not be blind to allocation for the duration of the study. They will open an envelope and reveal the allocation to the patient. They will then make referrals to hand therapy for orthosis and/or to the referring surgeon for the injection as required. </concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation sequence will be computer generated and concealed in sequentially numbered sealed, opaque envelopes by a person, not otherwise associated with this research, to eliminate any risk of randomisation/recruitment bias. Each envelope will contain a sheet of paper with the intervention group.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Factorial</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Baseline demographic and clinical data will be reported using descriptive statistics and will be tabulated. Between groups differences in baseline data will be examined using unpaired conventional tests of hypothesis depending on the nature of the data. Between group and within group differences in outcome measures over time will be examined using a priori unpaired and paired conventional tests of hypothesis depending on the nature of the data.  Linear mixed effects models will be used to examine the within and between group variability of the four groups. Bonferroni adjustments for multiple comparisons will be made where appropriate to mitigate risk of type-1 error.  
The complication rates will be reported in terms of frequency. The frequencies of complications will be compared using statistical analysis such as the Pearson chi-square statistic. 

160 participants will be recruited in the study (40 allocated to each group).

Recruitment is anticipated to take approximately 60 weeks based on historical patient presentation rate of this patient group and a 75% recruitment rate into the study. 
 
In calculating our sample size we have allowed for:
1.      30% loss to follow up
2.      Historical information from our unit that 25% of patients who are offered conservative management for this condition opt for surgery within 3 months.
 
This investigation has 95% power to detect a between group mean (SD) difference in the primary outcome pain (VAS) of 17 (3).
 </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/08/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>160</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Brisbane Private Hospital - Brisbane</hospital>
    <postcode>4000 - Brisbane</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Brisbane Hand and Upper Limb Research Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>9/259 Wickham Terrace, Brisbane, QLD 4000
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Brisbane Hand and Upper Limb Research Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>9/259 Wickham Terrace, Brisbane, QLD 4000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Arthritis at the base of the thumb is common in ageing adults.  It can result in pain and impact on function and quality of life. There are many treatments available to help relieve pain and improve hand function. Currently, it is common practice in Australia and overseas for health care providers (such as General Practitioners, Surgeons, Rheumatologists and Hand Therapists) to initially recommend non-surgical/conservative treatments for their patients. Treatments can include splinting the joint to relieve pain and enable hand function; injection of corticosteroid into the joint to reduce inflammation and provide pain relief; and hand therapy to provide exercises and patient education to inform on strategies for protecting the joints, managing pain and improving function. Preliminary research on these types of treatments has had mixed results, yet, health care professionals continue to offer these as treatments. This study will compare the effectiveness of the following non-surgical treatments: Push BraceTM splint; corticosteroid injection; and hand therapy treatment in relieving symptoms and improving function in adults with osteoarthritis at the base of the thumb. There has been no previous randomised controlled trial comparing the outcomes of these types of treatments. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Mater Human Research and Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>17/06/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Mark Ross</name>
      <address>Brisbane Hand and Upper Limb Research Institute
9/259 Wickham Terrace 
Brisbane 
QLD 4000</address>
      <phone>+ 61 7 3834 7069</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>research@upperlimb.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Susan Peters</name>
      <address>Brisbane Hand and Upper Limb Research Institute
9/259 Wickham Terrace
Brisbane 
QLD 4000</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3834 7069</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>research@upperlimb.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Susan Peters</name>
      <address>Brisbane Hand and Upper Limb Research Institute
9/259 Wickham Terrace
Brisbane 
QLD 4000</address>
      <phone>+ 61 7 3834 7069</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>research@upperlimb.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Susan Peters</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>