<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82334">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/10/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/10/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000535471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) Controlled Trial Investigation Of a Non-stimulant (A.C.T.I.O.N).</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised Controlled Trial Investigation of Atomoxetine in Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ACTION</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Phase A: 0.5 mg/kg atomoxetine, oral, once daily for one week; then 1.0 mg/kg atomoxetine, oral, once daily for 5 weeks. One week washout, crossover. Phase B: 6 weeks of identical looking placebo capsules. Randomised to receive Phase A or B first.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo (starch, silicone), identical capsule/markings.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 1: Inhibitory Capacity indexed by a computerised (IntegNeuro) 'Stroop'-like test (interference score).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: baseline, week 6 and week 13</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 2: Emotional Recognition indexed by computerised (IntegNeuro) emotion detection/reaction time test (happy, fear, sad, angry, disgust &amp; neutrual faces).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: baseline, week 6 and week 13</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 1: relationship between primary outcome measures and diagnostic features (externalising and internalising)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: baseline, week 6 and week 13</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Males and females between the ages of 8 and 16 years, of normal weight and height, with a primary diagnosis of ADHD will be eligible for inclusion in the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>8</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>16</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Individuals will not be admitted to the study if any of the following criteria are present: (1) long history of prescribed medications not related to ADHD; (2) current stimulant use; (3) any medical condition or disease that might interfere with the assessments (e.g. hearing impairment) or put them at increased risk when exposed to atomoxetine (e.g., cardiac irregularities); (4) any psychiatric or neurological condition, such as, seizure disorder, bipolar disorder, and schizophrenia (not including ADHD with common comorbidities such as internalising, externalizing and learning disorders); (5) consumption of two or more standard alcoholic drinks per day; (6) other drug abuse or extensive drug use; (7) any experimental drug within the past four months (prior to the study); (8) drug hypersensitivity or anaphylaxis; (9) heavy caffeine use (more than 4 cups of coffee or equivalent per day); (10) users of nicotine; (11) in the opinion of the investigator the subject is unable and/or unlikely to comprehend and follow the study procedures and instructions (12) do not sign informed consent (with parents/guardians) prior to study entry (13) do not agree to participation information and preparation requirements; (14) do not complete the demographic questionnaire; (15) not English literate.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation Concealment: Centralised (pair-wise) randomisation.</concealment>
    <sequence>centralised pairwise randomisation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>180</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Westmead Hospital, Sydney West Area Health Service</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Hawkesbury Road, Westmead, NSW, 2145</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NMHRC Project Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health &amp; Medical Research Council</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) is defined by marked changes in both cognitive and emotional functions. The majority of medicated ADHD individuals are treated with stimulants (controlled substances). Up to 30% do not respond to stimulant treatment, and in others the potential for abuse remains. Atomoxetine is a recently approved non-stimulant (non-controlled) to treat ADHD, with evidence of clinical effectiveness. Yet, the impact of atomoxetine on objective measures of a range of cognitive and emotional function has not been studied. Several lines of evidence indicate it is effective for these functions. Atomoxetine has been shown to alleviate inhibitory capacity, while stimulants have not. Common disturbances may underlie abnormal inhibitory capacity and impaired emotional recognition in ADHD that is best treated with atomoxetine rather than stimulants. The primary aims of this project are to: (1) Examine the efficacy of a non-stimulant medication (atomoxetine) in ADHD using a randomised controlled design. (2) Demonstrate that atomoxetine has efficacy for both cognitive and emotional functions, assessed using objective tests, with indicators of clinical improvement. The outcomes from this project will be a significant step towards a 'personalised medicine' approach to ADHD, providing clinicians with increased options in the treatment of ADHD. Should atomoxetine prove to be efficacious for stimulant non-responders it would contribute to reducing the significant social and financial burden of this disorder.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Michael Kohn</name>
      <address>Faculty of Medicine C29
C/O Children's Hospital Westmead,
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>02 9845 2446</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michaek2@chw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Michael Kohn</name>
      <address>Faculty of Medicine C29
C/O Children's Hospital Westmead,
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>02 9845 2446</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michaek2@chw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>