<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362215">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/03/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/03/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000360819</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Postprandial glycaemia and satiety in Asian type 2 diabetics</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Postprandial glycaemia and satiety in response to a rice and a rice mix meal in Asian people with type 2 diabetes</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1129-0183</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 diabetes mellitus</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>It is important for people with type 2 diabetes to keep blood glucose concentrations under control. Many Asians eat rice as a staple food and are reluctant to change dietary habits. We would bulk rice up with foods that elicit a smaller glycaemic response than the rice (beans, peas, corn grits, whole barley, whole oats) as an acceptable alternative to rice alone. Our hypothesis is that for equal sized portions, the mixed grains would elicit a smaller post-meal glycaemic response. The intervention will comprise participants consuming two cups of white rice or two cups of a rice mix that includes other grains and legumes. The meals will be consumed one week apart and the order that the meals will be eaten will be randomized to each participant. The meals will be cooked and served as an evening meal and consumed at the study premises.</interventions>
    <comparator>This is a crossover study in which each participant acts as his or her own control. Postprandial glycaemia measured three hours after eating a meal consisting of rice, other grains and legumes will be compared with postprandial glycaemia following the consumption of a meal of white rice. The comparator and control meals will have the same volume of two cups. There will be one week between treatments.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postprandial blood glucose concentration as assessed by Hemocue glucose meter using capillary blood</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurements taken at fixed intervals for 3 hours after eating. Capillary blood will be sampled before eating the meal (time 0 or baseline) and subsequently at 15, 30, 45, 60, 90, 120,150 and 180 min after eating.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postprandial satiety as assessed by visual analogue scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurements taken at fixed intervals for 3 hours after eating. Visual analogue scales will be filled in before eating the meal (time 0 or baseline) and subsequently at 30, 60, 90, 120,150 and 180 min after eating.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Asian people living in Auckland, New Zealand diagnosed with type 2 diabetes mellitus</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Diagnosis of cardiovascular disease, cancer, or diseases of the gastrointestinal system. Diabetes mellitus requiring insulin.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>People on a diabetes register will be invited to participate. The person enrolling the participants will be unaware of which treatment (rice or the rice mix) the participant will be started on. Treatment allocation will be managed by another investigator based on a predetermined randomization. ie: as participants are enrolled he or she will receive a study ID from 1 to 36. The order in which each participant consumes the meals will be held on a computer remote from the person enrolling the participants. Eighteen of the participants will have rice as the first meal and 18 the rice mix as the first meal.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using a randomization table created by computer software</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>36</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Otago</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Human Nutrition
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Otago</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Human Nutrition
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Greenlane Clinical Centre</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>214 Green Lane West
One Tree Hill
Auckland 1051</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>It is important for people with type 2 diabetes to keep blood glucose concentrations under control. Many Asians eat rice as a staple food and are reluctant to change dietary habits. We would bulk rice up with foods that elicit a smaller glycaemic response than the rice (beans, peas, corn grits, whole barley, whole oats) as an acceptable alternative to rice alone. Our hypothesis is that for equal sized portions, the mixed grains would elicit a smaller post-meal glycaemic response.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Otago Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Academic committees
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/02/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1/12/0003</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Bernard Venn</name>
      <address>Department of Human Nutrition
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</address>
      <phone>+6434795068</phone>
      <fax>+6434797958</fax>
      <email>bernard.venn@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Bernard Venn</name>
      <address>Department of Human Nutrition
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</address>
      <phone>+6434795068</phone>
      <fax>+6434797958</fax>
      <email>bernard.venn@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>