<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369172">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/08/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/09/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000960550</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Negative sensitivity effects associated with the fingers and wrist on bioimpedance measurements in healthy participants.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Pilot study: In the general population does negative sensitivity have a detrimental effect, or not, on bioimpedance measurements of the fingers and wrist?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>negative sensitivity in bioimpedance testing of the fingers and wrist.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Bio impedance devices measure the opposition (impedance) of body tissues to a small applied alternating electrical current.  Using a typical tetrapolar electrode arrangement, intended to reduce impedance  contributions from the electrodes themselves, the current is delivered through one pair of surface  electrodes and voltages measured across available voltage electrodes. Typically the voltage electrodes are placed several centimetres  distant from the current electrodes. The two components of impedance, namely, resistance  (opposition to the current passes through the tissue) and reactance (opposition due to capacitance of  the membranes, tissue interfaces and non-ionic tissues) provide information about (1) the tissue fluid  distribution and electrolyte composition and (2) cell membrane mass and status.

Bioimpedance testing applied involving six electrodes placed on hand with a voltage applied for 2 seconds which is not felt by the participant. 5 readings will be taken with ascending negative sensitivity applied to each bioimpedance measurement by switching the electrodes. One testing session of approximately 10 minutes with no further follow-up.</interventions>
    <comparator>N/A</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Negative sensitivity effect size as assessed against finite element modelling.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At each bioimpedance measurement taken during a single session.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Impedance change related to finite element modelling.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Following each measurement taken during a single session.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>25</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>For safety reasons those who have:
Implanted devices such as pacemakers
Pregnant women
Known medical conditions (heart disease)
Skin disease
Broken skin on hands,
Will be excluded</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Participant characteristics: about 10-15 males and 10-15 females of the ages of 18-25 years old. This is to ensure that a small but reliable sample size is obtained in participants of similar characteristics. Using other similar research done as a reference, this sample size should be enough to provide enough information to reach conclusive results. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Convenience sample</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>1/08/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>14</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/08/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>NSW 2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Ti2 Medical Pty Ltd</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>11 Averill St,
Rhodes, NSW 2138</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Negative sensitivity is one of the most significant source of error in regards to the tetrapolar method used most commonly in bio-impedance (Grimnes &amp; Martinsem 2006). The tetrapolar method consists of a pair of current carrying electrodes which sends tiny electrical current into a localised area. This current is then detected via another pair of electrodes, which help map out the resistance levels in the area. Numerous studies have been conducted making use of this method to help understand the underlying material composition of the area, without the need for time consuming imagery and surgeries (Oh &amp; Sadleir 2005 and Moretti et al. 2011). Unfortunately a common error which occurs in this method, is the occurrence of negative sensitivity, which acts an opposing force and distorts measurements made with the tetrapolar method. In particular, impedance measurements made around the fingers and wrist area, which has the highest concentration of resistivity in the body (Foster &amp; Lukaski 1996 and Gislason et al. 2010). Moreover, the use of FEM modelling and experimental data to help examine impedance readings have been well documented as a feasible method with good results for understanding the effects of errors in the execution of the tetrapolar method (Jafarppor et. al. 2011). While there are many causes where this error has affected measurements, there has yet to be any definitive research into negative sensitivity itself. Thus we hope to fill in the gaps left in the literature and conduct a pilot study into the origins and circumstances of negative sensitivity, rather than leaving it as an excuse for future error.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>NSW 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/07/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2014/1005</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alistair McEwan</name>
      <address>The University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61293517256</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alistair.mcewan@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alistair McEwan</name>
      <address>The University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61293517256</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alistair.mcewan@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alistair McEwan</name>
      <address>The University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61293517256</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alistair.mcewan@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>