<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="840">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/10/2005</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/11/2005</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12605000711617</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Early Intervention for amnestic Mild Cognitive Impairment: A Randomised Trial of Memory Management</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of a memory group intervention for mild cognitive impairment to improve everyday memory performance, use of strategies and psychological well-being of the person with mild cognitive impairment and the family.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Mild Cognitive Impairment</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study will investigate the efficacy of a memory group intervention for older people with memory difficulties (mild cognitive impairment) as well as older people who wish to improve their memory ability. The intervention will include family members or close friends and will focus on the management of everyday memory difficulties by developing increased awareness of changes in everyday memory that can occur as a result of health or aging and increasing knowledge of memory strategies that can be used to prevent everyday memory failures. A randomised pre-test, post-test, 6-month follow-up will be used to evaluate the impact of the 6-week memory group intervention (one 2hr session per week). Over successive cohorts, families will be randomly assigned to an early-ntervention group or a late-intervention control group.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants are randomsied into early- and late-intervention groups and compared at post-test and follow-up assessments. the late-intervention group will provide a control for intervention effects across assessment phases.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the efficacy of the intervention, outcome wil be assessed by performance on neuropsychological tests of memory impairment and disability in everyday memory; self-report of everyday memory ability; knowledge and self-report of use of memory strategies in everyday life by the participant and family participant.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessments, for both groups, will be undertaken at pre-intervention (baseline), post-intervention, and at 6-month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychological well-being: self-report and family report</outcome>
      <timepoint>Undertaken at pre-intervention (baseline), post-intervention, and at 6-month follow-up and these will be used to predict individual response to intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The sample will consist of families who have a family member reporting memory complaint and recently assessed within a Cognitive, Dementia &amp; Memory Service (CDAMS or memory clinic) and also healthy older adult volunteers recruited from the local community via advertising. Patients are referred to the Cognitive Dementia &amp; Memory Service for an evaluation of suspected dementia and will be assigned to the potential pool of participants if they receive a diagnosis of mild cognitive impairment after a comprehensive clinical assessment. MCI can describe a range of presentations with mild neuropsychological difficulties, but for this study the focus will be on amnestic MCI.Inclusion/exclusion criteria: (i) Participant presents with memory complaint; (ii)Objective memory impairment on neuropsychological tests; (iii) Normal general cognitive function; (iv) Adequate activities of daily living; (v) Fails to reach criterion for clinical dementia according to NINCDS-ADRDA guidelines.Additional selection criteria: (i) English speaker; (ii) Living in the community.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Diagnosis of dementia; co-morbid medical conditions associated with functional decline or impact on cognition; untreated major depression and any other severe psychiatric disorder and /or behavioural problems; significant impairment of vision or hearing or communication that would interfere with study participation; availability during the study period.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed envelopes containing group allocation are opened once the participant has been recruited into the study</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants are randomly allocated to either early-intervention or late-inetervention groups based on their order of entry into the research program. Random numbers are generated by SPSS v12 using a uniform distribution (i.e., RV.UNIFORM function) with the restriction that, within every block, equal numbers allocated to each group.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>La Trobe University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Plenty Road, Melbourne, Victoria 3086</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421
Canberra
ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Caulfield General Medical Centre</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>240 Kooyong Road, Caulfield, Melbourne, Victoria</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary />
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Glynda Kinsella</name>
      <address>Psychological Science
La Trobe University
Melbourne VIC 3086</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94792409</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 94791956</fax>
      <email>g.kinsella@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Glynda Kinsella</name>
      <address>Psychological Science
La Trobe University
Melbourne VIC 3086</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94792409</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 94791956</fax>
      <email>g.kinsella@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>