<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366294">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/05/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/05/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000514606</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The pharmacokinetics of intranasal droperidol in healthy volunteers.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised three-way cross-over study comparing the pharmacokinetics of intranasal droperidol to intramuscular and intravenous droperidol in healthy volunteers:</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>INKDROP Study (IntraNasal pharmacoKinetics of DROPeridol)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pharmacokinetics of intranasal drug delivery in healthy human volunteers.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intranasal administration of droperidol 0.02mg/kg as a single dose with 1 week wash out between study arms.</interventions>
    <comparator>Intravenous droperidol 0.02mg/kg as a single dose.
Intramuscular droperidol 0.02mg/kg as a single dose</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the pharmacokinetics of intranasal droperidol and to compare these with equivalent doses of intramuscular and intravenous droperidol administered to healthy volunteers.  

These will include peak serum droperidol concentration (Cmax), time to peak serum concentration (Tmax), terminal elimination half-life (t1/2), area under the time concentration curve (AUC).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pharmacokinetic blood sampling at time 0, 15, 30, 60 minutes post-dosing and 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 10 hours post-dosing.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess safety and tolerability of intranasal droperidol following a single low dose
Vital signs (blood pressure/heart rate/oxygen saturations/temperature)
Level of consciousness
Local adverse events: nasal irritation, bleeding, or any reported symptoms
Systemic adverse events
12-lead ECGs traces and QT-interval duration
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Subjects observed for 12 hours post-dosing for each study arm.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy adult males aged between 18 and 55 years
Body weight &gt; 50kg and &lt; 100 kg with BMI &lt; 28
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Allergy to droperidol 
Previous history of any dystonic reaction to medications
Abnormal nasal anatomy
Previous nasal surgery or nasal trauma that may interfere with administration of absorption of intranasal medication
Current or recent upper respiratory tract infection
Use of any prescription or non-prescription drugs that may affect droperidol metabolism or nasal physiology (vasoconstrictors e.g. phenylephrine) within the past seven days
Treatment with medication known to prolong the QT interval
Absolute QT calculated as the average of three limb lead and three chest lead (V2-V4) QT interval duration.
Abnormal 12-lead ECG on screening with QTcorrected&gt; 480 msec using Sagie regression QTc calculation formula and correlated with Isbister QT-heart rate pair nomogram.
Any known cardiovascular, gastrointestinal, pulmonary, renal, haematologic or liver disease
Any psychiatric or mental health disorder or previous history of antipsychotic medication use
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Volunteers will be recruited by advertisement on Monash University research web site and by advertisement at Dandenong Hospital.

A target number of 7 participants (completing all three arms of the study) will be sought. 

- Screening visit:
Potential participants will contact one of the study investigators and be asked to attend a screening visit, where the study protocol will be explained and any question answered. They will be asked questions regarding their general health and to confirm that meet the inclusion criteria, and have no exclusion criteria. If acceptable, written consent will be sought. Once consent is provided, participants will be allocated a study identification code and their eligibility for study randomization will be confirmed. They will be weighed and BMI will be calculated. A 12-lead ECG will be recorded and assessed for the presence of normal sinus rhythm, with normal conduction intervals and a normal QTc (&lt; 480msec). A pregnancy test will apply for female participants. If they do not have any exclusion criteria, the participants will be eligible to remain in the study and will be randomized to a sequence of drug administration on three subsequent visits, at least one week apart.

Participants not completing the study will be replaced and given the same randomization order. 

The route of droperidol administration will be randomized by random number generation and subjects allocated to a sequence at the time of enrolment from one of seven envelopes. Allocation will concealed from the enrolling investigator.</concealment>
    <sequence>Volunteers will be randomized by random number generation to the sequence of which route of droperidol administration will be first.

Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation). 
</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Pharmacokinetics</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Serum drug concentration will be reported as mean +/- SD in ng/ml. Statistical comparisons of the primary pharmacokinetic parameters will be compared between groups using one-way ANOVA with Newman-Keuls post-test for parametric data and Dunnets post-test for non-parametric data.

Previous pharmacokinetic studies using droperidol intravenously have reported serum drug concentrations after doses of up to 0.15 mg/kg. This is significantly (ten-fold) higher than the dose we will be using in this study. We expect that after intravenous administration of droperidol at the proposed dose of 0.02 mg/kg peak serum concentration will be around 150 to 200 ng/ml (+/- SD 30-40 ng/ml). If these concentrations are achieved in this study, it would give an acceptable 95% confidence interval of +/- 25 ng/ml.

With regards to intranasal drug delivery of droperidol, the only comparable data available is from the haloperidol study by Miller et al, (2008). In this study, mean peak haloperidol concentration in four subjects post-intranasal administration were 1/3 of those seen intravenously with a standard deviation of +/- 20 ng/ml. For the proposed study, using the expected peak droperidol concentration assumption above for the IV group, a calculated sample size of n = 7 subjects in the IN and IV arms would result in an expected mean peak serum concentration of droperidol in the intranasal group of around 60 ng/ml with a 95% CI of +/- 15 ng/ml. (Confidence intervals and sample size calculated using STATA statistical software using binomial confidence intervals).
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/07/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>16/01/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>7</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Dandenong Hospital - Dandenong</hospital>
    <postcode>3175 - Dandenong</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Emergency Medicine
Dandenong Hospital
125 David Street
Dandenong, 3175, Vic</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Emergency Medicine
Dandenong Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>125 David Street
Dandenong, 3175
Victoria
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Teleflex Medical</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>182-184 Stawell Street
Burnley , 3121
Victoria</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The intranasal (IN) route of drug administration has many advantages. It has the potential to eliminate the pain, anxiety, and distress that can be associated with the use of needles for IV or IMI drug delivery. The risk of needle-stick injury and blood-borne infection is also minimized by the use of needleless systems. In addition, drug administration can occur more quickly than intravenous administration as there is no need to spend time siting a cannula and there is reduced resource utilisation. 

Recent observational research in the ED setting has revealed that more than 50% of inserted intravenous cannulae are never used for therapeutic purposes and pose a significant risk for skin infection and septicaemia if left in-situ. 

There is currently no data examining the pharmacokinetic profile of intranasal droperidol. However, based upon results with intranasal haloperidol, it is likely that droperidol, having similar pharmacokinetic properties, may display a comparable intranasal absorption profile.  

Currently, there are no anti-emetics or antipsychotic medications being administered intranasally in the clinical setting. As a result, if the pharmacokinetic profile is favourable, droperidol may be a useful drug to consider for clinical trials of intranasal treatment of acute behavioural disturbance and anti-emesis.   </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash Health Human Research and Ethic Committee A</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Directorate
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Rd
Clayton, 3168, Vic</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/05/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>14127A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/04/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Andis Graudins</name>
      <address>Department of Emergency Medicine
Dandenong Hospital
125 David Street
Dandenong, Vic, 3175</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9554 9340</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andis.graudins@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Andis Graudins</name>
      <address>Department of Emergency Medicine
Dandenong Hospital
125 David Street
Dandenong, Vic, 3175</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9554 9340</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andis.graudins@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Andis Graudins</name>
      <address>Department of Emergency Medicine
Dandenong Hospital
125 David Street
Dandenong, Vic, 3175</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9554 9340</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andis.graudins@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>