<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368612">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/06/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/09/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001004550</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of sugar-sweetened drinks on psychological and metabolic outcomes.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Possible effects on healthy young adults of sugar- and artificially-sweetened drinks in terms of psychological and metabolic outcomes</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1170-4543</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Posible metabolic and psychological effects of sugar drink consumption</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants are randomly assigned to 3 arms: (1) Sugar group: 4.5L of sugar-sweetened drink per week; (2) Diet group: 4.5L of artificially-sweetened drink per week; (3) Water group: 4.5L of bottled water.  Intervention is for 12 weeks.  During this period all participants are required to abstain from consuming sweetened drinks other than those given to them.
Notes:
1. a) The sugar-sweetened drinks will be commercially available carbonated beverages with sucrose content in the range 9% - 11%.  Participants in this arm will be offered a choice between CocaCola, PepsiCola, Sprite and Fanta.
Participants in the Diet arm will be offered a choice between the equivalent sugar-free commercial beverages; e.g. Diet Coke, Coke Zero, Diet Pepsi, Sprite Light, which contain artificial sweeteners that can include aspartame, sucralose or stevia, or some combination.

b) Participants will be asked to consume no more than 3 of the 375-ml cans per day; otherwise it is up to them to decide when to consume their drink.

c) Monitoring of adherence to drinking all 12 cans each week consists of: 1.requiring that participants return the empty cans when they come to collect the next week's supply; and 2. reporting each week what beverages they have consumed in the previous week by completing the Brief 15-item Beverage Questionnaire (BEVQ-15) on each visit to the laboratory.

2.  Participants are not asked to change their normal diet other than comply with the instructions on beverages; i.e. there are no further dietary restrictions.   </interventions>
    <comparator>As indicated above, the Control treatment is to provide these participants with bottled water (Water group).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in cognitive function as measured by neuropsychological tests: the Logical Memory test and the Controlled Oral Word Association Test (COWAT).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change from baseline (Initial test) at the start of the intervention to the Midway test 6 weeks later, to the Completion test 12 weeks after the start of the intervention, with a Follow up test approximately 12 weeks after the Completion test.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Waist circumference</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change from baseline (Initial test) at the start of the intervention to the Midway test 6 weeks later, to the Completion test 12 weeks after the start of the intervention, with a Follow up test approximately 12 weeks after the Completion test.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body mass index (BMI). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Change from baseline (Initial test) at the start of the intervention to the Midway test 6 weeks later, to the Completion test 12 weeks after the start of the intervention, with a Follow up test approximately 12 weeks after the Completion test.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Go/No go test for response inhibition (GNG).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change from baseline (Initial test) at the start of the intervention to the Midway test 6 weeks later, to the Completion test 12 weeks after the start of the intervention, with a Follow up test approximately 12 weeks after the Completion test.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in metabolic function as measured by an Oral Glucose Tolerance Test (OGTT) in which blood sugar levels are measured at 15, 30, 45 and 60 min after consumption of 50g of glucose (dissolved in tap water) within 5 min.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change from baseline (Initial test) at start of intervention to the Completion test 12 weeks later.  NB The OGTT will not be administered in the Midway test or the Follow up test.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total body fat, as measured by Bio-electrical Impedance Analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change from baseline (Initial test) at the start of the intervention to the Midway test 6 weeks later, to the Completion test 12 weeks after the start of the intervention, with a Follow up test approximately 12 weeks after the Completion test.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sweetness preference test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change from baseline (Initial test) to Completion test 12 weeks later.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change from baseline (Initial test) at the start of the intervention to the Midway test 6 weeks later, to the Completion test 12 weeks after the start of the intervention, with a Follow test approximately 12 weeks after the Completion test.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Biochemical assays of fasting blood sample, including blood glucose, triglyceride, cholesterol and uric acid levels.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change from baseline (Initial test) to Completion test 12 weeks later.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy volunteers in the age range 18-35 years and with BMI in range 17.5-30 who regularly drink at least 2L of sugar-sweetened drinks per week.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>35</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Previous or current eating-related disorder; current mental health diagnosis; diabetic; food allergies or other disorder affecting either diet or memory</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>If an initial phone call indicates that a potential participant meets the above criteria, s/he is invited to a screening session that includes measurement of BMI and blood pressure.  If these and a further health questionnaire fail to reveal any health risk, then s/he is booked for Test session 1 (Baseline). Neither participants nor researchers will know which arm a potential participant will be allocated to until after a decision about eligibility has been made.

Provisional allocation of a participant to an arm will be made on arrival for Test session 1.  Block randomisation will use a random number generator for each blocks of 6 participants (2 for each group).

This process will be constrained by attempting to match the groups in terms of 4 participant characteristics; in order of priority these are : 1. BMI; 2. Initial report of sugar-sweetened beverage intake, as measured by the Hedricks BEVQ-15; 3. Proportion of sweet energy-rich foods in their normal diet, as measured by the DFS short questionnaire; 4. Gender.  It may well turn out to be impossible to stratify for more than the first two factors.

Allocation is not concealed.   </concealment>
    <sequence>Provisional allocation of a participant to an arm will be made on arrival for Test session 1.  Participants will be randomised in blocks of 6 (2 for each group), with the order within each block determined by a random number generator.
This process will be constrained by attempting to match the groups in terms of 4 participant characteristics; in order of priority these are:
1) BMI;
2) Initial report of sugar-sweetened beverage intake, as measured by the Hedricks BEVQ-15;
3) Proportion of sweet energy-rich foods in their normal diet, as measured by the DFS short questionnaire;
4. Gender.
It may well turn out to be impossible to stratify for more than the first two factors. 
</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>In a convenience sample, Francis and Stevenson (2011) found that a self-reported HFHS diet reduced performance on the Logical Memory test relative to a self-reported LFS diet with an effect size of d=0.81. In order for us to have 80% power to detect a significant effect of our dietary intervention of a slightly more conservative effect size of d=.70  and with a=.05 (two-tailed), a sample size of 34 per group is required. Based on Maersk et als (2012) dietary intervention, we anticipate an attrition rate of 33%. Therefore, we will aim to recruit and randomise a total of 153 participants to achieve a final sample of 34 per group.
Analyses will be conducted per protocol on those participants who complete the first three tests.  (Since a high drop out rate is expected for the final, 'follow up' test, data from this test will be treated separately.)  If a particular participant has less than 5% missing data, then s/he will be considered a 'completer' and the missing data will be imputed via multiple imputation.  Per protocol analysis is chosen because the study aims to assess the effects of the consumption of the three drinks and this requires that the participants actually consume the drinks that have been allocated to them.
The primary outcome, Logical Memory, will be analysed at Test 2, Test 3 and Test 4, separately via ANCOVAs, controlling for baseline Logical Memory scores (at Test 1).</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>11/04/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/09/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>153</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/04/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2006 - The University Of Sydney</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Robert Boakes</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Psychology (A18),
University of Sydney,
NSW 2006,
Australia.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 2702
CANBERRA
ACT 2601
AUSTRALIA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Sydney</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University of Sydney,
Sydney, NSW 2006</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Background. Various lines of evidence indicate that negative metabolic consequences follow when a person regularly drinks a large quantity of sugar-sweetened beverages (SSBs).  What is not known is whether SSBs also produce negative psychological effects, such as impairments in short-term memory and increased impulsiveness.  Switching from SSBs to diet beverages (non-nutritive sweetened beverages; NSBs) would seem to offer a relatively easy dietary change.  However, it has been claimed that this can be counter-productive in at least some circumstances.
Aims. 1. To test whether SSB consumption produces impairment on psychological tests, relative to NSB consumption and a water control condition; 2. To test whether the effects of NSB consumption depends on other aspects of a persons diet (e.g. consumption of sweet energy-rich foods).
Design.  In a non-blinded 3-group parallel design over a 12-week period the Sugar group is given SSBs, the Diet group is given NSBs and the Water group is given water.  Metabolic and cognitive/behavioural measures are taken at the outset of the intervention (Initial test), after 6 weeks (Midway test), at the end of the intervention (Completion test) and approximately 12 weeks later (Follow up test).
Main predictions:  1. In the Completion test the primary psychological outcome measure, scores on the Logical Memory test, will be lower in the Sugar group than in the other two groups. 2. In the Completion test the primary metabolic outcome, waist:hip ratio will be larger in the Sugar group than in the other two groups.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Office,
University of Sydney,
Sydney, NSW 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/04/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2015/074</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Local Health District Clinical Trials Subcommittee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Development Office,
Level 8, Building 14,
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital,
Camperdown, NSW 2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/02/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>X14-0366</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368612-1506BoakesSugarDrinkProtocolRevsn5.docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368612-1701SugarDrinkProtocolRevsn3plusFooter.docx</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Robert A. Boakes</name>
      <address>School of Psychology (A18),
University of Sydney,
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>(612) 9351 3347</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bob.boakes@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Robert A. Boakes</name>
      <address>School of Psychology (A18),
University of Sydney,
Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>(612) 9351 3347</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bob.boakes@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Robert A. Boakes</name>
      <address>School of Psychology (A18),
University of Sydney,
Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>(612) 9351 3347</phone>
      <fax>(612) 9351 2603</fax>
      <email>bob.boakes@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Robert A. Boakes</name>
      <address>School of Psychology (A18),
University of Sydney,
Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>(612) 9351 3347</phone>
      <fax>(612) 9351 2603</fax>
      <email>bob.boakes@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>