<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364291">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/05/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/05/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000589785</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can cervical auscultation improve the diagnosis of aspiration in children?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial comparing the effectiveness of clinical feeding evaluation versus clinical feeding evaluation with cervical auscultation in the diagnosis of aspiration in children.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Oropharyngeal aspiration</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Children will receive either a clinical feeding examination  only (CFE only) or clinical feeding examination + cervical auscultation (CFE+CA)assessment. 

The CFE involves a case history and mealtime observations of the childs oral sensorimotor, feeding and swallowing skills. The examination only provides an estimation of the co-ordination and movement of food/fluids through the pharyngeal phase. This is determined through visual observation of laryngeal movement, palpation of laryngeal movement and listening to clinical features (e.g. cough, wet voice, choking, voice change).

In the CFE+CA group, clinicians will be able to listen to the participant's breath and swallow sounds during the examination.  A microphone is attached to the participants neck to allow access to cervical sounds generated during the swallow and breath sounds pre- and post-swallow. 

All children will have a modified barium swallow (MBS) procedure (dynamic x-ray of the child's swallow in the oral and pharyngeal phases) after their clinical feeding evaluation. Timing of the MBS post clinical feeding evaluation is dependent on clinical constraints at the time of assessment and will range between 24 hrs to 2 weeks. Results of the MBS will be used to compare against their clinical assessment results.

Paticipants will undergo one assessment modality (CFE or CFE+CA) and one MBS only. Both assessment modalities will go for approximately 60 mins and the MBS procedure will go for approximately 30mins, with under 3 minutes of actual screening time.

All procedures and assessments will be completed by a speech pathologist, specialising in paediatric dysphagia mangagement at the Royal Children's Hospital, Brisbane. For MBS procedures, a radiographer and radiologist will also be present for the study.

The total duration of participant involvement in the study would be: CFE or CFE+CA (60mins) and MBS (30mins) = 90mins. No follow-up is necessary.

</interventions>
    <comparator>There is no control group. This is an open, randomized controlled study, comparing 2 groups (CFE+CA vs CFE only) to MBS. Results of modified barium swallow will act as the control/comparator. Outcome measure: identified aspiration or no aspiration.

Participants will receive one assessment (CFE or CFE+CA) and one modified barium swallow (MBS). MBS will occur 24hrs to 2 weeks post assessment, pending clinical constraints. All participants will be assessed by a speech pathologist, specialising in paediatric dysphagia at The Royal Children's Hospital.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Modified barium swallow results: aspiration, penetration or no aspiration.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Clinical feeding evaluation (initial timepoint) followed by modified barium swallow study (end timepoint) within 24hrs to 2 weeks of initial clinical feeding evaluation assessment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compare acoustic features of aspirating and non-aspirating swallow sounds (decibels, duration, frequency).Continuous variables will be analysed using a T-test (assuming normal distribution).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Clinical feeding evaluation only (first and end timepoint for this outcome)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Children aged under 18 years and who are referred for a feeding assessment or modified barium swallow study at The Royal Children's Hospital, Brisbane.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Children deemed medically unfit to complete a clinical feeding evaluation and modifed barium swallow study as determined by the treating medical team. Children can only participate for one series of evaluations.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Recruitment
The parents/guardians of eligible children will be initially approached by the clinical speech pathologist responsible for the child’s assessment. Parents/guardians interested in participating will then be referred to the principle investigator (TTF). The study will be explained using written information statements and face-to-face interview. Written informed consent will be obtained from the parents/guardians of children enrolled. Written informed assent will also be obtained from young people aged 12 years and over.

Randomisation
A computer generated simple randomisation list, stratified by age (&lt;1 year or =1 year) was produced by an external statistician. Allocation concealment will be maintained by group allocation (i.e. CFE or CFE+CA) being concealed in sequentially numbered, opaque envelopes until after consent and baseline information has been obtained. The envelope is opened in front of the treating speech pathologist and caregiver prior to the commencement of their feeding examination. 
</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software.
We stratified by age because swallowing function is influenced by age. The cut-off of 12 months was chosen based on 2 factors; (a) the swallow-respiration pattern changes at 1 week and between 6 to 12 months of age;and (b)  no statistically significant changes in temporal (i.e. durational) measures of a child’s swallow occurs between 2 to 15 months.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size
We plan a sample size of 216 children based on previous research, where the sensitivity of CFE for OPA was 76%. 108 children per group provides 80% power (two-sided a = 0.05) to detect a 15% difference between two groups. A smaller difference between groups was considered insufficient to influence clinical practice.

Statistical analyses
Baseline characteristics of the two groups will be presented as means/medians or proportions and their 95% Confidence Intervals and compared using t-tests for normally distributed data, Chi-square tests for proportions and the appropriate non-parametric methods for non-normally distributed data. For our primary aim, agreement between OPA determined clinical and MBS assessments will be calculated using percent agreement and a kappa coefficient. Taking MBS determination of presence or absence of OPA as the gold standard, sensitivity, specificity, negative predictor value (NPV), positive predictor value (PPV), pretest probability and likelihood ratios will also be calculated. Likelihood ratios will also be calculated. 

For our secondary aim, categorical variables of pre-, during and post-swallowing sound parameters will be analysed using a Chi-square test. Multivariate regression analysis will be used to determine if ages, gender, texture, method of intake or clinician level of experience are independent predictors on the absence/presence of particular swallowing sound parameters. The a priori statistical level of significance is p=0.05.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>27/09/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>27/09/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>27/09/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>216</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Children's Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <postcode>4029 - Royal Brisbane Hospital</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Children's Health Queensland Foundation, Queensland Children's Medical Research Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 4 Foundation Building 
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston Rd
Herston , QLD, 4029</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health &amp; Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Children's Health Queensland Foundation, Queensland Children's Medical Research Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 4 Foundation Building 
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston Rd
Herston , QLD, 4029</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Speech Pathology Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 2 / 11-19 Bank Place  
Melbourne  
Victoria  
3000  
Australia  
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Background: Oropharyngeal aspiration (OPA) can lead to recurrent respiratory illnesses and chronic lung disease in children. Current clinical feeding evaluations (CFE) performed by speech pathologists have poor reliability in detecting OPA when compared to radiological procedures such as the modified barium swallow (MBS). Improved ability to diagnose OPA accurately via clinical feeding evaluation potentially reduces reliance on expensive, less readily available, radiological procedures. Our study investigates the utility of adding cervical auscultation (CA), a technique of listening to swallowing sounds, in improving the diagnostic accuracy of a clinical feeding evaluation for the detection of OPA. 

Aims of the study
Our study investigates the utility of cervical auscultation (CA) in the assessment and diagnosis of OPA in children.  The primary aim is to determine whether the clinical feeding evaluation (CFE) combined with CA increases the detection of OPA determined by MBS, compared to the clinical feeding evaluation (CFE) only. We hypothesize that the use of CA (compared to not using CA) as an adjunctive clinical tool to assess oropharyngeal dysphagia, improves the detection of OPA in children as assessed with the current gold standard, MBS.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Queensland Medical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of QLD
St Lucia, QLD, 4067</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/09/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2011001295</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/09/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Children’s Health Services Human Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 3 Foundation Building
Royal Children's Hospital,
Herston, QLD, 4029</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/05/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/11/QRCH/52</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/05/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Thuy Frakking</name>
      <address>Level 4 Foundation Building
Queensland Children's Medical Research Institute
Royal Children's Hospital,
Herston, QLD, 4029.</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 5121</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>t.frakking@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Thuy Frakking</name>
      <address>Level 4 Foundation Building
Queensland Children's Medical Research Institute
Royal Children's Hospital,
Herston, QLD, 4029.</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 5121</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>t.frakking@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Thuy Frakking</name>
      <address>Level 4 Foundation Building
Queensland Children's Medical Research Institute
Royal Children's Hospital,
Herston, QLD, 4029.</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 5121</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>t.frakking@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Thuy Frakking</name>
      <address>Level 4 Foundation Building
Queensland Children's Medical Research Institute
Royal Children's Hospital,
Herston, QLD, 4029.</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 5121</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>t.frakking@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>