<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362236">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/03/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/03/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000315819</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Remote consultation by video-conferencing for people with diabetes</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of accuracy of video tele-consultation for people with type II diabetes by comparing the recommendations made through videoconferencing with those of in-person consultation</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Remote consultation for people with type II diabetes mellitus</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>People with type II diabetes who are referring to a diabetes clinic will be seen by endocrinologist consultant remotely via videoconferencing (real-time exchange of video and audio; a form of telemedicine). Duration of each consultation will be approximately 30 minutes. 
Arm 1: Patient will be seen by 2 doctors - one by a face to face consultation and the other a video consultation (intervention). The order of in-person and video consultations will be based on random basis.
Arm 2: Patient will be seen by 2 doctors by two face to face consultations one following the other (control)</interventions>
    <comparator>Conventional in-person consultations provided by endocrinologist consultant for people with type II diabetes. Duration of each consultation will be approximately 30 minutes. Each participant will undergo two in-person consultations, one following the other.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Level of disagreement between recommendations made via videoconferencing and in-person consultation</outcome>
      <timepoint>After each consultation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adult people with type II diabetes mellitus who are referring to diabetes clinic for review consultation</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>People who are referring to the clinic for the first time, people whose first language is not English and no interpreter is available.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A research nurse will call people with type II diabetes who have fixed an appointment with the Princess Alexandra Hospital diabetes clinic and invite them for participation after introducing the study. Enrolment will be made at the diabetes clinic after obtaining written consent on the appointment day. Once enrolled, the participant will select a sealed envelope which will determine allocation to intervention or control group.</concealment>
    <sequence>A table of random numbers will be generated using a random number generation software. Even numbers will donate allocation to intervention group and odd numbers to the control group. Each random number with corresponding allocated group will be printed on a sheet of paper and sealed in sequentially numbered opaque envelope. The set of envelopes will be kept in a box to be hold at the study site.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Centre for Online Health, The University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 3, Foundation Building
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston Road
Herston 4029
Queensland</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Queensland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Centre for Online Health
Level 3, Foundation Building
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston Road
Herston 4029
Queensland</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Diabetes and Endocrinology department, Princess Alexandra Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Princess Alexandra Hospital
Ipswich road
Woolloongabba
4102 QLD</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Diabetes is a chronic disease which has no cure, instead optimal glycaemic control is required to minimize complications.  However, only 40% of people with diabetes are achieving target glycaemic control, demonstrating that effective disease management for people with diabetes remains a challenge.  For some, particularly in rural areas, not achieving target glycaemic controls is at least in part due to poor access to qualified health care providers. Telemedicine has been shown to be effective in improving access to care and lowering the costs in some disciplines, but its application in chronic diseases such as diabetes is still controversial.

This research project is designed to evaluate the accuracy and reliability of clinical decisions made when a diabetic patient is consulted by videoconference. This evaluation will be based on comparing the outcomes of specialist consultations provided through face-to-face encounter with video-consultation. Each patient will be seen by 2 doctors  either two face to face consultations one following the other, or a face to face and video consultation.  Since doctors do not always agree on their decisions, this arrangement will enable us to determine whether any difference of opinion is a result of the video-conference method, or just normal variation between doctors.

If shown to be as reliable as face-to-face consultation for managing diabetes, there will be valuable evidence to support substituting in-person consultation with video-consultation, which paves the way for at least some specialist consultation for people living in rural areas to avoid the expense and inconvenience of long distance travel. In some cases, it may open the door for specialist advice that is currently not available.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Metro South Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Centres for Health Research
Princess Alexandra Hospital
Ipswich Road
Woolloongabba 4102 QLD</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/03/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/11/QPAH/645</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Farhad Fatehi</name>
      <address>Centre for Online Health
Level 3, Foundation Building
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston Road, Herston 4029
Queenland</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3646 9456</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3346 4705</fax>
      <email>f.fatehi@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Farhad Fatehi</name>
      <address>Centre for Online Health
Level 3, Foundation Building
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston Road, Herston 4029
Queenland</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3646 9456</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3346 4705</fax>
      <email>f.fatehi@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Farhad Fatehi</name>
      <address>Centre for Online Health
Level 3, Foundation Building
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston Road, Herston 4029
Queenland</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3646 9456</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3346 4705</fax>
      <email>f.fatehi@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>