<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362690">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/06/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/06/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000692831</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of Sulforaphane on the Vascular Status and Oxidative status of Type 2 Diabetes</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of a Sulforaphane-Yielding Encapsulated Product compared with Placebo on Arterial Stiffness and other Biochemical Markers in Type 2 Diabetics aged 18-45 years.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1132-1654</utrn>
    <trialacronym>EASY DIAB 2</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>ECB capsules each contain 700mg of 100% Myrosinase-active Broccoli Sprout powder.  Participants will take 3 capsules night and morning for 26 weeks.  All participants will be required to avoid eating cruciferous vegetables because phytochemicals in these foods may activate some of the same pathways as the capsule's active ingredient.</interventions>
    <comparator>Double-blinded, randomised, placebo-controlled, using a 2-piece gel capsule containing colour-matched maltodextrin, identical in appearance to the active product.  All participants will be required to avoid eating cruciferous vegetables because phytochemicals in these foods may activate some of the same pathways as the capsule's active ingredient.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>CLINICAL MARKER: Arterial Stiffness as measured via Pulse Wave Velocity (PWV) using applanation tonometry (SphygmoCor).  The procedure will be performed at rest at the Royal Brisbane &amp; Women's Hospital, Herston  Qld  4029.</outcome>
      <timepoint>To be measured at 13 weeks and 26 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>BIOCHEMICAL MARKER 1:  Leukocyte Quinone reductase.  Fasting blood samples will be taken a portion allocated for extraction of leukocytes for analysis of gene expression via Northern Blot Analysis.  

BIOCHEMICAL MARKER 2:  Ratio of oxidised:reduced glutathione.  Plasma erythrocytes will be assayed using the automated COBAS spectrophotometric Analyser at the University of Queensland, School of Human Movement Studies Oxidative Stress Laboratory.</outcome>
      <timepoint>To be measured at 13 weeks and 26 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure will be measured after the participant rests for 10 minutes in a seated position and using an automatic sphygmomanometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>To be measured at 13 weeks and 26 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>BIOCHEMICAL MARKERS:  Markers of oxidative stress.  The Oxidative Stress Laboratory in the School of Human Movement Studies at the University of Queensland routinely measures antioxidnt enzymes, cytokines, malondialdehyde and F2-isoprostanes using ant automated COBAS Spectrophotometric Analyser</outcome>
      <timepoint>To be measured at 13 weeks and 26 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Medically-diagnosed with Type 2 diabetes without disease complications.  Medication schedule must have been stable for at least 6 months and is not expected to change within the next 6 months.  Must be able to attend the research clinic on 4 separate occasions over the 6 month-period of the trial.  Must be prepared to take 6 plant-based capsules daily and refrain from eating cruciferous vegetables</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Evident diabetic complications such as retinopathy, neuropathy and nephropathy.  Those whose diabetic condition requires regular insulin. Smokers and those using recreational drugs.  Males conusming more than 4 alcoholic drinks and females consuing more than 2 alcoholic drinks daily. Those with BMI &gt; 30 or &lt; 20.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Research group personnel will determine eligibility based on the Inclusion and Exclusion criteria.  Following return of signed Informed Consent, each of the 82 eligible participants will be appropriately code numbered and the codes sent to the Royal Brisbane &amp; Women's Hospital Pharmacy where randomisation will be performed.  The Research personnel who determine eligibility will have no contact at any time with the pharmacy where randomisation will be performed.  The capsules (both active and placebo) will be dispensed in identical dosette containers named for the study and identified only by a code number from 1-82.  

Randomisation codes will be placed in sequentially numbered, opaque, heat sealed envelopes and will be kept in two separate locations: one copy in the office of Professor Coombes at the University of Queensland and the second copy in the office of Professor Robert Fassett at the Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens' Hospital in Brisbane.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation and concealment will be handled by the Pharmacy Department at the Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens' Hospital and will be conducted according to protocols suggested in the CONSORT Statement Items 8a- 11a. Randomisation will be used to avoid bias in the
assignment of subjects to the nature of the capsule, to increase the likelihood that known and unknown
subject attributes (e.g. demographics and baseline characteristics) are evenly balanced across groups, and
to enhance the validity of statistical comparisons across treatment groups.  A simple randomisation process will be employed, using a randomisation table from a statistics book.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>82</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>4000</postcode>
    <postcode>4005</postcode>
    <postcode>4010</postcode>
    <postcode>4015</postcode>
    <postcode>4020</postcode>
    <postcode>4025</postcode>
    <postcode>4030</postcode>
    <postcode>4035</postcode>
    <postcode>4040</postcode>
    <postcode>4045</postcode>
    <postcode>4050</postcode>
    <postcode>4055</postcode>
    <postcode>4060</postcode>
    <postcode>4065</postcode>
    <postcode>4070</postcode>
    <postcode>4075</postcode>
    <postcode>4080</postcode>
    <postcode>4085</postcode>
    <postcode>4090</postcode>
    <postcode>4095</postcode>
    <postcode>4100</postcode>
    <postcode>4105</postcode>
    <postcode>4110</postcode>
    <postcode>4115</postcode>
    <postcode>4120</postcode>
    <postcode>4125</postcode>
    <postcode>4130</postcode>
    <postcode>4135</postcode>
    <postcode>4140</postcode>
    <postcode>4145</postcode>
    <postcode>4150</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Human Movement Studies
St Lucia Brisbane  Qld  4072</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Brisbane &amp; Women's Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Bowen Bridge Road, Herston Brisbane  Qld  4029</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Cell-Logic Pty Ltd</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Brisbane Technology Park
7 Clunies Ross Court
Eight Mile Plains  Qld  4113</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The prevalence of Type 2 diabetes and its complications is increasing globally.  The condition is associated with lifestyle factors which impact biochemically at many levels.  Markers of oxidative stress are typically elevated in the diabetic condition but attempts to regulate oxidative stress with antioxidant vitamins have been generally unsuccessful.  The plant-derived capsules to be used in this trial yield a phytochemical, sulforaphane which has been shown to activate pathways leading to elevation of the cell's endogenous antioxidant enzymes and other cytoprotective compounds such as glutathione.  This trial is aimed at testing the efficacy of such capsules in modifying the disease parameters associated with Type 2 diabetes.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Medical Research Ethics Committee (MREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ethics Officer
Research &amp; Innovation Division
Cumbrae-Stewart Building (72)
THE UNIVERSITY OF QUEENSLAND QLD 4072</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/06/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Christine Houghton</name>
      <address>School of Human Movement Studies
University of Queensland
Connell Building (26B)
St Lucia, 4072</address>
      <phone>+617 3488 0385</phone>
      <fax>+617 3488 0389</fax>
      <email>christine.houghton@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Robert Fassett</name>
      <address>Renal Research
Level 9, Ned Hanlon Building
Royal Brisbane &amp; Women's Hospital
Herston  Qld  4029</address>
      <phone>+617 3636 2698</phone>
      <fax>+617 3636 8572</fax>
      <email>r.fassett@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Christine Houghton</name>
      <address>School of Human Movement Studies
University of Queensland
Connell Building (26B)
St Lucia, 4072</address>
      <phone>+617 3488 0385</phone>
      <fax>+617 3488 0389</fax>
      <email>christine.houghton@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>