<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363206">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/10/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/11/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001159842</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>New alternative therapeutical strategies in early senescence and immunosenescence</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effects of alternative therapies on cognitive deficits and immunosenescence in community aged subjects</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1136-3604</utrn>
    <trialacronym>AGEing</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Mild cognitive impairment</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Immunosenescence</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the immune system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The patients will be randomly divided in five different subgroups, checking afterwards that there are not any significant differences between the groups, regarding their age, sex, neuroimagistic findings, and their cognitive status reflected by Mini Mental State Examination (MMSE) scores. The minimental state examination (MMSE) is a brief 30-point questionnaire test that is used to screen for cognitive impairment. It is used to estimate the severity of cognitive impairment and to follow the course of cognitive changes in an individual over time, thus making it an effective way to document an individual's response to treatment. The subgroups will receive the treatment orally, for at least one year, to a maximum duration of two years. The overall duration of treatment will be decided after the subject's assessment at one year, upon completing the evaluation tests performed at that time. The study subgroups will receive the treatment as follows:
1. subgroup A that will comprise elderly subjects diagnosed with mild cognitive impairment (MCI), having the MMSE score between 21-28 points). This subgroup will be treated
with Piracetam 4 tablets/day (daily dose: 1600 mg);
2.  subgroup B that will comprise elderly subjects diagnosed with MCI, that will be treated with Rhodiola-rosea, 2 capsules/day (500 mg daily);
3.  subgroup C that will comprise elderly subjects diagnosed with MCI,which will be treated with Selezin ACE (Selenium 100 mcg, Zinc 15 mg; Vitamin A 1000 mcg, Vitamin B6 2,20 mg, Vitamin C 90 mg, Vitamin E 15 mg) and Coenzyme Q (10 mg daily);
4.  subgroup D that will comprise elderly subjects with MCI, treated with Selezin ACE, Coenzyme Q (10 mg daily) and Rhodiola Rosea (500 mg daily).</interventions>
    <comparator>There will be two control groups:

A control group that will comprise age-matched elderly subjects (over 65 years) without MCI (MMSE = 30 points) and without treatment (including placebo).

A control group (subgroup E) that will comprise elderly subjects with MCI (MMSE = 21-28 points), receiving placebo (a pill, identical in taste and appearance, but without the active ingredient).</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mild cognitive impairment improvement, as assessed by MMSE, clock, and Raven tests.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Initial screening, first assessment at 6 months, second assessment at one year.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Immunosenescence improvement, as assessed byimmune phenotype of peripheral blood CD8+ T cells.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Initial screening, and assessment at one year.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Subjects with 65 years of age and older than 65;
Subjects diagnosed with MCI (MMSE score =21-28 points).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Subjects younger than 65 years;
Subjects with MCI due to major depressive disorder and schizophrenia;
Subjects with moderate and severe cognitive impairment (MMSE score under 21 points).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>MCI individuals will be identified by screening subjects aged over 65 years from Arad county in western part of Romania, consenting to participate in the study. Neuropsychological scales will be administered, to assess the cognitive functions (MMSE score between 21- 28 points, Raven test and Clock test).
The subjects who will be selected for this study have a MMSE score between 21-28 points, and memory-related symptoms.
The subjects will be randomly divided in five different subgroups, checking afterwards that there are not any significant differences between the groups, regarding their age, sex, neuroimagistic findings, and their cognitive status reflected by MMSE scores. The allocation to intervention will be performed with concealment, by using sealed opaque envelopes .</concealment>
    <sequence>The subjects participating in the study will be randomly divided between the five treatment groups (subgroups A, B, C, D and E), receiving different therapeutical schemes. The selection of the subjects into the different subgroups will be performed by simple randomisation, using sealed opaque envelopes, each envelope containing the study subgroups:
1. subgroup A that will comprise elderly subjects diagnosed with MCI (MMSE = 21-28 points), that will be treated
with Piracetam 4 tablets/day (daily dose: 1600 mg);
2.  subgroup B that will comprise elderly subjects diagnosed with MCI, that will be treated with Rhodiola-rosea, 2 capsules/day (500 mg daily);
3.  subgroup C that will comprise elderly subjects diagnosed with MCI,which will be treated with Selezin ACE (Selenium 100 mcg, Zinc 15 mg; Vitamin A 1000 mcg, Vitamin B6 2,20 mg, Vitamin C 90 mg, Vitamin E 15 mg) and Coenzyme Q (10 mg daily);
4.  subgroup D that will comprise elderly subjects with MCI, treated with Selezin ACE, Coenzyme Q (10 mg daily) and Rhodiola Rosea (500 mg daily).
5. subgroup E, that will comprise elderly subjects with MCI (MMSE = 21-28 points), receiving placebo.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>400</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Romania</country>
      <state>Arad county</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Medicine and Pharmacy "Victor Babes" Timisoara</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>E. Murgu Sq. #2A, Timisoara, Romania</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Romania</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Romanian National Council of Research</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Schitu Magureanu st. no. 1,  Sector 5, Cod 050025,
Bucharest, Romania</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Romania</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>"Vasile Goldis" Western University of Arad</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Revolution Bld. no. 94, Arad</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Romania</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The final aim of the study is the significant improvement of the health state of the population, with special reference the elderly people, thus improving the quality of life, with the reduction of costs necessary for the medical services by developing preventive and therapeutical advanced procedures, extremely efficient for the specific dysfunctions which appear in the elderly people.
            The main objective of the trial is the early diagnosis for mild cognitive impairment and to assess the efficacy of alternative and complementary therapies used on elderly subjects.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Octavian Goga st. no. 17, 310022, Arad</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/10/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>21/2007</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/10/2007</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Romania</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Daniel Cioca, M.D., Ph.D.</name>
      <address>University of Medicine and Pharmacy "Victor Babes" Timisoara,
Eftimie Murgu Sq. no. 2A, 300041, Timisoara</address>
      <phone>+40-720056934</phone>
      <fax>+40-256-415681</fax>
      <email>dcioca@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Romania</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Daniel Cioca, M.D., Ph.D.</name>
      <address>University of Medicine and Pharmacy "Victor Babes" Timisoara,
Eftimie Murgu Sq. no. 2A, 300041, Timisoara</address>
      <phone>+40-720056934</phone>
      <fax>+40-256-415681</fax>
      <email>dcioca@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Romania</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Daniel Cioca, M.D., Ph.D.</name>
      <address>University of Medicine and Pharmacy "Victor Babes" Timisoara,
Eftimie Murgu Sq. no. 2A, 300041, Timisoara</address>
      <phone>+40-720056934</phone>
      <fax>+40-256-415681</fax>
      <email>dcioca@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Romania</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>