<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365723">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/01/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/02/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000161628</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A study exploring the ease with which placebo Suboxone sublingual films can be removed from the mouth after specified times, when administered stacked on top of each other compared to spaced out around the mouth.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An open-label study in Suboxone maintained clients exploring the effect of a stacked versus spaced oral administration of placebo Suboxone sublingual films on the ability to remove all or some of the films from the mouth after specified times.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Opioid dependence</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study will adopt a repeated measures crossover design with two conditions: film stacking and film spacing. The ease with which the film can be removed from the mouth, following dosing, will be examined. Participants will be provided with placebo film (equivalent in number to their usual dose denomination) and will be asked to try to remove the film following its administration. This will be repeated at various time points: 15 seconds, 30 seconds and 1 minute following administration. Hence, each subject will undergo six different dosing conditions (except for the patients on 1 Suboxone Film where stacking cannot occur, with only 3 conditions). Patients will be asked to estimate the proportion of the film removed on each occasion (none, partial, whole). All sessions will be conducted in a random order design, with 6 subjects required for those receiving one Film, and 12 subjects for each number of multiple films being administered (2,3 or 4), for a total of 42 subjects.

For the stacking conditions, participants will be instructed to administer the film by stacking (i.e. with more than 1 film, the participants will be asked to make the multiple films overlap). For the spaced (side by side) conditions, participants will be instructed to follow specific placement of the films in their mouth (i.e. maximum of 2 films to be placed side-by-side under the tongue and other films buccally on each cheek). Participants will be required to wait 15 minutes between each testing application and have a drink (30ml) of water immediately prior to administering film on each occasion. Hence each session should take approximately 3 hours per participant.</interventions>
    <comparator>Uncontrolled</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subjective estimate of amount of film able to be removed from the participant's mouth (ie. none, some, all) following sublingual (and buccal where applicable) administration</outcome>
      <timepoint>15 seconds, 30 seconds, 1 minute following administration of the last film</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subjective estimate of amount of film able to be removed from the participant's mouth (none, some, all) following administration, when multiple films are stacked sublingually compared to when the films are spaced around the mouth (ie. side by side sublingually and buccally).</outcome>
      <timepoint>15 seconds, 30 seconds, 1 minute following administration of the last film</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>a)	In Suboxone Film treatment (2-32mg/day) for at least 1 month
b)	Aged 18 years or over
c)	Confirmed as not pregnant with urine HCG (for female participants)
d)	Able to give written informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>a)	Participants who, in the opinion of the investigators, cannot fulfil the requirements of the protocol 
b)	Participants with concomitant severe, untreated medical or psychiatric conditions (as confirmed by treating clinician).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All participants are tested with matched placebo films, not active films. The number of films tested with is consistent with the number of films the participants normally receive with their usual active treatment.</concealment>
    <sequence>N/A</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>A total of 42 Suboxone patients will be recruited for this study, with approximately 21 patients targeted for each study site (2 sites in total). This sample size is based upon the number of clients receiving Suboxone film at both sites and provides a representative sample of this subset of clients.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/02/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>42</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>South Eastern Sydney Local Health District</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>District Executive Unit
Locked Mail Bag 21
TAREN POINT NSW 2229</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Reckitt Benckiser Pty Ltd.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>44 Wharf Road
West Ryde NSW 2114</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Associate Professor Nicholas Lintzeris</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>c/o The Langton Centre
591 South Dowling Street
Surry Hills
NSW 2010</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Participants will be provided with placebo film (equivalent in number to their usual Suboxone film dose denomination) and will be asked to try to remove the film following its administration sublingually. This will be repeated at various time points following administration (ie. 15 seconds, 30 seconds and 1 minute), under 2 different conditions. That is, the adherence of the film in the mouth (and subsequently ability to remove the film(s)) will be explored when multiple films are stacked as well as when spaced.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Reckitt Benckiser Pty Ltd is funding this study, in part, via award of an untied educational grant to the Chief Investigator.</publicnotes>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Nicholas Linzteris</name>
      <address>c/o The Langton Centre
591 South Dowling Street
Surry Hills
NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61293328703</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nicholas.lintzeris@sesiahs.health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Stefanie Leung</name>
      <address>c/o The Langton Centre
591 South Dowling Street
Surry Hills
NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61293328794</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>stefanie.leung@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Stefanie Leung</name>
      <address>c/o The Langton Centre
591 South Dowling Street
Surry Hills
NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61293328794</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>stefanie.leung@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Stefanie Leung</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>stefanie.leung@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>