<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="1277">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/05/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/05/2006</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000175572</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Community-based weight management of overweight and obese adolescents: a randomised controlled trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Community-based weight management of overweight and obese adolescents: a randomised controlled trial of extended therapeutic contact vs recommended care with primary outcomes body mass index standard deviation score and waist circumference standard deviation score</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Loozit</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention (G+E): current recommended treatment for adolescent overweight &amp; obesity + extended therapeutic contact.
Extended therapeutic contact will include a combination of telephone coaching, emails and short messaging service (SMS) text messaging
Current recommended treatment: group program weekly initially for 8 weeks followed by one booster group session each term for the next 7 terms.
Group program focuses on modification of behaviour, diet and physical activity, and building self-esteem 
Total time period of the intervention is 2 years</interventions>
    <comparator>Control (G): current recommended treatment for adolescent overweight and obesity</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body mass index standard deviation score (BMI z score)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 2 months, 12 months, and 24 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Waist circumference standard deviation score (waist z score)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 2 months, 12 months, and 24 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasting insulin, glucose total cholesterol, HDL cholesterol, LDL cholesterol</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 months, 12 months, 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 months, 12 months, 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 months, 12 months, 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Food intake and eating patterns</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 months, 12 months, 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychosocial assessment</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 months, 12 months, 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Overweight or obese by body mass index (ie BMI z score range 1.0  3.5); access to a landline telephone and either the internet or a mobile phone, or both; facility with English.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>13</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>17</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Severely obese adolescents (BMI z score &gt; 3.5 ), adolescents with secondary causes for overweight/obesity, intellectual disability, significant medical illness, psychiatric disturbance, lack of facility with spoken English, extreme dietary restriction, inability to take part in physical activity sessions, on medications that affect weight.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Concealed allocation to groups will be the responsibility of the trial manager. The subject ID will be written on the outside of a sealed opaque envelope which contains the group allocation. The trial manager will give the envelopes to the group facilitator. Facilitators will not know how the randomisation sequence was generated. Facilitators will explain the study and obtain consent from the adolescent and his/her parent. Only after consent is obtained will the next numbered envelope be opened and the group allocation logged with subject ID. A separate file will list subject ID and the group allocation and will be accessed only by the group facilitator, who is also responsible for contact with the subjects and intervention delivery. All data files will contain subject ID only. Measurements of subjects at each time point will be performed by a person who is blinded to group allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation to groups will be undertaken using minimization to balance age and gender between the two study groups. A computer generated randomisation schedule will be used to initially allocate participants to either the control (G) or the intervention (G+E) and then minimization will be used to resolve group imbalances if they occur. The strata that will be used in the minimization process will be as follows: boys aged 13-14 years, girls aged 13-14 years, boys aged 15-16 years and girls aged 15-16 years.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/06/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>20/06/2006</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>28/10/2008</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>168</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>151</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Children's Hospital at Westmead</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Locked Bag 4001
Westmead NSW 2145</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Sydney Research &amp; Development Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of Sydney, NSW 2006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Macquarie Bank Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 4294, Sydney NSW 1164</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Estate of the Late RT Hall</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Nexia Court &amp; Co., Chartered Accountants, PO Box H195, Australia Square NSW 1215</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to determine the effect of extended therapeutic contact over a 2 year period on a community-based weight management group program in overweight and obese young people aged 13-16 years. The additional therapeutic contact, via phone coaching, e-mail and SMS messages, is designed to give each young person the extra support and guidance to empower them to make and maintain healthy lifestyle changes. 168 young people will be randomised into either the group program, or the group program plus extended therapeutic contact. They will be followed up for 2 years to assess the effect of the program on a variety of health outcomes including weight, self-esteem and metabolic health.

Adolescents height, weight and waist circumference will be measured at baseline, 12 months and 24 months by contract staff who are blinded to treatment allocation. In addition, adolescents will be asked not to reveal their treatment allocation to staff who perform the measurements. Of course, it will not be possible for the adolescents to be blinded to treatment allocation.

If effective, we expect the following outcomes:

1) A reduction in levels of overweight and obesity in young people aged 13-16 years

2) The adoption and maintenance of healthy lifestyle behaviours in that segment of the population which has most to gain over a lifetime - overweight and obese young people

3) A novel, replicable, feasible, cost-effective community-based approach to overweight and obesity in young people tailored to the Australian health care system</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>1.	Shrewsbury VA,  OConnor J, Steinbeck KS, Stevenson K, Lee A, Hill AJ, Kohn MR, Shah S, Torvaldsen S, Baur LA. A randomised controlled trial of a community-based healthy lifestyle program for overweight and obese adolescents: the Loozit? study protocol. BMC Public Health 2009, 9:119 (http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2458/9/119).
2.	 Kornman KP, Shrewsbury VA, Chou AC, Nguyen B, Lee A, OConnor J, Steinbeck KS, Hill AJ, Kohn MR, Shah S, Baur LA. Electronic therapeutic contact for adolescent weight management: The Loozit® Study. Telemedicine and e-Health 2010; 16:678-685.
3.	Shrewsbury VA, Nguyen B, OConnor J, Steinbeck KS, Lee A, Hill AJ, Shah S, Kohn M, Torvaldsen S, Baur LA. Short-term outcomes of community-based adolescent weight management: The Loozit Study. BMC Pediatrics 2011; 11:13. Available at:  http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2431/11/13
4.	Twelve month outcomes of the Loozit randomized controlled trial: a community-based healthy lifestyle program for overweight and obese adolescents. Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med 2012; 166:170-177.
5.	Nguyen B, McGregor K, OConnor J, Shrewsbury VA, Lee A, Steinbeck KS, Hill AJ, Shah S, Kohn MR, Baur LA. Recruitment challenges and recommendations for adolescent obesity trials. J Paediatr Ch Health 2012; 48:38-43. 
6.	Nguyen T, Shrewsbury VA, OConnor J, Steinbeck KS, Hill AJ, Shah S, Kohn MR, Baur LA. Two-year outcomes of an adjunctive telephone coaching and electronic contact intervention for adolescent weight-loss maintenance: the Loozit randomized controlled trial. Int J Obesity 2013; 37:468-72.
7.	Nguyen B, Shrewsbury VA, OConnor J, Lau C, Steinbeck KS, Hill AJ, Baur LA.  Process evaluation of an adolescent weight management intervention. Health Prom Int 2015; 30:201-212. 
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Ethics Committee of the Children’s Hospital at Westmead</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>2006/004</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Sydney West Area Health Service Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/04/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2006/2/4.23(2295)</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Ethics Committee of the University of Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/05/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2006/004</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Louise Baur</name>
      <address>Discipline of Paediatrics &amp; Child Health
University of Sydney
The Childrens Hospital at Westmead
Locked Bag 4001
Westmead NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+61 2 98450000</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 98453389</fax>
      <email>louiseb3@chw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Mrs Janice O’Connor</name>
      <address>Clinical School
The Childrens Hospital at Westmead
Locked Bag 4001
Westmead NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+61 2 98451291</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 98453389</fax>
      <email>janiceo@chw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Louise Baur</name>
      <address>Clinical School, The Children's Hospital at Westmead, Locked Bag 4001, Westmead NSW 2145, AUSTRALIA</address>
      <phone>61-2-9845-0000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>louise.baur@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>