<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="878">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/11/2005</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/11/2005</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12605000724673</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A pilot study to examine whether an intervention that includes foot massage has any effect on the experience of nausea and vomiting following chemotherapy received by cancer patients in the ambulatory care setting.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot study to examine whether an intervention that includes foot massage has any effect on the experience of nausea and vomiting following chemotherapy received by cancer patients in the ambulatory care setting.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a pilot randomised unblinded cross-over trial of control (usual care) versus intervention (addition of foot massage) for nausea and vomiting in cancer patients undergoing chemotherapy.  As this study is a cross-over design all patients will receive both the intervention and usual care.  Participants allocated to Arm 1 will receive usual care first and the intervention second, participants allocated to Arm 2 will receive the intervention first and then the usual care. The foot massage intervention of 15 minutes will involve using slow firm or gentle strokes toward the heart from the base of the toes to the ankle area.  The fingertips will be used to make small circular movements around joints and between deep and superficial muscles, including the ankle, and between the metatarsals. A rhythmic lifting and squeezing of the flesh using both hands will be alternated with the other movements. Sorbolene cream with 10% glycerol (Hydraderm) will be used as the lubricant; this cream is readily available on the ward and is not perfumed.  The interaction between the masseur and the participant will be considered to be a part of the intervention.  It would be difficult to provide massage without interacting with the participant, and it is recognized that the effect of massage as a form of touch is unlikely to be distinguishable from the relationship with the participant. Patients must have at least one week between chemotherapy courses. Usual care is defined as the care received by patients attending the day chemotherapy ward which will involve no interaction with the pastoral care worker who is providing the intervention.  Participants will receive the foot massage prior to receiving the chemotherapy treatment.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control treatment is usual care.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>None</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>This pilot research project seeks to identify whether an intervention that includes a foot massage, given for 15 minutes prior to treatment of patients having moderate to high emetogenic chemotherapy  has an effect on the experience of nausea and vomiting in the ambulatory setting. Nausea and vomiting will be measured using the Chemotherapy Symptom Assessment Scale as well as a numerical rating scale for nausea (0 no nausea-10worst possible nausea) and a frequency of vomiting question.</outcome>
      <timepoint>72-96 hours post chemotherapy</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the effect the intervention of foot massage has on the occurrence, severity and distress of vomiting in cancer patients undergoing chemotherapy.  Distress of nausea and vomiting will be measured using the Chemotherapy Symptom Assessment Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>72-96 hours post chemotherapy</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine if there is any association between baseline distress score (using the Distress thermometer) and subsequent nausea and vomiting experience in cancer patients undergoing chemotherapy measured at 72-96 hours post chemotherapy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-chemotherapy and 
72-96 hours post chemotherapy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>To be eligible for the study, patients must be receiving chemotherapy in the ambulatory setting and: 1)Be receiving a chemotherapy that is moderately or highly emetogenic (Class III or IV) as listed in the guidelines for antiemetics for chemotherapy-induced emesis in adults; 2)Receiving at least the second course of chemotherapy and planned to receive at least 1 further cycle of the regimen at least one week apart; 3) Able to speak, read and write English sufficiently well to participate in the data collection process; 4)agree to data extraction from their medical record; 5)Have experienced nausea and/or vomiting since having chemotherapy.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1)	Are under the care of a psychiatrist
2)	Are scheduled to have chemotherapy as an in-patient treatment in the next 48 hours; 
3)	Are receiving chemotherapy treatment delivered as an in-patient; 
4)	Have a poor clinical performance status (ECOG &gt; 2); 
5)	Have an open skin wounds on their feet; 
6)	Have a foot tumour or foot metastasis, or radiation treatment to the feet.
7)	Have peripheral vascular disease
8)	Have lymphatic or venous occlusion / obstruction affecting the lower limbs.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The adaptive biased coin procedure will take place prior to commencement of the trial</concealment>
    <sequence>Following confirmation of eligibility patients will be randomly allocated in an approximately 1:1 ratio to receive either control then intervention or intervention then control. The method of randomisation will be based upon an adaptive biased coin procedure.  The primary researcher will inform the patient of group allocation</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Cathie Pigott</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 3 Nursing Education Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre Locked Bag 1 A'Beckett St Melbourne 8006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cancer Nurses Society Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>c/o Clinical Oncology Society of Australia
GPO Box 4708, Sydney NSW  2001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>N/A</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary />
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Cathie Pigott</name>
      <address>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
Level 3
Locked Bag 1
A'Beckett St
Melbourne VIC 8006</address>
      <phone>+61 3 96563561</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cathie.pigott@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Cathie Pigott</name>
      <address>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
Level 3
Locked Bag 1
A'Beckett St
Melbourne VIC 8006</address>
      <phone>+61 3 96563561</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cathie.pigott@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>