<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347907">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/01/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/01/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000034831</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>CHiRRP: Combating Haemophilus influenzae Related Respiratory Pathology</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A multi-centre, double-blind, randomised controlled trial to evaluate the efficacy of 10 valent-pneumococcal-Protein D conjugate vaccine compared to quadrivalent (ACYW135) meningococcal  conjugate vaccine  in reducing respiratory exacerbations in children aged greater than or equal to 18 months with suppurative lung disease.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1126-8627</utrn>
    <trialacronym>CHiRRP</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Suppurative lung disease (excluding cystic fibrosis)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>10valent pneumococcal - Protein D conjugate vaccine (10vPHiD), 0.5ml intramuscular injection, 2 doses, 2 months apart</interventions>
    <comparator>Quadrivalent (Men ACYW135) meningococcal conjugate vaccine: 0.5ml intramuscular injection, 2 doses, 2 months apart</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Respiratory exacerbation: An increase in sputum volume or purulence, or greater than 3-days of change in cough (&gt;20% increase in cough score (validated scale) or type [dry to wet]).  Participants will complete daily cough diaries for the duration of the study</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months post dose 2 of vaccine</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nasopharyngeal carriage of NTHi and vaccine type Streptococcus pneumoniae: specimens collected using cotton tip swab and analysed at the Menzies School of Health Research laboratory using both PCR and culture methodologies</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 months post dose 1 and six and 12 months following the second dose of study vaccine</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum antibody to Protein D, related NTHi proteins (P4 and P6) and to vaccine type pneumococcal serotypes: venus blood will be collected at study timepoints detailed below and analysed at the Telethon Institute for Child Health Research laboratory. </outcome>
      <timepoint>2 months post dose 1 and six and 12 months following the second dose of study vaccine expressed as anti-PD antibody geometric mean titres.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety: The safety and reactogenicity of vaccination (local and systemic reactions) and serious adverse events. Adverse event data will be collected using diary cards and via active surveillance for SAEs.

Local reactions to be assessed include pain, redness and swelling at the injection site.

Systemic reactions include fever, malaise, rash, nausea/vomiting, myalgia, nause/vomiting, diarrhoea</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 7 and day 30 post each dose of vaccine . Serious adverse events will be monitored over the entire active study period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>4.	Serum antibody to pneumococcal serotypes contained in the 10vPHiD vaccine (1, 5, 6B, 7F, 9V, 14, 23F, 4, 18C and 19F) expressed as anti-Pn antibody geometric mean titres.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 months post dose 1 and six and 12 months following the second dose of study vaccine</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mucosal antibody responses to Protein D, related NTHi proteins (P4 and P6) and vaccine type pneumococcal serotypes. Salivary specimens will be collected and analysed at the Telethon Institute for Child Health Research at the University of Western Australia</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 months post dose 1 and six and 12 months following the second dose of study vaccine</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Child aged greater than or equal to 18 months and &lt; 15 years with CSLD. The case definitions for CSLD are: a) CSLD: a clinical syndrome where there are symptoms indicating chronic endobronchial suppuration with or without HRCT evidence of radiological bronchiectasis. The main feature of the clinical syndrome is recurrent (3 or more episodes/yr) chronic (&gt;4 weeks) wet cough responding to antibiotics b) BE: confirmed by chest HRCT scan in last 5 years c) 3 or more episodes of Protracted Bacterial Bronchitis. Protracted bacterial bronchitis is defined as the presence of isolated chronic (&gt;4 weeks) of wet/moist cough that resolves with antibiotics in the absence of pointers suggestive of an alternative specific cause of cough.      2.	Receipt of meningococcal C conjugate monovalent vaccine at least 6 months prior to enrolment. 3	Provision of written informed consent from parent/guardian (assent if child aged greater than or equal to10 years) 4.	Parent/child willing and able to meet the requirements of the protocol 5.	Not planning to move from the study area in the 12 months following enrolment.
6. At least 2 respiratory exacerbations in the preceding 18 months</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Months</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>15</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Prior vaccination with PHiD-CV vaccine; contraindication to PHiD-CV and/or quadrivalent meningococcal conjugate vaccine as per the Australian Immunisation Handbook and product information sheets;10 known hypersensitivity to any component of the vaccines; confirmed or suspected immunosuppressive condition or immunodeficiency disorder; current (or within 90 days prior to receiving study vaccine) or planned (during the active study period) immunosuppressive therapy, including systemic corticosteroids (greater than14 days); administration of immunoglobulins and/or blood products with 90 days prior to receiving study vaccine, or planned administration of such products during the study period.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Potentially eligible children will be identified from the patient lists of the respiratory specialist departments and clinics at each of the participating study sites. The parents/guardians will be given a brief explanation of the study and provided with an information flyer and plain language statement to read at home. The attending specialist will obtain consent for the parent/guardian to be contacted by research staff to determine willingness to participate in the study. If parents/guardians are willing to discuss the study, they will be contacted by study staff for an interview over the phone to go through the study in detail. If they are interested in participating in the study, an appointment will be made for the first study visit.

Subjects will be assigned a unique subject number when written informed consent is provided. This number will identify the participant until randomisation. Once eligibility has been confirmed, a unique treatment number will be assigned at randomisation. This number will correspond to a vaccine pack which will be used to identify the participant for the duration of the study. 

Group allocation and vaccine code assignments will be maintained in secure electronic and paper files that are inaccessible to all investigators, study staff and participants.  The independent statistician will keep the randomisation code on file and emergency code break envelopes will be kept securely at QCMRI for use in case of an emergency. 

Vaccines will be repackaged and labelled at a Therapeutic Goods Administration approved Good Manufacturing Practice facility to appear identical to study personnel and participants. The study vaccines will be packed according to the randomisation code.</concealment>
    <sequence>A study statistician not directly involved in the analysis of study results will prepare the study randomisation code in a statistical database. A randomisation blocking scheme will be used to ensure that balance between the two treatment groups is maintained. Participants will be randomised to Group A or B (1:1 allocation), using computer generated random permuted block sizes. Randomisation will be stratified by age (&lt; 6yrs and greater than or equal to 6 yrs), and PBB vs other CSLD (4 strata). Six years is considered the age at which spirometry can be reliably performed in children. Treatment allocation will be determined using an internet based randomisation system administered by a statistician independent to the study.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/02/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>206</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Queensland
Brisbane QLD 4072</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>National Centre for Immunisation Research &amp; Surveillance</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University of Sydney
The Children's Hospital
Cnr Hawkesbury Rd &amp; Hainsworth St, 
Westmead NSW 2145</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Perth WA</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Menzies School of Health Research, Charles Darwin University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Rocklands Drive
TIWI NT 0810</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Chronic suppurative lung diseases in children are major causes of morbidity and mortality worldwide, particularly in disadvantaged populations. Repeated infections in childhood contribute to poor lung health in adulthood. The most common organism associated with infection is non-typeable Haemophilus influenzae (NTHi). This study aims to determine whether a vaccine against NTHi (10v-PHiD) can reduce repeated respiratory infections in children. We will be comparing the number of respiratory exacerbations  in the 12 months following vaccinated between children with chronic lung disease vaccinated with 10vPHiD and children who received a meningococcal vaccine (control vaccine).</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/02/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Kerry-Ann O'Grady</name>
      <address>Queensland Children's Medical Research Institute
Level 4, Foundation Building
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston Rd
HERSTON QLD 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3636 1296</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.ogrady@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Kerry-Ann O'Grady</name>
      <address>Queensland Children's Medical Research Institute
Level 4, Foundation Building
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston Rd
HERSTON QLD 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3636 1296</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.ogrady@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Kerry-Ann O'Grady</name>
      <address>Queensland Children's Medical Research Institute
Level 4, Foundation Building
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston Rd
HERSTON QLD 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3636 1296</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.ogrady@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kerry-Ann</name>
      <address>Queensland Children's Medical Research Institute
Level 4 Foundation Building
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston Road
Herston QLD 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3636 1296</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.ogrady@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>