<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369251">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/10/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/05/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000725369</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The PLAN Project: Pregnancy Lifestyle Activity and Nutrition: effectiveness of maternal lifestyle intervention commenced before 10 weeks gestation, in normal, overweight and obese mothers on maternal behaviours and infant's adiposity.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial investigating whether a maternal lifestyle intervention with behaviour change intervention commencing before 10 weeks gestation and consolidation phase to end of pregnancy, compared to usual clinical care, optimizes maternal lifestyle behaviour and reduces offspring adiposity.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1171-9320</utrn>
    <trialacronym>PLAN Project</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Pregnancy Lifestyle Activity Nutrition (PLAN) intervention is a 12-week program in early gestation, starting before 10 weeks gestation, which includes a web based application with a weight tracker, diet, physical activity and psychological modules. Accompanying the web-based programme, participants will have access to a one on one session with a dietitian/research nurse, and follow up with personalised, automated SMS follow up on SMART goal. SMART stands for Specific Measurable Attainable Realistic Time-Based. The SMART goal is decided on in consultation with the dietician. Following the end of the 12 week intervention period, the individual continues to have access to the web-site App and SMS SMART goal follow up until the end of pregnancy.

In further detail, the intervention includes:
1. Delivery of gestational weight gain guidelines according to the Institute of Medicine (The web-based application customised for this study provides a real-time feedback of a mothers weight synchronized to her stage of pregnancy.  It plots the individuals weight against an individualized optimal weight gain based on guidelines.  Immediate feedback is given when weight is entered.  According to level of adherence to guidelines, escalating support will be given in the form of SMS reminders, telephone or face to face visits); 
2. Web based delivery of Dietary education (on low glycemic index, low saturated fat, increased omega-3 fatty acid, increased fibre), cognitive behavioural materials to encourage goal setting, self-monitoring and problem solving and physical activity guidelines; 
3. One private session with a trained research assistant who will deliver tailored feedback on dietary intake and accelerometry with personalized diet and exercise plans, and SMART goal setting. (This occurs at approximately week 2 of the intervention and the duration is approximately 45-60 minutes.)
4.  Automated follow SMS targeted to the individuals SMART goal stipulated in the one on one session.

The web based intervention provides a combination of written material and interactive activities such as quizzes. The participants are progressively given access to the material with 3 modules delivered every week.  Participants are given email reminders to enter weight twice a week and also emails to inform them that new modules are available.  

Strategies to monitor adherence will include evidence of frequency of weight logging on the web based application.  </interventions>
    <comparator>Standard obstetric clinical care</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gestational weight gain in kg between start of intervention and to end of 12 weeks intervention</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured between start of intervention to end of 12 week intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neonatal and infant body fat percentage measured using the Cosmed PeaPod, a non-invasive assessment that uses air-displacement plethysmography. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Birth</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of gestational weight gain during pregnancy in kg/week.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At enrolment and 36 weeks gestation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>DNA methylation assessed on DNA extracted from cord blood</outcome>
      <timepoint>Birth</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Glucose tolerance as ascertained by routine oral glucose tolerance test at 28 weeks gestation</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 weeks gestation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Pregnant women who are recruited at &lt;10 weeks gestation and have a pre-pregnancy BMI of &gt;20, or BMI &gt;18 in high-risk ethnic groups.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Women with a current diagnosis of a serious pre-existing medical condition (e.g. type 1 or 2 diabetes, psychosis, eating disorder, thyroid condition or on medication for Polycystic Ovarian Syndrome)
Multiple births</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Written informed consent will be obtained before participating in an enrolment appointment. Each participating pregnant woman will be assigned a unique study number and randomly allocated to control or intervention.
Allocation is undertaken by a computer generated algorithm prespecified on RedCap which is stored on servers at a central administration site.  After enrolment, the research assistant accesses the computer generated allocation to group.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation schedule will be computer-generated (varying size of permuted blocks) and stratified by body mass index (BMI).
The randomisation will be produced by an independent party</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The primary clinical outcomes will be assessed on an intention-to-treat basis. 
Differences in gestational weight gain in kg between control and intervention group between start and end of intervention and total gestational weight gain will be assessed with linear regression. 
Differences between control and intervention group for outcomes in the infant of fat mass, and anthropometry will be assessed by linear mixed modelling adjusted for baseline and covariates (including sex and ethnicity of the infant).
Based on the maternal primary outcome, we require 333 per group to detect a 1.0 kg weight difference between groups (80% power, 0.05 level) .  Allowing for a 20% dropout, a total sample size of 800 (400 per group) is required.  The feasibility study involves a target of 40 in each group, total 80.  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1 / Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>15/12/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>6/04/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>57</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>6/02/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Joondalup Health Campus - Joondalup</hospital>
    <hospital>St John of God Hospital, Subiaco - Subiaco</hospital>
    <postcode>6027 - Joondalup</postcode>
    <postcode>6008 - Subiaco</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Telethon Kids Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>100 Roberts Road
Subiaco, WA, 6008</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Telethon Kids Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>100 Roberts Road
Subiaco, WA, 6008
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This RCT will test whether a lifestyle intervention in early pregnancy optimizes gestational weight gain and reduces offspring adiposity. The intervention will use smart phone web based applications to deliver diet, physical activity and well being advice to overweight or obese pregnant women in early pregnancy (commenced prior t0 10 weeks gestation) to optimise their gestational weight gain (weight gain during the course of the pregnancy) within the recommended medical guidelines. 

The project will then follow up to assess neonatal and infant outcomes in relation to fat percentage and anthropometry. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Joondalup Health Campus Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Grand Blvd &amp; Shenton Ave
Joondalup, WA, 6027</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/10/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1525</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/07/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St John of God Health Care Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>12 Salvado Road
Subiaco, WA, 6008</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/04/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>873</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/03/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Rae-Chi Huang</name>
      <address>Telethon Kids Institute
100 Roberts Road
Subiaco  WA  6008
Australia</address>
      <phone>+610894897924</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rae-chi.huang@telethonkids.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Rae-Chi Huang</name>
      <address>Telethon Kids Institute
100 Roberts Road 
Subiaco  WA  6008
Australia</address>
      <phone>+610894897924</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rae-chi.huang@telethonkids.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Rae-Chi Huang</name>
      <address>Telethon Kids Institute
100 Roberts Road
Subiaco  WA  6008
Australia</address>
      <phone>+610894897924</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rae-chi.huang@telethonkids.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Katherine Mackie</name>
      <address>Telethon Kids Institute
100 Roberts Road 
Subiaco  WA  6008
Australia</address>
      <phone>+610894897924</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>katherine.mackie@telethonkids.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>