<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371401">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/09/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/10/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001470482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Translating  research  evidence  from  the Healthy  Beginnings   Trial  to  prevent  childhood   obesity  at  the  beginning   of  life:  feasibility, effectiveness    and   cost-effectiveness</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Three Arm RCT of Communicating Healthy Beginnings Advice by Telephone (CHAT) to Mothers with Infants to Prevent Childhood Obesity</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>The CHAT study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NSW TRGS No. 200</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Child overweight and obese</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a three arm randomised controlled trial 

The proposed interventions are based upon the principles of the successful HBT intervention, to be delivered starting in the late antenatal period and over the first 12 months after birth (14 months). The timing of the staged intervention corresponds to milestones in early childhood development, in particular with regard to healthy feeding practices, nutrition and play as well as parent-child interactions. Below are the stages and contents of the interventions as well as intervention approaches: 

3rd trimester: 	
Health benefits of breastfeeding; strategies to address breastfeeding barriers; importance of tummy time - when and for how long; social support mechanisms.
 
1 month:
Breastfeeding support, overcome problems initiating breastfeeding; referral to Child and Family Health nurse team establishment of breastfeeding pattern and management of problems; if formula feeding - safe preparation; baby cues; sleep and settling routines; tummy time.    

3 months:
Establishment of breastfeeding patterns; support &amp; management of problems; tummy time; introduction of solids around 6 months; discuss breastfeeding and work; postnatal exercise and nutrition.

5-6 months:
Reinforce breastfeeding pattern; support management of problems; when and what food to introduce from around 6 months; encourage continued breastfeeding; activities that help develop babys strength &amp; control  continue tummy time; avoid distractions like TV.

8-9 months:
Encourage sustained breastfeeding; advice on balanced infant feeding; healthy snack ideas; quantity &amp; variety of fruits and veg; introduce cup feeding; discuss healthy drinks; maternal-child relationship &amp; feeding.

10-11 months: 	
Encourage active play and motor skills development; discuss play ideas and screen time

The SMS + Mail-outs intervention:  Written materials and checklists will be posted according to the developmental stage of the main issues at set times (3rd trimester, 1 month, 3 months, 5-6 months, 8-9 months, 10-11 months). The resources will be translated into Arabic or Chinese if indicated. Following the postage of the stage-specific intervention resource, mothers will be sent text messages to reinforce the health promotion messages 2 times/week for 4 weeks. We will employ three part-time research nurses to deliver both SMS and telephone support interventions. The SMS and telephone support will not be administered in Arabic or Chinese.

The telephone support + Mail-outs intervention: Following each posting of materials, the research nurses will contact mothers via phone to discuss the health promotion messages and address mothers concerns and needs regarding healthy beginnings of life and childhood obesity. It is anticipated that the duration of each telephone session will be ~20 minutes.

Ongoing process evaluations will be conducted by research officers supervised by research advisory committee. </interventions>
    <comparator>Mothers in the control group will only receive usual care, which all new mothers (including the intervention mothers) receive, provided by the Local Health District Child &amp; Family Health nursing service. To maximise the retention rate, we will post home safety promotion materials and a newsletter on Kids Safety to the control group 4 times within 14 months, as occurred in the previous Healthy Beginnings Trial, in order to keep them engaged in the study.  </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Children's BMI</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 12 and 24 months of age</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Breastfeeding duration self-reported by mother in study-specific survey</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 6 months and 12 months of  age</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome> timing of introduction of solids self-reported by mother in study-specific survey</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 6 months of age </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> time of starting tummy time and frequency of tummy time self-reported by mother in study-specific survey</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 6 months of age 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>whether child starts drinking from a cup self-reported by mother in study-specific survey

 
</outcome>
      <timepoint> at 12 months of age </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>screen-time self-reported by mother in study-specific survey</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 12 and 24 months of age </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>outdoor playtime on a typical weekday and a weekend day self-reported by mother in study-specific survey</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 12 and 24 months of age </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>dietary/nutrition (daily or weekly vegetable, fruit, soft drink, fast food consumption) self-reported by mother in study-specific survey</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 12 and 24 months of age </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Whether use food for reward self-reported by mother in study-specific survey
</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 12 and 24 months  of age </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Whether using bottle to go to  bed self-reported by mother in study-specific survey
</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 12 months of age</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Women will be eligible to participate if they are aged 16 years and over, at third trimester, are able to communicate in English (or can communicate with written information in Chinese or Arabic), have a mobile phone and live in the recruitment areas.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Women will be excluded from the study if they have a severe medical condition based on advice given by their doctors. Women who cannot give informed consent, and those with babies with known major fetal anomalies will also be excluded.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is concealed with sealed opaque envelopes
</concealment>
    <sequence>The random allocation will be determined by a standard concealment with a computer generated random number using random permuted blocks, stratified by Local Health District. A research assistant who has no direct contact with participating women will be responsible for generating the random numbers and preparing the sealed opaque envelopes containing the group allocation.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>a three arm RCT</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>With a Type I error rate=0.05 and 80% power, a sample size of 288 for per group is needed to detect a difference in mean body mass index (BMI) of 0.35 units between the intervention and control groups at age 2 years. This was based on a conservative estimate  of mean effect size of 0.35 in BMI with standard deviation of 1.5 from the Healthy Beginnings Trial. To allow for an estimated 20% lost to follow-up, a total of 360 participants will be needed in each group. Therefore, the sample size will be 1080 in total. 

Outcomes will be compared between the intervention group and the control group using intention-to-treat principles and CONSORT guidelines.   For continuous variables, means will be compared using t-tests .For categorical variables, chi-squared tests will be used. Survival analysis will be used for breastfeeding time: Kaplan-Meier curves will be used to estimate median breastfeeding time and log-rank tests will be used to compare groups. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>16/01/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>23/02/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/07/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>27/07/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>1080</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>1155</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/09/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>Liverpool Hospital - Liverpool</hospital>
    <hospital>Canterbury Hospital - Campsie</hospital>
    <hospital>St George Hospital - Kogarah</hospital>
    <hospital>Campbelltown Hospital - Campbelltown</hospital>
    <hospital>Queanbeyan District Hospital - Queanbeyan</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Hospital for Women - Randwick</hospital>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>2170 - Liverpool</postcode>
    <postcode>2194 - Campsie</postcode>
    <postcode>2217 - Kogarah</postcode>
    <postcode>2560 - Campbelltown</postcode>
    <postcode>2620 - Queanbeyan</postcode>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>A/Prof. Li Ming Wen</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 9 North, King George V Building, Missenden Rd. Camperdown. NSW 2050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The NSW Ministry of Health Translational Research Grants Scheme</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>73 Miller St North Sydney NSW 2060</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Prof Chris Rissel </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Level 6, The Hub, D17 Charles Perkins Centre, The University of Sydney, Camperdown, NSW 2006.</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Childhood obesity is a serious public health challenge. About one in five Australian children aged 2 to 3 years is now either overweight or obese. Early intervention is important as excess weight and fast weight gain in early childhood are related to being overweight later in life with considerable impact upon health and health services. 

Over the past 7 years we have developed, implemented and evaluated an early obesity intervention program funded by NHMRC. The project tilted Healthy Beginnings Trial (HBT)was designed to improve infant feeding practices, eating habits, active play, and reduce TV viewing time to prevent childhood obesity in the first two years of life through staged home visiting. However, the high cost associated with home visits potentially limits population reach. To translate the successful evidence from the HBT into scaled-up practice applicable across the state with low-cost and broad-reach approaches, we propose this study to promote healthy infant feeding and active play using telephone support and Short Message Service (SMS).

The proposed study aims to test the effectiveness of telephone support or SMS with mail-outs in reducing child BMI z-score, promoting healthy infant feeding practice and active play in the first 12 months of life; and examine the cost-effectiveness of these interventions.

We hypothesise that the staged early intervention using either mailed self-motivating written materials plus SMS or plus telephone support delivered in the antenatal period and over the first 12 months of life, relative to usual care, will:

1) lead to reduced child BMI z-score and rapid weight gain at age 12 months compared to usual care.
2) improve infant feeding practices and decrease the prevalence of obesity-related behaviours at 12 months compared to usual care.
3) be more cost-effective compared to usual care, and SMS will be more cost-effective than telephone support.

Both qualitative and quantitative methods will be used in this study. A total of 921 women at late pregnancy will be recruited from main hospitals in four Local Health Districts. They will be randomly allocated to one of three arms. Randomisation will be stratified by Local Health District. Telephone survey will be used to collect data at baseline and 6 months. Face-to-face interview will be used to collect data at 12 months.  

In addition, qualitative interviews will be conducted with subgroup of mothers (n=20 per group) who will receive telephone support and SMS. The purpose is to gain a better understanding of usefulness of telephone support and SMS.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>SLHD Ethics Review Committee (RPAH Zone) (EC00113)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Development Office
RPAH Medical Centre
Suite 210A
100 Carillon Avenue
NEWTOWN NSW 2042
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/10/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>640008 Dec 11</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/08/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Li Ming Wen</name>
      <address>Sydney Local Health District. Level 9 North, King George V Building, Missenden Rd. Camperdown. NSW. 2050. 
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 95159055</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 95159056</fax>
      <email>LiMing.Wen@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Li Ming Wen</name>
      <address>Sydney Local Health District. Level 9 North, King George V Building, Missenden Rd. Camperdown. NSW. 2050.</address>
      <phone>+61 2 95159055</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 95159056</fax>
      <email>liming.wen@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Li Ming Wen</name>
      <address>Sydney Local Health District. Level 9 North, King George V Building, Missenden Rd. Camperdown. NSW. 2050.</address>
      <phone>+61 2 95159055</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 95159056</fax>
      <email>liming.wen@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Huilan Xu</name>
      <address>Sydney Local Health District. Level 9 North, King George V Building, Missenden Rd. Camperdown. NSW. 2050.</address>
      <phone>+61 2 95159055</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 95159056</fax>
      <email>huilan.xu@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>