<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83942">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/05/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/06/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000421235</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of a nutritional supplement on weight gain after initiation of atypical antipsychotic medication in Early Psychosis patients.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of a nutritional supplement on weight gain after initiation of atypical antipsychotic medication in Early Psychosis patients.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>2009/036</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Early Psychosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Psychosis and personality disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The aim of this project is to see if daily 2g oral capsule dose of Omega 3 supplement will improve the participants ability to minimise any possible weight gain that may occur when taking antipsychotic medication.  The oral capsules will be taken once daily when the participants take there medically prescribed medication. To meet the 2g dose amount participants are required to take 4 oral capsule daily (at one time)  as each capsule only contains 500mg of active ingredient. 

We are proposing that the use of this dose Omega 3 will reduce the participants appetite and help with any possible rapid weight gain.  Currently this is a new field of research and no one has tested this idea with young people who are taking antipsychotic medications for the first time.  The evidence does show that many young people who start antipsychotic medications gain weight and then stop taking the medication, placing them at greater risk of getting sick again.  Weight gain on antipsychotic medications is usually the most rapid during the start of treatment and in the first few weeks of starting medication.  This study aims to test if using a product that is widely available with little known side effects can assist with minimising any possible weight gain that may occur on antipsychotic medications.  
The nutritional supplement has been widely researched in other areas of health and has been shown to improve mood.  No known side effects of the nutritional supplemnt has been documented.  The nutritional supplement is widely available in stores and without prescription.   

Each person will be asked to participate for 14 weeks in total.  The first group (participants are randomly assigned to either group 1 or 2) will start on the active ingredient for 6 weeks then go onto the placebo for 8 weeks (allowing a 2 week wash out period post active ingredient).  The second group will start on the placebo for 8 weeks (which is 6 weeks on placebo and then 2 weeks wash out ahead of starting the active tablets - just for consistency in the length of the trial (total 14 weeks for both groups) and then start the active ingredients for the remaining 6 weeks. 

Every two weeks either the nutritional supplement or the placebo will be provided by the treating doctor.</interventions>
    <comparator>a placebo medication that contains olive oil and no active ingredient. The plcebo's dose and talets are the same as the active ingredients.  that is, each participant will be required to take 4 capsules daily at the same time that they take their medically prescribed medication. 

The placebo capsules are the same size and colour as the active capsules and the administarion will be identical.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary objective is to establish if the use of the nutritional supplementation at the commencement of atypical antipsychotic medication can reduce weight gain in young people with early psychosis and assist in minimising rapid weight gain associated with these medications.

the methods of assessment includes, clincial psychological assessments of mental state and compliance (routine assessments already completed at service) , blood test to look at compliance of supplement, a food history and food diary record and weight/ body mass index (BMI) measurements.  All these  measurements (and the same measurements) are taken at baseline, crossover and end point.</outcome>
      <timepoint>weight gain measures at start, cross over and end point</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A secondary aim is to see whether the intervention improves compliance with treatment as a result of reduced weight gain.  The indirect nature of the effect requires that it be relegated to a secondary status in this small project.

As stated above:

the methods of assessment includes, clincial psychological assessments of mental state and compliance (routine assessments already completed at service) , blood test to look at compliance of supplement, a food history and food diary record and weight/ body mass index (BMI) measurements.</outcome>
      <timepoint>compliance at start, cross over and end point</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Are accepted in to the Early Psychosis service at Princess Alexandra Hospital, Division of Mental Health.

Are aged between 18 and 25 years.
Have a family member/ carer/ significant other who is able to participate in the study to provide a history of food behaviours and changes...

Have not been on any antipsychotic medication for greater than 4 weeks. 

Not currently underweight (less than 18 body mass index (BMI))</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>25</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Outside nominated age range

No family member/ significant other who can participate in diet history  

Underweight (less than 18 BMI)

Established on antipsychotic medication

Not able to understand written consent form

Already taking fish oil</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/07/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>12</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>4122</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Queensland University of Technology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Queensland Univerity of Technology
Institute of Health and Biomedical Innovation (ihbi)
Level 3, 5 School Street
Kelvin Grove Urban Village
Kelvin Grove, Queensland, 4059</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Queensland University of Technology</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Queensland Univerity of Technology
Institute of Health and Biomedical Innovation (ihbi)
Level 3, 5 School Street
Kelvin Grove Urban Village
Kelvin Grove, Queensland, 4059</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Princess Alexandra Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>519 Kessels Road 
MacGregor 4122
Queensland</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To see if using a nutritional supplement while starting atypical antipsychotic medications can reduce the risk of weight gain for a target group of young people aged 18-25years with Early Psychosis</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Princess ALexandar Hopsital  Helath Service District Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ipswich Road
Woolloongabba 4103
Queensland</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/03/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Carina Capra</name>
      <address>519 Kessels Road
MacGrgeor</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3167 8444</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Carina_Capra@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Carina Capra</name>
      <address>519 Kessels Road
MacGrgeor</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3167 8444</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Carina_Capra@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>