<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373242">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/07/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001115325</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparing Pre-prostatectomy and Post-prostatectomy Exercise Intervention for Prostate Cancer Patients.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparing the effect of either a Pre-prostatectomy and Post-prostatectomy Exercise Intervention and Assessment on Patient outcomes for Prostate Cancer Patients.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Prostate cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Prostate</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A randomized controlled trial study design will be used to evaluate and compare the effectiveness of a 6- week comprehensive individually supervised pre-surgical exercise program, with assessments conducted at Edith Cowan University Exercise Medicine Institute (EMRI). The exercise group (PresurgEx) will exercise prior to surgery and receive usual care after surgery. The delay-exercise usual care control group (Delay) will only be provided with the current usual care prior to surgery and offered 6 weeks of exercise post-surgery. Testing will be conducted at baseline, pre-surgery, 6 weeks post-surgery (6PS), and 12 weeks post-surgery (12PS). In addition, a 24-hr pad test will be undertaken after discharge from hospital. The Delay group will start exercise after 6PS. The intervention involves resistance (chest press, leg press, seated row, leg curls, leg extension, bicep curls, and calf raises) and aerobic training (Treadmill) undertaken thrice weekly in an exercise setting. Patients will be invited to participate by their attending specialists, who are part of this project. This replicates an existing collaboration between EMRI and the urologist at the participating hospitals. Information about the program will be provided and those that express interest will be contacted by the research team. A sample size calculation (2-tailed, alpha = 0.05 and power = 95%) based on expected effect size differences in muscle strength reported in previous studies and using G*Power indicated that each group requires a sample of 16 participants. It is estimated that we will be able to recruit approximately 20 participants per group (factoring in a 30% attrition rate) over a one year period. The eligibility criteria to participate includes: localised PCa; at least seven weeks between diagnosis of cancer and surgery date; absence of any acute illness or any musculoskeletal, cardiovascular or neurological disorder that could inhibit the ability to walk 400m unassisted and undertake upper- and lower-body exercise; medically cleared by their physician; and written consent.

Exercise intervention
Each supervised exercise session will be ~90 minutes in duration. Sessions will commence with a 5-minute warm-up consisting of a moderate level of aerobic exercise (~60% heart rate maximum (HRmax)), as well as stretching exercises of the major muscle groups. This will be followed by a previously used resistance-training regime targeting upper- and lower-limb exercises. Progression of resistance exercise will follow guidelines previously outlined. Specifically, training phases were: week 1  2 (two sets 12 repetition maximum (RM)), week 3 (three sets of 10 RM), week 4  5 (three sets of 8 RM), and week 6 (four sets of 6 RM). This will be followed by 15 minutes of exercises focusing on the trunk stabilising muscles which includes three sets of three different exercises [planks (anterior abdominals), reverse bridge on Swiss ball (back extensors) and side planks (oblique abdominals)] with a rest of 30 to 60 seconds between sets. Finally the session will conclude with 20 minutes of aerobic exercise at 60  80% (intensity) of the estimated HRmax (220  age in years) followed by a 5-minute cool-down. All sessions will be conducted by an accredited exercise physiologist (RA) to ensure safety and adherence (number of sessions attended, number of sessions missed will be compiled).
</interventions>
    <comparator>Delay exercise usual care control group (Delay)
The delay-exercise usual care control group (Delay) will only be provided with the current usual care prior to surgery (no activity specifically prescribed) and offered 6 weeks of exercise post-surgery. This group will receive the current standard practice prior to surgery and information on performing exercises on the trunk stabilising muscles similar to the exercise intervention. Testing will be conducted at baseline, pre-surgery, 6 weeks post-surgery (6PS), and 12 weeks post-surgery (12PS). In addition, a 24-hr pad test will be undertaken after discharge from hospital. The Delay group will be provided an option to partake in the above described exercise intervention after the 6PS assessment session.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical Function assessed by one repetition strength test and Physical function test. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Testing will be conducted at baseline, pre-surgery, 6 weeks post-surgery (6PS) (Primary time point), and 12 weeks post-surgery (12PS).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>DEXA Scan measured by Body composition</outcome>
      <timepoint>Testing will be conducted at baseline, pre-surgery, 6 weeks post-surgery (6PS) (Primary time point), and 12 weeks post-surgery (12PS).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>quality of Life assessed by SF-36
</outcome>
      <timepoint> Testing will be conducted at baseline, pre-surgery, 6 weeks post- surgery (6PS), and 12 weeks post-surgery (12PS). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria
1.	Localised prostate cancer.
2.	Have at least seven weeks between diagnosis of cancer and surgery date.
3.	No acute illness, musculoskeletal, cardiovascular or neurological disorder that could place the participant at risk of injury or illness resulting from the exercise. 
4.	Ability to walk 400m unassisted and undertake upper- and lower-body exercise.
5.	Not be performing regular exercise defined as undertaking structured aerobic or resistance training two or more times per week within the past 3 months.
6.	Be able to read and speak English.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>45</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1)  metastasised cancer patient
2)  any illness and inability to walk 400m unassisted 
3) patient undertaking structured resistance exercise </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The proposed sample size will allow for the determination of an effect size of d = 0.5 used to examine clinically meaningful changes across time. The main outcomes measured in this trial will be analyzed using MANOVA, comparing changes  within and between groups.  Where appropriate,  posthoc testing  with  Holm-Bonferroni adjustment will be employed to locate the source of significant difference. An intention-to-treat approach will be used for all  analyses with maximum likelihood imputation of missing values  (expectation maximisation).  All results will be recorded as mean + SD, and the size of change and precision will be provided by reporting the change in  mean values  and the  95%  confidence intervals  (95%CI).  Statistical significance  will be  set at  an alpha level of 0.05. The effect size (ES) will be calculated for all results: ES = (MeanPost - MeanPre/SDPre).

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>31/10/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/03/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/06/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St John of God Hospital, Murdoch - Murdoch</hospital>
    <hospital>Hollywood Private Hospital - Nedlands</hospital>
    <hospital>Fiona Stanley Hospital - Murdoch</hospital>
    <postcode>6150 - Murdoch</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Favil Singh</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>270 Joondalup Drive
Joondalup 6027
WA</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Edith Cowan University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>270 Joondalup Drive
Joondalup 6027
WA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to evaluate the effectiveness of a 6- week comprehensive supervised pre-surgical exercise program in prostate cancer patients scheduled for prostatectomy.

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to join this study if you are a male aged between 45 and 80 years of age and have been diagnosed with localised prostate cancer with at least seven weeks to until scheduled surgery date.

Study details
Study participants will be allocated by chance to one of the two groups. First group will receive a 6- week comprehensive supervised pre-surgical exercise program consisting of progressive resistance and aerobic exercise. Second group will receive usual care during the pre-surgery period along with information on performing exercises on the trunk stabilising muscles similar to the exercise intervention. This group will be provided an option to partake in the exercise intervention at completion of 6 weeks post-surgery assessments.
Testing will be conducted at baseline, pre-surgery, 6 weeks post- surgery (6PS), and 12 weeks post-surgery (12PS). In addition, a 24-hr pad test will be undertaken after discharge from hospital.

This research is a critical step in a series of studies required to determine the most effective and efficient ways to maximize prostate cancer patient health and therefore lay the foundation for future research.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>All current recruited participant are referred from private urologist and they are only recruited after the approval of ethics from Edith Cowan University. The second Ethic approval on a later date is from South Metropolitan Health Service-Research Ethics &amp; Governance which governs the public hospitals. No study participant has been recruited from Fiona Stanley Hospital which falls under the South Metropolitan Health Service-Research Ethics &amp; Governance. </publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Edith Cowan University HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>270 Joondalup Drive
Joondalup 6027
WA</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/03/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Project #14320</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Metropolitan Health Service-Research Ethics&amp;Governance</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 3
Southern Research Facility (Perkins Building)
11 Robin Warren Drive
Murdoch 6150
WA </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/12/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016-171</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Favil Singh</name>
      <address>Exercise Medicine Research Institute
Building 21
Edith Cowan University
270 Joondalup Drive
Joondalup WA, 6027
</address>
      <phone>+61 8 63042369</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>f.singh@ecu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Favil Singh</name>
      <address>Exercise Medicine Research Institute
Building 21
Edith Cowan University
270 Joondalup Drive
Joondalup WA, 6027</address>
      <phone>+61 8 63042369</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>f.singh@ecu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>f.singh@ecu.edu.au</name>
      <address>Exercise Medicine Research Institute
Building 21
Edith Cowan University
270 Joondalup Drive
Joondalup WA, 6027</address>
      <phone>+61 8 63042369</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>f.singh@ecu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>