<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371154">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001151426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Improving independence in driving for people with Autism Spectrum Disorder</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effectiveness of an Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD)-specific driver training package in supporting learner drivers with ASD to obtain a driver's license.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Autism Spectrum Disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Autistic spectrum disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is the ASD-specific driver training package which includes face to face training, online training and on-road driving training. The intervention will be delivered by two driving instructors (WA and NSW) who will be trained by the project team. Parents in the intervention group will also be trained in the use of the ASD-specific training package prior to the commencement of the intervention.

This RCT study is the final stage of a big project.  It is a three and a half year project. Contents for each proposed component are built from initial studies which involve literature review, focus group interviews and observation studies as follows:

Study 1: Scoping the literature and obtaining end-user and expert opinion:
- Summarise current knowledge on the driving behaviours of learner drivers with ASD.
- Identify and evaluate international and local resources that address the driving needs of people with ASD.
- Understand end-user and stakeholder perspectives on the difficulties learner drivers with ASD encounter while learning to drive; the driving behaviours they exhibit; and the strategies they use to support safe driving behaviours.
Study 2: Assess off- and on-road driving behaviours of learner drivers with ASD.
Study 3: Develop and pilot test the feasibility and appropriateness of a driver training package containing ASD-specific on- and off-road training sessions in supporting learner drivers with ASD to obtain a drivers licence and maintain on-road safety.

The findings from these studies will be used to design and finalise the contents of the proposed components of the ASD-specific driver training package.  We are currently conducting Study 1, therefore we are not able to provide any specific details for the proposed components.  We hope to have the contents designed for each component by Dec 2017.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control treatment is the conventional driver training. 

The conventional driver training is the on-road driving training under a qualified supervisor.  The learner drivers can use the driver's handbook provided by the Department of Transport (WA) or the Roads and Maritime Service (NSW) as a guide to safe driving.
 
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome measure is pass or fail of the practical driving test to provide an objective, un-biased estimate of the effectiveness of the package. 

The driving test is the practical driving assessment conducted by the Department of Transport (WA) and the Roads and Maritime Services (NSW).</outcome>
      <timepoint>10 weeks after intervention commencement </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The number of attempts to successfully pass the practical driving test. Participants to answer this in a survey form.</outcome>
      <timepoint>10 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pre- and post-intervention Driving behaviour. Using assessment instrument such as The Performance Analysis of Driving Ability (P-Drive).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 10 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Driving Behaviour post-intervention.  Survey instrument such as the Manchester Driving Behaviour and the Adelaide Driving Self-Efficacy Scale will be used.</outcome>
      <timepoint>10-weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of training lessons. Participants to answer in this in a survey form.</outcome>
      <timepoint>10-weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>To be eligible for the study, the participants have to be a learner driver aged 16 to 35 diagnosed with ASD who intend to learn driving, but have not started any formal driving training.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>35</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants who cannot speak and understand English, and cannot understand instructions will be excluded.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealment will be carried out using sealed envelopes. </concealment>
    <sequence>A set of sealed envelopes, each containing a treatment allocation (on the inside of the sealed envelope) and a study numbered representing sequence of enrolment (on the outside of the envelope), will be provided to the research officer in NSW and WA. After each new participant is checked for eligibility, provided consent to take part in the study, and has baseline measurements taken, they will be assigned a study number and the relevant envelope will be opened to reveal their allocated treatment. During the baseline assessment, both the researchers and participants will be blinded to group allocation. The sequences will be created using computer-generated random numbers (using the SAS version 9.2 software).  </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>We employ the primary outcome measure, pass or fail of the driving test in each group to estimate the sample size.  We assume that the study participants who are in the control group (driving instructor package) experience a 50% pass rate on their first attempt at the driving test.  If we anticipate that those participants who undergo the additional pre-test training (the AS-Specific Training Package) will have a pass rate of 85%, then a sample of size N = 27 in each group will be adequate to detect this difference with 80% power and using a=0.05.  The AS-specific training package are built up with reference to the requirements of licencing requirements of the Transportation Department, with special attention to the needs of AS-learner drivers.  Expectation of the participants who has received the training to achieve a higher rate of passing is reasonable.  We recruit 30 participant in each control and intervention group, taking into account of 10% estimated attrition rate.

The primary outcome measure is the pass or fail of the driving test, and this will be used to provide an objective, un-biased estimate of the effectiveness of the package.  This outcome will be compared between the intervention and control groups using the Chi-square statistic.  The secondary measures of the effectiveness of the training package include the number of attempts participants to successfully obtain a provisional licence (either a t-test or a non-parametric Wilcoxon 2-sample test), number of training lessons (t-test or Wilcoxon) and changes in driving performance score after training. The changes in the driving performance score for will be calculated for each participant (post minus pre scores).  These changes in scores will then be compared between the intervention and control groups using either a t-test or Wilcoxon test (depending on skewness). A t-test or Wilcoxon test will also be used to determine the statistical significance of difference between intervention and control groups in the post-test measure outcomes including the Manchester Driving Behaviour and the Adelaide Driving Self-Efficacy Scale.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2018</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>21/09/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/11/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Hoe Lee</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Associate Professor Hoe Lee
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth Western Australia
6845</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Autism CRC Limited</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 3 Foxtail Building
Long Pocket Campus, The University of Queensland
80 Meiers Road, Indooroopilly, QLD 4068</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Individuals with autism spectrum disorders (ASD) face social and cognitive difficulties that affect their ability to establish relationships, maintain employment and participate in community activities. Difficulties in community mobility act as barriers to their social inclusion. Driving is often difficult for people with ASD, as it requires the individual to make quick decisions and solve problems in response to road conditions and unpredictable traffic. There is currently a lack of understanding on how learner drivers with ASD read and respond to traffic and hazards on the road. The problem is further confounded as there are currently no established standards in Australia for assessing driving behaviours.  

The aim of the proposed research is to address community mobility challenges experienced by young adults with ASD by designing, pilot testing and evaluating the feasibility, appropriateness and effectiveness of an ASD-specific driver training package in supporting learner drivers with ASD to obtain a drivers license and maintain on-road safety.

The driving project will involve four studies. The Randomised-Controlled Trial study is the last study of this project with the aim to test the effectiveness and appropriateness of the ASD-specific driver training package: 
-  Reducing the number of attempts learner drivers with ASD take to successfully obtain a provisional licence.
-  Reducing the number of face-to-face practice training sessions learner drivers with ASD require before obtaining a drivers licence.
-  Improving driving behaviour, hazard perception skills and attitude to risk taking of learner drivers with ASD.
-  Improving learner drivers reflection on their driving. 

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin Human Research Ethics </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Research and Development
GPO Box U1987
Perth Western Australia 6845</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/07/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HRE2016-0130</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/04/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Western Sydney University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Locked Bag 1797
Penrith NSW 2751 Australia
Research Engagement, Development and Innovation (REDI)</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/07/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>RH11772</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/07/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371154-20160715 Driving Curtin HREC Approved.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371154-H11772 - UWS_Driving Human Ethics Reciprocal Approval -  Jul 2016.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371154-20160801 Driving_Proposal_RCT Registration.docx</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Hoe Lee</name>
      <address>Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth
Western Australia
6845</address>
      <phone>+618 9266 4652</phone>
      <fax>+618 9266 3636</fax>
      <email>H.Lee@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Hoe Lee</name>
      <address>Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth
Western Australia
6845</address>
      <phone>+618 9266 4652</phone>
      <fax>+618 9266 3636</fax>
      <email>H.Lee@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Hoe Lee</name>
      <address>Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth
Western Australia
6845</address>
      <phone>+618 9266 4652</phone>
      <fax>+618 9266 3636</fax>
      <email>H.Lee@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Elinda Lee</name>
      <address>Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth
Western Australia
6845</address>
      <phone>+618 9266 1790</phone>
      <fax>+618 9266 3636</fax>
      <email>elinda.lee@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>