<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372920">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/05/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000712303</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluating the impact of the Students As LifeStyle Activists (SALSA) project on dietary and physical activity of high school students</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pre-post evaluation of the Students As LifeStyle Activists (SALSA) project on dietary and physical activity behaviours of high school students in western Sydney</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>SALSA project</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Non-communicable disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The SALSA program is a peer-led educational intervention to motivate high school students to make healthier lifestyle choices. The broad aims of the SALSA program are to promote healthy eating patterns and regular physical activity in an engaging, fun and supportive school environment. The SALSA program is incorporated into each schools Personal Development, Health and Physical Education (PDHPE) curriculum to complement lessons taught by PDHPE teachers. The program specifically targets schools in western Sydney where the risk for overweight and obesity development is a major public health concern. 
The theoretical framework of the SALSA program is based on Banduras Social Cognitive Theory and empowerment education approach. The Social Cognitive Theory proposes a reciprocal determinism in the interaction between a person, a targeted behaviour and a particular social context. It emphasises that people learn not only from their own experiences but also by observing the actions of others. Accordingly adolescents are encouraged to (i) observe and imitate the positive behaviours of others; (ii) see positive behaviours modelled and practised; (iii) empower and increase their own capability and confidence to implement new skills; (iv) adopt positive attitudes about implementing new skills and; (v) use their new skills in a supportive environment. The intervention strategies are based on the empowerment education approach, wherein students gain knowledge through group sharing and understanding of the social influences that affect their lives, set their own priorities and decide on group action in order to change conditions or resolve issues. 
A variety of strategies including a video, games, role-playing and a quiz show are used in the program, with participation and fun central to all aspects of learning. The program materials and delivery of the four lessons by the SALSA Year 10 Peer Leaders to Year 8 students are standardised through the use of structured lessons using the Peer Leaders Manual and the Ryans Goal video (available at www.sydney.edu.au/medicine/public-health/salsa-triple-a/).

Implementation of the SALSA program in 2014-15
Initially, project staff train volunteer university students from health and education disciplines as SALSA Educators. The SALSA educator training is completed in a face-to-face, one-day (~8 hour) workshop. University students are required to attend one workshop and provide a Working With Children Check clearance before visiting the high schools. 
[96 university students were trained in four workshops, two in 2014 and two in 2015]
Next, the SALSA program is delivered to high schools as a three-step process involving university students, and high school students as both learners and educators. Delivery of the SALSA program is designed to be flexible and work within the school timetable. Each participating school appoints a teacher (SALSA coordinator) to coordinate the following intervention components in conjunction with SALSA program staff. 
Three step process:
Step 1: Trained SALSA Educators (university students) coach volunteer or teacher selected Year 10 students as SALSA Peer Leaders for the program, during a one-day workshop. The Peer Leaders learn about nutrition and physical activity and acquire skills in group facilitation, teaching and leadership.
[32 peer leader workshops were held, with 96 university students training 869 Year 10 SALSA peer leaders across 23 high schools]
Step 2: The school SALSA coordinator allocates trained peer leaders to deliver the SALSA lessons in groups. We recommended a minimum of four students per group. Each group of peer leaders delivers the 4 x 70 minute lessons to Year 8 students using the Peer Leaders Manual as a guide. Lesson delivery is usually completed in less than 4 weeks. Students learn about nutrition, physical activity and healthy lifestyle behaviours through videos, games and activities. The Year 8 PDHPE teacher provides general supervision and only assisted with behaviour management as needed. Schools 
[869 SALSA peer leaders educated over 3,800 Year 8 students in 23 high schools]
Step 3: Wider dissemination of healthy lifestyle information occurs when students from the Year 8 classes develop a personal goal and a school-action plan in the final SALSA lesson. We expect that students implement the personal goals set as part of the SALSA program, leading to health-related behaviour change, and share their experience in the program with their friends and family. The school action plan is developed during the final SALSA lesson for students to lead in improving their school environment e.g. organise sports, start breakfast clubs, change food availability in canteens. The implementation of these action plans was not recorded in this study.  

Study design 
The present study adopted a pre-post evaluation design. At each school, all Year 8 classes and a select group of Year 10 students (to be trained as SALSA peer leaders) completed a 10-minute online evaluation questionnaire. 

A range of process data was collected throughout the project to monitor implementation fidelity and the acceptability of the SALSA program to the target populations. 
*Training workshops: At the conclusion of the training workshops, all university SALSA Educators and Year 10 Peer Leaders completed a paper-based feedback questionnaire regarding their training experience. 
*Year 10 peer leader debriefing session: A second paper-based questionnaire was completed by Year 10 Peer Leaders to obtain further feedback after the four SALSA lessons had been delivered. A debrief discussion was also facilitated post-workshop and responses were scribed and recorded for analysis.
*Year 8 teachers: School PDHPE teachers were asked to complete lesson logs to monitor the SALSA program implementation in 2014 and 2015. For each of the four SALSA lessons, the date of completion, number of Peer Leaders and number of Year 8 students were recorded by the teachers, and returned to SALSA staff at the completion of the program. 
*Principals and School SALSA coordinators: The Project Leader and Project Officer conducted additional informal interviews with the teachers who coordinated the SALSA programs and school principals to get their feedback on the program. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome variable of the 2014/15 SALSA program survey is the within subject change in frequency (days per week) of Year 8 students eating breakfast from pre to post SALSA intervention. Reported through an online questionnaire designed specifically for this study, based on a validated item.  

Bruening M, Eisenberg M, MacLehose R, Nanney MS, Story M, Neumark-Sztainer D. Relationship between adolescents' and their friends' eating behaviors: breakfast, fruit, vegetable, whole-grain, and dairy intake. J Acad Nutr Diet. 2012
Oct;112(10):1608-13.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three time points were identified for data collection:
pre-intervention i.e. before participation;
post-intervention (within 2 weeks after completion of the program) and;
follow-up (Term 4, approximately three-five months after program completion ).  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Usual intake of fruit (serves per day) reported through an online questionnaire designed specifically for this study, based on a validated item.  

Niven P, Scully M, Morley B, Crawford D, Baur LA, Wakefield M; NaSSDA Study Team. Socio-economic disparities in Australian adolescents' eating behaviours. Public Health Nutr. 2014 Dec;17(12):2753-8.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three time points.
pre-intervention i.e. before participation;
post-intervention (within 2 weeks after completion of the program) and;
follow-up (Term 4, approximately three-five months after program completion ).  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Usual intake of vegetables (serves per day) reported through an online questionnaire designed specifically for this study, based on a validated item.  

Niven P, Scully M, Morley B, Crawford D, Baur LA, Wakefield M; NaSSDA Study Team. Socio-economic disparities in Australian adolescents' eating behaviours. Public Health Nutr. 2014 Dec;17(12):2753-8.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three time points.
pre-intervention i.e. before participation;
post-intervention (within 2 weeks after completion of the program) and;
follow-up (Term 4, approximately three-five months after program completion ).  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Usual daily consumption of sugar sweetened beverages (e.g. soft drinks, fruit juice, cordials, sports drinks and energy drinks). Reported through an online questionnaire designed specifically for this study, based on a validated item.  

Niven P, Scully M, Morley B, Crawford D, Baur LA, Wakefield M; NaSSDA Study Team. Socio-economic disparities in Australian adolescents' eating behaviours. Public Health Nutr. 2014 Dec;17(12):2753-8.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three time points.
pre-intervention i.e. before participation;
post-intervention (within 2 weeks after completion of the program) and;
follow-up (Term 4, approximately three-five months after program completion).  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Frequency of being sufficiently physically active (i.e. 60  minutes or more daily). Reported through an online questionnaire designed specifically for this study, based on a validated item.  

Scott JJ, Morgan PJ, Plotnikoff RC, Lubans DR. Reliability and validity of a
single-item physical activity measure for adolescents. J Paediatr Child Health.
2015 Aug;51(8):787-93.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three time points.
pre-intervention i.e. before participation;
post-intervention (within 2 weeks after completion of the program) and;
follow-up (Term 4, approximately three-five months after program completion).  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Usual daily recreational screen use reported through an online questionnaire designed specifically for this study, based on a validated item.  

Lubans DR, Lonsdale C, Plotnikoff RC, Smith J, Dally K, Morgan PJ. Development
and evaluation of the Motivation to Limit Screen-time Questionnaire (MLSQ) for adolescents. Prev Med. 2013 Nov;57(5):561-6.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three time points.
pre-intervention i.e. before participation;
post-intervention (within 2 weeks after completion of the program) and;
follow-up (Term 4, approximately three-five months after program completion).  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intentions to eat breakfast every day over the next month reported through an online questionnaire designed specifically for this study, based on a validated item. 

Dewar DL, Lubans DR, Plotnikoff RC, Morgan PJ. Development and evaluation of social cognitive measures related to adolescent dietary behaviors. Int J Behav Nutr Phys Act. 2012 Apr 2;9:36.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three time points.
pre-intervention i.e. before participation;
post-intervention (within 2 weeks after completion of the program) and;
follow-up (Term 4, approximately three-five months after program completion).  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intentions to eat fruit over the next month reported through an online questionnaire designed specifically for this study, based on a validated item. 

Dewar DL, Lubans DR, Plotnikoff RC, Morgan PJ. Development and evaluation of social cognitive measures related to adolescent dietary behaviors. Int J Behav Nutr Phys Act. 2012 Apr 2;9:36.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three time points.
pre-intervention i.e. before participation;
post-intervention (within 2 weeks after completion of the program) and;
follow-up (Term 4, approximately three-five months after program completion).  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intentions to eat vegetables over the next month reported through an online questionnaire designed specifically for this study, based on a validated item. 

Dewar DL, Lubans DR, Plotnikoff RC, Morgan PJ. Development and evaluation of social cognitive measures related to adolescent dietary behaviors. Int J Behav Nutr Phys Act. 2012 Apr 2;9:36.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three time points.
pre-intervention i.e. before participation;
post-intervention (within 2 weeks after completion of the program) and;
follow-up (Term 4, approximately three-five months after program completion).  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intentions to be physically active on all or most days of the week reported through an online questionnaire designed specifically for this study, based on a validated item.

Dewar DL, Lubans DR, Plotnikoff RC, Morgan PJ. Development and evaluation of social cognitive measures related to adolescent dietary behaviors. Int J Behav Nutr Phys Act. 2012; 9:36.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three time points.
pre-intervention i.e. before participation;
post-intervention (within 2 weeks after completion of the program) and;
follow-up (Term 4, approximately three-five months after program completion).  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intentions to spend less free time sitting and doing activities involving screens (e.g. mobile phone, tablet, computer, gaming console, TV). Reported through an online questionnaire designed specifically for this study, based social cognitive theory, as in other secondary outcome measures. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three time points.
pre-intervention i.e. before participation;
post-intervention (within 2 weeks after completion of the program) and;
follow-up (Term 4, approximately three-five months after program completion).  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acceptability:
*Training workshops: At the conclusion of the training workshops, all university SALSA Educators and Year 10 Peer Leaders completed a paper-based feedback questionnaire regarding their training experience. 
*Year 10 peer leader debriefing session: An additional paper-based questionnaire was completed by Year 10 Peer Leaders to obtain further feedback after the four SALSA lessons had been delivered. A debrief discussion was also facilitated post-workshop and responses were scribed and recorded for analysis.
*Year 8 teachers: School PDHPE teachers were asked to complete lesson logs to monitor the SALSA program implementation in 2014 and 2015. For each of the four SALSA lessons, the date of completion, number of Peer Leaders and number of Year 8 students were recorded by the teachers, and returned to SALSA staff at the completion of the program. 
*Principals and School SALSA coordinators: The Project Leader and Project Officer conducted additional informal interviews with the teachers who coordinated the SALSA programs and school principals to get their feedback on the program. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>*University student training workshop feedback was collected on the same day as the workshop, after all activities had been completed. 
*Year 8 teachers completed lesson logs on the same day as program delivery in their classroom. 
*Peer leader debriefing post-intervention, within 2 weeks after completion of the program. 
*Additional informal interviews with the teachers who coordinated the SALSA programs and school principals to get their feedback on the program were completed at post-intervention, within 2 weeks after completion of the program. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fidelity
*Training workshops: At the conclusion of the training workshops, all university SALSA Educators and Year 10 Peer Leaders completed a paper-based feedback questionnaire regarding their training experience. 
*Year 10 peer leader debriefing session: An additional paper-based questionnaire was completed by Year 10 Peer Leaders to obtain further feedback after the four SALSA lessons had been delivered. A debrief discussion was also facilitated post-workshop and responses were scribed and recorded for analysis.
*Year 8 teachers: School PDHPE teachers were asked to complete lesson logs to monitor the SALSA program implementation in 2014 and 2015. For each of the four SALSA lessons, the date of completion, number of Peer Leaders and number of Year 8 students were recorded by the teachers, and returned to SALSA staff at the completion of the program. 
*Principals and School SALSA coordinators: The Project Leader and Project Officer conducted additional informal interviews with the teachers who coordinated the SALSA programs and school principals to get their feedback on the program. </outcome>
      <timepoint>*University student training workshop feedback was collected on the same day as the workshop, after all activities had been completed. 
*Year 8 teachers completed lesson logs on the same day as program delivery in their classroom. 
*Peer leader debriefing post-intervention, within 2 weeks after completion of the program. 
*Additional informal interviews with the teachers who coordinated the SALSA programs and school principals to get their feedback on the program were completed at post-intervention, within 2 weeks after completion of the program. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All participants will be school aged children attending secondary schools (Government, Catholic and independent) in Western Sydney, New South Wales, Australia, who have accepted the SALSA program as part of the school PDHPE curriculum.
Participants will include:
*Year 8 male and female students (aged 13-14 years)
*Year 10 Peer Leaders, male and female (aged 15-16 years).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>13</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>16</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Schools dedicated to educating students with special needs </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/05/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>3/06/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>1428</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>2056</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>30/09/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Western Sydney Local Health District</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 533, Westmead NSW 2145, Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Government Department of Health, Chronic Disease Prevention and Service Improvement Fund, </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Health
GPO Box 9848,
Canberra ACT 2601, Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Sydney Medical School, The University of Sydney</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>PO Box 533, Westmead NSW 2145, Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The SALSA (Students As LifeStyle Activists) program is a school-based, peer-led initiative to improve nutritional intake and increase physical activity amongst high school students. Since 2004, the SALSA program has been provided to high schools in Western Sydney with the support of various organisations including Rooty Hill High School, Mt Druitt and Blacktown Medical Practitioners Associations, Primary Health Care Education and Research Unit, the University of Sydney and Western Sydney Medicare Local. The Commonwealth Department of Health has provided funding to support the implementation and evaluation of the SALSA program in high schools in 2014/15.
The SALSA program is incorporated into each schools curriculum to complement lessons taught by teachers. The program is simply described in this brief video: https://youtu.be/jiudp1few9Q
This research aims to determine the extent in which the SALSA program influences positive changes in key dietary and physical activity behaviours, and intentions regarding these behvaiours, associated with a healthy lifestyle in Year 8 participants and Year 10 peer leaders. Key outcomes were:
* Frequency of breakfast intake, and intention to eat breakfast daily.
* Usual daily intake of fruit; and intention to eat more fruit. 
* Usual daily intake of vegetables; and intention to eat more vegetables. 
* Usual daily consumption of fruit juice and other sugary drinks (e.g. soft drinks, cordials, sports drinks and energy drinks).
* Frequency of being sufficiently physically active (i.e. 60 minutes or more daily); and intention to be physically active more often. 
* Usual daily recreational screen use; and intention to devote less recreational time to screen activities. 
We hypothesised that the SALSA program would influence positive changes in the frequency of breakfast eating and other health related behaviours in Year 8 students and Year 10 Peer Leaders.
In Year 8 students and Year 10 peer leaders, behaviours and behavioural intentions were measured before the SALSA program, 2 weeks after completing the program, and 3-5 months after completing the program. Ethical approval was granted in 2014 from the University of Sydney and the Department of Education (the University of Sydney no: 2014/203; SERAP no: 2014096). In late 2014, we also received approval from the Catholic Education Office to approach and recruit Catholic Schools in western Sydney to participate in the SALSA program evaluation. All high schools that implemented the SALSA program agreed to participate in the evaluation. As partners, they were responsible for distributing a letter to parents/caregivers of Peer Leaders and Year 8 students informing them of the schools and their childs invitation to participate in SALSA program. If parents did not wish for their child to participate in the program evaluation, a tear off slip was to be signed and returned to the school. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://sydney.edu.au/medicine/public-health/salsa-triple-a/salsa/</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Ethical approval was granted in 2014 from the University of Sydney and the Department of Education (the University of Sydney no: 2014/203; SERAP no: 2014096). In late 2014, we also received approval from the Catholic Education Office to approach and recruit Catholic Schools in western Sydney to participate in the SALSA program evaluation.
All high schools that implemented the SALSA program agreed to participate in the evaluation. As partners, they were responsible for distributing a letter to parents/caregivers of Peer Leaders and Year 8 students informing them of the schools and their childs invitation to participate in SALSA program. If parents did not wish for their child to participate in the program evaluation, a tear off slip was to be signed and returned to the school. 
</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 6, Jane Foss Russell
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006 Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/04/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2014/203</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/03/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>State Education Reserach Application Process</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>School Policy and Information Management (SERAP)
NSW Department of Education
Locked Bag 53
Darlinghurst NSW 1300</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/05/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2014096</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/04/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Catholic Education Office</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>12 Victoria Road
Parramatta NSW 2150</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/12/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/11/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372920-Catholic ethics approval letter.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372920-SERAP 2014096 Approval.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372920-Ethics final outcome 24.4.14.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372920-ANZCTRSample size statement.docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372920-Shrewsbury et al  supplementary file 1 10 16.docx</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Smita Shah</name>
      <address>Primary Health Care Education and Research Unit
Research and Education Network, Western Sydney Local Health District
PO Box 533, Westmead, NSW, 2145 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 2 98456505</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>smita.shah@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Smita Shah</name>
      <address>Primary Health Care Education and Research Unit
Research and Education Network, Western Sydney Local Health District
PO Box 533, Westmead, NSW, 2145 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 2 98456505</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>smita.shah@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Smita Shah</name>
      <address>Primary Health Care Education and Research Unit
Research and Education Network, Western Sydney Local Health District
PO Box 533, Westmead, NSW, 2145 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 2 98456505</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>smita.shah@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>