<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373442">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/08/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/08/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001188325</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Healthcare Pathways for Children with Chronic Conditions</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled study to evaluate an the effect of an integrated care pathway on quality of life for children with chronic disease  connecting the dots in healthcare provision</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Developmental chronic condition</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human Genetics and Inherited Disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other human genetics and inherited disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Autistic spectrum disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Learning disabilities</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Children in the intervention group (e.g. integrated care pathway) will have access to an allied health liaison officer (AHLO). The AHLO qualification will be from an allied health background (e.g. speech pathologist, social worker, dietician, physiotherapist, psychologist, music therapist, occupational therapist). The AHLO will facilitate care coordination across hospital, primary, community and educational settings at 1 week, 3 months, 6 months and
12 months post diagnosis via a combination of face-to-face sessions and telephone consults, as clinically required by the family. The duration of face-to-face and telephone consults will range between 10 minutes (if caregiver reports no concerns) to a maximum of 60 minutes (if caregiver has concerns/needs requiring attention). For children &lt;8 years, face-to-face and telephone sessions will occur with the caregiver only. For children &gt;8 years, face-to-face and telephone sessions will occur with both the caregiver and child present. 

Frequency: caregivers will be asked to fill in questionnaires either in face to face or via phone (depending on caregiver preferences) at 1 week, 3 months, 6 months and 12 months after their appointment with the Paediatrician. Please note that care coordination tasks will be completed and/or new care coordination tasks identified at the above timepoints.  Duration: It is anticipated that the questionnaires will take about 1 hour or so to complete. Appointments with General Practitioners, schools, service providers may also be arranged for children in the integrated care pathway group to help manage their chronic condition. The frequency of contact with other professionals will be dependent on the individual needs of the child and caregiver. 

Location: The AHLO will complete contact with the child and caregiver at various locations throughout the care pathway, pending the support requirements of each individual participant. This can include phone calls or face to face appointments at GP clinics and/or in school settings with other professionals. 

The AHLO will go through the following checklist to ensure appropriate care coordination. Please note, liaison with other professionals and agencies will occur, as appropriate throughout the duration of the study. Each process used and outcome will be documented to guide process evaluation for the AHLO role. Examples of care coordination tasks include:
 Completion of forms  literacy assistance
 Identification and acceptance to community agencies. Where there is a delay in acceptance, the AHLO will contact the relevant agency to determine what additional information is required and help facilitate the process (e.g. agency may be awaiting documentation from caregiver or letter from hospital provider)
o Disability Services Queensland (DSQ), Child Development Services (CDS), Autism Queensland, Cerebral Palsy League of Queensland (CPLQ), Special Education Unit (SEU)
 Check progress of financial assistance with Centrelink or similar agency
o Carers Allowance
 Organising school supports by providing hospital reports; connecting professionals from community agencies to the child's school case worker to develop an individualised education plan.
 Navigation on use of eligible initiatives (Better Start, Chronic Disease Management Plan, Mental Health Care Plan, ATSI Plan)
Organising multidisciplinary team meetings for the child and caregiver at school or with the treating GP. This can involve other professionals currently providing educational and/or healthcare support for the child.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group (no treatment/access to AHLO): self-directed care pathway involves the caregiver being the primary advocate and liaison for their child post medical review with the Paediatrician. This means that they will coordinate and organise all of their child's appointments with other professionals in the school, primary care and community sectors. No additional support will be provided to the child and caregiver to coordinate their care pathway after their medical review with the Paediatrician. 

The caregivers will be asked to fill in questionnaires either in person or via phone at 1 week, 3 months, 6 months and 12 months after their appointment with the Paediatrician. The questionnaires will take about 1 hour or so to complete. 

</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pediatric Quality of Life (PedQOL) Child - Score 0 to 100. (Parent or child completed)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week, 6 months, 12 months post (endpoint) medical review with Paediatrician</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PedQOL Family Impact - Score 0 to 100. (Parent completed)</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week, 6 months and 12 months (endpoint) post medical review with Paediatrician</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subjective Units of Distress Scale (SUDS) - Score 0 to 100. (Parent completed)</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week, 6 months and 12 months post (end point)  medical review with Paediatrician</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome measure: Child Behaviour Checklist (CBCL)  Percentiles. (Parent completed). </outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months, 6 months and 12 months post (end point) medical review with Paediatrician</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome measure: Rotters Locus of Control Scale - Score 0 to 23 (Parent completed)</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week, 6 months and 12 months post (end point) medical review with Paediatrician</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of GP visits, accessed via Medicare data</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week, 3 months and 6 months post medical review with Paediatrician</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of hospital admissions, accessed via Medicare data</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week, 3 months and 6 months post medical review with Paediatrician</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of specialist appointments, accessed via Medicare data</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week, 3 months and 6 months post medical review with Paediatrician</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of absent school days, accessed by Education Queensland Central Office records</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week, 3 months and 6 months post medical review with Paediatrician</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of caregiver missed employment days based on parental report</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week, 3 months and 6 months post medical review with Paediatrician</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of school suspensions, measured in days; accessed by Education Queensland Central Office records</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week, 3 months and 6 months post medical review with Paediatrician</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of services accessed at the time, based on parental report</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week, 3 months and 6 months post medical review with Paediatrician</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Children 0 to 16 years seen by Paediatrician at Caboolture Hospital or Gold Coast University Hospital and newly diagnosed with a developmental chronic condition where community based health or family support services are part of the management plan. Chronic conditions are expected to last more than 6 months and to produce consequences that impact on the childs quality of life.

Examples of developmental chronic conditions include (but are not limited to): Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD), Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD), Intellectual Impairment (II), Specific Language Impairment (SLI), Oppositional Defiance Disorder (ODD), Fetal Alcohol Spectrum Disorder (FASD), Cerebral Palsy (CP).
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>16</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>	Children with acute medical conditions requiring urgent intervention where community follow-up is deemed inappropriate by the treating Paediatrician.
	Children with a chronic medical condition primarily managed by medical consultation alone and those conditions where hospital based multidisciplinary teams provide coordinated care.
	Examples of excluded chronic conditions include: cancer, cystic fibrosis, asthma, epilepsy.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>We plan for a total sample size of 112 children (80 % power to detect a mean effect difference of 15 between groups on the quality of life scale) at 0.05 significance level. This sample size has been adjusted for an anticipated high attrition rate of 50%. A 2-sample test of proportions will be used to compare baseline characteristics of both groups.

All analyses will be conducted using an intention to treat (ITT) analysis where all subjects will be compared in the groups which they were originally assigned (regardless of withdrawal or lost to follow-up). For our primary objective, Mann Whitney U test will be used to determine if differences in quality of life measures exist between the ICCC versus self-directed care groups. 

For our secondary objective, we will perform univariable analysis to determine which health economic parameters (e.g. missed school days, number of hospital admissions) are related to higher quality of life scores. Stepwise regression will then examine the various combinations via of health economic parameters to generate aROC curves to determine a clinical prediction index for higher quality of life scores. Parameters chosen will be based on using factors that were significant plus those with P &lt; .25 level in the univariable analysis and other variables known to have a strong association with poorer health outcomes (e.g. multiple co-morbidities) within the literature. An aROC of =0.75 will be considered a clinically relevant cut-off score.

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/09/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>112</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Caboolture Hospital - Caboolture</hospital>
    <hospital>Gold Coast University Hospital - Southport</hospital>
    <postcode>4510 - Caboolture</postcode>
    <postcode>4215 - Southport</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Thuy Frakking</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Research Development Unit
Caboolture Hospital
McKean St, 
Caboolture, 
QLD, 4510.  </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Allied Health Professions Of Queensland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Allied Health Professions' Office of Queensland
PO Box 2368, Fortitude Valley BC, 
QLD 4006.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Background: Children with chronic health conditions have better health-related outcomes when their care is managed in a personalised and coordinated way. However, increased demand on Australian ambulatory care hospital services has led to longer waitlist times to access specialists and appropriate intervention services; placing vulnerable children at increased risk of poorer short-term (e.g. social difficulties) and long-term (e.g. convictions) health and social outcomes. Traditional approaches to increasing frequency and service of delivery are expensive and can have minimal impact on caregiver burden. A community based service-integration approach, rather than self-directed care is proposed as a better health systems approach, as increased service linkages are more likely to occur thus and improving the health outcomes of children with a chronic health condition resulting in health economic benefits . 

Aim:To determine the effectiveness of an integrated care pathway led by an allied health liaison officer in the management of chronic disease in children.


Methods: An open, unblinded, multi-centre randomised controlled trial in two Australian public hospitals. 112 children (0-16 years) fulfilling the inclusion criteria will be randomised to one of two clinical pathways for management of their chronic health condition: (1) integrated childrens care clinic (ICCC) or (2) self-directed care pathway. All children and caregivers will be interviewed at 1 week, 3, 6 and 12 months time intervals. Primary outcome measures include the Pediatric Quality of Life (PedQOL) questionnaire, subjective units of distress scale, child behaviour checklist (CBCL) and Rotters locus of control scale. Secondary outcome measures include the total number of medical appointments, school days missed and quantity of services accessed. Our main objectives are to determine if the ICCC results in better health and economics outcomes compared to the self-directed care pathway. 

Hypotheses:
 a)	Children who access the ICCC will have improved quality of life (child and family impact) scores than children who access the self-directed care pathway.
b)	The ICCC pathway is more cost-effective than a self-directed care pathway.

Discussion: The success of a health systems approach needs to be balanced against clinical, mortality and cost-effectiveness data for long-term sustainability within a publicly funded health system. A clinical pathway that is sustainable, cost-effective, provides efficient evidence-based care and improves the quality of life outcomes for children with chronic health conditions has the potential to reduce waitlist times to access health services, increase consumer satisfaction; and prevent costs associated with poorly managed chronic health conditions</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Children's Health Queensland Hospital and Health Service Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 7, Centre for Children's Health Research
Lady Cilento Children's Hospital Precinct 
62 Graham Street, South Brisbane
QLD 4101.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/08/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/17/QRCH/159</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/07/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373442-HREC approval letter.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Thuy Frakking</name>
      <address>Research Development Unit
Executive Building 3
Caboolture Hospital
McKean St,
Caboolture, QLD, 4510.</address>
      <phone>+61753165972</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>thuy.frakking@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Thuy Frakking</name>
      <address>Research Development Unit
Executive Building 3
Caboolture Hospital
McKean St
Caboolture, QLD, 4510.</address>
      <phone>+61753165972</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>thuy.frakking@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Thuy Frakking</name>
      <address>Research Development Unit
Executive Building 3
McKean St
Caboolture Hospital
Caboolture, QLD, 4510.</address>
      <phone>+61753165972</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>thuy.frakking@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Thuy Frakking</name>
      <address>Research Development Unit
Executive Building 3
Caboolture Hospital
Caboolture, QLD, 4510.</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>