<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373443">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/08/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/08/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001183370p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A tailored fall prevention program for people with Parkinson's disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A tailored and multifactorial fall prevention program for people with Parkinson's disease: a single group feasibility and acceptability study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Parkinson's disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>falls</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Parkinson's disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention will be a multifactorial fall prevention program (i.e. multiple interventions tailored to the individual and targeting their specific fall risk factors) which will run for 4-6  months (depending on the participant's needs). The intervention will  consist of environmental modification, behavioural modification and exercise, which will be delivered to participants in their homes by occupational therapists and physiotherapists. Participants will receive 6 to 12 therapy home visits depending on their need. The ratio of physiotherapy and occupational therapy home visits will depend on each participants physical abilities, functional cognition, ability to engage with the different components of the intervention, identified goals and issues of safety. All participants will receive weekly phone calls between visits to monitor progress and address any intervention related problems which arise.

The environmental and behavioural components of the program will be delivered as a home and community safety package. Strategies will be discussed with the participant (and any care-partner), and implemented through the use of diaries and goal setting. Environmental adaptations to reduce fall risk will be introduced (eg, removal of clutter, improving lighting) and participants who display unsafe patterns of movement will be taught how to use cues and strategies to initiate and maintain safe movement. Participants with be provided with a home safety booklet which will be adapted to their cognitive abilities and will outline recommendations. Situational cues will be used as prompts to reinforce behaviour. Adherence to the environmental and behavioural components of the program will be monitored by the occupational therapist through discussions with the participant and any care-partner and the use of participant diaries.

The home-based exercise component of the program will be individually prescribed and delivered and will include commonly used exercises for fall prevention (www.webb.org.au) These exercises address known remediable risk factors for falls in people with PD (i.e. leg muscle weakness, poor balance and freezing of gait). Exercises will be performed in 30 minute sessions, up to 6 times per week. In order to maximise efficacy and minimise adverse events, programs will be individually prescribed and progressed according to the participants physical and cognitive abilities. Participants will be shown how to exercise with a stable support nearby if necessary. Exercises will also be taught to any care-partner who will provide supervision and assistance (including appropriate cueing) as required. Participants and any care partner will be provided with an exercise booklet which will include clear pictorial and simple written instructions, as well as a log book in which they will record completed exercise.</interventions>
    <comparator>None</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility of the intervention, evaluated through:
recruitment rates
retention rates
adherence to the program and 
adverse events associated with the program.</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acceptability of the intervention and assessment process, determined from open-ended interview data </outcome>
      <timepoint>End of study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Falls rates collected using a falls calendar</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monthly throughout the study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of fall related-injuries collected using the falls calendar</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monthly throughout the study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of fallers collected using falls calendars</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monthly throughout the study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceptions of fall risk and response to these perceptions, collected via a semi-structured interview</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to commencing the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fall prevention behaviours collected with the Falls Behavioural Scale for the Older Person questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fear of falling using the Iconographical Falls Efficacy Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Freezing of gait using the New Freezing of Gait Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Balance using the miniBESTest</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fall risk using the Physiological Profile Assessment (includes measures of visual contrast sensitivity, proprioception, quadriceps strength, hand reaction time and postural sway while standing on a rubber mat with eyes open).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Walking speed (measured over 4m)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognition measured with the Montreal Cognitive Assessment</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety and Depression (measured with the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity measured with the Incidental and Planned Exercise Questionnaire for older people</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health-related quality of life measured with the Parkinson's disease Questionnaire-39 (PDQ-39)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain measured with the King's Parkinson's Disease Pain Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Care-partner burden measured with the Zarit Burden Interview questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain measured with the Brief Pain Inventory</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>At least 1 fall in the prior 6 months
No change to Parkinson's disease medications in the 2 weeks prior to commencing the study
Able to walk at least 10 m with or without a walking aid
Participants with significant cognitive impairment (Montreal Cognitive Assessment &lt;19 or, a level of functional cognition that the researchers deem requires assistance to participate) will require an able care-partner who is willing to participate with them to assist them with the intervention.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Medical conditions which would preclude or interfere with study safety and conduct.
Severe cognitive impairment (Montreal Cognitive Assessment &lt;5)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Mixed methods study with a multifactorial fall prevention intervention and semi-structured interviews</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Twenty participants with idiopathic PD (and where appropriate, their care-partners) will be recruited. Twenty participants will be sufficient to determine the feasibility and acceptability of this protocol, and to inform the future design of a randomised trial.

Feasibility and secondary outcomes will be explored using descriptive statistics. Any changes in secondary outcome measures between baseline and post-test will be explored with paired samples t-tests. The qualitative data analysis will be explored through analysis of the interview data.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>18/09/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Sydney
NSW 2006
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Sydney, Ageing in Place Seed Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The University of Sydney
NSW 2006
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Despite advances in management, falls continue to be a major problem for people with Parkinsons disease (PD). Most falls prevention research excludes people with PD with cognitive impairment; however these are the people most at risk of falls. The objective of this study is to determine the feasibility and acceptability of a multifactorial fall prevention program and assessment for people with PD, including people with impaired cognition and freezing of gait. 

A mixed methods study with a single group trial of a 4 to 6 month multifactorial home-based fall prevention intervention will be conducted. The intervention will consist of behavioural modification, environmental modification and exercise. The intervention will be delivered by physiotherapists and occupational therapists. 

Semi-structured interviews will be conducted with participants before and after the intervention. Before the intervention the interview will explore participants perceptions of risk and their response to this perceived risk, and after the intervention questions will explore intervention acceptability.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The University of Sydney
NSW 2006
Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/07/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Natalie Allen</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences
The University of Sydney
PO Box 170
Lidcombe, NSW, 1825</address>
      <phone>+61293519016</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>natalie.allen@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Natalie Allen</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences
The University of Sydney
PO Box 170
Lidcombe, NSW, 1825</address>
      <phone>+61293519016</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>natalie.allen@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Natalie Allen</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences
The University of Sydney
PO Box 170
Lidcombe, NSW, 1825</address>
      <phone>+61293519016</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>natalie.allen@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Natalie Allen</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences
The University of Sydney
PO Box 170
Lidcombe, NSW, 1825</address>
      <phone>+61293519016</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>natalie.allen@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>