<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370401">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/03/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/04/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000431426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of the link between blood glucose levels and neurocardiogenic syncope in adults who experience fainting episodes.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of the link between blood glucose levels and neurocardiogenic syncope in adults undergoing tilt table testing for syncopal events.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>None</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Neurocardiogenic syncope</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Hypoglycemia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The normal procedure for a heads-up tilt test  is were the test is divided into two sections, Before the test commences the patient's blood pressure and heart rate are assessed.  A small needle (like a blood test) will be placed in the arm (IV cannula) which medication will be given in the second part of the test.

The patient  lies  flat on the tilt bed that has a footplate at the end to stand on when the bed has been tilted so that they are standing upright. Small straps are placed around the body, like seat belts that stabilize the patient in case they become dizzy or faint.

After 10 minutes in this  in the upright standing position, or sooner if they become dizzy or feel faint, the bed will be returned to the normal position so that they are lying flat.
The heart rate and blood pressure will be taken frequently.

If no blackouts or dizziness occurs, then the second part of the test begins.

The tilt test is repeated with the addition of a medication (Isoprenaline) given via the small needle  (IV cannula) in the arm The Isoprenaline stimulates the heart rate (making the heart beat stronger and faster), it makes you feel like you have gone for a brisk walk or run, similar to how you feel when you exercise.

Similar to the first part of the tilt table test the second part of the test continues for 10 minutes or until the patient becomes dizzy or feels faint.

As part of this project we will be checking the patient's venous blood glucose level at the following time points:
-Before the test begins (Baseline)
-After the first part of the tilt (after 10minutes)
-2 minutes after the Isoprenaline infusion part of the test has commenced
-After the end of the Isoprenaline  phase of the test (End of test)

The only change from a standard tilt table test is the blood sample collection and testing for blood glucose levels. 



</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The evaluate the change in circulating blood glucose levels in response to syncope.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Ee will be checking the patient's venous blood glucose level at the following time points:
-Before the test begins (Baseline)
-After the first part of the tilt (after 10minutes)
-2 minutes after the Isoprenaline infusion part of the test has commenced
-After the end of the Isoprenaline  phase of the test (End of test)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To analyse the blood glucose levels of participants in Tilt Table Testing who have a positive result on the test (ie hypotension) and compare the blood glucose levels to those who have a negative result, to see if any change in blood glucose levels can be related to the occurrence of hypotension itself rather than other aspects of the test. </outcome>
      <timepoint>We will be checking the patient's venous blood glucose level at the following time points:
-Before the test begins (Baseline)
-After the first part of the tilt (after 10minutes)
-2 minutes after the Isoprenaline infusion part of the test has commenced
-After the end of the Isoprenaline  phase of the test (End of test)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Referred for Tilt Table Testing for syncopal events.  
Participants will be over 18 years of age
Willing and able to sign an informed consent form</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Those who  are diabetic, 
Those that are taking medication that interferes with blood glucose levels.  </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>The serial blood glucose measurements from the syncopal patients will be compared to those in the control group using analysis of variance.  Clinically significant hypoglycemia will be defined as a blood sugar &lt;3.0 and the proportion of patients with symptomatic hypoglycemia will be determined in both the symptomatic and control groups.  If a significant proportion of patients do show evidence of clinically significant hypoglycemia then an attempt will be made to correlate the occurrence of clinically significant hypoglycemia with gender and age.
In the past patient's frequently reported that they could stop syncopal events by taking sugar. From this observation we decided that 50 patients would be enough to show a difference in the glucose levels at different time points. No formal power calculation was performed.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>10/03/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>30/06/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>50</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Box Hill Hospital - Box Hill</hospital>
    <postcode>3128 - Box Hill</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Angas Hamer</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Box Hill Hospital
Cardiology Department
8 Arnold St
Box Hill, Vic, 3128</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cardiology Department - Box Hill Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Box Hill Hospital
Cardiology Department
8 Arnold St
Box Hill, Vic, 3128</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Given the hypothesis that reactive hypoglycemia may occur during hypotensive (neurocardiogenic) syncope we wish to study blood glucose levels in patients who may have a hypotensive syncopal event.  Establishing a link between reactive hypoglycemia and neurocardiogenic hypotensive syncope could be beneficial to these patients as it may lead to new strategies to help these patients manage their events.  

This study differs from previous studies by testing the blood glucose levels in a large number of patients referred for an investigation of neurocardiogenic before and during syncope induced by a Tilt Table Test, using referred patients who do not have syncope induced during the test as a control group.   

</summary>
    <trialwebsite>None</trialwebsite>
    <publication>None</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>This study is now completed, and awaiting publication</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Eastern Health Research and Ethics</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Eastern Health
5 Arnold St
Box Hill, Vic, 3128</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/06/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>E92/0809</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/04/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Angas Hamer</name>
      <address>Box Hill Hospital
Cardiology Department
Level 2, Building B
Nelson Rd
Box Hill, Vic 3128</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9895 4855</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9895 4834</fax>
      <email>aham8655@bigpond.net.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Louise Roberts</name>
      <address>Box Hill Hospital
Cardiology Research
Level 2, 5 Arnold St
Box Hill, Vic 3128</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9095 2441</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9895 4834</fax>
      <email>Louise.roberts@easternhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Louise Roberts</name>
      <address>Box Hill Hospital
Cardiology Research
Level 2, 5 Arnold St
Box Hill, Vic 3128</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9095 2441</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9895 4834</fax>
      <email>Louise.roberts@easternhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Louise Roberts</name>
      <address>Box Hill Hospital
Cardiology Research
Level 2, 5 Arnold St
Box Hill, VIC 3128</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9095 2441</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9895 4834</fax>
      <email>Louise.roberts@easternhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>