<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371576">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/09/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/10/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001405404</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparing gastrointestinal motility in clozapine-treated patients before and after laxative guided by the Porirua Protocol</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparing gastrointestinal motility in clozapine-treated patients before and after laxative treatment guided by the Porirua Protocol</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1188-1548 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>clozapine-induced gastrointestinal hypomotility</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Schizophrenia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The condition observed is colonic transit time (as measured by radiopaque marker studies using the Metcalf technique). The exposure is laxative treatment prescribed according to the Porirua Protocol (which is attached). At the first timepoint colonic transit time was measured in the absence of the Porirua Protocol. Participants were then established on the Porirua Protocol by their clinical teams (the Protocol is treatment as usual in the service where this study takes place. The study design was observational; treatment was guided by the Protocol and determined by the clinical teams and participants, treatment was not manipulated by the researchers). After at least two months of treatment on the Protocol, colonic transit time was measured again.</interventions>
    <comparator>This is a pre and post treatment design with each patient acting as their own control with comparisons made before and after treatment with the Porirua Protocol. The design was chosen due to ethical considerations: a placebo control group could not be justified in a cohort with high rates of clozapine-induced gastrointestinal hypomotility.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Colonic transit time as measured by radiopaque marker studies</outcome>
      <timepoint>From the time the first radiopaque marker is ingested until time=72 hours (if 2/3 or more of the ROMs are expelled at t=72) or time=144 hours (if  less than 2/3 of ROMs are excreted at t=72)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subjective symptoms of constipation as assessed by modified ROME III constipation criteria</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 72 hours after commencing study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported constipation</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 72 hours after commencing study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse effects using a clinician administered checklist which asks whether the participant has experienced bloating, cramping, diarrhoea, abdominal pain, nausea, increase thirst or other effect they believe to be related to the laxatives, and to describe each effect they may have experienced </outcome>
      <timepoint>at 72 and 144 hours after commencing study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Male and female adult patients (&gt;18) prescribed clozapine (any dose) for at least 3 months, who are able to provide informed consent, had previously consented to baseline bowel motility testing and who have then received laxatives prescribed in accordance with the Porirua Protocol for at least two months. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients under the age of 18, unable to provide informed consent or who do not understand English. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>The primary outcome variable is colonic transit time (CTT) as measured by radiopaque marker (ROM) transit studies, reported as both continuous (CTT in hours) and categorical outcome measures (normal or abnormal test). A CTT &gt;2SD above the population mean (i.e. &gt;64.9 hours) was pre-specified as a positive test for colonic hypomotility. A CTT &gt;4SD above the population mean (i.e. &gt;101 hours) was defined as severe colonic hypomotility.

Descriptive statistics (medians with IQR, and plotted distributions of transit times) provide data summaries for transit times. 

Kaplan-Meier survival analysis calculates median transit times (with 95% CI). 

Differences in CTT without  and with laxative treatment are compared using the Wilcoxon signed-rank test. The proportion of participants with gastrointestinal hypomotility and severe gastrointestinal hypomotility are compared between the two  timepoints using McNemars 2-sided exact test, which takes into account the paired nature of the observations.

While CTTs displayed a skewed distribution, we also calculated means and standard deviation for comparison with population normative values.

Differences between pre- and post-treatment groups were considered statistically significant when p&lt;0.05.

No similar studies had been conducted, making power calculations speculative. At alpha=0.05 and beta=0.8, a sample size of 20 (the target sample size) is adequately powered to detect a difference between two dependent means (pre and post treatment transit times) of &gt;10 hours (SD=15). It A priori it was possible this study may have been underpowered to detect a true difference, but was intended to inform any future studies. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>27/11/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>1/05/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>14</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>16/11/2015</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>14/09/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Wellington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Susanna Every-Palmer</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Psychological Medicine, University of Otago, Wellington
PO Box 7343
Wellington 6242</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Capital and Coast District Health Board Small Research Grant </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Capital and Coast District Health Board, Private Bag 7902, Wellington 6021</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Peter Ellis</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of Psychological Medicine, University of Otago, Wellington PO Box 7343 Wellington 6242 </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Mike Nowitz</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Medicine, University of Otago, Wellington, PO Box 7343, Wellington 6242</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>James Stanley</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Medicine, University of Otago, Wellington, PO Box 7343, Wellington 6242</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Eve Grant</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Te Korowai Whariki Central Regional Forensic Service, Capital and District Health Board, PO Box 50-233, Porirua</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Mark Huthwaite</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Psychological Medicine, University of Otago, Wellington, PO Box 7343, Wellington 6242</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Helen Dunn</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Pharmacy Department, Capital and Coast District Health Board, Private Bag 7902, Wellington 6021</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Clozapine, an antipsychotic used in treatment-resistant schizophrenia, causes marked gastrointestinal hypomotility in 50-80% of patients. Clozapine-induced gastrointestinal hypomotility is both common and serious; it can result in severe constipation, ileus, bowel obstruction and related complications. Little evidence exists on its prevention and management. Subjective constipation has been found unreliable in predicting objective hypomotility. 

In this study, using a standardized radiopaque marker (Metcalf) method we compare the colonic transit times of clozapine-treated inpatients at baseline (while not receiving laxatives) with transit times when receiving laxatives, with treatment prescribed according to the Porirua Protocol (see attachment) for clozapine-related constipation (docusate &amp; senna augmented by macrogol 3350 in treatment-resistant cases).  Treatment is guided by the Protocol (which is standard treatment at the clinical site this research took place in) and not manipulated by the researchers. 

Our objective was to determine in this naturalistic setting whether use of the Porirua Protocol in clozapine-treated psychiatric inpatients changed gastrointestinal motility. 

Methods were specified a-priori in the protocol, published in the University of Otago Research Archive (http://hdl.handle.net/10523/6392).
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Central Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health Freyberg Building 20 Aitken Street PO Box 5013 Wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/10/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>13/CEN/153</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371576-Figure 1- The Porirua Protocol.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Susanna Every-Palmer</name>
      <address>Department of Psychological Medicine, University of Otago, Wellington, PO Box 7343, Wellington 6242</address>
      <phone>+6421767675</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Susanna.every-palmer@ccdhb.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Susanna Every-Palmer</name>
      <address>Department of Psychological Medicine, University of Otago, Wellington, PO Box 7343, Wellington 6242</address>
      <phone>+6421767675</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Susanna.every-palmer@ccdhb.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Susanna Every-Palmer</name>
      <address>Department of Psychological Medicine, University of Otago, Wellington, PO Box 7343, Wellington 6242</address>
      <phone>+64 21767675</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Susanna.every-palmer@ccdhb.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>