<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373696">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/09/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/10/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001415392</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle> Ultrasound Therapy in Peyronies Disease: a non-invasive treatment.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle> Efficacy of Ultrasound Therapy in Peyronies Disease as a non-invasive treatment option.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Peyronies Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other renal and urogenital disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Application of therapeutic ultrasound  will be provided to men who have been diagnosed with Peyronies Disease. Twelve 10 min sessions of continuous ultrasound therapy at a dosage ranging from 1.5 w/cm2- 2.5w/cm2 depending on participants tolerance level , will be applied  to the area of fibrosis as identified on penile duplex doppler ultrasound scan (PDDU), using a 3MHz sound head. This will be conducted over a 4 week period will be administered by a physiotherapist. Three sessions/week over 4 weeks is the plan for administering ultrasound . Adherence to the intervention will be ensured as each ultrasound session will be delivered to the participant by a physiotherapist</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group has a delayed entry of 4 weeks to receiving diagnostic ultrasound with pre and post PDDU scans, then subsequent 12 sessions of therapeutic ultrasound and repeat PDDU.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>.Therapeutic ultrasound may assist in the resolution of Peyronies Disease 
This can be measured by an initial penile duplex doppler scan, (PDDU) which determines the presence and size of fibrosis and/ or plaque formation. The PDDU is completed pre-trial and post trial.to assess for changes in tissue pathology which is measured as a composite outcome.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>The  PDDU is assessed pre -trial and following 12 sessions of therapeutic ultrasound, post-trial. approximately 4 weeks from the commencement of the intervention.
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A subjective Peyronies Disease Questionnaire (PDQ) is also utilised to determine subjective assessment of pain and function as a composite outcome .This is completed pre-trial and post trial.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The PDQ is assessed pre -trial and following 12 sessions of therapeutic ultrasound, post-trial. approximately 4 weeks from the commencement of the intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Erectile function is to be assessed using the International Index of Erectile Function (IIEF) </outcome>
      <timepoint>The IIEF will be administered pre- trial and following 12 sessions of therapeutic ultrasound approximately 4 weeks post commencement of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>We intend to recruit 40 healthy males, aged &gt;18years with a history of Peyronies Disease.

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria
-	History of diabetes type 1 or 2.
-	Current smokers (&lt;1 year post cessation)

</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants who are referred to the study will sequentially receive an envelope displaying either 'control' or 'intervention' group. If selected for control delayed entry of 4 weeks is instigated. If selected for the intervention group immediate commencement of the 12 sessions of therapeutic ultrasound.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>SPSS</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/10/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>34</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/12/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Western Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Human Services
Entrance 4 Parkway
Crawley 6009
Western Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>SKG Radiology Hollywood</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>SKG Radiology Hollywood
95 Monash St, 
Nedlands 6009

</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Joanne Milios</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Complete Physiotherapy &amp; Men's Health
U7/12 Davallia Rd, 
Duncraig 6023
Western Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Joanne Milios</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Complete Physiotherapy &amp; Men's Health
U7/12 Davallia Rd, 
Duncraig 6023
Western Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The health of penile tissue is dependent on adequate blood flow. In Peyronies disease, fibrous plaques develop in the muscular tissue of the penis  as a result of reduced blood flow, caused by aging, diabetes or trauma such as surgery for prostate cancer.. The hardened plaques can be firm to feel,cause pain, prevent normal stretching and cause curvature of the penis, making sexual activity difficult or if severe enough, not possible.  The negative impact on quality of life is significant and more than 70% men with PD experience depression or relationship difficulties as a result. Currently, Peyronies disease is treated with surgical intervention or penile implant surgery, which may cause further scar tissue development, penile shortening and erectile dysfunction. Therapeutic ultrasound is commonly used to treat soft tissue trauma in musculoskeletal injuries and has no know side effects. It reduces inflammation, minimizes tissue damage, improves blood flow and helps soften scar tissue. The purpose of this study is to assess if therapeutic ultrasound assists in the resolution of Peyronies Disease.  

Rationale:
To date, treatment for Peyronies disease has been invasive or mostly ineffective. Surgical correction for example, shortens the penis and contributes to further fibrosis and scarring. Less invasive techniques such as injections have had mixed results and sometimes cause pain, inflammation and increased scarring. In a recent case, complete resolution of Peyronies disease occurred as a result of therapeutic ultrasound use, as analyzed under Doppler scan (Dr Kaard).In addition, Ms Milios has observed promising results in her clinical practice. There is also some evidence in the literature of older studies that ultrasound might be a useful therapy (Miller, HC, Ardizzone J. Urology 1983 22(6) 584-85, Frank IN, Scott WW. The ultrasonic treatment of Peyronies disease.1971 J o Urol 106 : 883) The pathophysiological mechanisms by which ultrasound might be effective are currently unknown ,but in theory relate to the piezoelectric force that bombards the fibrotic tissue via high intensity vibration and heating to a depth of up to 5cm (1 MHz soundhead).
In summary, there are clinical case reports and some non-randomized and uncontrolled experimental evidence that ultrasound might be helpful in the treatment of Peyronies Disease. 

</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>SKG Hollywood provided a reduced rate for subsequent PDDU scans after patients paid for their initial scan, pre-trial scan</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Ethics Office of Research Enterprise The University of Western Australia </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The University of Western Australia M459, 35 Stirling Highway Crawley WA 6009 Australia
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/05/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec> RA/4/1/8089  </hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/02/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Joanne Milios</name>
      <address>The University of Western Australia 
Entrance 4, Parkway
Crawley 6009
Western Australia
and 
Complete Physiotherapy &amp; Men's Health
U7/12 Davallia Rd, 
Duncraig 6023
Western Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 0408 022 950</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>info.prost.inc@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Joanne Milios</name>
      <address>The University of Western Australia 
Entrance 4, Parkway
Crawley 6009
Western Australia
and 
Complete Physiotherapy &amp; Men's Health
U7/12 Davallia Rd, 
Duncraig 6023
Western Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 0408 022 950</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>info.prost.inc@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Daniel Green</name>
      <address>The University of Western Australia
Department of Human Services
Entrance 4 Parkway Rd, 
Crawley 6009
Western Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 0400 1968 01</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>danny.green@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>