<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336666">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/03/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/03/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000288921</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Acupuncture for the treatment of Anorexia Nervosa: a pilot study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot study to examine the role of acupuncture to restore weight, improve eating behaviours and reduce anxiety and depression in those with Anorexia Nervosa.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Weight restoration in sufferers of Anorexia Nervosa.</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Eating behaviours in sufferers of Anorexia Nervosa</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety in sufferers of Anorexia Nervosa</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Depression in sufferers of Anorexia Nervosa</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Study group 1: Traditional Acupuncture while receiving their usual care at the Hills Private Hospital.  Usual care is the participant's individually tailored Hills treatment which involves a combination of medical, pharmacological and psychological therapy and rehabilitation.
Pragmatic acupuncture based on Traditional Chinese Medicine (TCM) diagnosis will be used.  Two treatments a week will be administered for the first three weeks while they are an inpatient and then weekly for three weeks during their attendance as an outpatient.  Acupuncture will be applied bilaterally.  Duration of each treatment is 45 minutes.  Acupuncture needles will be inserted to tissue level and stimulated manually to elicit the needling sensation de qi and stimulated once more during this treatment session. Needles will be retained for a minimum of 20 minutes.  Single-use disposable stainless steel needles (0.25 x 40mm) will be used.  All points will be located according to the WHO International Standard Acupuncture Point Locations that was agreed on at Tsukuba, Japan, November 2006.</interventions>
    <comparator>Study group 2: The active control group will receive light massage (plus usual care) involving acupressure and light longitudinal massage therapy.  The acupressure will be applied bilaterally.  Longitudinal massage therapy will also be applied bilaterally.  Trial procedures will be identical to the acupuncture group regarding duration, and interaction with the practitioner will be the same for the light massage control group. 
Study group 3:  Usual care only.  Participants in this group will receive the usual care at the Hills Private Hospital only.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weight restoration measured by body weight and BMI</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6, 12 and 26 weeks.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Eating behaviour as measured by the Eating Disorder Inventory-3 (EDI-3) and the Eating Disorder Examination Questionnaire (EDE-Q v 16).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6, 12 and 26 weeks.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression and anxiety as measured by the DAAS.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6, 12 and 26 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life specific for those with eating disorders as measured by the EDQoL.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6, 12 and 26 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Qualitative assessment of the perceptions of the intervention and the participants experience of it and its effects via an in-depth interview</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of the trial.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Analysis of acceptability of the intervention, views towards it, randomisation, likes and dislikes and expectancy and clinicians views of the intervention via self-report</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of the trial.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants 15 years or greater with a primary clinical diagnosis of Anorexia Nervosa with purging and/or restricting subtype.  Participants must be medical stable (e.g. heart rate of &gt;40bpm, blood pressure &gt; 90/60mmHg, no electrolyte abnormalities and temperature &gt; 36 degrees C.  They must be receiving treatment at the Hills Private Hospital and also have the ability to provide informed written consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>15</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any serious co morbid medical illness other than the complications of malnutrition associated with Anorexia Nervosa, substance dependence, psychosis or bipolar disorder.  Unable to attend the allocated intervention sessions or the concurrent use of acupuncture or light massage.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Screening for eligibility will be undertaken over the phone by the research acupuncturist.  Participants will need to be 15 years or greater with a primary diagnosis of Anorexia Nervosa, medically stable and receiving treatment at the Hills Private Hospital. If the participant is eligible and interested then an appointment will be made.  Participants who consent will be randomly allocated to the study by taking the next sequentially numbered sealed opaque envelope. Randomisation will be into two study groups, acupuncture and treatment as usual or light massage and treatment as usual.  
Treatment as usual is not randomised.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation schedule will be prepared by a researcher not directly involved with the trial. The randomisation sequence will be computer generated.  The sequence will be concealed and held in a locked filling cabinet at the Centre for Complementary Medicine Research.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Western Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Locked Bad 1797
Penrith South  NSW 1797</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Western Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Locked Bag 1797
Penrith South  NSW 1797</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>THe Hills Priviate Hospital</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>499 Windsor Rd
Baulkham Hills 
NSW 2153</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This pilot study looks at the role of acupuncture as an adjunct therapy to restore weight, improve eating behaviours and reduce anxiety and depression in those suffering from Anorexia Nervosa.  You can join this study if you are receiving treatment at the Hills Private Hospital and you are medically stable.  Participants who consent to be randomised will receive acupuncture plus usual care or light massage plus usual care.  Those participants who declined to be randomised will be invited to participate in the study as usual care only group. Both the acupuncture and light massage groups receive three weeks of twice weekly treatment followed by three weeks of once weekly treatment. Effective management of Anorexia Nervosa is important to achieve positive ling term physical and mental health outcomes.  Preliminary reports suggest that acupuncture may help improve quality of life and anxiety. The results of this study will be used in the design of a larger trial on the use of acupuncture as an adjunct therapy for the treatment of Anorexia Nervosa.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Western Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Locked Bag 1797
Penrith South DC 1797</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>H8934</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/02/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Caroline Smith</name>
      <address>Centre for Complementary Medicine Research
LG Building 5 Cambelltown Campus
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith South DC 1797</address>
      <phone>+61 2 46203777</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 2 46203291</fax>
      <email>caroline.smith@uws.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sarah Fogarty</name>
      <address>Centre for Complementary Medicine Research
LG Building 5 Cambelltown Campus
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith South DC 1797</address>
      <phone>+61 2 46203290</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.fogarty@uws.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sarah Fogarty</name>
      <address>Centre for Complementary Medicine Research
LG Building 5 Cambelltown Campus
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith South DC 1797</address>
      <phone>+61 2 46203290</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.fogarty@uws.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>