<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372837">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/05/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000659303p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of high carbohydrate and low carbohydrate suppers on fasting blood glucose levels (BGLs) in gestational diabetes mellitus (GDM): GDM Supper Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of high carbohydrate and low carbohydrate suppers on fasting blood glucose levels (BGLs) in gestational diabetes mellitus (GDM)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>None</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>gestational diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fetal medicine and complications of pregnancy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Women will be informed of the study at their first education class.  Women will be enrolled into the study following their initial Dietitian review if they have greater than or equal to two fasting BGLs in the preceding week between 4.7-5.4 mmol/L and post-prandial levels not requiring insulin treatment, following informed consent being obtained. The dietitians delivering the intervention all have extensive clinical experience of a minimum of 5 years. There is not expected to be any carry-over effect of the treatments so the "wash out" period between treatments is the intervening daytime only.

Participants will be asked to:
a	take a standardised, healthy carbohydrate based snack for five days
b	take a standardised, higher protein, lower carbohydrate snack for five days
c	have five days without any supper snack
d      The snack will be consumed at least 2 hours after dinner (between 7pm and 12am depending on the timing of their dinner between 5pm and 8pm)
e	record fasting and post-prandial BGLs daily for the fifteen day period
f	record activity levels (low/moderate/high) intensity and record sleep quality (poor/moderate/good) each day

If they consent to participating in the study, they will be randomly allocated to an order in which to take their snacks:
1	Higher carbohydrate snack: Yoghurt tub (175g) and an apple (medium ~150g)
	Yoghurt = 88cal, 12.3g CHO, 8.8g protein, 0.2g fat
	Apple = 68cal, 14.6g CHO, 0.4g protein, 0g fat 
	TOTAL = 156cal; 26.9g carbohydrate; 9.2g protein, 0.2g fat 

2	Lower carbohydrate snack:  Almonds (10 nuts) and 2 squares (20g) of dark chocolate 
	Almonds = 72cal, 0.6g CHO, 2.3g protein, 6.6g fat 
	Dark chocolate = 112cal, 6.8g CHO, 1.9g protein, 8.2g fat 
	TOTAL = 184cal; 7.4g CHO, 4.2g protein, 14.8g fat 

3      No snack

Food will be provided to the study participants in esky containers for transport home.  It will be prepared by kitchen staff at the hospital. Women will record their BGLs, quality of sleep and activity levels each day on a record sheet provided to them (attached). They will also record with a tick whether they complied with the prescribed snack.


As the patients are not on insulin there are no safety concerns regarding missing an evening snack.  If a participant requires insulin while the study is ongoing (as decided by the physician) then their participation in the study is ceased.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Crossover design, ie participants are their own controls. The control treatment is that currently recommended by the hospital which is the high carbohydrate snack (apple and yoghurt) This is currently the standard recommendation for women with gestational diabetes and elevated fasting glucose levels by dietitians in clinical practice</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasting capillary glucose level as measured with a home glucometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>The outcome is assessed by the participant checking their fasting capillary glucose every day during the 15 day period (each day of the 3 different 5 day intervention periods) of the trial.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Requirement for insulin as assessed by the physician based on fasting glucose levels, gestation, fetal growth and maternal weight</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the completion of the 15 day intervention or at any timepoint if concern is raised by the participant or treating dietitian regarding the level of their fasting or postprandial glucose levels</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>a	Have gestational diabetes diagnosed on routine oral glucose tolerance test. OGTT will diagnose gestational diabetes if fasting BSL is greater than or equal to 5.1, 1 hour reading is greater than or equal to 10, 2 hours greater than or equal to 8.5.
b	Be on diet control (no oral hypoglycaemic agents or insulin)
c	Have two or more fasting BGLs of 4.7-5.4mmol/L in the week prior to recruitment
d	Have a singleton pregnancy
e	Are between 28 and 34 weeks gestation
f	Have not had hospital admissions or Celestone therapy for the 2 weeks of the study
g	Have no food allergies or intolerances that preclude them taking the snack
h	Are compliant with BGL monitoring
i	Fasting BGL recorded between 6am to 8am with a minimum time of 8 hours since their evening snack
j	Are capable of giving informed consent
k	Are women aged greater than or equal to 18 years of age
l	Have dinner between the hours of 5pm and 8 pm, with a 2 hour minimum time between evening meal and evening snack
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>a	Requiring NovoRapid (fast acting insulin) with meals or requiring Protaphane (long acting insulin) during the two week period (as per treating physicians decision)
b	Patients on metformin or other medications which may affect glucose metabolism (as per treating physicians decision) during the study 
c	Shift workers, or irregular meal times for any other reason
d	greater than or equal to 3 fasting BGLs greater or equal to 5.2mmol/L in the week prior to recruitment
e	Macrosomic foetus, defined as AC greater than 90 percentile or polyhydramnios
f	Women who require an interpreting service
g	Women who have had bariatric surgery
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealment is being used using sealed envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>Concealed envelope randomisation with permuted block randomisation</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A sample size of  66 has been calculated to be enough to show a 0.2mmol drop in fasting blood glucose levels (with a standard deviation of 0.5mmol/l) using an alpha value of 0.05 and a beta of 0.9. Students t test will be used to compare the average fasting blood glucose levels.  If underlying assumptions for the t-test are not met, non-parametric tests will be used. Bonferonni corrections will be used when multiple tests are performed. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/09/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>66</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>16/09/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>King Edward Memorial Hospital - Subiaco</hospital>
    <postcode>6008 - Subiaco</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Dorothy Graham</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>King Edward Memorial Hospital
Bagot Road
Subiaco WA 6008</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>King Edward Memorial Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>King Edward Memorial Hospital
Bagot Road
Subiaco WA 6008</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Dr Dorothy Graham</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>King Edward Memorial Hospital
Bagot Rd Subiaco, 6008, WA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Diabetes in pregnancy is the most common metabolic dysfunction in pregnancy.  Many women are managed with diet control alone.  It is therefore essential that women are receiving accurate nutritional advice.

Current practice at our hospital is to advise women to have a bedtime snack to help meet the caloric requirements of pregnancy, and with the expectation that it may suppress hepatic gluconeogenesis thus achieving lower fasting blood glucose levels (BGLs).  Recommending supper in GDM is widely practiced across Australia and is contained in the Dietitians Association of Australia resources, and supported by the Canadian and American Diabetes Associations Guidelines; however, there is no strong or recent evidence to support this.

This study aims to recruit 66 women and measure the effect of two different snacks: a higher carbohydrate snack (apple and yoghurt) and a lower carbohydrate snack (nuts and dark chocolate) as compared to no snack, to see what influence each of these has on fasting BGLs.  Each snack will be consumed for five consecutive days.  Women will be randomly allocated an order in which to consume each snack.  Women will also be required to record their activity levels each day, in order to monitor the effect that this has on fasting BGLs

It is expected that women will have lower fasting BGLs when consuming either snack than when they are not having a snack.  It is also expected that those women with higher physical activity levels will have lower fasting BGLs.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>WNHS Human Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>King Edward Memorial Hospital 
Bagot Road
Subiaco WA 6008</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/05/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Meg Henze</name>
      <address>King Edward Memorial Hospital
Bagot Road
Subiaco WA 6008</address>
      <phone>+61 8 6458 2222</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>meg.henze@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Meg Henze</name>
      <address>King Edward Memorial Hospital
Bagot Road
Subiaco WA 6008</address>
      <phone>+61 8 6458 2222</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>meg.henze@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Meg Henze</name>
      <address>King Edward Memorial Hospital
Bagot Road
Subiaco WA 6008</address>
      <phone>+61 8 6458 2222</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>meg.henze@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>