<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335029">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/01/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/01/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000053022</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The QUeensland Accelerated Risk Trial (QUART): Accelerated pathways in the assessment of suspected acute coronary syndrome in the Emergency Department.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In patients presenting to the emergency department with potential acute coroanry syndrome (ACS) is there a difference in the change in troponin (absolute and rate) and a traditional mulitmarker approach with risk stratification tools in excluding significant coronary artery disease?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute coronary syndromes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study is designed to prospectively validate that an accelerated chest pain algorithm involving blood levels of Troponin I, creatine-kinase MB fraction (CK-MB), and myoglobin or  delta troponin measurements over a 2 hour time period from presentation with a risk stratification process allows ealry futher testing or discharge of patients with intermediate risk for acute coronary syndrome (ACS) presenting to the Emergency department (ED). These results will be used to develop a pathway for investigation of pateints with potential acute coronary syndrome (ACS).

We will focus on delta troponin, as well as myoglobin, and CK-MB combinations and look at absolute change in biomarker levels and rates of change to identify the population at risk for ACS. 
The overall duration will be ~ 2years.</interventions>
    <comparator>Current practice for identification of high risk patients involves a risk stratification process of serial electrocardiograms (ECGs), and Troponin I (TnI) testing 0 and 6hr post-presentation. This will continue to be performed, and patients care will be based on CURRENT practice.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>cardiac death as adjudicated by cardiologists</outcome>
      <timepoint>45 days from index presentation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>acute myocardial infarction as adjudicated by cardiologists</outcome>
      <timepoint>45 days from index presentation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>revascularization procedure as adjudicated by cardiologists</outcome>
      <timepoint>45 days from index presentation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>acute coronary syndrome as adjudicated by cardiologists</outcome>
      <timepoint>45 days from index presentation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>All cause mortalityas adjudicated by cardiologists</outcome>
      <timepoint>45 days from index presentation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria include all patients who present to the ED with at least 5 minutes of chest pain suggestive of ACS. In accord with American Heart Association (AHA) guidelines, these will include the presence of acute chest, epigastric, neck, jaw or arm pain or discomfort or pressure or breathlessness without apparent non-cardiac source. More general/atypical symptoms (such as fatigue, nausea, vomiting, sweating and faintness) will not be used as inclusion criteria. 

Patients who have chest discomfort and in whom the attending staff consider it necessary to perform an electrocardiogram (ECG) for the assessment of possible ACS will be enrolled.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnancy
Patients under the age of 18 years old
Unable or unwilling to consent
Patients for whom follow-up will not be possible either due to lack of contact address or because they will be overseas.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/10/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>29/10/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>20/10/2008</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>4/02/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>1000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Queensland Emergency Medicine Research Foundation</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>88 L'Estrange tce, 
Kelvin Grove, Queensland 4059</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Queensland Emergency Medicine Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>88 L'Estrange Tce
Kelvin Grove, Queensland 4059</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study examines whether patients presenting to emergency with chest pain can be managed more rapidly than current standard care. The current process involves blood tests over 6-24 hours. The study study examines the safety of an accelerated chest pain algorithm . That is whether combining the results of blood tests such as Troponin I, creatine-kinase MB fraction (CK-MB), and myoglobin over a 2 hour time period from presentation with a risk stratification process allows early futher testing or discharge of patients with potential acute coronary syndrome (ACS). These results will be used to develop a pathway for investigation of pateints with potential acute coronary syndrome (ACS) in the Emergency Department. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Cullen L, Parsonage WA, Greenslade J, Lamanna A, Hammett CJ, Than M, Ungerer JP, Chu K, O'Kane S, Brown AF. Comparison of early biomarker strategies with the Heart Foundation of Australia/Cardiac Society of Australia and New Zealand guidelines for risk stratification of emergency department patients with chest pain. Emerg Med Australas. 2012;24:595-603.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human research ethics commmitee (HREC) - Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Butterfield St,
Herston Queensland 4029</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/09/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2008/101</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/08/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Dr Louise Cullen</name>
      <address>Dept of Emergency Medicine,
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Butterfield St
Herston Queensland 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3636 7901</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>louise_cullen@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Dr Louise Cullen</name>
      <address>Dept of Emergency Medicine,
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Butterfiled St
Herston Queensland 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3636 7901</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>louise_cullen@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Louise Cullen</name>
      <address>Department of Emergency Medicine, Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital, Butterfield Street, HERSTON QLD 4029</address>
      <phone>+617 36467901</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>louise.cullen@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>