<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368703">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/06/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/06/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000652572</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Dispensing study to assess the visual performance of optimised prototype contact lenses</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Prospective, double-masked, bilateral wear, crossover, dispensing clinical trial to assess visual performance of multiple optimised prototype contact lens designs compared to commercial contact lenses</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Presbyopia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal eye development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Multiple prototype contact lens designs made from etafilcon A material will be assessed during the study, where each design will be worn daily for up to a week on a daily disposable modality. Participants will attend separate fitting and assessment visits for each lens type (Fitting Visit on Day 1, and Assessment Visit on Day 7 at the latest, but may be as early as 6 hours after the Fitting Visit). There will be a minimum 24 hour washout period between lens designs, i.e. after an assessment visit but before the next fitting visit. 

Prototype lenses all have a multifocal design and each design will be available in +6 to -10 dioptre powers. The difference between the prototype designs are in their manipulation of higher order spherical aberrations via their optics (i.e. differing power distribution throughout the lens), in order to achieve an increased depth of focus. Different manipulations can achieve either different or similar depths of focus. 

Up to 25 contact lens designs will be tested in the study, however each individual participant will test a maximum of 10 prototype designs. However, as participants are able to withdraw at any time, the final number of lenses tested by each participant is essentially determined by them.

Participants are asked to bring in any leftover lenses to the Assessment Visit as well as the foils of the lens blisters they open and use, to assist us in monitoring adherence.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants will test at least 1 commercially available contact lens as a control for up to a week. The control lenses are 1-Day Acuvue Moist, 1-Day Acuvue Moist Multifocal, Dailies Aqua Comfort Plus, Dailies Aqua Comfort Plus Multifocal, Biotrue ONEday for Presbyopia, Clariti 1 Day Multifocal, SEED 1dayPure moisture Multistage, Proclear Multifocal and MiSight. All will be worn on a daily disposable modality.

There will be a minimum 1 night washout period between lens designs. Participants will attend separate visits at the beginning and end of each wear period.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Visual acuity, measured at distance with a computerised LogMAR chart and at near with a near LogMAR chart.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 1 week after lens fitting.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subjective rating of vision will be assessed for each pair of lenses with a questionnaire based on a 1-10 scale. The questionnaire has been designed specifically for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 1 week after lens fitting.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subjective rating of comfort assessed for each pair of lenses with a questionnaire on a 1-10 scale. The questionnaire has been designed specifically for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 1 week after lens fitting</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Willingness to purchase the lenses assessed with a yes/no response questionnaire. The questionnaire has been designed specifically for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 1 week after lens fitting</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Able to read and comprehend English and give informed consent as demonstrated by signing a record of informed consent.
Be at least 18 years old, male or female.
Willing to comply with the wearing and clinical trial visit schedule as directed by the Investigator.
Have ocular health findings considered to be normal and which would not prevent the participant from safely wearing contact lenses.
Is correctable to at least 6/12 (20/40) or better in each eye with contact lenses.
Be suitable and willing to wear contact lenses.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any pre-existing ocular irritation, injury or condition (including
infection or disease) of the cornea, conjunctiva or eyelids that would preclude contact lens fitting and safe wearing of contact lenses.
Any systemic disease that adversely affects ocular health e.g.
diabetes, Graves disease, and auto immune diseases such as
ankylosing spondylitis, multiple sclerosis, Sjogrens syndrome and systemic lupus erythematosus. Conditions such as systemic hypertension and arthritis do not automatically exclude prospective participants.
Use of or a need for concurrent category S3 and above ocular
medication at enrolment. Ocular medication can be prescribed during the course of the trial as per standard optometric practice.
Use of or a need for any systemic medication or topical medications which may alter normal ocular findings / are known to affect a participants ocular health / physiology or contact lens performance either in an adverse or beneficial manner at enrolment and/or during the clinical trial. NB: Systemic antihistamines are allowed on an as needed basis, provided they are not used prophylactically during the trial and at least 24 hours before the clinical trial product is used.
Eye surgery within 12 weeks immediately prior to enrolment for this trial.
Previous corneal refractive surgery.
Contraindications to contact lens wear.
Known allergy or intolerance to ingredients in any of the clinical trial products.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be screened for general clinical trial suitability by way of a routine eye examination which includes refraction, visual acuity and general eye health. Informed consent will be obtained prior to any clinical trial procedures. 

Participants are stratified into the presbyope group or non-presbyope group depending on their add requirement, and the order in which they test lenses will be randomised.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomised to the order of testing lens designs. The randomisation plan will be generated from http://www.randomization.com/. The website's second random generator will be used to create a random permutation of lens types for each participant. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A minimum of 10 participants in each arm of the study (presbyope and non-presbyope) are required in order to demonstrate a statistically significant paired difference between the control lenses and each iteration in visual acuity of 0.1 +/-0.1 logMAR units at the 5% level of significance and 80% power. The minimum sample size is a requirement at each stage of the cross over trial. The sample size is not adjusted for drop outs due to the short nature of each stage. Participants will need to be replaced if drop outs occur within an arm.

Visual acuity will be recorded on a logMAR scale. Data will be summarised as means +/- standard deviations. No transformation is likely to be required. Visual acuity will be compared between each lens design and control lens types. The significance of lens design will be determined for each visit.
Repeated effects linear mixed model with subject random intercepts or paired t tests will be employed for the analysis of visual acuity. Analysis will be performed within each study arm namely presbyopes and non-presbyopes.

Subjective ratings will be recorded on a scale of 1 to 10 on steps of 1. Data will be summarised as means +/- standard deviations. No transformation is likely to be required. Subjective ratings will be compared between each lens design and control lens types. The significance of lens design will be determined for each visit. Repeated effects linear mixed model with subject random intercepts or paired t tests will be employed for the analysis of subjective ratings. Analysis will be performed within each study arm namely presbyopes and non-presbyopes.

When a family of test lens designs are compared to the control, the best design within the family for each participant is selected prior to paired analysis. This design is selected by computing the average of subjective ratings of distance, intermediate, near and overall vision satisfaction for each participant. The design that maximises this computed average is selected for the family type paired analysis compared to controls.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>16/10/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>1/12/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>161</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>7/02/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2052 - Unsw Sydney</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Brien Holden Vision Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 4, North Wing, Rupert Myers Building, Gate 14, Barker Street, UNSW Sydney NSW 2052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Brien Holden Vision Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 4, North Wing, Rupert Myers Building, Gate 14, Barker Street, UNSW Sydney NSW 2052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To assess visual performance of multiple optimised prototype soft contact lens designs compared to commercially available contact lenses</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Limited</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>129 Glen Osmond Road, Eastwood
South Australia 5063</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/06/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2015-04-256</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jennifer Sha</name>
      <address>Brien Holden Vision Institute, Level 5 North Wing, Rupert Myers Building, Gate 14, Barker Street, UNSW, Sydney NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61293859811</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.sha@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kassandra Wagenfuehr</name>
      <address>Brien Holden Vision Institute, Level 5 North Wing, Rupert Myers Building, Gate 14, Barker Street, UNSW, Sydney NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61293855934</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.wagenfuehr@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jennifer Sha</name>
      <address>Brien Holden Vision Institute, Level 5 North Wing, Rupert Myers Building, Gate 14, Barker Street, UNSW, Sydney NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61293859811</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.sha@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jennifer Sha</name>
      <address>Brien Holden Vision Institute, Level 5 North Wing, Rupert Myers Building, Gate 14, Barker Street, UNSW, Sydney NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61293859811</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.sha@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>