<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347656">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/11/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/01/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000005853</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Lymphoedema Prevention Following Inguinal or Ilioinguinal Dissection for Metastatic Melanoma</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Are compression garments and manual lymphatic drainage more effective than no compression or drainage in reducing the incidence/severity of lymphoedema in patients with metastatic melanoma (Stage III), following inguinal or ilioinguinal dissection?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Lymphoedema following inguinal or ilioinguinal groin dissection for metastatic melanoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Malignant melanoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Thigh length, 20-30mmHg compression garments on the leg of the operative side, and medical grade compression shorts will be worn approximately 12 hours a day and removed for hygienne and sleeping.  The specific garment utilised will depend on the individual patient measurements regarding best fit and fabric characteristics so may include garments from Sigvaris, Jobst, Juzo or if required, even be custom made.  Unless medical co-morbidities dictate caution, all leg garments will be 20-30mmHg.   All garments will be applied following removal of post operative drains. 
Simple, or self lymphatic drainage (SLD) will be taught to participants in the intervention group by trained lymphoedema therapists.  They will be provided an individual body map and drainage pathway and guidelines.  They will receive three half hour formal 1:1 education sessions regarding self lymphatic drainage and are asked to conduct this each day for 6 months following post operative removal of drains. Training and education regarding correct garment donning and doffing of garments will occur at initial fitting with trained lymphoedema therapists ensuring that the participant (or carer) are able to correctly and safely apply and remove the garments. Drainage techniques and garment wear will continue to be assessed and monitored throughout the 6 month intervention phase.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group participants will be monitored via 3 monthly assessment (bioimpedence, circumferential and quality of life).  If signs of lymphoedema arise, they will be offered comprehensive lymphoedema treatment.  This is standard treatment.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction in the rate of lymphoedema of 45% to 18% with statistical significance of p = 0.05.  Allowing for a 33% two year mortality and 10% attrition a total of 155 participants need to be recruited to the study in order to achieve a sample of size of 88.
There is no worldwide consensus regarding quanitification of lymphoedema and this creates problems for classifying lymphoedema.  
For the purpose of this study, our team have defined lymphoedema as a volume change of greater than 10% compared to the unaffected limb in addition to a bioimpedance change of 10 points from pre-operative baseline.  The International Society of Lymphology defines "mild" lymphoedema as less than a 20% volume change.  
Circumferential tape measurements at 10cm intervals (using a measuring board) will be taken of the operated side and contralateral leg.  In addition, bioimpedence analysis will also be taken.  
Quality of Life self rating scales (EORTC and the LYMQOL-leg) will also be utilised. 
Assessments will be conducted by a blinded assessor pre-operatively, at 6 weeks post operatively and then at 3 monthly intervals for 2 years following surgery.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At two years after randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction in severity of lymphoedema between groups.

This will be quantified by the volume of lymphoedema measured using both circumferential measures to calculate volume and using bioimpedence measures.

LYMQOL-leg is a self-rating questionaire asking patients to quantify their perception of how lymphoedema is impacting on their life and function.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At two years after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess quality of life for all patients.

EORTC and the LYMQOL (leg) will be administered to control and intervention groups to assess quality of life.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At two years after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessing the impact of the following in development of lymphoedema (seroma, wound complications, co-morbidities, BMI, adjuvant radiotherapy).


Whilst evidence exists to support that increased BMI and radiotherapy may negatively impact on development of lymphoedema, we wish to analyse whether the number of pre-existing co-morbidities OR wound complications further contribue to lymphoedema development.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At two years after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Aged 18 years and over
English speaking (or interpreter available)
Ability to provide informed consent
Ability to attend regular followup
Confirmed metastatic melanoma
Ability to apply and remove garment, conduct simple lymphatic drainage (or carer available to do so)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Peripheral arterial disease (ABPI &lt;.6)
Pre-existing lymphoedema
Bilateral groin dissection
Previous contralateral groin dissection</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Concealed allocation by sealed envelopes. 

Eligible participants will be identified by research nurse at time of booking for surgery in both public and private consulting rooms.  Interested and eligible participants will be provided with written information and offered to sign consent to be recruited into the study.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomised control trial via Mater Reseach Support Centre randomisation generated envelopes.
Computer generated randomised variable permuted block concealed allocation.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Any participant on the control arm of the study who develops lymphoedema will be offered intervention and may therefore there may be some participants will crossover from control to intervention.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Baseline demographic characteristics of the control and intervention gorups will be reported; continuous variables using mean and standard deviation (SD) or median and interquartile range (IQR), depedent on whether the variable is normally distributed, as assessed by the Shapiro-Wilk test and the visual confirmation using histograms) and the frequencies and proportions for categorical variables.   Primary outcome will be compared between the two groups using the difference of proportions, and will be presented as the absolute difference, corresponding 95% confidence interval (CI) and p-value; an intention to treat analysis will be used.  Continuous secondary outcome measures will be assessed for differences between the control and intervention groups by reporting the mean (SD) or median (IQR) and associated 95% CI's; categorical secondary outcome measures will be treated similar to the priamry outcome.  As the study is not powered to detect differences in the secondary outcome measures p-values will not be presented.  To determine if there are factors that affect development of lymphoedema multivariate logistic regresssion will be undertaken including possible independent predictors (such as BMI, medical complications) that were identified as significant through bivariate analysis.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/01/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>24/07/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>155</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Mater Health Services</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Raymond Terrace
South Brisbane 
Queensland 4101</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Suncorp</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Suncorp Centre, Level 18, 
36 Wickham Tce BRISBANE, QLD, 4000.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Melody Brown</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Mater Adult Hospital
Occupational Therapy Dept
Raymond Terrace
South Brisbane 
Queensland 4101</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to determine whether compression garments and self massage can prevent or reduce lymphoedema (fluid retention) following groin dissection for metaststic melanoma.

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to join this study if you are a male or female aged 18 years and over with confirmed metastatic melanoma.  You should be able to attend regular follow-up appointments over a period of 2 years.

Trial details.
Participants in this trial will be randomly (by chance) allocated to one of two groups.  Participants in one group will wear compression stockings 12 hours a day for 6 months and conduct daily self massage for a period of 6 months following post operative removal of drains. Participants in this group will receive 1:1 training in self massage over 3 half hour sessions.  They will also receive education and training to ensure they (or their carer) are able to safely put on and remove the compression garment.
Participants in the other group will be monitored via 3 monthly assessments.  If lymphoedema arises, they will be offered comprehensive treatment (as is standard treatment).
All participants will be assessed every 3 months to determine the incidence/severity of lymphoedema and quality of life, and whether this differs between groups.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Mater Health Services Human Research Ethics Committee (EC00332)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Mater Adult Hospital
Raymond Terrace
South Brisbane, Queensland 4101</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/07/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Mater Health Services - HREC approval number 1885A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/11/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Chris Allan</name>
      <address>Mater Adult Hospital Raymond Terrace South Brisbane
Queensland Australia 4101</address>
      <phone>+61 7 31638111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c.allan@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Melody Brown</name>
      <address>Occupational Therapy Dept
Mater Adult Hospital
Level 2 
Raymond Tce
South Brisbane, Queensland 4101</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3163 6000 pager 4312</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>melody.brown@mater.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jenny Hallinan/Melody Brown</name>
      <address>Mater Medical Research Institute
Level 3 
Aubigny Place
Raymond Terrace
South Brisbane 
Queensland, Australia 4101</address>
      <phone>+61(0)468971161</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jhallinan@mmri.mater.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Melody Brown</name>
      <address>Mater Adult Hosptial
Occupational Therapy Department
Raymond Terrace
South Brisbane
Queensland Australia  4101</address>
      <phone>+61 7 31636000 pager 4312</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>melody.brown@mater.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>