<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83442">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/12/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/02/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000100291</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Osteo-cise: Strong Bones for Life. An Inclusive Evidence-based Multi-component Exercise, Falls Prevention and Osteoporosis Education Program.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effectiveness and feasibility of a multi-site, multi-faceted exercise intervention combined with an osteoporosis education program on bone mineral density, muscle function and quality of life in community dwelling older adults at risk of osteoporosis.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Osteoporosis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Sarcopenia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoporosis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal musculoskeletal and cartilage development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal metabolism and endocrine development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>An 18 month randomised controlled trial (12 month intervention with 6 month follow-up) consisting of a multi-component exercise program involving resistance (strength) and power training, balance and mobility activities (60 minutes, 3 times per week for 12 months) combined with osteoporosis education sessions. These interactive education sessions (~60 minutes) will be held every 3 months (4 sessions over 12 months) at a local community/recreation centre and will include information (presentation and handout material) related to: risk factors for osteoporosis; best practice exercise and nutrition guidelines; understanding bone density results; strategies to reduce the risk of falling; communicating clearly with your doctor, and medications for the treatment of osteoporosis. All participants will receive daily calcium (700 mg) and vitamin D (1200 IU) supplements.  Follow-up testing will be conducted 6 months after the intervention to assess any residual benefits.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard care self-management control group that will receive osteoporosis information (handouts) in the mail every 4 months for 12 months. Participants assigned to this group will receive general information relevant to osteoporosis (eg. Osteoporosis Australia fact sheets related to osteoporosis and risk factors, healthful nutrition recommendations, exercise for osteoporosis and falls prevention, medications and treatments for osteoporosis). The aim is to encourage participants to actively take charge of their health in seeking out appropriate medical information and services to prevent osteoporosis, falls and fractures. All participants will receive the same daily calcium (700 mg) and vitamin D (1200 IU) supplements as the intervention group</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total body, hip and lumbar spine bone mineral density measured by Dual Energy X-ray Absorptiometry (DXA) and bone structure (distal femur and proximal tibia) measured by magnetic resonance imaging (MRI).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurements will be made at baseline, 12 and 18 months (except for MRI which will be assessed at baseline and 18 months only).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Muscle strength and power of the back and lower limbs measued by one repetition maximum (1-RM) testing; body composition (lean mass and fat mass) measured by DXA and MRI.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Strength measurements will made at baseline and every 6 months during the 12 month intervention, and then at the 6 month follow-up testing. Body composition will be measured as per the body density testing</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dynamic balance, power and gait speed will be measured using the timed-up-and-go, functional reach, four square and stair-climbing tests.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurements will be made at baseline and every 6 months during the 12 month intervention, and then at the 6 month follow-up testing.
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum vitamin D, parathyroid hormone and bone turnover markers.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurements will be made at baseline, 6, 12 and 18 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Risk factors for cardiovascular disease (pro- and anti- inflammatory markers and profile of lipids).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurements will be made at baseline, 6, 12 and 18 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Knee volume and structure (cartilage defects, bone size and bone marrow lesions) will be assessed by MRI.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurements will be made at baseline and 18 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Falls incidence monitored by a falls calendar</outcome>
      <timepoint>Everyday during the 12 month intervention and 6 month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Osteoporosis knowledge, beliefs, attitudes and prevention behaviours assessed by the Osteoporosis Knowledge and the Osteoporosis Health Belief Scale questionnaires.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurements will be made at baseline, 6, 12 and 18 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health-related quality of life assessed by the SF-36 questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurements will be made at baseline, 6, 12 and 18 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Osteopenia in the hip (Femoral neck or total hip BMD T-score: -1.0 to -2.5 SD)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Current or prior (6 months) participation in resistance training or a structured weight-bearing exercise program, acute or terminal illness, moderate or severe cognitive impairment (inability to understand and provide written informed consent and/or follow instructions), unstable or ongoing cardiovascular/respiratory disorders, musculoskeletal or neurological disease disrupting voluntary movement or that might limit training, upper or lower extremity fracture in the past 3 months, unwillingness to be randomised to one of the two groups or complete the study requirements.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participant ID numbers will be randomly allocated by personnel not involved in the study.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation list will be computer generated (using a random number generator) in blocks after stratification by gender.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>17/11/2009</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>180</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Medicine
Western Hospital
Footscray
Victoria 3011</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>JO &amp; JR Wicking Trust/Osteoporosis Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 121
Sydney 2001
New South Wales</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Deakin University
</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Centre for Physical Activity and Nutrition Research
221 Burwood Highway
Burwood, Melbourne, Victoria 3129</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Osteoporosis and low trauma fractures currently affect 2.2 million Australians, which is projected to rise to three million people by 2021, with a fracture occurring every 3½ minutes. Currently the medical paradigm of cure for osteoporosis is less than ideal because the limited pharmacological agents available are directed to those who already have the disease or are at increased risk. A more effective approach to reduce the burden of this disease is prevention at the population level. That is, defining models that are efficacious, safe, and can be implemented to a large cross-section of the community. Exercise fulfils most of these criteria, with the added advantage of having beneficial effects on multiple health outcomes. The aim of this 18 month RCT is to evaluate the feasibility and effectiveness of a community-based exercise (high velocity resistance and weight-bearing exercise) and osteoporosis education/awareness program for optimising musculoskeletal health and function and general well-being in older Australians at increased risk of osteoporosis and fractures.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Melbourne Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office for Research
6 East, Main Block
The Royal Melbourne Hospital
PARKVILLE  VIC  3050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/09/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2008-136</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Robin Daly</name>
      <address>Deakin University
Centre for Physical Activity and Nutrition Research
221 Burwood Highway
Burwood, Melbourne Victoria 3125</address>
      <phone>+61392446040</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rmdaly@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Christine Bailey</name>
      <address>The University of Melbourne
Department of Medicine
Western Hospital
Footscray
Victoria 3011</address>
      <phone>+6138345 7164</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cbailey@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Robin Daly</name>
      <address>Deakin University
Centre for Physical Activity and Nutrition Research
221 Burwood Highway
Burwood, Melbourne 3125</address>
      <phone>+61392446040</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rmdaly@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Robin Daly</name>
      <address>Deakin University
Centre for Physical Activity and Nutrition Research
221 Burwood Highway
Burwood, Melbourne Victoria 3125</address>
      <phone>+6139244 6040</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rmdaly@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>