<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366350">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/05/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/06/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000612617</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Phase I/II Study of the Tolerability, Safety and Pharmacokinetics of Oral Monepantel (MPL) in Individuals with Treatment-Refractory Solid Tumours.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase I/II Study of the Tolerability, Safety and Pharmacokinetics of Oral Monepantel (MPL) in Individuals with Treatment-Refractory Solid Tumours.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1156-8971 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>LL1</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Any cancer</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Oral Monepantel (MPL) once daily for 28 days in escalating dose cohorts.  Starting dose for the first cohort is 5 mg/kg bw, with planned dose escalations to 25 mg/kg bw and 62.5 mg/kg bw in subsequent dose cohorts.  An additional dose cohort may be enrolled, dependent emerging results from earlier cohorts.

Study participants will also be required to complete a dosing diary card for each dose of study medication, and return any unused medication at the next clinic visit.

Following completion of the 28 day treatment period study participants may opt to continue extension period, during which time they will continue to receive access to study medication.  During the extension period, participants will be required to attend monthly outpatient visits for medical review, collection of blood samples, measurements of vital signs etc.  At each monthly visit you will be required to return any unused study medication, and will be dispensed with enough study medication for one month of daily home dosing. Participants will receive standard medical care from their usual treating doctors/team.  Participation in the Extension Period may occur indefinitely, or until the participant withdraws or experiences disease progression.</interventions>
    <comparator>None</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Describe the safety, tolerability, dose-limiting toxicities, and maximum-tolerated dose (MTD) of MPL in humans with treatment-refractory solid tumours. 

All adverse events will be assessed for dose limiting toxicity potential using NCI Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE v.4). Regular vital signs and clinical laboratory tests will be conducted throughout study participation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Over 28 days of daily dosing with MPL.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Describe the multiple-dose pharmacokinetics of MPL in participants with treatment-refractory solid tumours.

Serial blood samples for pharmacokinetic analysis will be collected after commencement of study drug on Day 1, with regular samples being collected over the whole treatment period.  Blood samples will be analysed for concentration of MPL and its metabolites.  Spot urine samples over the course of the treatment period will be collected to provide information on MPL accumulation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During 28 days of daily dosing with MPL.

Multiple blood samples will be taken following drug administration at Day 1 during an overnight stay period.  Blood samples will also be collected daily to Day 7, then weekly for the remainder of the treatment period.  Participants continuing in the Extension Period will provide once monthly blood samples.

Blood samples will continue to be collected monthly until the participant discontinues in the Extension Period.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluate evidence for anti-cancer activity of MPL in humans.

Evidence for anti-cancer activitiy will be evaluated from the results of PET/CT scans reported according to RECIST criteria.  CT scans and time to disease progresion will alo be evaluated.  Biopsy tissue and/or ascitic fluid (additional optional consent required) will be collected for exploratory assays assessing cell proliferation and apoptosis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Following 28 days of daily dosing with MPL.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Male or female patients with progressing and unresectable tumours in whom all standard treatments have been exhausted or have been contraindicated.
Life expectancy of at least 3 months, in the opinion of the Investigator.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Recent treatment (i.e. within 14 days of screening) with any systemic anticancer therapy.

Participants for whom standard therapy exists, and in the view of the Invesigator, is appropriate.

Unresolved recovery from recent major surgery, or unresolved toxicity from recent radiotherapy.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1 / Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/06/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>15/05/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>9</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>5</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Stopped early</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/06/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis>Data collected is being analysed</dataanalysis>
    <withdrawnreason>Other reasons/comments</withdrawnreason>
    <withdrawnreasonother>Sufficient data was obtained to permit proceeding to Phase II study, i.e. a safe and active dose.  The study was also terminated to permit reformulation of study drug to a more palatable formulation.</withdrawnreasonother>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>PharmAust Limited</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Suite 7, The Avenue
Nedlands WA  6009</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>PharmAust Limited</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Suite 7, The Avenue
Nedlands
WA 6009</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is evaluating the tolerability, safety and pharmacokinetics of Oral Monepantel (MPL) in patients with advanced solid tumours that do not respond to standard treatments. 

Who is it for? 
You may be eligible to joint this study if you have progressing and unresectable tumours, and have a life expectancy of greater than three months. All standard treatments need to have been exhausted or are contraindicated. 

Study details 
Following enrolment in the study, participants will receive an oral liquid dose of MPL once daily for 28 days. The first three participants enrolled in the study will receive 5mg /kg of body weight in each dose. If there are no toxicities or safety events observed in the first three participants, another three participants will be enrolled and receive 25 mg/kg of body weight in each dose. An additional three participants will be enrolled at 62.5 mg/kg body weight per dose if no toxicities/safety events are observed at 25 mg /kg body weight. If dose-limiting toxicities are observed at any dose level, an additional three participants will be enrolled at the same dose level, before the next dose level is initiated. 

This study design aims to determine whether there is a safe maximum dose that can be provided to patients with this condition. 

The results of the study will contribute towards the development of MPL as an anticancer treatment. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital - Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
SA 5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/04/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/RAH/39</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/02/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Michael Brown</name>
      <address>Director, Cancer Clinical Trials Unit
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide
SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 4157</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michael.brown@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Louise Pirc</name>
      <address>CMAX 
Level 5, Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 3923</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>louise.pirc@cmax.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Roger Aston</name>
      <address>PharmAust Ltd
Suite 7, The Avenue
Nedlands
WA  6007</address>
      <phone>+61 402 762 204</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rogeraston@aol.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Zoe Harrison</name>
      <address>CMAX
Level 5, East Wing
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61  8 8222 3923</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8223 3475</fax>
      <email>zoe.harrison@cmax.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>