<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371435">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/06/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000867392</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Telehealth compared to face to face delivered whole body vibration training in children with Cystic Fibrosis (CF).</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Musculoskeletal clinical  outcomes of Whole Body Vibration Training as an adjunct to physiotherapy in children with Cystic Fibrosis: a comparison of telehealth and face to face therapy delivery.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1187-1861 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cystic Fibrosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human Genetics and Inherited Disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Cystic fibrosis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>who: 32 pre-pubertal outpatients with CF over 5 years of age  (n=16 intervention, n=16 control). Random allocation of subjects will be to home or face-to-face intervention or to the control group.
materials: HYPERVIBE G14 vibration plates will be used in the intervention group (n=16), usual care for controls (n=16). what: intervention- 5 x per week for total 12 week whole body vibration training (WBVT) program consisting of 1 min on: 1 min off intervals for 20mins total working up to 25Hz on the vibration plate in the patients own home. Physio follow up is provided at week 4 and week 8 at home, via telehealth (for 8 patients) or face-to-face at LCCH (8 patients), as dependent on initial random allocation. All controls will perform the initial and 12 week assessments and are provided with usual 3 monthly clinical care. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>16 pre-pubertal individuals with CF form the same hospital clinical will be recruited exactly the same as the intervention subjects. This group will be involved in baseline line and  12 week follow-up assessments, but not perform the 12 WBVT intervention or 2 x 4 weekly reviews via teleheath. The control subjects will perform their routine daily physiotherapy and attend usual clinical scheduled appointments. This group then will form the comparator group as "usual care".</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lean body mass via DXA (LBM/ht2)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Each participant will have final measures taken within a week of completion of the 12 week program. Individuals will have a staggered commencement of the study between Jan- November 2017. Differences between the groups will be analysed at the completion of the intervention; to be expected in January 2018.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bone mineral density via, (1) dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry (DXA, areal BMD, gm/cm2) and (2) peripheral quantitative computed tomography (pQCT, gm/cm3).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Each participant will have final measures taken within a week of completion of the 12 week program. Individuals will have a staggered commencement of the study between Jan- November 2017. Differences between the groups will be analysed at the completion of the intervention; to be expected in January 2018.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>respiratory function via lung clearance index and respiratory function test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Each participant will have final measures taken within a week of completion of the 12 week program. Individuals will have a staggered commencement of the study between Jan- November 2017. Differences between the groups will be analysed at the completion of the intervention; to be expected in January 2018.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cystic Fibrosis Quality of Life Questionnaire-Revised (CFQ-R). 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Each participant will have final measures taken within a week of completion of the 12 week program. Individuals will have a staggered commencement of the study between Jan- November 2017. Differences between the groups will be analysed at the completion of the intervention; to be expected in January 2018.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>lower limb strength via vertical jump height</outcome>
      <timepoint>Each participant will have final measures taken within a week of completion of the 12 week program. Individuals will have a staggered commencement of the study between Jan- November 2017. Differences between the groups will be analysed at the completion of the intervention; to be expected in January 2018.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Core muscle physiology (pertaining to the external and internal obliques, and transverse abdominis), specifically the activation (contraction and relaxation) and size of the transverse abdominis via abdominal real time ultrasound.
 </outcome>
      <timepoint>Each participant will have final measures taken within a week of completion of the 12 week program. Individuals will have a staggered commencement of the study between Jan- November 2017. Differences between the groups will be analysed at the completion of the intervention; to be expected in January 2018.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>grip strength via hand held dynamometry </outcome>
      <timepoint>Each participant will have final measures taken within a week of completion of the 12 week program. Individuals will have a staggered commencement of the study between Jan- November 2017. Differences between the groups will be analysed at the completion of the intervention; to be expected in January 2018.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure of thoracic kyphosis, using the tragus to wall measurement, i.e., the distance of a subject standing upright against a wall to the tragus (part of the ear).  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Each participant will have final measures taken within a week of completion of the 12 week program. Individuals will have a staggered commencement of the study between Jan- November 2017. Differences between the groups will be analysed at the completion of the intervention; to be expected in January 2018.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>questionnaire for urinary continence diagnosis (QUID)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Each participant will have final measures taken within a week of completion of the 12 week program. Individuals will have a staggered commencement of the study between Jan- November 2017. Differences between the groups will be analysed at the completion of the intervention; to be expected in January 2018.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Young individuals registered with the CF respiratory clinic at Lady Cilento Children's Hospital, South Brisbane; confirmed diagnosis of cystic fibrosis; over 6 years of age; Pre-pubertal (Tanner stage 1); ability to attend regular clinical visits at LCCH every 4 weeks over the duration of the 12 week project; must have access to computer for the provision of telehealth.

Children of aboriginal and Torres Straight Islander descent are infrequently diagnosed with CF. However, if recruited, it is anticipated there will not be any concerns to the participation in the study as the outcomes measures do not relate to culture or descent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>12</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Primary bone disorder; pubertal (greater or equal to Tanner stage 2); non-English speaking; People with a disability or mental impairment </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>simple randomisation</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Pre-post t-test and Correlations (Primary outcome measure (dependent variable) = lean body mass) against secondary measures of bone parameters and respiratory function</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>6/03/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/07/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>32</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/01/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Lady Cilento Children's Hospital - South Brisbane</hospital>
    <postcode>4101 - South Brisbane</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Lady Cilento Children's Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>501 Stanley St, South Brisbane QLD 4101</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Queensland Government Health Practitioners Research Scheme </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Health
Allied Health Professions' Office of Queensland
PO Box 2368
Fortitude Valley BC Qld 4006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The University of Queensland</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>CCHR
62 Graham St
South Brisbane, QLD 4101</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>With increasing life expectancy of individuals with cystic fibrosis (CF), the musculoskeletal sequelae of this chronic disease results in an increased burden of management and demand on healthcare services. Bone mineral density deficits, with fragility fractures (osteoporosis) and, more recently, reduced muscle mass (sarcopenia), are recognised as a long term health concerns. Importantly, muscle mass has been shown as an independent predictor of bone accrual in individuals with CF.
Whole body vibration training (WBVT) has been shown to have a therapeutic impact on bone and muscle response in adults, and some paediatric cohorts, with CF. These data appear to support WBVT as an emerging therapeutic alternative for preventing/reversing sarcopenia and possibly osteoporosis. 
Efficient and novel models of service delivery are required to provide equitable, safe, and effective healthcare across extensive geographical regions of the state of Queensland. Telehealth provides a viable means of accessing specialist health services not available to consumers in their local areas. Queensland Health has recently provided infrastructure to support telehealth within regional facilities and homes, especially for chronic disease management. 
Our project aims to demonstrate the utility of telehealth-supported home treatments with WBVT via a model of service delivery which reduces travel time, costs, and negative impacts on quality of life(QOL), while providing an efficacious clinical intervention. 
A state-wide study of 32 pre-pubertal outpatients with CF, over 6 years of age, will be recruited to the study conducted over a 12-week period. Stratified randomisation will allocate the 32 subjects to either a control group or WBVT group. The control cohort (n=16) will continue their normal physiotherapy airway clearance regime. The WBVT cohort (n=16) will participate in the WBVT arm. Participants in the WBVT cohort will be reviewed either face-to-face or via telehealth at weeks 2,4,8 of their program. WBVT participants will perform a standardised WBVT program (20 minutes in duration), 5 times a week, in combination with their normal physiotherapy airway clearance regime. Outcome measures will be taken at weeks 0 and 12 of the program, and include primary outcome measures of lean body mass (LBM) via dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry (DXA), converted as an index (LBM/Ht2). Secondary outcome measures include Cystic Fibrosis Quality of Life Questionnaire-Revised (CFQ-R), Spirometry and Lung Clearance Index (LCI), muscle and bone parameters via DXA and peripheral Quantitative Computed Tomography (pQCT), vertical jump height, transversus abdominus real-time ultrasound, urinary continence and thoracic kyphosis measure.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Children’s Health Queensland  Human Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 7, Centre for Childrens Health Research
Lady Cilento Children's Hospital Precinct
62 Graham Street, South Brisbane  QLD  4101
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/02/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/QRCH/103AM01.     SSA/16/QRCH/364</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/07/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Elise Alexander</name>
      <address>7A Clinical Directorate
Level 7 
Lady Cilento Children's Hospital
South Brisbane 
QLD 4101</address>
      <phone>+61438170287</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>elise.alexander@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Denise Brookes</name>
      <address>Centre of Children's Health Research
Level 6, 62 Graham St
South Brisbane
QLD  4101</address>
      <phone>+61409053374</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.brookes@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Denise Brookes</name>
      <address>Centre of Children's Health Research
Level 6, 62 Graham St
South Brisbane
QLD  4101</address>
      <phone>+61409053374</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.brookes@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Elise Alexander</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>