<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366902">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/08/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/09/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000998640</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of Continuous Positive Airway Pressure Mask Systems: Comparison of Cushions, Frames, Headgear, Components and Accessories</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In Obstructive Sleep Apnea patients, do novel continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) masks, compared to commercially available CPAP masks, improve the subjective comfort, seal, stability, and general usability of CPAP therapy?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obstructive Sleep Apnea (OSA)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sleep apnoea</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A variety of unregistered prototype CPAP masks will be used as the intervention in this study. The number of intervention masks a participant may test will range from 1 to 2 masks. There will be no washout period between masks. CPAP masks may be full face, nasal, or nasal pillows masks (covering mouth and nose, covering nose only, or inserted into nostrils).

As this study protocol aims to facilitate the product development of CPAP masks (an iterative process), this protocol allows for a prototype mask to be designed, used as a trial intervention, improved based on patient feedback, and then retested again as trial intervention. This process may occur for several cycles. This particular protocol also allows for the testing of several different prototype masks. As such, the total number of intervention masks being evaluated under this protocol at the beginning of the study is unknown, but will reported at the completion of the study.

All CPAP masks will be used for a minimum of 3 nights and a maximum of 7 nights. Other than 'mask type' setting, patient's CPAP therapy settings will not be changed.

Adherence will be monitored through data downloads directly from the patient's device or SD card. Adherence may also be monitored through an approved wireless therapy monitoring system (EasyCare Online).
</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator for this study will be one or more of the following:
- commercially available, approved CPAP mask currently used by the patient
- commercially available, approved CPAP mask not currently used by the patient
- another unapproved CPAP mask

The number of intervention masks a participant may test will range from 1 to 2 masks. There will be no washout period between masks. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subjective mask comfort as assessed by patient questionnaire (ie. 11-point Likert scale designed for this protocol)</outcome>
      <timepoint>After maximum of 7 nights on CPAP mask</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subjective mask seal as assessed by patient questionnaire (ie. 11-point Likert scale designed for this protocol)</outcome>
      <timepoint>After a maximum of 7 nights on CPAP mask</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subjective mask stability as assessed by patient questionnaire (ie. 11-point Likert scale designed for this protocol)</outcome>
      <timepoint>After a maximum of 7 nights on CPAP mask</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Objective mask efficacy as assessed by CPAP device data</outcome>
      <timepoint>After a maximum of 7 nights on CPAP mask</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Objective mask leak as assessed by CPAP device data</outcome>
      <timepoint>After a maximum of 7 nights on CPAP mask</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Objective mask usage assessed by CPAP device data</outcome>
      <timepoint>After a maximum of 7 nights on CPAP mask</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Objective mask pressure as assessed by CPAP device data</outcome>
      <timepoint>After a maximum of 7 nights on CPAP mask</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome: Subjective general usability as assessed by patient questionnaire (ie. 11-point Likert scale designed for this protocol)</outcome>
      <timepoint>After a maximum of 7 nights of CPAP mask</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients willing to give written informed consent
Patients who are able to comprehend written and spoken English
Patients who have been diagnosed with OSA
Patients who are established CPAP therapy users
Patients who are at least 18 years of age
Patients who are using an appropriate current mask system and size for the particular study
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients who are not able to provide written informed consent
Patients who are unable to comprehend written and spoken English
Patients who are not using an appropriate current mask system and size for the particular study
Patients who are pregnant
Patients with a pre existing lung disease/ condition that would predispose them to pneumothorax (for example: COPD, lung cancer; fibrosis of the lungs; recent (&lt; 2years) case of pneumonia or lung infection; lung injury.
Patients who are unsuitable for inclusion in the opinion of the investigator
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation).</sequence>
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>8/12/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>23/03/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>ResMed Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>1 Elizabeth Macarthur Drive
Bella Vista
NSW 2153</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>ResMed Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1 Elizabeth Macarthur Drive
Bella Vista
NSW 2153</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Obstructive sleep apnoea (OSA) is characterised by a partial or complete collapse of the upper airway during sleep. Continuous Positive Airway Pressure (CPAP) therapy acts as a positive airway splint, delivering a fixed positive airway pressure to the upper airway via a tube and mask. CPAP compliance is strongly influenced by the patients mask system. As masks are worn every night the comfort, seal, stability and ease of use of a CPAP mask is highly important. The product development of mask systems is an iterative process. Evaluation of the comfort, seal, stability and ease of use of the mask system by patients in their home environment provides the required information for these iterative design changes. This project will allow the iterative testing of mask systems by patients by comparing them to already released masks or acceptable subjective levels.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>This study protocol aims to facilitate the product development of CPAP masks. As product development is an iterative process, this protocol allows for a prototype mask to be designed, used as a trial intervention, improved based on patient feedback, and then retested again as trial intervention. This process may occur for several cycles. This particular protocol also allows for the testing of several different prototype masks.

The sample size is the approximate sample size that will be recruited per prototype trial.</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>UNSW HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/10/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/08/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Klaus Schindhelm</name>
      <address>ResMed Ltd
1 Elizabeth Macarthur Drive
Bella Vista
NSW 2153</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8884 1000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>klaus.schindhelm@resmed.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Sahisha Ketheeswaran</name>
      <address>ResMed Ltd
1 Elizabeth Macarthur Drive
Bella Vista
NSW 2153</address>
      <phone>+61 2  8884 1000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sahisha.ketheeswaran@resmed.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Sahisha Ketheeswaran</name>
      <address>ResMed Ltd
1 Elizabeth Macarthur Drive
Bella Vista
NSW 2153</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8884 1000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sahisha.ketheeswaran@resmed.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>