<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368865">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/10/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/10/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001121550p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Effect of Diet and Nutritional Supplementation on Behaviour, Quantitative Electroencephalography (QEEG) and Cognitive Functioning in Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Effect of Diet and Nutritional Supplementation on Behaviour, Quantitative Electroencephalography (QEEG) and Cognitive Functioning in Children with Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1173-6767</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The first appointment involved in the trial is with Dr Jacques Duff. He will explain the dietary and nutritional supplementation requirements of the study to parents of participants and answer any questions they may have about the treatment protocol. Dr Duff is a Registered Psychologist and also Neuroscientist and Nutritionist. Participants will be asked to not start their child on the diet and supplements until after their next visit (where all baseline testing will take place). He will also provide parents with a kit and instructions on how to collect a faecal sample from your child that will be sent by courier to Bioscreen Medical for analysis. 

Please see the attached nutrition form for details about the administration and dosage requirements for the nutritional supplements in the study.

The 6 month dietary alteration period eliminates all additives, preservatives, food colourings, gluten (in particular wheat), dairy products, cereal grains, excess sugar and refined carbohydrates. Patients are encouraged to eat more fish, fruit, vegetables, legumes, pulses and selenium containing foods (e.g., Brazil nuts). They are also encouraged to eat eggs, beef, free range chicken and goats meat in moderation. The nutritional supplementation includes Fish oils, zinc citrate, vitamin E, magnesium, cognisense, vitamin C and vitamin D3.

As outlined in the Information to Participants in Research document, dietary compliance will be monitored by at each of the bimonthly appointments at the clinic and by parents via a monthly diary which will be made available either online or hard copy. </interventions>
    <comparator>The proposed study will not be using a control group. All participants baseline scores will be compared at a 6 month follow up assessment.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 1: Quantitative Electroencephalography (QEEG) observed changes in Theta power. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: Baseline and at 6 month follow up.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 2: Changes in Faecal Microbial Analysis results (including count of bacteria such as Streptococcus, E.coli and Enterococcus).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: Baseline and at 6 month follow up.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 3: Mean score changes on the Test of Variables of Attention.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 6 month follow up.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 1: Actigraphy (using an Actiwatch) measuring sleep efficiency.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: Baseline and at 6 month follow up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 2: Inattention, hyperactivity/impulsivity, learning problems, executive functioning, aggression, and peer relations assessed by Conners Rating Scales, 3rd Edition.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: Baseline and at 6 month follow up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 3: ADHD Rating Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: Baseline and at 6 month follow up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 4: Diet Compliance, made available online or hard copy for parents to complete on a monthly basis..</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: Baseline and at one month intervals for a period of 6 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 5: Test of Everyday Attention for Children subtests.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: Baseline and at 6 month follow up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome - Quantitative Electroencephalography (QEEG) observed changes in Delta power.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 6 month follow up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome - Quantitative Electroencephalography (QEEG) observed changes in Beta power.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 6 month follow up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome - Quantitative Electroencephalography (QEEG) observed changes in Alpha power.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 6 month follow up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be required to have a diagnosis of Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) according to the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, Fifth Edition (DSM-5). People with ADHD display persistent patterns of inattention and/or hyperactivity-impulsivity that interferes with functioning or development.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>13</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>No significant co-morbidities (for example a diagnosis of autism or depression as well as ADHD).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>All participants will be allocated to the treatment group.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>After parental consent is obtained participants will be asked to attend 6 visits at the Behavioural Neurotherapy clinic across six months for this study. At the first clinic appointment the treatment regime (diet and nutritional supplements - details provided in Step 3 - Intervention/Exposure of this application) will be explained by clinician Dr Jacques Duff. This appointment will take 60 minutes. Parents will be asked not to begin the diet/nutrition intervention until after baseline evaluations have been completed (at the next session). The Bioscreen FMA kit will also be provided at this initial
appointment, to be taken and sent to Bioscreen Medical for analysis on the morning of their baseline evaluation session. Please refer to the attached FMA procedure protocol for detailas regarding the collection of the faecal sample.
The second visit will take place within 14 days of the fist visit, and this is when baseline evaluations will take place. In reality we will attempt to arrange the second appointment as quickly as possible after the first so that the treatment can begin with minimum delay. This is only restricted by parent availability. This session will include QEEG (45-60 minutes) followed by cognitive testing (TOVA and selected subtests of the TEA-Ch) (45-60 minutes).
Subsequent to the baseline evaluation, the 6 month dietary alteration and nutritional supplementation period will commence. Once the 6 month dietary and nutritional intervention has begun, parents will be requested to make 3 appointments (once every 8 weeks) at the Behavioural Neurotherapy Clinic with Dr Jacques Duff for treatment monitoring. Dr. Duff will discuss diet compliance (participants will also be given a short dietary compliance questionnaire to complete) and any challenges participants may be facing throughout the treatment period at these appointments. The post-treatment evaluation will occur after the 6 month protocol. This follow up assessment will include the same evaluations as the baseline After this session participation in the study will cease. Should patients wish to continue to see Dr Duff then this would be done at their own volition and under the usual fee structure.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Practical, financial and statistical considerations have been taken into account regarding the selection of 30 participants for this study. The study will help provide useful information regarding the outcome measures used, including effect sizes that will be useful in informing future studies. Therefore it is considered a feasibility study for future clinical trials.

Power analysis for the combined total group (analysis conducted on G*Power 3.1) show that with a sample size of 30 (alpha = .05,
power = 0.8) large effect sizes will achieve significance using a variety of tests: t-tests difference between two dependent means
(dz = 0.5) and Wilcoxon non-parametric test (dz = 0.5).

These analyses will be used to explore differences in cognitive results, QEEG, questionnaires and actigraphy data due to dietary alterations and nutritional supplementation in the data collected from the two evaluations.

Stool samples will be analysed using the FMA test. This analysis uses a stool sample to culture, identify and quantify faecal bacteria with a focus on anaerobic and aerobic microflora and yeasts. Participants will be categorized as to their response to specific microbiota. Inferential statistics as outlined above will also be used to explore these changes. Past investigations using FMA in a different population suggest that this data may not be normally distributed, in which case noninferential statistics (e.g. Mann Whitney test) will be used.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/11/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>27/05/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Victoria University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Ballarat Road, Footscray, VIC, 3011</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Autism ADHD Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>2/314 Manningham Rd Doncaster VIC 3108 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There is now a growing amount of research supporting the notion of communication between gut microbiota (microorganisms; e.g. ecoli, streptococcus) and the central nervous system (CNS) (known as the brain-gut axis). According to Cryan and Dinan (2012) communication between the gut and CNS may be occurring through neural, endocrine and immune pathways indicating the possibility of alterations to gut microbiota as a form of therapy for treatment of CNS related disorders. According to a review by Kidd (2000) integrative
treatments such as correction of intestinal dysbiosis, nutritional supplementation and dietary modifications can be a successful way to help children with ADHD reduce symptoms and move towards a productive and normal life. A review by Stevens, Kuczek, Burgess, Hurt, and Arnold (2011) states that there are a number of studies that have found encouraging results in ADHD children following an elimination diet (Pelsser et al., 2011; Pelsser et al., 2009) and diets challenging with or removing any artificial food dyes (Bateman et al., 2004; McCann et al., 2007). This review supported the use of dietary interventions in at least subpopulations of ADHD children, concluding diets that removed artificial colours significantly improve symptoms that return when challenged (Stevens et al., 2011). These authors also concluded that elimination diets would be an appropriate intervention for children who have not responded satisfactorily to traditional treatment. Moreover, Villagomez and Ramtekkar (2014) concluded that the use of nutritional supplementation in children with ADHD may be a justified and importantly safe intervention, where a number of studies have observed improvements in ADHD related symptomatology following nutritional supplementation (Bilici et al., 2004; Harding, Judah,&amp; Gant, 2003; Hawkey &amp; Nigg, 2014; Huss, Volp, &amp; StaussGrabo, 2010). Further, due to the understanding of the microbiomes connection to neurodevelopment, it is compelling to consider the role it is likely to play in disorders such as ADHD (Theije et al., 2014). Unlike autism spectrum disorders (ASDs), there have been no studies investigating the microbial composition and status of ADHD children, which could help provide some important insights into the effects of food or food allergy on behaviour (Theije et al., 2014). 

Previously no study has investigated the effects of diet and nutrition upon psychological functioning (cognition, brain activity, and sleep), together with gut microbial composition in this population. This is important because investigations of gut composition have to date largely been ignored in children with ADHD (Theije et al., 2014) and this information could be used as an important indicator to guide clinical decisions on an individualised level. Although this study is applying a standardised protocol in the interests of experimental control, this information could still be important for future individualized treatments.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Victoria University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ballarat Road, Footscray, VIC, 3011.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/09/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368865-ADHD Consent Form final 1.docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368865-ADHD Participant Info final.docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368865-Test ProceduresFinal.docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368865-ADHD References.docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368865-ADHD Advertisement.docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368865-Section 7 Supplement Attachment.docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368865-Updated Nutrition Form JH2.docx</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michelle Ball</name>
      <address>Victoria University, Ballarat Road, Footscray, VIC, 3011</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9919 2536</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michelle.ball@vu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Jordan Hince</name>
      <address>Victoria University, Ballarat Road, Footscray VIC 3011</address>
      <phone>+61 433 641 687</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jordan.hince@live.vu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michelle Ball</name>
      <address>Victoria University, Ballarat Road, Footscray, VIC, 3011
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9919 2536</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michelle.ball@vu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Jordan Hince</name>
      <address>Victoria University, Ballarat Road, Footscray VIC 3011</address>
      <phone>+61 433 641 687</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jordan.hince@live.vu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>