<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371075">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/09/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/09/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001232426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Post-operative exercise training for peripheral arterial disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Targeting microvascular impairment in patients with peripheral arterial disease: efficacy of lower limb revascularisation combined with supervised exercise therapy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Peripheral arterial disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Standard post-operative care plus supervised exercise therapy

The revascularisation intervention will be delivered by vascular surgeons at Nambour General Hospital. Revascularisation performed on the participant includes both open surgery and endovascular procedures. This will be personalised to each participant as considered necessary for optimal treatment by the vascular surgeon.
Following revascularisation, all patients will receive standard care that is based on international PAD management guidelines, including educational material with an emphasis on physical activity, smoking, and diet (Norgren et al. 2007). The vascular surgeon and the general practitioner of each participant will be sent a letter immediately after revascularisation and at 6-10 weeks after revascularisation, requesting that they adhere to clinical guidelines and targets (Norgren et al. 2007) (which will be outlined) so that all patients receive standardised care. 
Patients allocated to the exercise intervention group will undergo an 8-week supervised exercise training program, commencing within six weeks after the revascularisation procedure (within two to six weeks post-revascularisation, depending on the vascular procedure completed and clearance to commence the study intervention by the patients vascular surgeon). 
The exercise therapy intervention will be supervised by researchers (accredited physical therapists) at the University of the Sunshine Coast. Patients will attend group exercise sessions (3 sessions per week on non-consecutive days). Each session will include a combination of treadmill-walking and plantar-flexion exercise (both legs) as per recommended guidelines (Askew et al. 2014). Treadmill walking will consist of 20 min of intermittent walking that will be progressively increased in duration from 2.5 min in the first week, to 10 min in the last. Patients will walk at an intensity corresponding to the onset of mild-moderate claudication (e.g. 3-4 out of 5 in the claudication rating scale, where 0 = no pain and 5 = maximum pain). After the walking training, each patient will perform plantar flexion exercise using an isometric plantar flexion dynamometer. Participants will be seated with their hip and knee flexed, and with their foot resting on a foot-plate, and will perform three bouts of 5-min unilateral isometric contractions (2 s contraction: 3 s recovery) with each leg. Plantar-flexion exercise will be progressively increased in intensity from 40% of patients maximal force in the first week, to 70% of their maximal force in the last. 
Adherence to the supervised exercise therapy will be recorded by the investigators responsible for the delivery as the total number of visits recorded. Efforts to improve exercise adherence include group exercise sessions. If participants are unable to complete a bout of exercise they will be offered a 30 second rest period and the opportunity to complete the bout after the rest. Patients will be required to attend at least 85% of sessions (=21 sessions) for successful completion of the supervised exercise program. </interventions>
    <comparator>Standard post-operative care and monitoring (standard care)

The revascularisation intervention will be delivered by vascular surgeons at Nambour General Hospital. Revascularisation performed on the participant includes both open surgery and endovascular procedures. This will be personalised to each participant as considered necessary for optimal treatment by the vascular surgeon.
Following revascularisation, all patients will receive standard care that is based on international PAD management guidelines, including educational material with an emphasis on physical activity, smoking, and diet (Norgren et al. 2007). The vascular surgeon and the general practitioner of each participant will be sent a letter immediately after revascularisation and at 6-10 weeks after revascularisation, requesting that they adhere to clinical guidelines and targets (Norgren et al. 2007) (which will be outlined) so that all patients receive standardised care. 
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Walking capacity (6 minute walking distance) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcome measurements will be performed at baseline prior to revascularisation, then repeated following full recovery from revascularisation (2-6 weeks post-procedure), and then again at the completion of the 8 week post-operative intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Calf muscle microvascular blood flow (using contrast-enhanced ultrasound [CEU])</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcome measurements will be performed at baseline prior to revascularisation, then repeated following full recovery from revascularisation (2-6 weeks post-procedure), and then again at the completion of the 8 week post-operative intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Leg muscle function (plantar-flexion strength and fatigue) measured with an isometric plantar flexion dynamometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcome measurements will be performed at baseline prior to revascularisation, then repeated following full recovery from revascularisation (2-6 weeks post-procedure), and then again at the completion of the 8 week post-operative intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ankle brachial index</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcome measurements will be performed at baseline prior to revascularisation, then repeated following full recovery from revascularisation (2-6 weeks post-procedure), and then again at the completion of the 8 week post-operative intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Arterial stiffness (augumentation index and carotid-femoral pulse wave velocity) measured using the Sphygmocor XCEL system (Atcor, NSW, Australia).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcome measurements will be performed at baseline prior to revascularisation, then repeated following full recovery from revascularisation (2-6 weeks post-procedure), and then again at the completion of the 8 week post-operative intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Brachial and femoral artery function (flow mediated dilation)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcome measurements will be performed at baseline prior to revascularisation, then repeated following full recovery from revascularisation (2-6 weeks post-procedure), and then again at the completion of the 8 week post-operative intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resting and exercise leg blood flow (using venous occlusion plethysmography [VOP])</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcome measurements will be performed at baseline prior to revascularisation, then repeated following full recovery from revascularisation (2-6 weeks post-procedure), and then again at the completion of the 8 week post-operative intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self reported walking impairment  (Walking Impairment questionnaire)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcome measurements will be performed at baseline prior to revascularisation, then repeated following full recovery from revascularisation (2-6 weeks post-procedure), and then again at the completion of the 8 week post-operative intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life (measured using SF-36 questionnaire)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcome measurements will be performed at baseline prior to revascularisation, then repeated following full recovery from revascularisation (2-6 weeks post-procedure), and then again at the completion of the 8 week post-operative intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Patients scheduled for lower limb revascularisation, including open surgery (e.g. bypass), an endovascular procedure, or a hybrid procedure (e.g. endarterectomy plus angioplasty);
2. Documented diagnosis of PAD based on symptoms (claudication or critical limb ischaemia), an ABI &lt; 0.90, and imaging evidence of a significant (&gt;50%) stenosis in at least one lower-limb arterial segment;
3. Stable medication and treatment regimen (&gt;3 months); 
4. Physician-assessed ability to undertake the intervention and exercise testing. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>90</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Not able to walk independently prior to revascularisation, or walking capacity is limited by symptoms not related to PAD (including neuropathy); 
2.	Have had or are undergoing a significant amputation (e.g. forefoot, leg) that is expected to limit ability to walk independently after surgery; 
3.	Exercise testing is contraindicated for reasons such as unstable angina, uncontrolled hypertension (&gt;160/100), limiting venous disease or uncontrolled cardiac dysrhythmias;
4.	Current or planned involvement in a supervised exercise rehabilitation program. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A recruitment coordinator will oversee the screening, recruitment and blinded-randomisation of participants. Where possible, investigators and those collecting and analysing outcome data will be blinded to the treatment allocation at the time of randomisation and throughout the study. Participants will be stratified according to the type of intervention (endovascular or open surgery/hybrid).  Randomisation will occur following revascularisation using a concealed envelope system.  </concealment>
    <sequence>Block randomisation, using random block sizes will be used to ensure that group allocation at any point in time remains similar. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>We hypothesise that participants will improve their 6-min walking distance by 50+/-50m with revascularisation (Stefanovic 2012), that there will be no further change with ongoing standard care, and a further 60+/-50m increase in the exercise-therapy group (effects size aprox. 1.2). This is similar to the effect we have observed with exercise following revascularisation in a previous study (Stefanovic 2012). We require 15 participants per group (power 90%, alpha 0.05, 1:1) to detect the hypothesised increase in walking capacity with post operative exercise therapy.
Assessment of combined therapy versus revascularisation outcomes (group x time interactions) will be determined using linear repeated measures mixed models. Covariates will be included as appropriate, including hypothesised confounders (e.g. age, gender, diabetes) and any outcomes where there is a significant group difference at baseline. Linear regression will be performed to determine the relationships between baseline values and changes in primary and secondary outcomes. Analysis of all outcomes will be undertaken on an intention-to-treat basis. In addition, for secondary variables, we will undertake per-treatment analysis using complete data-sets.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/10/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>4/08/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/04/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>1</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/06/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Nambour General Hospital - Nambour</hospital>
    <hospital>Sunshine Coast University Hospital - Birtinya</hospital>
    <postcode>4560 - Nambour</postcode>
    <postcode>4575 - Birtinya</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of the Sunshine Coast</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>90 Sippy Downs Dr, Sippy Downs QLD 4556</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of the Sunshine Coast</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>90 Sippy Downs Dr, Sippy Downs QLD 4556</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Peripheral Arterial Disease (PAD) is characterised by blockages in the large arteries of the lower limbs. Chronic reductions in leg blood flow leads to microvascular impairment, including a reduction in muscle capillary density. These macro and microvascular impairments are independently associated with a severe reduction in functional (walking) ability. Patients are limited during daily activities by leg muscle pain and discomfort (claudication), and many develop signs of severe critical ischaemia, including rest-pain, tissue ulceration and gangrene. Lower limb revascularization procedures improve claudication symptoms by improving limb blood flow, but do not address the microvascular impairment, and do not fully restore functional capacity. However, when revascularisation procedures are combined with exercise therapy, greater gains are made in functional capacity without further change in large-artery blood flow. Based on evidence that supervised exercise therapy induces skeletal muscle capillary growth, and gains in functional capacity are related to increased muscle capillarisation, we hypothesise that the combination of revascularization plus post-operative supervised exercise therapy will lead to further improvements in outcomes (e.g. exercise tolerance and skeletal muscle microcirculation) compared to revascularisation alone. Therefore, this study aims to compare the efficacy of lower limb revascularisation plus supervised exercise therapy, with revascularisation alone, for improvement of walking capacity and skeletal muscle blood flow in PAD patients. This study will be conducted at the University of Sunshine Coast and the Department of Cardiology at Nambour General Hospital. Patients with PAD and symptoms of intermittent claudication, who are scheduled to undergo lower limb revascularisation, will be randomly assigned to one of two interventions at study entry: (1) standard post-operative care and monitoring (standard care) or (2) standard post-operative care plus an 8-week supervised exercise therapy program. Primary outcome measures will include walking capacity (6 minute walking distance) and calf muscle microvascular blood flow (using contrast-enhanced ultrasound [CEU]). Secondary outcomes will include i) leg muscle function (plantar-flexion strength and fatigue), ii) ankle brachial index, iii) arterial stiffness (augumentation index and carotid-femoral pulse wave velocity), iv) brachial and femoral artery function (flow mediated dilation) and v) leg blood flow (using venous occlusion plethysmography [VOP]). All parameters will be assessed in the limb undergoing revascularisation. Outcome measurements will be performed at baseline prior to revascularisation, then repeated following full recovery from revascularisation (2-6 weeks post-procedure), and then again at the completion of the 8 week post-operative intervention.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://www.surveymonkey.com/r/vasoactive

http://www.usc.edu.au/explore/structure/faculty-of-science-health-education-and-engineering/staff/associate-professor-chris-askew



</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Prince Charles Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>627 Rode Rd, Chermside QLD 4032   


</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/07/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/QPCH/148</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/05/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Christopher Askew</name>
      <address>University of the Sunshine Coast
90 Sippy Downs Dr, Sippy Downs QLD 4556
</address>
      <phone>+61 7 5456 5961</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>caskew@usc.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Christopher Askew</name>
      <address>University of the Sunshine Coast
90 Sippy Downs Dr, Sippy Downs QLD 4556</address>
      <phone>+61 7 5456 5961</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>caskew@usc.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Christopher Askew</name>
      <address>University of the Sunshine Coast
90 Sippy Downs Dr, Sippy Downs QLD 4556</address>
      <phone>+61 7 5456 5961</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>caskew@usc.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Christopher Askew</name>
      <address>University of the Sunshine Coast
90 Sippy Downs Dr, Sippy Downs QLD 4556</address>
      <phone>+61 7 5456 5961</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>caskew@usc.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>