<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370103">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/11/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/11/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001641482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Tobacco Harm Reduction with Vaporised Nicotine (THRiVe): Feasibility Study </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Tobacco Harm Reduction with Vaporised Nicotine (THRiVe): An uncontrolled feasibility study of novel nicotine replacement products among people living with HIV (PLHIV) who smoke  </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1179-4374</utrn>
    <trialacronym>THRiVe: Feasibility Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NONE</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Tobacco Addiction</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Smoking</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Acquired immune deficiency syndrome (AIDS / HIV)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study is an uncontrolled study of a harm reduction intervention, using vaporised nicotine in people living with HIV who smoke cigarettes. 
Participants will receive two study devices (Innokin Endura T18, and Innokin Endura T22) each device is a type of vaporised nicotine product that deliver the study medicine (Nicophar brand nicotine liquid, containing; 1.2% nicotine, 82.8% glycerol and water 16%) to use over a 12 week treatment period and asked to replace as many cigarettes as possible (if not all) with use of the vaporised nicotine products (VNPs). Participants are free to use both devices interchangeably or only one based on their own own personal preference over the 12 week treatment period. The study will investigate they way people use the VNPs and what they think of the devices and people use the VNPs based on their needs and preferences, adherence is therefore not measured in this study. 

Participants will receive 10 x 10mL bottles of e-liquid for every four-week period to use. This concentration is in common use and recommended by the manufacturer as the most appropriate strength to be used with the Innokin Endura devices.

The device administers the liquid nicotine to reduce tobacco withdrawal symptoms, such as craving cigarettes (similar to other fast acting NRT products). The frequency with which the device (and its liquid nicotine) is used is therefore dependent on the user's level of nicotine dependence. Literature suggests people who use vaporised nicotine self-titrate, similar to their self-titration of tobacco cigarettes or NRT products. 

Participants will  also receive an 'intervention pack' containing;
a. A list of participant instructions
b. A Positively Quitting booklet designed to help people living with HIV to quit smoking (this booklet was developed by and available from Queensland Positive People, a peer-based advocacy organisation for people living with HIV.
c. Information on using the devices instead of smoking instructions on how to use, store and handle the investigational products
d. Copies of device user manuals
e. Links and information on quitting supports (such as Quitline)
f. A study wallet card to confirm participation in trial

</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acceptability of the novel vaporised nicotine products (Innokin Endura T18 and Innokin Endura T22) and an e-liquid (containing 12mg/mL of nicotine in vegetable glycerol and water) for quitting smoking or reducing the number of cigarettes smoked per day, among people living with HIV who smoke 5 or more cigarettes per day.

Acceptability will be measured using a combination of both quantitative survey items (using a number of formats such as yes/no, multiple choice and likert scales) and semi-structured interviews. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Quantitative survey items: Baseline and weeks; 4, 8, 12, 24
Interviews: Baseline and week 12 </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participant use of novel vaporised nicotine products (Innokin Endura T18 and Innokin Endura T22) and an e-liquid (containing 12mg/mL of nicotine in vegetable glycerol and water) for quitting smoking or reducing the number of cigarettes smoked per day, among people living with HIV who smoke 5 or more cigarettes per day.
Use (i.e. which product/s were used and details of use, for example where use occurred) will be measured using a combination of both quantitative survey items (using a number of formats such as yes/no, multiple choice and likert scales) and semi-structured interviews. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Quantitative survey items: Baseline and weeks; 4, 8, 12, 24
Interview: Baseline and week 12 </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of quit attempts. 
The number of quit attempts made between each major contact point will be measured using participant self report, to forced choice survey items (for example "Since you completed the week 4 survey for us, have you made a quit attempt"). The number of quit attempts and length of the longest quit attempt will also be measured in participants who report having made a quit attempt.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 4, 8, 12, 24 post treatment initiation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Short-term abstinence (7-day abstinence) from tobacco cigarettes will be measured using a series of self-report survey items designed for the study. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and weeks 4, 8, 12 and 24 post treatment initiation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Medium-term abstinence (continuous, abstinence from tobacco smoking for at least 8 weeks)  will be measured using a series of self-report survey items designed for the study. </outcome>
      <timepoint>12 and 24 weeks post treatment initiation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feedback on the information packs (which included information on the nicotine vaporisers) provided to participants will be collected during the semi-structured interview at week 12. </outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks (end of treatment). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Whether participation influences quitting motivation, measured using quantitative survey items designed for the study. 


</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and week 12 post treatment initiation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Whether participants using the study devices and medicine can reduce tobacco smoking will be measured using the self-reported average of number of cigarettes smoked per day at each survey point. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and weeks 4, 8, 12 and 24 post treatment initiation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Whether participation influences level of knowledge of health impacts of smoking, measured using quantitative survey items designed for the study to measure participants' knowledge of harm from smoking. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and week 12 post treatment initiation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Whether participation influences quit self-efficacy, measured using quantitative survey items designed for the study. 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and week 12 post treatment initiation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Whether participation influences level of nicotine dependence measured using the Fagerstrom Test for Nicotine Dependence and the Glover-Nilsson Smoking Behavioural Questionnaire. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and week 12 post treatment initiation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	A diagnosis of HIV
2.	Aged 18 years (or over)
3.	Smoke 5 (or more) cigarettes per day, at the time of enrolment into the trial
4.	Have been smoking for at least 12 months  
5.	Have capacity to consent and able to understand study instructions and procedures (e.g. sufficient English language ability).
6.	Willing to attempt to quit tobacco smoking within 1 week of enrolment  
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Currently participating in a smoking-cessation program 
2.	Aged &lt;18 years 
3.	Currently pregnant, measured by self-report, with confirmation by self-administered pregnancy test where there is doubt, or planning to become pregnant during trial participation period
4.	Currently breast-feeding (measured by self-report) or planning to be during trial participation period
5.	Insufficient capacity to provide informed consent or complete the study requirements (e.g. completing surveys in English)
6.	Has experienced chest pain, or another cardiovascular event or procedure (e.g. heart attack, stroke, insertion of stent, bypass surgery) in the last month
7.	Being treated with oxygen therapy.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Not applicable. </concealment>
    <sequence>Not applicable. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Survey data will be analysed using descriptive statistics (counts and percentages). 

Interview data will be analysed qualitatively using thematic analysis. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>9/01/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>21/02/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>15/05/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>15/05/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>30</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/10/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <postcode>4102 - Woolloongabba</postcode>
    <postcode>4000 - Brisbane City</postcode>
    <postcode>4169 - East Brisbane</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Queensland
Brisbane QLD 4072 Australia
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>HIV Foundation Queensland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
725 Ann Street
Fortitude Valley
Brisbane QLD 4006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There is mounting evidence of widespread use of vaporised nicotine products (VNPs) among the general population of smokers. There is also evidence of their effectiveness at achieving short-term cessation with few reported side effects, although limited long term efficacy and safety data is available. VNPs may offer a harm reduction approach to tobacco in populations such as people living with HIV who have high rates of smoking and experience significant associated health consequences. This study will examine whether such products that deliver liquid nicotine are acceptable to people living with HIV who smoke and whether a larger, randomised controlled trial to assess long-term cessation outcomes and relapse prevention would be feasible. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Recruitment to the study includes both self-referring participants and via three study site: 
1. Princess Alexandra Sexual Health at the  Princess Alexandra Hospital ( Metro South Hospital and Health Service)
2. Metro North Sexual Health and HIV Service based at the Biala City Community Health Centre (Metro North Hospital and Health Service) 
3. Queensland Positive People at East Brisbane</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Metro South HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PAH Centres for Health Research
Level 7, Translational Research Institute
37 Kent Street
Woolloongabba QLD 4102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/11/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/QPAH/693</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/10/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Queensland’s Human Research Ethics Committees A &amp; B</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Cumbrae-Stewart Building #72
The University of Queensland
St Lucia, QLD 4072</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/01/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016001749 / HREC/16/QPAH/693</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Coral Gartner</name>
      <address>School of Public Health The University of Queensland Public Health Building
Herston Road Herston Qld 4006</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3346 5478</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3365 5442</fax>
      <email>c.gartner@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Stephanie Bell </name>
      <address>School of Public Health The University of Queensland Public Health Building
Herston Road Herston Qld 4006</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3346 5473</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.bell@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Stephanie Bell </name>
      <address>School of Public Health The University of Queensland Public Health Building
Herston Road Herston Qld 4006</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3346 5473</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.bell@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Stephanie Bell </name>
      <address>School of Public Health The University of Queensland Public Health Building
Herston Road Herston Qld 4006</address>
      <phone>07 33465473</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.bell@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>