<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343057">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/06/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/06/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000609954</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can nitrate-rich green leafy vegetables lower blood pressure?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Can nitrate-rich green leafy vegetables lower blood pressure in men and women with high-normal blood pressure?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Blood pressure</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Vascular function</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Hypertension</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A randomised, controlled, cross-over design trial will be performed.

Trial periods
1.	Run-in (washout) period: 1 week. 
All participants will begin the trial consuming a low nitrate/low green leafy vegetable (usual) diet (containing less than ~100 mg/d of nitrate). 

2.	First intervention period: 1 week. 
Participants will then either: continue on the low nitrate diet; or increase the intake of green leafy vegetables resulting in an estimated nitrate intake of greater than 400 mg/d.

3.	 Washout period: 1 week. 
As for 1 above

4.	 Second intervention period: 1 week. 
As for 2 above

The order of the two interventions (low nitrate; high nitrate) will be randomized.


Diets
1.	The low nitrate (usual) diet will involve reducing green leafy vegetables as well as a limited number of other foods rich in nitrate (beetroot, celery, parsley) in the diet, but only if this is required to limit nitrate intake to less than ~100 mg/d. The average nitrate intake in Western populations is often well under 100 mg/d, so for most participants there will be minimal change to their diet and nitrate intake; and

2.	The high nitrate diet will involve adding green leafy vegetables to the diet. Leafy greens added to the diet will include: spinach (dried and powdered, fresh and frozen); lettuce (all types); rocket; and Chinese greens (such as bok choy; choy sum, Chinese cabbage). To enhance compliance participants will be provided with all intervention foods (frozen and fresh).The objective will be to include at least 300 g/d of green leafy vegetables into the diet, increasing estimated nitrate intake to greater than 400 mg/d. A dietitian will provide individual advice on how to include the green leafy vegetables without altering energy or macronutrient intakes.</interventions>
    <comparator>Low nitrate diet</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure: ambulatory blood pressure assessed using a Spacelabs monitor (Spacelabs Medical Inc. Redmond, WA, USA)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at the end of each 1 week washout and intervention period as 10-hour day time ambulatory blood pressure, with blood pressure and heart rate measured every 20 minutes.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure: home monitored blood pressure assessed using an A&amp;D home blood pressure monitor</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured twice daily thoughout the entire study period</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Vascular function  assessed as arterial pulse wave velocity using the SphygmoCor CPV system</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at the end of each 1 week washout and intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood plasma and saliva nitrogen oxides and related compounds.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at the end of each 1 week washout and intervention period and 48 hour after the end of each 1 week intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Biomarkers of inflammation such as HS-CRP assessed using routine methods and oxidative stress assessed by measuring plasma isoprostanes using GC-MS</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at the end of each 1 week washout and intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Men and women aged 20 to 70 years with high-normal blood pressure (systolic blood pressure 120-139 mm Hg or diastolic blood pressure 80-89 mm Hg)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Use of antihypertensive medication; systolic blood pressure &lt; 120 mm Hg or &gt; 139 mm Hg and diastolic blood pressure &lt;80 mm Hg or &gt;89 mm Hg;  a diet high in green leafy vegetables; use of antibacterial mouth wash (which kills bacteria responsible for nitrate reduction in the mouth); use of antibiotics (within previous 2 months); current or recent (&lt;12 months) smoking; history of cardiovascular or peripheral vascular disease; recent history of a psychiatric illness or other major illnesses such as cancer; recent history of asthma, renal, liver or gastrointestinal disease, or gout; a change in drug therapy within the previous 3 months, or the likelihood that drug therapy would change during the study; current or recent (within previous 6 months) significant weight loss or gain (&gt; 6% of body weight); alcohol intake &gt; 140 g per wk; reported participation in night shift work during the study period; and inability or unwillingness to follow the study protocol.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The treatment order for eligible individuals will be randomly assigned using computer generated random numbers. The treatment order allocation will be sealed in numbered envelopes. The envelopes will be used for randomisation by opening an envelope, in consecutive order, as participants are entered into the study. The envelopes will be held by an independent person within the University of Western Australia. The study coordinator will contact the independent person to obtain the next available envelope once an individual is deemed eligible. The envelope will be opened and the code will be recorded.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer-generated random numbers using Microsoft Excel</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>27/06/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>27/06/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>15/08/2012</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>15/08/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>38</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Western Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Western Australia, 35 Stirling Highway, Crawley, WA 6009</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council, GPO Box 1421, Canberra, ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary objective of this study is to determine if regular consumption of nitrate-rich green leafy vegetables can reduce blood pressure in men and women with high-normal blood pressure. We will also investigate the claim that dietary nitrate contributes to the bodys NO stores and that these stores represent a physiologically relevant reservoir of NO.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Bondonno CP, Liu AH, Croft KD, Ward NC, Yang X, Considine MJ, Puddey IB, Woodman RJ, Hodgson JM. Short-term effects of nitrate-rich green leafy vegetables on blood pressure and arterial stiffness in individuals with high-normal blood pressure. Free Rad Biol Med 2014; 77:353-362. </publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Westren Australia Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The University of Western Australia, 35 Stirling Highway, Crawley, WA 6009</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/04/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>RA/4/4669</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Jonathan Hodgson</name>
      <address>UWA School of Medicine and Pharmacology, GPO Box X2213, Perth, WA 6847</address>
      <phone>61 (0)8 9224 0267</phone>
      <fax>61 (0)8 9224 0246</fax>
      <email>Jonathan.Hodgson@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Jonathan Hodgson</name>
      <address>UWA School of Medicine and Pharmacology, GPO Box X2213, Perth, WA 6847</address>
      <phone>61 (0)8 9224 0267</phone>
      <fax>61 (0)8 9224 0246</fax>
      <email>Jonathan.Hodgson@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Jonathan Hodgson</name>
      <address>UWA School of Medicine and Pharmacology, GPO Box X2213, Perth, WA 6847</address>
      <phone>61 (0)8 9224 0267</phone>
      <fax>61 (0)8 9224 0246</fax>
      <email>Jonathan.Hodgson@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Jonathan Hodgson</name>
      <address>UWA School of Medicine and Pharmacology, GPO Box X2213, Perth, WA 6847</address>
      <phone>61 (0)8 9224 0267</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Jonathan.Hodgson@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>