<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365921">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/03/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/03/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000297628</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Treatment Approaches for Children and Young people in Child and Adolescent Mental Health Services (CAMHS) Study: Comparing the Modular Approach to Therapy for Children (MATCH-ADTC) with usual care in improving clinical outcomes of children and adolescents with depression, anxiety, trauma or conduct problems
   
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In children and adolescents (aged 7-14) attending Child and Adolescent Mental Health Services (CAMHS) for depression, anxiety, trauma or conduct problems does the Modular Approach to Therapy for Children (MATCH-ADTC), compared to usual care, improve clinical outcomes (measured by comparing difference in trajectory of change of clinical severity)?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1154-1934</utrn>
    <trialacronym>The TrACY study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Trauma symptoms</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Conduct problems</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>MATCH (intervention) consists of a manual and a training package (i.e. five days of block training and a year of weekly telephone/Skype consultation sessions (60 minutes in duration) from a MATCH trainer to support clinicians in the use of MATCH). MATCH was specifically designed to combine the effective elements of the evidence based therapies (EBTs) for anxiety, depression, trauma-related symptoms and disruptive behaviour in one protocol, cater for co-morbidity and provide an opportunity to address different disorders that may emerge during therapy. 
MATCH is comprised of 33 modules/specific treatment procedures which can be organised in a flexible manner. Children/adolescents and their families are also given an integral role in defining the goals of therapy. Clinicians use a web-based system (specifically developed for this study) to monitor progress and adapt therapy in consultation with a child/adolescent and their family until a problem is resolved.
MATCH provides flexibility for the clinician to use a selection of modules depending on the needs of the child and his/her family. To guide the selection of modules, clinicians monitor progress and use MATCH flowcharts to identify which modules are required. All sessions are done face-to-face and are one-on-one with the child or his/her family. There is no standard duration of treatment. Sessions typically last between 45 and 60 minutes and are usually weekly (depending on the individual clinic and the child/family's circumstances).  Not all modules need to be administered for every child/family. 
To monitor adherence to the treatment protocol, all sessions will be audio-recorded and a sample of these recordings will be coded to ascertain the content. Clinicians will also be required to keep a log of their therapy sessions and treatment approaches (use of modules) will be discussed in weekly Skype supervision.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care/UC group: Usual care will be the treatment that is usually provided to a child/adolescent at a Child and Adolescent Mental Health Services (CAMHS) (e.g. case management, therapeutic group work and psychotherapy). </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary clinical outcome measure will be the Brief Problem Monitor (BPM). BPM will be collected weekly via telephone.</outcome>
      <timepoint>On a weekly basis until therapy is completed.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome measure of the delivery of evidence based therapy will be made via coding of audio taped therapy sessions. All MATCH and UC therapy sessions will be audiotaped.  A randomly selected subset  approximately 5-10 % (both MATCH and UC) will be assessed by the research team (blind to treatment allocation) for EBT content using the methods and the coding system developed for the initial trial of MATCH</outcome>
      <timepoint>Coding of randomly selected therapy sessions will be done throughout the study until all data is collected. As we are coding only a random selection of recorded sessions, there will not be a regular interval on which the frequency of coding is based.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome measure of the efficiency of services will be made through a comparisons between MATCH and UC for the following:  
1) Total therapy input by clinicians (in minutes) (using a self-report therapy log collected weekly)
2) contact with the CAMHS (in weeks), (using a self-report therapy log collected weekly)
3) number of therapy sessions and (using a self-report therapy log collected weekly)
4) number of missed therapy sessions (using a self-report therapy log collected weekly).    
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post intervention - This will vary according to treatment duration for each individual participant.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire (SDQ)  </outcome>
      <timepoint>SDQ will be collected monthly</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Top Problems Assessment (TPA) </outcome>
      <timepoint>TPA will be collected weekly</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Development and Well-Being Assessment (DAWBA) </outcome>
      <timepoint>DAWBA will be collected at baseline and post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Child Health Utility (CHU9D) </outcome>
      <timepoint>CHU9D will be collected at baseline, post intervention and at 3 month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Children and adolescents will be eligible for inclusion in the trial if:
1) They are newly referred to a participating CAMHS with a primary disorder that includes anxiety, depression, trauma-related symptoms or disruptive behaviour; 
2) They are 7 to 14 years of age on the date of consent;
3) They are able to provide written consent (or verbal assent) and have written parental/guardian consent; and,
4) The child and their parent/guardian can speak English or there is a clinician who can provide the necessary treatment, according to the treatment arm the participant is randomised to, in the familys native language.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>7</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>14</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Children and adolescent will be ineligible for inclusion in the trial if:
1) They are currently receiving other treatment for their disorder from the CAMHS (or another service); or,
2) They do not have a primary disorder of psychosis, severe intellectual disability, attention deficit-hyperactivity disorder (where the primary reason for referral is inattention and/or over-activity), autism or other pervasive developmental disorder, anorexia nervosa or bulimia nervosa;
3) The young person is acutely suicidal; or,
4) They have a sibling that has previously been recruited into the study.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Recruitment will be via CAMHS clinicians.  Eligible participants will be invited to participate by a clinician whom they have met during their standard initial assessment (or intake assessment).  
Child and adolescent participants and their parents/caregivers will be given written information sheets and consent forms.  Written consent will be collected from all parents/caregivers. Written consent (or verbal assent for younger participants) will be collected from all child or adolescent participants.  
Once consent is collected, the clinician will enter the participant's details into a custom-made online tracking system which will generate the treatment allocation. This will be emailed to the clinic's administrator. The child/adolescent will be allocated a clinician according to treatment allocation. </concealment>
    <sequence> Randomisation of child and adolescent participants: After the eligibility check, and once consent/assent and collection of baseline assessments have been completed, participants will be randomised in a 1:1 ratio to receive MATCH or UC stratified by sex and ethnicity.  

Allocation concealment will be assured by using centralised computer generation of the randomisation sequence.  

We will use web-based randomisation procedures to determine treatment allocation.
</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Randomisation occurs on two levels:

1) Randomisation of clinicians: All clinicians from participating CAMHS teams will be invited to participate.  Consenting CAMHS clinicians will be block randomised (by service/team) in a 1:1 ratio to MATCH or UC.  The block size will vary across sites depending upon the number of individuals likely to be recruited from each site.  Clinicians will be stratified on the basis of previous evidence-based therapy training (i.e. those with versus those without accredited training in cognitive behavioural therapy or behavioural parent training).    

2) Randomisation of children/adolescents </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Analyses: We will assess the comparability of baseline of both treatment groups (i.e. MATCH and UC) using descriptive analyses, in terms of age, sex, symptom severity, diagnosis and ethnicity. Both treatments may vary in content and duration, so that pre-post and follow-up (three months after treatment has ended) analyses are potentially confounded by treatment duration and/or dose. To deal with this, we propose to use the trajectories of change across time on the d BPM as our primary outcome measure.  We will carry out per-protocol analyses and intention to treat analyses. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/03/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>30/10/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>400</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Health Research Council (HRC)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 3 - ProCARE Building, Grafton Mews, at 110 Stanley Street, Auckland 1010, New Zealand</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Health Research Council (HRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 3 - ProCARE Building, Grafton Mews, at 110 Stanley Street, Auckland 1010, New Zealand


</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The long term costs of mental illness in children and adolescents are considerable and long lasting, yet services often do not deliver the best available treatment because of practical difficulties with current evidence based therapies (EBTs). MATCH (Modular Approach to Therapy for Children and Adolescent with anxiety, depression, trauma related symptoms and disruptive behaviour) is a new flexible modular system that combines EBTs for common mental health problems. MATCH has been developed by Professor John Weisz and his team in the USA. Prof Weisz is a world leading
expert in EBTs. MATCH has been shown to be more effective than usual care in a large clinical trial (Weisz et al., 2012, Archives of General Psychiatry, 29(3)). Training in MATCH is relatively brief. Our main objective is to improve the clinical outcomes of children and adolescents attending participating mental health services in New Zealand. We will carry out a rigorous real world clinical trial (a randomised controlled trial/RCT) to evaluate MATCH in the NZ context. We will train CAMHS clinicians in MATCH. The control group of clinicians will deliver usual care. We will evaluate which group delivers more EBT and better mental health outcomes for children and adolescents. Our study design ensures that we can show effectiveness separately for Maori and Pacific children. If results are positive we will work towards implementing national training in MATCH.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health And Disability Ethics Committees</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
No 1 The Terrace
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6011
New Zealand</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/09/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>13/CEN/97</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Sally Merry</name>
      <address>Department of Psychological Medicine
Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>649 3737599</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.merry@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sarah Hopkins</name>
      <address>Department of Psychological Medicine
Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>649 3737599 ext 82015</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.hopkins@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sarah Hopkins</name>
      <address>Department of Psychological Medicine
Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>649 3737599 ext 82015</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.hopkins@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sarah Hopkins</name>
      <address>Department of Psychological Medicine
Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>649 3737599 ext 82015</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.hopkins@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>