<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368922">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/07/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/09/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000923561</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>APProve: CAn Probiotics ImPROVE Breastfeeding Outcomes?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Probiotics for the Prevention of Mastitis in Breastfeeding Women: A Randomised Controlled Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>APProve</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Mastitis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast feeding</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the immune system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The participant will be given an 8 week supply of the probiotic sachets containing Lactobacillus Fermentum  (1x10^10 CFU/mL). Participants will be advised to take one sachet daily for a period of 8 weeks following the birth of her baby. The contents of the sachet should be mixed with water, juice or milk, stirred and consumed immediately.  The number of unused sachets will be collected by the research coordinator at the end of the 8 week period. 

Daily data on treatment intake, breast pain, infection symptoms and infant feeding will be collected by participants via the mobile phone application system (APP). Weekly questionnaires will collect data on maternal and infant well-being, unscheduled doctors visits, and medication intake. Women not using the mobile phone application system will receive a 2 month calendar diary to record her daily responses, along with a weekly questionnaire accessed by an emailed web-link. For all participants, follow-up questionnaires  will be sent at 2, 6 and 12 months to collect secondary outcomes.</interventions>
    <comparator>The participant will be given an 8 week supply of the placebo sachets which are identical in every way to the treatment sachets but do not contain the active Lactobacillus fermentum ingredient. Participants will be advised to take one sachet daily for a period of 8 weeks following the birth of her baby. The contents of the sachet should be mixed with water, juice or milk, stirred and consumed immediately. The number of unused sachets will be collected by the research coordinator at the end of the 8 week period. 

Daily data on treatment intake, breast pain, infection symptoms and infant feeding will be collected by participants via the mobile phone application system (APP).  Weekly questionnaires will collect data on maternal and infant well-being, unscheduled doctors visits, and medication intake. Women not using the mobile phone application system will receive a 2 month calendar diary to record her daily responses, along with a weekly questionnaire accessed by an emailed web-link. For all participants, follow-up questionnaires will be sent at 2, 6 and 12 months to collect secondary outcomes.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome will be incidence of mastitis up to 8 weeks following delivery as measured by: 
1.	Clinical diagnosis of mastitis
OR
2.	At least two of the following breast symptoms:
        *Pain
        *Redness / inflammation
        *Lump / swelling
AND at least one of the following systemic symptoms:
        *flu-like symptoms (body aches, headaches and chills) 
        *fever greater or equal to 38 degrees C
(Above symptoms must present for at least 24 hours - i.e. recorded for 2 or more consecutive days on the mobile phone application system or calendar diary.)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 8 weeks following delivery.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of time breastfeeding assessed by patient surveys designed specifically for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily and weekly x 8 weeks and at 2, 6, and 12 months postpartum.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Breastfeeding complications assessed by patient surveys designed specifically for this study.  Examples include development of breast abscess, cracked nipples, or recurrence of mastitis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily and weekly x 8 weeks, then at 2, 6 and 12 months postpartum.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall maternal health and well-being assessed by patient surveys including SF-12 Quality of Life Questionnaire and the State-Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI-6), as well as surveys designed specifically for this study.  Examples include number of doctors visits, adverse effects of treatment, incidence of primary mastitis, and postpartum use of antibiotics.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weekly x 8 weeks and at 2, 6 and 12 weeks postpartum.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acceptability and compliance of trial using a mobile phone application system assessed by patient surveys and comparative data collection between APP and non-APP users. The surveys have been designed specifically for this study.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 months postpartum.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Preference for method of postnatal questionnaires assessed by tick-box of patient preference.  Examples include postal or  web-link.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2, 6 and 12 months postpartum.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Infant health and well-being measured by patient surveys designed specifically for this study.  Examples include: gastroenteritis, growth and development in the first year of life (infant weight and measurements), doctors visits, infections, admission to hospital, allergic reactions, and use of antibiotics.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weekly x 8 weeks and at 2, 6 and 12 weeks postpartum.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Pregnant women at least 18 years of age at 37 weeks gestation or later with a singleton pregnancy will be invited to participate in the trial. They will currently not be taking commercial probiotics containing lactobacillus fermentum; and will own a smartphone. Their intention at the time of consent will be to breastfeed their baby.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Women with a history of Raynaud syndrome will not be eligible to participate in the trial. Any delivery/breast complication rendering the infant unable to breastfeed will be excluded. Women unable to speak/understand English will not be consented.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Eligible women will be identified and approached by a local researcher on the postnatal ward within 72 hours of delivery. The researcher will explain the trial, review the Patient Information Sheet, obtain informed consent and collect baseline data. The participant will then be randomised to either “probiotic” or “placebo” and provided with the study intervention. 
</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation schedule will be prepared and centrally administered by a researcher not involved in patient care. A computer random number generator will be used to prepare the randomisation schedule in blocks, stratified by previous mastitis and sequentially numbered opaque envelopes will be used to ensure allocation concealment. The randomisation sequence will be concealed until all data has been collected. The participant and researcher will be blinded as to treatment allocation.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The sample size is based on an expected rate of mastitis in the control group of 18%, two-sided 5% significance level and a power of 80%, we estimated a total sample size of 452 would be required. However, given studies related to the duration of breastfeeding report a cessation rate in the first 8 weeks post-partum of up to 20%, and a potential loss-to follow-up of 5-10% may occur with withdrawals or non-compliance, we inflated the sample size by a further 30% to ensure complete data. Hence, we estimated a total sample size of approximately 600 women would be required (300 per group) for this trial. 

Primary and secondary outcomes will be analysed using an intention-to-treat approach, which includes all losses-to follow-up, non-compliances or withdrawals. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>21/04/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>21/04/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/11/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>600</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal North Shore Hospital - St Leonards</hospital>
    <postcode>2065 - St Leonards</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Perinatal Research Group, Kolling Institute, University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Perinatal Research Group
Level 2, Building 52, RNSH
Reserve Road
St Leonards NSW 2065</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Perinatal Research Group, Kolling Institute, University of Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Perinatal Research Group
Level 2, Building 52, RNSH
Reserve Road
St Leonards NSW 2065</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Puremedic Pty Ltd.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Unit 3, 6-7 Gilda Court
Mulgrave VIC 3170</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ramsay Research and Teaching Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Kolling Institute
Northern Sydney Local Health District
Kolling Building, Level 13
Reserve Road
St Leonards NSW 2066</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary aim of the project is to evaluate the effectiveness of oral probiotics for the prevention of mastitis in lactating women. Secondary aims will assess maternal breastfeeding outcomes, infant infections including
gastroenteritis, and the acceptability of a novel mobile app.
The primary hypothesis is that regular ingestion of probiotics by women in the first two months following birth will decrease the incidence of mastitis in lactating women.
The secondary hypotheses are that exposure to probiotics may also confer a benefit to breastfeeding mothers and
reduce risk of infection among infants, particularly gastroenteritis. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Sydney Local Health District HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Kolling Building, Level 13
Royal North Shore Hospital
Reserve Road
St Leonards NSW 2065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/11/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/HAWKE/358</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Natasha Nassar</name>
      <address>Perinatal Research
Level 2, Building 52, RNSH
Reserve Road
St. Leonards NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9462 9792</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>natasha.nassar@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Diana Bond</name>
      <address>Perinatal Research
Level 2, Building 52, RNSH
Reserve Road
St. Leonards NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9462 9796</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>diana.bond@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Natasha Nassar</name>
      <address>Perinatal Research
Level 2, Building 52, RNSH
Reserve Road
St. Leonards NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9462 9792</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>natasha.nassar@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Diana Bond</name>
      <address>Perinatal Research
Level 2, Building 52, RNSH
Reserve Road
St. Leonards NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9462 9796</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>diana.bond@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>