<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363470">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/01/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/01/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000119796</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Neoadjuvant chemotherapy with nab-paclitaxel in women with HER2-negative high-risk breast cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Phase III, open-label, randomised trial of nab-paclitaxel versus paclitaxel in patients with HER2-negative, not metastatic unilateral breast cancer who are at risk of disease recurrence to assess treatment response</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>ETNA (Evaluating Treatment with Neoadjuvant Abraxane)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Breast Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Subjects will receive 4 cycles of Abraxane (Investigational Product) (125mg/m2) intravenously over 30 min given week 1, 2 and 3 followed by 1 week rest or the comparator. This will be followed by 4 cycles of anthracycline-containing chemotherapy (AC/EC or FEC - based on clinician decision). AC Doxorubicin 60mg/m2, Cyclophosphamide 600mg/m2 intravenously over 30 min given once every 3 weeks;  EC Epirubicin 90mg/m2, Cyclophosphamide 600mg/m2 intravenously over 30 min given once every 3 weeks; FEC Fluorouracil 600mg/m2 Epirubicin 90mg/m2 Cyclophosphamide 600mg/m2 intravenously over 30 min given once every 3 weeks</interventions>
    <comparator>Subjects will receive 4 cycles of paclitaxel (90mg/m2 diluted in 250mL of WFI) intravenously over 1 hour given week 1, 2 and 3 followed by 1 week rest.
This will be followed by 4 cycles of anthracycline-containing chemotherapy (AC/EC or FEC- based on clinician decision). AC Doxorubicin 60mg/m2, Cyclophosphamide 600mg/m2 intravenously over 30 min given once every 3 weeks;  EC Epirubicin 90mg/m2, Cyclophosphamide 600mg/m2 intravenously over 30 min given once every 3 weeks; FEC Fluorouracil 600mg/m2 Epirubicin 90mg/m2 Cyclophosphamide 600mg/m2 intravenously over 30 min given once every 3 weeks</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary endpoint is to compare the rate of pathological Complete response (pCR) at surgery between abraxane and paclitaxel containing regimens.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of surgery the absence of invasive disease in breast and nodes will be measured by histopathological examination. Surgery will occur between 3 to 5 weeks following last cycle of chemotherapy.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>clinical Overall Response (cOR) after the first 4 cycles of abraxane vs paclitaxel, and after the entire pre-operative chemotherapy (before surgery) in the study arms of abraxane vs paclitaxel</outcome>
      <timepoint>after 4 cycles and before surgery by palpation of the breast and axilla.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>to compare Event Free Survival (Distant, Local, Regional) in the study arms of abraxane vs paclitaxel</outcome>
      <timepoint> diagnosis of breast cancer progression during treatment or recurrence after surgery will be assessed by the investigator and confirmed by clinical, laboratory, radiological and/or histological findings. The protocol defines what is considered acceptable to confirm the event free survivals listed above. After surgery patients will be follwed up for 10 years after surgery. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Survival in the study arms of abraxane vs paclitaxel</outcome>
      <timepoint>Overall Survival is defined as the time from randomisation to the date of death. Patients alive at the end of the study (10 years) will be considered at their last contact.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluation of the tolerability of the treatment regimens in the different study arms will be measured by using the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) verison 4.0</outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration of study up to 28 days after treatment (if surgery not performed) or surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>to conduct molecular and clinical analyses to assess the presence of predictive markers of benefit </outcome>
      <timepoint> Tumour tissue blocks at diagnosis and at surgery are mandatory. bloods/serum and plasma at baseline and after the chemotherapy treatment is optional. Further tissue samples at other time points are optional and defined in the protocol</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients with HER-2 negative, invasive unilateral breast cancer with known hormone receptor status and tumour grade. ECOG status 0 or 1.
Clinical stage should be either
- T2, T3, T4 disease, triple negative
- T2, T3, T4 disease, ER or PgR positive and moderately differentiated or poorly differentiated tumour grade (G II-III).
Paraffin-embedded tumour block should be available for central confirmation of eligiblity criteria. 
Written consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- contralateral breast cancer or presence of metastatic disease (exception: contralateral in situ ductal cancer)
- surgical axillary staging prior to study entry (exception: FNA of 1 axillary node is permitted, and, but not recommended, a pre-neoadjuvant therapy sentinel lymph node biopsy for patients with clinically negative axillary nodes)
- pregnant and lactating women.
- women with childbearing potential unless appropriate contraception as described in protocol
- treatment including radiation therapy, chemotherapy, biotherapy, and/or hormonal therapy for current diagnosed breast cancer.
- previous investigational product within 4 weeks of randomisation
- patients on therapy with a strong CYP3A4 ihibitor, and on therapy with warferin
- previous or concomitant malignancy of other type that could affect compliance.
- pre-existing motor or sensory neuropathy of Grade &gt;1 for any reason
- patients with hypersensitivity due to drugs containing polyoxyethylene castor oil, or hardened castor oil.
- other serious illness or medical condition (examples included in the protocol)
- patients with a history of uncontrolled seizures, contral nervous system disorders or psychaitric disability judged to be clinically significant
- serious uncontrolled infections or poorly controlled diabetes mellitus
- Abonrmal laboratory values at baseline: ANC &lt;1.5 x 109/L; platelet count &lt; 100 x 109/L; Hb &lt; 10g/dL; serum total bilirubin &gt; 1.5xULN (except documented Gilbert's syndrome); ALT &gt; 1.25 x ULN; serum creatinine &gt; 1.5x ULN
- Baseline LVEF &lt; 50% by echocardiography or MUGA scan

 
- </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subject to meeting all eligibility criteria,  the Sponsor will confirm eligibility and via the Electronic Data CApture system the patient will be automatically randomised according to the stratification variables being:
a) cooperative research group
b) disease stage (operable and locally advanced)
c) tumour subtype (triple negative vs luminal B high and luminal B intermediate)</concealment>
    <sequence>Patients will be randomised to one of the 2 possible treatments arms in a 1:1 ratio (abraxane vs paclitaxel) using  Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation).
Patients will be stratified by Cooperative Research Group, Operable (T2N0-1; T3N0) versus locally advanced (T3N1, T4, anyN2N3); and tumour sub-type (Luminal B intermediate Her2 negative, ER/PR positive Ki67 14-20% vs Luminal B high Her2 negative, ER/PR positive Ki67&gt;20% vs Triple negative Her2 negative, ER and PR negative)</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/04/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/08/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>10/02/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>632</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>695</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/12/2025</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,SA,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Perth Hospital - Perth</hospital>
    <hospital>Maroondah Hospital - Ringwood East</hospital>
    <hospital>Box Hill Hospital - Box Hill</hospital>
    <hospital>Breast Cancer Research Centre - Western Australia - Perth</hospital>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Austria</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Singapore</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Fondazione Michelangelo</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Michelangelo Operations Office
c/o Fondazione IRCCS Istituto Nazionale dei Tumori
Via G. Venezian, 1
20133 Milano</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Italy</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Investigator Initiated Research Grant from Celgene</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Investigator initiated research grant from Celgene
Celgene Corporation
86 Morris Avenue
Summit, NJ 07901
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Breast Cancer Research Centre of Western Australia (BCRC-WA)</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Hollywood Private Hospital
Entrance 3, Lower Ground Floor
101 Monash Avenue
Nedlands WA 6009</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is comparing the treatment response to pre-operative chemotherapy with nab-paclitaxel versus paclitaxel in women with breast cancer.

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged over 18 years and have been diagnosed with HER-2 negative, invasive unilateral breast cancer with known hormone receptor status and tumour grade.

Trial details
Participants in this trial will be randomly (by chance) allocated to receive either 4 cycles of nab-paclitaxel (abraxane) or 4 cycles of paclitaxel, followed by 4 cycles of chemotherapy containing anthracyclines. Approximately 2-4 weeks following chemotherapy the patients will undergo breast surgery as part of local regional treatment. 

All patients will be followed for 10 years after the date of randomisation in order to evaluate treatment response and safety.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Mount Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>140 Mounts Bay Road
Perth WA 6000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/04/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC74.2</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/02/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hollywood Private Hospital Research Ethics Commitee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 141
Nedlands WA 6909</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/02/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/01/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Arlene Chan</name>
      <address>BCRC-WA
Hollywood Private Hospital
Entrance 3, Lower Ground Floor
101 Monash Avenue
Nedlands WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9481 4522</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>admin.profachan@me.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Arlene Chan</name>
      <address>BCRC-WA
Hollywood Private Hospital
Entrance 3, Lower Ground Floor
101 Monash Avenue
Nedlands WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9481 4522</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>admin.profachan@me.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Arlene Chan</name>
      <address>BCRC-WA
Hollywood Private Hospital
Entrance 3, Lower Ground Floor
101 Monash Avenue
Nedlands WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9481 4522</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>admin.profachan@me.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Jeannette Devoto</name>
      <address>BCRC-WA
Hollywood Private Hospital
Entrance 3, Lower Ground Floor
101 Monash Avenue
Nedlands WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 6500 5556</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>BCTU@bcrc-wa.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>