<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82645">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/02/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/02/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000116325</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Gait, balance and falls risk in people with knee osteoarthritis before and after knee replacement surgery</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Gait, balance and falls risk in people with knee osteoarthritis before and after knee replacement surgery</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>knee osteoarthritis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>knee replacement surgery</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>participants with end stage of knee osteoarthritis (on a waiting list for knee surgery) will be assessed before undergoing knee replacement surgery and after knee replacement surgery for a follow up of 1 year.</interventions>
    <comparator>none</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Falls risk. 
The falls risk will be assessed using a series of tests of physiological function (the Physiological Profile Assessment). The assessment includes tests of vision (edge contrast sensitivity, visual acuity), peripheral sensation (a lower limb matching task for determining position sense), lower limb strength (knee extension strength), reaction time, and balance (sway when standing on a medium density foam rubber mat).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before knee replacement surgery and at 4 and 12 months after the surgery.
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gait. 
Swing limb kinematics and kinetic, toe clearance and foot function will be assessed during walking using three dimensional motion analysis system and force platforms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before knee replacement surgery and at 4 and 12 months after the surgery.
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life, pain and knee function.
The quality of life of the participants will be measured using the Assessment of Quality of Life (AQoL) utility instrument, a self-administered health-related questionnaire on quality of life. 
The self-reported physical function and pain of the participants will be assessed using the Western Ontario and McMasters University Osteoarthritis Index (WOMAC).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before knee replacement surgery and at 4 and 12 months after the surgery.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>patients with diagnosed unilateral or bilateral medial compartment knee OA (on a waiting list for knee replacement) aged 50 and over (of either gender)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>95</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients will be excluded if they had uncontrolled systemic disease, previous knee surgery and a pre-existing neurological or other orthopaedic condition affecting walking. Participants will be also excluded from the study if they have had the following foot conditions: partial foot amputation or ulceration, foot fractures, any neurological condition that affects lower limb strength (eg: stroke, polio), or any other musculoskeletal conditions which may affect the foot (eg: rheumatoid arthritis, gout).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>longitudinal study
participants from the control group will be age and gender matched to the osteoarthritis group</designfeatures>
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>3086</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Musculoskeletal Research Centre, La Trobe University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Musculoskeletal Research Centre

Faculty of Health Sciences, La Trobe University

Bundoora, Victoria 3086, Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Arthritis Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Arthritis Foundation Australia
1st floor 52 Parramatta Road Forest Lodge NSW 2037</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Falls are among the most common cause of injury and hospital admissions in older people in Australia, and due to the ageing of the population, are a major public health concern. The detection of factors associated with falls may allow clinicians and professionals to implement effective falls prevention programs targeted to those at greatest risk, such as older people with knee osteoarthritis (knee OA). This study will assess the falls risk of individuals with knee osteoarthritis before and at 4 and 12 months following knee replacement surgery using the a series of validated tests (the Physiological Profile Assessment). Additionally, this study will investigate walking patterns (including the minimum foot clearance and the swing limb kinematics and kinetics) in patients with knee osteoarthritis (prior to undergoing knee replacement and 4 and 12 months following surgery) and compare them to an asymptomatic age-matched control group. As such this study will identify the balance and gait characteristics that may predispose older people with knee osteoarthritis to tripping and falling.

The research hypotheses are:

(i)         Patients with knee osteoarthritis will demonstrate different falls risk before and after knee replacement. 

(ii)        Patients with knee osteoarthritis will demonstrate altered minimum toe clearance and swing limb mechanics compared to age matched controls.

(iii)        Patients with knee osteoarthritis will show different minimum toe clearance and swing limb biomechanics before and after knee replacement surgery.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/02/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/02/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Pazit Levinger</name>
      <address>Musculoskeletal Research Centre

Faculty of Health Sciences, La Trobe University

Bundoora, Victoria 3086, Australia</address>
      <phone>03-94795260</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.levinger@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Pazit Levinger</name>
      <address>Musculoskeletal Research Centre

Faculty of Health Sciences, La Trobe University

Bundoora, Victoria 3086, Australia</address>
      <phone>03-94795260</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.levinger@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Pazit Levinger</name>
      <address>Musculoskeletal Research Centre

Faculty of Health Sciences, La Trobe University

Bundoora, Victoria 3086, Australia</address>
      <phone>03-94795260</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.levinger@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>