<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362083">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/02/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/02/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000225819</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>MRI based computer navigation of total hip replacement</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Total hip replacement: MRI navigation
Assessment of acetabular component position with and without MRI navigation</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Osteoarthritis of hip joints</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Navigation of hip joint replacement based on MRI preop findings. Follow up results with CT scan
A standard MRI scan of the hip was used preoperatively to investigate the patient's hip anatomy in order to design the navigation tool specific to each patient. This takes approximately 30 minutes over one day. One scan is required before the operation for each patient.
A CT scan of the pelvis is obtained post-operatively to assess the position of the acetabular component and this is to be compared between the MRI navigation group and the standard free hand group. This takes approximately 30 minutes over one day. One scan is required for each patient.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard free-hand technique versus MRI based navigation

The standard free hand technique has been used in every single operation in New Zealand and mostly worldwide. This refers to implantation of the acetabular prosthesis without any computer navigation but simply judged by the surgeon during the procedure. It has been used since the hip joint replacement has first been introduced. For the purpose of the study some patients will be randomly allocated to this free hand group. Essentially they will received the same procedure as the standard treatment used currently in New Zealand. The control technique takes an average of one hour in our hospital to perform. The current practice of the control technique in hip joint replacement occurs on average once a day in our hospital.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Position of acetabular cup based on CT scan of the pelvis post op</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Complications of MRI based navigation technique
The MRI navigation tool is a pilot study. The main different feature of this navigation is the use of MRI scan prior to surgery. MRI scan is a safe procedure without any harm to the patients.
During surgery the navigation will use a cutting block to fit into the specific patient's pelvis and the block secured wires into the pelvis. This has been safely applied oversea without any complications clinically. However potential complications such as fracture and infection associated with this can be assessed with CT scan following surgery and subsequent follow up of patient's progress at outpatient clinic. Appropriate blood tests will be obtained if there is a clinical suspicion of infection.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Osteoarthritis of hip joint</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>100</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>People who do not consent to the trial
People who are unable to undero MRI scan</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients attending orthopaedic outpatient clinic for consultation of osteoarthritis of their hips
Information sheet will be given by the consultant surgeon
Details of the study will be discussed
Patient's consent will be respected
Opaque envelopes containing either standard free hand or MRI navigation will be used to randomised patients at the initial consultation after consent. This will be randomly shuffled and withdrawn</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Study will be finished if the navigation group has high complication rate 
Study will be finished if the navigation group shows early superior results than standard free hand group</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1 / Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/03/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Northland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Northland District health board</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Whangarei Hospital
Maunu Road, Private Bag 9742, 
Whangarei 0148</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Northland District health board</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Whangarei Hospital
Maunu Road, Private Bag 9742, 
Whangarei 0148</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>MRI computer navigation aims to improve the acetabular cup placement of the prosthesis in the pelvis. This will influence the risk of complications and survivorship of the implant. Current free hand technique leads to an excessive high percentage of position outside the standardised safe zone. The study is to investigate the position of prosthesis of acetabular cup with the MRI based navigation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern X ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Private Bag 92-522, Wellesley St
Auckland 1141</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/03/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Justin Chou</name>
      <address>Whangarei Hospital
Maunu Road, Private Bag 9742, Whangarei 0148</address>
      <phone>00 64 9 4304100</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>choch550@gmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Justin Chou</name>
      <address>Whangarei Hospital
Maunu Road, Private Bag 9742, Whangarei 0148</address>
      <phone>00 64 9 4304100</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>choch550@gmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>