<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363827">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/03/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/07/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000735752</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Investigating side-lying for bottle feeding preterm infants on respiratory support</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In preterm infants receiving respiratory support does a side-lying position   compared to a standard cradle-hold position  improve physiological stability</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>prematurity
chronic lung disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Complications of newborn</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Infants will have a study feed in two positions, the standard cradle-hold and the side-lying position. Infants will have a maximum of 30 minutes to complete the feed.  If the total volume of milk offered is not consumed it will be admiinistered via the infants gastric tube.
At least 12hours later they will have the second feed in the alternate position. </interventions>
    <comparator>Infants will have a study feed in two positions, the standard cradle hold (control) and the other feed in the alternate side-lying position. Infants will have a maximum of 30 minutes to complete the feed.  If the total volume of milk offered is not consumed it will be admiinistered via the infants gastric tube.
At least 12hours later they will have the second feed in the alternate position. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Oxygen saturation during the bottle feed will be measured by pulse oximeter</outcome>
      <timepoint>variable according to how long it takes the infant to complete the bottle feed or 30 minutes whichever occurs first</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Heart rate during the study bottle feeds will be measured by pulse oximeter</outcome>
      <timepoint>variable according to how long it takes the infant to complete the bottle feed or 30 minutes whichever occurs first</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Efficiency of feed measured by volume (per kilogram weight) consumed during the feed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>variable according to how long it takes the infant to complete the bottle feed or 30 minutes whichever occurs first</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Infants born preterm (&lt;34weeks gestation) who are having bottle feeds whilst currently recieiving respiratory support, eg CPAP, or sub nasal oxygen administered at low or high flows</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>23</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Weeks</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>33</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Weeks</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Infants with craniofacial/structural abnormalities.
Infants receiving bottle feeds using a special needs bottle.
Infants who are likely to be transferred to another neonatal unit before both study feeds can be completed.  </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Demographic and clinical data including gestational age, birth weight, post-menstrual age, weight at time of study, oxygen concentration, and type of respiratory support will be extracted from the infants clinical record. The mean HR, RR, and SpO2 before, during and after feeds will be determined from the pulse oximeter downloads. Paired t tests will be used to compare continuous data, HR, RR, SpO2 and EtCO2. Proportions will be compared using the chi-squared test. Logistic regression with adjustment for repeated measures will be used to explore whether type of hold during feeding affects the probability of an infant experiencing an SpO2 &lt; 80%. The data will be analysed using Stata (Intercooled 12.0, Statacorp Texas, USA).
Sample size: Data from our previous feeding study showed that 7/8 (87%) infants receiving respiratory support during a cradle-hold bottle feed experienced a period of SpO2 &lt; 80% during a feed.  A sample size of 46 infants with each infant receiving a feed in each position (i.e. two study feeds) would be sufficient to detect a reduction in the number of infants experiencing an SpO2 &lt; 80% during a feed from 87% to 44% (a 50% reduction), with 90% power and a 2-tailed alpha-error of 0.05.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>8/07/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>4/09/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/06/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>46</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Women's Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Royal Women's Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>20 Flemington Road, Parkville, Victoria, 3052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Infants born prematurely often require gastric tube feeding. The transition from gastric tube feeds to sucking feeds (breast and/ or bottle) usually starts around 32-34 weeks post menstrual age when infants begin to demonstrate the ability to coordinate sucking, swallowing and breathing. However, during sucking feeds immature infants may experience physiological instability, including lower oxygen saturations (SpO2) and heart rates (HR), and periods of apnoea or cyanosis. However, preterm infants may have sucking feeds by bottle for a number of reasons, for example infants whose mothers are no longer expressing, or who are unable to be present for a breastfeed.
During bottle feeds infants typically feed cradled in a flexed, semi-reclining en face position. In contrast, during breastfeeding infants are generaly placed so that they lie across the mothers abdomen in an unflexed position with the infants head in a straight line with their body. In a pilot study, comparing a side-lying position against a semi-upright position for bottle feeding preterm infants, Clark reported an improvement in SpO2 measurements in the side-lying position 
In our previous study at RWH with 25 preterm infants we showed there was little difference in mean (SD) SpO2 during feeds between the cradle-hold and side-lying position 94(6)% versus 95(6)% respectively (p=0.55, CI -1.4, 5.4). During feeds 17/ 25 (68%) experienced a period of SpO2 &lt;80% in the cradle-hold position compared with 14/25(56)% in the side-lying position (p=0.26, CI 0.68, 4.10). However, in post hoc analysis we saw that in 8 infants receiving
respiratory support during feeds 7/8 (87%) versus 5/8 (62%) in cradle versus side lying feeding positions experienced a SpO2 &lt; 80% (p=0.25). There are several reports showing that there is a reduction in oxygen saturation in preterm infants with bronchopulmonary dysplasia (BPD) during bottle feeds in the cradle-hold position. Residual lung disease is probably the most
prevalent sequela of prematurity that affects feeding. There are no reports measuring the effect of alternate bottle feeding positions for infants receiving respiratory support during bottle feeding. We hypothesise that for infants who are receiving respiratory support there might be increased physiological stability during bottle-feeding in the side-lying versus the cradle-hold position.
The aim of this study is to determine the physiological stability and efficiency of bottle feeding in the side lying position (SLP) in preterm infants receiving respiratory support who are transitioning to suck feeds.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Royal Women's Hospital Research and Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Royal Women's Hospital
20 Flemington Road
Parkville, Victoria, 3052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/09/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/03/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jennifer Dawson</name>
      <address>Newborn Research
The Royal Women's Hosptial
20 Flemington Road
Parkville, Victoria, 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8345 3791</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jennifer.dawson@thewomens.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jennifer Dawson</name>
      <address>Newborn Research
The Royal Women's Hosptial
20 Flemington Road
Parkville, Victoria, 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8345 3791</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jennifer.dawson@thewomens.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jennifer Dawson</name>
      <address>Newborn Research
The Royal Women's Hosptial
20 Flemington Road
Parkville, Victoria, 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8345 3791</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jennifer.dawson@thewomens.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jennifer Dawson</name>
      <address>Newborn Research
The Royal Women's Hosptial
20 Flemington Road
Parkville, Victoria, 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8345 3791</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jennifer.dawson@thewomens.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>