<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366040">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/03/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/03/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000344695</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Routine Monitoring and Evaluation of efficacy and safety of Dihydroartemisinin-Piperaquine  in Trapaeng Raeng Centre (Kampot), in Phnom Dek Centre ( Preah Vihear), in  Snuol Centre (Kratie), and in Veunsai centre (Ratanakiri) for the treatment of uncompleted Plasmodium falciparum malaria and Plasmodium vivax malaria (Only in Kampot and Ratanakiri) in Cambodia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Routine Monitoring and Evaluation of efficacy and safety of Dihydroartemisinin-Piperaquine  in Trapaeng Raeng Centre (Kampot), in Phnom Dek Centre ( Preah Vihear), in  Snuol Centre (Kratie), and in Veunsai centre (Ratanakiri) for the treatment of uncompleted Plasmodium falciparum malaria and Plasmodium vivax malaria (Only in Kampot and Ratanakiri) in Cambodia</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1154-8495</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Patient with Plasmodium falciparum infection</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Patient with Plasmodium vivax infection</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>-Patients with P. falciparum or P. vivax infection are orally treated with Dihydroartemisinin-Piperaquine with the adult dose of 2-4 mg/kg for Dihydroartemisinin and 20mg/kg for Piperaquine over 3 consecutive days. 
- Patients have to take each dose of drug in front of the medical staff at the study site and closely observed for the first 30 minutes following each dose.
- Patients who vomit in less than 30 minutes or vomit after one hour after administration of the treatment will be re-administered the full dose of the treatment". 
</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group </comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- Proportion of adequate clinical and parasitological response of the patients with P.falciparum and P. vivax to the treatment of DHA-PIP.
- Polymerase chain reaction is used to differentiate between reinfection and recrudescence for the recurrent infection at day 28 and day 42.</outcome>
      <timepoint>the treatment outcome will be evaluated at day 28  and day 42 after the completion of a complete 3-day treatment course at day0, day 1 and day2.  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of treatment failure of the patients with P. falciparum and P. vivax to Dihydroartemisinin-Piperaquine by applying the method of polymerase chain reaction (PCR) which is to differentiate between the reinfection and recrudescence at day 28 and day 42. </outcome>
      <timepoint>the treatment outcome will be evaluated at day 28 and day 42 after the completion of a complete 3-day treatment course at day0, day 1 and day2.  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- age between 2 and 60 years except unmarried females between 12 and 18 years old (potential unpredicted pregnancy); 
- mono-infection with P. falciparum or P. vivax detected by microscopy; P. falciparum or P. vivax parasitaemia of 500-100,000/microliter asexual forms;
- ability to swallow oral [by mouth] medication;
- ability and willingness to comply with the study protocol for the duration of the study and to comply with the study visit schedule
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>2</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- presence of general danger signs in children aged under 5 years or signs of severe falciparum malaria according to the definitions of WHO;
- mixed or mono-infection with another Plasmodium species detected by microscopy;
-presence of severe malnutrition (defined as a child whose growth standard is below 3 z-score, has symmetrical oedema involving at least the feet or has a mid-upper arm circumference &lt; 110 mm);
- presence of febrile conditions due to diseases other than malaria 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>- Patients were evaluated clinically and parasitically based on the specific inclusion criteria: over two years of age; fever (equal or greater than 37.5 degrees) or history of fever in the last two days; P. falciparum mono-infection with parasite density between 500 to 200,000 asexual parasites/microliter and the exclusion criteria of the study; 
- If a patient is eligible for the study the researcher asks if the patient can involve in the study by explaining all the process, procedure and all potential risks of drug side effects.
- If the patient agrees to participate in the study then the patient needs to sign in an inform consent. 
- The patients are to stay at the health facilities for 3 or 4 days until the parasites completely clear from their bodies 
- The patient has to come back to the study site for follow up on weekly basis over 42 days. 
- During the follow up the patient receives the physical and parasitological examination (i.e, blood slide). </concealment>
    <sequence>Nil </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>- As the treatment failure rate to DHA-PIP in the area is 10%, 10% has been chosen. At a confidence level of 95% and a precision around the estimate of 8%, a minimum of 54 patients must be included. With a 10% increase to allow loss to follow-up and withdrawals during the 42-day follow-up period, 60 patients should be included in the study per site and per species.  

- The primary efficacy analysis was evaluated for the per-protocol population
- The exact two-side 95% confidence interval (calculated with Person-Clop per limits) for the primary end point for day-28 cure rate in each study group.
- A similar analysis was executed for the proportion of subjects with cure on days 42. 
- Kaplan-Meier analysis with a log-rank test were applied for the comparison of treatment failure rates among several groups. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/11/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>9/11/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>24/02/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>30/11/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>240</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Cambodia</country>
      <state>Kampot</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Cambodia</country>
      <state>Kratie</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Cambodia</country>
      <state>Preah Vihear</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Cambodia</country>
      <state>Rattanakiri</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Ministry of Health of Cambodia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>No. 151-153, Kampuchea Krom Blvd (128), 12252 Phnom Penh</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Cambodia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>World Health Organization</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>20 Av. Appia, 1211 Geneva 27</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Switzerland</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>National Center for Parasitology, Entomology and Malaria Control</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>#372 Monivong Blvd (Corner St. 322), Phnom Penh</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Cambodia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study is to evaluate the efficacy and safety of dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine for the treatment of uncomplicated P. falciparum and P. vivax malaria  in Cambodia</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>National Ethics Committee for Health Research</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress># 2 Blvd, KIM YL SUNG, Khan Tuol Kok, Phnom Penh</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/05/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>0079 NECHR</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/05/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Cambodia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/366040-Ethic committee 20130001.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/366040-6-Protocol 2013 15052013 at 3h55mn pm.doc</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rithea Leang</name>
      <address>National Centre for Parasitology, Entomology and Malaria Control
Head of Health Research Unit
# 372 Monivong Blvd (322 Corner St.), Phnom Penh</address>
      <phone>855 12 715 666</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rithealeang@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Cambodia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mey Bouth Denis</name>
      <address>National Centre for Parasitology, Entomology and Malaria Control
# 372 Monivong Blvd (322 Corner St.), Phnom Penh</address>
      <phone>855 12  858 320</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>meybouthd@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Cambodia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Didier Menard</name>
      <address>Institute Pasteur of Cambodia
5 Blvd Monivong, BP 983
Phnom Penh, Cambodia
</address>
      <phone>855 12 715 666</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dmenard@pasteur-kh.org</email>
      <country>Cambodia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>