<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370962">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/06/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/06/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000849493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy of a parent-delivered intervention for speech problems in children</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Speech P.E.A.S: The Role of Parents in Intervention for Speech Problems in Children</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Speech Sound Disorder</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Phonological Impairment</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Speech therapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The aim of this study is to determine if intervention for speech problems in preschool-aged children is effective when delivered by parents and a speech pathologist. Specifically, this study will determine if multiple oppositions intervention, an approach established as effective when delivered intensively by a speech pathologist, is still effective when modified and delivered by parents in conjunction with a speech pathologist, with children who have a speech sound disorder.

The multiple oppositions approach is an evidence-based treatment for childhood speech sound disorders. It was developed from linguistic and behavioural principles, and is known to be effective when treating children with moderate to severe speech sound disorders.

Children and one of their parents will attend 1 one-to-one session lasting 60 minutes per week for 9 weeks. At this session, one of the researchers (who is also a speech pathologist) will deliver the multiple oppositions approach to the child and will train parents in how to deliver the multiple oppositions approach to their child. Parents will then provide the treatment at home (home practice) for up to 30 minutes twice per week.

The outline of the study is as follows:
*Eligibility assessment to determine if the child/parent meet the inclusion criteria for the study
*3  6 weeks of baseline data collection (children will be randomised to receive either 3, 4 , 5 or 6 baseline probes, in which a speech sample is collected from a child once per week monitor their speech)
*9 weeks of treatment in the clinic where the intervention is delivered by the researcher/speech pathologist and parents are trained. Sessions lasting 1 hour will be delivered once per week. During the 9 weeks, parents will be asked to do home practice for up to 30 minutes on two days.
*Immediate follow-up assessment lasting 60 minutes to monitor changes to the childs speech
*Final follow-up assessment of childs speech, four weeks after the immediate follow-up. At this session, parents will be interviewed about their experience of delivering the intervention at home. In total, this session will last 90 minutes.

Adherence will be monitored through parent self-report of home practice.</interventions>
    <comparator>Children's speech will be monitored during a baseline period of 3-6 weeks prior to the commencement of intervention. This will serve as the control for each participant. No treatment will be administered during this period.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pre-treatment and post-treatment comparison of performance on: the Diagnostic Evaluation of Articulation and Phonology (Dodd, Hua, Crosbie, Holm &amp; Ozanne, 2002); the Phonological Assessment of Collapses of Contrast (Baker, 2013); the Polysyllable Preschool Test (Baker, 2013); through a connected speech sample, and; on probes of treated and untreated words (e.g. the baseline probe). These are all measures of speech accuracy, and form a composite outcome.</outcome>
      <timepoint>These will be collected at the initial (pre-treatment) assessment, immediate follow-up assessment (immediately following the final treatment session) and final follow-up assessment (four weeks after the final treatment session).

Probe data will be collected once per week during the baseline phase (e.g. 3 to 6 times depending on which baseline group the child is randomised to), and weekly during the treatment phase. It will also be conducted at the immediate follow-up assessment (immediately following the final treatment session) and final follow-up assessment (four weeks after the final treatment session).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parents ability to implement the multiple oppositions approach, as measured by analysis of treatment fidelity. 

This will include: assessment of number of home treatment sessions completed according to a home treatment diary, and; inclusion of key aspects of the intervention, as measured through parent self-report and an audio recording of four randomly allocated home-based sessions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Parents will be asked to record how often they completed home treatment each week.

Inclusion of key aspects of intervention will be measured at four (4) randomly allocated time points during the 9 week treatment phase of the study. Parents will be asked to complete a self-checklist of their inclusion of key aspects of the intervention, and will audio record these home treatment activities for analysis by the research team.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Children recruited to this study will meet the following inclusion criteria:
Aged 3 years 0 months to 5 years 11 months
Willing to participate
Diagnosis of a speech sound disorder that is appropriate to treat using the multiple oppositions intervention approach (i.e. at least 6 sounds consistently in error across 2 or 3 manner categories of consonant production)
Normal receptive language, normal hearing and oral structure and function, and no other concomitant developmental diagnoses (e.g., autism)
English as strongest or equal-strongest language

Primary caregivers will meet the following inclusion criteria:
Willingness to attend weekly intervention sessions at The Universitys speech pathology in Lidcombe and complete home practice activities between sessions, given training
Functional level of English</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>3</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>6</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>None</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>This is a multiple baseline across participants single-subject design. Participants will be randomly allocated to a baseline condition (i.e. 3, 4, 5 or 6 baseline probes). All participants will receive the same intervention.

Sealed opaque envelopes will be used to conceal allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>There are four baseline conditions. We will collect 3, 4, 5 or 6 baseline probes from participating children. Each child will be randomly assigned to a baseline length using concealed allocation. That is, cards with baseline duration (i.e. 3, 4, 5 or 6) will be placed in opaque envelopes.

An independent person will randomly draw an envelope for each participant upon their enrolment in the study.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This is a multiple baseline across participants single-subject design.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Data from the intervention study (such as changes to production of speech sounds) will be plotted and analysed using visual analysis (Kazdin, 2011). Additionally, pre-, post- and follow-up assessment results will be compared for each participant using ANOVAs and other statistical methods as appropriate. Effect sizes for intervention will be calculated according to procedures outlined in Gierut et al. (2015). 

Qualitative data from the post-intervention interviews will be analysed using thematic analysis. This is a qualitative analysis method commonly used for identifying and reporting patterns within interview data (Braun &amp; Clarke, 2006). 

Sample size calculations were not performed.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>23/09/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>22/02/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>12</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>5</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>5/07/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Faculty of Health Sciences, University of Sydney 
75 East Street, Lidcombe 
NSW 2141</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Faculty of Health Sciences, University of Sydney 
75 East Street, Lidcombe 
NSW 2141</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to determine if intervention for speech problems in preschool-aged children is effective when delivered by parents and a speech pathologist. Specifically, this study will determine if multiple oppositions intervention, an approach established as effective when delivered intensively by a speech pathologist, is still effective when modified and delivered by parents in conjunction with a speech pathologist, with children who have a speech sound disorder.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>HREC The University of Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Margaret Telfer Building (K07)
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/08/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/04/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Elise Baker</name>
      <address>Speech Pathology
Building C43S
Cumberland Campus
The University of Sydney
Lidcombe, NSW, 2141</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 9121</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>elise.baker@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Ellie Sugden</name>
      <address>Speech Pathology
Building C43S
Cumberland Campus
The University of Sydney
Lidcombe, NSW, 2141</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 9642</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ellie.sugden@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Elise Baker</name>
      <address>Speech Pathology
Building C43S
Cumberland Campus
The University of Sydney
Lidcombe, NSW, 2141</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 9121</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>elise.baker@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Ellie Sugden</name>
      <address>Speech Pathology
Building C43S
Cumberland Campus
The University of Sydney
Lidcombe, NSW, 2141</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 9642</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ellie.sugden@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>