<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83196">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/09/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/12/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000611325</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Russells Viper Coagulopathy Fresh Frozen Plasma Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised controlled trial of fresh frozen plasma to speed the recovering of venom induced consumption coagulopathy in patients with Russell's Viper envenoming in Sri Lanka.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Snake Envenoming</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Clotting disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intravenous fresh frozen plasma, 10mL/kg up to 4 units, within 4 hours of the commencement of first antivenom therapy. Antivenom treatment will be according to the current recommendation in Sril Lanka of 20 vials of Indian polyvalent antisnake venom (VINS or Haffkine) administered over 1 hour intravenously.</interventions>
    <comparator>Intravenous normal saline, 10mL/kg, within 4 hours of the commencement of first antivenom therapy. Antivenom treatment will be according to the current recommendation in Sril Lanka of 20 vials of Indian polyvalent antisnake venom (VINS or Haffkine) administered over 1 hour intravenously.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of patients with a significant return of coagulation function defined by an International Normalised Ratio (INR) &lt; 2.0 (or prothrombin time (PT) &lt; 24 seconds where INR was not performed)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 hours after antivenom treatment is commenced</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The frequency of major adverse outcomes in the fresh frozen plasma (FFP) arm compared to the non-FFP arm. Major adverse outcomes will be defined as: 
1.	Severe anaphylaxis according to the Brown Criteria (this will be recorded and no attempt will be made to attribute to antivenom or FFP)
2.	Transfusion-Related Acute Lung Injury (TRALI) according to the following criteria:
(i)	Acute onset within 6 hours of the administration of FFP or antivenom
(ii)	Hypoxaemia: pO2 &lt; 90% or other evidence of hypoxaemia if oxygen saturation not available.  
(iii)	Bilateral infiltrates on a frontal chest X-ray (if no X-ray available then this criteria will be waived)
(iv)	No evidence of circulatory overload/left atrial hypertension
(v)	No preceding acute lung injury
(vi)	No temporal relationship to an alternative risk factor for acute lung injury
3.	Death occurring prior to discharge from hospital.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Any time during the study which will continue until the patient is discharged from hospital. All patients will be seen by study investigators every 8 hours during the study.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvement in clotting function and increase in clotting factors measured by blood analyis at 3 hours and 6 hours:
a.	Fibrinogen
b.	Factor V
c.	Factor VIII
d.	Prothrombin
e.	Factor X</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 3 hours and 6 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time from commencing antivenom until discharge from hospital (hours)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Discharge from hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Major bleeding, as defined by the International Society on Thrombosis and Haemostasis5:
(i)	Fatal bleeding, 
(ii)	Symptomatic bleeding in a critical area or organ, such as intracranial, intraspinal, intraocular, retroperitoneal, intra-articular or pericardial, or intramuscular with compartment syndrome,
(iii)	Bleeding causing a fall in haemoglobin level of 20 g/L or more, or leading to transfusion of two or more units of whole blood or red cells.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Bleeding will be assessed by clinical examination when the patient is seen daily on ward rounds and every 8 hours by the study team up until the time of discharge from hospital.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>a)	Venom induced consumption coagulopathy defined as: whole blood clotting time (WBCT) &gt; 20 minutes
b)	No known adverse reactions to blood products
c)	Antivenom is or will be administered to treat the patient
d)	Up to a maximum of 4 units of FFP is available and can be commenced to the patient within 4 hours of commencing antivenom.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>14</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>a)	Age &lt; 14 year
b)	Pregnancy</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Once a snake envenoming case is identified by the research assistants or investigators the patient will be assessed for suitability for inclusion in the study. If they meet the inclusion criteria they will be consented to the study. The patient will be randomly allocated to receive either 10mL/kg of FFP (up to a maximum of 4 units) over 60 minutes or 10mL/kg of normal saline over 60 minutes. 

Allocation will be done by the research team contacting an "off-site" person who will provide the randomisation to them over the phone.</concealment>
    <sequence>An adaptive biased coin randomisation schedule will be used. This will be done by having simple randomisation on a study hand held computer and then uploading recruited cases with baseline details and treatment allocation to a central database. The central database will be monitored by an independent member of the South Asian Clinical Toxicology Research Collaboration who will not be involved in patient treatment, random allocation or data collection. If the randomisation becomes unbalanced (ie. &gt; 50% or &lt;50% in the FFP arm) then the probability will be biased to correct the imbalance (ie. 0.6/0.4 instead of 0.5/0.5) by implementing a biased coin randomisation to the PDAs. In addition to balancing FFP across all patients, there will be additional minimisation protocol based on the time of antivenom after the bite with patients being put into 3 groups: AVS &lt; 4hrs from bite; AVS between 4 and 8 hours after the bite; and AVS &gt; 8 hours after the bite.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>700</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Withdrawn</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason>Lack of funding/staff/facilities</withdrawnreason>
    <withdrawnreasonother>As above</withdrawnreasonother>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sri Lanka</country>
      <state>Central and North Central</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Geoff Isbister</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Calvary Mater Newcastle Hospital
Edith St
Waratah NSW 2298</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Indika Gawarammana</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Dept of Clinical Medicine
Faculty of Medicine
University Dr
University of Peradeniya
Peradeniya</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Sri Lanka</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is a controlled trial of factor replacement (fresh frozen plasma) in snake bite coagulopathy from Russell's viper bite, after a neutralising dose of antivenom to determine whether it will result in a rapid return of clotting function.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Committee on Research and Ethical Review</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Faculty of Medicine
University Peradeniya
University Dr
Peradeniya</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/04/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2008/EC/26</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Sri Lanka</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Geoff Isbister</name>
      <address>Calvary Mater Newcastle Hospital
Edith St
Waratah NSW 2298</address>
      <phone>+61 2 49211211</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>geoff.isbister@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Indika Gawarammana</name>
      <address>Dept of Clinical Medicine
Faculty of Medicine
University of Peradeniya
University Dr
Peradeniya</address>
      <phone>+94814479822</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>geoff.isbister@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Sri Lanka</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Geoff Isbister</name>
      <address>Calvary Mater Newcastle Hospital
Edith St
Waratah NSW 2298</address>
      <phone>+61 2 49211211</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 49211870</fax>
      <email>geoff.isbister@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Geoffrey Isbister</name>
      <address>Calvary Mater Newcastle
Waratah NSW 2298</address>
      <phone>0438466471</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>geoff.isbister@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>