<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="361997">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/01/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/01/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000134820</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial of high-normal dose protein compared to standard-normal dose protein intake after cardiac surgery.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Nephro-protective effects of L-amino acids versus standard care/usual care in cardiac surgery adult patients at risk of developing acute kidney injury. A pilot randomised controlled trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Cardiac Nephro-Protective Trial</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cardiac Bypass Surgery Patients</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Acute Kidney Injury</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Supplementary infusion of L-amino acids to achieve 2g/kg/day total protein intake on each day that they have a central venous catheter insitu.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard Care / Usual Care, which encompasses all aspects of standard / usual care delivered post operatively to cardiac bypass surgery patients.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of days of clinically significant renal dysfunction, assessed and defined using the Brussels Table standards (Bernard GR, Doig GS, Hudson LD et al. Qualification of organ failure for clinical trials and clinical practice. Am J Res Crit Care Med 1995;151:A323).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration of Hospital Stay</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severity of renal dysfunction, assessed and defined using the Acute Dialysis Quality Initiative's published criteria (Bellomo R, Ronco C, Kellum JA et al. Acute renal failure-definition, outcome measures, animal models, fluid therapy and information technology needs: The second International Consensus Conference of the Acute Dialysis Quality Initiative Group. Crit Care 2004;8:R204-212).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured during Hospital Stay</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of days of renal replacement therapy (RRT) delivered Assessed by prospectively observing and recording renal replacement therapy (RRT) delivered to enrolled patients.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured during Hospital Stay</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life assessed using RAND-36.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at Day 90 Post randomisation into the trial</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Need for dialysis - i.e. is the patient receiving or scheduled to receive any form of dialysis (continuous haemodyalsis, intermittent peritoneal dialysis etc) at Day 90</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at Day 90 post randomisation into the trial</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of ICU and Hospital Stay. Assessed by prospectively observing and recording Intensive Care Unit (ICU) and Hospital Stay</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at Day 90 post randomisation into the trial</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of Mechanical Ventilation. Assessed by prospectively observing and recording Mechanical Ventilation delivered to enrolled patients.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured during ICU Stay</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Days of antibiotic use. Asessed by prospectively observing and recording Antibiotics delivered to enrolled patients on each day of Hospital Stay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured during Hospital Stay</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients with pre-existing Chronic Kidney Disease Stage 3 or higher (eGFR &lt;60 ml/min/1.73m2) who are scheduled to undergo on-pump valve replacement or on-pump coronary artery bypass graft surgery expected to require longer than one hour on-pump will be considered eligible. Unless at least one of the Exclusion Criteria listed below is met, these patients will be approached to provide informed consent to participate.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients will be considered ineligible for the trial if any of the following exclusion criteria are met at the time of screening: 1)Was the actual on-pump surgical time less than 1 hour; 2) The patient does not have a central venous access line through which the study intervention could be delivered; 3) The patient is not able to tolerate at least 1L of fluid volume per day; 4) The patient is currently less than 18 years old; 5) Is the patient receiving NSAID, with specific emphasis on COX-2 inhibitors during their ICU or hospital stay; 6) Is the patient currently enrolled into a clinical trial evaluating a nitric oxide (NO) inhibitor; 7) Is the patient receiving Acetazolamide, which is a diuretic that works on the proximal tubule; 8) Is the patient's current eGFR &lt; 20 ml/min/1.73 m2; 9) Is the patient currently known to have severe Acute Kidney Injury, defined as a Current serum creatinine (SCr) increased 3 times pre-acute illness value OR SCr &gt;350umol/L with recent increase greater than 44 umol/L; 10) Is the patient receiving or scheduled to begin dialysis/renal replacement therapy; 11) Has the patient ever had a kidney transplant; 12) Is the patient expected to receive palliative care only and is not expected to survive ICU or hospital discharge; 13) Is the patient moribund and not expected to survive 24 hrs; 14) Is the patient brain dead or suspected to be brain dead; 15) Has the patient been taking Nardil (phenelzine) within the last 6 weeks; 16) Has the patient previously been enrolled and randomised into this study; 17) Does the patient have a documented contraindication to the study intervention (IV amino acids) as listed on the TGA product licensing document.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Centralised randomisation by computer using a password protected webserver. As in any centralised method, individual patient treatment assignment will not be revealed until the potential participant is determined to be truly eligible for the trial and patient identifiers are submitted over the web to the centralised computer. Persons recruiting patients into the trial will not be able to predict or influence treatment assignments, hence allocation is concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerised (SAS)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>72</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Sydney
Sydney NSW 2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>North Shore Heart Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>North Shore Heart Research Foundation    
PO Box 543
St Leonards, NSW 1590</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this research study is to investigate whether a treatment involving the delivery of protein supplements into the vein (intravenous) can protect cardiac bypass surgery patients from the onset of a new kidney injury, when compared with standard treatment.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Harbour HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Royal North Shore Hospital
Building 51
Pacific Hwy
St Leonards
NSW 2065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/01/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Prof Gordon Doig</name>
      <address>Royal North Shore Hospital,
Intensive Care Unit, Level 6,
Pacific Hwy,
St Leonards, NSW, 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9926 8656</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gdoig@med.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Prof Gordon Doig</name>
      <address>Royal North Shore Hospital,
Intensive Care Unit, Level 6,
Pacific Hwy,
St Leonards, NSW, 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9926 8656</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gdoig@med.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Elizabeth Sweetman</name>
      <address>Royal North Shore Hospital,
Intensive Care Unit, Level 6,
Pacific Hwy,
St Leonards, NSW, 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9926 8656</phone>
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>