<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369659">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/11/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/11/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001287527</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A PHASE I , Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Pharmacokinetic Study of the Chrono Nicotine Replacement Therapy System</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Pharmacokinetic Study of the Chrono Nicotine Replacement Therapy System for adult male smokers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1176-7190 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>PK2015-002</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Smoking cessation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>To characterize the pharmacokinetic (PK) concentration profile of nicotine delivered by the drug delivery system / device. This study will use  a wearable drug delivery prototype device that is strapped to the arm.  The  device delivers nicotine transdermally to achieve repeated peaks and troughs throughout the day.  By tailoring these doses to pre-empt the regular craving and peak smoking episodes that smokers experience during the day; the product may significantly increase the efficacy of existing nicotine replacement therapy (NRT) products.
The nicotine formulation - 6% weight per volume (w/v) concentration in a 50/50 volume per volume (v/v) ethanol/water (EtOH/H20) mixture.  A bolus of 125 microliters  of nicotine or placebo will be delivered to the subjects via the device at Time = 0, 0.5, 1, 7, 7.5, and 13 hours. The solutions are immediately absorbed onto Transdermal Membrane of the devices. Subject are confined for 30 hours and followed up for 7 days post treatment.</interventions>
    <comparator>The placebo formulation - a 50/50 volume per volume (v/v) ethanol/water (EtOH/H20) mixture only</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To characterize the pharmacokinetic (PK) concentration profile of nicotine delivered by the drug delivery system. 

Pharmacokinetic Analysis: Pharmacokinetic endpoints (e.g., Tmax, Cmax, AUCs, t1/2) will be evaluated and summarized using descriptive statistics.  Nicotine concentrations also will be summarized with descriptive statistics.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pharmacokinetic (PK) sampling: blood samples will be collected prior to the first dose, every 30 minutes for the first 3 hours, hourly thereafter through Hour 16, then every 2 hours through Hour 30</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess safety, tolerability of the drug delivery system / device</outcome>
      <timepoint>Adverse event (AE) assessment and vital signs (including temperature, pulse, respiratory rate, and systolic/diastolic blood pressure) will be monitored and collected prior to the first dose, every 30 minutes for the first 3 hours, hourly thereafter through Hour 16, then every 2 hours by the Investigator or designed staff for the 30 hours of confinement and at the Day 7 Follow-up visit. 

Clinical safety labs (chemistry and hematology) will be assessed at screening, admission and follow-up. Laboratory values that are out of range will be identified and may be repeated at the Investigators discretion.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess nicotine craving post administration of nicotine formulation verses placebo formulation by the device </outcome>
      <timepoint>The Fagerstrom Test for Nicotine Dependence (FTND) will be completed prior to study drug dosing on Day 1.

Cravings assessment:  The 10-item Question of Smoking Urges (QSU) will be completed prior to study drug dosing on Day 1.  A single question cravings assessment will be performed at 5 minutes (+/- 1 minute) after every 2 hours through Hour 22.  

The QSU will be repeated at hour 14. 

The Mood and physical symptoms scale (MPSS) assessment will be completed at hour 24 to obtain a retrospective assessment of their cravings</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Caucasian males, aged 1850 years, inclusive.
2. Smokers consuming on average between 20 and 40 cigarettes per day
3. Body mass index (BMI) between 18.50 and 29.99 kg/m2.
4. Ability to understand study procedures and provide written informed consent.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Subjects with screening clinical laboratory tests, physical examination (PE), or electrocardiogram (ECG) outside normal range 
2. Subjects who have known or suspected infection with tuberculosis (TB), human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), hepatitis B virus (HBV), or hepatitis C virus (HCV).  
3. Subjects with positive screening urine test for non-prescription drugs, including opiates, amphetamines, barbiturates, benzodiazepines, methadone, cocaine and its metabolites, or cannabinoids. 
4. Subjects who are mentally or legally incapacitated, or have a history of psychiatric disorder.
5. Subjects with severe hepatic, renal, cardiovascular, endocrine, or hematologic diseases, or with a history or illness 
6. Subjects with any sign of infection, with dermatologic diseases, or any condition that would inhibit transdermal absorption.
7. Subjects who consume more than two alcoholic beverages per day on average 
8. Subjects who require any medications that may interfere with the absorption, metabolism, or excretion of the study drug.
9. Subjects that have tattoos that could interfere with skin assessments.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Pharmacokinetics</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Analysis Methods for the Primary and Secondary Endpoints and Testing Procedures:
Plasma concentrations of nicotine will be quantitated after administration of multiple doses via the device.  
No power calculations were performed for this study.  All comparisons will be considered exploratory and hypothesis generating.  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>19/09/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>24/09/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>24</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>24</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Chrono Therapeutics Australia Pty LTD</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>C/- MPR Group Pty LTD Floor 19, HWT Tower
40 City Road
Southbank, VIC  3006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Chrono Therapeutics Australia Pty LTD</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>C/- MPR Group Pty LTD Floor 19, HWT Tower
40 City Road
Southbank, VIC  3006
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is a Phase I, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled PK study of nicotine levels over a 30 hour period in healthy Caucasian male volunteers, 12 per arm (blinded), who are smokers, using the Chrono Nicotine Replacement Therapy System.
Study participation will involve:
*Screening: 1 site visit (up to 14 days prior to Day 1)
* Study Treatment: 30 hours in an in-patient facility
* Follow-up: 1 site visit (within 7 to 10 days of discharge)
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Health (ABN 27 318 956 319)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/09/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>388/15</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/08/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jason Lickliter </name>
      <address>Nucleus Network Pty LTD
The Burnet Tower, 5th Floor
89 Commercial Road
Melbourne, VIC  3004
</address>
      <phone>+61 407 527 307</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9076 8911</fax>
      <email>J.Lickliter@nucleusnetwork.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Elizabeth Glatz </name>
      <address>Nucleus Network Pty LTD
The Burnet Tower, 5th Floor
89 Commercial Road
Melbourne, VIC  3004
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 8921  </phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9076 8911</fax>
      <email>E.Glatz@nucleusnetwork.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Patricia Oto</name>
      <address>Chrono Therapeutics 
3953 Point Eden Way
Hayward, California 
94545 USA</address>
      <phone>+1 (510) 362-7788</phone>
      <fax>+1 (510) 362-7787</fax>
      <email>poto@chronothera.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Taylor Kilfoil</name>
      <address>C/- MPR Group Pty LTD Floor 19, HWT Tower
40 City Road
Southbank, VIC  3006</address>
      <phone>04008880403</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>taylorkilfoil@inclin.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>