<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367134">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/09/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/10/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001105639</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Fit4Two - Usability and initial efficacy testing of a website-delivered behaviour change intervention designed to promote physical activity among pregnant women.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Fit4Two - Usability and initial efficacy testing of a website-delivered behaviour change intervention designed to promote physical activity among pregnant women.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1162-0529 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>Fit4Two</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pregnancy
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Sedentary behaviour
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Physical inactivity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal pregnancy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study is a 4 week pilot 2-arm RCT investigating the acceptability, feasibility and preliminary efficacy of an online behaviour change intervention designed to promote exercise among women during pregnancy. Participants will be recruited from the Rockhampton region of Australia through collaboration with partnering organisations.The primary outcome is weekly physical activity levels measured using accelerometers. The trial will be conducted and reported according to CONSORT guidelines.

Arm 1- Fit4Two Intervention Group

Participants randomised into this condition will be given access to a theory-based computer-tailored program over a 4 week period. Each week participants will complete modules that will provide advice and feedback unique to the individual that relates to key determinants of physical activity adoption and maintenance among breast cancer survivors (as stipulated by previous research in the field and Social Cognitive Theory). The advice participants receive will be tailored using information derived from individual weekly assessments. Each module will take approximately 30 minutes for participants to complete. This also includes the participants receiving and reading through their tailored feedback.

Arm 2  Fit4Two Control Group 

Participants randomised into this group will receive usual care and be given access to the resources section of the website only for the duration of the study. Upon completion, participants in this group will also be given full access to the website.

Adherence to the intervention will be monitored through computer software that can see how often participants logged on, what modules they completed / did not complete, how long they spent on the site etc.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants randomised into this group will receive usual care and be given access to the resources section of the website only for the duration of the study. Upon completion of the 4 week intervention period, participants in this group will also be given full access to the website.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome variables, minutes of PA (aerobic and resistance) per week will be assessed using an adapted version (Liebreich, Plotnikoff et al. 2009) of the validated Godin Leisure-Time Exercise Questionnaire (GLTEQ) (Godin and Shepard 1997).

The adapted version will incorporate a resistance training (RT) measure (Plotnikoff, Taylor et al. 2006; Liebreich, Plotnikoff et al. 2009) that asks participants to report the frequency (times per week) and duration (average times per session) of resistance training activities on average over the last month

GeneActiv Accelerometers will also be used to measure PA at baseline and immediate follow up (4 week post baseline) for 7 days at each point.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and immediate follow-up (4 weeks post baseline)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence to PA guidelines

Participants will be categorised as "inactive" (not doing any activity), "insufficiently active (not meeting the guidelines)" or "sufficiently active (meeting the guidelines)" based on whether they meet the exercise during pregnancy guidelines (outlined by Motolla 2011).

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, week 1-4 and follow-up (4 weeks post baseline)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Social Cognitive Determinants of Physical Activity (outcome expectations, self-efficacy and goal setting) 

Outcome expectations:
Measured on a 5 point Likert scale where 1=strongly disagree, 2=disagree, 3=undecided, 4=agree, 5=strongly agree. Based on validated work of Fjeldsoe, Miller and Marshall, 2013.

Self-efficacy:
Measured on a 5 point Likert scale where 1=not at all confident, 2=slightly confident, 3=moderately confident, 4=very confident, 5=extremely confident. Based on validated work of Plotnikoff, Blanchard, Hotz and Rhodes, 2001.

Goal Setting:
Measured on a 5 point Likert scale where 1=strongly disagree, 2=disagree, 3=undecided, 4=agree, 5=strongly agree. Based on validated work of Rhodes, Hunt Matherson and Mark (2010).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, week 1-4 and follow-up (4 weeks post baseline)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Usability and Acceptability of website (SUS - The system Usability Scale, Brooke (1986) modified for the current study) will be determined by a series of questions as a part of the follow-up questionnaire. The questions are multiple-choice based (example item: 'did the material catch your attention?') requiring participants to rate their responses on a Likert scale (e.g., '1 = not at all' - '5 = very much'). The assessment will also contain one open-ended questions inviting participants to provide additional feedback. </outcome>
      <timepoint>5 weeks post-baseline (Immediate post-intervention follow-up) </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Eligibality Criteria:
must be currently pregnant
must be 18+ years of age
must be able to read and write in english
must be between 10-20 weeks gestation
must be considered healthy and free of pregancy contraindications, or have medical approval to participate</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion Criteria:
not currently pregnant
not 18+ years of age
not able to read and write in english
not between 10-20 weeks gestation
not considered healthy and free of pregancy contraindications, or have medical approval to participate</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Willing participants will log onto intervention website where they will be required to complete a screening eligibality questionnaire. If eligible, participants then register their contact details. Participants are then contacted and enrolled into intervention. Software randomly allocates the participants to either intervention or control upon successful enrollment</concealment>
    <sequence>Software randomly allocated the participants to either intervention or control upon successful enrollment</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Standard data cleaning procedures will be used. Descriptive statistics will be conducted on all baseline variables. ANCOVA will be used to assess between group differences at the primary endpoint. Only baseline physical activity will be included as a covariate in the model. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/10/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/04/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>64</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>4701 - North Rockhampton</postcode>
    <postcode>4700 - Rockhampton</postcode>
    <postcode>4702 - Gracemere</postcode>
    <postcode>4703 - Yeppoon</postcode>
    <postcode>4714 - Mount Morgan</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Central Queensland Medicare Local</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 1
44A William Street
Rockhampton QLD  4700</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>CQUniversity
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>CQUniversity
Bruce Highway
Rockhampton QLD 4702</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The 'Fit4Two - Usability and initial efficacy testing of a website-delivered behaviour change intervention. The Fit4Two study is a 4 week pilot 2-arm RCT investigating the acceptability, feasibility and preliminary efficacy of a behaviour change intervention designed to promote exercise among women during pregnancy. Participants will be recruited from the Rockhampton region of Australia through collaboration with partnering organisations. The primary outcome is
weekly physical activity levels measured using valid and reliable accelerometers. The trial will be conducted and reported
according CONSORT guidelines. Participants randomly allocated to the Fit4Two intervention group will receive a web-based
intervention, which will provide them with personalised advice based on information derived from an online assessment.
Participants randomly allocated to the control group will receive usual care, access to the resources library of the program, but
no computer-tailored feedback. The program will be delivered at no cost to participants. Participants will now also receive resources and referrals to other programs, services, 
and avenues for support. Each program participant will be provided with tailored physical activity advice and feedback to help them make a positive lifestyle change, which inturn might improve their health and the health of their baby and reduce chronic disease.
All respondents will be clearly informed that they SHOULD NOT participate in the study if they believe it may be unsafe or unhealthy for them to do so. This screening procedure has been used by similar studies. No adverse events have occurred. There is substantial evidence that increasing physical activity is safe and leads to health benefits rather than health damage in pregnant women. The information provided to participants will be evidence-based and reflect the physical activity guidelines for pregnant women. The trial will be aimed at pregnant women in their second trimester. The benefits (the evaluation of a potentially effective physical activity intervention that might improve health outcomes among pregnant women and their child) of this research largely outweigh the minimal risk to participants. Should there be any unanticipated difficulties, all participants are provided with contact details for the principal researcher.


</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.fit4two.org.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>CQUniversity Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>CQUniversity
Bruce Highway
Rockhampton, QLD, 4702</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/09/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H14/02-031</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Melanie Hayman</name>
      <address>Building 18/1.31
School of Medical and Applied Sciences
Bruce Highway 
CQUniversity, Rockhampton Campus, QLD 4702


</address>
      <phone>+61749232185</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.j.hayman@cqu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Melanie Hayman</name>
      <address>Building 18/1.31
School of Medical and Applied Sciences
Bruce Highway
CQUniversity, Rockhampton Campus, QLD 4702
</address>
      <phone>+61749232185</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.j.hayman@cqu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Melanie Hayman</name>
      <address>Building 18/1.31
School of Medical and Applied Sciences
Bruce Highway
CQUniversity, Rockhampton Campus, QLD 4702</address>
      <phone>+61749232185</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.j.hayman@cqu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Melanie Hayman</name>
      <address>Building 18/1.31
School of Medical and Applied Sciences
Bruce Highway
CQUniversity, Rockhampton Campus, QLD 4702</address>
      <phone>+61749232185</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.j.hayman@cqu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>