<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363042">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/09/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/09/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001028897</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Stepping Up Study: A Cluster Randomised Controlled Trial of team-based transition to insulin in primary care compared to usual care to improve HbA1c for patients with poorly controlled type 2 diabetes</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Stepping Up To Insulin: A Cluster Randomised Controlled Trial of team-based transition to insulin in primary care compared to usual care to improve HbA1c for patients with poorly controlled type 2 diabetes</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 diabetes (T2D)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Stepping Up program involves two elements that address key factors that are important and influential in the way insulin is initiated and titrated in general practice:
a. Supportive education for GP and Practice Nurse (PN) that addresses inter-professional culture and clarifies roles particularly in enhanced role for PN
b. Practice systems change that is congruent with work practices of GP and PN and needs of patients to facilitate timely introduction and titration of insulin glargine and glulisine
The Stepping Up program training will be delivered by the study team during practice visit. The 1-2 hour training session covers evidence around insulin initiation, common barriers and how to deal with them, motivational interviewing and goal setting strategies, and hands on familiarisation with insulin delivery systems and insulin titration tools. Case studies derived from general practices patients are used as the basis of the training. Referrals to an endocrinologist, diabetes educators or other health professionals will be part of management options for GPs managing study patients.
GP and PN will be supported by Study Diabetes Nurse Educator (DNE) as required during 12-month follow-up period via practice visits, telephone and emails to individualise and embed the model of care to their in-practice systems.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care by General Practitioners. This may involve referrals to an endocrinologist, diabetes educators or other health professionals.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>an absolute HbA1c reduction of 0.5% in the intervention group compared with the control group</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 12 months post baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>proportion of participants transferring to insulin</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 12 months post baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>the level of HbA1c at which insulin initiation occurs</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 12 months post baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>proportion of participants achieving adequate glycaemic control (HbA1c &lt;7%)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 12 months post baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>proportion of participants achieving individualised HbA1c targets according to the Australian Diabetes Society guidelines</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 12 months post baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>impact on psychometric scores as assessed using the Assessment of Quality of Life (AQoL-8D), Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9) and Problem Areas in Diabetes (PAID)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 12 months post baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>reduction in net healthcare utilisation and costs as assessed using Medicare Benefits Scheme and Pharmaceutical Benefits Scheme and Victorian Department of Health data linkage (subject to approval)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 12 months post baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. T2D patients who are insulin naive.
2. At least 2 oral hypoglycaemic agents (OHA)  (eg. metformin, sulphonylurea, TZDs, DPP-4 inhibitor) at maximal tolerated doses, or in the opinion of the responsible medical practitioner, insulin is deemed necessary.
3. Doses of the OHAs should be stable for at least 3 months prior to enrollment into the study (or medical practitioner discretion).
4. HbA1c&gt;=7.5% in the last 6 months 
5. T2D patients willing to monitor glucose levels at least twice daily.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Type 1 diabetes.
2. Previous or current treatment with insulin (excluding the short term (&lt;2 weeks) use of insulin in acute illness or during hospitalization).
3. Non-English speaking.
4. Significant cognitive impairment.
5. Impaired vision or any other physical handicap precluding reliable glucose monitoring administration of insulin.
6. Significant renal impairment (eGFR &lt; 20).
7. Any life-threatening illness.
8. Pregnancy or planned pregnancy.
9. Major psychiatric disorder.
10. Substance misuse (alcoholism, drug addiction, etc)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>General practices that employ a practice nurse will be recruited from the University of Melbourne database, the VicREN practice based Research Network and Victorian Medicare Local databases. The study will also be promoted through professional organisations such as RACGP and APNA. Practices will also be recruited using a snowballing method from key clinicians identified in the field. 
General practices that express an interest to take part will be asked to obtain a comprehensive list of eligible patients. Practices will use a range of search methods including their own electronic medical records database, the PEN clinical data extraction tool, or a list of HbA1c results from their local pathology providers. The study team will assist GP and PN to screen their patients.
Each practice will be allocated a practice ID once signed consents (at least one from GP and one from PN) are received by the research team and the practice has identified one or more eligible patients. The unit of randomisation is the general practice. Randomisation will occur prior to patient baseline assessment.

Patient recruitment involves: 
1. An invitation pack from the Practice inviting eligible patients to participate and 
2. follow-up call(s) from the PN and/or GP.
Patients who agree to participate will also be asked to sign the consent form and return it with the baseline demographic questionnaire in a reply paid envelope.  They will be asked to attend Melbourne Pathology to have HbA1c, lipids, U&amp;E and spot urine albumin:creatinine ratio tests.  
Patients who have HbA1c&gt;=7.5% will be eligible to participate and will be mailed a baseline survey.
Patient identification and recruitment can be repeated at 3 month intervals allowing patients to enter the study sequentially and ensuring the initiation of insulin and patient management is easily embedded within routine clinical work. Each practice will ideally recruit four to five patients to the study.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be stratified by:
1. practice size (&lt;=2 EFT GPs vs &gt;2 EFT GPs) ,
2. practice type (Community Health Centres vs private/corporate); and 
3. participation in the Australian Primary Care Collaboratives program (www.apcc.org.au). 
Randomisation will be undertaken by a statistician independent of the research team.  The statistician the will be blinded to practice stratification characteristics and random allocation. The Study Coordinator will assign codes specific to each practice stratification characteristics and group allocation. The statistician will generate a computerized random number in random block allocation. Practices will be randomised after consenting, prior to patient baseline data collection. The Study Coordinator will email stratification codes of consenting practice to the statistician who will inform the study team of practice random allocation codes by email within 24-48 hours. Stratification in random block randomisation method is required to minimize imbalances between study groups.
The research team will inform practices of their random allocation by phone call, fax or mail. Following randomisation, the research team will assist practices to identify and recruit more patients.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>2/11/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>11/04/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>290</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>266</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Primary Health Care and General Practice Academic Centre
200 Berkeley St
Carlton VIC 3053</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO BOx 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Roche Diagnostics Australia Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>31 Victoria Avenue
Castle Hill NSW 2154</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Sanofi Australia and New Zealand</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Talavera Corporate Centre, Building D, 12-24 Talavera Road, Macquarie Park, NSW 2113</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr John Furler</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Primary Health Care and General Practice Academic Centre
The University of Melbourne
200 Berkeley St Carlton VIC 3053</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Diabetes Australia Victoria</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>570 Elizabeth Street, Melbourne VIC 3000</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Melbourne EpiCentre</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>c/o The Royal Melbourne Hospital
RMH VIC 3050</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Prof Carl May</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Faculty of Health Sciences
Building 67 (Nightingale)
University of Southampton
Highfield Campus
University Road
Southampton SO17 1BJ</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>United Kingdom</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Prof Leonie Segal</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Nursing and Midwifery
Division of Health Sciences
University of South Australia
Playford Building P4-26, City East Campus
CEA-24
North Terrace, Adelaide, SA 5000</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Stepping Up is a cluster randomised controlled trial that examines the effectiveness of the Stepping Up program in general practice to help patients with poorly controlled type 2 diabetes for whom insulin is indicated move onto insulin in a timely evidence-based manner.
The Stepping Up program involves two elements that address key factors we have found to be important and influential in the way insulin is or is not initiated in general practice. These elements are:
-supportive education for GP, Practice Nurse (PN) and Credentialed Diabetes EducatorRegistered Nurse (CDE-RN) that addresses inter-professional culture and clarifies roles and 
-practice systems change that is congruent with work practices of GP and PN and needs of patients to facilitate timely introduction and titration of insulin.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.gp.unimelb.edu.au/stepping_up</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee, the University of Melbourne</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 5, Alan Gilbert Building,
161 Barry St (corner Grattan St)
Carlton VIC 3053</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/05/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC1237406</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Dr John Furler</name>
      <address>Primary Health Care and General Practice Academic Centre
The University of Melbourne
200 Berkeley St Carlton VIC 3053</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 4747</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9347 6136</fax>
      <email>j.furler@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>John Furler</name>
      <address>Primary Health Care and General Practice Academic Centre
The University of Melbourne
200 Berkeley St Carlton VIC 3053</address>
      <phone>+61383444747</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9347 6136</fax>
      <email>j.furler@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Irene Blackberry</name>
      <address>Primary Health Care and General Practice Academic Centre
The University of Melbourne
200 Berkeley St Carlton VIC 3053</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 3373</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9347 6136</fax>
      <email>i.blackberry@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>John Furler</name>
      <address>Dept General Practice
The University of Melbourne
200 Berkeley St Carlton VIC 3053</address>
      <phone>+61383444747</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.furler@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>