<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370197">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/03/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/05/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000620426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparing success rates of two surgical techniques for involutional entropion of the lower eyelid: the everting sutures and the lateral tarsal strip.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Prospective randomised controlled trial to compare success rates of two surgical techniques for involutional entropion of the lower eyelid:the everting sutures and the lateral tarsal strip.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn> U1111-1180-0298</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition> Involutional entropion of the lower eyelid.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients suffering from primary involutional entropion will participate in the study.  Patients will be randomised to everting sutures technique (commonly used)  and  to lateral tarsal strip technique (commonly not used as standard practice). 
The lateral tarsal strip technique:
Cantholysis of the lateral palpebral ligament.
Preparation of an outer tarsus flap (sling) by removing the dermis, the orbicularis muscle  and the conjuctiva.
Flap fixation by using sutures 5.0 to  the temporal orbit periosteum .
Wound restorarion by using 6.0 sutures.
These procedures will be performed by the qualified ophthalmologist Elias Nakos expert in oculoplastics.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group: The everting sutures technique.
It consists in the insertion of three (3) absorbable sutures 6.0 with double needle obliquely from the lower limit of the palpebral conjuctiva through rhe skin of the eyelid below the eyelashes.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Success rate.
The success is assessed by clinical examination. At the follow-up visit, eyelid is asessed in the primary and downgaze position.
The patients will also asked to squeeze their eyelids closed to detect any latent recurrence.
The surgical success is defined as complete resolution of the inward eyelid margin rotation  and symptoms.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 (six) months and 1 (one) year follow up..</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life by using the VQF-25 Questionnaire preoperatively and at six months follow-up.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Preoperatively and at 6(six) months..</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Complications rate  by using clinical examination and asking the patient for possible problems postoperatively.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 (six) months and 1 (one) year follow up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Lower eyelid involutional entropion.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>25</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Scarry entropion.
Another surgery for the same reason.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>simple randomisation using a randomisation table from a statistic book</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>About 40 to 60 patients is a satisfacory number of patients if we take under consideration the prevalence of the lower eyelid entropion in the general population.
Methods: 
  A.t-test :  1.  independent samples t- test and  
                  2. paired samples t-test. 
In these two t tests, the null hypothesis being tested is that quantitative variable average values in both populations from which the planned "samples" are derived are equal. Thus, the p-value, the difference between the means of two "samples" and the 95% confidence interval for the difference,  are calculated. 
When the p-value is less than a value, which is usually defined at the level of 0.05, then the null hypothesis is rejected and the difference between the means of the two populations are statistically significant.     
 B.  Non-parametric methods which take into account the provisions of observations rather than actual values of observations, making  possible their application in the case of 'samples' with a small number of observations. In non-parametric methods, the null hypothesis is not the comparison of average  populations prices  from which they derive the "samples", but comparing medians. 
 Where the "samples" are two and independently the statistical test of Wilcoxon (wilcoxon rank-sum test devices) is used..
 In the case where the "samples" are two, but in pairs, so for each observation in the first group there is a corresponding remark in the second group, the Wilcoxon  signed-ranked test or sign test  will be used.        
 C. If i need to make some correlation, the type and size of the linear relationship between two quantitative variables that follow the normal distribution is estimated by the correlation coefficient of Pearson (Pearson's coefficient of correlation), while when one of the two quantitative variables  does not follow the normal distribution, then the correlation coefficient of Spearman provisions is used (Spearman's rank correlation coefficient).                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>13/05/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>1/02/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>54</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>54</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/02/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Aristotle university medical school, lab of experimental ophthalmology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University city of Thessaloniki, Thessaloniki, Agiou Dimitriou st, 54124.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Greece</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Aristotle university medical school</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University city of Thessaloniki, Thessaloniki, Agiou Dimitriou st, 54124.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Greece</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>AHEPA University General Hospital of Thessaloniki</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Kiriakidi 1, Thessaloniki, 54621.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Greece</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>424 General Military Hospital of Thessaloniki</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Egnatia ring road of Thessaloniki, Thessaloniki, 56429.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Greece</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>NONE</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>NONE</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The surgical treatment of the involutional entropion of the lower eyelid by using two techniques:
1.	the everting sutures and 
2.	the lateral tarsal strip technique. 
Prospective randomized comparative study of these two techniques.
I want to find which is the best procedure, the outcome  of anatomical and functional recovery over time and their contribution to improving patients quality of life.
SURGICAL TECHNIQUES:
1.  the everting sutures technique:
It consists in the insertion of three (3) absorbable sutures 6.0 with double needle  obliquely from the lower limit of the palpebral conjunctiva through  the skin of the eyelid below the eyelashes.
2. the lateral tarsal strip technique:
Cantholysis of the lateral palpebral ligament.
Preparation of an outer tarsus flap (sling) by removing the dermis, the orbicularis muscle  and the conjuctiva.
Flap fixation by using sutures 5.0 to  the temporal orbit periosteum .
Wound restorarion by using 6.0 sutures.
Based on the existing literature, there are some questions to be answered:
Which  is the most appropriate surgical rehabilitation technique for the lower involutional eyelid entropion with the best success rates, fewer complications and the lower recurrence rates?
 Importance:
The result of the investigation may lead to the predominance of one technique over the other and to establish criteria for their selection.
 

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bioethics commitee of Aristotle university medical school</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University city of Thessaloniki, Thessaloniki, Agiou Dimitriou st, 54124.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/10/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/07/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Greece</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nakos Elias</name>
      <address>Eye Clinic, 424 General Military Hospital of Thessaloniki, Thessaloniki, ring road Egnatia, 56429</address>
      <phone>+306949194259</phone>
      <fax>+302310638193</fax>
      <email>nakos342000@yahoo.gr</email>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nakos Elias</name>
      <address>Eye Clinic, 424 General Military Hospital of Thessaloniki, Thessalonki, ring road Egnatia, 56429</address>
      <phone>+306949194259</phone>
      <fax>+302310638193</fax>
      <email>nakos342000@yahoo.gr</email>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nakos Elias</name>
      <address>Eye Clinic, 424 General Military Hospital of Thessaloniki, Thessaloniki, ring road Egnatia, 56429</address>
      <phone>+306949194259</phone>
      <fax>+302310638193</fax>
      <email>nakos342000@yahoo.gr</email>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nakos Elias</name>
      <address>Eye Clinic, 424 General Military Hospital of Thessaloniki, Thessaloniki, ring road Egnatia, 56429.</address>
      <phone>+306949194259</phone>
      <fax>+302310638193</fax>
      <email>nakos342000@yahoo.gr</email>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>