<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82801">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/05/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/05/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000241336</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Asphelia Trichuris Suis Ova in Moderately Active Crohn's Disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Trial Of Asp1002 (Trichuris Suis Ova [Tso]) Therapy For Moderately Active Crohns Disease</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Crohn's Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Inflammatory bowel disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>15ml(167eggs/ml) oral Asp1002 (Trichuris Suis Ova [Tso]) taken every fortnight for 12 weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>The investigational placebo product is an aqueous suspension of phosphate-stabilized buffer (pH 3) in a volume of 15 (±1) ml.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>percentage of patients who achieve response (reduction of CDAI[Crohn's Disease Activity Index] of ? 100 points) by Week 12,</outcome>
      <timepoint>no. of patients in remission at week 12 that remain in remission at week 24</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome: Safety and Tolerability of ASP1002 (TSO)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at week 12 and 24 after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>time to response and remission</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>percentage of patients with healed ileal and colonic mucosa at Week 12 based on the Crohn?s disease endoscopic index of severity (CDEIS),</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>need for additional CD medications</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To Evaluate Clinical Responseexamine immunological and inflammatory biomarkers, faecal samples and clinical response of ASP1002 (TSO)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at week 12 and 24 after intervention commencement. 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Diagnosis of CD involving the ileum, colon, or ileum and colon of 
at least 6 months in duration as determined by medical history 
2. CDAI (Crohn's Disease Activity Index)= 220 and = 350, as scored from 7 days during the 
Screening period 
3. Must have had colonoscopy with no significant findings and with 
findings consistent with CD within 6 months of study entry 
(Week 0) 
4. Male or female, age 18 to 70 years, inclusive 
5. If on the following medications at Screening Visit 1, patients must 
meet the following criteria: 
a. Corticosteroids: stable treatment for at least 4 weeks prior to 
study entry (Week 0) with a maximum dose of 15 mg/day 
b. Immunosuppressants [azathioprine (AZA), 
6-mercaptopurine (6-MP), methotrexate (MTX)]: treatment 
for at least 3 months with a stable dose for four weeks prior to 
study entry (Week 0) 
c. Antibiotics: ciprofloxacin can be continued at a stable dose 
for up to two weeks if the patient is on treatment at Screening 
Visit 1 
d. Anti-inflammatory: Mesalamine can be continued if the 
patient has been on a stable dose (up to 1.2 gms/daily) for 6 
weeks prior to study entry (Week 0) 


6. Able to read, understand, and sign an ethics committee approved 
informed consent form</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Patients whose CD was diagnosed more than 5 years ago 
2. Patients whose CD is anticipated to require surgical, endoscopic, 
or radiologic intervention while on study 
3. Hospitalization for CD within the last 2 months or at risk for 
hospitalization secondary to CD within the next 2 months 
4. CD requiring total parental nutrition (TPN) 
5. Evidence of bowel obstruction within 3 months of Screening 
6. Symptomatic stricture of the small or large intestine within 3 
months of study entry (Week 0) 
7. Active fistula not adequately drained or non-perianal fistula 
8. Intestinal or abdominal abscess 
9. History of bowel resection of any length in the last 6 months from 
study entry (Week 0) or total bowel resection(s) &gt; 100 cm. 
Patients with total bowel resection(s) = 100 cm can be enrolled 
provided that the Screening fecal calprotectin level is 100 mcg/g 
feces to confirm that the bowel symptoms (i.e., diarrhea) are 
linked to CD and not to short bowel syndrome. 
10. Ileostomy or colostomy 
11. Uncontrolled gastrointestinal (GI) bleeding 
12. Short bowel syndrome 
13. Diagnosis of ulcerative colitis 
14. Scleroderma 
15. Asthma necessitating daily controller medication 
16. Clinically detectable splenomegaly 
17. Positive stool culture for C difficile toxin A or B, bacterial enteric 
pathogens, rotavirus, cryptosporidium species or pathogenic 
ova/parasites 
18. Co-infection with Campylobacter jejuni 
19. Women, who are pregnant, breast feeding or planning to become 
pregnant during the study. All women of childbearing potential 
must have a negative serum pregnancy test prior to study entry 
(Week 0) 
20. Men and women of children bearing potential not using adequate 
birth control measures (e.g., abstinence, oral contraceptives, 
intrauterine device, barrier method with spermicide, or surgical 
sterilization) 
21. Current or recent serious systemic disorder including clinically 
significant impairment in cardiac, pulmonary, liver, renal, 
endocrine, hematologic, or neurologic function 
22. Positive for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) 
23. Any condition associated with significant immunosuppression 
24. Patients currently receiving the following concomitant 
medications: 
a. Prednisone or its equivalent, greater than 15 mg/day 
b. Local steroids such as budesonide, Colifoam, and Predsol 
enemas 
c. Non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDS), 
Cyclooxygenase (COX)-2 inhibitors, or aspirin 
&gt;100 mg/day within 1 week of study entry (Week 0) 
d. TNF-alpha inhibitors such as infliximab (Remicade®), 
adalimumab (Humira®) or other biological agents within 3 
months of study entry (Week 0) 
e. Metronidazole 
25. Receipt of any investigational agent within the past 12 weeks 
from study entry (Week 0) 
26. Blood transfusion within the past 3 months from study entry 
(Week 0) 
27. Current or prior malignancy within five years, excluding non-
melanoma skin cancer, or precancerous dysplasia 
28. Positive for Hepatitis BsAg or Hepatitis C antibody 
29. Presence of the following abnormal laboratory parameters at 
Screening: 
a. Hemoglobin &lt; 10.0 g/dL. The hemoglobin may be retested 
one time prior to study entry (Week 0) if the first screening 
test is &lt; 10.0 g/dL 
b. White blood Count (WBC) &lt; 4,000 or &gt; 20,000/mm3 
c. Platelets &lt; 100,000 or &gt; 800,000/mm3 
d. Amylase or lipase &gt; 2 × upper limit of normal (ULN) 
e. Total bilirubin &gt; 1.5 × ULN 
f. Alanine transaminase (ALT) and aspartate transaminase 
(AST) &gt; 2 × ULN 
g. Alkaline phosphatase (ALK) or gamma glutamyl transferase 
(GGT) &gt; 1.5 × ULN 
h. Creatinine &gt; 1.5 × ULN 
30. Known vitamin B12 deficiency (unless treated greater than one 
month prior to study entry [Week 0]) 
31. Iron saturation level of less than 15%. The patient may be treated 
and re-screened for participation provided that no iron 
transfusions would be required during the study. 
32. Current drug or alcohol abuse that may interfere with the 
objectives of the study 
33. Inability to comply with the planned schedule of study visits 
34. Inability to understand the nature and requirements of the study, 
or to comply with the study procedures 
35. Any social or medical condition that, in the opinion of the 
investigator, would preclude provision of informed consent, make 
participation in the study unsafe, complicate interpretation of 
study outcome data, or otherwise interfere with achieving the 
study objectives.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Interactive Voice Response Randomisation system</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated sequencing There are no stratification factors planned for this randomization. Patients will be assigned a unique identification number. This randomisation assignment will not be revealed until the last patient has completed last visit at week 12</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/06/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Asphelia Pharmaceuticals Inc.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>4365 Executive Drive, Suite 1500, San Diego, CA 92121</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Asphelia Pharmaceuticals Inc.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>4365 Executive Drive, Suite 1500, San Diego, CA 92121</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Novotech (Australia) Pty Ltd</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Level 3, 19 Harris Street, Pyrmont, NSW 2009</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) is a chronic, relapsing condition of the gastrointestinal (GI) tract. IBD is thought to result from inappropriate T cell activation due to a combination of genetic and environmental factors. This leads to a deregulated immune response and characteristic inflammation. Crohns disease (CD) is a form of IBD.
One theory suggests that underexposure to helminths is a major environmental factor in predisposing to CD. This hygiene hypothesis is based on epidemiologic findings of an inverse relationship between IBD incidence and helminthic colonization.
In the proposed study, the pig whipworm Trichuris suis (T. suis), formulated as ASP1002 [Trichuris suis Ova (TSO)], a suspension for oral administration, will be administered in the clinic as a single dose for 6 times. T. suis is similar morphologically to the human whipworm but is cleared too rapidly from the human host to establish infection. Therefore, it has potential for being a natural immune modulator without significant risk of causing disease in humans.
The expected duration of study participation is approximately 26 to 27 weeks, including up to 2 - 3 weeks screening, a 12 week treatment period and a follow-up visit at Week 24.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/05/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Xavier Frapaise</name>
      <address>Asphelia Pharmaceuticals Inc. 4365 Executive Drive, Suite 1500, San Diego, CA 92121</address>
      <phone>+1 (0)858 7318520</phone>
      <fax>+1 (0)858 731-8501</fax>
      <email>xfrapaise@AspheliaPharma.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Lena Chapman</name>
      <address>Level 3, 19 Harris Street, Pyrmont, NSW 2009</address>
      <phone>+61 (0) 2 85691400</phone>
      <fax>+61 (0) 2 8569 1498</fax>
      <email>lena.chapman@novotech-cro.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Lena Chapman</name>
      <address>Level 3, 19 Harris Street, Pyrmont, NSW 2009</address>
      <phone>+61 (0) 2 85691400</phone>
      <fax>+61 (0) 2 85691498</fax>
      <email>lena.chapman@novotech-cro.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>