<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371011">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/07/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001056482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy of computer versus group memory training for memory rehabilitation post-stroke</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Comparison of Compensatory and Restorative Approaches to Memory Rehabilitation Post-STroke</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>cognition</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>memory loss</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be randomly allocated into one of three conditions; restoration, compensation or a wait list control group. Participants allocated into the restoration condition will be asked to complete  six weeks of computer memory training while participants in the compensation condition will be asked to attend a face to face memory group once a week for six weeks. Further details of  each respective intervention are provided below.

For the computer memory training (i.e. restoration condition), participants will be required to complete a project specific suite of memory games developed in collaboration with Lumos labs. Training is completed on a computer at home for 30 minutes, five times per week for six weeks. Participants can flexibly decide upon which days and times to train . There are 13 different memory games that form apart of the training, with each session alternating between these games. Researchers will be in regular contact with participants throughout the 6 week training period to address any concerns or technical complications. Frequency of training will be monitored electronically by researchers. 

For the group memory sessions (i.e. compensation), participants will be required to attend a face to face memory skills group for 2 hours on a weekday for a six week period. The groups are held in Notting Hill, the Austin Hospital and Monash Health sites and are run by neuropsychologists who have experience in the field of brain injury. Groups provide participants with education surrounding the impact of stroke on memory and cover a number of strategies that aim to minimise the impact of these changes on daily functioning. For instance, the group covers strategies that may be helpful to remember peoples names. Compliance with group training will be monitored using a register of attendance at each session. We will attempt to match participants to the closest group where possible. 

Finally all participants will be asked to complete 'pen and paper' memory tasks immediately prior to the rehabilitation, immediately following the rehabilitation and at a six week follow up. </interventions>
    <comparator>If allocated to the waitlist control condition, participants will be placed on a waiting list for a 12 week period but will be given the choice about which rehabilitation they would like to complete (i.e. either the group or the computer training).  </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Goal Attainment Scaling will be used to evaluate the extent to which participants percieve thier personalised memory goals were accomplished during the course of the intervention.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline prior to the start of an intervention, immediately following the completion of the intervention and six weeks post end of intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total score on Royal Prince Alfred Prospective Memory Task (RPA-ProMem)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline prior to the start of an intervention, immediately following the completion of the intervention and six weeks post end of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total self reported memory failures on the Everyday Memory Questionnaire-Revised </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline prior to the start of an intervention, immediately following the completion of the intervention and six weeks post end of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bilateral working memory performance as assessed by aged scaled scores on Digits backwards and Spatial span subtest of the Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale Fourth Edition (WAIS-IV) and Wechsler Memory Scale Fourth Edition (WMS-IV) respectivley</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline prior to the start of an intervention, immediately following the completion of the intervention and six weeks post end of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Visual memory and learning T-scores on the Brief Visuospatial Memory Test Revised (BVMT-R)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline prior to the start of an intervention, immediately following the completion of the intervention and six weeks post end of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Other reports of patient memory failure assessed on the other version of the Comprehensive Assessment of Prospective Memory (CAPM-other)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline prior to the start of an intervention, immediately following the completion of the intervention and six weeks post end of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life as assessed by the Assessment of Quality of Life (AQoL-8D)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline prior to the start of an intervention, immediately following the completion of the intervention and six weeks post end of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety total scores on the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline prior to the start of an intervention, immediately following the completion of the intervention and six weeks post end of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self reported prospective memory failures on the Comprehensive Assessment of Prospective Memory (CAPM)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline prior to the start of an intervention, immediately following the completion of the intervention and six weeks post end of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression total score on the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline prior to the start of an intervention, immediately following the completion of the intervention and six weeks post end of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>*diagnosis of stroke occurring at least three months prior to the intervention start date
*Sufficient English language and cognition to ensure successful and valid completion of outcome measures and rehabilitation
*Access to a computer and the internet and computer proficiency necessary to navigate through an online platform of training 
*Subjective (self or other) memory complaints 
*Ability to attend weekly memory groups held at Notting Hill, the Austin hospital or Monash Health sites</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>*History of other neurological conditions such as epilepsy and  traumatic brain injury 
*Diagnosis of dementia or mild cognitive impairment 
*Diagnosis of transient ischemic attack (TIA) rather than stroke
*History of psychiatric or medical issues impacting upon cognition </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>allocation was concealed in opaque sealed envelopes </concealment>
    <sequence>Block randomization will be used to create the random order for allocation of participants.  Block sequences will be generated through computer software and sealed by a person independent to the research project </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Nil other features</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A 3(restorative, compensation, waitlist) x 3(baseline, post intervention, follow up) mixed model ANOVA will be conducted.

G*power calculations (version 3.1), with an expected small-medium effect size (conservative estimate based upon recent meta analytic findings), suggest that a sample size of 69 would achieve 80% power, at an alpha level of .05. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/04/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>1/02/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>69</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>65</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/02/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>15/03/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Kingston Centre - Cheltenham</hospital>
    <postcode>3800 - Monash University</postcode>
    <postcode>3152 - Knox City Centre</postcode>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
    <postcode>3153 - Bayswater</postcode>
    <postcode>3192 - Cheltenham</postcode>
    <postcode>3199 - Frankston</postcode>
    <postcode>3191 - Sandringham</postcode>
    <postcode>3150 - Brandon Park</postcode>
    <postcode>3150 - Wheelers Hill</postcode>
    <postcode>3150 - Glen Waverley</postcode>
    <postcode>3152 - Studfield</postcode>
    <postcode>3154 - The Basin</postcode>
    <postcode>3151 - Burwood East</postcode>
    <postcode>3156 - Ferntree Gully</postcode>
    <postcode>3158 - Upwey</postcode>
    <postcode>3159 - Menzies Creek</postcode>
    <postcode>3162 - Caulfield</postcode>
    <postcode>3163 - Glen Huntly</postcode>
    <postcode>3166 - Oakleigh</postcode>
    <postcode>3167 - Oakleigh South</postcode>
    <postcode>3101 - Kew</postcode>
    <postcode>3103 - Balwyn</postcode>
    <postcode>3105 - Bulleen</postcode>
    <postcode>3108 - Doncaster</postcode>
    <postcode>3109 - Tunstall Square Po</postcode>
    <postcode>3102 - Kew East</postcode>
    <postcode>3121 - Burnley</postcode>
    <postcode>3121 - Richmond</postcode>
    <postcode>3122 - Hawthorn</postcode>
    <postcode>3124 - Camberwell</postcode>
    <postcode>3128 - Box Hill</postcode>
    <postcode>3126 - Canterbury</postcode>
    <postcode>3125 - Burwood</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Psychological Sciences, 18 Innovation Walk, Monash University, Clayton 3800 VIC</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Monash Unviersity</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>School of Psychological Sciences, 18 Innovation Walk, Monash University, Clayton, VIC 3800</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Nil</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Monash Health</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>246 Clayton Rd, Clayton VIC 3168</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Approximately half of all survivors of stroke experience memory impairment, which can significantly impact functional independence and quality of life. Two different approaches have typically been implemented in an effort to rehabilitate memory: restoration (computer based training) and compensation (group based training).
Overall, there is no clear consensus as to whether either computer-based training or compensatory approaches to memory rehabilitation are effective or efficient for stroke patients. As a result, many survivors of stroke are purchasing costly computer training programs with unknown effectiveness.

At Monash University, we are currently running a randomised controlled trial to explore the efficacy and cost efficiency of different approaches to memory rehabilitation post stroke. Eligible participants will be randomised into a waitlist control,memory group or computer training group and will receive  free memory rehabilitation over a six week period.

 In doing so we aim to explore the most cost-efficient and effective way in which memory can be rehabilitated post stroke, thereby addressing a clear gap in service provision.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>246 Clayton Rd, Clayton VIC 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/03/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>15037A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>22/01/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash University Human Research Ethics Committee (MUHREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Monash University

Room 111, Chancellery Building E

24 Sports Walk, Clayton Campus, Wellington Rd, Clayton VIC 3800, Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/03/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CF15/916 - 2015000408</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/03/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371011-HREC &amp; SSA Approval Letter (1).pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371011-MUHREC approval.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371011-study advert for participants (1).pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371011-study summary.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rene Stolwyk</name>
      <address>School of Psychological Sciences, 18 Innovation Walk, Monash Unviersity, Clayton 3800 VIC</address>
      <phone>+61 434 194 230</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rene.stolwyk@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Toni Withiel </name>
      <address>School of Psychological Sciences, 18 Innovation Walk, Monash Unviersity, Clayton 3800 VIC</address>
      <phone>+61 411 729 045</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>toni.withiel@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Toni Withiel</name>
      <address>School of Psychological Sciences, 18 Innovation Walk, Monash Unviersity, Clayton 3800 VIC</address>
      <phone>+61 411 729 045</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>toni.withiel@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Toni Withiel </name>
      <address>School of Psychological Sciences, 18 Innovation Walk, Monash Unviersity, Clayton 3800 VIC</address>
      <phone>+61 411 729 045</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>toni.withiel@monash.edu</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>