<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367660">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/01/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/01/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000046505</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of growth hormone on muscle function</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of growth hormone (GH) on anaerobic capacity: a double blind placebo-controlled study in growth hormone deficient (GHD) adults</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1127-1004</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Growth hormone deficiency </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal metabolism and endocrine development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A 2-month double-blind placebo controlled GH treatment (0.5mg/d) study with a crossover at 1 month, followed by an open-label active treatment phase (0.5mg/d) for 6 months in 20 GHD adults. There is no 'wash out' period between treatment periods. 4 weeks of Placebo treatment is adequate to wash out any GH effect on Wingate performance based on pilot data from our laboratory. GH is administered via subcutaneous injection. Adherence to the intervention will be assessed by counting empty drug vials and measuring plasma IGF1 levels.</interventions>
    <comparator>Saline injection</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anaerobic Capacity was assessed by a 30-second all out sprint on a cycle ergometer during the Wingate test
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 1, 2 and 8 months </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Aerobic capacity was measured as VO2max during an incremental exercise test on a cycle ergometer

</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 1, 2 and 8 months </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Chair-stand test. This measures the number of chair-stand repetitions during 30 seconds

</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 1, 2 and 8 months </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stair-climb test. This measures the time taken to climb 4 flights of stairs.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 1, 2 and 8 months </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>7-day Pedometry. This measures the number of step counts over 7 days by a pedometer. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 1, 2 and 8 months </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Metabolic gene expression in skeletal muscle.

This will be undertaken by studying genes regulating energy metabolism by microarray analysis of biopsies of quadriceps muscle</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 1, 2 and 8 months </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body composition assessed by DEXA scan
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 1, 2 and 8 months </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Growth hormone deficiency (diagnosed as per internationally accepted criteria)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Cardiac, respiratory, renal, liver or neurological disease
2.	Pregnancy 
3.	Malignancy
4.	Inability to consent</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>GHD adults are recruited from outpatient clinics at the Princess Alexandra Hospital.
Randomisation codes are kept in an opaque, sealed envelope. Subjects are allocated to GH or placebo by a member of the team who is not involved in the study.</concealment>
    <sequence>20 random numbers are generated by a computer assigning a specific treatment order to each number. These numbers are randomly allocated to 20 subjects.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>In the double blind placebo controlled crossover study, the significance of differences between treatment groups will be evaluated by repeated measures ANOVA. These data will be analyzed for a carryover effect using mixed model analysis looking at the effect of the interaction between treatment order and treatment itself on the outcome measures. 

In the 6-month open label study, the effects of GH on outcome measures will be analysed using paired t-test. 

Associations will be analysed by simple linear regressions. Independent predictors of outcome measures will be analysed by multiple regression analysis. 
The sample size is based on anaerobic capacity data from our studies in athletes and aerobic performance data from the literature. A sample size of 15 is required to show a 5% improvement in Wingate power and 18 for a 15% improvement in VO2max at a 0.05 level significance with 80% power.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>19/02/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>19/02/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>9/04/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>9/04/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>19</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <postcode>4102 - Woolloongabba</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Princess Alexandra Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>199 Ipswich Rd, Brisbane, QLD 4102</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Princess Alexandra Hospital Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>199 Ipswich Rd, Brisbane, QLD 4102</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Novo Nordisk</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Level 3
21 Solent Circuit
BAULKHAM HILLS NSW 2153
AUSTRALIA</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Aerobic energy powers endurance exercises e.g. jogging, long distance running etc. and it is used as a measure of fitness. On the other hand, initiation of any activity (e.g. rushing for a bus, climbing stairs) relies on anaerobic energy that is provided by preformed energy in form of phosphocreatine and glycolysis (breakdown of glucose) that occurs in absence of oxygen. Hence, individuals with inadequate anaerobic energy levels usually struggle to carry out their activities of daily living and suffer from chronic fatigue. What regulates the Anaerobic Energy System (AES) is not well studied and the factors that enhance AES apart from physical training are not known.

Adults with Growth Hormone Deficiency (GHD) typically suffer from chronic fatigue and loss of vitality, symptoms suggesting impairment of the AES. These symptoms improve with GH replacement. However, the mechanisms underlying the symptomatology and how it is improved are poorly understood.

New research shows that GH plays a vital role in energy provision. A recent study showed that administration to healthy subjects with GH enhanced sprinting, which is a marker of anaerobic capacity. However, GH did not improve any other measures of physical performance. Another research studied the effects of GH treatment in GHD subjects at a cellular level and found that GH favored the use of glucose (anaerobic glycolysis) over fat as a fuel for energy provision in muscle cells. These studies indicate that GH may have a positive role in regulating the AES.

The main aims of this study are to investigate the effects of GH on anaerobic capacity and genes governing energy metabolism in skeletal muscle, and study the relationship between the AES and physical function.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Metro South Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 7, Translational Research Institute, 37 Kent Street, Brisbane, QLD 4102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/04/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/12/QPAH/126</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ken Ho</name>
      <address>Level 7, Translational Research Institute, 37 Kent Street, Brisbane, QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3443 8065</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.ho@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Viral Chikani</name>
      <address>Dept of Diabetes and Endocrinology,
Princess Alexandra Hospital
199 Ipswich Rd, Brisbane, QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3176 2111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>v.chikani@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ken Ho</name>
      <address>Level 7, Translational Research Institute, 37 Kent Street, Brisbane, QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3443 8065</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.ho@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Viral Chikani</name>
      <address>Dept of Diabetes and Endocrinology,
Princess Alexandra Hospital
199 Ipswich Rd, Brisbane, QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3176 2111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>v.chikani@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>