<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373403">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/08/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/09/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001328369</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of Dejarnettes Blocks on chronic back pain</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Impact of Dejarnette's Blocks on low back pain and strength of stabilising muscles in dancers.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>chronic low back pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is performed by a physiotherapist. 
The experimental group will be the placement of the blocks, 5 minutes in flexion and 5 minutes en extension. The base of the blocks are placed on the hip joints and the tips of the blocks towards the navel to bring the pelvis to flexion. To carry the pelvis to extension the base of the blocks is placed on the iliac crests and the tips towards the pubis.
The treatment is administered once in each participant. 
The control group will remain without intervention for 10 minutes lying on the stretcher in the prone position. Once the study for the control group was concluded, the same treatment as that applied to the experimental group was obtained.
With the technique of blocks we intend to normalize the movements of the iliac crests, L4, L5 and sacrum and reduce the pain that is directly related by joints, ligaments, muscles and nerves.
The tests of orthopedic strength of the pyramidal muscles, gluteal medius, gluteus maximus and psoas-iliac according to Daniels will be used as diagnostic maneuvers. They will be measured with the force dynamometer by performing 3 repetitions of each test and obtaining the average value. The duration of each test will be 5 seconds.
The tests will be performed before and after the placement of the Dejarnette blocks and one week later of placement of the bloks.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will be left without intervention for 10 minutes lying on the stretcher in prone position. Once the study for the control group was concluded the same treatment as that applied to the experimental group.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceived lumbar pain by Visual Analogue Scale
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before, immediately following treatment
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Test maximal and mean strength of the pyramidal, gluteus medius, gluteus maximus and psoas-iliac muscles bilaterally using The Lafayette Manual Muscle Testing (MMT) System</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before treatment and immediately following treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Roland Morris Questionnaire
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before treatment and one week after treatment. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceived lumbar pain by Visual Analogue Scale
</outcome>
      <timepoint>One week after treatment
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Test maximal and mean strength of the pyramidal, gluteus medius, gluteus maximus and psoas-iliac muscles bilaterally using The Lafayette Manual Muscle Testing (MMT) System</outcome>
      <timepoint>One week after treatment
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-All participants are dancers.
- That the parents or guardians give written consent for the minor children to be part of the study.
- With low non-specific lower back pain of less than 3 months
- No diagnosed disc pathologies.
- No surgical interventions in the lower limbs or rachis.
- No pathology of dental or bite occlusion.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>14</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>26</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Women with low non-specific lower back pain of less than 3 months.
- That we have received osteopathic treatment in the last 3 months.
- That they were medicated low-back pain, at least two months in advance, for the same pathology.
- That was done with pathologies of graves diagnosed in the feet, knees or hips.
- Those who have not taken medication during the 72 hours prior to the study.
- Pregnant at the time of study.
- That they present some type of contraindication to the therapy with wedges of Dejarnette.
- Women with plantar supports.
- That suffered cervical whiplash or traffic accident or trauma.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>central randomisation by computer.</concealment>
    <sequence>In the first consultation of the first patient and once decided their participation in the study, the assignment of subjects is selected using the random number software www.randomizer.org.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The subjects of the study are dancers with low non-specific low back pain of more than three months and recruited from different dance schools and conservatories of Valencia.
It is intended to create two groups of 20 subjects each.
A repeated measures ANOVA will be carried out</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>26/10/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>21/11/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>22/12/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>valencia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Francisco Selva</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Physiotherapy, University of Valencia, Calle Gascó Oliag 3, Valencia, 46010, Spain. </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Spain</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Francisco Selva</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1Own Master in evaluation, physiotherapy and reconditioning in sports science. Department of Physiotherapy, University of Valencia, Calle Gascó Oliag 3, Valencia, 46010, Spain. </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to decrease the perception of low back pain and to improve the maximum strength of the lumbar muscles.
The hypotheses of the study are:
- Following treatment with Dejarnette blocks for 10 minutes, there is a significant increase in maximal strength of the pyramidal, gluteus medius, gluteus maximus and psoas-iliac muscles bilaterally.
- Following the treatment with Dejarnette blocks for 10 minutes, there is a significant increase in mean strength performed during the 5 second test before and after treatment of the pyramidal, gluteus medius, gluteus maximus and psoas-iliac muscles bilaterally.
- After treatment with Dejarnette blocks for 10 minutes, there is an improvement in the perception of immediate local pain using Visual Analogue Scale (VAS).
- After a week of treatment with Dejarnette blocks for 10 minutes, there is an improvement in local pain perception using Visual Analogue Scale (VAS).
- After one week of treatment with Dejarnette blocks for 10 minutes, there is an improvement in the perception of low back pain using the Roland Morris Questionnaire.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Commission of ethics in experimental research. University of Valencia, Spain</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress> Av. de Blasco Ibáñez, 13, 46010 València.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/09/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H1504616010653</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/09/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Spain</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Francisco Selva</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy, University of Valencia, Calle Gascó Oliag 3, Valencia, 46010, Spain.</address>
      <phone>+34634590640</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>paco.selva.s@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Francisco Selva</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy, University of Valencia, Calle Gascó Oliag 3, Valencia, 46010, Spain.</address>
      <phone>+34634590640</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>info@franciscoselva.com</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Francisco Selva</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy, University of Valencia, Calle Gascó Oliag 3, Valencia, 46010, Spain.</address>
      <phone>+34 963983855   </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>paco.selva@uv.es</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>