<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362348">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/04/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/04/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000411842</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Eccentric resistance ergometry in knee osteoarthritis rehabilitation: a randomized clinical trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effects of adding eccentric ergometry to standard physiotherapy management on quadriceps strength and physical function in individuals with knee osteoarthritis: a randomized clinical study.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>EUREKA</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Impairments in lower limb muscular performance in symptomatic knee osteoarthritis.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients randomized to the intervention arm would receive standard physiotherapy treatment and they will exercise on an eccentric ergometer. Both Physiotherapy and ergometry training will be delivered individually. Standard physiotherapy treatment would be delivered by experienced Physiotherapists. Specifically, the standard Physiotherapy treatment comprises a combination of manual therapy and therapeutic exercises. For the manual therapy component, the techniques chosen comprise passive physiological and accessory movements, muscle stretching, and soft tissue mobilization. These techniques will be applied by the treating physiotherapists in accordance to their assessment findings. For the therapeutic-exercises component, the exercises will be supervised by the treating physiotherapists and the exercises consist of (i) active range-of-motion exercises, (ii) muscle strengthening exercises, and (iii) balance and functional training. All manual therapy techniques and therapeutic exercises would be progressed only if the symptoms and signs of OA (pain, knee effusion, and muscle soreness) are decreasing.

Eccentric ergometry training involves cycling on an eccentric ergometer. Exercise intensity will be determined by the Borgs rating of perceived exertion (RPE) scale. Dosage will be 15 minutes per session. In the absence of increased knee pain, effusion, or excessive fatigue, the patients are allowed to gradually progress from an initial RPE rating of "very very light intensity" on the first session to an RPE rating of hard intensity" in the subsequent sessions.

Physiotherapy treatment will be delivered twice weekly for the first 3 weeks and once weekly for the next 5 weeks. Each treatment session is 30mins in duration.

Patients will train twice weekly on the eccentric ergometer and each session is 15mins in duration.</interventions>
    <comparator>Patients randomized to the comparator arm would receive standard physiotherapy treatment and they would exercise on a concentric ergometer. Both Physiotherapy and ergometry training will be delivered individually.Standard physiotherapy treatment follows that for the intervention arm. 

Concentric ergometry training involves cycling on an concentric ergometer. Exercise intensity will be determined by the Borgs rating of perceived exertion (RPE) scale. Dosage will be 15 minutes per session. In the absence of increased knee pain, effusion, or excessive fatigue, the patients are allowed to gradually progress from an initial RPE rating of "very very light intensity" on the first session to an RPE rating of hard intensity" in the subsequent sessions.

Physiotherapy treatment will be delivered twice weekly for the first 3 weeks and once weekly for the next 5 weeks. Each treatment session is 30mins in duration.

Patients will train twice weekly on the concentric ergometer and each session is 15mins in duration.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Isometric knee extensor torque output measured by an isokinetic dynamometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline assessment and 8 weeks post randomization</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stopwatch-timed fast paced gait speed over a 10-metre course</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline assessment and 8 weeks post randomization</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Medical Outcomes Survey Short Form-36 (SF-36) physical function and bodily pain</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline assessment and 8 weeks post randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Knee pain intensity measured by the numeric pain rating scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline assessment and 8 weeks post randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Standing balance as measured using a Nintendo Wii Balance Board</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline assessment and 8 weeks post randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bridging (supine position) performance as measured using a Nintendo Wii Balance Board</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline assessment and 8 weeks post randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Knee passive range-of-motion as measured using goniometry</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline assessment and 8 weeks post randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(i) Patients with primary medial tibiofemoral OA 

(ii) Knee flexion range of motion greater or equal to 100 degrees</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>90</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(1) Patellofemoral joint symptoms overshadowing tibiofemoral symptoms, as determined from clinical examination
 
(2) Current or past (within 4 weeks) oral corticosteroid use; 

(3) Systemic arthritic conditions; 

(4) A previous history of hip or knee joint replacement or tibial osteotomy

(5i) Inability to ambulate 10 metres without a gait aid.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be identified and recruited from the outpatient orthopaedic clinic of a large tertiary institution in Singapore. Once the participant has provided written informed consent, pre-intervention testing would be performed and participants will be randomised into one of two groups: (i) standard Physiotherapy management and cycling on an eccentric ergometer and (ii) standard Physiotherapy management and cycling on a concentric ergometer. 

The randomisation schedule will be prepared by a research physiotherapist who is not involved in the study. He will be the only person with access to the schedule, which will be kept in a locked location. To conceal randomisation, consecutively numbered, sealed, opaque envelopes will be used and maintained centrally.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be performed by random permuted blocks stratified according to gender.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>None</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/04/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Singapore</country>
      <state>NA</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Singapore General Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>SINGAPORE GENERAL HOSPITAL 
Outram Road
Singapore 169608
Tel: 6222 3322
Fax: 6224 9221</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Singapore</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Singhealth Foundation Start-Up Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Singapore Health Services Pte Ltd
7 Hospital Drive, Block A, #02-01
SingHealth Research Facilities
Singapore 169611</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Singapore</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary aim of this randomized controlled trial (RCT) is to compare the symptomatic and biomechanical effects of standard Physiotherapy treatment with the addition of eccentric ergometry with those of standard Physiotherapy treatment with concentric ergometry in people with symptomatic medial tibiofemoral OA</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>SGH Institutional Review Board</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Singapore General Hospital
Bowyer Block A Level 3
Outram Road Singapore 169608</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/04/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CIRB2010/232/D</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>31/03/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Singapore</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Yong-Hao Pua</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
Block 1 Level 1
Singapore General Hospital
Outram Road
Singapore 169608</address>
      <phone>+65 90188129</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pua.yong.hao@sgh.com.sg</email>
      <country>Singapore</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Yong-Hao Pua</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
Block 1 Level 1
Singapore General Hospital
Outram Road
Singapore 169608</address>
      <phone>+65 90188129</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pua.yong.hao@sgh.com.sg</email>
      <country>Singapore</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>