<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373210">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/06/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001056381</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effects of fish oil supplementation and resistance exercise on inflammation in healthy post-menopausal women</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effects of acute post-exercise biochemical milieu of older women following fish oil supplementation and satellite cell cycling</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>PSS (PUFA Serum Study)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Menopause</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Sarcopenia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal metabolism and endocrine development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All Participants will perform a light session of resistance-based exercise following a thorough warm up. The session of resistance-based exercise consists of machine-based exercises (described below) that provide a supporting surface for balance when performing the exercise. All participants will also undertake pre-testing and measures of body composition one week prior to the trial to ensure the amount of weight lifted during the exercise session can be safely and confidently performed.

This study is a randomised cross over trial, meaning that participants will be randomised into two groups. Either group 1 (fish oil) or group 2 (coconut oil/placebo). After a washout period of 4 weeks, participants will swap groups so that at the end of the trial each participant will have completed a period of fish oil supplementation and a period of coconut oil supplementation. Participants will be randomly allocated to one of the following two experimental:
Group 1: Fish Oil supplementation
Participants allocated to this group will be required to consume 4 fish oil capsules (6g/d containing 2.16g of EPA and 1.42g of DHA) PUFA daily for 4 weeks. We recommend that participants space their consumption of the fish oil evenly throughout the day and advise participants to take two fish oil capsules in the morning and two capsules in the evening.

Side effects: The side effects of fish oil supplementation are rare but may include heartburn, nausea, loose stools and rash. Consumption of fish oil supplements can also lead a fishy after taste that may be unpleasant. The fish oil supplement we have chosen for this study is designed to minimise fishy after taste. If you have a known allergy or hypersensitivity to fish or other fish products (including shellfish), you should be not consuming fish oil supplements.

Exercise session 
The duration of the exercise session, including adequate warm-ups, will be ~60 minutes. The following exercises have been selected as they are low risk and easy for untrained individuals to complete. The following exercises have been selected based on previous established protocols as they are low risk and the most basic exercises for untrained individuals to complete. The following exercises have been used in previous studies thus deemed safe for older adults to perform.
Acute Resistance Exercise Session:
1.	Leg Press - 3x10 @ RPE 7-8
2.	Leg Extensions - 2 x 12 @ RPE 7-8
3.	Machine Chest Press - 3 x 10 @ RPE 7-8
4.	Dumbbell Side Lateral Raises - 3 x 12 @ RPE 7-8

Resistance exercise will take place at the end of the supplementation periods
To monitor adherence to the intervention participants will be asked to return capsules not consumed. Analysis of blood will also determine adherence to the intervention </interventions>
    <comparator>Group 2: Placebo (Coconut Oil)
Participants allocated to this this group will be required to consume 6 coconut oil capsules (6g) daily for 4 weeks. We recommend that participants space their consumption of the coconut oil evenly throughout the day and advise participants to take 3 capsules in the morning and 3 capsules in the evening.

Side effects: There are no known side effects of coconut oil
</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Inflammatory markers in blood (TNF-a, Il-6, Il-1)</outcome>
      <timepoint>After Fish Oil supplementation (at the end of 4 week intervention period).
Samples will be collected before and after the exercise sessions.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>in-vitro analysis of muscle cell activation.

Serum will be isolated from the blood of participants and used to investigate its effect on muscle cell growth </outcome>
      <timepoint>Serum taken collected from participants before supplementation, after supplementation and after exercise with supplementation will be used to grow muscle cells in-vitro to investigate their effects on muscle cell growth.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>i)	Female aged 50-65 yo
ii)	Are currently Post-Menopausal (no periods for 12 and over consecutive months)
iii)	Have a Body Mass Index (BMI) of 18.5-29
iv)	Not exercising more than 3 times per week
v)	Not currently taking any blood thinning medication e.g. (Warfarin, Aspirin or Dabigatran), anti-inflammatory medication or supplements (anti-allergenic) and not taking fish oil supplements 
vi)	Do not have any known allergies to fish products or coconut oil 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Smoker
Currently taking taking any blood thinning medication e.g. (Warfarin, Aspirin or Dabigatran), anti-inflammatory medication or supplements (anti-allergenic) and taking fish oil supplements 
Type 2 diabetes
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>4 week washout period between groups</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/07/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>20/04/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>12</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>20/04/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Bill Tachtsis</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Mary MacKillop Institute for Health Research
115 Victoria Parade, Fitzroy VIC 3065</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Catholic University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>115 Victoria Parade, Fitzroy VIC 3065</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aims of this project are to:
a.	 investigate whether the serum composition of post-menopausal women can be altered with  4 weeks of fish oil supplementation and an acute bout of resistance exercise 
b.	Can changes to inflammatory markers in serum alter the activity of muscle cells grown in-vitro
Proposal research design:
The study is a randomized cross-over design study with a 4 week washout period between groups:
Fish Oil group. Participants will be required to ingest 4 fish oil capsules (6g/d containing 2.16g of EPA and 1.42g of DHA) PUFA daily for 4 weeks. This dose has been selected as it is the dosage range recommended by the Australian Heart Foundation for lowering plasma triglyceride concentrations in hypertriglyceridemic subjects and has therefore previously been shown to be physiologically relevant in human subjects.

Placebo group. Participants will be required to ingest equivalent amounts of coconut oil (6g/d) for 4 weeks. Coconut oil has been selected as it has been used as a control in other studies involving fish oil.

Resistance Exercise. The acute exercise intervention will consist of both upper and lower body exercises including: the leg press, leg extensions, the bench press and dumbbell side lateral raises. The duration of the exercise session, including adequate warm-ups, will be ~60 minutes. 

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>ACU Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 968
North Sydney
NSW 2059

</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/04/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2017-10H </hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/01/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Bill Tachtsis</name>
      <address>Mary MacKillop Institute for Health Research
215 Spring St, Melbourne VIC 3000</address>
      <phone>+61 431599428</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bill.tachtsis@myacu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Bill Tachtsis</name>
      <address>Mary MacKillop Institute for Health Research
215 Spring St, Melbourne VIC 3000</address>
      <phone>+61 431599428</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bill.tachtsis@myacu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Bill Tachtsis</name>
      <address>Mary MacKillop Institute for Health Research
215 Spring St, Melbourne VIC 3000</address>
      <phone>+61 431599428</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bill.tachtsis@myacu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Bill Tachtsis</name>
      <address>Mary MacKillop Institute for Health Research
215 Spring St, Melbourne VIC 3000</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>bill.tachtsis@myacu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>