<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372066">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/12/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/02/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000275369</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of the effects of rehabilitation with the use of virtual reality in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of hospital based physiotherapy for chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) patients with the use of virtual reality on physical fitness, lung function and dyspnea</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The objective of the study is to evaluate the usefulness of exercise training using the Xbox Kinect system during hospital rehabilitation of patients with COPD. In this project, it is proposed to: Implement and evaluate Xbox Kinect training session as a tool in pulmonary rehabilitation and compare the effects of a standard rehabilitation program with the results of the program enriched with sessions using X-box Kinect.
For the study will be recruited 120 patients with COPD (II and III GOLD) Hospital Interior Ministry in Glucholazy. The subjects will be randomly assigned to 3 groups.
Group I is the control group. Patients will participate in improving the existing models of pulmonary rehabilitation by Szczegielniak. Pulmonary rehabilitation program will last for three weeks
Group II will participate in pulmonary rehabilitation by Szczegielniak models, in addition to participating in 20 minutes training using video games available for the Xbox Kinect system.
Group III will participate in pulmonary rehabilitation by Szczegielniak models, but the training on a cycle ergometer or treadmill will be replaced by the Xbox Kinect system.
Patients, depending on their exercise tolerance will be enrolled to appropriate model of rehabilitation and then undergo different types of physiotherapy treatment, mainly based on physical exercise on a bicycle ergometer. 
Patients with COPD will be enrolled to model B or C of PR by Szczegielniak based on the results of submaximal exercise and spirometry tests. 
Model B
* specific respiratory exercises for 30 minutes - relaxation exercises for breathing muscles, strengthening exercises the diaphragm with resistance, exercises to increase costal or chest breathing, prolonged exhalation exercise, chest percussion, once a day for 30 min, 5-time a week;
* training on a cycle ergometer or treadmill, twice a day for 20-30 min.- until the Heart Rate reaches 60% of the HRmax (220-age),
* 30 minutes of fitness and respiratory exercises - coordination and balance exercises, stretching exercises using elastic bands, balls rehabilitation, sensory pillows. Performed in a standing position, kneeling, sitting, lying on side, abdomen and back.
* walking / Nordic Walking (depending on weather and health condition of the patient) for 45 min.;
* relaxation training by Shultz and Jacobson. The technique involves the daily practice of sessions that last around 15 minutes. During each session, the practitioner repeats a set of visualisations that induce a state of relaxation. Each session can be practiced in a position chosen amongst a set of recommended postures (for example, lying down, sitting meditation, sitting like a rag doll). The technique can be used to alleviate many stress-induced psychosomatic disorders.
           Model C
* specific respiratory exercises for 30 minutes - relaxation exercises for breathing muscles, strengthening exercises the diaphragm with resistance, exercises to increase costal or chest breathing, prolonged exhalation exercise, chest percussion, once a day for 30 min, 5-time a week;
* training on a cycle ergometer or treadmill, once a day for 20-30 min.- until the Heart Rate reaches 60% of the HRmax (220-age),
* 30 minutes of fitness and respiratory exercises - coordination and balance exercises, stretching exercises using elastic bands, balls rehabilitation, sensory pillows. Performed in a standing position, kneeling, sitting, lying on side, abdomen and back.
* walking / Nordic Walking (depending on weather and health condition of the patient) for 45 min.;
* relaxation training by Shultz and Jacobson. The technique involves the daily practice of sessions that last around 15 minutes. During each session, the practitioner repeats a set of visualisations that induce a state of relaxation. Each session can be practiced in a position chosen amongst a set of recommended postures (for example, lying down, sitting meditation, sitting like a rag doll). The technique can be used to alleviate many stress-induced psychosomatic disorders.
Interventions are delivered in a groups.
Kinect training for II and III group:
In each game participant is to score the highest number of points awarded for quantitative and qualitative elements. The subjects will be played in each game at a basic level. During participation in the session, patients will be equipped with a device for measuring the heart rate, so as not to exceed the value of training established during the initial investigation. If the patient does not reach the heart rate of the training session will be extended.  Expected time for one session of 15-30 minutes. Each training session will be consisted of 4 Kinect Adventures games:
* 20,000 Leaks - The player positions his/her limbs and head to plug cracks as sea creatures cause cracks and holes in the glass cube. Each game consists of three waves, which are timed and progress in difficulty as the game continues. As the game progresses the player may have to plug up to five cracks simultaneously requiring them to use their entire body. Each wave continues until time runs out or player is able to cover all cracks, points are awarded for each crack covered and for time remaining.
* Curvy Creek - The player stands in a raft and must try to collect as many adventure pins as possible throughout the course by weight-shifting, side-stepping or reaching to steer the raft. The player loses points by crashing into barriers
* Rally Ball - The player uses his/her limbs and head to hit balls at targets and blocks which are located in front of him/her. When specific targets are hit, the ball splits in to multiple balls which must be hit simultaneously, increasing the difficulty. This game consists of three rounds in which the player earns points for each target hit, balls collected, and remaining time.
* Reflex Ridge - The player stands on a moving platform that travels through a wooden track course. Player must squat/duck and lean side-to-side in order to avoid obstacles. Pins can be earned by avoiding obstacles, reaching to collect pins, and remaining time.
Game performance success will be evaluated as a number of points awarded to the participant. All interventions will take place in Hospital Interior Ministry in Glucholazy supervised by a physiotherapist 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group will be  assesses before and after 3-weeks pulmonary rehabilitation.
Model B
* specific respiratory exercises for 30 minutes - relaxation exercises for breathing muscles, strengthening exercises the diaphragm with resistance, exercises to increase costal or chest breathing, prolonged exhalation exercise, chest percussion, once a day for 30 min, 5-time a week;
* training on a cycle ergometer or treadmill, twice a day for 20-30 min.- until the Heart Rate reaches 60% of the HRmax (220-age),
* 30 minutes of fitness and respiratory exercises - coordination and balance exercises, stretching exercises using elastic bands, balls rehabilitation, sensory pillows. Performed in a standing position, kneeling, sitting, lying on side, abdomen and back.
* walking / Nordic Walking (depending on weather and health condition of the patient) for 45 min.;
* relaxation training by Shultz and Jacobson. The technique involves the daily practice of sessions that last around 15 minutes. During each session, the practitioner repeats a set of visualisations that induce a state of relaxation. Each session can be practiced in a position chosen amongst a set of recommended postures (for example, lying down, sitting meditation, sitting like a rag doll). The technique can be used to alleviate many stress-induced psychosomatic disorders.
           Model C
* specific respiratory exercises for 30 minutes - relaxation exercises for breathing muscles, strengthening exercises the diaphragm with resistance, exercises to increase costal or chest breathing, prolonged exhalation exercise, chest percussion, once a day for 30 min, 5-time a week;
* training on a cycle ergometer or treadmill, once a day for 20-30 min.- until the Heart Rate reaches 60% of the HRmax (220-age),
* 30 minutes of fitness and respiratory exercises - coordination and balance exercises, stretching exercises using elastic bands, balls rehabilitation, sensory pillows. Performed in a standing position, kneeling, sitting, lying on side, abdomen and back.
* walking / Nordic Walking (depending on weather and health condition of the patient) for 45 min.;
* relaxation training by Shultz and Jacobson. The technique involves the daily practice of sessions that last around 15 minutes. During each session, the practitioner repeats a set of visualisations that induce a state of relaxation. Each session can be practiced in a position chosen amongst a set of recommended postures (for example, lying down, sitting meditation, sitting like a rag doll). The technique can be used to alleviate many stress-induced psychosomatic disorders.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>physical fitness (endurance, fatigue) assessed using Functional Fitness Test</outcome>
      <timepoint>1. baseline - Initial assessment of the patient, 
2. 3 weeks - Final assessment of patient after 3 weeks of PR including physical fitness assessment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lung function (composite of FEV1, FVC, FEV1%FVC) assessed using spirometry</outcome>
      <timepoint>1. baseline - Initial assessment of the patient, 
2. 3 weeks - Final assessment of patient after 3 weeks of PR including physical fitness assessment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>dyspnea assessed using Borg Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>1. baseline - Initial assessment of the patient, 
2. 3 weeks - Final assessment of patient after 3 weeks of PR including physical fitness assessment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>quality of life assessed using St George's Respiratory Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>1. baseline - Initial assessment of the patient,</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Diagnosed COPD in categories B,  C GOLD; 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>* No patient consent to participate in research 
* Age below 40 and above 70 years of age
* Pneumonia, tuberculosis and other respiratory inflammatory disease in all stages and forms
* Condition after a heart attack
* Diabetes
* State after thoracic and cardiac surgery 
* Heart failure (stage III, IV ° NYHA)
* Advanced hypertension
* Diseases and injuries that can impair the function of the musculoskeletal system of transportation
* Cognitive disorders, to prevent contact with the patient.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The statistical analysis will be carried out using Statistica 10 software.  It was planned to determine the distribution of variables. In the absence of Fundamentals reject the hypothesis of a normal distribution is performed ANOVA with Tukey's test reproducible measurements do post-hoc, and with the rejection of the hypothesis of a normal distribution will be done Friedman ANOVA.The statistical significance level was accepted at p&lt;0.05 for all tests.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>3/08/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>10/11/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>106</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>2/12/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Opole</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Opole University of Technology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>76 Proszkowska Street
45-758 Opole</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Poland</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Opole University of Technology</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>76 Proszkowska Street
45-758 Opole</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Poland</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>none</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>none</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>1. The objective of the study is to evaluate the usefulness of exercise training using the Xbox Kinect system during hospital rehabilitation of patients with COPD.
2. Information for the patients about aims and principle in research and written consent of participation from the patients.
The aim of the study was to assess the effect of rehabilitation program conducted on fitness and exercise capacity, lung ventilatory function and dyspnea. Additionally, possibility for rehabilitation in patients with COPD</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bioethical commission Opole Medical Chamber in Opole</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>grunwaldzka 23 street
Opole</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/02/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>199/07.02.2013</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/12/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Poland</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372066-decyzjakomisjaPRELUDIUM.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372066-Bioethical commission Opole Medical Chamber in Opole.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Sebastian Rutkowski</name>
      <address>Opole University of Technology 76 Proszkowska Street 45-758 Opole</address>
      <phone>+48507027792</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.rutkowski@po.opole.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Sebastian Rutkowski</name>
      <address>Opole University of Technology 76 Proszkowska Street 45-758 Opole</address>
      <phone>+48507027792</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.rutkowski@po.opole.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Jan Szczegielniak</name>
      <address>Opole University of Technology 76 Proszkowska Street 45-758 Opole</address>
      <phone>+48774498000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jan.szczegielniak@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>