<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370944">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/06/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000978460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy and safety of dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine for uncomplicated falciparum and vivax malaria cases</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy and safety of dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine for the treatment of uncomplicated Plasmodium falciparum and Plasmodium vivax malaria in 2 sentinel sites in Indonesia</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>malaria</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>To assess the efficacy and safety of  DHA-PIP (containing 40 mg dihydroartemisinin and 320 mg piperaquine) tablets will be administered once a day for 3 days, administered as a weight per dose regimen of 2.25 and 18 mg/kg of dihydroartemisinin and piperaquine. The treatment will be taken orally under direct supervision by the health worker. Eligibile subjects will be treated for three days and followed up for 42 days.  </interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of DHP-PIP treatment failure (with early treatment failure, late clinical failure, late parasitological failure).

Participants will be assessed for parasitological (using microscopy), clinical responses during the 42 days follow-up and treatment outcomes will be classified according to the latest WHO protocol. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 42-day follow-up of DHP-PIP treatments </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The known adverse events of dihydroartemisinin and piperaquine are abdominal pain, asthenia, cough, diarrhoea, dizziness, insomnia, loss of appetite, nausea, vomiting.

Parents or guardians of all enrolled patients will be asked routinely about previous symptoms and about symptoms that have emerged since the previous follow-up visit. When clinically indicated, patients will be evaluated and treated appropriately. All adverse events will be recorded on the case report form. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At day 42 following initiation of treatment. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prevalence of artemisinin resistance molecular markers (K13).
Parasite DNA extracted from the dried blood spots will be analyzed by PCR and sequencing for the presence of K13 (molecular marker for artemisinin resistance). 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Day 0 (prior initiation of treatment) </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. age between one year (weight more than 5 kgs) to 65 years old 
2. parasitaemia of more than 500 asexual parasites/micro litter for P.falciparum  and 250 asexual parasites/micro litter P.vivax
3. presence of axillary temperature greater than 37.5 degrees celsius or history of fever during the past 24 h
4. ability to swallow oral medication
5. ability and willingness to comply with the study protocol for the duration of the study and to comply with the study visit schedule; and
6. informed consent from the patient or from a parent or guardian in the case of children.
7. informed consent from the patient or from a parent or guardian in the case of children aged less than 18 years (age of majority in this country)
8. informed assent from any minor participant aged from 12 to age of majority years; and
9. consent for pregnancy testing from female of child-bearing potential and from their parent or guardian if under the age of majority years
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>1</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. presence of general danger signs in children aged under 5 years or signs of severe falciparum malaria according to the definitions of WHO
2. mixed or mono-infection with another Plasmodium species detected by microscopy
3. presence of severe malnutrition (defined as a child whose growth standard is below 3 z-score, has symmetrical oedema involving at least the feet or has a mid-upper arm circumference less than  110 mm)
4. presence of febrile conditions due to diseases other than malaria (e.g. measles, acute lower respiratory tract infection, severe diarrhoea with dehydration) or other known underlying chronic or severe diseases (e.g. cardiac, renal and hepatic diseases, HIV/AIDS)
5. regular medication, which may interfere with antimalarial pharmacokinetics
6. history of hypersensitivity reactions or contraindications to any of the medicine(s) being tested or used as alternative treatment(s)
7. a positive pregnancy test or breastfeeding (include this criterion only if adults are included)
8. unable to or unwilling to take pregnancy test or to use contraception for women of child-bearing age and who are sexually active.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>As the treatment failure rate to DHP in the area is unknown, a rate of 30% has been chosen. At a confidence level of 95% and a precision around the estimate of 10%, a minimum of 50 patients must be included in each arm. With a 20% increase to allow loss to follow-up and withdrawals during the 42-day follow-up period, a total of 120 patients (60 with P. falciparum and 60 with P. vivax malaria) should be included in the study per site. 

The data will be double entered and validated by using Epidata software and will be analysed by using SPSS for windows . Data will be analysed by two methods: the Kaplan-Meier method and per-protocol analysis. In addition to the reasons for withdrawal  will be considered withdrawn from the analysis if the PCR results are unclassifiable or if the results of PCR indicate that the failure is due to reinfection with P. falciparum or P. vivax.
The final analysis will include:
1. a description of all patients screened and the distribution of reasons for non-inclusion in the study
2. a description of all the patients included in the study
3. the proportion of adverse events and serious adverse events in all the patients included in the study
4. the proportion of patients lost to follow-up or withdrawn, with 95% confidence intervals and a list of reasons for withdrawal
5. the cumulative incidence of success and failure rates at day 42, PCR-uncorrected and PCR-corrected
6. the proportion of early treatment failure, late clinical failure, late parasitological failure and adequate clinical and parasitological response at day 42, with 95% confidence intervals, PCR-uncorrected and PCR-corrected
7. the proportion of patients with asexual parasitemia on day 3
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/08/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/06/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Indonesia</country>
      <state>Papua Province (Jayapura and Keroom Districts); Bengkulu Province (Bengkulu Utara Province)</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Ministry of Research, Technology and Higher Education, Republic of Indonesia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Lembaga Biologi Molekuler Eijkman
Jalan Diponegoro No. 69
jakarta 10430</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Indonesia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>World Health Organization</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>World Health Organization-Indonesia
 Jl. HR. Rasuna Said
Bina Mulia Building
9th floor Jakarta Pusat Indonesia
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Indonesia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ministry of Health, Republic of Indonesia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Subdit Malaria Direktorat P2P Tular Vektor &amp; Zoonotik
Ditjen Pencegahan dan Pengendalian Penyakit
Gedung C Lantai 2
Jl. Percetakan Negara No. 29
Jakarta 10560</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Indonesia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ministry of Research, Technology and Higher Education, Republic of Indonesia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Lembaga Biologi Molekuler Eijkman
Jalan Diponegoro No. 69
jakarta 10430</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Indonesia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Title: Efficacy and safety of dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine (DHA-PIP) for the treatment of uncomplicated Plasmodium falciparum and Plasmodium vivax in 2 sentinel sites in Indonesia.

Purpose: To assess the efficacy of the current first treatment policy

Objective: To assess the efficacy and safety of dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine for the treatment of uncomplicated P. falciparum and P. vivax malaria infections.

Study Sites: Papua Province and Bengkulu Province.
Study Period: July 2016 to June 2017.
Study Design: One arm prospective study. 

Patient population: Febrile patients aged between one year to 65 years old, with confirmed uncomplicated P. falciparum or P. vivax infection. Young females of child bearing age (12 years and above or those who had their menarche) will be excluded due to culturally sensitive reasons.

Sample Size: A total of 120 patients (60 with P. falciparum and 60 with P. vivax malaria) will be enrolled in each site per each antimalarial drug.

Treatment(s) and follow-up: DHA-PIP (containing 40 mg dihydroartemisinin and 320 mg piperaquine) tablets will be administered once a day for 3 days, administered as a weight per dose regimen of 2.25 and 18 mg/kg of dihydroartemisinin and piperaquine. Clinical and parasitological parameters will be monitored over a 42-day follow-up period to evaluate drug efficacy.

Primary endpoints: The proportion of patients with early treatment failure, late clinical failure, late parasitological failure or an adequate clinical and parasitological response as indicators of efficacy.  Recrudescence will be distinguished from re-infection by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) analysis.

Secondary endpoints: The frequency and nature of adverse events.
Optional exploratory endpoints: 
1. to determine the polymorphism of molecular markers for name of the antimalarial drug(s) resistance.
2. to determine the blood concentration of piperaquine. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>N/A</trialwebsite>
    <publication>N/A</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>KOMITE ETIK PENELITIAN KESEHATAN, Fakultas Kedokteran Universitas Hasanuddin, RSPTN Universitas Hasanuddin RSUP dr. Wahidin Sudirohusodo Makassar</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Lantai 2 Gedung Laboratorium Terpadu FKUH
JL.PERINTIS KEMERDEKAAN KAMPUS TAMALANREA KM.10 MAKASSAR 90245
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/05/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>UH16040426</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/05/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Indonesia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Din Syafruddin</name>
      <address>Eijkman Institute for Molecular Biology
Jalan Diponegoro 69
Jakarta 10430</address>
      <phone>+62 21 3917131</phone>
      <fax>+62 21 3147982</fax>
      <email>din@eijkman.go.id</email>
      <country>Indonesia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Puji BS Asih</name>
      <address>Eijkman Institute for Molecular Biology
Jalan Diponegoro 69
Jakarta 10430</address>
      <phone>+62 21 3917131</phone>
      <fax>+62 21 3147982</fax>
      <email>puji@eijkman.go.id</email>
      <country>Indonesia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Din Syafruddin</name>
      <address>Eijkman Institute for Molecular Biology
Jalan Diponegoro 69
Jakarta 10430</address>
      <phone>+62 21 3917131</phone>
      <fax>+62 21 3147982</fax>
      <email>din@eijkman.go.id</email>
      <country>Indonesia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Puji BS Asih</name>
      <address>Eijkman Institute for Molecular Biology
Jalan Diponegoro 69
Jakarta 10430</address>
      <phone>+62 21 3917131</phone>
      <fax>+62 21 3147982</fax>
      <email>puji@eijkman.go.id</email>
      <country>Indonesia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>