<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372516">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/03/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/03/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000424303</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Efficacy of Ajapa Japa Meditation on Symptoms of Anxiety Disorder</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The efficacy of Ajapa Japa Meditation on Anxiety Symptoms in patients with Anxiety</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1193-9881</utrn>
    <trialacronym>-</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>-</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>anxiety</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Aims of the project:
 
This research study intends to evaluate the efficacy of an 8-week yoga meditation intervention utilising an ancient meditation technique known as Ajapa Japa in reducing anxiety, sleep problems, improving quality of life and increasing trait mindfulness for individuals with Anxiety Disorders. This meditation technique has never previously been used with Anxiety Disorder patients.
 
Research Design:
 
Participants:
The participants will be volunteers from St John of God Outpatient programs (SJOG) who have Anxiety Disorders, who are 18 years or older, English speakers, have not had a previous psychotic episode and who are not experienced meditators. 
Method:
These participants will perform the Ajapa japa meditation at least three times a week over 8 weeks. The meditation in total would take 15  minutes per session. The participants will be lead in person through the meditation by the student researcher Sally Blair once a week in the Outpatient Hospital suite. The other 2 meditations will be done by way of an audio meditation which is lead by Dr Swami Shankadev who is a medical doctor, a yoga swami and psychotherapist who lives and works in Sydney. The participants will receive the meditation via google drive and will download it onto their computer or personal device. The participants will perform track 3 and 4 of the meditation a minimum of twice a week at a time and place of their choosing. Thus, the participants will have one live session of meditation at the hospital per week and do two audio sessions of meditation a time and place of their choosing at least twice per week. 

Adherence to the meditation will be assessed by asking the participants to complete a sheet determining a) how many times they did the meditation 2) whether they were engaged in the meditation in a mindful fashion or not. These sheets will be returned to the student researcher after 8 weeks.

Importantly, the participants will be still receiving their usual outpatient treatment throughout the 8-week period. 

</interventions>
    <comparator>Control Groups:
The control groups for this experiment would consist of a waitlist group from the outpatients programs at SJOG Burwood who are currently participating in treatment as usual in their Outpatient Group.

The control group will be sent the meditation intervention by way of Google Drive following the 12 week follow-up period.

The usual treatment is a CBT-based outpatient group therapy for individuals with Anxiety Disorders. Topics covered include: 
understanding anxiety
dealing with anxiety
managing anxious and negative thoughts
relaxation strategies and other stress management techniques
mindfulness meditation and skills.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>    The Beck Anxiety Inventory (BAI: Beck, Epstein, Brown, &amp; Steer, 1988). The BAI is a brief 21-item questionnaire that assesses anxiety symptoms (0-3 Likert scale; total score 0-63).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 8-weeks and 12-weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> 

*The Five Facet Mindfulness Questionnaire (FFMQ; Baer, Smith, Hopkins, Krietemeyer, &amp; Toney, 2006). The FFMQ is a 39-item that assesses mindfulness on five scales (1-5 Likert scale; total score 39-195).  

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 8-weeks and 12-weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>* The Quality of Life Inventory (QOLI; Frisch, Cornell, Villanueva, &amp; Retzlaff, 1992). The QOLI assesses the importance of (0-2) Likert scale) and satisfaction with (-3 to 3 Likert scale) 16 life domains on 32 items (total score -6 to 6);     </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 8 weeks and 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Insomnia Severity Index (ISI; Morin, 1993). The ISI is a brief questionnaire that assesses insomnia on 7 items (0-4 Likert scale; total score 0-28);
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 8 weeks and 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The participants must have an Anxiety Disorder, not have had a  psychotic episode, not be experienced meditators and be able to understand English.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>The absence of an Anxiety Disorder.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by computer.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Whilst group 1 does the meditation they are also receiving treatment as usual in their outpatient group. Group 2 will only be receiving the treatment as usual in their outpatient group during the same time period.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>To determine the sample size required, an a priori power analysis was conducted using G*Power 3.1.9.2 This identified that to achieve a target power of .80 with p &lt; .05, an anticipated medium effect size, and two predictor variables (time and meditation), a sample size of 86 would be required. However, as this is a pilot study, a smaller number of participants is anticipated.
 
To determine the participants anxiety levels, quality of life, trait mindfulness and sleep quality over the 8-week time period in both the treatment and control group, a 2 (participant type: control vs treatment) by 3 (time: pre, 8 weeks, 12 weeks) mixed design ANOVA will be performed.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>86</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St John of God Hospital - Burwood</hospital>
    <postcode>2134 - Burwood</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australian Catholic University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>25A Barker St, Strathfield NSW 2135</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Catholic University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>25A Barker St, Strathfield, NSW 2135</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>St John of God, Burwood</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>13 Grantham St, Burwood, NSW 2134</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This research proposal makes four hypotheses:

1. The practice of Ajapa Japa meditation will reduce the levels of anxiety symptoms experienced by participants;

2. The practice of Ajapa Japa meditation will improve the quality of sleep experienced by participants;

3. The practice of Ajapa Japa meditation will improve the participants quality of life; &amp;

4. The practice of Ajapa Japa will increase the participants trait mindfulness.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>-</trialwebsite>
    <publication>-</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>-</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>ACU Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>25A Barker Rd, Strathfield, NSW 2135</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/02/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016-306E</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/09/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372516-ACU participant info letter with logos.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372516-Memorandum of Agreement SJOG.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Ewa Geba</name>
      <address>Mary Aikenhead Clinic
Australian Catholic University
163-167 Albert Rd, Strathfield, NSW 2135</address>
      <phone>+61 2, 9701 4708</phone>
      <fax>-</fax>
      <email>ewa.geba@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sally Blair</name>
      <address>Mary Aikenhead Clinic
Australian Catholic University
163-167 Albert Rd, Strathfield, NSW 2135</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9701 4708</phone>
      <fax>-</fax>
      <email>sally.blair@myacu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Ewa Geba</name>
      <address>Mary Aikenhead Clinic
Australian Catholic University
163-167 Albert Rd, Strathfield, NSW 2135</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9701 4708</phone>
      <fax>-</fax>
      <email>ewa.geba@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sally Blair</name>
      <address>Mary Aikenhead Clinic
Australian Catholic University
163-167 Albert Rd, Strathfield, NSW 2135</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9701 4708</phone>
      <fax>-</fax>
      <email>sally.blair@myacu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>