<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="81619">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/10/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/11/2006</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000471583</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>OVATURE (OVArian TUmor REsponse) study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Multi-Center, Randomized, Double-Blind, Phase III Efficacy Study Comparing Phenoxodiol (Oral Dosage Form) in Combination with Carboplatin versus Carboplatin with Placebo in Patients with Platinum-Resistant or Platinum-Refractory Late-Stage Epithelial Ovarian, Fallopian or Primary Peritoneal Cancer Following at Least Second Line Platinum Therapy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>OVATURE</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Epithelial ovarian, fallopian or primary peritoneal cancer that is resistant or refractory to 2-weekly, 3- or 4-weekly platinum drug therapy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ovarian and primary peritoneal</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention group The Phenoxodiol oral dose will be 2x200mg capsules taken 8 hourly (three times per day). Patients will receive carboplatin at a dosage of (Area Under the Curve) AUC=2, administered by intravenous injection once a week. Carboplatin will be administered weekly as a change in regimen from 3-weekly to weekly has been shown with taxanes to provide tumor response in patients whose tumors have become resistant to a 3-weekly regimen. The OVATURE study will compare Phenoxodiol (in the oral dosage form) combined with Carboplatin against Placebo combined with Carboplatin. The duration of each treatment cycle will be 4 weeks and there is no limit to the number of treatment cycles that can be administered. The expected overall trial completion date is March 2010. Treatment cycles will be discontinued in the case of unacceptable toxicity, disease progression, patient voluntary withdrawal, or if the Investigator or Sponsor asks for the patient to be withdrawn.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group The Placebo (sugar pill) oral dose will be 2x200mg capsules taken 8 hourly (three times per day). All patients will receive carboplatin at a dosage of AUC=2(Area Under the Curve),  administered by intravenous injection once a week. There is no maximum or minimum limit to the number of cycles a patient may undertake, however patient may withdraw at any time for any reason. Therefore, the control group will continue through cycles from 10/2006 until 03/2010 taking placebo unless the subject withdraws or is asked to withdraw.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression-free survival (PFS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>From time of randomisation until disease progression (CT scan every 8 weeks, cancer tumour marker (CA125) measured every 2 weeks)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Drug-associated toxicity and intolerance</outcome>
      <timepoint>Medical examination at screening, every 4 weeks and at end of study; Electrocardiogram (ECG) at screening and end of treatment visit; blood tests at screening, every week and at end of study.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Efficacy: Overall survival</outcome>
      <timepoint>From randomisation until patient death from any cause</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tertiary Efficacy: Overall response rate </outcome>
      <timepoint>CT scan taken every 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of response</outcome>
      <timepoint>CT scan taken every 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical status evaluated by Karnofsky Performance Score</outcome>
      <timepoint>Screening visit, every 4 weeks, at the end of treatment and 4 weeks post-treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life </outcome>
      <timepoint>At screening visit, every 8 weeks, end of treatment and 4 weeks post treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) histologically-confirmed ovarian, fallopian, or primary peritoneal carcinoma of epithelial origin; 2) recurrent or persistent advanced disease; 3) have measurable disease; 4) Treatment response history; 5) undergone at least two courses of therapy with a platinum drug (cisplatin or carboplatin) and have responded to the first of those courses of therapy as determined by either RECIST or GCIG criteria; 6)shown disease relapse as determined by either RECIST or GCIG criteria within 6 months of completion of the second or greater course of platinum therapy using a 2-3 or 4 -weekly regimen and have a platinum-free interval of no greater than 6 months at the time of enrollment; 7) can have any number of previous courses of platinum therapy or non-platinum therapy; 8) be considered likely to survive at least 3 months; 9) have a Karnofsky Performance Score of at least 60%; 10) have adequate physiological function without evidence of major organ dysfunction; 11) have adequate hematological function defined by platelets &gt; 100,000/ mm3, WCC &gt; 3,000/mm3, neutrophils &gt; 1,500 /mm3, hemoglobin more than or equal to 8.0 g/dl; 12) Have a negative pregnancy test (HCG) in patients of childbearing potential 13) be aged 18 or older and be able to understand the risks and benefits of the study and give written informed consent to participation.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) patients with mucinous histological type of ovarian cancer; 2) patients who have failed to show a clinical response (RECIST or GCIG criteria) to at least one prior course of platinum therapy; 3) patients with active infection; 4) patients with concurrent severe and/or uncontrolled medical disease (e.g., uncontrolled diabetes, hypertension, ischemic heart disease, congestive heart failure, etc.); 5) patients with a history of chronic active hepatitis or cirrhosis; 6) patients with HIV; 7) patients with active CNS metastases. Patients with known CNS metastases must have received prior radiation therapy, and CNS metastatic disease must be stable for 4 weeks; 8) patients who have not recovered from the acute effects of any prior anti-neoplastic therapy; 9) and patients with known hypersensitivity to platinum drugs drugs that can not be managed with concomitant medication.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central Randomisation by Phone</concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted Block Randomisation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>subjects, doctors/investigators, nurses, study coordinators, pharmacists, sponsor of drug, data management</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/10/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>340</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,SA</recruitmentstate>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <state>TX, CA, NJ, KS, CT, TN, UT, OH, VA, NV, GA, MI, NC, NY, NM, AZ, LA</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Leuven, Edegam</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Gdansk, Bialystok, Krakow, Warszawa, Gliwice, Poznan,</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Glasgow, Wirral, Birmingham, Edinburgh, London, Nottingham, Sutton, Leeds, Somerset, Dundee,</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona, Alincante, Valencia,</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Marshall Edwards Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>140 Wicks Rd
North Ryde 2113</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Marshall Edwards Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>140 Wicks Rd
North Ryde 2113</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The OVATURE study will compare the investigational drug Phenoxodiol combined with the chemotherapy drug Carboplatin against a placebo combined with Carboplatin. It is hypothesised that Phenoxodiol will reverse chemo-resistance to platinum drugs in late stage ovarian, fallopian and primary peritoneal cancers.

For more information on the study and sponsor go to http://www.marshalledwardsinc.com/ or
www.phenoxodiol.com</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.OVATUREtrial.com</trialwebsite>
    <publication>ESGO 2007 Symposium</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Brisbane Mater Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/09/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>989A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/09/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>060824</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Prince of Wales Hospital Randwick</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/10/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>06/143</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Womens Hospital Melbourne(not currently recruiting)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/10/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>06/29</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Westmead Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/10/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2006/7/4.4(2382)</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal North Shore Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/03/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Alan Husband</name>
      <address>140 Wicks Rd
North Ryde NSW 2113</address>
      <phone>+61 2 98780088</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 98780055</fax>
      <email>drugtrials@novogen.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Alan Husband</name>
      <address>140 Wicks Rd
North Ryde NSW 2113</address>
      <phone>+61 2 98780088</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 98780055</fax>
      <email>drugtrials@novogen.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Iris Alhassid</name>
      <address>140 Wicks Road
North Ryde 2113</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>Iris.Alhassid@novogen.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>