<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371577">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/10/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/10/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001413415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An ex vivo investigation into diagnosis of coeliac disease by multiple light-based methods. A proof of principle study towards future development of an in vivo point of care diagnosis device.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An ex vivo investigation into diagnosis of coeliac disease by multiple spectroscopic methods. A proof of principle study towards development of an in vivo point of care diagnosis device.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1184-1036</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>coeliac disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>During a gastroscopy procedure (that the patient is already undertaking) an additional 2-4 biopsies will be collected from the duodenum. These additional biopsies will be analysed spectroscopically followed by standard histological analysis for diagnosis of coeliac disease. The spectroscopic techniques to be carried out on the biopsied tissue  include Raman, near-infrared, mid-infrared and fluorescence spectroscopy. These biopsies will be used to determine if a particular form or combination of spectroscopic techniques is a valid potential method for diagnosis of gastrointestinal illnesses. This procedure will only occur once per patient and should not interfere with the reason for undertaking the gastroscopy and any subsequent diagnoses in the first place. In addition patients will be asked some questions relating to their medical history and medication to check for interfering variables.</interventions>
    <comparator>Patients who are undergoing a gastroscopy for reasons not related to coeliac disease diagnosis will be invited to act as controls in this study. Their biopsies will undergo the exact same combination of spectroscopic and histological analysis to ensure they are indeed controls based on the histological results. The histological analysis will act as the comparator to the spectroscopic analysis in this study.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine if a combination of spectroscopic methods can be used to detect the presence/absence of coeliac disease. The sensitivity and selectivity of these methods will be determined using the current "gold standard" for coeliac diagnosis - histological analysis. The first 2/3rds patients will be used in the spectroscopic model development in combination with multivariate data analysis methods and the final 1/3rd of patients biopsies will act as an independent test set.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The primary outcome will be established approximately one year into data collection or after 80 patients biopsies have been analysed. The biopsies will be collected from each participant in the study at the time of the scheduled gastroscopy. Spectroscopic analysis will be carried out within 2 hours of the biopsy collection, with the sample then immediately being sent on for histological analysis. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In addition to the presence/absence of coeliac disease, we would like to determine if the severity of coeliac disease present can be detected using spectroscopic methods with the histological analysis acting as the standard for determining degree of damage to the villi.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Approximately 1 year into the study or after 80 patients biopsies have been analysed.
The biopsies will be collected from each participant in the study at the time of the scheduled gastroscopy. Spectroscopic analysis will be carried out within 2 hours of the biopsy collection, with the sample then immediately being sent on for histological analysis. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients already undergoing a gastroscopy for either coeliac disease detection or an unrelated reason (control) are invited for inclusion in this study so that the risk of inclusion in the study is associated with an additional 2-4 biopsies collected rather than the gastroscopic procedure itself.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Minors are excluded from this study.
To minimise the risk of bleeding or infection due to biopsy, patients who are at risk of these complications are excluded from this study such as patients with bleeding disorders, taking anticoagulation medicine or patients who are severely immunocompromised .
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The group that the patient will belong to is dependent on the histological results - Coeliac disease present versus control/coeliac disease not detected. The first 2/3rds of patients data will be used as the model development for relating the spectroscopic data to the diagnosis whereas the final 1/3rd of patients will act as a blind test set to determine the sensitivitly and selectivity of the spectroscopic detection methods.</concealment>
    <sequence>First 2/3rds of patients will be used as model development and the final 1/3rd of patients will act as an independent test set.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>All patients are treated equally with an additional set of biopsies collected and analysed independently of their reason for undergoing a gastroscopy. Involvement in the study will not alter their treatment in any way. Their grouping in the study is dependent on their tissue diagnosis (coeliac disease versus control) and time point at which their biopsy was collected during the study (model set versus test set).</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>2-4 biopsies will be collected from 80 patients (160-320 biopsies). Each biopsy will be analysed 5x with each spectroscopic technique studied to give 800-1600 spectra/technique. This would mean model development will contain 533-1067 spectra (from ~53 patients) with approximately equal proportions from the control and coeliac diseased tissues. The remaining  267-533 spectra (from ~27 patients) will act as the independent test set to determine the diagnostics prediction models sensitivity and selectivity. The diagnositic prediction models for the spectroscopic data will be setup using multivariate analysis methods such as partial least squares discriminant analysis.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/10/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>11/11/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/07/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>19</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/07/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Otago</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dunedin School of Medicine, University of Otago</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Dunedin School of Medicine
PO Box 56
Dunedin
9054
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>New Zealand Society of Gastroenterology</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>4th Floor, RACP College Office 
99 The Terrace 
PO Box 10-601
Wellington 6143
New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Otago Research Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of Otago
Dunedin
New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to determine if spectroscopic (light-based) techniques such as Raman, infrared and fluorescence spectroscopy can be used to detect illnesses of the gastrointestinal tract. The model illness studied here is coeliac disease to determine if any one or a combination of these spectroscopic techniques can differentiate diseased from healthy tissue with high sensitivity and selectivity. Should this study give promising results then future work will involve the development of a spectroscopic probe for point of care diagnosis during a gastroscopy.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and disability ethics committee, NZ</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Freyberg Building
20 Aitken Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/09/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>16/CEN/113</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/08/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sara Miller</name>
      <address>Department of Chemistry,
University of Otago,
P.O. Box 56, 
Dunedin 
9054</address>
      <phone>+64 21 0279 0500</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sara.miller@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Michael Schultz</name>
      <address>Dunedin School of Medicine
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin
9054</address>
      <phone>+64 3 474 0999</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michael.schultz@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Keith Gordon</name>
      <address>Department of Chemistry,
University of Otago,
P.O. Box 56, 
Dunedin 
9054</address>
      <phone> +64 3 479 7599</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>keith.gordon@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>