<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83587">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/02/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/05/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000277246</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Phase I intratumoural trial of Coxsackievirus A21 (CAVATAK) in late stage Head and Neck Cancer patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A phase I, open-label, dosage escalation, study of multiple doses of CAVATAKTM (CVA21; Coxsackievirus A21) administered intratumourally in the treatment of squamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck bearing ICAM-1 receptors</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NCT00832559 ClinicalTrials.gov</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Head and Neck Squamous Cell Carcinoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Head and neck</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients will receive an intratumoural dose of CAVATAK estimated to be 30% of the injected tumour volume, with a maximum dose of 2mL.  All doses will be 10^9 50% Tissue Culture Infectivity Dose (TCID50).  The first cohort of patients will receive one dose, the second cohort will receive 3 doses 48 hours apart and the third and final cohort will receive 6 doses 48 hours apart.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety: Patients will be monitored by the trial investigators for vital signs, blood chemistry, haematology, Electrocardiogram (ECG) and adverse events.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patients will be monitored by 11 visits over 127 days post treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Size of the injected tumour and non-injected tumours will be measured in each patient to assess the effect of the treatment against the Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumours (RECIST) criteria</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patients will be monitored by 11 visits over 127 days post treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients who are willing and able to provide written informed consent to participate in the study. Patients with histologically confirmed metastatic or recurrent squamous cell carcinoma of the head or neck currently documented as progressive disease. Head and neck cancer patients with at least one tumour mass where the tumour mass is accessible for intratumoural injection and can be measured at periodic intervals for tumour size using callipers and/or ultrasound.  All patients to have histologically confirmed squamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck (excluding nasopharyngeal) that had recurred or relapsed after surgery and/or radiotherapy and/or chemotherapy. The longest diameter of the target injectable tumour being no greater than 6 cm or no less than 1 cm in the longest diameter.
The tumour mass to be intratumourally injected to be easily accessible for injection and amenable to measurement by physical examination and / or radiographically.
Patients to be 18 years or older
Absence of circulating antibodies to CVA21 (titre &lt; 1:16).
Adequate haematological, hepatic and renal function, defined as:
ANC &gt; 1.5 x 109/L, platelets &gt; 100 x 109/L
Bilirubin &lt; 20umol/L, AST &lt; 2.5 times the upper limit of normal
Calculated creatinine clearance &gt; 30 mL/minute 
Adequate immunologic function, defined as:
Serum IgG &gt; 5g/L
T cell subsets within normal limits
Fertile males and females must agree to the use of an adequate form of
contraception.  Hormonal contraceptives should be supplemented with an additional barrier method.  Negative pregnancy test is required in female patients of child-bearing potential.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients receiving radiotherapy to the proposed injected tumour or radiotherapy within the last 3 weeks 
Performance status &gt; 1 on the Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) scale 
Life expectancy &lt; 6 months.
Pregnancy or breastfeeding.
Primary or secondary immunodeficiency, including immunosuppressive disease, and immunosuppressive doses of corticosteroids (e.g. prednisolone &gt; 7.5mg per day) or other immunosuppressive medications including cyclosporine, azathioprine, interferons, within the past 4 weeks.
Positive serology for Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), Hepatitis B or Hepatitis C.
Splenectomy.
Presence of uncontrolled infection.
Any uncontrolled medical condition that in the opinion of the Investigator is likely to place the patient at unacceptable risk during the study or reduce their ability to complete the study
Participation in another study requiring administration of an investigational drug or biological agent within the last 4 weeks
Known allergy to treatment medication or its excipients</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/02/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>9</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Terminated</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Viralytics Limited</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>1b 55 Grandview Street, Pymble, NSW 2073</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Viralytics Limited</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1b 55 Grandview Street, Pymble, NSW 2073</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study assesses the safety and effectiveness of intratumoural CAVATAK treatment of squamous cell carcinoma (SCC) of the head and neck.
Patients can join the study where:
- they have recurring or relapsed SCC after standard chemotherapy,
- their tumour cells are shown to bear ICAM-1 receptors.
Patients will receive one, three or six doses of CAVATAK injected directly into a tumour.  the injected tumour and other non injected tumours will be measured by calipers and CT scans to assess the effect of the treatment.
Patients will be monitors for 127 days after treatment.
CAVATAK is a benign cancer killing virus that preferentially attacks tumour cells that are expressing the ICAM-1 receptor.
The aim of the study is to investigate the safety and effectiveness of CAVATAK in the treatment of head and neck cancer</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Health Human Research Ethics Committee A</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Directorate
Level 4, Main Block,
246 Clayton Road,
Clayton 3168
VIC</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>11089A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/03/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Assoc. Prof. Darren Shafren</name>
      <address>1b 55 Grandview Street, Pymble NSW 2073</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4913 8158</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>darren.shafren@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Stephen Ackland</name>
      <address>Department of Medical Oncology
Calvary Mater Hospital Newcastle
Edith Street
Waratah 2310</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4921 1770</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>stephen.ackland@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Stephen Goodall</name>
      <address>1b 55 Grandview Street, Pymble, NSW 2073</address>
      <phone>0417 751 244</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>stephen.goodall@viralytics.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>