<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369906">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/01/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/02/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000269437</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Qualitative Study of the Efficacy of Physical Activity Consultation as an Adjunct to Standard Smoking Cessation Treatment in the Context of Malaysia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Qualitative Study of the Efficacy of Physical Activity Consultation as an Adjunct to Standard Smoking Cessation Treatment in the Context of Malaysia</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>smoking addiction</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>smoking withdrawal symptoms</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is a combination of the standard smoking cessation treatment in Malaysia and Physical Activity Consultation (PAC). 

PAC is a customized intervention that combines a number of techniques supported by research, including motivational interviewing, self-efficacy theory, including mastery goal setting, the Transtheoretical Model of Behaviour Change  and relapse prevention. In this study, the PAC aimed to increase physical activity among smokers trying to quit smoking.

Smoking cessation consultation sessions were provided by a nurse with a counselling licence approved by the Malaysian Board of Counsellors. The nurse gave participants behavioural counselling and nicotine replacement therapy in the form of varenicline (Champix). Participants attended the clinic after one week for follow-up. Subsequent visits were scheduled by the clinic nurse depending on participants needs. These consultation sessions were conducted as often as needed by the participants until they were successfully abstinent. 

Smokers who attended the clinic for the first time to seek smoking cessation treatment were invited to participate in the study.  They were approached one week after their first smoking cessation consultation. This ensured participants established their smoking cessation program before starting another intervention. 

PAC was conducted by a facilitator who maintained contact with participants for 21 weeks. PAC consisted of one face-to-face consultation session which lasted for 30 to 40 minutes and two follow-up phone sessions which lasted between 15 to 20 minutes. In the face-to-face consultation, we sought to understand participants level of physical activity, general view on physical activity, provide motivation and help them shape their own path for change, at the same time providing them with a sense of autonomy. We assessed participants for their current stage of change and advised on physical activity to suit their current fitness levels. Advice also covered realistic goal setting and relapse prevention. Phone calls at Weeks 3 and 6 functioned as follow-ups with participants on their progress, as well as providing encouragement and motivation. The phone calls were also strategies to help monitor adherence. The intervention ended at Week 8 and follow up interviews (post-intervention) were conducted at Week 9 and Week 21. 

</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants' scores for withdrawal symptoms measured using the Shiffman-Jarvik Withdrawal Scale.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Week 0 (baseline), Week 9 and Week 21</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants' scores for smoking cessation self-efficacy measured using the Cessation Self-Efficacy Questionnaire.


</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Week 0 (baseline), Week 9 and Week 21</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants' scores for physical activity involvement measured using the International Physical Activity Questionnaire </outcome>
      <timepoint>At Week 0 (baseline), Week 9 and Week 21</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants qualitative experiences with smoking cessation and the PAC, assessed through face-to-face post-intervention interviews.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Week 9 and Week 21</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants' scores for mood measured using the Brunel Mood Scale. 

[Note: This is a primary outcome]</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0 (baseline), Week 9 and Week 21</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants' scores for exercise self-efficacy measured using the Exercise Self-Efficacy Questionnaire.

[Note: This is a primary outcome]</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0 (baseline), Week 9 and Week 21</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Males, over 18 years of age, smoked 10 or more cigarettes per day, the first cigarette smoked within 30 minutes of waking, and were not medically dependent or intellectually impaired.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Started smoking less than 6 months ago, </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>15/04/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>15/01/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>41</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <state>Wilayah Persekutuan Kuala Lumpur</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr. Selina Khoo</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Jalan Universiti, 50603 Kuala Lumpur, Wilayah Persekutuan Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Malaysia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Malaya</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Jalan Universiti, 50603 Kuala Lumpur, Wilayah Persekutuan Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Malaysia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In the present study, we examined the effectiveness of PAC as an adjunct to the standard smoking cessation treatment used in Malaysia. This study aimed to measure and monitor abstinence, changes in self-efficacy for physical activity, withdrawal, smoking cessation, and mood states at baseline, Week 9, and Week 21 of the study. We also aimed to explore individual experiences of participants who undergo a combined physical activity and smoking cessation intervention using in-depth interviews supported by tests of withdrawal, cessation self-efficacy, physical activity involvement, self-efficacy for physical activity and mood. We hypothesized that the PAC will help to increase physical activity involvement, physical activity self-efficacy, smoking cessation self-efficacy and decrease withdrawal symptoms and negative moods.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Malaysian Ministry of Health Medical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Secretariat of National Institutes of Health (NIHSEC)
c/o Institute for Health Management
Jalan Rumah Sakit, Bangsar
59000 Kuala Lumpur</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/04/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Malaysia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Selina Khoo</name>
      <address>Pusat Sukan, Jalan Universiti, 50603 Kuala Lumpur, Wilayah Persekutuan Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia</address>
      <phone>+60 3-7955 2595</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>selina@um.edu.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Selina Khoo</name>
      <address>Pusat Sukan, Jalan Universiti, 50603 Kuala Lumpur, Wilayah Persekutuan Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia</address>
      <phone>+60 3-7955 2595</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>selina@um.edu.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Selina Khoo</name>
      <address>Pusat Sukan, Jalan Universiti, 50603 Kuala Lumpur, Wilayah Persekutuan Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia</address>
      <phone>+60 3-7955 2595</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>selina@um.edu.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Yuin Yi Lee</name>
      <address>395-J Jalan Thamby Abdullah, Bandar Hilir, 75000 Melaka, Malaysia</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>joeynyi@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>