<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362904">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/08/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/08/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000882820</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Talking to Babies in a Neonatal Intensive Care Unit: The impact of verbal soothing on measures of infant stress during painful procedures.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>What is the effect of vocal soothing on preterm infant stress during painful procedures?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1133-5470</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Preterm infant stress</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Complications of newborn</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All infants in this randomized controlled study will be exposed to the two study conditions  vocal soothing by a non parental adult during a routine heel prick procedure and no vocal soothing during a routine heel prick procedure.  The vocal soothing will be offered by the primary investigator for this study.  Vocal soothing will comprise matching vocal tone to the perceived infant emotional and physical experience, for example higher pitch, loud and with shorter sounds during the infants high arousal and a lower pitch, quieter, longer sounds during low arousal.  The purpose of the intervention will be to communicate to the infant that an adult is there and is sympathetic towards them.   The vocal soothing intervention will be offered for 1 hour over the time of the heel prick procedure and subsequent care activities.  There will be at least 12 hours between conditions.  The exact timing between conditions will vary as the second study will take place at the time of the infant's next scheduled heelprick blood test, which will be dependant on clinical need.</interventions>
    <comparator>Each infant will  serve as their own control, receiving two heel prick blood tests, one with  the soothing voice and one without the soothing voice.  A previous study in the NICU that this research will be conducted in found that nurses did not vocally soothe infants in 95%  (95% CI 0.6% - 17%) of heel prick procedures, so the control condition is akin to usual care in most cases.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction of infant stress as assessed by salivary cortisol measures.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Salivary cortisol measures will be taken before the heel prick (baseline), 20 minutes following the heel prick (peak) and 50 minutes following the heel prick (recovery).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction of behavioural measures of infant stress as measured by the Premature Infant Pain Profile (PIPP)</outcome>
      <timepoint>The PIPP score will be calculated for two minutes over the time of the heel prick blood test.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction of infant stress as measured by heart rate variability.  Heart rate will be measured by spectral analysis from an ECG signal.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Heart rate will be recorded continuously for up to 90 minutes over the time of the scheduled heel prick blood test.  The exact length of time will include a period of baseline monitoring and will then depend on how long it takes the nurse to complete the heelprick, cares and feed for each baby.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction of infant stress as measured by oxygen saturations.  Oxygen saturations will be measured by oximetry using the compumetics sleep system.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Oxygen saturations will be recorded continuously for up to 90 minutes over the time of the scheduled heel prick blood test.  The exact length of time will include a period of baseline monitoring and will then depend on how long it takes the nurse to complete the heelprick, cares and feed for each baby.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Non-surgical preterm infants born at 32-35 weeks gestational age, who are in their first two weeks of life, having the heel prick blood tests as part of their usual care and are thought to be healthy enough to participate by their nurse.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>24</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Hours</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>2</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Weeks</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Infants who are sedated, on respiratory support or have had a surgical procedure (surgical infants)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Parents of eligible infants will be provided with a brief verbal overview by the principal investigator, as well as a written information sheet.   The parents who have indicated an interest but have not consented, will be followed up by the principal investigator.   The infants will be randomly allocated to the order of conditions by computer generation.  Order allocation is not concealed, as the principal investigator has the order allocation list and assigns infants to it in the order of received signed consent forms.</concealment>
    <sequence>The order allocation list was randomised using a computer package (R 2.15.1, R Foundation, Vienna, Austria) so that there were equal numbers of voice first/silent first infants in the list. The randomisation was done by blocks.</sequence>
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>27/08/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>63</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Department of Paediatrics and Child health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Otago, Wellington
P O Box 7343
Wellington South 6242</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Hawkes Bay Medical Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 956
Napier 4140</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Otago Fanny Evans Scholarship</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>P O Box 7343
Wellington South 6242</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Neonatal Intensive Care Unit</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Wellington Hospital
Riddiford Street
Newtown
Wellington 6021</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study addresses the question of whether there are differences in measures of infant stress during a routine heel prick blood sampling procedure between two conditions: a non-parental adult talking empathically during the procedure compared with silence during the procedure.
Participating infants will be allocated to the two conditions, in random order.  Each preterm infant will be 32 to 35 weeks gestational age at birth and will be having the heel prick blood tests as part of their usual treatment.
Behavioural measures of infant stress will be captured on video.  Physiological measures of stress will be assessed through continuous monitoring of infant heart rate, breathing and blood oxygen levels during the study period as well as six cotton wool swab saliva samples per infant to measure the stress hormone cortisol.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Central Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 5013
Lambton Quay
Wellington 6145</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/08/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CEN/12/06/021</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Lucie Zwimpfer</name>
      <address>Department of Paediatrics and Child Health
University of Otago, Wellington
PO Box 7343
Wellington South 6242</address>
      <phone>+64-4-918 5062</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Lucie.Zwimpfer@xtra.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Lucie Zwimpfer</name>
      <address>Department of Paediatrics and Child Health
University of Otago, Wellington
PO Box 7343
Wellington South 6242</address>
      <phone>+64-4-918 5062</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Lucie.Zwimpfer@xtra.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>