<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371312">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001133426p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Phase II of The Sildenafil during Coronary artery bypass graft Operations to Reduce Endpoints for patients with Coronary ARtery Disease (SCORECARD) Project</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Phase II of The Sildenafil during Coronary artery bypass graft Operations to Reduce Endpoints for patients with Coronary ARtery Disease (SCORECARD) Project</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1186-5405</utrn>
    <trialacronym>The SCORECARD Project</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Coronary artery disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients who are randomised to the exposure group will receive sildenafil according to the following regime:
Day before CABG:
sildenafil 50 mg orally three times daily.

Day of CABG:
sildenafil 100 mg orally via nasogastric tube at time of commencement of median sternotomy immediately followed by a 25 mL normal saline flush.
sildenafil 50 mg orally at 22:00.

Postoperatively days 1-28:
sildenafil 50 mg orally three times daily. Sildenafil will be delivered orally but, where not possible (such as immediately postoperatively in the Cardiovascular Intensive Care Unit, will be given via nasogastric tube followed by a 25 mL normal saline flush.

NB: Three 50 mg tablets will be reconstituted with a sweetened solution according to local processes in order to create a 75 mL solution, which is equivalent to 150 mg sildenafil. Patients will be given 25 mL of sildenafil solution three times daily.

Cardiothoracic wards, Cardiovascular Intensive Care Units and patients will all be asked to retain empty patient bottles in the designated SCORECARD box, which will be collected by a SCORECARD Project investigator in order to measure adherence. Unused drug will be retained and, once accounted for by a SCORECARD Project investigator, will be given to the locality pharmacy for disposal according to local processes.</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator treatment in this study will be a placebo solution made up of Ora-Sweet (Registered Trademark) solution also given as 25 mL three times daily. The comparator treatment will be designed to taste and look not dissimilar to the exposure group treatment.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pulsatility index measured as transit time flowmetry with the MiraQ(TM) Cardiac Unit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Continuous monitoring for up to two minutes immediately after bypass graft anastomosis for each graft anastomosed.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Graft flow in mL per minute as transit time flowmetry with the MiraQ/(TM) cardiac Unit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Continuous monitoring for up to two minutes immediately after bypass graft anastomosis for each graft anastomosed.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diastolic filling (percentage) as transit time flowmetry using the MiraQ(TM) Cardiac Unit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Continuous monitoring for up to two minutes immediately after bypass graft anastomosis for each graft anastomosed.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mortality-rate</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 30 days postoperatively.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum Troponin T level measured using LabPLUS protocols.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured in ng/L at 2, 4, 6, 8, 12, 18, 24, 36 and 48 hours, postoperatively.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) Patients who are undergoing CABG +/- valve replacement at Auckland or Waikato District Health Board.
2) Patients who are undergoing CABG +/- valve replacement between 1 February 2017 and 1 February 2018.
3) Patients who are recommended and offered elective CABG +/- valve replacement.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients will not be eligible for recruitment if they meet any of the following exclusion criteria:
1) Creatinine clearance less than or equal to 30 mL·min-1.
2) Hepatic failure as determined by Child-Pugh class B or class C.
3) BP less than or equal to 90/50 mm·Hg.
4) Any previous open cardiac surgical procedure.
5) Any history of:
- Pulmonary arterial hypertension.
- Postural hypotension.
- Non-arteritic anterior ischaemic optic neuropathy.
- Hereditary degenerative retinal disorders such as retinitis pigmentosa.
- Recent commencement or increases in alpha blocker dosages.
- Current pregnancy or lactation.
- Allergy to any component of ViagraTM tablet.
6) Any use of sildenafil citrate, tadalafil or vardenafil within the one month prior to enrolment.
7) Any use of glyceryl trinitrate within the previous 24 hours.
8) Concomitant use of isosorbide mononitrate.
9) Concomitant use of potent CYP 3A4 inhibitors:
- Erythromycin.
- Saquinavir.
- Ketoconazole.
- Itraconazole.
- Ritonavir.
10) Presence of any metalware that precludes CMR-use.
11) Unable to provide informed consent.
12) Not eligible for public funding.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>This Feasibility Study will be a double-blind study. The allocation status will be blinded to participants and participants’ clinical teams including their anaesthetist and surgeon. Only the Randomisation Investigator and SCORECARD Pharmacist at each of Auckland and Waikato DHB will have knowledge of participants’ allocation statuses. In the event of emergency unblinding, the Emergency Coordinator will be able to access the patient’s allocation status and may disclose the status to the participant’s clinical team if it s relevant to do so.

Allocation will involve the Principal Investigator contacting the Randomisation Coordinator, who will retain the allocation schedule in a secure firewall-protected database and who is located at a central administration site. The Randomisation Coordinator will update the participant's details and allocation status within the database that is otherwise accessible only to SCORECARD Pharmacists. In this way, allocation statuses will remain blinded.



</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The purpose of this study is to determine the sample size required in order to determine statistical significance in a future phase III trial.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>29/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/02/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland and Waikato</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Auckland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Anaesthesiology
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Auckland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Anaesthesiology
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The gold-standard revascularisation approach for patients with left main stem or multi-vessel coronary artery disease (CAD) is coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) surgery. Vasospasm, graft occlusion and ischaemia-reperfusion injury are complications that commonly arise and significantly impact upon CABG success-rates.
Sildenafil is a type 5 phosphodiesterase inhibitor that has vasodilatory, antiplatelet and ischaemia-reperfusion injury-preventing properties. We hypothesise that these properties of sildenafil could be exploited in patients undergoing CABG by reducing vasospasm, graft occlusion and ischaemia-reperfusion injury complication-rates.
The Sildenafil during CABG Operations to Reduce Endpoints for patients with Coronary ARtery Disease (SCORECARD) Project is a novel multi-centre double-blind randomised controlled trial concept in which the vasodilatory, antiplatelet and ischaemia-reperfusion injury-preventing properties of sildenafil will be investigated in elective patients undergoing CABG. However, a population sample that is of sufficient size and power must first be calculated so that a significant difference can be detected in the future trial.
In this feasibility study, a phase II trial will be undertaken in order to establish the magnitude of the difference in outcomes between sildenafil-treated and placebo-treated groups. Two hundred patients admitted under either Auckland or Waikato District Health Boards cardiothoracic service for elective CABG between 1 February 2017 and 1 February 2018 will be screened against inclusion and exclusion criteria. Patients will be randomised in a double-blind fashion to receive either a sildenafil- or placebo-drug regime. We will collect and compare preoperative and postoperative cardiac magnetic resonance images, transit time flowmetry data, postoperative serum troponin T levels in the first 48 hours and mortality-rates at 30 days.
The results from Phase II of The SCORECARD Project will establish the magnitude of the difference in vasopasm, graft occlusion and ischaemia-reperfusion injury complication-rates between sildenafil-treated and placebo-treated groups. These data will allow for sample size calculations, which will ultimately dictate whether or not it is feasible to proceed with conducting Phase III of The SCORECARD Project.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.scorecard.ac.nz</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Ethics Department
Freyberg Building
Reception  Ground Floor
20 Aitken Street
Wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/12/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Steve Waqanivavalagi</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesiology
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64275370425</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.waqanivavalagi@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Steve Waqanivavalagi</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesiology
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64275370425</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.waqanivavalagi@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Steve Waqanivavalagi</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesiology
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64275370425</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.waqanivavalagi@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Steve Waqanivavalagi</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesiology
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64275370425</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.waqanivavalagi@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>