<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371126">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/07/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000967482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effects of activating nuts on acceptance and gastrointestinal tolerance among healthy individuals</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effects of activating nuts on acceptance and gastrointestinal tolerance among healthy individuals: a randomised crossover study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Gastrointestinal intolerance</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This will be a randomised crossover study with four arms:
Arm 1: 30g per day of  whole raw almonds
Arm 2: 30g per day of sliced raw almonds
Arm 3: 30g per day of whole soaked almonds 
Arm 4: 30g per day of sliced soaked almonds
This study will assess the effects of consuming 4 different types of almonds on consumer acceptance and gastrointestinal tolerance. Participant will be assigned in random order to receive the 4 treatments. Each treatment will last 12 days, with a 2 day washout between treatments.
Participants can eat the almonds anyway time of the day, and can choose to eat them how they wish. 
The almonds will be soaked in water (2 cups of water per 1 cup of nuts) containing 1 tsp of salt per cup of nuts, for 24 hours. The nuts will then be dried for either 12 hours (whole nuts) or 8 hours (sliced nuts) at 65 degrees Celcius. 
Participants will be supplied with their daily portion of 30 g of nuts in individual bags. Adherence will be monitored by the return of these bags. Any uneaten nuts will be weighed.</interventions>
    <comparator>The raw nuts will be compared to the soaked nut treatments</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acceptance. This will be measure on a 10cm visual analogue scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily over the 12 day intervention period</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gastrointestinal tolerance.
Incidence will be measure by a yes/no response.
If participants respond 'yes' we will  measure severity on a 10cm visual analogue scale.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily over the 12 day intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy males and females aged 18 years and over</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>People with allergies or intolerances to nuts
Pregnant women</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation will involve contacting the holder of the allocation scedulem who is an off-site biostatistician</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The outcomes will be modelled using linear mixed models with random participant and random participant effects to accommodate the two levels of repeated measures. Where othe overall test for differences between treatments is significant, pairwise comparisons between groups will be made. For gastrointestinal tolerance, baseline values will also be controlled for. All analysis will be performed using  Stata Statistical Software 12.0 (Statacorp LP, College Station TX, USA). All tests will be performed at the two-sided 0.05 level. 

To provide 90% power to detect a mean difference of 10 mm in acceptance ratings between any two nut types (soaked vs unsoaked), for a particular form, (whole, sliced), and any two nut forms for a particular type, or an two combinations of nut type and form, assuming a standard deviation of 25 mm, which is consistent with our other research and reflects a standardised effect size of 0.4 which can be seen as a small-to-medium difference, using a two-sided significant level of 5% and assuming a correlation of 0.7 or higher between repeated measures, 66 participants would be required with complete data. Allowing for 10% missing or unusable data, 74 participants would need to be recruited. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>25/07/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>25/07/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>15/08/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>15/08/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>74</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>76</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>19/09/2016</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>7/10/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Otago</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Otago</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 56 
Dunedin
9013</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Otago</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 56
Dunedin
9013</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Although nuts are nutrient dense, they are also high in phytate, a compound which can
inhibit the absorption of vitamins and minerals. Soaking nuts is a practice reported in the lay literature as a means of reducing phytate and thus increasing nutrient bioavailability. Soaking is also purported to enhance the gastrointestinal tolerance of nuts. Currently there is no research to support these claims. Our research group will examine the effects of soaking different forms of almonds on consumer acceptance and gastrointestinal symptoms. Acceptance is an important measure because it provides an indication of long-term compliance to eat nuts regularly.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Otago HUman Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 56
Dunedin
9013</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/05/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>16/072</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/05/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rachel Brown</name>
      <address>Department of Human Nutrition
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin
9013</address>
      <phone>+64 3 479 5839</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rachel.brown@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rachel Brown</name>
      <address>Department of Human Nutrition
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin
9013</address>
      <phone>+64 3 479 5839</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rachel.brown@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rachel Brown</name>
      <address>Department of Human Nutrition
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin
9013</address>
      <phone>+64 3 479 5839</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rachel.brown@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rachel Brown</name>
      <address>Department of Human Nutrition
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin</address>
      <phone>+64 3 479 5839</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rachel.brown@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>