<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373506">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/09/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/09/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001380381p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The PEBBLES study  Testing a strategy for preventing eczema and food allergy in high risk infants</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>THE PEBBLES STUDY: A randomised controlled trial to prevent eczema, food allergy and sensitisation using a skin barrier improvement strategy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1201-0431 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>PEBBLES</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Eczema/Atopic Dermatitis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Food Allergy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dermatological conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Allergies</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Twice daily use of a ceramide dominant cream (EpiCeram) to infants skin. Ingredients in the formulation are Capric Acid, Cholesterol, Citric Acid, Conjugated Linoleic Acid, Dimethicone, Disodium EDTA, E. Cerifera (Candelilla)
Wax, Food Starch Modified Corn Syrup Solids, Glycerin, Glyceryl Stearate, Hydroxypropyl Bispalmitamide MEA
(Ceramide), Palmitic Acid, PEG-100 Stearate, Petrolatum, Phenoxyethanol, Potassium Hydroxide, Purified Water,
Sorbic Acid, Squalane, Xanthan Gum. 
Parents will be instructed to apply EpiCeram to the full skin surface of their child twice per day.  The prophylactic use of EpiCeram is the intervention that is being tested for its effect on infant skin barrier function.  We will instruct parents to apply approximately 6 grams of EpiCeram per application at two regular times each day, including after bathing the infant, or at the time they would normally bathe their child.  The PEBBLES study recruiter will demonstrate the application of the cream to parents during the baseline assessment.  Duration of treatment is 6 months.
Mothers will be asked to bring all tubes of cream (both used and unused) with them to all follow-up assessments (when the child is approximately 6 weeks, and 6 months (26 weeks) of age), so that the study coordinator can weigh the remaining cream.  This will allow for an estimate of the total amount of cream applied to the babys skin.  We will also ask mothers how frequently cream was applied and how often applications were missed (Survey 4), and to complete a diary card documenting the days on which cream was applied (Diary Card  treatment group, Diary Card  no treatment group).  Non-adherence will be defined as using the study cream on average for less than five days per week (once per day).</interventions>
    <comparator>The study staff will not provide any directions to parents in the control arm on how to manage their child's skin. No attempt will be made to alter or influence parents treatment of their child's skin in this arm of the study. This is defined as standard skin care. Duration of care is 6 months.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Presence of eczema as assessed using i) the UK working party criteria for eczema and/or ii) blinded investigator observed eczema.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months of age.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Food challenge confirmed food allergy.
A skin prick test to six common allergens will be performed (egg white, cows milk, peanut, dust mite, cat dander, and rye grass) along with a negative (saline) and a positive (histamine) control. Participants that are sensitised to certain foods (&gt;=1mm wheal) during the skin prick testing will be given a challenge to determine if they are allergic to those foods. This will be conducted at the MCRI Allergy Clinic under the supervision of a Doctor specifically trained in oral food challenges.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months of age.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Skin barrier function - as assessed by Trans-epidermal water loss.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks and 6 and 12 months of age.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Eczema severity assessed using the EASI score.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months of age.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parent report of a community doctor diagnosis of eczema.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months of age.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Skin prick test reactivity to any of six allergens; (egg white, cows milk, peanut, dust mite, cat dander, and rye grass). Both a negative (saline) and a positive (histamine) control will be used.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months of age.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine if twice daily application of a ceramide dominant emollient improves infant skin barrier function as assessed by Trans-epidermal water loss</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 weeks and 6 and 12 months of age.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the level of parental compliance with a program to build infant skin barrier function as assessed by parental completion of weekly diary cards and weighing of the tubes of study cream at each visit</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 weeks and 6 months of age.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To confirm that a ceramide dominant emollient does not cause adverse effects in infants as assessed by the documentation of any untoward medical occurrence in a participant enrolled into this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From recruitment of infant until final study visit at 12 months of age.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the level of compliance required to demonstrate an improvement in infant skin barrier function as assessed by the parental completion of weekly diary cards and weighing of the tubes of study cream at each visit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks, 6 and 12 months of age.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine if twice daily application of a ceramide dominant emollient influences infant skinmicrobial colonisation, or skin lipid profile as assessed by Trans-epidermal water loss.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 weeks and 6 and 12 months of age.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Infants will be eligible for this study if their mother, father, or an older sibling has a self-reported history of at least one of the following conditions:
asthma, 
eczema/atopic dermatitis, 
hay fever/ allergic rhinitis 
or food allergy.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>3</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Weeks</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Infants with any of the following will be excluded:
A parent who has a known hypersensitivity to any of the ingredients of EpiCeram will be excluded, as it would be difficult for these parents to apply EpiCeram to their infant, and there is likely to be an increased risk of the infant reacting to the cream.  
Multiple births (twins, triplets etc.) will be excluded, due to the difficulty in randomising individual twins and because of the clustering effect of multiple children from the same family which would reduce the effective sample size of the study.  
Who are born premature (&lt;36 weeks) as the effect of the intervention may be different in premature infants.
Who have major birth or early life medical complications that require admission into a special care nursery, as it will be difficult for parents to comply with the study requirements.
Whose parents do not have sufficient English language skills to be able to answer questions. 
Whose parents are not able to comply with all protocol required visits and procedures.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The random allocation list will be held by the Pharmacy Department for each recruiting cite. Pharmacy staff will be independent from the participant recruitment or testing. The allocation list will be concealed from the study coordinator and other study investigators who will manage participant recruitment.
The PEBBLES study co-ordinator will call the Pharmacy Department by telephone at the end of the one week-baseline assessment to determine the group of allocation. The study coordinator will provide the child's name and this will be recorded on the allocation list. The infant will be allocated to the next study number and assigned to the group corresponding to that unique study identification number.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer generated random allocation list will be generated with variable blocks sizes. Randomisation will be stratified for the number of parents affected by allergic disease (1vs 2). Simple randomisation will be used, with equal numbers of children being allocated to the control and intervention groups.
</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>We will require 760 participants (380 in each group). With 380 infants per group, we will have (1) 86% power to demonstrate that the intervention causes an absolute risk reduction for eczema of 12% (from 40% to 28%, RR=0.7), and (2) 84% power to detect a 11% reduction in sensitisation (from 33% to 22%, RR=0.66), and 3) 80% power to detect a 7.5% reduction in food allergy at 12 months (from 15% to 7.5%, RR=0.5). The estimates of baseline risk of eczema and sensitisation come from our published clinical trial in a similar population, while the prevalence of food allergy comes from our observational study. These estimates allows for up to a 20% loss to follow-up and an alpha of 0.05. Our recent trials have achieved a higher rate of follow-up, making this a conservative estimate. 
Secondary aim: The population prevalence of FLG null mutations is approximately 10%, so in this high risk population we expect it to be at least 15%. This will result in 45 infants per group (allowing for loss to follow-up) with one or more such mutations. We will have approximately 80% power to detect a relative risk of 0.40 (20% vs 50%) induced by the treatment for the outcome of eczema. for the control group to 19 g/cm2/hour in the intervention group (assuming a sd = 11 and an alpha level of 0.05).
The primary analysis will be the comparison of primary outcomes at six, and 12 months of age between participants in the standard skin care group and the intervention group. The primary analysis will be performed using the using the modified intention to treat (ITT) principle analysis. Regardless of the level of compliance with the study protocol or whether they discontinued use of the study treatment, they will be analysed in the group to which they were allocated. The modification of ITT will be that a complete case analysis will be performed. For our main dichotomous outcome measures (eczema, food allergy), the magnitude of any between-group differences will be quantified by calculating relative risk ratio, as well as absolute risk difference and number needed to treat, with 95% confidence intervals for the corresponding population estimates. Further analyses using multivariable log-binomial regression will be undertaken to explore the sensitivity of the effect estimates to imbalance between the groups at baseline on prognostic factors.  Parental compliance to the intervention will be defined as 5 days per week (at least once per day), and a planned per-protocol analysis including only those infants in the intervention group who meet this level of treatment compliance, will be performed. . Both parental report of frequency of administration, and weight of cream used will be used as a potential predictor of risk of eczema. This will help determine if less frequent (or smaller quantity of) application of the study cream could be sufficient to reduce the risk of eczema.

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>3/02/2020</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>760</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>8/02/2021</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Women's Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Mercy Hospital for Women - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Clayton campus - Clayton</hospital>
    <hospital>Frances Perry House - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Jessie McPherson Private Hospital - Clayton</hospital>
    <hospital>The Women’s at Sandringham - Sandringham</hospital>
    <hospital>Cabrini Hospital - Malvern - Malvern</hospital>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
    <postcode>3191 - Sandringham</postcode>
    <postcode>3144 - Malvern</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress> Parkville VIC 3010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>PuraCap</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>20 Kingsbridge Rd
Piscataway Township, NJ 08854, USA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Murdoch Children's Research Institute</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>50 Flemington Road
Parkville,Victoria 3052. </othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary objective of this study is to demonstrate that twice daily application of a ceramide dominant emollient reduces the risk of eczema and food allergy, when compared to standard skin management. Secondary objectives are to determine if twice daily application of a ceramide dominant emollient reduces the risk of infants developing allergic sensitisation (as measured by skin prick test); to determine if twice daily application of a ceramide dominant emollient improves infant skin barrier function; to determine the level of parental compliance with a program to build infant skin barrier function; to confirm that a ceramide dominant emollient does not cause adverse effects in infants; to determine the level of compliance required to demonstrate an improvement in infant skin barrier function and to determine if twice daily application of a ceramide dominant emollient influences infant skinmicrobial colonisation, or skin lipid profile.
This is a phase III, single blind (outcome assessor is blinded), randomised controlled multicentre trial of the effect of EpiCeram emollient for improving and maintaining skin barrier function and reducing incidence of eczema and food allergy in high risk infants.  
A total of 760 participants with a first degree family history of allergic disease (asthma, eczema, allergic rhinitis or food allergy) will be recruited (380 each group) from maternity wards of seven hospitals.
Treatment will be from birth until six months, with a six week, six month and twelve month follow-up. An initial assessment will be performed at baseline which incorporates three surveys, a skin assessment, diary card (which is to be completed weekly and measures compliance), a breast milk sample, guthrie card and tape stripping. The six week and six month assessments entail a skin assessment, survey, compliance check, breast milk sample, tape stripping and guthrie card. Primary outcomes are assessed at the 12 month follow up where in addition to the aforementioned items, a saliva sample will also be taken and skin prick testing and food challenges will be performed when children have a positive SPT to one or more foods.. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Lowe, A.J., et al., A phase I study of daily treatment with a ceramide-dominant triple lipid mixture commencing in neonates. BMC Dermatol, 2012. 12: p. 3.
Lowe, A.J., et al., A randomised trial of a barrier lipid replacement strategy for the prevention of atopic dermatitis and allergic sensitisation: The PEBBLES Pilot Study. Br J Dermatol, 2017 (accepted 15/6/2017).

</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Children's Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>50 Flemington Road
Parkville,Victoria 3052. </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/08/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Adrian Lowe</name>
      <address>Allergy and Lung Health Unit
Centre for Epidemiology and Biostatistics
Melbourne School of Population and Global Health
University of Melbourne VIC 3010
Level 3, 207 Bouverie Street  
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 0878</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9349 5815</fax>
      <email>lowea@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Shaie O'Brien</name>
      <address>Allergy and Lung Health Unit
Centre for Epidemiology and Biostatistics
Melbourne School of Population and Global Health
University of Melbourne VIC 3010
Level 3, 207 Bouverie Street  
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 0643</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9349 5815</fax>
      <email>sdobrien@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Adrian Lowe</name>
      <address>Allergy and Lung Health Unit
Centre for Epidemiology and Biostatistics
Melbourne School of Population and Global Health
University of Melbourne VIC 3010
Level 3, 207 Bouverie Street  </address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 0878</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9349 5815</fax>
      <email>lowea@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Shaie O'Brien</name>
      <address>Allergy and Lung Health Unit
Centre for Epidemiology and Biostatistics
Melbourne School of Population and Global Health
University of Melbourne VIC 3010
Level 3, 207 Bouverie Street  </address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 0643</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9349 5815</fax>
      <email>sdobrien@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>