<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="81655">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/10/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/10/2006</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000451505</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Selection of Nicotine Therapy to Increase Quitting</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A single-blind randomised controlled trial to determine whether smokers who have more choice over which Nicotine Replacement Therapy (NRT) delivery methods they use are more likely to have quit smoking at six months, than smokers with current practice (with NRT available only by patch and/or gum).</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>SONIQ</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>HRC</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Smoking (healthy participants who smoke)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be randomised to a selection box of NRT or current practice.  Telephone counselling and advice will be available to all participants in the usual manner, via Quitline. 

Selection box group: Participants will be sent a box containing four different NRT delivery methods, namely patch (21mg), gum (4mg, fruit and mint), inhaler (10mg), and sublingual tablet (2mg), along with a culturally appropriate video/DVD and printed material.  Participants will be asked to try out each product over a week prior to their quit attempt. Participants will then be contacted by telephone and asked to choose one or two preferred methods of delivery to use for eight weeks after their Quit day.  </interventions>
    <comparator>Control group: Participants in the current practice group will be supported by Quitline in the usual way for an eight week period, with NRT provided as required in the form of patches (7mg, 14mg or 21mg) and/or gum (2mg or 4mg, mint or fruit).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of participants who report 7-day point prevalence abstinence</outcome>
      <timepoint>At six months after Quit day (biochemically verified)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>7-day point prevalence abstinence rates </outcome>
      <timepoint>One week (treatment group only), three weeks and three month.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Three week, three month, and six month continuous abstinence rates (Russell Standard).  Biochemically verified at six months.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three week, three month, and six month after Quit day. Biochemically verified at 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of participants who have significantly reduced (at least 25% reduction) daily smoking levels.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Six months after Quit day.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Current smoking details, if still smoking (including daily consumption level) at one week after selection box use (treatment group only) plus. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At three weeks, three months, and six months after Quit day.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-rated chances of quitting (treatment group only, after one weeks use of selection box)</outcome>
      <timepoint>One week after Quit day.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost information: Cost outcomes will include cost per quitter, cost per person reducing their daily cigarette consumption, and cost per Quality Adjusted Life Year (QALY) of life saved among quitters. The tobacco expenditure savings to individual smokers will also be calculated using data on the daily amount smoked prior to quitting and the price of the particular products smoked. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Six months after Quit day.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Information on NRT delivery three weeks after Quit day: How participants rate the ease of obtaining the NRT (i.e. Delivery to door of NRT for treatment group versus delivery to door of Quit Card and visit to pharmacy for control group). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Three weeks after Quit day</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Information on choice of NRT (treatment group only after one week of use of the selection box): NRT selection (type, dose, flavour), reasons for selection; concerns regarding the use of the products; adequacy of knowledge regarding the use of the products, the importance of having a choice over which products to use, and the importance of the postal delivery of the selection box.</outcome>
      <timepoint>One week after Quit day</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>NRT use (type, dose, flavour, frequency).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At three weeks, three months and six months after Quit day.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serious adverse events after one weeks use of NRT in the selection box (treatment group only).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 1 week after Quit day</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serious adverse events</outcome>
      <timepoint>At three weeks, three months and six months after Quit day.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be people from throughout New Zealand who smoke, who contact Quitline (by phone) for smoking cessation advice and assistance. Smokers will be eligible provided they: want to stop smoking within the next two weeks; have their first cigarette within 30 minutes of waking; are able to provide verbal consent; have a telephone.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnant women and women who are breastfeeding will be excluded from the trial.  People will also be excluded from the trial if they meet any of the following criteria:  current users of NRT products; current users of Zyban (buproprion), clonidine or nortriptyline; use only non-cigarette tobacco products (e.g. pipes, cigars); have had a myocardial infarction within the last three months; and have had unstable or progressive angina pectoris, Prinzmetals angina, severe cardiac arrhythmia or a stroke in acute phase.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by computer</concealment>
    <sequence>Stratified minimisation by sex, ethnicity and level of nicotine dependence (as determined by the time to their first cigarette - a key question in the Fagerstrom Tolerance Questionnaire)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Due to the nature of the intervention only single blinding (of researchers, not of participants) is possible.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Clinical Trials Research Unit, School of Population Health, Auckland University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Private Bag 92019, Auckland</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Health Research Council of New Zealand</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO BOX 5541, Wellesley Street, Auckland, New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The National Heart Foundation of New Zealand</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>P O Box 17-160, Greenlane
9 Kalmia Street, Ellerslie
AUCKLAND 1546
New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The Auckland Tobacco Control Research Centre, School of Population Health, University of Auckland and Health New Zealand Ltd, Christchurch</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Private Bag 92019, Auckland</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Smoking is a major cause of death and disease in New Zealand.  Nicotine replacement therapy (NRT) is a key aid to stopping smoking, and can be achieved with patches, gum, inhaler, or tablets. In New Zealand only the patch and gum are subsidised. New ways are urgently needed to get more people to use effective NRT to help them quit. The SONIQ trial will investigate whether smokers who have more choice over which NRT delivery methods they use are more likely to have quit smoking at six months, than smokers with current practice (with NRT available only by patch and/or gum). Smokers in the treatment group will try out the four different forms of NRT for a week, before choosing one or two to use for eight weeks.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Walker N, Howe C, Bullen C, Grigg M, Glover M, McRobbie H, Laugesen M, Jiang J, Chen MH, Whittaker R, Rodgers A. Does improved access and greater choice of nicotine replacement therapy affect smoking cessation success? Findings from a randomised controlled trial. Addiction 2011;106(6):1176-85. doi: 10.1111/j.1360-0443.2011.03419.x.
Walker N, Bullen C, Chen X, Glover M, Grigg M, Howe C, Lin L, McRobbie H. Validation of quit status using NicAlerttm test strips distributed by post: findings from two community-based cessation trials [poster]. Society for Research on Nicotine and Tobacco (SRNT) conference, Dublin, Ireland, 27  30 April 2009
Walker N, Howe C, Grigg M, Bullen C, Glover M, Vander Hoorn S, McRobbie H, Laugesen M, Whittaker R, Rodgers A.  What impact is there on quit rates if smokers are allowed to choose their own NRT: Findings from the SONIQ trial [poster].  16th Annual Society for Research on Nicotine and Tobacco (SRNT) conference, Baltimore USA, 24  27 February 201</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Natalie Walker</name>
      <address>Clinical Trials Research Unit,
School of Population Health
University of Auckland, 
Private Bag 92019,
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>64 3 383 5853</phone>
      <fax>64 3 383 5853</fax>
      <email>n.walker@ctru.auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Colin Howe</name>
      <address>Clinical Trials Research Unit,
School of Population Health
University of Auckland, 
Private Bag 92019,
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>64 9 373 7599 ext. 84765</phone>
      <fax>64 9 373 1710</fax>
      <email>c.howe@ctru.auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>regtrials@ctru.auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>