<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370515">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/04/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000944437</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pilot study investigating how Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation (ECMO) affects the major breathing muscles.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation and Development Of Diaphragm Atrophy.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1181-8511</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Diaphragm atrophy</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>ECMO</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Ultrasound of diaphragm, to identify onset and rate of diaphragm atrophy in ECMO patients. Initial ultrasound measurements will be taken as soon as possible after initiation of ECMO therapy. Repeat ultrasound measurements will be taken every 48 hours until cessation of ECMO therapy. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diaphragm thickness as measured by diagnostic ultrasound</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured on cannulation of ECMO, and then every 48 hours until decannulation of ECMO.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mechanical ventilation time. Mechanical ventilation time is assesed by extracting data from MetaVision. The Prince Charles Hospital electronic medical record  system in the ICU which is linked to both the mechanical ventilator and ECMO circuits
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patients total mechanical ventilation time</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of mechanical ventilation weaning process. Mechanical ventilation time is assesed by extracting data from MetaVision. The Prince Charles Hospital electronic medical record  system in the ICU which is linked to both the mechanical ventilator and ECMO circuits
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patients total mechanical ventilation weaning process time</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Re-intubation rate. Reintubation rate will be assesed by extracting data from MetaVision. The Prince Charles Hospital electronic medical record  system in the ICU which is linked to both the mechanical ventilator and ECMO circuits
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Number of times patient re-intubated post extubation. This will be assessed via  extracting data from MetaVision. The Prince Charles Hospital electronic medical record  system in the ICU. This will be from the first attempt at a patients exubation to successful discharge from the ICU in that episode of care. It will not seperate ICU admissions for that patient.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All patients &gt; 18 years old receiving ECMO therapy at The Prince Charles Hospital
Written informed consent by patient or legally authorised person.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients for whom consent was unable to be obtained
Male or female &lt; 18 years old
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>This is a within subject design and repeated measures ANOVA will be used for statistical analysis.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Convenience sample</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/08/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Prince Charles Hospital - Chermside</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Trent Donnelly</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Physiotherapy Department, The Prince Charles Hospital
Rode Road
Chermside, 4032
QLD</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Extracorporeal Life Support Organisation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>2800 Plymouth Rd
Building 300, Room 303
Ann Arbor, MI  48109-2800</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The diaphragm; the major breathing muscle, as a result of life supporting mechanical ventilation reduces in size, thickness and function (Umbrello, 2016). Diaphragm atrophy and dysfunction as a result of mechanical ventilation can lead to critically ill patients having a higher intensive care unit (ICU) mortality rate, increased ICU length of stay (LOS), increased mechanical ventilation duration and a higher rate of
re-intubation (Demoule et al, 2013;). There is currently no body of evidence regarding the onset or extent of diaphragm atrophy in patients who receive Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation (ECMO) therapy; a patient cohort predisposed to atrophy and dysfunction of the diaphragm due to very low lung volumes delivered by the breathing machine, deep sedation and immobility.
By using diagnostic ultrasound (US) in this study, we can accurately assess diaphragm thickness and determine the onset and rate of diaphragm atrophy in the ECMO cohort
Aims: 

This pilot study aims to investigate if diaphragm atrophy occurs and the rate of
diaphragm atrophy incurred whilst a patient is receiving ECMO therapy. The research
questions are:

1. Does ECMO therapy lead to diaphragm atrophy as measured by diaphragm thickness
on ultrasound?
2. What is the rate of diaphragm atrophy for patients receiving ECMO therapy?
3. Is there a difference in the rate of diaphragm atrophy between patients on VV versus
patients on VA ECMO?
Design:
As this is a pilot study, we will recruit all patients that receive ECMO therapy after consent is obtained from the patients next of kin. Ultrasound data and other measurements will be collected at the onset of ECMO insertion and every second day until ECMO decannulation to identify the onset and rate of diaphragm atrophy.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Prince Charles Hospital, Metro North Hospital and Health Service Human Research and Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/05/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/04/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Trent Donnelly</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
The Prince Charles Hospital, Rode Rd
Chermside, 4032
QLD</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3139 4443 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>trent.donnelly@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Trent Donnelly</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
The Prince Charles Hospital, Rode Rd
Chermside, 4032
QLD</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3139 4443 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>trent.donnelly@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Trent Donnelly</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
The Prince Charles Hospital, Rode Rd
Chermside, 4032
QLD</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3139 4443 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>trent.donnelly@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Trent Donnelly</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
The Prince Charles Hospital
Chermside, 4032
QLD</address>
      <phone>31394443</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>trent.donnelly@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>