<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369368">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/09/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/11/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001305516</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>High Flow Nasal Cannula Treatment for Infants and Children with Acute Respiratory Failure</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Feasibility of High Flow Nasal Cannula Treatment and standard practice for Infants and Children with Acute Respiratory Failure</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>PARIS 2 - pilot trial</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute Respiratory Failure</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>High Flow Nasal Cannula Oxygen Delivery at a rate of 2L/kg/min for the duration of oxygen requirement. Initially FiO2 is set at 0.21 and SpO2 observed for 10 minutes. If SpO2 remains less than 94% after 10 minutes then FiO2 is increased and titrated to achieve SpO2 greater than or equal to 94%. If patient presents with SpO2 less than 85% then FiO2 is immediately increased to achieve SpO2 equal to or greater than 94%. FiO2 is adjusted to achieve and maintain SpO2 of 94-98% avoiding long periods of hyperoxia with SpO2 of 100%. For any flow rates greater than 25 L/min the flow rates are increased gradually over two minutes and observe how the flow rates are tolerated. These alterations are made by the treating physician or nurse in attendance and recorded on the patients respiratory observation chart.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard subnasal 100% O2 is offered at a rate of 0-2 L/min for infants up to 2 years of age or 0-4 L/min for children 2years  up to 16 years of age, or via a face mask with a maximum of 8L/min and O2 flow rate titrated to achieve SpO2 of 94-98%. The study design is only prescriptive for the oxygen delivery method. For the remaining respiratory management the individual hospital internal protocols will be followed, including pharmacological management.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the feasibility of High Flow Nasal Cannula therapy in comparison to standard oxygen delivery through statical analysis of treatment data completed</outcome>
      <timepoint>At end of study, once all participants have finished treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the proportion of study participants who were admitted to intensive care at any point during their stay in hospital by review of medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At end of study, once all participants have finished treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the proportion of patients requiring escalation of therapy such as non-invasive or invasive ventilation through review of hospital medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>During hospital admission</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To measure the side effects of High Flow Nasal Cannula therapy compared with standard oxygen therapy.
Treatment failure of either control standard oxygen therapy or HFNC therapy arm is defined if three of the four following criteria are met and an escalation of treatment or level of care is required
1. Heart rate remains unchanged or increased compared to admission/enrolment observations assessed through ECG.
2. Respiratory rate remains unchanged or increased compared to admission/enrolment observations assessed through ECG.
3. To maintain SpO2 94-98%, oxygen requirement in HFNC therapy arm exceeds FiO2 equal to or greater than 50% or oxygen requirement in control arm exceeds the following measured with oximetry.  Standard subnasal oxygen &gt; 2L/min in the 0-2 years of age group   </outcome>
      <timepoint>Continual monitoring for side effects or adverse events will occur through out trial until child is discharge from hospital. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the health care costs between HFNC therapy compared with standard oxygen therapy through review of medical records and current industry cost.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During study period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Infants and children aged 0-16 years with the clinical diagnosis of lower respiratory tract infection and an oxygen requirement in room air (SpO2 &lt;94%)
Included are infants with reactive airway disease &gt;12 months and an oxygen requirement in room air (SpO2 &lt;94%). This includes infants &gt;12 months with the diagnosis of bronchiolitis
Informed consent from parents or guardians
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>16</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Upper airway obstruction
Craniofacial malformations
Critically ill infants requiring immediate higher level of respiratory support i.e. NIV or invasive ventilation, low level of consciousness.
Basal skull fracture
Cyanotic Heart Disease
Home Oxygen therapy
Apnoeas</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Children and infants with respiratory failure in either the emergency department or ward will be screened.
Subjects that meet inclusion and exclusion criteria will be randomised by sealed envelope allocation. </concealment>
    <sequence>Subjects that meet inclusion and exclusion criteria will be randomly assigned 1:1 ratio to either high flow nasal cannula therapy or standard care. Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software will be used (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Descriptive statistics will be utilised to report on the baseline characteristics of the total study cohort, as well as by site.  The primary outcome measure investigating clinical treatment failure will be analysed using test of two proportions, and will be reported as the difference, 95% confidence interval and p-value.  The primary outcome measure investigating length of stay will likely be non-normally distributed, and as such will be analysed using Mann-Whitney U test; if it is normally distributed independent samples t-test will be used.  Analysis of secondary outcomes includes both comparisons of measurements and proportions, using confidence intervals of differences as the major method of presentation where possible, otherwise techniques as described previously.  All analyses will be by intention-to-treat. Statistical significance will be set at the 0.05 level.

Both parametric and non-parametric bootstrapping techniques will be employed to compare mean difference in the costs between groups, and to estimate a confidence interval around the mean. It is anticipated that HFNC therapy will be cost saving to the health system.]
There is currently no data on intubation rates and admission rates to intensive care for infants and children requiring HFNC therapy for acute respiratory failure. In the State of Queensland Australia with a population of 4.7 million there were between July 2010 and July 2015 1850 infants and children with respiratory failure other than bronchiolitis treated with non-invasive ventilation (336 patients per year) with an average age of 4.02 +/- 4.6 years. This figure approximately represents 10-15 % of these patients admitted to an emergency department and then requiring transfer to PICU for respiratory support.
Approximately 25% of admissions to paediatric intensive care are due to respiratory conditions and approximately 50% of infants and children admitted to a general intensive care unit (ANZPIC Annual Report 2013). For the Lady Cilento Childrens Hospital, Brisbane, Queensland with an anticipated overall PICU admission rate of 2200 patients/annum, this translates to 550 admissions. Approximately half of these admissions are attributed to bronchiolitis &lt;12 months of age. Hence approximately 250-270 admissions per annum have the above inclusion criteria when presenting to the emergency department of the Lady Cilento Childrens Hospital, which is consistent with the above-mentioned patient numbers. For a 50% reduction (using a power of 80%) from 15% to 7.5% an anticipated sample size of 280 patients will be needed per arm. We will cover the summer and winter season 2015-2016 with recruitment of patients and anticipate enrolling 200-300 patients into the pilot study and test in this convenient sample the feasibility and the suspected reduction in admissions to PICU in view to expand the trail to a fully powered RCT including multiple regional and tertiary centres.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>20/06/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/07/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>19/06/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>450</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>19/06/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Lady Cilento Children's Hospital - South Brisbane</hospital>
    <postcode>4101 - South Brisbane</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Lady Cilento Children's Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>501 Stanly St
South Brisbane 
Queensland 4101</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Paediatric Critical Care Research Group </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Paediatric Critical Care Research Group
Level 7, Centre for Childrens Health Research
Lady Cilento Children's Hospital Precinct
62 Graham Street, South Brisbane QLD 4101</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to develop a multi-centre trial and to assess which infants and children with acute respiratory failure benefit using High Flow Nasal Cannula Therapy (HFNC). For this purpose we will perform a randomised controlled trial comparing current best practice
(standard oxygen delivery via subnasal prongs, facemask, venturi mask) versus HFNC therapy. With the introduction of this simple to use respiratory system in regional and tertiary centres we aim to investigate if HFNC therapy has a lower treatment failure rate in comparison to standard oxygen delivery, and to investigate if there is a reduction in the need for transfer of these patients to a tertiary hospital or admit to an intensive care unit.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Children's Health Service Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Childrens Health Queensland Human Research Ethics Committee
Level 7, Centre for Childrens Health Research
Lady Cilento Children's Hospital Precinct
62 Graham Street, South Brisbane QLD 4101</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/09/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/QRCH/159</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Andreas Schibler</name>
      <address>Lady Cilento Children's Hospital 
501 Stanley St 
South Brisbane Qld 4101 </address>
      <phone>+617 3068 5733</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.schibler@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Andreas Schibler</name>
      <address>Lady Cilento Children's Hospital 
501 Stanley St 
South Brisbane Qld 4101 </address>
      <phone>+617 3068 5733</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.schibler@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Andreas Schibler</name>
      <address>Lady Cilento Children's Hospital 
501 Stanley St 
South Brisbane Qld 4101 </address>
      <phone>+617 3068 5733</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.schibler@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Andreas Schibler</name>
      <address>Lady Cilento Children's Hospital 
501 Stanley St 
South Brisbane Qld 4101 </address>
      <phone>+617 3068 5733</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.schibler@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>