<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82701">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/06/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/08/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000426381</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparison of Alemtuzumab and Rebif (registered trademark) Efficacy in Multiple Sclerosis, Study Two</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 3 Randomized, Rater- and Dose-Blinded Study Comparing Two Annual Cycles of Intravenous Low- and High-Dose Alemtuzumab to Three-Times Weekly Subcutaneous Interferon Beta-1a (Rebif (Registered trademark)) on Relapse Rate and Time to Sustained Accumulation of Disability in Patients with Relapsing-Remitting Multiple Sclerosis Who Have Relapsed on Therapy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>CARE-MS II</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>ClinicalTrials.gov NCT00548405</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Multiple Sclerosis, Relapsing-Remitting</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Multiple sclerosis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>alemtuzumab: 12 mg per day administered through intravenous therapy (IV), once a day for 5 consecutive days at Month 0 and 12 mg per day administered through IV, once a day for 3 consecutive days at Month 12
alemtuzumab: 24 mg per day administered through IV, once a day for 5 consecutive days at Month 0 and 24 mg per day administered through IV, once a day for 3 consecutive days at Month 12 (Note: The 24 mg alemtuzumab dose is closed to enrollment.)</interventions>
    <comparator>Interferon beta-1a (Rebif (registered trademark)): 44 micrograms (mcg) administered 3-times weekly by subcutaneous (SC) injections for 2 years</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Sustained Accumulation of Disability (SAD) based on increases in scores on the Expanded Disability Status Scale (EDSS) lasting at least 6 months</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored at baseline and quarterly thereafter for 2 years.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relapse Rate based on patient report with physician confirmation of objective neurologic changes</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored continuously for 2 years.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients who are relapse free at Year 2</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 Years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in EDSS</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored at baseline and quarterly thereafter for 2 years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acquisition of disability as measured by change from baseline in Multiple Sclerosis Functional Composite (MSFC)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored at baseline and quarterly thereafter for 2 years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percent change from baseline in magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) T2-weighted hyperintense lesion volume at Year 2</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored at baseline and annually thereafter for 2 years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety, based on adverse event reporting and laboratory testing.  These are safety provisions outlined in the protocol and not secondary outcomes</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored continuously, including monthly blood tests.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Diagnosis of MS (Multiple Sclerosis) and MRI scan demonstrating white matter lesions attributable to MS 
2. Onset of MS symptoms within 10 years 
3. EDSS score 0.0 to 5.0 
4. Greater than or equal to 2 MS attacks within 24 months, with greater than or equal to 1 attack within 12 months
5. Greater than or equal to 1 MS attack (relapse) during treatment with a interferon beta therapy or glatiramer acetate after having been on that therapy for at least 6 months within 10 years</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Previous treatment with alemtuzumab 
2. Previous treatment with any investigational drug (i.e. medication that is not approved at any dose for any indication)
3. Treatment with natalizumab, methotrexate, azothioprine or cyclosporine in the past 6 months
4. Previous treatment with mitoxantrone, cyclophosphamide, cladribine, rituximab, or any other immunosuppressive, or cytotoxic therapy (other than steroid treatment)
5. Any progressive form of MS 
6. Any disability acquired from trauma or another illness that could interfere with evaluation of disability due to MS 
7. Major systemic disease that cannot be treated or adequately controlled by therapy 
8. Active infection or high risk for infection
9. Autoimmune disorder (other than MS) 
10. Impaired hepatic or renal function 
11. History of malignancy, except basal skin cell carcinoma 
12. Medical, psychiatric, cognitive, or other conditions that compromise the patient's ability to understand the patient information, to give informed consent, to comply with the trial protocol, or to complete the study
13. Known bleeding disorder 
14. Of childbearing potential with a positive serum pregnancy test, pregnant, or lactating 
15. Current participation in another clinical study or previous participation in CAMMS323 
16. Previous hypersensitivity reaction to anyimmunoglobulin product 
17. Known allergy or intolerance to interferon beta, human albumin, or mannitol 
18. Intolerance of pulsed corticosteroids, especially a history of steroid psychosis 
19. Inability to self-administer subcutaneous (SC) injections or receive SC injections from caregiver 
20. Inability to undergo MRI with gadolinium administration 
21. Unwilling to use a reliable and acceptable contraceptive method throughout the study period (fertile patients only)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/10/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>700</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>4215</postcode>
    <postcode>5011</postcode>
    <postcode>4066</postcode>
    <postcode>3050</postcode>
    <postcode>3084</postcode>
    <postcode>3065</postcode>
    <postcode>2145</postcode>
    <postcode>2139</postcode>
    <postcode>7000</postcode>
    <postcode>2217</postcode>
    <postcode>2170</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Argentina</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czech Republic</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Denmark</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mexico</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Serbia and Montenegro</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ukraine</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Croatia</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Genzyme Corporation</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>500 Kendall Street Cambridge, Massachusetts 02142</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Genzyme Corporation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>500 Kendall Street Cambridge, Massachusetts 02142</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Bayer Schering Pharma AG</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>13342 Berlin</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Germany</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to establish the efficacy and safety of two different doses of alemtuzumab as a treatment for relapsing-remitting multiple sclerosis (MS), in comparison with Rebif (Registered trademark for interferon beta-1a). The study will enroll patients who have received an adequate trial of disease-modifying therapies but continued to relapse while being treated, and who meet a minimum severity of disease as measured by MRI. Patients will have monthly laboratory tests and comprehensive testing every 3 months. 
Every patient will receive active treatment; there is no placebo. The 24 mg alemtuzumab dose is closed to enrollment so newly enrolled patients will be randomly assigned to treatment with either 12 mg alemtuzumab or Rebif (registered trademark)  at a 2:1 ratio (ie, 2 given 12 mg alemtuzumab for every 1 given Rebif (registered trademark)).  Patients will not be able to guess which treatment will be randomly assigned to them. Alemtuzumab will be administered in two annual cycles, once at the beginning of the study and again 1 year later. Rebif (registered trademark) will be self-injected 3 times per week for 2 years. All patients will be required to return to their study site every 3 months for neurologic assessment. In addition, safety-related laboratory tests will be performed at least monthly. Participation in this study will end 2 years after the start of treatment for each patient. Additionally, all patients who receive alemtuzumab will be followed in an extension study for safety and efficacy assessments. Patients who receive Rebif (registered trademark) and complete 2 years on study may be eligible to receive alemtuzumab in an extension study.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>1) Coles AJ, Cox A, Le Page E, et al. The window of therapeutic opportunity in multiple sclerosis: evidence from monoclonal antibody therapy. J Neurol. 2006;253(1);98-108. 
2) Fox E, Sullivan H, Gazda S. Open label, single-arm, Phase II study of alemtuzumab in patients with active relapsing-remitting multiple sclerosis who have failed licensed beta-interferon therapies. Poster presentation P06.07 at the 59th Annual Meeting of the American Academy of Neurology (AAN) on 03 May 2007. 
3) CAMMS223 Trial Investigators, Coles AJ, Compston DA, Selmaj KW, Lake SL, Moran S, Margolin DH, Norris K, Tandon PK.  Alemtuzumab vs. interferon beta-1a in early multiple sclerosis. N Engl J Med. 2008 Oct 23;359(17):1786-801</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Gold Coast Health Services District Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>108 Nerang Street
Southport, QLD 4215</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/10/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>30/10/2007</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Genzyme Medical Information</name>
      <address>Level 1, Building C,12-24 Talavera Road
North Ryde NSW 2113
Mailing Address: PO Box 282, North Ryde B/C NSW 1670</address>
      <phone>1800 359 131</phone>
      <fax>1800 232 565</fax>
      <email>medinfo_ANZ@genzyme.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Genzyme Medical Information</name>
      <address>Level 1, Building C,12-24 Talavera Road
North Ryde NSW 2113
Mailing Address: PO Box 282, North Ryde B/C NSW 1670</address>
      <phone>1800 359 131</phone>
      <fax>1800 232 565</fax>
      <email>medinfo_ANZ@genzyme.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>