<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362042">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/02/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/02/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000156886</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial to evaluate paediatric critical care telemedicine in Queensland</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>For children who have a remote intensive care consultation does telemedicine compared with standard telephone consultation improve clinical outcomes and provide economic savings to the health service?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1127-8931</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Remote consultation for critically ill children</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Arm 1: consultation by telemedicine (intervention)

When a consultation for a sick child is required between a clinciian at a referring hospital and a specialist at the tertiary hospital, it will be conducted using real-time video (a form of telemedicine). Telemedicine will allow audio-video interaction between clinicians at a distance. It will also allow the specialist to view the patient, medical images and medical equipment (e.g. the patient monitor, ventilator etc) in real time. Duration of consultations will vary according to clinical circumstance.</interventions>
    <comparator>Consultation by telephone (usual care)

When a consultation for a sick child is required between a clinician at a referring hospital and a specialist at the tertiary hospital, it will be conducted by telephone (usual care). Visual information will be unavailable. Duration of consultations will vary according to clinical circumstance.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient's physiological status (repeated measure, two time points), scored using CEWT (Children's Emergency Warning Tool).</outcome>
      <timepoint>1. Time of initial call from the referring hospital to the tertiary paediatric intensive care unit.
2. Time of arrival of the retrieval team at referring hospital.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stabilisation time (time spent on site at the referring hospital by the retrieval team, adjusted for initial risk using PIM2).</outcome>
      <timepoint>1. Recorded at time of departure of the retrieval team to the tertiary hospital.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in diagnosis (repeated measure taked at three timepoints).</outcome>
      <timepoint>1. Time of initial call to tertiary hospital.
2. Time of arrival of retrieval team at the referring hospital.
3. Time of arrival of the retrieved patient at the tertiary hospital.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in destination of retrieved patients at the tertiary hospital (e.g. general ward vs. PICU).</outcome>
      <timepoint>1. Time of arrival of the retrieved patient at the tertiary hospital.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Whether telemedicine provided new clinically significant information.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post hoc independent expert review of audio/video recording of consultation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Whether telemedicine led to a change in intervention (carried out or avoided).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post hoc independent expert review of audio/video recording of consultation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Whether telemedicine allowed avoidance of retrieval.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post hoc independent expert review of audio/video recording of consultation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>From the health services perspective, whether telemecicine provides economic benefits.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post hoc economic evaluation of the cost of providing telemedicine versus the savings associated with avoided retreival and tertiary admission.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>30 day mortality</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days post admission to tertiary hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All children at the study sites for whom advice is need from the tertiary PICU and for whom parental consent can be obtained.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>15</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Nil</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Initial contact between the referring hospital physician and the tertiary PICU will always be made by telephone. 

On receiving that call, the on-call PICU staff will select a sealed envelope from a box (one box per participating site) which will determine whether the consultation continues by telephone (i.e. usual care, control), or by telemedicine (the intervention).

Informed consent will be gained by attending staff at the referring hospital. A patient information sheet and a consent form will be provided for this purpose.</concealment>
    <sequence>A table of random numbers will be generated using a computer random number geenration program. Odd numbers will denote allocation to the control group and even numbers to the intervention. Allocation to either group, based on the random number table will be printed on a piece of paper and sealed in sequentially numbered opaque envelopes. Five sets of envelopes will be produced, one for each study site. These will be placed in five tamper-proof boxes to be held at the tertiary PICU. Each box will be clearly labelled with the name of the remote study site. This process of generating the sequence, envelopes and boxes will be conducted by an independent party).</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/03/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Centre for Online Health
Level 3, Foundation Building
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston Road
Herston 4029
Queensland</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Queensland Children's Medical Research Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Royal Children's Hospital
Herston Road
Herston 4029
Queensland</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Royal Children's Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Paediatric Intensive Care Unit
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston Road
Herston 4029
Queensland</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In Queensland, facilities for seriously ill children are centralised in Brisbane. The Paediatric Intensive Care Unit (PICU) at the Royal Children's Hospital provides advice and retrieval services for children who have presented at rural and regional hospitals throughout Queensland. When advice is needed, it is provided by telephone and this relies on the ability of the remote clinician to provide a good verbal description of the patient and an accurate interpretation of paediatric x-rays. Clinicians at the remote hospital may be relatively inexperienced at caring for critically ill children. Support from the PICU is essential.

Telemedicine allows clinicians to hold a consultation at a distance by video. In addition to face-to-face communication, telemedicine may be used to view the patient, the monitors and x-rays - as if present in the same room. The addition of visual information offers the potential for a much richer dialogue than is possible by telephone alone. Alongside high-quality local care and a well co-ordinated retrieval service, telemedicine may be a potentially useful tool.

This is a new area of research and very little has been reported in the literature. A limited number of studies in the USA have shown that telemedicine assists in the management of seriously ill children at a distance.

Over a three year period, this study will formally evaluate the use of telemedicine to provide critical care support from the RCH PICU to four regional hospital emergency departments. The study will provide evidence on the feasibility, clinical usefulness and economics of the approach within the Queensland context.

The following hypotheses will be tested:

Efficacy

Paediatric critical care consultation by telemedicine will:

(i) improve patient condition between initial call and retrieval team arrival;
(ii) reduce the time needed by the retrieval team to stablise the patient before transport;
(iii) reduce diagnostic discordance;
(iv) reduce the number of retrieved patients admitted to general wards;
(v) improve 30 day mortality.

Economics 

Paediatric critical care telemedicine is economically beneficial from the health service perspective reducing the number and therefore cost of retrieval and unnecessary tertiary admission.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Queensland Children's Health Service Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/01/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/11/QRCH/175</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>21/11/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Nigel R. Armfield</name>
      <address>Centre for Online Health
Level 3, Foundation Building
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston 4029
Queenland</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3346 4754</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>N.R.Armfield@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Nigel R. Armfield</name>
      <address>Centre for Online Health
Level 3, Foundation Building
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston 4029
Queenland</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3346 4754</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>N.R.Armfield@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>