<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83156">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/09/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/10/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000526370</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Sleep electroencephalogram (EEG) recordings in interferon-alpha treated hepatitis C patients  Pilot Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A study to evaluate the effects of Interferon-alpha treatment on sleep electroencephalogram (EEG) changes in hepatitis C patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NHS (United Hospitals Bristol) sponsorship and research and development number: ME/2008/2829</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Mood side effects of interferon alpha treatment</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Mood effects of interferon treatment of hepatitis C patients</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Mood and brain serotonin functioning changes with interferon treatment in hepatitis C patients. 
1) Mood changes will be assessed by: a computerised psychiatric diagnostic programme will also be administered; the CIS-R (Lewis et al., 1992) is a computerised interview schedule that establishes the nature and severity of neurotic symptoms experienced over the previous 7 days and identifies the presence of neurosis. Additional rating scales will be taken. Mood: Beck Depression Inventory (BDI). Anxiety: Spielberger state anxiety inventory (SSAI) and Panic State Inventory (PSI). Irritability: Spielberger state anger expression inventory (STAXI) and Visual Analogue Scales (VAS-each category is measured on 100mm line, anchored from 0: not at all to 100: the most ever). Sleep: Bristol Sleep Profile, short clinical interview to elicit any sleep disorder.
Brain serotonin functioning will be measured by changes in sleep electroencephalogram architecture: priamary measures are reduced rapid eye movement latency and increased sleep fragmentation. Secondary measures will be: increased rapid eye movement percentage of sleep, reduced stage 2 sleep
2) The study duration will be approximately 7 weeks; one week prior to staring interferon and after six weeks of interferon treatment.Each assessment lasts for approximately 1.5-2hours for the questionnaires and computer programing. The sleep EEG recording runs overnight (approximately 8 hours) for each assessment session.  In addition psychiatric diagnosis will be collected for all patients the treating team feel may be suffering from a psychiatric illness for the duration of their interferon treatment (usually six or twelve months).</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sleep EEG changes: Rapid Eye Movement latency and sleep fragmentation</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 6 weeks.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mood changes: Depression, Becks Depression Inventory, visual analogue scales.</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and 6 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mood changes: anxiety, speilberger state/trait anxiety inventory, panic state inventory, visual analogue scales</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baesline and 6 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mood changes: irritability, spielberger state/trait anger expression inventory, visual analogue scales.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and six weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychiatric diagnosis: revised clinical interview schedule (CIS-R), also clinical diagnosis by a study psychiatrist</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and week 6. Any timepoint for duration of interferon treatment (the duration of interferon treatment is decided by the treating team independant from the study. It is usually either 6 months or 12 months duration depending upon the genotype of hepatitis C and the early response, measured by plasma viral load, to treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Hepatitis C, receiving interferon alpha treatment.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Current mental illness or drug/alcohol abuse at baseline. History of schizophrenia or bipolar affective disorder. Current unstable medical illness. Taking medicine that affect sleep EEG measures (antidepressants). Current occupational history of nightshift working</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Convenience sample</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>15</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Bristol</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>United Hospitals Bristol</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Research and Effectiveness Department
    Education Centre
    Level 3
    Upper Maudlin Street
    Bristol BS2 8AE</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United Kingdom</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>David Telling Charitable trust</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>2nd Floor, Dolphin House
Bristol Royal Infirmary
Bristol BS2 8HW</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United Kingdom</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Schering-Plough</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Shire Park
Welwyn Garden City
Hertfordshire
AL7 1TW</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United Kingdom</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of Bristol</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Psychopharmacology Unit, 
Level 5, Dorothy Hodgkin Building, 
Whitson Street, 
Bristol
BS1 3NY</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>United Kingdom</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Hepatitis C is a condition that is often treated successfully with interferon. However, interferon treatment can sometimes cause mood problems, including depression. One possible reason for this is that interferon may affect a chemical called serotonin in the brain, which governs mood and sleep. No-one has studied  changes in the brains serotonin system during interferon treatment. Discovering how interferon causes depression will help us to provide more effective treatment, or prevention, of this for future patients undergoing interferon treatment. It may also help us discover what is happening to the brain in other forms of depression.

The purpose of this study is to measure the brain activity during sleep, before and during interferon treatment. This will give us a measure of how the brains serotonin system changes during interferon treatment and whether this can be linked to the development of depression. 
Hypothesis: there will be a shorter period until REM (dreaming sleep) and greater sleep fragmentation (more broken sleep) when patient are taking interferon compared to before treatment. Secondary hypothesis: the degree of sleep change will correlate with worsening scores upon mood, anxiety and irritability scales. Further hypothesis: the degree of sleep change may predict later episodes of depression further on in treatment</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bath Local Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Room 11, John Apley Building
Research Ethics Office
Royal United Hospital
Combe Park
Bath
BA1 3NG</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/06/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>08/H0101/76</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>United Kingdom</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>David Christmas</name>
      <address>Psychopharmacology Unit, 
Level 5, 
Dorothy Hodgkin Building, 
Whitson Street, 
Bristol, 
BS1 3NY
UK</address>
      <phone>+44-(0)117-3313178</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>david.christmas@bristol.ac.uk</email>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>David Christmas</name>
      <address>Psychopharmacology Unit, 
Level 5, 
Dorothy Hodgkin Building, 
Whitson Street, 
Bristol, 
BS1 3NY
UK</address>
      <phone>+44-(0)117-3313178</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>david.christmas@bristol.ac.uk</email>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>David Christmas</name>
      <address>Psychopharmacology Unit, 
Level 5, 
Dorothy Hodgkin Building, 
Whitson Street, 
Bristol, 
BS1 3NY
UK</address>
      <phone>+44-(0)117-3313178</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>david.christmas@bristol.ac.uk</email>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>