<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365491">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/06/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/06/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000641695</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An interventional study on physicians adherence to hypertension guidelines </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of a complex intervention involving primary care doctors on blood pressure control in patients with hypertension</scientifictitle>
    <utrn> U1111-1150-8720</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Implementing, Innovation, In-Practice Study (IIIP) Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hypertension</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Hypertension</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a before-and-after study using clinical support tools and health care professional training. Assessments are done at 0-3 months post intervention for immediate effect of intervention and 3-6 months post interventions for sustainability of intervention. 

The intervention package consists of :

1. A training session conducted by senior academicians to modify the primary care physicians' practice according to guidelines recommendations pre intervention

2. A quick reference guide summarising recommendations from the guideline to put on desktops as well as online on computers of each consultation room for easy access and reference for doctors throughout the study duration

3. At patient's first visit: 
(i) Patients have to fill self assessment forms prior to consultation with doctor
(ii) Patients' anthropometric parameters (weight, height and waist circumference) are measured by nurses
(iii) A personalized checklist for the doctors is placed in the patient's medical record to be utilized as a quick reference and reminder to the doctor on the essential parameters that are required for evaluation. The checklist includes documentation of cardiovascular risk factors and comorbidities, secondary causes, investigations ordered, target organ damage, patient's estimated cardiovascular risk, medications, BP measurement and physcical examination findings.
(iv) Sets of investigations forms are placed in the medical records as reminder for doctors and for ease of administration

4. At patients' follow up visits at 3 to 6 months, a checklist is placed in the medical records that includes documentation of weight, blood pressure, investigations ordered, medications, presence of target organ damage and complications.   </interventions>
    <comparator>none</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome is the proportion of patients with controlled blood pressure. Controlled blood pressure is defined as blood pressure less than 140/90mmHg and measured using mercury sphygmomanometer by the doctors.  
</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 to 3 months post intervention for immediate effect of intervention, 3 to 6 months post intervention for sustainability of intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The rates of documentation of process indicators and outcome indicators from the checklist provided in the medical records: these include the rate of documentation of process indicators (BP, weight measurement, assessment of cardiovascular risk factors, target organ damage and comorbidities, examinations, investigatory tests ordered) and the rate of documentation of outcome indicators (medication use) </outcome>
      <timepoint>0 to 3 months post intervention for immediate effect of intervention, 3 to 6 months post intervention for sustainability of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All primary care physician working at the Primary Care Clinic at the University Malaya Medical Centre (UMMC) who are treating the cohort of patients with hypertension from earlier phase of this study (patient with hypertension for at least a year and have been followed up at the Primary Care Clinic). 

Earlier phase of the study is a retrospective review of records and it is not registered as it is not an intervention trial. We have published a paper from earlier phase of the study :

Liew et al.: Statins use is associated with poorer
glycaemic control in a cohort of hypertensive patients with diabetes and without diabetes. Diabetology &amp; Metabolic Syndrome 2014 6:53. doi:10.1186/1758-5996-6-53</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>All primary care physician working at the Primary Care Clinic at the University Malaya Medical Centre (UMMC) who are not treating the cohort of patients with hypertension from earlier phase of the study  </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All primary care physician working at the Primary Care Clinic at the University Malaya Medical Centre (UMMC) who are treating the cohort of patients with hypertension from earlier phase of the study are approached to participate the study and informed consent obtained. In addition, all patients with hypertension for at least 1 year and has been followed up in this clinic and are in the earlier phase of the study cohort who attended the clinic during the study period are approached to participate in the study. A patient information sheet would be given and  consent sought.
 
</concealment>
    <sequence>Non randomized. All doctors who fulfill the criteria are included</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>sample size calculation:
We estimate the change of proportion of patients from uncontrolled blood pressure to controlled blood pressure is 10% while the change of proportion of patients from controlled blood pressure to uncontrolled blood pressure is 5%; for a power of 0.8 and significance level set at 0.05, a sample size of 469 is needed. To account for an estimate of 20% drop out, 570 are recruited.  

For analysis of study data, chi square tests, paired t test, repeated measures of ANOVA tests will be used.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/10/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>7/10/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>15/05/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>15/05/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>570</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <state>Kuala Lumpur</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Malaya</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Malaya, Jalan Lembah Pantai, 50603, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Malaysia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University Malaya Research Grant (UMRG) 315- 11 HTM, Institute of Research Management and Monitoring (IPPP), University of Malaya, Malaysia
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of Malaya, Jalan Lembah Pantai, 50603, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Malaysia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University Malaya Research Grant (UMRG) 513- 13 HTM, Institute of Research Management and Monitoring (IPPP), University of Malaya, Malaysia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of Malaya, Jalan Lembah Pantai, 50603, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Malaysia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to find out whether an intervention including training of doctors, and using forms to collect and document necessary information and assessment on high blood pressure according to guidelines from patient and doctors will improve blood pressure control. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Medical Ethics Committee, University Malaya Medical Centre (UMMC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University Malaya Medical Centre, Lembah pantai, 59100, Kuala Lumpur</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/11/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>890.14</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/10/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Malaysia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ee Ming Khoo</name>
      <address>Department of Primary Care Medicine,
Faculty of Medicine, 
University of Malaya,
Jalan Lembah Pantai 
50603, Kuala Lumpur</address>
      <phone>+603 79492306</phone>
      <fax>+603 79577941</fax>
      <email>khooem@um.edu.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ee Ming Khoo</name>
      <address>Department of Primary Care Medicine,
Faculty of Medicine, 
University of Malaya,
Jalan Lembah Pantai 
50603, Kuala Lumpur,</address>
      <phone>+603 79492306</phone>
      <fax>+603 79577941</fax>
      <email>khooem@um.edu.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ee Ming Khoo</name>
      <address>Department of Primary Care Medicine,
Faculty of Medicine, 
University of Malaya,
Jalan Lembah Pantai 
50603, Kuala Lumpur,</address>
      <phone>+603 79492306</phone>
      <fax>+603 79577941</fax>
      <email>khooem@um.edu.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ee Ming Khoo</name>
      <address>Department of Primary Care Medicine,
Faculty of Medicine, 
University of Malaya,
Jalan Lembah Pantai 
50603, Kuala Lumpur,</address>
      <phone>+603 79492306</phone>
      <fax>+603 79577941</fax>
      <email>khooem@um.edu.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>