<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83124">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/09/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/11/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000566336</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Myopia control lens efficacy trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Investigation of the efficacy of the second generation Myopia Control Progressive Addition Lenses in the retardation of juvenile onset myopic progression in 6 to 12 year old children.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>MCPAL2</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Juvenile onset myopia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal eye development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Custom designed Progressive Addition Lenses worn binocularly during normal waking hours and for all tasks where spectacles can and normally would be worn. There are two designs: a 1.00 D addition and the 1.50 D addition power, subjects are assigned to either of these designs or a single-vision lens control condition according to a pre-defined randomized sequence assigned on an incremental recruitment number. The study will compare the effectiveness of these two addition powers. The addition power reduces the accommodative demand of the wearer while doing near vision tasks (&lt; 75 cm). The lens has a progressively increasing addition power starting at the distance viewing reference point and reaching the prescribed addition at approximately 14 mm below the fitting cross. The patient's regular prescription is additionally surfaced on the back surface of these lenses to correct any ocular errors of the eye. This may include Sphere and / or Cylinder corrections. Patients wear the lenses during normal waking hours and for all tasks where spectacles can be worn for a period of 24 months.</interventions>
    <comparator>Single Vision prescription lens. These lenses are to be worn binocularly during normal waking hours and for all tasks where spectacles can and normally would be worn for a period of 24 months. They correct the wearers ocular errors of focus. This may include Sphere and or Cylinder corrections. Patients wear the lenses during normal waking hours and for all tasks where spectacles can be worn.</comparator>
    <control>Dose comparison</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Refractive error (autorefraction) using one of the following machines -

1. Shin-Nippon SRW-5000
2. Shin Nippon NVision K5001
3. Grand Seiko FR5000 open-field autorefractor</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline and 6, 12, 18 &amp; 24 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Axial length of the eye. This will be measured using a Carl Zeiss Meditec 'IOL Master' http://www.meditec.zeiss.com/iolmaster</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline and 6, 12, 18 &amp; 24 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Peripheral refractive error. An open field auto-refractor will be used, the following models are acceptable - 1. Shin-Nippon SRW-5000 2. Shin Nippon NVision K5001 3. Grand Seiko FR5000 open-field autorefractor, 4. Grand Seiko WAM5500 open field autorefractor. The peripheral autorefraction will be measured at 5, 15, 25 &amp; 35 degrees both Nasal and Temporal of the line of foveal sight. If 35 degrees is not possible due to subject eye-rotation limitations or equipment issues then 30 degrees may be substituted for 35 degrees (25 if 30 is not possible). Subjects will fixate targets while the peripheral refraction is made in order to minimize eye-movements. Either the subject can rotate the eye to targets eccentric to the primary measurement axis of the machine OR the machine may be rotated around the stationary eye (which ever technique best suits the equipment and investigators). Care should be taken when measuring eccentric positions that all instrument centration cues are located on the correct parts of the eye-image. Four readings will be taken at each eccentricity and the average Rx (produced by the instrument) will be used. Averages (if not calculated by the autorefractor) will be calculated by converting each of the 4 left and 4 right eye Sph, Cyl &amp; Axis measures according to Mean sphere (M) and J0 / J45 components, averaging the 4 decomposed M, J0 &amp; J45 components for each eye, prior to converting back to a Sph, Cyl &amp; Axis for each eye.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline and 6, 12, 18 &amp; 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Spherical equivalent refractive error (SER) of 0.50 to -4.50 D.
2. Astigmatism of not more than -1.50 D.
3. Anisometropia of not more than -1.50 D in spherical or cylindrical error. 
4. Visual acuity with best subjective correction of 0.00 LogMAR or better.
5. Normal ocular health other than myopia.
6. No prior use of bifocal or progressive lenses in the last 12 months. 
7. No rigid contact lenses or Bi-Focal contact lens experience and must be willing not to wear contact lenses.
8. In satisfactory health.
9. Willing and able to tolerate cycloplegia.
10. Informed parental consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>12</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Outside the age range 6 to 12 years at time of recruitment.
2. Not willing to wear spectacles continuously.
3. Not available for follow-up for at least 2 years.
4. Absence of parental consent to the random assignment of their child to one of three spectacle lens groups.
5. Any systemic condition which might affect refractive development or systemic diseases which may affect vision or refractive error.
6. Previous use of contact lens/PALs or other treatment for myopia within the last 12 months.
7. Defective binocular function.
8. Amblyopia and or manifested squint.
9. Vestibular disorders or motor imbalance.
10. Any other conditions precluding adherence to the Protocol.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Advertising may be used to attract subjects to the study, or alternatively patient populations presenting naturally at the study site may be used. The study will be seeking those children &amp; parents concerned about the development or continuing development of myopia. Ideally subjects with a demonstrated progressing myopic condition would be recruited.

The objectives of the recruitment session will be to determine if the child and family met the ocular criteria for participation, inform the family verbally about the study, provide a written information sheet and answer any questions raised.

The families will be told that if they participated then 'special' spectacles would be provided free-of-charge and that travel expenses for the child and one accompanying adult would be provided for future visits. Families will not be told the nature of the two treatments being offered and it will be emphasized that allocation to a treatment would be at random and could not be requested.

1. A non-cycloplegic refraction will be carried out and Visual Acuity (VA) (logMAR) measured with the lowest minus correction. A cover test will be carried out to exclude strabismus with the distance correction and with an addition of +1.50 D. Ophthalmoscopy and biomicroscopy will be carried out to identify any abnormal ocular condition present.

2. If the child meets the ocular selection criteria, the family will be informed and its consent will be obtained. Then the child will be allocated, according to a pre-determined random sequence, to either the Progressive Addition Lens (PAL), treatment group, or the Single Vision (SV) lens, control group.

The inclusion criteria are

1) Spherical equivalent refractive error (SER) of –0.50 to -4.50 D (measured under cycloplegia).
2) Astigmatism of not more than -1.50 D.
3) Anisometropia of not more than -1.50 D in spherical or cylindrical error. 
4) Have best corrected visual acuity of at least 6/9 (20/30) in each eye.
5) Normal ocular health other than myopia.
6) No prior use of bifocal or progressive lenses in the last 12 months. 
7) No RPG contact lens experience and must be willing not to wear contact lenses.
8) In satisfactory health.
9) Willing and able to tolerate cycloplegia (no previous reaction to cycloplegics).
10) Age 6 to 12 years at time of recruitment.
11) Willing to wear spectacles constantly.
12) Available for follow-up for at least 2 years.
13) Parents must understand and accept that there would be random assignment to one of three spectacle lens groups.
14) Able to obtain informed parental consent.

Allocation concealment will be used. The investigator assessing and enrolling the subjects will not know the condition to which the child will be assigned. Allocation is carried out by the central administration according to a predefined (randomized) assignment schedule applied in numerical recruitment order by the laboratory making the lenses for the trial.</concealment>
    <sequence>The Microsoft Excel randomization function is used as follows -

1. The function: ‘INT(RAND()*2.99)’ is used to generate random integers between 0 and 2.

2. This formula is copied into N cells where N is the number of subjects in the trial at the selected site.

3.The page is refreshed to change the seed of the RAND function until approximately equal numbers of 0, 1 &amp; 2 are generated in the list.

4. The results are copied and pasted as values into a new spreadsheet. This becomes the master allocation table for the three conditions in the trial.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/09/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>21/01/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>9/09/2009</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Wenzhou</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Okayama</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Carl Zeiss Vision</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>19 Cooroora Crescent Lonsdale 5160, Adelaide. SA.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Carl Zeiss Vision</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>19 Cooroora Crescent Lonsdale 5160, South Australia, Adelaide.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Okayama University Hospital of Medicine and Dentistry</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Okayama University
2-5-1 Shikata-cho, Okayama 700-8558
Japan</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Japan</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Eye Hospital of Wenzhou Medical College</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>270 Xueyuan Road 
Wenzhou 
Zhejiang 
325027 
270 Xueyuan Road 
Wenzhou 
Zhejiang 
325027 
China, People's Republic</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>China</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To determine the effectiveness of a specially designed spectacle lens in the control of myopia progression in children.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Hasebe S, Jun J, Varnas SR., Myopia control with positively aspherized progressive addition lenses: a 2-year, multicenter, randomized, controlled trial. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 2014;55:71777188.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Eulji University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>601-1 Shil Chong Gwan, 212 Yang Ji Dong
Su Jong Gu, Song Nam Shi
461-713 Gyonggi Province</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/09/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EU 08-19</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Korea, Republic Of</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Eye hospital, Wenzhou Medical College</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>270 Xueyuan Road 
Wenzhou 
Zhejiang 
325027 
270 Xueyuan Road 
Wenzhou 
Zhejiang 
325027 
China, People's Republic</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/12/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>N/A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/12/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>China</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Committee of the Okayama University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>2-5-1 Shikata-cho, Okayama 700-8558</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/11/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>622</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>8/10/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Japan</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Saulius Varnas</name>
      <address>Carl Zeiss - Business Group Vision Care,
Technology &amp; Innovation / R&amp;D,
26 Cooroora Crescent, Lonsdale, SA 5160</address>
      <phone>08 83928327</phone>
      <fax>08 83928400</fax>
      <email>saulius.varnas@zeiss.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Saulius Varnas</name>
      <address>Carl Zeiss - Business Group Vision Care,
Technology &amp; Innovation / R&amp;D,
26 Cooroora Crescent, Lonsdale, SA 5160</address>
      <phone>08 83928327</phone>
      <fax>08 83928400</fax>
      <email>saulius.varnas@zeiss.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Saulius Varnas</name>
      <address>Carl Zeiss - Business Group Vision Care,
Technology &amp; Innovation / R&amp;D,
26 Cooroora Crescent, Lonsdale, SA 5160</address>
      <phone>08 83928327</phone>
      <fax>08 83928400</fax>
      <email>saulius.varnas@zeiss.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Saulius Varnas</name>
      <address>Carl Zeiss - Business Group Vision Care,
Technology &amp; Innovation / R&amp;D,
26 Cooroora Crescent,
Lonsdale, SA 5160
</address>
      <phone>+618 8392 8327</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>saulius.varnas@zeiss.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>