<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365129">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/10/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/10/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001139763</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of an autonomy-support intervention with physiotherapists</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of an autonomy-support intervention with physiotherapists: Effects on interpersonal style, relationship quality, and client adherence.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Interpersonal relationships between physiotherapists and their clients</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A 3-hour autonomy support intervention will be developed according to self-determination theory (Deci &amp; Ryan 1985), recent meta-analytical evidence (Su &amp; Reeve, 2011) and applications in pedagogical settings (e.g., Aelterman et al., 2013). The intervention will consist of three parts: (i) relevant theory, (ii) specific motivational strategies, and (iii) skills application. The relevant theory component will provide participants an overview of the key tenets of self-determination theory and the link between theory and practice. The specific motivational strategies applied in the second section will provide participants concrete guidelines applicable to common situations experienced in the physiotherapy environment. The final component, skills application, will provide participants with the opportunity to practice various motivating strategies. Pen-and-paper activities and role-playing exercises will enable participants to gain experience in developing action plans for their own practice. The session will be delivered as a single face-to-face group workshop, facilitated by a registered psychologist. 

Aelterman, N., Vansteenkiste, M., Van Keer, H., De Meyer, J., Van Den Berghe, L., &amp; Haerens, L. (2013). Development and evaluation of a training on need-supportive teaching in physical education: Qualitative and quantitative findings. Teaching and Teacher Education, 29, 64-75. doi: 10.1016/j.tate.2012.09.001

Deci, E. L., &amp; Ryan, R. M. (1985). Intrinsic motivation and self-determination in human behavior. New York: Plenum.

Su, Y.L., &amp; Reeve, J. (2011). A Meta-analysis of the Effectiveness of Intervention Programs Designed to Support Autonomy. Educational Psychology Review, 23, 159-188. doi: 10.1007/s10648-010-9142-7</interventions>
    <comparator>An active control group will receive a session on up-to-date evidence on different treatment modalities for physiotherapists. The session will be designed such that it mirrors the experimental condition in time (3 hours), mode (face-to-face, single group session), and structure (theory/evidence, strategies, skills application).  </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Indicators of interpersonal relationship quality and functioning including: autonomy support (healthcare climate questionnaire), controlling behaviours (adaptation of the controlling coach behaviours scale), motivation (treatment self-regulation questionnaire), tripartite efficacy (self-efficacy, other-efficacy, relation-inferred self-efficacy), and relationship quality (relationship assessment scale). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (prior to randomisation) and 4 weeks after the delivery of the interventions. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Client-reported adherence (sport injury adherence scale)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (prior to randomisation) and 4 weeks after the delivery of the interventions. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria for physiotherapists: participant (i) is an Australian-registered physiotherapist; (ii) has been employed as a physiotherapist for at least 12 months; (iii) is clinically active (engages in at least 5 hours of practice weekly); (iv) works with clients with chronic conditions (e.g., arthritis) or who require extended rehabilitation (e.g., athletes); and (v) is able to attend either of the two intervention sessions. 

Inclusion criteria for clients: Client is (i) cognitively able to accurately complete the survey package, (ii) is willing and able to complete and return the survey packages to the researchers within the allotted time periods, and (iii) has a chronic condition or requires prolonged rehabilitation (&gt;6 weeks).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria for physiotherapists: participant (i) is not clinically active; (ii) has less than 12 months employment as a physiotherapist; (iii) has previous experience with related professional development activities such as motivational interviewing; and/or (iv) is unavailable for either of the two intervention sessions. 

Exclusion criteria for physiotherapy clients: The client (i) suffers a cognitive ailment that would yield inaccurate completion of the survey packages, (ii) is not able nor willing to complete the survey package for any reason, and (iii) does not have a chronic condition or require prolonged rehabilitation (&gt;6 weeks).
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Physiotherapists who meet the inclusion/exclusion criteria and register their interest to participate in the study will be directed to a website where they will complete a multi-section survey package. 

Once baseline data is obtained, a computer generated program will be used to randomly assign half of the physiotherapists to either intervention or active control conditions. The allocation will be concealed as it will be done by central randomisation by computer.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation and allocation to intervention and active control groups will be conducted after baseline measures are completed by physiotherapists, and will occur at the cluster level (i.e., physiotherapist). </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample sizes were calculated based on the effect sizes calculated from Lonsdale et al.s (2012) study protocol for a similar intervention. A priori power analyses suggest an approximate sample size of 78 clients per condition to detect a between-group effect (alpha level of 0.05, power level of 0.80, effect size of 0.40). Application of the correction factor for the clustered nature of the data (i.e., approx 3 clients per physio, ICC of approx .10) means 187 clients will be required.  

Statistical methods:
Multilevel modeling will be used to account for clustering of participants. Specifically, a two-level (client within physio) model will be examined. Effects of group allocation on the outcomes will be examined using a multilevel regression model. Two-tailed tests with an alpha level of .05 will be used to determine the significance of all results.

Lonsdale, C., Hall, A. M., Williams, G. C., McDonough, S. M., Ntoumanis, N., Murray, A., &amp; Hurley, D. A. (2012). Communication style and exercise compliance in physiotherapy (CONNECT). A cluster randomized controlled trial to test a theory-based intervention to increase chronic low back pain patients adherence to physiotherapists recommendations: Study rationale, design, and methods. BMJ Musculoskeletal Disorders, 13, 104. doi: 10.1186/1471-2474-13-104</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>13/01/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>70</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Suspended</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Curtin University </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Physiotherapy and Exercise Science
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987, Perth, WA, 6845</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Curtin University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>School of Physiotherapy and Exercise Science
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987, Perth, WA, 6845</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of the study is to examine whether a brief (3-hour) professional development session on autonomy-support can enhance a physiotherapists' interpersonal style with clients, and improved client rehab adherence. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin University </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Research and Development
Curtin University 
GPO Box U 1987
Perth, Western Australia 6845</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/10/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/10/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Daniel Gucciardi</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy and Exercise Science
Curtin University 
GPO Box U 1987
Perth, Western Australia 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 3653</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.gucciardi@curtin.edu.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Daniel Gucciardi</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy and Exercise Science
Curtin University 
GPO Box U 1987
Perth, Western Australia 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 3653</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.gucciardi@curtin.edu.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Daniel Gucciardi</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy and Exercise Science
Curtin University 
GPO Box U 1987
Perth, Western Australia 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 3653</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.gucciardi@curtin.edu.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Daniel Gucciardi</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy and Exercise Science
Curtin University 
GPO Box U 1987
Perth, Western Australia 6845</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>