<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363442">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/01/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/01/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000009718</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A novel device in the treatment of Obstructive Sleep Apnea and Snoring.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Multi Center, Open Label Study to evaluate a Tongue Advancement Retainer Device in the treatment of Subjects with Obstructive Sleep Apnea and Snoring.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>The Universal Trial Number (UTN) is U1111-1138-2366 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>OPEN 002</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obstructive Sleep Apnoea (OSA)</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Snoring</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sleep apnoea</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Tongue Advancement Retainer Device has been designed to decrease the severity of OSA and Snoring by maintaining the tongue in an extended position, thus preventing the tongue from falling backwards during sleep, preventing the engagement with the soft palate and airway.  

Participants will wear the device nightly for a 4 week period. The device will be fitted by the participant before going to sleep and removed upon waking. The clinician will instruct the participant on how to correctly fit the device, and choose the most appropriate size for the participants mouth. 

A polysomnogram (PSG), otherwise known as a sleep study, will be conducted at baseline and end of study to assess efficacy of the device. For the sleep study the participant attends the sleep lab in the early evening, and over the next 12 hours is introduced to the setting and "wired up" so that multiple channels of data can be recorded when he/she falls asleep. The recording will measure breathing, heart rate, brain activity, and body movement all night. During the study, the technician observes sleep activity by looking at the video monitor and the computer screen that displays all the data second by second. The test is completed and the participant goes home around 7 a.m.  </interventions>
    <comparator>Uncontrolled. 
The trial is an unblinded, non-randomised, single arm trial to assess safety and efficacy.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcomes are the safety of the device measured through the safety data; and efficacy measured in the change in the overall Apnea Hypopnea Index (AHI).

The AHI is a standard clinical measurement to determine severity of OSA. It is the average number of apneas or hypopneas that are observed during the sleep study each hour.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 4 - End of Study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcomes are the safety of the device measured through the safety data. All Adverse events (AE's) will be collected from the time of enrollment. AE's will be tabulated by their preferred terms and severity. Serious 
Adverse and Device related events will also be tabulated. In addition all events will be listed in the listings. The tables and listings will presented be as the number and percentage for each AE.

Oral appliances for snoring and sleep apnea are generally well tolerated after an initial acclimatization phase. They may produce tooth and jaw discomfort, excessive salivation, and a temporary awareness of bite change on waking. The symptoms tend to be minor and transient, dissipating after 2 to 3 weeks of use. Devices which are in contact with the teeth may be associated with movement of teeth, although when this occurs it is usually minor. Temporo mandibular joint dysfunction is a rare complication of treatment. The oral appliance may dislodge during sleep, but the size of the device minimizes the risk of choking. It is theoretically possible that breakage of the device could result in aspiration a component of the device, but that has not been reported in the literature.

In summary the risks include: Jaw discomfort, Salivation, Bite change, Teeth movement, Temporo-mandibular dysfunction, Choking, Aspiration.

This device specifically engages the tongue although several steps have been taken in the design of the device to minimize the likelihood of any adverse effects on the tongue, abrasion, inflammation, swelling, soreness, bruising or incision of the tongue or surrounding soft or hard structures of the oral cavity is possible. In all likelihood, all of these events are likely to be transient.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>From enrollment to End of Study (EOS).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compliance: 
Each morning the participant completes a short questionnaire, which includes the total hours the patient felt they slept that night, and the total hours slept with the device. This is a subjective measurement. The proportion of subjects in the treatment phase who note wearing the device &gt;=4 hours each night for &gt;=70% of the treatment period. The result will be presented as the number and percentage of device usage. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>From enrollment to EOS</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tolerability:
Each morning the participant completes a short questionnaire, which includes the total hours the patient felt they slept that night, and the total hours slept with the device. This is a subjective measurement. The proportion of subjects who used the device by night/week/overall regardless of time the device was used. The result will be presented as the number and percentage of device usage. 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>From enrollment to EOS</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tolerability:
Subjective total hours of device usage/subjective total hours of sleep by night/week/overall. Each morning the participant completes a short questionnaire, which includes the total hours the patient felt they slept that night, and the total hours slept with the device.  The result will be presented as the number and percentage of device usage.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>From enrollment to EOS</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tolerability:
Subjective total hours of device usage/subjective total hours of sleep by night/week/overall. Each morning the participant completes a short questionnaire, which includes the total hours the patient felt they slept that night, and the total hours slept with the device.  The proportion of subjects in the treatment phase who wear the device &gt;4 hours by night/week/overall will be presented as the number and percentage of device usage.
 </outcome>
      <timepoint>From enrollment to EOS</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Efficacy:
Changes in the Sleep Study results from baseline to EOS. All PSG's report set criteria as per the American Academy of Sleep Medicine Criteria. The mean results from the PSG will be summarised as n, mean, Standard Deviation, Range for baseline and EOS, and the mean change.</outcome>
      <timepoint>EOS</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Aged 18-65 

AHI greater than or equal to 10 but less than or equal to 60 (&lt;10 AHI &lt;60/hr)
Fluency in both written and spoken English
Complete set of lower anterior incisors with no evidence of periodontal disease or mobility and the ability to floss between teeth

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Central sleep apnea events &gt;10% of the total events 
Evidence of Cheyne stokes breathing
Currently on treatment for OSA or OSA treatment discontinued less than 3 months prior.
Currently on regular treatment with prescription hypnosedatives  or prescription stimulants
Very severe OSA, defined as AHI&gt;60/hour and/or minimum oxygen saturation &lt;75%
Need for immediate initiation of treatment as assessed by physician (e.g. Excessive sleepiness posing driving risk)
Previous upper airway surgery for OSA (other than nasal surgery)
Evidence of periodontal disease or tooth mobility
Severe nasal obstruction or enlarged tonsils based on clinical assessment
Unstable cardiovascular disease (untreated hypertension acceptable). 
Inability to tolerate oral device due to oral condition or claustrophobia as determined by the study investigator
Pregnant/Breast Feeding
Any known factor or disease that might interfere with treatment compliance, study conduct or interpretation of the results such as co-existent other sleep disorder, psychiatric disease, history of non compliance to medical regimens, or unwillingness to comply with study requirements.
Inability to understand the English language
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The trial is an unblinded, non-randomised, single arm trial. 

Participants who agree to participate will undergo the informed consent process. After written informed consent is obtained, a unique subject number will be assigned to the participant.</concealment>
    <sequence>Not applicable: The trial is an unblinded, non-randomised, single arm trial.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Nil</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The safety of the device will be measured through the safety data. All Adverse Events (AE's) will be presented in the the listings. Adverse events with a &gt;= 5% incidence rate will be presented in the tables.

The efficacy endpoints are change from baseline. The primary endpoint mean change will be presented as the mean at baseline, mean at End Of study (EOS), and a mean change score with a 95% CI. 

The secondary endpoints will be presented as the mean at baseline, end of study and mean change only. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/01/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>7/01/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/10/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>8/03/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>21</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Terminated</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal North Shore Hospital - St Leonards</hospital>
    <postcode>2065 - Royal North Shore Hospital</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <state>California &amp; Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Sleepy Inc.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>2570 W. El Camino Real, Suite 310
Mountain View, CA  95050
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Sleepy Inc.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>2570 W. El Camino Real, Suite 310
Mountain View, CA  95050
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Royal North Shore Hospital is currently trialing a new treatment for Obstructive Sleep Apnoea and snoring. 
The trial is for 4 weeks, and will involve wearing the device every night. The study will assess the safety and efficacy of the device.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Have you been recently diagnosed with Obstructive Sleep Apnoea (OSA)?
Do you snore?
Are you between 18-65 years?
Would you like to trial a new treatment for OSA?
Royal North Shore Hospital is currently trialing a new treatment for Obstructive Sleep Apnoea and snoring. 
The trial is for 4 weeks, and will involve wearing the device every night. 
</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>North Sydney Local Health District</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Office 
Krolling Building
Royal North Shore Hospital
St Leonards
NSW 2065
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/10/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/12/HAWKE/335. NSLHD: 1212-438M</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/10/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter A. Cistulli</name>
      <address>Royal North Shore Hospital
Reserve Rd, St. Leonards, 
NSW 2065, Australia</address>
      <phone>Australia</phone>
      <fax>+61-2-99268673</fax>
      <email>peter.cistulli@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Peter Singh</name>
      <address>Royal North Shore Hospital
Reserve Rd, St. Leonards, 
NSW 2065, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9463 2925</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9463 2099</fax>
      <email>peter.singh@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Peter Singh</name>
      <address>Royal North Shore Hospital
Reserve Rd, St. Leonards, 
NSW 2065, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9463 2925</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9463 2099</fax>
      <email>peter.singh@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Peter Robertson</name>
      <address>13/76 Reserve Road, Artarmon NSW 2064 </address>
      <phone>+61 400543070</phone>
      <fax>61 (0)2 9460 6677 </fax>
      <email>peter@fivecorners.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>