<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368693">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/06/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/07/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000694516</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Acceptability and impact of a web-based Lifestyle and sElf management Education Program (LEEP) for people with epilepsy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of a web-based Lifestyle and sElf Management Education Program (LEEP) when compared to treatment as usual on seizure frequency, mood, resilience, self-management and quality of life measures for people with epilepsy. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Epilepsy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Epilepsy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Lifestyle sElf management Education Program (LEEP) is a mobile device application that has three main foci - factual disease related information, providing information related to managing the psychosocial aspects of epilepsy and increasing accessibility of information and support.  The participants will complete four (4) education modules across four (4) weeks (i.e. one module per week). Each module should take participants a total of 30 minutes to complete.  Information related to participant's adherence to using the intervention will be reported through the application to the research team.  The participants will also be receiving a weekly 'check in' telephone call by study staff to see how they are progressing with the program.  Participants are required to complete each module weekly over the four weeks, however will have access to the intervention for a total of 8 weeks in the event that they may need extra time to complete modules. </interventions>
    <comparator>Treatment as usual which includes their contact with their treating specialist neurologist and/or any other healthcare professional on their treatment team.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Seizure frequency as assessed by self-report seizure diary.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 3 months and 6 months after the intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-management ability assessed by Epilepsy Self-Management Scale (ESMS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 3 months and 6 months after the intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health Related Quality of Life as assessed by the Quality of Life in Epilepsy Inventory  QOLIE-31. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 3 months and 6 months after the intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acceptability of intervention for people with epilepsy assessed by fidelity data (routine use and adherence to program).  The program is delivered to participants in mobile phone application.  The application will have reporting properties available to the study team to monitor usage and completion of modules. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months after the intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Economic impact as assessed by direct comparison to usual care and all cause hospital admissions. Data related to hospital admissions with be extrapolated from participant's medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months after the intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mood will be assessed by the Neurological Disorder Depression Inventory for Epilepsy (NDDI-E). This is a Primary Outcome.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 3 months and 6 months after the intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resilience as assessed by Connor-Davidson Resilience scale CD-RISC. This is a Primary Outcome.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 3 months and 6 months after the intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be patients who have a diagnosis of the following types of epilepsy - temporal lobe epilepsy, frontal lobe epilepsy, parietal lobe epilepsy, occipital lobe epilepsy, symptomatic generalized epilepsy, idiopathic (genetic) generalised epilepsy, and reflex epilepsy. Additionally, participants can be of any sex, cultural background, and educational background.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Inability to give informed consent and inability to understand English, other types of brain injury that could impact on the persons ability to provide informed consent or ability to participate in the study. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be randomly allocated to two groups (Lifestyle Self-Management Education Group (LEEP) vs. control). Once the participant is enrolled, the researcher will then complete baseline questionnaires, and contact the study coordinator who will obtain the randomisation allocation from the trial centre. Data will be entered into a study database. Consenting participants will be randomly assigned to one of the two study groups with 1:1 allocation ratio. Clinical staff enrolling participants will be blind to the allocation. Participants will not be blind to the allocation. The statistician will be blinded for comparison of the data sets.</concealment>
    <sequence>The study coordinator will obtain the randomisation allocation from the trial centre. Data will be entered into a study database. Consenting participants will be randomly assigned to one of the two study groups with 1:1 allocation ratio.  Simple randomisation table will be created using a computerised sequence generator.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Descriptive and exploratory analysis will be undertaken on the data, and the balance of groups at baseline will be checked. The main analysis will comprise a multivariate treatment of the data (multivariate analysis of variance, MANOVA), in which the significance of the intervention on a linear combination of outcome measures will be assessed. If appropriate, baseline scores will be used as a covariate in a multivariate analysis of covariance (MANCOVA) procedure. Blocking factors will be accounted for in the analysis if appropriate. A significant finding from the MANOVA or MANCOVA procedures will be followed-up with univariate ANOVAs to identify the measures that best discriminate between groups. If assumptions of equality of variance-covariance matrices and multivariate normality of the data are not violated, a discriminant function analysis will also be undertaken to aid interpretation of the linear combination of outcomes and to assess the ability of the outcome measures to classify cases. Cross-validation procedures will also be undertaken to assess the portability of the model, including diagnostic procedures to identify any influential data points. Cross-validation procedures will also be undertaken to assess the portability of the model, including diagnostic procedures to identify any influential data points.  We wish to recruit sufficient participants to allow us to demonstrate that a proportionate change in the mean rates of seizure between education groups of 50% is statistically significant at a standard level of power (80%), with significance level set at 0.05. This level of variability is of clinical importance requires 63 participants in total (126 in each arm). However, to allow for a 15% attrition loss we aim to recruit a total of 75 participants in each arm of this study (i.e. 150 in total). </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne) Ltd - Fitzroy</hospital>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Private Hospital - Fitzroy</hospital>
    <postcode>3065 - Fitzroy</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>St Vincent's Private Hospital Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>59-61 Victoria Parade
Fitzroy Victoria 3065</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>St Vincent's Private Hospital Melbourne</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>59-61 Victoria Parade
Fitzroy Victoria 3065
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>People with epilepsy consistently report the importance of lifestyle factors that can predispose a seizure. Despite this, lifestyle education is not a standard feature of patient care in clinical practice. Using a randomized controlled trial the objectives of this study are (1) to inform clinical care practice by examining the impact of a Lifestyle Education Intervention (LEEP) on seizure frequency, well being, quality of life and resilience, (2) to provide information related to seizure control and health related quality of life related to lifestyle self-management, (3) assess the acceptability of LEEP to consumers and (4) to translate the package to practice in a sustainable and effective manner. The study will use a randomized controlled trial design to test six hypothesis which are as follows -  H1 Lifestyle self-management education for people with epilepsy program (LEEP) will make a difference seizure frequency; H2 LEEP will improve the patients experience of subjective wellbeing; H3 LEEP will make a positive difference to resilience scores; H4 LEEP will improve the persons health related quality of life (HRQoL); H5  LEEP will improve the persons self management abilities; and  H6 LEEP will be acceptable and affordable to people living with epilepsy. The objectives of this study are (1) to inform clinical care practice by empirically examining the impact of a Lifestyle Education Intervention on seizure frequency, wellbeing, quality of life, self management abilities and resilience in order to reduce frequency of seizures and unplanned emergency department and hospital re-admissions (2) to provide information related to seizure control and health related quality of life, enhancing resilience and self management and (3) to translate the education package to practice in a sustainable and cost effective and acceptable manner.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Australian Catholic University HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/04/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Karen-leigh Edward</name>
      <address>St Vincent's Private Hospital Melbourne
Nursing Research Unit
59-61 Victoria Parade Fitzroy Vic 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94117338</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>karen-leigh.edward@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Karen-leigh Edward</name>
      <address>St Vincent's Private Hospital Melbourne
Nursing Research Unit
59-61 Victoria Parade Fitzroy Vic 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94117338</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>karen-leigh.edward@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Karen-leigh Edward</name>
      <address>St Vincent's Private Hospital Melbourne
Nursing Research Unit
59-61 Victoria Parade Fitzroy Vic 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94117338</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>karen-leigh.edward@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Karen-leigh Edward</name>
      <address>St Vincent's Private Hospital Melbourne
Nursing Research Unit
59-61 Victoria Parade Fitzroy Vic 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94117338</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>karen-leigh.edward@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>