<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362293">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/03/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/09/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000957897</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Exenatide in acute ischemic stroke- a randomised controlled trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Exenatide in acute ischemic stroke - a randomised controlled trial to look at its effect on post-stroke hyperglycemia, final infarct size and recanalisation and clinical outcome at 3 months</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1129-4139</utrn>
    <trialacronym>EXAIS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute ischemic stroke</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Hyperglycemia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Administering Exenatide injection 5 mcg twice daily to a selected group of acute ischemic stroke patients within 9 hours of stroke onset. Exenatide will be given for a period of 5 days maximum and then stopped.
Exenatide group patients will receive metoclopramide 10 mg or ondansetron 4mg twice daily intravenously for the first three days of exenatide treatment</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group will be 25 patients of acute ischemic stroke who will be randomly allocated. All controls will receive standard stroke therapy similar to the Exenatide group. Standard stroke therapy includes thrombolytic therapy with tissue plasminogen activator to eligible patients, admission to stroke unit, supportive treatment and treatment of complications, antiplatetlet, anticoagulant, antihypertensive treatment as appropriate. Box Hill stroke unit follows protocols advocated by the national stroke foundation and this will be adhered to in the management of patients in both groups</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Glycemic control in patients with acute ischemic stroke.
Capillary glucose levels will be measured using a continuous glucose monitoring system for the first 72 hours following admission. Following this, CGM will be stopped and finger-prick glucose will be done four time daily for the next 48 hours</outcome>
      <timepoint>CGM will be used to assess glucose levels in the first 72 hours. After this, finger prick glucose measurement will be done in the next 48 hours. Comparisons will be made between the glycemic control in both groups.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse events of exenatide - frequency or nausea, vomiting and hypoglycemic episodes. In addition any new adverse event will be documented and a causal relationship with exenatide will be explored. 
Hypoglycemia will be defined as any glucose measurment less than 3.3 mmol/l or &lt; 4mmol/l if accompanied by symptoms attributable to hypoglycemia.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the period of administration of exenatide and till up to two weeks after stopping the medication.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Final infarct size and recanalisation rate. All patients will have a MRI scan or CR scan of brain at 72 hours after admission. MRI scan will be the preferred modality, but if contraindicated, a CT scan will be done. This is a part of the standard stroke imaging protocol at Box Hill Hospital</outcome>
      <timepoint>72 hours post stroke</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical outcome - NIHSS and modified Rankin Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 days and 3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Age 18-90 years
Stroke symptom onset within 9 hours
Measurable NIHSS of 4-22
Blood sugar level on admission less than or equal to 3mmol/L
Pre-morbid modified Rankin Scale (mRS) score of 0-2
CT Brain has excluded intracerebral haemorrhage</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>90</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Unlikely to survive beyond 14 days
Have a known allergy or hypersensitivity to exenatide 
Pregnant (known or suspected) or breast feeding
Diabetic patients already on exenatide, or combination insulin and oral hypoglycaemic agents 
Past history of pancreatitis or evidence of active pancreatitis 
Patients with other severe gastrointestinal disease like gastroparesis and dumping syndrome
Patients with end stage renal disease (creatinine clearance &lt; 30 ml/min)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>50 patients with acute ischemic stroke will be selected as per inclusion criteria and randomised to either receive Exenatide injection 5 mcg BD or to no injection.  The control group will receive all other standard stroke therapy like the Exenatide group. Allocation will be concealed as described below.</concealment>
    <sequence>Block randomisation will be used to allocate the participants to the two groups. A statistician who is not involved in the recruitment and treatment of patients will create this allocation list.  The allocation list will be stored in the Pharmacy Department away from the Emergency Department and Stroke Ward where patients are assessed.  Pharmacy staff will be instructed to keep this list private and only reveal treatment allocation after receiving evidence that the patient is eligible for and consented for the study.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash University eastern clinical research unit</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 2, 5 Arnold street, Box Hill Hospital, Box Hill, Victoria 3128, Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Monash University eastern clinical research unit</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 2, 5 Arnold street, Box Hill Hospital, Box Hill, Victoria 3128, Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Eastern Health Research Grant 2012</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 2, 5 Arnold street, Box Hill Hospital, Box Hill, Victoria 3128, 
Australia
The study has been approved this grant and any additional expenditure will be from the Monash university eastern clinical research unit (ECRU) fund.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will investigate the use of a drug called Exenatide in patients with acute ischaemic stroke.
Exenatide is a drug currently approved for use in patients with type 2 diabetes to help control glucose levels. Research in animals and other laboratory studies suggests that exenatide may have a protective effect on brain cells by protecting cells that are at risk of dying in ischaemic stroke, as well as controlling glucose levels.  Exenatide has also been shown to reduce the area of brain damaged by stroke.
In this study we aim to have two groups of 25 patients  an exenatide treatment group and a control group.  One group will receive an exenatide injection twice daily for 5 days after stroke, with the first dose given within 9 hours of the onset of stroke symptoms.  These patients will also receive either metoclopramide 10 mg or ondansetron 4 mg twice daily intravenously  to prevent nausea and vomiting for the first 3 days.  The control group will have standard stroke care without exenatide treatment.  Patients in both groups are also eligible to receive tPA therapy.
Blood tests will be taken on days 0,1, 3, 5, 7 and 14 to assess glucose levels and other blood markers.  Standard imaging for stroke patients will be done for participants in the study, including a CT scan before starting the trial and CT or MRI 3-5 days after the stroke. All the patients will also have continuous glucose monitoring done in the first 72 hours. This will be done by equipment called Guardian real-time CGM system (Medtronic), which has a sensor with a subcutaneous needle.
We aim to look for any significant differences between the two groups for blood sugar control, clinical outcome and size of stroke on CT/MRI.  We will also monitor participants closely for adverse events that may be linked to exenatide treatment.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Eastern Health Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 4, 5 Arnold street, Box Hill Hospital, Victoria 3128</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/08/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>E55/1112</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/03/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Christopher Bladin</name>
      <address>Level 2, 5 Arnold street, Box Hill, Victoria 3128</address>
      <phone>+61398954974</phone>
      <fax>+61398999137</fax>
      <email>christopher.bladin@easternhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Christopher Bladin</name>
      <address>Level 2, 5 Arnold street, Box Hill, Victoria 3128</address>
      <phone>+61398954974</phone>
      <fax>+61398999137</fax>
      <email>christopher.bladin@easternhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Christopher Bladin</name>
      <address>Level 2, 5 Arnold street, Box Hill, Victoria 3128</address>
      <phone>+61398954974</phone>
      <fax>+61398999137</fax>
      <email>christopher.bladin@easternhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>