<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343325">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/08/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/09/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000950965</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of outcomes from correction of vitamin D levels in residential care facility residents</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised, double-blind, placebo controlled cohort study of the benefits of sufficient levels of vitamin D3 as defined by decreasing the number of fractures, acute illnesses and exacerbation of chronic conditions, the need for hospitalisation as well as the mortality rate for permanent residents of  residential care facilities.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Fractures</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>acute illnesses and exacerbation of chronic conditions</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>the need of hospitalisation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>the mortality rate</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Vitamin D deficiency</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other public health</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fractures</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Vitamin D3 - Cholecalciferol 1000IU.  Unscored white tablet with D3 on one side.  
Loading dose of 3000IU daily for six weeks, then 1000IU daily taken daily for 12 months.  Total trial period is 58 weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>Two separate control groups will be used:
1.  The placebo group recieve an enteric coated unscored white tablet (placebo) with identical appearance to the vitamin D tablet of the study group. It is taken initially at 3000IU per day for six weeks then 1000IU daily for 52weeks (total trial period of 58 weeks).

2.  The "no treatment group" will be allocated from those consenting participants who have serum 25(OH)D levels &gt; 50nmol/L.  These participants will be permenant residential aged care residents who are under current GP management and may or may not be on Vitamin D medication.  This group represent the current, standard residential population without study input.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in the frequency of unplanned hospital and GP visits.
The research nurse will regularly conduct a data search from participants' medical records at Aged Care Facilities, and ACT Health hospital databases to obtain such information.</outcome>
      <timepoint>14 months following randomisation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in the frequency of fractures
The research nurse will regularly a conduct data search from participants medical records at the Residential Aged Care Facilities, and ACT Health hospital databases to obtain such information.</outcome>
      <timepoint>14 months following randomisation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in mortality rate.
The research nurse will regularly conduct a data search from participants medical records at Residential Aged Care Facilities, and ACT Health hospitals to obtain such information. At the end of the study, formal requests will be made to Australia's National Agency for Health and Welfare Statistics and Information (AIHW) to validate with in-house data collection.</outcome>
      <timepoint>14 months following randomisation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The prevalence of vitamin D deficiency in the studied cohort. At the initial visit, the research nurse will collect baseline blood samples from partcipants to detemine their background vitamin D levels.</outcome>
      <timepoint>14 months following randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Permenant residents of long-term care facilities in the ACT.
Aged 65 years or more.
Willing to partipate in the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Residents with Aged Care Assesment Team ACFI assessment of 'High' for behaviour (verbal or physical).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Residential Aged Care Facilities will be invited to participate in the study and with their consent for their residents to be approached. The RACF mail-out  database will be accessed and letters sent to all potenial  participants guardians.  Interested potential participants will return the study consent forms, after which they will be approached by the study team and initial bloods taken. On review of the pathology results randomisation to one of the two treatment arms will occur and participants commenced on treatment or placebo.  At six weeks participants will be retested for 25(OH)D levels and maintenance treatment commenced. Baseline measures and outcome data will be collected from participants quarterly.  The final pathology test will be collected from each participant at the end of the study.
A research associate will create a computer generated list of random numbers to allocate to the study participants.  The study participant is allocated to the study arm based on the initial pathology results by the research associate who is based at the central administration site.  The research associate packs the allocated study drug into sealed non-transparent packages with the allocated study drug number on it, and these are delivered by another member of the research team to the participating pharmacies.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation list (placebo and study) will be generated using a random allocation generator tool. These will be attached in the order they present in the list, to each newly consented participant with a 25(OH) vitamin D level &lt; 50nmol/L. Of the 250 recruits, those participants with serum 25(OH) vitamin D levels of 50nmol/L or greater will be categorised as group 3 and not receive any intervention. 12-month prospective clinical data will be recorded and examined for comparison analysis with randomised participants in groups 1 and 2.

All researchers (apart from the associate researcher doing the randomisation), remain blinded to treatment allocation throughout the study.

There will be no randomisation process attached to the selection of group 3 participants with serum 25(OH) vitamin D levels =/&gt; 50nmol/L.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3 / Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>19/09/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>250</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>2605</postcode>
    <postcode>2611</postcode>
    <postcode>2603</postcode>
    <postcode>2614</postcode>
    <postcode>2617</postcode>
    <postcode>2615</postcode>
    <postcode>2602</postcode>
    <postcode>2607</postcode>
    <postcode>2904</postcode>
    <postcode>2604</postcode>
    <postcode>2602</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>ACT Government Health Directorate</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Canberra Hospital
Yamba Drive, 
Garran, ACT 2605</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Private Practice Fund Administration</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Canberra Hospital
PO Box 11 Woden, ACT 2606</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The Vitamin D study in ACT Residential Care Facilities (RCFs)will examine whether a maintenance dose of vitamin D3 is effective in improving outcomes such as illness presentations, exacerbations of chronic illness, fractures and death in residents of aged care facilities.  The main features of this trial are the assessment of 25(OH)D insufficiency and the commencement of the study drug or a placebo while a control group continues on the usual medications prescribed by thier GPs.  After treatment with vitamin D3 or placebo for 12 months, the frequency of unplanned GP visits, hospitalisation, falls and mortality will be assessed.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>ACT Government Health Directorate Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>ACT Health Research Office
Level 6, Building 10
Canberra Hospital, 
Yamba Drive
Garran, ACT 2605</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/08/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>ETH.3.11.036</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/03/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Prof. Michael Davis</name>
      <address>Department of Geriatric Medicine
Canberra Hospital
Building 3, Level 2.
Yamba Drive,
Garran, ACT 2605</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6244 4192</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 6244 4036</fax>
      <email>MichaelW.Davis@act.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. W. Srikusalanukul</name>
      <address>Clinical Trials Unit
Canberra Hospital
Yamba Drive,
Garran, ACT 2605</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6244 4251</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 6244 4036</fax>
      <email>wichat.srikusalanukul@act.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>L. Fryer</name>
      <address>Canberra Hospital
Building 3, Level 2.
Yamba Drive,
Garran, ACT 2605</address>
      <phone>+61 2 62443702</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 6244 4036</fax>
      <email>lyn.fryer@act.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>