<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308285">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/07/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/10/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000867291</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Upper Gastrointestinal Capsule Endoscopy as a Tool for the Triage of Haematemasis and Melaena</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An open labelled, single arm and single blinded study of the diagnostic utility of capsule endoscopy over standard endoscopy for the diagnosis of upper gastrointestinal haemorrhage.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute upper gastrointestinal haemorrhage.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Study participants will swallow a capsule endoscope specifically designed to view the oesophagus and upper gastrointestinal tract. Images are transmitted wirelessly to a data recorder worn by the patient. The procedure is expected to take 2 hours. The capsule passes naturally through the bowel and is usually excreted in a bowel motion after 24 to 48 hours.

All patients will have a gastroscopy which is current standard treatment. Gastroscopy takes 15 minutes to perform. This will occur at least 2 hours after capsule ingestion.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control treatment</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The success of capsule endoscopy in diagnosing (or excluding) causes of upper gastrointestinal bleeding. 

Images obtained by the capsule endoscopy will be interpreted by two gastroenterologist blinded to the results of the gastroscopy. Consensus agreement will be made if there are major discrepancies between the two reports. The results of capsule endoscopy will be directly compared to the results and diagnosis obtained during the gastroscopy. A standardise reporting sheet will be used for all procedures.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours after intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Correlation of findings seen on capsule endoscopy compared to gastroscopy.

This will be assessed using reports optained after visual examination of the images taken by both methods.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours after intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compare the patient tolerability and satisfaction between the procedures.

This will be assed by using a patient questionnaire and use of a visual analogue scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>48 hours after intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety of upper gastrointestinal capsule endoscopy in the setting of acute gastrointestinal haemorrhage. 

Assessment will include adverse events related to adminstration of the capsule. The main adverse event expected is capsule retention within the bowel.

Adverse events will be assessed by direct contact witht he patient at day 14. Where it is not clear that the capsule has passed, an abdominal xray will be performed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>14 days after intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All male and female patients 18 years or older admitted to the Alfred Hospital with symptoms and signs of upper gastrointestinal haemorrhage AND the patient requires an urgent gastroscopy (within 24hrs) for standard of care.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any significant condition that would make capsule endoscopy inappropriate including unstable medical conditions, the need for urgent surgery or immediate gastroscopy; Known or suspected obstructions or strictures in the gastrointestinal tract, including Crohns disease, significant prior abdominal surgery (excluding appendicectomy or cholecystectomy) or abdominal/ pelvic radiotherapy; Clinically significant dysphagia or a swallowing disorder; Excessive non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drug use; Known or suspected pregnancy or breast feeding; Inability to follow instructions; The need for magnetic resonance imaging within a week of capsule ingestion; The patient cannot give informed consent.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Investigators reporting the capsule endoscopy will be blinded to the results of the gastroscopy.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/10/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>1/10/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Given Imaging, Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>2 Hacarmel St.
New Industrial Park 
POB 258
Yoqneam 20692</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Israel</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Alfred, Department of Gastroenterology research fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The Alfred
55 Commercial Rd,
Melbourne
Victoria. 3004</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Capsule endoscopy has the potential to be used as a fast and minimally invasive tool for the triage of patients presenting to hospital with bleeding from the upper gastrointestinal tract. 

This study aims to determine the utility of capsule endoscopy in this setting by comparing its success in finding a diagnosis for the bleeding when compared to findings made at gastroscopy.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Presentation:

Risk stratification of upper gi bleeding with pillcam ESO capsule. 
Chandran S., Urquhart P., Testro A., Ong S., Shelton E., La Nauze R., Vaughan R., Kemp W., Brown G.J., Froomes P.R. 
Gastrointestinal Endoscopy. Conference: Digestive Diease Week 2012, DDW 2012 San Diego, CA United States. Conference Start: 20120519 Conference End: 20120522. Conference Publication: (var.pagings). 75 (4 SUPPL. 1) (pp AB256), 2012. Date of Publication: April 2012. 

Publication:

Risk stratification of upper GI bleeding with an esophageal capsule.
Chandran S, Testro A, Urquhart P, La Nauze R, Ong S, Shelton E, Philpott H, Sood S, Vaughan R, Kemp W, Brown G, Froomes P.
Gastrointest Endosc. 2013 Jun;77(6):891-8. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2013.01.003. Epub 2013 Feb 26

</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Hospital Ethics Committee (EC00315)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Alfred Hospital, 
55 Commercial Road, 
Melbourne, 
Victoria.  3004</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/09/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>272/09</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/07/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Richard La Nauze</name>
      <address>Department of Gastroenterology and Hepatology
The Alfred
PO Box 315
Prahran
Victoria
3181</address>
      <phone>+613 9076 2000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.lanauze@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Richard La Nauze</name>
      <address>Department of Gastroenterology and Hepatology
The Alfred
PO Box 315
Prahran
Victoria
3181</address>
      <phone>+613 9076 2000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.lanauze@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Paul Frooms</name>
      <address>Austin Hospital
145 Studley Road
 Heidelberg, 
Victoria, 
Australia, 3084</address>
      <phone> +613 9496 5000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pfroomes@me.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>