<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347574">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/10/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/10/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611001081909</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A short-term step training exergame intervention to improve parameters of fall-risk in independent living older people : A pilot randomized controlled study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A short-term step training exergame intervention vs no intervention to improve parameters of fall-risk in independent living older people</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>accidental falls in older people</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>cognitive function in older people</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>physical function in older people</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Subjects will play an adapted open source active computer game (exergame) via their TV. A step pad and a computer unit will be provided to them. 
While stepping on the step pad subjects interact with the computer. The game idea is to step as accurately as possible in terms of direction and timing. Arrows drift up the screen; when they reach a location on top of screen the subject's task is to step on the corresponding arrow of the step pad.
They will play this game to music but will not step in the rhythm to the music. In addition they will be distracted by other elements on the screen for which their task is not to step.
Participants will be asked to play as many times as they want with the recommended dose of 2-3 sessions per week for 15-20 minutes over a period of 8 weeks. The participants can play more often if they want to.
In addition subjects will be asked to do a choice stepping reaction time task once a week. In this game/test subjects step as quickly as they can in different step directions depending on arrows changing their color on the screen.
The intervention will be unsupervised. Participants will be instructed at the beginning of the study period in their homes when the system will be installed. To control for compliance people will be contacted by phone in week 1, 2, 3 and 6.</interventions>
    <comparator>None - during the study period, the control group will follow its usual activities
After this trial is finished the control group will receive the same intervention as the intervention group did.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Choice Stepping Reaction Time (CSRT) in milliseconds measured using a step pad</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline and 8-9 weeks after randomization</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical/physiological fall-risk assessed by the Physiological Profile Assessment (PPA); this test battery involves 5 tests of different physiological functions involved in postural stability (contrast sensitivity, proprioception lower extremities, strength lower extremities, postural sway, hand reaction time). An overall score is generated from these 5 weighted sub-scores.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline and 8-9 weeks after randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fear of falling is measured by the short version of the Icon-FES, an iconographic questionnaire (10 items).</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline and 8-9 weeks after randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>physical performance measured using the Timed up &amp; go test (TUG), Sit to Stand 5 times (5STS), Alternate Step test (AST), 6m-walk</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline and 8-9 weeks after randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>cognitive functions measured using pen- and paper-based neuropsychological tests as well as newly developed combined tests of stepping and cognition (Stroop test, Trailmaking Test A&amp;B, Digit Symbol Substitution test)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline and 8-9 weeks after randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>physical activity measured using the Incidental and Planned Exercise Questionnaire (IPEQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline and 8-9 weeks after randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>age&gt;65 years
independent living
ambulant with or without walking aid
able to step unassisted on the step pad</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>cognitive impairment (MMSE&lt;24)
neurodegenerative diseases (e.g. Parkinson)
health problems that affect stepping ability (e.g. acute painful joint inflammation, mobility problems after stroke)
unstable health conditions</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A central randomisation by computer will be used. The central randomisation office is remote from participant recruitment centre and participant details will be provided by Email. The person performing the randomisation will not be involved in the clinical part of this study. Screening for eligibility and pre-assessment will be undertaken before randomisation.</concealment>
    <sequence>We will use block-randomisation to form the allocation for the two comparison groups, using computer-generated random numbers. Couples (participants living in the same household) will be randomised into their own blocks.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>18/10/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>18/10/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>7/11/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>38</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Prof Stephen R Lord</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Neuroscience Research Australia
Barker Street, Randwick, NSW 2031
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GHD Building Level 1, 16 Marcus Clarke St
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Stuart T Smith</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Neuroscience Research Australia
Barker Street, Randwick, NSW 2031
Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>One in three people 65 years and older fall each year with consequences for the individual and a high burden for society. Stepping is often the last protective option to prevent a fall. Studies have shown that impaired stepping is prevalent in older people and that impaired stepping is associated with high risk of falls. In this study a low-cost computer game device (dance pad) that enables a human-computer interaction via movements (exergame) will be used to as a home-based interactive step training in independent living older people. This randomised controlled pilot trial aims at improving parameters of fall-risk and physical function. Further aim is to investigate whether this step training to cognitive stimuli on a screen (TV) can improve parameters of cognitive function.
This study proposes to test the hypothesis that: a short-term volitional step training intervention using a dance pad can significantly improve risk factors for falls as well as measures of cognition in independent living older people.
The intervention will last 8 weeks and participants are asked to play a game of step co-ordination at least 2-3 times per week for 15 to 20 minutes and to do a choice stepping reaction time task once a week. People in the control group will maintain their usual activities.
Primary outcome measure will be the choice stepping reaction time (CSRT). Further outcomes are the Physiological Profile Assessment (PPA), tests of combined motor and cognitive function, tests of physical performance, tests of cognitive functions, and a iconographic measure of Fear of Falling.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Schoene D, Lord SR, Delbaere K, Severino C, Davies TA, Smith ST. A randomized controlled pilot study of home-based step training in older people using videogame technology. PLoS One. 2013;8(3):e57734. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0057734. </publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee University of New South Wales</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ethics Secretariat
UNSW Grants Management Office
Rupert Myers Building, Level 3, South Wing
The University of New South Wales 
SYDNEY NSW 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/06/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>08351</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/05/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Stephen R Lord</name>
      <address>Neuroscience Research Australia
Barker Street, Randwick, NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9399 1061</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9399 1204</fax>
      <email>s.lord@neura.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Stephen R Lord</name>
      <address>Neuroscience Research Australia
Barker Street, Randwick, NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9399 1061</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9399 1204</fax>
      <email>s.lord@neura.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Daniel Schoene</name>
      <address>Neuroscience Research Australia
Barker Street, Randwick, NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9399 1801</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9399 1204</fax>
      <email>d.schoene@neura.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Stephen R Lord</name>
      <address>Neuroscience Research Australia
Falls and Balance Research Group
Barker St
Randwick, NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9399 1061</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.lord@neura.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>