<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308080">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/06/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/06/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000497202</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Help-seeking for Depression by Young People - considering the impact of Stigma</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised control trial for the effectiveness of a mental health literacy intervention promoting a biological model of depression to facilitate a reduction in stigma and increase help-seeking intention in young people</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>The effectiveness of a mental health literacy intervention promoting a biological model of depression to facilitate a reduction in stigma and increase help-seeking intention in young people</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Epidemiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>It will comprise a randomised control trial (RCT) where students are randomly assigned to one of three educational paradigms: a biological attribution condition, a psychosocial attribution condition or a control condition involving the provision of general information about depression.  The intervention will be delivered online.

The Biological Condition

Content for this experimental intervention will include a vignette outlining information about the biological basis for depression.  The general message will be that 'Depression is an illness like any other illness' and that the onset of depression is due to a chemical imbalance in the brain.

The Psychosocial Condition

Content for this experimental intervention will include a vignette outlining information about the psychosocial basis for depression.  The general message will be that depression results from the stress in our social environment and our reactions to it.

The survey and intervention will be completed online in one lesson of the normal class schedule (approximately 50 minutes), in a one-off educational intervention.</interventions>
    <comparator>This intervention will comprise a vignette and standard general information around depression which focuses on the symptoms experienced by a person with depression (eg. trouble sleeping, low mood, irritability, feeling lethargic) without providing a causal explanation.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction in anticipated self-stigma for depression</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately post-intervention using Barney's (2007) Self-Stigma for Depression Scale (SSDS)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Increased general help-seeking intention by young people for depression</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately post-intervention using Rickwood's General Help-Seeking Questionnaire (GHSQ)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>This will be a universal intervention (ie, participants selected regardless of mental health status) involving all Year 11 and 12 students in each college.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>20</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>15 years or under.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>We anticipate that all Year 11 and 12 students in the consenting colleges will be invited to participate.  We propose operating on the basis of passive consent for participation from the parents/guardians of students and informed consent (via online acceptance) from each student who participates.

The participants will be young mature minors aged 16 to 18 years. As college students they are likely to have achieved a sufficient maturity and competence to enable them to understand fully what is proposed  (NS4.2a: Consent by children under the age of majority but with sufficient competence to decide).  

We anticipate that the young person's consent is implied by clicking on the “I agree” button at the bottom of the online Information and Consent page and by completing the questionnaire and intervention.   .  

Parental consent is normally required where an anonymous questionnaire is to be administered to children in schools. However, the experience of other researchers in schools is that there are major barriers to receiving back such permission forms in the school context as they become lost in bags or otherwise mislaid or overlooked. Given the age and educational level of the students, potential benefits of the study and the low level of risk (particularly as the survey is anonymous and no data can be linked to individual students) and the provision of opt-out options for parents, we ask that the committee approve the proposed implied consent from parents and active consent from young people.  

Conditions are randomly allocated to students via a sealed white envelope, inside which is a piece of paper with a 'password' code that is required to be entered into the online environment.  Each group has a unique colour code allocated to that condition.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomly allocated to one of three intervention conditions.  The randomisation will occur via sealed intervention envelopes, prepared by a statistician who will prepare the intervention envelopes using a computer based random number generator, independently of the primary investigator prior to the intervention taking place.

Envelopes are then handed out in order to the school students as they sit at the computers.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This intervention will be delivered in a single lesson over approximately 50 minutes.  Each participant will complete an online survey with data collected on a server hosted behind a firewall by the Centre for Mental Health Research.  The first screen will ask for the participants consent and when consent is provided then each participant will independently work through the online questionnaire.  Participants will be randomly allocated into a group via the manual process outlined earlier.  Data extraction will be automated and no identifying information will be collected from participants or attached to data.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>19/06/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>480</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australian National University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Psychology
Building 39
Australian National University
Acton  ACT  0200</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian National University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Centre for Mental Health Research
College of Medicine, Biology and Environment
Eggleston Road
Acton ACT 0200</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Kerry Howard</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>PO Box 4003
WESTON CREEK  ACT  2611</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Based on biological attribution theory it is hypothesised that the biological explanation for depression will lead to a greater decrease in young peoples anticipated self-stigma associated with depression than the other two conditions. It is further hypothesised that any decrease in self-stigma will lead to increased help-seeking intention (from a mental health professional) by these young people if they were to experience depression in the future.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://mentalhealth.anu.edu.au/survey</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Australian National University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Office
Chancelry Building 10B LG
East Road
Australian National University
Acton ACT 0200</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/06/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2009/208</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/05/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Kathy Griffiths</name>
      <address>Centre for Mental Health Research
Australian National University
Eggleston Road
ACTON  ACT  2601</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6125 9723</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Kathy.Griffiths@anu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kerry Howard</name>
      <address>PO Box 4003
WESTON CREEK  ACT 2611</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6287 1019</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>u4233173@anu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kerry Howard</name>
      <address>PO Box 4003
WESTON CREEK  ACT 2611</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6287 1019</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>u4233173@anu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>