<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368902">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/07/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/08/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000812594</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Epidemiological study of Hidradenitis Suppurativa (HS) to determine the prevalence and severity of the disease in the Australian population.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A two stage, epidemiological, cross-sectional survey study of the Australian population, to determine the prevalence and severity of Hidradenitis Suppurativa (HS). </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>HS-Epi</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hidradenitis Suppurativa</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dermatological conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This a two stage cross-sectional, observational survey study to determine the prevalence and severity of HS in the Australian population. No intervention will be administered and the population will not be exposed to an exposure factor. 
Stage one: Screening of the Australian population for those who potentially have HS 
The Single Source Establishment Survey is a household survey conducted by an Australian market research company, with purpose to obtain demographic data from individuals aged 18 years and over. The Single Source Survey covers all Australian States and Territories. Questions that indicate a potential diagnosis of HS, will be added to the Single Source Survey administered in all Australian States and Territories, except the Northern Territory*. 
Prior the specific HS questions being asked, the interviewee will be asked if he or she verbally consents to being asked these questions. 
If the interviewee qualifies for a potential HS diagnosis, he or she will then be asked to participate in stage two. 
*The Northern Territory has been excluded from this study due to lack of a local dermatology clinic to confirm diagnosis in stage two.
Stage two: Dermatology consult, diagnosis confirmation and severity assessment 
If the subject provides written consent to participating in the study, a researcher will then contact them and invite them to participate in a dermatology consult at a participating local dermatology clinic. If the subject agrees, upon their arrival to the clinic, they will provide written consent to participating in the research study, undergoing a physical examination and having clinical photographs taken by a dermatologist, as well as the storage and future use of the information collected. The clinician will record the diagnosis and clinical notes on severity on a form. All patient data including written information and clinical photographs will be de-identified. 
Confirmation of HS diagnosis and confirmation of moderate to severe HS diagnosis will be made by the attending dermatologist according to Hurley Stage System, as well as via a central expert review of the clinical notes and photographs.
Data collected will be statistically analysed to determine the prevalence and severity of HS in the Australian population. 
No medication or treatment will be administered. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>No comparator</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prevalence of HS - based on dermatologist diagnosis of HS, and the statistical analysis of the number of diagnoses in the Australian population. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured after a dermatologist has reviewed a patient for  HS and confirmed diagnosis, and a central expert dermatologist has reviewed all cases for consistency in diagnosis. Statistical analysis of the data collected will be then be conducted to determine prevalence. Anticipated to be a month after all surveys are conducted. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severity of HS via Hurley Stage method - based on dermatologist diagnosis of moderate to severe HS, and the statistical analysis of the number of moderate to severe cases in the Australian population. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured after a dermatologist has reviewed a patient for  HS, confirmed diagnosis, provided severity as per the Hurley Stage Method, and a central expert dermatologist has reviewed all cases for consistency in severity grading. Statistical analysis of the data collected will be then be conducted to determine severity in the Australian population. Anticipated to be a month after all surveys are conducted.  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All those who participates in the 'Single Source Survey'. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Those who are under 18 years of age and have not consented to the 'Single Source Survey' .</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Data from the survey will be categorised according to HS and non-HS groups. Frequency count and the percentage of subjects within each category will be calculated. Comparison between HS group and non-HS group will be done using an independent T-test. Crude prevalence rates for HS and their 95% CI will be estimated using the number of confirmed HS diagnoses. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Random sample</selection>
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>22/08/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>15/08/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/10/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>11/12/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>7000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>11433</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/10/2015</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>8/02/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,QLD,SA,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>AbbVie Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>32-34 Lord Street
Botany NSW 2019
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Abbvie Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>32-34 Lord Street
Botany NSW 2019
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other Collaborative groups</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>George Clinical, as part of The George Institute</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Level 13/321 Kent St Sydney, NSW 2000</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Hidradenitis Suppurativa (HS) is a chronic skin disease that appears as pea-sized to marble-sized lumps under the skin. The lumps form most often in the armpits, under the breasts, inner thighs, groin and buttocks. HS can be painful and cause scarring and pus in affected areas. Flare-ups may be triggered by perspiration, hormonal changes (such as monthly cycles in women), humidity and heat, and friction from clothing.

The objectives of this study are to determine the prevalence of HS in the Australian population and characterize the patterns of disease severity in this patient population. 

A cross-sectional, observational, population-based study will be used to investigate the epidemiology of HS. The study will be administered via a survey.

If responses indicate that the participant potentially has HS, they will be contacted by a researcher to invite them to attend a dermatology clinic for further assessment. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>129 Glen Osmund Rd Eastwood, Adelaide, South Australia 5063</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/08/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>17/06/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Diana Rubel</name>
      <address>Woden Dermatology: Level 1, 1 Bowes Place, Phillip ACT 2606 
</address>
      <phone>+61262828410</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>trials@wodendermatology.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Helen Valcanis</name>
      <address>AbbVie Pty Ltd: Level 7, 241 ORiordan Street
Mascot NSW 2020
</address>
      <phone>+61 447 620 031</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>helen.valcanis@abbvie.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Helen Valcanis</name>
      <address>AbbVie Pty Ltd: Level 7, 241 ORiordan Street
Mascot NSW 2020
</address>
      <phone>+61 447 620 031</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>helen.valcanis@abbvie.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Jen Than</name>
      <address>George Clinical, as part of The George Institute:
Level 13/321 Kent St
Sydney
NSW 2000</address>
      <phone>+61296570356</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jthan@georgeclinical.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>