<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366155">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/04/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/04/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000435684</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Enhancing cognitive-behavioural therapy for recurrent headache by integrating into it a new approach to the management of headache triggers (Learning to Cope with Triggers)
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluating the impact of incorporating a learning to cope with triggers compared to avoidance of triggers as part of cognitive behavioural therapy for tension-type headache and migraine sufferers by measuring the primary outcomes of (a) daily headache activity; (b) headache medication usage: (c) the presence of triggers and (d) the impact of headache on daily living.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1155-6532</utrn>
    <trialacronym>ENHANCE- Enhanced treatment for headaches</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Migraines

</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Tension Type Headaches</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Conditions of unknown or disputed aetiology (such as chronic fatigue syndrome/myalgic encephalomyelitis)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention 1: 12 weekly sessions of cognitive behavioural therapy, relaxation therapy and exposure as an opportunity to practice coping skills or when not possible the use of avoidance of triggers. Each 50 minute session will be administered in an individual format by a registered psychologist.

Intervention 2: 12 weekly sessions of cognitive behavioural therapy, relaxation techniques including components on the avoidance of triggers. Each 50 minute session will be administered in an individual format by a registered psychologist.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Wait list Control no treatment. The wait list control group will be offered treatment following the post assessment period (12 weeks of treatment and 4 week followup). The wait list control group will be offered either treatment 1 (learning to cope with triggers) or treatment 2 (Avoidance of triggers). Treatment type will be according to the participants preference.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-monitoring of daily headache activity using a headache diary


</outcome>
      <timepoint>The diaries will be assessed at baseline (for 4 weeks prior to commencement of treatment), throughout treatment, immediately post treatment (for 4 weeks), four and 12 month follow-up (for 4 weeks).
Throughout treatment means monitoring this on a daily basis over the 12 weeks of treatment.
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-monitoring of daily medication use using a daily headache diary</outcome>
      <timepoint>The diaries will be assessed at baseline (for 4 weeks prior to commencement of treatment), throughout treatment, immediately post treatment (for 4 weeks), four and 12 month follow-up (for 4 weeks).
Throughout treatment means monitoring this on a daily basis over the 12 weeks of treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Headache Disability Inventory (HDI)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurement time points: baseline, post treatment, four and 12 month follow-up
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Headache Triggers Avoidance Questionnaire (HTAQ). 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurement time points: baseline, post treatment, four and 12 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Headache Management Self-Efficacy Scale (HMSESv2 ). 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurement time points: baseline, post treatment, four and 12 month follow-up
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Headache-Specific Locus of Control (HSLC) 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurement time points: baseline, post treatment, four and 12 month follow-up
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Coping Strategies Inventory (CSI) 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurement time points: baseline, post treatment, four and 12 month follow-up
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Short-Form Health Survey version 2  (SF-36v2).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurement time points: baseline, post treatment, four and 12 month follow-up
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>i) Diagnosed as either migraine without aura, typical aura with migraine headache, chronic migraine, frequent episodic tension-type headache, or chronic tension-type headache; (ii) minimum of 6 headache days per month; (iii) minimum headache chronicity of 12 months, and pattern of headache symptoms stable over last six months</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Diagnosed as medication overuse headache; (ii) headaches present continuously; (iii) recent changes in prophylactic medication (study requires that medication has been stable for previous month) (iv) pregnant, planning pregnancy during trial period or lactating iv) currently receiving psychological or psychiatric treatment.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation will occur off-site via computer. The co-investigator with statistical responsibility and no involvement with participants will take responsibility for randomisation</concealment>
    <sequence>Use of a randomisation table created by computer software (computer sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>N/A</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The design of the proposed study will focus on the interaction test of a mixed factorial design. Data will be tested for assumptions underlying both univariate and multivariate parametric analysis.
 The power analysis is based primarily on the effect sizes generated in previous clinical trials of f = 0.33 to 0.42. Based on previous results an effect size of f =.25 (commonly accepted convention for a medium effect) can be confidently predicted. Power analysis using a G-Power software package indicates that for a three-group mixed factorial design with 40 participants per group and alpha = .05, moderate effects (f =.25) would be reliably identified with power .93 and a large effect (f = 0.4)would have an almost certain probability of being reliably identified.
Any missing data will be considered on an intention-to-treat basis and fully analysed for the presence of MAR, MCAR, and NMAR patterns.   In addition to exploratory descriptive and correlational analyses, group by phase factorial ANOVAs using a Linear Mixed Models approach will be the main method of analysis for assessing treatment outcome.  These will be supplemented by analyses of simple main effects and trend analysis (ie. analysis of orthogonal polynomials) to examine the pattern of change over time for the experimental group.  A linear mixed modelling approach has been chosen in order to permit: flexible structuring of the repeated covariance associated with the phase effect; more options for dealing with missing values; the analysis of individual change via growth curves; and options for analysing multi-level models, should they be theoretically or clinically relevant.  For all inferential tests, measure of effect size (ie. either d or eta 2) will be calculated, including confidence intervals around those measures.  A range of clinical significance measures will also be considered.  Finally, regression analyses will be used to examine predictors of response to treatment, and the approach of Preacher and Hayes (2008) to moderation analysis will be used to examine the client-treatment matching hypotheses.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/05/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>30/01/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>4215 - Southport</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Paul Martin (Principal Investigator)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Applied Psychology
Mt Gravatt Campus, Griffith University
176 Messines Ridge Road
Mt Gravatt, QLD 4122 
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC 
National Health and Medical Research Council
APP1046745</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress> GPO Box 1421 Canberra ACT 2601
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Peter Goadsby (Co-Investigator)
</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Professor of Neurology
Director, NIHR-Wellcome Trust Clinical Research Facility
Imperial College London, South Kensington Campus, London SW7 2AZ

</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>United Kingdom</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Simon Broadley (Co-Investigator)</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School: Medicine Gold Coast Campus
Griffith Health Centre
Cnr of Olsen Ave and Parklands Drive 
Southport, QLD 4215

</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Colin Macleod (Co-Investigator)</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Psychology 	
University of Western Australia
35 Stirling Highway
Crawley, WA 6009
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Associate Professor John Reese (Co-Investigator)</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Division of Psychology
RMIT University
Bundoora Campus
PO Box 71 Bundoora, Vic 3083
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this research is to investigate a behavioural treatment for the management of headache triggers within a cognitive-behavioural therapy program.  The research will compare two variations of trigger management, one being the traditional approach (avoidance of all triggers) and one being a variation of the traditional approach (learning to cope with triggers). The investigators hypothesise that the enhanced approach which assists individuals to manage triggers rather than simply avoid them will have more positive outcomes including reduced headache frequency, reduced use of pain medication and improved quality of life

</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.griffith.edu.au/health/enhanced-treatment-headaches</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Approval Griffith University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Manager, Research Ethics
Office for Research
Gold Coast campus
Room 4.25, The Learning Commons Building (G11)
Griffith University
Parklands Drive, Southport QLD 4215


</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/10/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>PSY/31/13HREC</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Queensland Health Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Gold Coast University Hospital Ethics Committee
Gold Coast University Hospital and Health Service
1 Hospital Boulevard Southport
QLD 4215</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/07/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/QGC/72</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Paul R Martin</name>
      <address>School of Applied Psychology
Mt Gravatt Campus, Griffith University
176 Messines Ridge Road
Mt Gravatt, QLD 4122


</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3735 3322</phone>
      <fax />
      <email> paul.martin@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Paul R Martin</name>
      <address>School of Applied Psychology
Mt Gravatt Campus, Griffith University
176 Messines Ridge Road
Mt Gravatt, QLD 4122
</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3735 3322</phone>
      <fax />
      <email> paul.martin@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Paul R Martin</name>
      <address>School of Applied Psychology
Mt Gravatt Campus, Griffith University
176 Messines Ridge Road
Mt Gravatt, QLD 4122</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3735 3322</phone>
      <fax />
      <email> paul.martin@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Paul R Martin</name>
      <address>School of Applied Psychology Mt Gravatt Campus, Griffith University 176 Messines Ridge Road Mt Gravatt, QLD 4122</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3735 3322</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>paul.martin@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>