<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365281">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/03/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/01/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000014550</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Motivational interviewing for people undergoing home dialysis to improve treatment adherence: A randomised controlled trial.

</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Motivational interviewing conducted by nurses for people undergoing home dialysis to improve treatment adherence: A randomised controlled trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>MIA Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Patients with End Stage Kidney Disease (ESKD) on automated peritoneal dialysis and/or haemodialysis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Intervention Group  

Group 1, Motivational Interviewing intervention: Following  completion of the questionnaire (10 minutes) and random allocation, each participant in Group 1 will receive information relating to their treatment from the registered nurse will conduct a once off 30 minutes interview, with Motivational Interviewing strategies using the 5As model. This model is designed to formally involve you in decision making about the education and information you receive for your care. Any other routine or usual care from the regular medical and nursing clinicians from the Home Independent Dialysis treatment service HIDTS will also be provided."</interventions>
    <comparator>Group 2, the Control Group (Routine or Usual care):  Following completion of the questionnaire and random allocation, each participant in Group 2 will receive an assessment along with written and verbal information using the usual education processes by the registered nurses from the HIDTS service. Any other routine or usual care from the regular medical and nursing clinicians from the HIDTS will also be provided. 
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-management of dialysis sessions (a composite outcome)as prescribed over 12 weeks as measured by the validated instrument, Strategies Used by People to Promote Health (SUPPH), Objective measurements including pathology results and treatment times for patients with ESKD. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks and 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Diet and fluid adherence measured by the Morisky scale for Adherence for patients with ESKD.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 6 and Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants undergoing automated peritoneal dialysis, haemodialysis and ESKD patients who attend and or receive renal services from nurses of the Home Independent and Dialysis Treatment Services (HIDTS).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>&lt;18 years of age</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>About 72 participants are expected to participate in this study and the duration of participation is expected to be 12 weeks. Once consent has been obtained, the Renal Nurses will ring the off site randomiser. Participants will either be in the control group or the intervention. They will be randomly allocated into one of the two (2) groups:Group 1 (Motivational Interviewing Intervention) and Group 2 (Routine or Usual Care). Particpants and those providing the treatment will be blinded to the randomisation process. Participants will be blinded to the Intervention as they are unaware as to whom has been trained in the counselling intervention. The researcher is blinded to the data collection and input. </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software will randomly allocate the participants.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample Size:  To see a minimum clinical difference of 15 points on the primary outcome measure the SUPPH (self-efficacy scale) with a standard deviation of 10, using a 5% level of significance and 80% power, 36 patients per group was required. That is 36 in the intervention and 36 in the control groups. 

Data Analysis: All statistical data will be analysed using SPSS. Categorical data will be expressed as frequencies and percentages. Fishers exact test and logistic regression will be used to compare differences between groups. Continuous data will be expressed as the difference between 12 weeks and baseline, and will be described by means and standard deviations.  ANOVA and t-tests will be used to analyse the relationships between two or more groups. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/10/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>31/10/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/04/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>3/03/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>72</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <postcode>4029 - Royal Brisbane Hospital</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Carol Reid</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Nursing 
Queensland University of Technology
Victoria Park Rd, Kelvin grove, 4171
Brisbane, QLD 
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Butterfield St 
Herston  QLD  4029</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Psycho-educational support is recommended as essential for patients undertaking self-management of their dialysis treatment An intervention such as motivational interviewing (MI), the use of the 5 As model and information giving from nurses may promote behavioural change to enhance adherence to prescribed treatments and to reduce risk factors associated with severe life threatening medical complications. This randomized controlled trial will examine the effectiveness of this intervention for people with ESKD and who live at home, undergoing either automated peritoneal dialysis or haemodialysis. This intervention may improve adherence to dialysis session times; fluid and dietary intake, diet and taking prescribed medications.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Carol Reid</name>
      <address>Queensland University of Technology
Victoria Park Rd
Kelvin Grove QLD 4059
</address>
      <phone>61 7 31389607</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c2.reid@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Carol Reid</name>
      <address>Queensland University of Technology
Victoria Park Rd
Kelvin Grove QLD 4059</address>
      <phone>61 7 31389607</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c2.reid@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Carol Reid</name>
      <address>Queensland University of Technology
Victoria Park Rd
Kelvin Grove, 4029
Queensland </address>
      <phone>61 7 31389607</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c2.reid@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Carol Reid</name>
      <address>Queensland University of Technology
Victoria Park Rd
Kelvin Grove</address>
      <phone>61 7 31389607</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c2.reid@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>