<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="498">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/09/2005</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/09/2005</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12605000461695</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The value of GP endorsement on participation in rescreening for colorectal cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The value of GP endorsement on participation in rescreening for colorectal cancer</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Screening for bowel cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Bowel - Back passage (rectum) or large bowel (colon)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The aim is to determine the value of GP endorsement for faecal occult blood test based re-screening colorectal cancer. The interventions are conducted within the setting of a population screening program where invitees are recruited from general practice patient lists. 
Intervention 1: Invitation letter to re-screen on central screening facility letterhead with statement from invitee's general practice endorsing participation in screening, signed by screening coordinator.
Intervention 2: Invitation letter to rescreen on practice letterhead with statement from practice endorsing screening, signed by invitee's general practitioner.
Comparison group: recruited from electoral roll receiving control invitation to rescreen.
Duration: Four annual rounds of screening offers.
All people received the same invitation type over the 4 rounds of screening invitations.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control: Generic invitation to re-screen for colorectal cancer letter on central screening facility letterhead, signed by screening coordinator.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Paricipation in screening defined as return of a screening kit 12 weeks from offer.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Test positivity rate</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Yield of neoplasia</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All people on patient lists of 2 general practices.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>People identified by the collaborating practices and practitioners as having gastrointestinal conditions that invalidate screening results, people with mental and physical disabilities that prevent them from following the study protocol, people known to have had a neoplasia negative colonoscopy 5 years prior to a screening offer, people who inform the screening facility that they do not want further contact.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Invitees are randomised to one of 4 invitation groups that differ by invitation type or source of subjects. Allocation to invitation group is not concealed from the investigators and office staff who print and package invitation kits for postal delivery, but there is no direct contact with between investigators and invitees. Invitees are unaware that there are more than one invitation type. A help line is available and inquiries are answered without knowledge of invitation type.</concealment>
    <sequence>Group sizes of 600 each were determined by power analysis assuming that an intervention that produces a 10% increase in participation over control is a significant program improvement. For people aged 50-80 recruited from general practices, practice lists were were firstly combined. All people were assigned a random number using the MicroSoft Excel RAND function. The listing was ordered by ascending random number. The first 600 people were assigned to Intervention group 1 (Generic letter), the second 600 to Intervention group 2 (endorsement from practice) and the third 600 to the Intervention group 3 (strong endorsement, signed by GP). For the comparison group (people recruited from the electoral roll), 600 people aged 50-80 were randomly selected. All were allocated to a single group.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/12/2000</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>2400</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Prof. Graeme Young MD, FRACP</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Beckman Coulter Inc</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Enterix Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Bushel Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Mr Stephen Cole</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Improved participation in screening for bowel cancer is desirable. Large scale screening programs must recruit invitees through comprehensive population registers. Depending on the country and health system these may be primary care practice lists or other registers such as the electoral roll. If primary care patient lists are available, considerable practice time may be required to organise the screening program, alternatively the implicit practice endorsement of screening may increase the participation rate to make that investment worthwhile. As screening is most effective when conducted regularly, it is important to determine if any increase in participation rate due to practice or practitioner endorsement is maintained over several rounds of screening offers. This study aims to follow screening participation over 4 rounds of offers in 4 treatment groups, and to use innovative statistical methods to determine the value of practice involvement in re-sceening participation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Repatriation General Hospital Daw Park</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Daws Rd, Daw Park, SA 5041</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mr Stephen Cole</name>
      <address>Bowel Health Service
Repatriation General Hospital Daw Park
Daws Road
Daw Park SA 5041</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82751838</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 82751083</fax>
      <email>scoles@rgh.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Alicia Smith</name>
      <address>Bowel Health Service
Repatriation General Hospital Daw Park
Daws Rd
Daw Park SA 5041</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82751075</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 02751083</fax>
      <email>alicia.smith@rgh.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>