<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336061">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/10/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/10/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000919011</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Radiostereometric Analysis (RSA) study of the Hyperion uncemented stem in patients with degenerative hip disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Radiostereometric Analysis (RSA) study of the Hyperion uncemented stem in patients with degenerative hip disease</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Degenerative hip disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The purpose of the clinical study is to determine the predicted long-term safety and effectiveness of the Hyperion uncemented stem using Radiostereometric Analysis (RSA) to yield early results in small number of patients.
RSA is engaged to provide information to assess implant migration and can be used for early trials of new implant designs, potentially reducing the number of revisions by identifying new prosthesis that fail.
The medical device will be implanted using standard surgical technique, depending on the investigators standard procedure. Instrumentation specific for the device will be used. This is the only intervention for the patient and the intervention generally is completed within two hours.</interventions>
    <comparator>n/a</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary objective of this study is to evaluate migration of the Hyperion 
uncemented femoral stem in primary total hip replacement using Radiostereometric Analysis (RSA). RSA will be performed at discharge, 6 months, 1 year, 2 years and 5 years following surgery</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patients will be seen at the 6 month, 1 year, 2 and 5 year interval post surgery. The Oxford Hip Questionnaire12 and the Hip disability and osteoarthritis outcome score (HOOS)13 will be collected at the 1 year, 2 year and 5 year interval.

Radiographs will be taken postoperatively, and at 2 and 5 years following surgery. The following postoperative radiographs will be taken on all patients after implantation.

	Anterior Posterior (AP)x ray of the pelvis and both hips (to include the entire prosthesis)
	Lateral x ray of affected hip

Post operative radiographs will be evaluated by the Investigator to determine component alignment, lucencies, and bone condition. The alignment of the femoral prosthesis will be measured as the angle between the central axes of the proximal femoral canal and the femoral prosthesis. Angles will be classified as varus, valgus or neutral.







Evidence of radiographic failure is defined as any of the following:
	Radioluciencies greater than 50 percent of the total bone prosthesis interface
	Radiolucencies greater than 2 mm in greater than 2 zones
	Subsidence or migration of any component greater than 5 mm


RSA assessments are completed at a follow-up of post-operative (discharge), 6 months, 1, 2, and 5 years.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Radiographs will be assessed for evidence of any component failure that would result in device removal (e.g. breakage).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Radiographs will be taken postoperatively, and at 2 and 5 years following surgery.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary objective of this study is to estimate the clinical and complication rates for the Hyperion uncemented femoral stem implant. Clinical evaluations will include the Oxford Hip Score, and the Hip Disability and Osteoarthritis Outcomes Score (HOOS), and an evaluation of any adverse events including clinical and radiological underperformance. 
Information on surgery, operative site complications will be collected throughout the study at the 6 month, 1 year, 2 year and 5 year intervals. Outcomes using the Oxford Hip Score and the Hip Disability and Osteoarthritis Outcomes Score (HOOS), will be collected pre-operatively, 1 year, 2 years and 5 years following surgery.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patients will be seen at the 6 month, 1 year, 2 and 5 year interval post surgery. The Oxford Hip Questionnaire and the Hip disability and osteoarthritis outcome score (HOOS) will be collected at the 1 year, 2 year and 5 year interval.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients must meet all of the following characteristics for inclusion in the study.

1.	Patient is of legal age to consent and skeletally mature.

2.	Patient requires primary total hip arthroplasty due to non-inflammatory 	degenerative joint disease (e.g. osteoarthritis, traumatic arthritis, avascular 	necrosis, and dysplasia or developmental dysplasia of the hip (DDH)) who are candidates for an uncemented femoral 	stem as determined jointly by the surgeon and patient.

3.	Patient has met an acceptable preoperative medical clearance and is free 	from or treated for cardiac, pulmonary, haematological, etc., conditions that 	would pose excessive operative risk.

4.	Patient who understands the conditions of the study and are willing and able 	to give written informed consent to participate in the length of the study and 	prescribed follow-ups.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>95</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with any of the following characteristics must be excluded from participation in the study.

1.	Patient has active infection or sepsis (treated or untreated).

2.	Patient has any vascular insufficiency, muscular atrophy, or neuromuscular 	disease severe enough to compromise implant stability or post-operative 	recovery.

3.	Patient is female of child-bearing age and not taking contraceptive 	precautions.

4.	Patient has inadequate bone stock to support the device (e.g., severe 	osteopenia, family history of severe osteoporosis) 

5.	Patient has inflammatory joint disease (e.g., rheumatoid arthritis).

6.	Patient has known moderate to severe renal insufficiency.

7.	Patient has a known or suspected metal sensitivity.

8.	Patient is immunosuppressed with diseases such as Aquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome (AIDS) or receiving high 	doses of corticosteroids.

9.	Patient has an emotional or neurological condition that would pre-empt their 	ability or unwillingness to participate in the study including mental illness, 	intellectual disability, or drug, alcohol abuse.


10.	Patient is severely overweight. Body Mass Index ( BMI) &gt; 40.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The clinical investigator(s) or authorised delegate of the participating site will identify patients who meet the inclusion criteria. Patient enrolment is planned for an initial
period of approximately 12 months and will be performed as a consecutive case recruitment.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/10/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australian Orthopaedic Fixation Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>18 Kinkaid Ave North Plympton SA 5037</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Orthopaedic Fixation Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>18 Kinkaid Ave North Plympton SA 5037</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary objective of this study is to evaluate migration of the Hyperion 
uncemented femoral stem in primary total hip replacement using Radiostereometric Analysis (RSA). RSA will be performed at discharge, 6 months, 1 year, 2 years and 5 years following surgery</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Adelaide Health Service/Flinders University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Southern Adelaide Health Service/Flinders University
Flinders Clinical Research Ethics Committee, Room 2A 221 Flinders Medical Centre, Flinders Drive, Bedford Park SA 5042.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/10/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Adrian Blue</name>
      <address>Austofix Pty Ltd 18 Kinkaid Ave North Plympton 5037</address>
      <phone>+61(08)83510644</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>adrian.blue@austofix.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Adrian Blue</name>
      <address>Austofix Pty Ltd 18 Kinkaid Ave North Plympton 5037</address>
      <phone>+61(08)83510644</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>adrian.blue@austofix.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>