<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371735">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/10/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/11/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001537448</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Management of dental decay in young Aboriginal children</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Minimally invasive approach to manage early childhood caries in Aboriginal preschoolers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1189-1708</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NHMRC Project APP1121982</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>dental decay</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Aboriginal communities in the Kimberley region of Western Australia will be invited to participate. Communities will be randomised to intervention or control.  Children identified with dental decay in the intervention communities will be offered care in which minimally invasive approach based on the Atraumatic Restorative Treatment approach, including the Hall crown technique, will be used to provide the necessary care. Treatment will be provided by dental therapists with at least 5-years post-graduate experience to deliver ART and the Hall crowns . The ART approach will use hand instruments to remove dental decay, without the use of local analgesia, while placement of the Hall stainless steel crown will be undertaken without any tooth preparation or use of local analgesia. Any remaining at risk tooth surfaces will also be provided with a glass-ionomer fissure sealant. Treatment will be provided using portable dental equipment within community settings. The procedures are expected to take 30 minutes on each occasions while the number of occasions of treatment will vary, depending on the level of need for care. Children will also be provided with fluoride varnish applications and oral health promotion intervention by the dental therapist to the child and their carers to reduce the incidence of dental decay. The fluoride varnish, 0.25 ml of Duraphat varnish (22,600 ppm fluoride) will be applied to at risk surfaces at each checkup visit. The oral health promotion will also be delivered by dental therapists, face-to-face at recall check-ups and in group setting within the community, using the Aboriginal-specific resource kit for early childhood caries developed by the Dental Health Services (DHS), comprising flashcards on specific topics with relevant information. Face-to face intervention will take between 5-10 minutes while group sessions will be undertaken at the baseline, six-month and 12-month visit to the communities and will take approximately 45 minutes. Interested significant community members will also be provided with training and continuing support by dental therapists to undertake community oral health promotion activities, including yarning sessions with parents of newborn children, again using the DHS resource kit, based on anticipatory guidance and motivational interviewing approaches. The half-day training will involve a presentation outlining the causes of early childhood dental decay and role-play in the use of traditional "yarning" as a process of delivering information and motivating mothers/carers to change behaviour. The children will have six-monthly dental check-ups for 12 months, a total of 3 checkups, one at baseline, then at 6 months and then at 12 months; and further treatment as required will be provided at the appointments. Types of treatments provided and attendance for care will be reviewed from case-notes of the participants.</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator will be children in the communities allocated to the standard care arm of the trial, which comprise screening of children by health care workers and application of fluoride varnish to prevent dental decay. Children found to be in need of restorative care will be provided with appropriate referral for care to be delivered by local oral health care practitioners, as per the prevailing standard care pathway. The children will be reviewed for the study evaluations after 12 months, after which time the communities will be offered the option of participating in the intervention treatment as delayed intervention.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of children with dental decay successfully managed in each arm of the trial by reviewing case notes to determine the number of children referred for specialist paediatric dental care under general anaesthesia.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months post-treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in child oral health related quality of life using the Early Childhood Oral Health Impact Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change from baseline and 12 months post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dental decay increment using the International Caries Detection and Assessment System (ICDAS) by examiners masked to group allocation status.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change from baseline and 12 months post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluate the child dental anxiety by using the Modified Child Dental Anxiety Scale FACES (MCDAS) where appropriate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change from baseline and 12 months post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of dental infections from parent/carer reports and clinical case notes.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Children younger than 72 months of age with early childhood dental decay within an Aboriginal community.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>72</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Months</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Children with medical or developmental conditions requiring specialist treatment under general anaesthesia. Children with acute dental infections requiring urgent dental care.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The study is a cluster randomised trial where participating communities will be randomly allocated to intervention or control group. Group assignment will be undertaken by the central study coordinator not involved in treatment of the children.</concealment>
    <sequence>The allocation will be determined through a computer-generated random list.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The study will use a delayed intervention whereby the control group will be offered the intervention after a 12-month period. Because of the lack of access to dental care by children in Aboriginal communities, and while only children younger than 72 months of age will be evaluated within the study, all children within the community will be offered care, depending on resources availability. Masking of treatment clinicians nor study participants to the intervention will not be possible. The 12-month post-treatment evaluation will be undertaken by masked calibrated examiners.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>sample size  estimate based on recently completed study in WA, which reported a nine-fold difference in the proportion of children referred for specialist paediatric dentist care (5% vs 49%) using ART. A conservative difference in effect size of 2.5 was assumed to estimate the sample size (10% vs 25%). The intra cluster correlation was estimated from the caries experience of Aboriginal children participating in another cluster randomized trial (0.05). Using these parameters, with 15 clusters available in each arm of the trial, the estimated sample size required, at 80% power and alpha at 0.05, was 165 in each arm of the trial with 11 children per cluster. Allowing for loss to follow-up of 25%, the estimated sample size is 220 per arm of the study or 15 children per cluster.
Statistical Analysis  Data will be analysed on an intention-to-treat, and per protocol basis. Descriptive statistics will be presented and baseline variables will be compared between groups to test for fairness with respect to the randomisation. Test of proportions and logistic regression to control for potentially confounding factors will be used to assess proportion of children referred for specialist care. Changes in health utility and COHRQoL will be tested using paired (within group) and unpaired (between groups) and parametric and non-parametric tests as appropriate, and multivariate analysis using linear regression for continuous variables and Poisson regression for count variables to control for possible inter-group imbalances. Responsiveness of the COHRQoL scale will be determined by calculation of effect sizes for the scale overall and specific domains. Statistical significance will be set at alpha 0.05. All analyses will take account of the cluster design and will incorporate multi-level analyses where indicated. Multiple imputation of missing data will be further undertaken to evaluate its impact on the primary and secondary outcomes.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>30/11/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>440</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/11/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>peter arrow</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Dental Health Services
Locked Bag 15
Bentley Delivery Centre 6983
Perth, Western Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of Adelaide</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Australian Research Centre for Population Oral Health
The University of Adelaide, AUSTRALIA 5005</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Deakin University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Deakin University
Melbourne Burwood Campus, 221 Burwood Highway, Burwood, VIC 3125</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Griffith University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Griffith University (Nathan campus - N78 1.11)
170 Kessels Road
Nathan Qld 4111, Australia</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Kimberley Aboriginal Medical Services</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>12 Napier Terrace
PO Box 1377,
Broome
Western Australia, 6725</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of Western Australia</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>The University of Western Australia
35 Stirling Highway
Perth WA 6009
Australia</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Flinders University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>GPO Box 2100
Adelaide 5001, South Australia</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Murdoch University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>90 South Street, Murdoch
Western Australia 6150</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The principal aim of the proposed study is to develop, implement and evaluate a minimally invasive model of care to deliver effective primary dental services, including treatment and preventive services, to Aboriginal pre-school children. This will be compared with standard care for cost and benefits in terms of improved dental health, quality of life and reduced childhood dental anxiety.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Western Australian Aboriginal Health Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>450 Beaufort Street, Highgate
Perth WA 6003</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/08/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec> WAAHEC HREC Project Reference: 790</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Adelaide HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 4, Rundle Mall Plaza
50 Rundle Mall
Adelaide, SA, 5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/02/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H-2017-015</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Western Australia Country Health Service HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>WA Country Health Service, HREC
189 Wellington Street
Perth, WA, 6000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/08/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/01/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371735-H-2017-015 approval letter.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371735-eDoc - CO - 2017.01 Letter - Approval Letter 09082017 (ED-CO-17-4878).pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371735-WAAHEC HREC 790 Approval Letter.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>peter arrow</name>
      <address>WA Dental Health Services
Locked Bag 15
Bentley Delivery Centre 6983
Perth, Western Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 93130 600</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9313 1302</fax>
      <email>parrow@ozemail.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>peter arrow</name>
      <address>WA Dental Health Services
Locked Bag 15
Bentley Delivery Centre 6983
Perth, Western Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 93130 600</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9313 1302</fax>
      <email>parrow@ozemail.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>peter arrow</name>
      <address>WA Dental Health Services
Locked Bag 15
Bentley Delivery Centre 6983
Perth, Western Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 93130 600</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9313 1302</fax>
      <email>parrow@ozemail.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>peter arrow</name>
      <address>WA Dental Health Services
Locked Bag 15
Bentley Delivery Centre 6983
Perth, Western Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 08 93130 600</phone>
      <fax>+61 08 9313 1302</fax>
      <email>parrow@ozemail.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>