<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347755">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/11/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/11/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611001223921</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effects of different exercise intensities in chronic kidney disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of high intensity interval training on exercise capacity in patients with chronic kidney disease</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Stage 3 &amp; 4 chronic kidney disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Arm 1- high intensity interval training
Arm 2- moderate intensity continuous training
Arm 3- control group

Intervention: The study will consist of 3 groups- 2 exercise interventions and a control group. Supervised by an accredited Exercise Physiologist, the 2 exercise interventions of high intensity interval training (HIIT) and moderate continuous training (MCT) will be completed over 12 weeks. The control group will undergo usual medical practitioner care. The exercise intervention groups will complete 3 supervised training sessions per week.

The two exercise interventions will be iso-caloric meaning that the MCT group will train for longer during each session. Exercise intensities will be monitored using heart rate monitors and the peak heart rate (PHR) that will be obtained during the exercise stress test.

Exercise Intensities:
HIIT: 1:00 minute intervals (90-95%), 1:00 minute active recovery (60-70% PHR)
MCT: ~40 minutes continuous exercise (60-70% PHR)

Exercise Modalities: The modality of the equipment utilized in the exercise intervention will differ each session between 3 pieces of equipment. These will include treadmill walking/running, rowing and cycle ergometer. The high intensity interval will involve walking up a hill or running on the treadmill (depending on the persons capabilities), or changing the resistance or speed on the rower and bike.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will recieve standard treatment as provided currently by their General Practitioners and Specialists. The usual Nephrologist treatment consists of clinical care (treating kidney function, blood pressure, diabetes etc.), regular blood tests and urine analysis</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Exercise capacity measured by maximal oxygen uptake (VO2 peak)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention (3 months)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiovascular risk factors as measured by arterial stiffness and central blood pressure</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention (3 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Muscle atrophy and catabolic pathways measured by muscle biopsy</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention (3 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria:
Completion of Landmark 3 study
Aged 18-75
Stage 3 or 4 chronic kidney disease (eGFR &gt;25ml/min or &lt;60ml/min)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria:
Unable or unwilling to give informed consent
Pregnant
Life expectancy less than 6 months
Current involvement in other research studies
Organ transplant
History of significant coronary artery disease</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants who meet the eligibility criteria will be randomized into one of 3 groups: 1) high intensity interval training, 2) moderate continuous training or 3) control (1:1:1). Groups will be stratified for kidney function.  Opaque sealed envelopes will be used to conceal the allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomistaion will be conducted by a statistician not associated with the trial using a computer program to generate the random sequence.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>School of Human Movement Studies, University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Queensland
Rm. 535 Connell Building
St Lucia, 4072
QLD, Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research council (NHMRC) Centre for Clinical Research Excellence (CCRE) in Cardiovascular, Metabolic and Renal Diseases.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Exercise therapy, in particular aerobic exercise, in the CKD population has been shown to decrease cardiovascular risk factors and subsequent CVD, however there has been little work comparing the effectiveness of different exercise prescriptions. Furthermore, patients with CKD endure significant muscle wasting which greatly impacts on their ability to complete day to day activities and their quality of life. 

The primary measure will be cardiorespiratory fitness, measured as maximal oxygen uptake using expired air gas analysis during an exercise stress test. 

Additionally, although previous studies in chronic disease populations have demonstrated exercise therapy to be effective in reducing muscle wastage, the intensity of the training required for maximum benefits is still equivocal. The effects of training intensity on muscle wasting will be assessed through whole body composition dual x-ray absorptiometry. As the mechanisms of the persistent loss of muscle mass observed in patients with CKD is poorly understood, this study also aims to investigate the effects of exercise training on pathways of muscle breakdown. To investigate the mechanisms, plasma samples will be collected and muscle biopsies will be performed before and after the training.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/11/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Jeff Coombes</name>
      <address>School of Human Movement Studies
University of Queensland
Rm. 535 Connell Building
St Lucia, 4072
QLD, Australia</address>
      <phone>61 07 336-56767</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jcoombes@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kassia Weston</name>
      <address>Level 4 School of Medicine,
Building 1,
Princess Alexandra Hospital,
Ipswich Rd, Woolloongabba,
QLD, Australia 4102</address>
      <phone>61 07 3176 7650</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.weston@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>