<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370710">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/05/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/05/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000667415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of intense pulsed light therapy for dry eye relief</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of the efficacy and mechanism of action of intense pulsed light for the treatment of meibomian gland dysfunction</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1181-5488</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Meibomian gland dysfunction</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Evaporative dry eye</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Brief name: Treatment of meibomian gland dysfunction (MGD) with intense pulsed light (IPL)
Description: Eligible participants with various severities of symptomatic MGD will be recruited for the interventional study, and provided with a Participant Information Sheet. Volunteers have the opportunity to discuss any concerns with the researchers prior to signing a written consent form. Eligible participants will be required to attend at least five visits over 105 days. All products involved in the study are commercially available, and all tests performed are standard clinical procedures and will be carried out by New Zealand registered therapeutic optometrists. Research procedures will be performed at the Ocular Surface Laboratory, Department of Ophthalmology, University of Auckland, New Zealand.
In this prospective, double-masked, placebo-controlled trial, four adjacent, but overlapping IPL pulses (E-Eye IPL device, E-Swin, France) will be administered to the skin area immediately below the lower eyelid at an intensity level related to the individuals Fitzpatrick Skin Type (ranging from 9 - 13 J/cm2). IPL therapy will be administered on Day 1, Day 15, Day 45 and Day 75 as per manufacturers recommendations. The treatment duration is approximately 20 seconds per eye and this is followed by 40 minutes of standard clinical ophthalmic testing. A fifth follow-up visit is arranged on Day 105 to measure clinical outcomes only (no IPL treatment at this visit). Visits on Day 15, 45 and 75 will each take up to 45 minutes; the remaining two visits will each take approximately 80-90 minutes. The IPL therapy will be applied to both eyes of each participant, however, half the participants will be randomly assigned to receive a mock treatment. Neither the researcher collecting clinical data, nor the participant will be privy to the treatment group assignment.  </interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo treatment (neither the participant, nor the researcher collecting clinical data will have knowledge of participants assigned treatment group until study completion). For the placebo treatment, the E-Eye IPL device will be administered to the skin area immediately below the lower eyelid but no pulses will be directly applied to the area.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in non-invasive tear breakup time as measured by the Oculus Keratograph 5M.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, then on Day 15, Day 45, Day 75 and Day 105 after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in lipid layer thickness as graded from interference patterns observed on imaging by the Oculus Keratograph 5M.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, then on Day 15, Day 45, Day 75 and Day 105 after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Symptom Assessment in Dry Eye (SANDE) questionnaire score, which comprises of two questions that use a 100 mm horizontal linear visual analogue scale to quantify both severity and frequency of dry eye symptoms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, then on Day 15, Day 45, Day 75 and Day 105 after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in best spectacle corrected visual acuity (logMAR).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, then on Day 15, Day 45, Day 75 and Day 105 after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Ocular Surface Disease Index (OSDI) questionnaire score.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, then on Day 15, Day 45, Day 75 and Day 105 after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in tear meniscus height (tear fluid adjacent to the lower eyelid) will be digitally analysed to determine the exact tear meniscus height by the Oculus Keratograph 5M.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, then on Day 15, Day 45, Day 75 and Day 105 after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in bulbar conjunctival redness (redness of the white part of the eye) will be digitally analysed using a coloured image of the eye taken by the Oculus Keratograph 5M.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, then on Day 15, Day 45, Day 75 and Day 105 after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in non-contact meibography, which involves recording an image of the patients everted upper and lower eyelid using the Oculus Keratograph 5M.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and Day 105 after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in central corneal nerve density as determined by imaging with in-vivo confocal microscopy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and Day 105 after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in lid margin Demodex mite population as determined by lash epilation with slit lamp biomicroscopy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and Day 105 after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in ocular bacterial species determined by culturing eyelid margin swabs.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and Day 105 after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in lipid composition within whole tear samples, analysed by mass spectrometry.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and Day 105 after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tear osmolarity (saltiness of tear film) as measured non-invasively with the Tearlab System (Tearlab, USA).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, then on Day 15, Day 45, Day 75 and Day 105 after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ocular surface staining with lissamine green dye, observed by slit lamp biomicroscopy and graded according to the Oxford scheme.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, then on Day 15, Day 45, Day 75 and Day 105 after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ocular surface staining with fluorescein sodium dye, observed by slit lamp biomicroscopy and graded according to the Oxford scheme.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, then on Day 15, Day 45, Day 75 and Day 105 after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tear evaporation rate, assessed non-invasively with the VapoMeter (Delfin, Finland).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, then on Day 15, Day 45, Day 75 and Day 105 after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in central corneal sensitivity is assessed using validated non-contact aesthesiometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and Day 105 after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants with symptomatic dry eye caused by meibomian gland dysfunction.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Contraindications to light therapy e.g. clinical skin treatments within last two months, implants beneath the lower eyelid area, tattoos, semi-permanent make-up, or pigmented lesions in the treatment area will also be excluded from the study. Contact lens wearers must refrain from wearing contacts within one week of commencing the study, and during the study. Individuals taking prescribed photosensitising medications such as doxycycline within 3 months of study commencement.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>This study is a randomised, double-masked, placebo-controlled clinical trial. Therefore the researcher determining the participant’s eligibility, and collecting clinical outcomes will be unaware as to the treatment group allocation. The interventional treatment (IPL or placebo) will be carried out by a third party not involved in the collection of research data..</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerised random number generation to create a randomisation table onto which consecutive participant numbers will be applied.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Sham treatment in the control group will be matched as closely as possible to actual treatment, but without applying the device to the skin beneath the eyes.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Up to 100 participants will be recruited to achieve a completed sample of at least 72 (allowing for drop out). The sample size is based on results collected from previous pilot study (Craig et al, 2015).  Power calculations show that a minimum of 36 subjects is required, to detect a clinically significant difference of 1 lipid layer grade, in pairwise comparisons, with 80% power (beta = 0.2), and at a two-sided statistical significance level of 5% (a = 0.05). The SD of normal values was estimated at 1 lipid layer grade. Sample size estimates were determined using a uniform non-parametric adjustment, with PASS 2002 (NCSS Statistical Software LLC, Utah, USA).. Post IPL scores at Day 1, 15, 45, and 75 will be compared to pre-IPL scores at baseline. Repeated measures analysis will be utilised to compare data across the various time points and paired analyses to compare pre- and post-IPL data at individual time points. Variables will be tested for normality using the Kolmogarav-Smirnoff test. Ordinal variables and those with non-normal distributions will be analysed with Friedman two-way analysis of variance, with pairwise Wilcoxon (paired) or Mann-Whitney (non-paired) post-hoc testing as required. Normally distributed continuous data will be assessed with a repeated measures two-way ANOVA with Tukeys HSD post-hoc testing. Differences between treated and non-treated participant data will be compared with the paired samples t-test and the Wilcoxon signed-rank test for parametric and nonparametric data, respectively. Correlations between parametric and nonparametric data will be assessed with Pearsons product-moment correlation or Spearmans rank order correction, respectively. Outcomes will be considered significant if p&lt;0.05.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/05/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Auckland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Auckland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>E-Swin</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>34 RUE BRUNEL
75017 Paris</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>France</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Dry eye is a widespread disease that can affect individuals of any age. People who suffer from this condition frequently complain of irritated, burning and gritty eyes. A common reason for this is a reduction of the tear film lipid layer due to the eyelid glands malfunctioning (meibomian gland dysfunction). Intense pulsed light (IPL) therapy conventionally used to treat facial pigmentation has been found serendipitously to provide dry eye relief in meibomian gland dysfunction (MGD). A prospective trial of IPL for the treatment of MGD by the lead investigators team confirmed significant improvements. On account of our previous research in this area, we are conducting an evaluation on the effectiveness of IPL for the relief of evaporative dry eye. The study aims to provide more information about the management of MGD, so that optometrists and ophthalmologists can improve clinical decisions in practice. We are recruiting up to 100 participants with symptoms of dry eye; the study will be carried out by New Zealand registered optometrists in the Department of Ophthalmology at the University of Auckland. Participants will attend at least five visits, over a period of 105 days (15 weeks). Three of the visits will each take up to 45 minutes, and the remaining two will each take approximately 80-90 minutes. The E-Eye IPL device used in this study will be applied to the skin area below the eyes; it is a commercially available and medically certified product, applied according to manufacturer's instructions. The procedures performed are all standard clinical tests.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Auckland Human Participants Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/05/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>017173</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/04/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Jennifer P Craig</name>
      <address>Department of Ophthalmology
The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+6499238173</phone>
      <fax>+6493677173</fax>
      <email>jp.craig@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Jennifer P Craig</name>
      <address>Department of Ophthalmology
The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+6499238173</phone>
      <fax>+6493677173</fax>
      <email>jp.craig@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Jennifer P Craig</name>
      <address>Department of Ophthalmology
The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+6499238173</phone>
      <fax>+6493677173</fax>
      <email>jp.craig@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Jennifer P Craig</name>
      <address>Department of Ophthalmology
The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+6499238173</phone>
      <fax>+6493677173</fax>
      <email>jp.craig@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>