<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370068">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/02/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/02/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000233426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>INtegrated combination Therapy, Electronic General practice support tool, phaRmacy led intervention And combination Therapy Evaluation (INTEGRATE): An integrated general practice and pharmacy-based intervention to promote the prescription and use of appropriate preventive medications among individuals at high cardiovascular risk</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>INTEGRATE Study: A pragmatic cluster randomised controlled trial of an integrated general practice and pharmacy-based intervention to promote the prescription and use of appropriate preventive medications among individuals at high cardiovascular risk.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>INTEGRATE</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cardiovascular disease and their risk factors
</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other public health</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Using a randomised controlled trial design, 70 Australian General Practice and Pharmacy pairs (35 intervention and 35 control) will be recruited. Each GP/Pharmacy pair in the intervention group will be exposed to three interventions (HealthTracker, CVD polypills and PASS). Each GP/pharmacy pair in the intervention arm will be encouraged to continue with the intervention 18 months from the time the last practice is recruited (based on results from the TORPEDO study1). At the end of this period, data will be collected from the GP/Pharmacy pairs in both study arms. 
1 Peiris D, Usherwood T, Panaretto K, Harris M, Hunt J, Redfern J, et al. Effect of a Computer-Guided, Quality Improvement Program for Cardiovascular Disease Risk Management in Primary Health Care: The Treatment of Cardiovascular Risk Using Electronic Decision Support Cluster-Randomized Trial. Circulation: Cardiovascular Quality and Outcomes. 2015; 8(1): 87-95.

The integrated intervention comprises of the following three elements: (1) HealthTracker, (2) availability of the Polypills and (3)Pharmacy Adherence Support Service (PASS).

(1) HealthTracker is an electronic decision support tool that aims to assist general practitioners in the management of cardiovascular disease (CVD) risk. It aims to promote best practice care by giving management advice to health care providers based on national guidelines. HealthTracker incorporates a single, extensively validated screening and management algorithm, based on a synthesis of recommendations from several guidelines for CVD, kidney disease and diabetes prevention and management. HealthTracker interfaces with Medical Director (MD) and Best Practice (BP), two clinical practice software systems that together comprise around 80% of general practice record systems in Australia. Data from the patient records in MD or BP pre-populate HealthTracker which then provides the GP point-of-care recommendations on optimal use of CVD risk preventive medications (including option of polypill), based on that patients absolute CVD risk estimate.

(2). Eight CVD polypills will be available and they are: 
(i) Name: PolyPill Hydrotelmi; Components: Telmisartan (40mg) + hydrochlorothiazide (12.5mg) + rosuvastatin (10mg)
(ii) Name: PolyPill Hydrotelmi Asp; Components: Telmisartan (40mg) + hydrochlorothiazide (12.5mg) + rosuvastatin (10mg)  + aspirin (100mg)
(iii) Name: PolyPill Amtelmi; Components: Telmisartan (40mg)  + amlodipine (5mg) + rosuvastatin (10mg)
(iv) Name: PolyPill Amtelmi Asp; Components: Telmisartan (40mg)  + amlodipine (5mg) + rosuvastatin (10mg) + aspirin (100mg)
(v) Name: PolyPill Perindap; Components: Perindopril (4mg) + indapamide (1.25mg) + atorvastatin (40mg
(vi) Name: PolyPill Perindap Asp; Components: Perindopril (4mg) + indapamide (1.25mg) + atorvastatin (40mg) + aspirin (100mg)
(vii) Name: PolyPill Peramlo; Components: Perindopril (4mg) + amlodipine (5mg) + atorvastatin (40mg)
(viii) Name: PolyPill Peramlo Asp; Components:Perindopril (4mg) + amlodipine (5mg) + atorvastatin (40mg) + aspirin (100mg)

(3) Pharmacy Adherence Support Service (PASS): This intervention involves supporting patients with their medication journey by a trained pharmacist. Patients who have been prescribed a Polypill or a new CVD preventative medication will be referred by the GP to a partner Pharmacist who will firstly administer the 7 item Adherence to Refills and Medications Scale (ARMS-7) for assessing medication adherence in patients presenting with new CVD preventative medication prescriptions. A score of greater than 7 indicates unsatisfactory adherence to their medication regimen and the patient is recommended to participate in PASS. PASS, is a customised adherence program which involves a structured clinical interview (approximately 20 minutes) focused on: (i) understanding how the patient actually uses their medications; (ii) understanding patient beliefs about their medications; and (iii) capturing patient-reported barriers to adherence. The structured interview is based on a modified version of the Brief Medication Questionnaire 1 (BMQ1), which will be used to systematically review and collect adherence data. Depending on the individualised recommendations, pharmacists may see enrolled patients at approximately 2 weeks (telephone discussion, 5 minutes), and during scheduled pharmacy visits at approximately 1, 3, 6 and 12 months after enrolment, to coincide with prescription re-fills (patients may however present each month for a regular re-fill of their medications). Adherence issues and barriers to medication taking will be reviewed at each visit (10 minutes). An electronic software (PASS Application) has been developed to deliver the ARMS-7 and the PASS via a Tablet/Ipad provided to Pharmacists.

The use of HealthTracker will be monitored centrally by the research team. The use of PASS will be monitored by Project Officers who will contact and visit pharmacies regularly. Fidelity measures (e.g. number of times a recommendation was clicked or the PASS intervention was delivered) will be collected throughout the study. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>General Practices allocated to the control arm will continue usual practice with their current systems and without access to the integrated intervention.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of high-risk patients who were not on full treatment at baseline achieving recommended target (i) BP and (ii) LDL-C target levels, at the end of the study. This is a composite primary outcome. These levels will be extracted from the general practice software systems using a general practice data auditing tool known as Clinical Audit Tool (CAT). Data is de-identified prior to extraction. 

Definitions:
- High CVD risk: either (i)  history of CVD (diagnosis of coronary heart disease, ischaemic stroke, peripheral vascular disease); (ii) presence of any guideline-stipulated clinically high risk conditions (diabetes and age greater than 60 years, diabetes and albuminuria, stage3B chronic kidney disease (CKD), or extreme risk factor elevations - systolic BP greater than or equal to 180mmHg, diastolic BP greater than or equal to 110 mmHg, total cholesterol  greater than 7.5 mmol);  or (3) a calculated 5-year CVD risk of  greater than 15% using the 1991 Anderson Framingham equation. In the TORPEDO study, this comprised 27% of the study population. 

- BP and LDL-C target levels: BP less than or equal to 140/90 mmHg in general or people with CKD; less than or equal to 130/80 mmHg in all people with diabetes; less than or equal to 130/80 mmHg if albuminuria (UACR greater than 2.5 mg/mmol in men and greater than 3.5 mg/m in women); and LDL-C less then 2.0 mmol/L in all high risk individuals.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At end of study (when a median of 18 months follow-up has ended).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1. Proportion of high-risk patients who were not on full treatment at
baseline achieving recommended target BP levels at study end;
Note: not composite. Data for will be extracted from the general practice software systems using CAT. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At end of study (when a median of 18 months follow-up has ended).
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2. Proportion of under-treated high-risk patients achieving recommended BP or LDL-C targets. Note: not composite. Data will be extracted from the general practice software systems using CAT. Under-treated includes patients at high risk of a CV event, not on full treatment at baseline. Full treatment: at least 1 BP-lowering drug and a statin for patients without established CVD; for those with CVD, full treatment will additionally require at least 1 antiplatelet drug.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At end of study (when a median of 18 months follow-up has ended).
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3. Proportion of all high-risk patients achieving BP and LDL-C targets. Data will be extracted from the general practice software systems using CAT. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At end of study (when a median of 18 months follow-up has ended).
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>4. Proportion of patients achieving BP and LDL-C targets and prescribed antiplatelet (if relevant).  Data will be extracted from the general practice software systems using CAT. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At end of study (when a median of 18 months follow-up has ended).
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>5. Risk factor measurement and mean levels. Data will be extracted from the general practice software systems using CAT. Risk factor measurement is calculated by HealthTracker. High CVD risk is defined as either (i) history of CVD (diagnosis of coronary heart disease, ischaemic stroke, peripheral vascular disease); (ii) presence of any guideline-stipulated clinically high risk conditions (diabetes and age greater than 60 years, diabetes and albuminuria, stage3B chronic kidney disease (CKD), or extreme risk factor elevations - systolic BP greater than or equal to 180mmHg, diastolic BP greater than or equal to 110 mmHg, total cholesterol greater than 7.5 mmol);  or (3) a calculated 5-year CVD risk of  greater than 15% using the 1991 Anderson Framingham equation. In the TORPEDO study, this comprised 27% of the study population. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At end of study (when a median of 18 months follow-up has ended).
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>6. Treatment intensity in high-risk patients. Proportion of high-risk patients who receive a dose escalation or addition to their prescribed medication during the intervention period. De-identified data will be extracted from the general practice software systems using CAT.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At end of study (when a median of 18 months follow-up has ended).
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>7. Polypill prescriptions - will be assessed from the number of consent forms signed for the polypill and the supply of polypills. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At end of study (when a median of 18 months follow-up has ended).
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>8. Participation in pharmacy adherence support programs. Will be assessed from the number of consent forms for the PASS. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At end of study (when a median of 18 months follow-up has ended).
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>9. Proportion of non-high risk patients receiving either BP lowering or statin and or anti-platelet therapy (looking at all the therapies individually and combined). Assessed by the number of new BP lowering, statin and anti-platelet medication prescriptions in non-high risk patients.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At end of study (when a median of 18 months follow-up has ended).
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>General Practice eligibility:
1. Not currently or previously involved in other studies using HealthTracker (e.g. TORPEDO, Q-Pulse).
2. Use of either Medical Director or Best Practice for electronic health record (EHR) management.
3. Exclusive use of these systems to record risk factors and prescribe drugs.
4. Agreement that a majority of GPs and other designated staff are willing to use the integrated intervention.
5. Agreement to encourage patients to fill prescriptions at a designated partner pharmacy and consider enrolment in the pharmacy adherence program.

Pharmacy eligibility:
1. Agreement to stock and dispense the polypill formulations.
2. Agreement to conduct the pharmacy adherence program.

Patient eligibility:
1. All adult patients (18 years) attending the GP will be potentially be eligible to receive the HealthTracker intervention.
2. All adult patients who are recommended for the component medications according to current guidelines are eligible to be prescribed the polypill therapy.
3. All adult patients attending the paired pharmacy with a new prescription for a CVD prevention medication (either for an existing medication or a new medication), from the partner GP, will be eligible to receive the pharmacy intervention.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>General practice:
1. Involved in other studies using HealthTracker (eg:TORPEDO, CONNECT)
2. Not using either Medical Director or Best Practice

Pharmacy:
1. Unwilling to stock and dispense the polypill formulation
2. Unwilling to conduct PASS</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Using a cluster randomised controlled design, health services will be centrally randomised using a web-based platform.</concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted block randomisation</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Randomisation of 70 practices (35 per arm) will provide 90% power (2a=0.05) with a mean cluster size of 60 to detect:
1.	Relative risk of  greater than or equal to 1.15 in the proportion achieving BP targets for intervention vs. usual care. This assumes an ICC=0.03 and 55% of relevant patients from usual care practices will have BP levels at or below target by the end of follow-up.
2.	Relative risk of greater than or equal to 1.25 in the proportion achieving LDL-C targets for intervention vs. usual care. This assumes an ICC=0.05 and 40% of relevant patients from usual care practices will have LDL-C levels at or below target by the end of follow-up.
3.	Relative risk of greater than or equal to 1.35 in the proportion achieving BP and LDL-C targets for intervention vs. control. This assumes an ICC=0.02 and 14% of relevant patients from usual care practices will have BP and LDL-C levels at or below target by the end of follow-up.
Patient-level data analysis will be used performed on an intention-to-treat basis using generalised estimating equations with an exchangeable correlation structure to account for clustering of patients within services. The population for the primary analyses will be the cohort of eligible patients whose health record data are extracted at both randomisation and end-of-study periods.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>4200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/12/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The George Institute of Global Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 10, King George V (KGV) Building,
Missenden Rd
Camperdown NSW 2050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 5
20 Allara St
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>The University of Sydney</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>The University of Sydney
NSW 2006
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Despite the strength of evidence about the benefits of medicines for the prevention of cardiovascular events, particularly in those at high-risk, there are substantial evidence-practice gaps. This study will test the hypothesis that an integrated intervention combining three evidence based approaches: (1) a CVD polypill (fixed dose-combination of generic blood pressure lowering and lipid modifying, with or without antiplatelet drugs), (2) a GP focused point-of-care electronic decision support and (3) a pharmacy-led medication adherence intervention will increase prescription and long-term use of recommended medications, leading to improvements in CVD risk factor levels compared to usual care. This will be done using a pragmatic cluster randomised control trial of 70 general medical practices.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The University of Sydney
NSW 2006
Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/11/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2015/616</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/04/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Anushka Patel</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health Level 10, King George V (KGV)
Building Missenden Rd Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9993 4500</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9993 4501</fax>
      <email>apatel@georgeinstitute.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Anushka Patel</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health Level 10, King George V (KGV)
Building Missenden Rd Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9993 4500</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9993 4501</fax>
      <email>apatel@georgeinstitute.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Anushka Patel</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health Level 10, King George V (KGV)
Building Missenden Rd Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9993 4500</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9993 4501</fax>
      <email>apatel@georgeinstitute.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Anushka Patel</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health Level 10, King George V (KGV)
Building Missenden Rd Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9993 4500</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9993 4501</fax>
      <email>apatel@georgeinstitute.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>