<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372369">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/02/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/03/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000447358</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparison of the efficacy of rehabilitation robotics in gait rehabilitation in patients with multiple sclerosis.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparison of the efficacy of rehabilitation robotics as the Lokomat and the Exosceleton EKSO GT in gait rehabilitation in patients with multiple sclerosis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>multiple sclerosis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>gait limitations</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>postural control</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>fatigue</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>muscle strength</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Multiple sclerosis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>People with multiple sclerosis will participate in the study. 
The main objective of the study is the comparison of effectiveness the gait rehabilitation with the use of a lower body exoskeleton EKSO GT with Variable Assist software extension (EKSO Bionics, Richmond, CA, USA) and Robot-Assisted Treadmill Therapy (Lokomat, Hocoma, Volketswil, Switzerland). The assessment will be undertaken before program and after 3 weeks of training with EKSO GT and Lokomat.  All measurement procedures will be performed by members of the research team. Participants who meet eligibility requirements will be randomly divided into group with EKSO (n=18) and group with Lokomat (n=18). Each patient will participate in 15 training sessions with using EKSO GT. 
Each patient's training will last 3 weeks, 5 times a week (form Monday to Friday). Time of each training session is - from 45 to 60 minutes.
Robotic gait training in both groups will be conducted by a physiotherapist who is not participating neither in a basic survey nor in a control test. Training parameters for each patient will be individually tailored by the physiotherapist. The duration of each training session will depend on the patient walking capabilities. Participation in the training is confirmed in medical records.
Participants from both groups will implement a standard rehabilitation program.
Physiotherapists who conduct the trainings, are certified EKSO and Lokomat
specialists. Each training session in Ekso GT and Lokomat will be stored in software 
and recorded in patient's medical documentation. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Members of the control group will undergo the training on Robot-Assisted Treadmill Therapy  Lokomat. The gait speed will be adjusted to the patients individual abilities. The amount of body weight support will not exceed 10% of patients body weight. Lokomat gait training time- 45 to 60 minutes. Number of trainings- 15, 3 weeks (form Monday to Friday). Alongside the treadmill training, the control group will also undergo a daily rehabilitation program, including 90 minutes of excersise therapy.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in muscular strength assessed by isokinetic dynamometer during knee flexion-extension (Biodex System 4 Pro, Biodex Medical Systems Inc. USA)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, before program and after 3 weeks treatment with Ekso GT or Lokomat</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in balance assessed by baropodometric platform (Zebris FDM-S, Zebris Medical GmbH, Germany). Stabilometric evaluation of quiet standing (eyes open/eyes closed), weight bearing during quiet standing</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, before program and after 3 weeks treatment with Ekso Gt or Lokomat</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluation of the spatial-temporal gait parameters by BTS G-Walk system (BTS Bioengineering). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, before program and after 3 weeks treatment with Ekso Gt or Lokomat</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in gait speed assessed by timed 25-foot walk test (T25FWT)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, before program and after 3 weeks treatment with Ekso Gt or Lokomat</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in muscular strength assessed by isokinetic dynamometer during shoulders internal and external rotation (Biodex System 4 Pro, Biodex Medical Systems Inc. USA)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, before program and after 3 weeks treatment with Ekso Gt or Lokomat</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fatigue assessed by Fatigue Severity Scale (FSS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, before program and after 3 weeks treatment with Ekso Gt or Lokomat</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dynamic balance will be assessed by the Timed Up and Go Test and the choice stepping reaction time test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, before program and after 3 weeks treatment with Ekso Gt or Lokomat</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Balance assessed via the Berg Balance Scale (BBS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, before program and after 3 weeks treatment with Ekso Gt or Lokomat</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants with Multiple Sclerosis,
Expanded Disability Status Scale (EDSS) 6,0-7,0</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Difference in lower limbs length bigger then 2 cm
Weight above 100 kg
Height lower then 150 cm or above 190 cm
History of significant problems with skin breakdown or current skin breakdown that would prevent subject from wearing the device
Joint contractures of the hip, knee, or ankle that might limit normal ROM during ambulation
Medical issue that precludes full weight bearing and ambulation (e.g. orthopedic injuries, pain, severe osteoporosis, or severe spasticity)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a computer generated from an external web-based randomisation service.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>2-arm trial</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/04/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>23/06/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>36</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>14/07/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Podkarpackie</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Rzeszow</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Rzeszow
Aleja Rejtana 16c
35-959 Rzeszow</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Poland</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Rzeszow</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of Rzeszow
Aleja Rejtana 16c
35-959 Rzeszow</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Poland</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National MS Rehabilitation Center in Dabek</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>DABEK 129
06-561 STUPSK MAZOWIECKI 
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Poland</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The limitation of the possibility of efficient and independent movement is one of the major problems among people with MS. The optimal level of locomotion is also a balance, strength and endurance. They allow the safe and efficient movement. The robots are often used in rehabilitation of people with neurological diseases especially with severe symptoms and significantly limitation ability to walk. So far, only few studies were conducted using the Lokomat in gait rehabilitation among the patients with MS as well as there are a few studies evaluating the effects of gait rehabilitation using the walking robots. There are no studies comparing these two types of robots. The main objective of the study is to compare of effectiveness the gait rehabilitation in patients with MS with the use of two kind of robots: lower body exoskeleton EKSO GT and Assisted Treadmill Therapy (Lokomat). The survey will be conducted in a specialized rehabilitation center. The study will include patients with MS (EDSS 6 do 7). The study will include 36 patients who will be randomly divided into two groups. Study group (n=18) which will practice using Ekso GT and control group which will practice using Lokomat. Both groups will have 15 training sessions during 3 weeks. The time of each training session will last from 45 to 60 minutes. An assessment of the patients will be carried out before the start of the program and after its completion. The gait (speed, cadence), static and dynamic balance, muscle strength of upper and lower extremities and the level of fatigue will be evaluated. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Ethical Committee of Regional Medical Chamber in Krakow</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>ul. Krupnicza 11a
31-123 Krakow</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/12/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>173/KBL/OIL/2015</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/10/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Poland</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mariusz Druzbicki</name>
      <address>University of Rzeszow
Institute of Physiotherapy
Warszawska st. 26a
35-205 Rzeszow</address>
      <phone>+48178721941</phone>
      <fax>+48178721930</fax>
      <email>mdruzb@ur.edu.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mariusz Druzbicki</name>
      <address>University of Rzeszow
Institute of Physiotherapy
Warszawska st. 26a
35-205 Rzeszow</address>
      <phone>+48178721941</phone>
      <fax>+48178721930</fax>
      <email>mdruzb@ur.edu.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mariusz Druzbicki</name>
      <address>University of Rzeszow
Institute of Physiotherapy
Warszawska st. 26a
35-205 Rzeszow</address>
      <phone>+48178721941</phone>
      <fax>+48 8721930</fax>
      <email>mdruzb@ur.edu.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>