<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336554">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/04/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/05/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000486921</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The PASS study: A performance assessment system for success in residential aged care</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Performance assessment system for success (PASS) in residential aged care</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>The PASS trial</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Quality of care</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Three monthly benchmarking information for selected quality indicators provided at month six then three monthly to month 15 to both arms of the study. In addition  quality improvment activites interventions were provided to the intervention arm including: one individual site visit by an advanced practice gerontological nurse to explain the benchmarking; how the results could be used to improve resident outcomes and provide support with the intervention; a best practice quality tool kit for the prevention harm; voiced over power point education sessions of best practice in the prevention of harm that could be used at any time by facility staff and  two quality forums by telephone conferencing. the intervention was implemented after six months of data collection over a three month period. The resources provided were designed to be able to be used by the hospital over the final 6 months of the study as well</interventions>
    <comparator>Three monthly benchmarking information for selected quality indicators provided at month 6, 9,12 and 15. Quality indicator for fall, pressure ulcers, restraint use, urinary tract infections and indwelling urinary catheters was analysed using means for each facility and graphed. The three monthly benchmarking reports were placed on the password protected website for ease of access by the facilities. The facilites identified their data by their confidential research ID. All particpants were able to access webiste for the benckmarking reports. 
At months 6 and 15 staffing hours per resident per day for all direct care staff were benchmarked and a Shortells staff survey was also benchmarked at months 6 and 15.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction in adverse outcomes for the residents in residential aged care hospitals from pre to post intervention as measure by significance for the quality improvement activities group measured at individual resident level</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months pre intervention of data collection, 3 months intervention and 6 months post intervention of data collection</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction in adverse outcomes for the residents in residential aged care hospitals from pre to post intervention as measure by significance for the benchmarking measured at individual resident level</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months pre intervention of data collection, 3 months intervention and 6 months post intervention of data collection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All RAC providers that were listed as a hospital from the Northland, Waitemata, Auckland, Counties Manukau, Waikato, and the Bay of Plenty District Health Boards on the Ministry of Health certification list, June 2008  and held an Age Related Residential Care  Service Provider Agreement with their local District Health Board and provided continuing hopsital level care.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Continuing care Hospitals operated by District Health Boards were excluded as they have additional funding streams and different case mix.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Continuing care hospitals were recruited, rather than individual residents, as the intervention was focused on influencing the actions of staff in caring out care processes provided to residents. To ensure that the sampling frame was as large as possible it was decided to invite all 137 eligible continuing hospitals to participate. once recruitment was completed and consents were obtained  blinding of researchers  to allocation status was achieved by providing a biostatistician with the participants’ research numbers and the number of beds in each facility and she  undertook the process of cluster randomisation</concealment>
    <sequence>Cluster randomisation was used to achieve a probability sampling strategy that involved successive random sampling of the hospitals progressing from large to small in bed numbers. Cluster sampling requires computing the mean for the individual sampling unit and multiplying this by the number of units in the population to determine the population's estimated value. The precision limit on this estimate was also be computed.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Auckland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The School of Nursing
Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences
The University of Auckland 
Private Bag 92019
Auckland Mail Centre 1142, New Zealand</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Auckland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The School of Nursing
Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences
The University of Auckland 
Private Bag 92019
Auckland Mail Centre 1142, New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study seeks to identify how providers of hospital level residential aged care can improve their performance in keeping residetns free from harm. This will be achieved by gaining an understanding of good outcomes for residents and what measures these outcomes, then using selected quality indicators to measure the quality of basic care provided to indivdual residents. The study will establish if benchmarking quality indicator data alone or whether additional quality improvement activities support increases the number of days residents are free from harm or and adverse event. Finally this information will be utilised to develop a balanced score card for success.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>New Zealand Ministry of Health Multi-Regional Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>c/- Ministry of Health
1-3 The Terrace
Level 1
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/05/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>MEC/08/16/EXP</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/04/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Noeline Whitehead</name>
      <address>1/38 Tawhiri Rd
One Tree Hill
Auckland 1061</address>
      <phone>64 9 6366296</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>noels.home@xtra.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Noeline Whitehead</name>
      <address>1/38 Tawhiri Rd
One Tree Hill
Auckland 1061</address>
      <phone>64 9 6366296</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>noels.home@xtra.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Noeline Whitehead</name>
      <address>1/38 Tawhiri Rd
One Tree Hill
Auckland 1061</address>
      <phone>64 9 6366296</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>noels.home@xtra.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>