<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320917">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/05/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/06/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000439044</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effects of a physiotherapy program on pain and physical function in individuals with hip joint osteoarthritis.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effects of a physiotherapy program on pain and physical function in individuals with hip joint osteoarthritis: a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hip osteoarthritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A multimodal physiotherapy program, involving manual therapy, exercise and advice, delivered by experienced musculoskeletal Physiotherapists. There will be 10 treatment sessions over 12 weeks. The initial two sessions are 45 minutes each with subsequent sessions 30 minutes each. In order not to unblind potential participants, we are unable to provide a description of the physiotherapy program.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants allocated to the sham physiotherapy group will receive realistic 'sham' physiotherapy treatment (inactive ultrasound and inert gel) that does not address the modifiable impairments seen in hip osteoarthritis. There will be 10 treatment sessions over 12 weeks. The initial two sessions are 45 minutes each with subsequent sessions 30 minutes each. In order not to unblind potential participants, we are unable to provide a description of the sham physiotherapy program.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome will be hip pain measured using visual analog scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be administered at baseline, 12 weeks and 9 months (6 months post treatment).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self report physical function- Western Ontario and McMasters Universities (WOMAC) Osteoarthritis Index</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be administered at baseline, 12 weeks and 9 months (6 months post treatment).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health-related quality of life- The Assessment of Quality of Life (AQoL) instrument.</outcome>
      <timepoint>These will be administered at baseline, 12 weeks and 9 months (6 months post treatment).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participant perceived response to treatment (change in pain and physical function) on a 7 point ordinal scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>These will be administered at 12 weeks and 9 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Range of motion of the hip internal rotators, external rotators, abductors, flexors and extensors measured with a goniometer and averaged over two repetitions. Strength of the hip internal rotators, external rotators, abductors, flexors and extensors measured with a hand held force transducer with the best of two repetitions taken. Strength of the quadriceps and hamstrings measured with Isokinetic dynamometer, with the best of two repetitions taken. Functional tests, which include the Step Test (number of steps completed in 15 seconds), the time to ascend and descend a series of 5 steps (average of 2 repetitions), the number of times a person can stand-up and sit back down in 30 seconds, the Four Square Step Test which is the time taken to step feet in 4 separate squares clockwise and then anti-clockwise (average of two repetitions) and the time taken to walk 20m in a straight line (average of two repetitions). Gait analyses will also be performed using infrared cameras and force plates to obtain kinetic and kinematic gait data.</outcome>
      <timepoint>These will be administered at baseline and at 12 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity levels as measured by the Physical Activity Scale for the Elderly (PASE) questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>These will be administered at baseline, 12 weeks and 9 months (6 months post treatment).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse effects by use of open ended questions asked by physiotherapists and by the project examiner. Possible adverse events include delayed onset muscle soreness or increased hip pain.</outcome>
      <timepoint>These will be administered at 12 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Success of blinding- participants will nominate participant's group allocation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>These will be administered at 12 weeks and 9 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Direct health care costs, as measured by a recall questionnaire of all use of health professionals, medical tests, medications, professional home care and hospitalisation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>These will be administered monthly from baseline for 9 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Daily number of steps using a pedometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>These will be administered at baseline, 12 weeks and 9 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>People with hip osteoarthritis aged greater than 50 years fulfilling American College of Rheumatology classification criteria and reporting average hip pain &gt;3 on visual analogue scale (to ensure a minimal level of pain) will be recruited. Hip osteoarthritis (OA) is defined as pain in the groin or hip region on most days of the past month, in addition to joint space narrowing and femoral or acetabular osteophytes on x-ray.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>The exclusion criteria are: (i) hip surgery within 6 months; (ii) awaiting hip joint replacement surgery due to the length of followup; (iii) current or past (within 3 months) oral or intra-articular corticosteroid use; (iv) systemic arthritic conditions; (v) history of hip or knee joint replacement or osteotomy; (vi) symptomatic knee OA or other muscular, joint or neurological condition affecting lower limb function; (vii) physiotherapy treatment or exercises specifically for hip and trunk in past 6 months; (viii) inability to walk unaided; (ix) unable to comply with protocol.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Project Examiner A will conduct preliminary screening over the phone. A standardised hip x-ray will then be obtained. This will be used to determine eligibility and to grade osteoarthritis severity. Baseline testing will be performed following which the participant will be randomised into one of two groups: (i) physiotherapy or (ii) sham physiotherapy. The randomisation schedule will be prepared by the study biostatistician. To conceal randomisation, consecutively numbered, sealed, opaque envelopes will be used and maintained centrally. The envelopes will be kept in a locked location accessible only by a research administrator.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be by random permuted blocks stratified according to therapist (to control for therapist variation).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/05/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>128</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>3053</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Melbourne, School of Physiotherapy</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>200 Berkeley St Carlton VIC 3053</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1 16 Marcus Clarke Street Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project primarily aims to investigate the efficacy of a physiotherapy program to treat hip joint osteoarthritis. Secondary aims are to assess changes in relevant musculoskeletal impairments with treatment, maintenance of treatment effects over 6 months and the cost-effectiveness of physiotherapy.
Primary hypothesis:
A 12-week multimodal physiotherapy program will result in significantly greater improvements in pain and physical function than sham physiotherapy immediately post-treatment in individuals with hip OA.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Melbourne VIC 3010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>0932812.1</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>13/11/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kim Bennell</name>
      <address>Centre for Health, Exercise and Sports Medicine
School of Physiotherapy
The University of Melbourne
Victoria
Australia 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 4135</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 8344 3771</fax>
      <email>k.bennell@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kim Bennell</name>
      <address>Centre for Health, Exercise and Sports Medicine
School of Physiotherapy
The University of Melbourne
Victoria
Australia 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 4135</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 8344 3771</fax>
      <email>k.bennell@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Fiona McManus</name>
      <address>Centre for Health, Exercise and Sports Medicine
School of Physiotherapy
The University of Melbourne
Victoria
Australia 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 0426</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 8344 3771</fax>
      <email>fmcmanus@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>