<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373736">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/09/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/10/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001404314p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Accelerometer-based facilitated walking program in addition to usual care for the management of patients with low back pain at medium or high risk of chronicity: a randomised controlled trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Accelerometer-based facilitated walking program in addition to usual care for the management of patients with low back pain at medium or high risk of chronicity: a randomised controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Low Back Pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants in the experimental group will receive a Fitbit walking intervention provided by the investigators in addition to usual physiotherapy care provided by their treating physiotherapist. 
During the baseline period, participants will be requested to wear a physical activity monitor (Axivity AX3) for seven continuous days, to measure the total number of habitual walking steps per week. The baseline average daily walking steps for participants will be calculated by dividing the total number of habitual walking steps per week by seven (total walking steps per week/7). During the intervention each participants average daily walking steps will be progressed each week by a minimum 10%. To comply with current physical activity guidelines, participants will be asked to walk the prescribed number of steps at a moderate intensity (i.e. brisk walking, 100 step/min). Participants will be asked to partake in the prescribed walking program at least five days per week for 8 weeks. 
Participants in the experimental group will receive a Fitbit Flex wearable device and will attend a training session delivered by the investigator to: 1) install and set up the Fitbit wearable device and account, 2) register the participant in the 10,000 Steps website and synchronise the device with the Fitbit account, and 3) provided with instructions of using the device and account including monitoring step counts as well as other features. Additionally, participants will receive a handbook detailing all of the instructions provided from the training session. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants allocated in the control group will receive usual physiotherapy care provided by their treating physiotherapist. Also, they will be given instructions to maintain their usual physical activity level during the treatment period. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disability.
Disability will be measured by the modified Oswestry Disability Index.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention, follow-up (week 26)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain.
Pain intensity will be measured by the Visual Analogue Scale .</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention, follow-up (week 26)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Habitual physical activity level. 
Habitual physical activity level in both groups will be measured objectively by Axivity AX3 (Newcastle upon Tyne, UK; product website: http://axivity.com/product/ax3) for seven continuous days.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention, follow-up (week 26)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Daily walking steps. 
Daily walking steps in both groups will be measured objectively by Axivity AX3 (Newcastle upon Tyne, UK; product website: http://axivity.com/product/ax3) for seven continuous days.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention, follow-up (week 26)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>
Depression.
Depression will be measured by Beck Depression Inventory. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention, follow-up (week 26)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain catastrophising.
Participants experience of pain will be measured by Pain Catastrophising Scale. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention, follow-up (week 26)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fear of movement.
Fear of movement will be measured by Tampa Scale for Kinesiophobia. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention, follow-up (week 26)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be included in this study if they:
1)	are diagnosed by physiotherapist with non-specific LBP;
2)	are aged 18 years or over;
3)	are categorized as being at medium or high risk of chronicity using STarT Back Screening Tool;
4)	are classified as physically inactive (those who engage in  less than 150 minutes/week of moderate intensity, or  less than 75 minutes/week of vigorous intensity or an equivalent combination of the two intensities of physical activity as determined by International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ);
5)	are ready and able to participate in physical activity  as determined by The Physical Activity Readiness Questionnaire (PAR-Q). Those deemed  not fit  to participate in physical activity by the PAR-Q or aged over 69 years, will need a clearance from their medical practitioner before engaging in physical activity;
6)	have internet access.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants will be excluded if they have any:
1)	contraindications to physical exercise (cardiovascular diseases e.g. myocardial infarction, embolism, or uncontrolled diabetes; orthopaedic impairments; balance problems); 
2)	serious spinal pathologies (e.g. fractures, tumours or inflammatory diseases such as ankylosing spondylitis);
3)	neurological compromise (e.g. spinal nerve compromise or cauda equina syndrome);
4)	pregnancy.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The allocation sequence will be concealed from the investigator screening participants for inclusion and contained in sequentially, numbered, opaque and sealed envelopes. </concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation process will be performed using computer-generated random numbers. 
Stratified block randomisation will be used to ensure fidelity and balance of the usual physiotherapy care given to participants in both groups at each participating clinic, and also to ensure equal sample sizes.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Data will be analyzed using Statistical Package for Social Sciences (SPSS) version 22. Sociodemographic variables, physical activity and clinical characteristics will be described by means, standard deviations and frequencies. Generalized linear models will be used to evaluate the effect of the treatment on the primary and secondary outcomes. The statistical analysis will follow the intention-to-treat principle  in which all participants will be analysed in the groups to which they were randomised, regardless of whether they withdraw from their allocation. However, if participants withdraw from their randomised group, attempts will be made to obtain permission to collect outcome data at the follow-up time points. The statistical analysis will be conducted by an investigator who will be blinded to the subjects intervention group. 

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/10/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>68</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>THE UNIVERSITY OF SYDNEY
Faculty of Health Sciences
Cumberland Campus 
 75 East Street  
Lidcombe 
NSW 2141    
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Lifecare Clinics.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Lifecare Central Office
Address: 416 High Street, Kew, VIC 3101

</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This trial will investigate the effect of using a Fitbit device to facilitate a walking intervention in addition to usual care provided by a physiotherapist. We will be able to determine the effect of progressive walking in management LBP. 
We have developed the Fitbit facilitated walking intervention program to improve the patients adherence to the graded walking program and then increasing the physical activity level. Results from this study will inform clinical practice by providing evidence about the effectiveness of this program in reducing disability and pain, increasing physical activity levels, and improving functional and psychological status in participants with LBP. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Sydney  Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/09/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Debra Shirley</name>
      <address>The University of Sydney	
Faculty of Health Sciences 
Cumberland Campus
Room O158
Building O
75 East Street 
Lidcombe 
NSW 2141
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 9177</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>debra.shirley@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Hosam Alzahrani</name>
      <address>The University of Sydney
Faculty of Health Sciences
Cumberland Campus
Discipline of Physiotherapy
Room S223
Building S  
75 East Street 
Lidcombe
NSW 2141  </address>
      <phone>+61450101435</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>halz2656@uni.sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Hosam Alzahrani</name>
      <address>The University of Sydney
Faculty of Health Sciences
Cumberland Campus
Discipline of Physiotherapy
Room S223
Building S  
75 East Street 
Lidcombe
NSW 2141  </address>
      <phone>+61450101435</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>halz2656@uni.sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone>+61450101435</phone>
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>