<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343095">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/07/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/07/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000687998</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can writing reduce stress and improve health in older people?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In healthy older adults, can a brief expressive writing intervention reduce psychological stress and improve the rate of healing of a 4mm dermal punch biopsy wound on the inner, upper arm?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1122-3945</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>psychological stress</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>dermal wound healing</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal skin development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the immune system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Expressive Writing Intervention (3 days of consecutive writing, 20 minutes of writing on each day).

WRITING INTERVENTION:
Intervention: Expressive Writing Group - Participants in this group will be asked to write about their most traumatic/upsetting experience in their life.  Specifically, to disclose their deepest thoughts, feelings, and emotions about the event, ideally not previously shared with others. 

Control:  Time Management Group - Participants allocated to this group will be asked to write descriptively about time management (i.e. what they will be doing the next day).  This group will be asked not to mention emotions, opinions, or beliefs.

Participants will be randomly allocated to either the intervention group or the control group by the RA.  Each participant will meet with a research assistant (RA) one-on-one, during which the RA will explain the writing instructions (either the Expressive Writing or Time Management instructions), and provide the participant with an exercise book and pen.  

The RA will telephone each participant the next day to remind the participant to complete their writing task, and to answer any questions they may have.  The RA follows up with each participant after a few more days to ensure the three writing tasks have been completed.    

The writing tasks are unsupervised - they are completed by the participant at a time and place most convenient to them; however, we request the participant finds a quiet place to do the writing, so they will not be disturbed during the 20 minutes.     

The exercise books are collected approximately two weeks after they have finished the writing task.  The writing is not shared with other participants.  Only the researchers and RA have access the essays for analysis.   

The researcher collects the exercise books from the participants, and gives these books to the RA.  The RA then re-assigns a new ID code to each exercise book (and 'blacks out' the former ID code), and returns the book to the researcher, in order for the researcher to transcribe the essays electronically yet remain blinded to group allocation.  (i.e. ID code 2wf will be reassigned a new code  by the RA (i.e. 3mp) to prevent the researcher from inadvertently associating the former ID code (2wf) with the essay). 

WOUND HEALING:
Punch Biopsy: The punch biopsy occurs approximately two weeks after the first writing session. The punch biopsy procedure is performed by a licensed general practitioner (GP).  The punch is 4mm diameter, and is created on the upper, inner non-dominant arm, under local anesthesia.   Once the wound is created, a photo of the wound is taken (baseline).  The wound is then covered with DuoDerm (a hydrocolloid dressing) and a waterproof bandage for 7 days.  After 7 days, the wound is gently cleaned with sterile saline, photographed, and redressed.  This same procedure is carried out every 3-4 days until the wound is healed.  Healed is defined as full re-epithelialization of the wound, as determined by the study dermatologist, based on the wound photographs taken at each time point. 

BLOOD DRAWS:
One blood sample is taken the day of the writing instruction administration, and a second blood sample is taken the day of the punch biopsy.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control:  Time Management Group - Participants allocated to this group will be asked to write descriptively about time management (i.e. what they will be doing the next day).  This group will be asked not to mention emotions, opinions, or beliefs. They will be asked to write for 20 minutes a day, over three consecutive days.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(1) The time needed for a 4mm skin biopsy punch wound (inner, upper arm) to heal between individuals in the Expressive Writing group and individuals in the Time Management group (active control)

We define 'healed' as full re-epithelialization of the wound, as determined by the study dermatologist, based on bi-weekly wound photographs.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Wounds photographed at Days 0, 7, 10/11, 14, 17/18, 21, 24/25, 28, etc. until 'healed'.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(1)  Pro-inflammatory cytokine concentrations (e.g. IL-1beta, IL-6, TNF-alpha) in lipopolysaccharide-stimulated blood samples (repeated measure; between-groups comparison).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood collected pre-writing intervention (baseline) and again at post-writing intervention (approximately 2 weeks later)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(2) Activation of immune cells (e.g. macrophage) and expression of Langerhans cells (antigen presenting dendritic cells) in the skin biopsy tissue.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Tissue collected at time of punch biopsy procedure.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(3) Changes in perceived psychological stress (repeated measure; between-groups comparison)

Perceived stress will be assessed using the 10-item Perceived Stress Scale (paper-and-pen self-report questionnaire)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Perceived Stress will be assessed at baseline (pre-writing intervention),  at 2 weeks, and at 8 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(4) Changes in the frequency of causal/insightful words included in essays over the course of the three writing sessions (a measure of cognitive restructuring) (repeated measure; between-groups comparison)


Note: hand-written essays will be electronically transcribed and analyzed using the LIWC (Linguistic Inquiry and Word Counts) software package.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Essays from Day 1, 2, and 3.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(5) Number of doctor's visits in a 12 week period (repeated measure; between-groups comparison).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants are asked at baseline for the pre-intervention time point, and telephoned at 12 weeks post punch biopsy procedure for the post-intervention time point.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(6) Changes in mood state (repeated measure; between-groups comparison)

Mood state will be assessed using the 15-item Geriatric Depression Scale (paper-and-pen self-report questionnaire)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Mood will be assessed at baseline (pre-writing intervention),  at 2 weeks, and at 8 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>healthy older adults (&gt;65 years) living in 'independent living' accommodations at retirement villages in Auckland area</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(1) unable to hand-write or type (e.g. on a computer or typewriter) in English
(2) Cognitive impairments that prevent making informed consent
(3) currently have clinical depression
(4) skin complaints (e.g. eczema, psoriasis, keloid scarring)
(5) smoker
(6) allergic to lignocaine</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Study flyers are distributed to the letterboxes of 'independent living' residents at retirement villages (providing management consent).   When permitted, a brief (20 minute) presentation about the study is provided to independent living residents at the retirement villages.
Interested residents can sign up to be volunteers after the presentation, or they can call the researchers to volunteer.

Allocation concealment procedures:

All interested individuals undergo a 'pre-study' interview screen over the telephone, to ensure eligibility.  This 'pre-study' interview is carried out by the researcher. 


If eligible to participate, the researcher would then assign this individual a 'participant ID' code.  This ID code is 
a 3 digit alpha-numeric code (i.e. 2wf).  


Next, the researcher would give the 'participant ID' code to a RA, and the RA would assign this ID code to either the Expressive Writing or Time Management Group (based on a computer generated randomiszation table).  

The RA (NOT the researcher) administers the writing instructions (i.e. Expressive Writing or Time Management instructions) in order to keep the researcher blinded to group allocation.   The RA also requests that the participant does not share details about their writing instructions to others (i.e. other participants and/or residents in the retirement village). 

The RA also follows up with each participant over the days following the writing intervention to answer any questions they have about the writing task, to keep the other researchers blinded to group allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. "research randomizer" http://www.randomizer.org/form.htm)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>23/03/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>70</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Auckland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Auckland 
Private Bag 92019 Auckland
Mail Centre Auckland 
1142 New Zealand</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Auckland Faculty Research Development Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The University of Auckland 
Private Bag 92019 Auckland
Mail Centre Auckland 
1142 New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Maurice and Phyllis Paykel Trust</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 37 760 Parnell
Auckland 1151, New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Performance Based Research Fund - School of Medicine - The University of Auckland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The University of Auckland 
Private Bag 92019 Auckland
Mail Centre Auckland 
1142 New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Researchers at the Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences at the University of Auckland are running a study to see whether writing can improve the health of older people and are looking for volunteers to participate.   

The study involves writing confidentially about different topics.  You will be asked to answer some questionnaires about your mood and health-related behaviours, provide two blood samples, and have a small punch biopsy wound (4mm diameter) made to your upper, inner arm.  The wound will be photographed twice a week, for up to seven weeks, to monitor healing. 
 	
This study will be important to help establish whether the health of older adults can be improved through writing.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Auckland Human Participants Ethics Committee (UAHPEC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The University of Auckland
Ethics and Biological Safety Administration
Level 3, Building 438
76 Symonds Street
Grafton, Auckland
1010 New Zealand</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/12/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2010/532</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Elizabeth Broadbent</name>
      <address>Department of Psychological Medicine
Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences
The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland Mail Centre 1142
Auckland, New Zealand</address>
      <phone>64 9 373 7599 ext 86756</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.broadbent@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Elizabeth Broadbent</name>
      <address>Department of Psychological Medicine
Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences
The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland Mail Centre 1142
Auckland, New Zealand</address>
      <phone>64 9 373 7599 ext 86756</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.broadbent@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>