<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364806">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/08/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/12/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001332718</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Clinical Treatment of Acute and Chronic Wounds using Autologous Stromal Vascular Fraction Isolated from Lipoaspirate
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of autologous stromal vascular fraction (SVF) on healing time of acute and chronic wounds</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic venous ulcer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other skin conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Prospective randomized controlled study of patients from Royal Adelaide Hospital with venous ulcers on their leg. Autologous lipoaspirate will be collected from patients in groups 1 and 2 using syringe aspiration from a healthy donor site. Group 1 will have their lipoaspirate sample centrifuged in the operating theatre and subsequently injected into the wound. Group 2 will have their lipoaspirate sample processed in a sterile laboratory to isolate the SVF and subsequently injected into the wound. Group 3 will have no autologous lipoaspirate harvest or injection. The primary outcome measured will be time to complete wound closure. 


Aspiration and injection procedure:
The procedure will be performed under local anaesthetic and sedation in an operating theatre. This will involve intravenous sedation being administered by an Anesthetist. Following this local anaesthetic will be administered by the operating surgeon. 

Prophylactic antibiotics will be given at the time of surgery. 
First the ulcer will be gently debrided to remove any debris. 

Following standard tumescent infiltration, autologous lipoaspirate will be harvested from the thigh or abdominal region using syringe aspiration with a 2mm diameter cannula and a 10ml syringe. A total volume of 20ml of adipose will be obtained from each patient. 

Group 1. The lipoaspirate sample will be centrifuged in theatre at the bedside and immediately injected in theatre. The patient will then be woken from their anaesthetic. 

Group 2. The lipoaspirate sample will be immediately transferred to a Class 350 laboratory (SA Pathology-Therapeutic Products Facility, Haematology). The patient will then be woken from their anaesthetic. The SVF once processed will be injected immediately after isolation under local anaesthetic on the same day (60-90 minutes). 

Injection technique
For groups 1 and 2, the sample for injection will be transferred to a 1ml syringe. An 18-gauge needle will be used for injection. The sample will be carefully deposited at the dermal-epidermal junction at the edges of the ulcer and also directly subjacent to the wound bed. 
Multiple radiating passages will be made through the same insertion site to disperse the sample in different directions. Injection will only be performed on axial withdrawal of the needle. The volume of tissue grafted beneath the wound will be a function of the size of open wound and scar requiring treatment. As a rule, 1ml of sample will be injected for each 2.5cm2 area of open wound surface. Care will be taken to avoid overgrafting.
All wounds will be dressed with gelonet, gauze and multilayer compression stockings.  Patients will be discharged the following day. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Group 3 will have no aspiration or injection</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>All patients will be reviewed at weekly intervals to assess clinical progress in the Plastics outpatients clinic. A Registered Nurse who is blinded to the treatment group will perform assessment. 
Clinical photography
Digital measurement of ulcer size using Visitrak (Smith &amp; Nephew) 
Clinical assessment of any complications such as infection. 

The primary outcome measure will be ulcer healing. Ulcer healing was defined as complete re-epithelialisation of the leg. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed weekly until the ulcer has healed</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>infection - clinical assessment, microbiology, blood tests</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed weekly until the ulcer has healed</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-	Male or female, aged &gt;18 years
-	Venous ulceration for longer than 4 weeks between the knee and malleoli
-	Ulcer size &lt;10cm2
-	Ankle brachial pressure index of 0.85 or greater
-	superficial or deep venous reflux on duplex scanning. 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-	duplex scanning not possible 
-	multilayer compression therapy not practical
-	those who are unable or unwilling to give informed consent
-	those with deep venous occlusion
-	those unfit for local anaesthetic and sedation 
-	those with malignant ulceration.
-	infection, cellulitis, or osteomyelitis in the affected leg diagnosed by MRI and microbiologic culture results
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Consecutive enrollment</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation method – randomization will take place immediately following recruitment. Computer generated random numbers will be sealed in sequentially numbered envelopes. Group allocation will be independent of time, place, and person delivering the treatment.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>no</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size calculations were based on the requirement that effects be detected at the 0.05 alpha-level with 80% statistical power. Based on available evidence, it was assumed that the hazard rate in the optimum treatment group would be 0.4 and that survival time would follow an exponential distribution. A sample size of 19 patients per treatment group would be required to detect a hazard ratio of 2.5 across treatment arms under these assumptions.  If the clinically meaningful effect was determined to be a hazard ratio of 2.0 across treatment arms, then a sample of 30 patients per group would be required.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Adelaide Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 5, North Wing Link
North Terrace
5000
Adelaide
SA</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Adelaide Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 5, North Wing Link
North Terrace
5000
Adelaide
SA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Clinical Treatment of Venous Ulcers using Autologous Stromal Vascular Fraction Isolated from Lipoaspirate

INTRODUCTION
Stromal vascular fraction (SVF) harvested from lipoaspirate consists of a heterogenous mixture of cell types including adipose-derived stem cells (ASC), fibroblasts and endothelial cells. There is evidence to suggest that the cells contained in SVF have angiogenic and regenerative properties that may be effective in treating venous ulcers.

OBJECTIVE
The goal of this study is to determine the effectiveness of autologous stromal vascular fraction (SVF) from lipoaspirate for the treatment of venous ulcers. 

METHODS
Prospective randomized controlled study of patients from Royal Adelaide Hospital with venous ulcers on their leg. Autologous lipoaspirate will be collected from all patients using syringe aspiration from a healthy donor site. Group 1 will have their lipoaspirate sample centrifuged in the operating theatre and subsequently injected into the wound. Group 2 will have their lipoaspirate sample processed in a sterile laboratory to isolate the SVF and subsequently injected into the wound. Group 3 will have no injection. The primary outcome measured will be time to complete wound closure. 

CONCLUSION
The results of this study will be statistically analysed and summarised, will be presented at a plastic surgery conference, and will be submitted for publication in a peer-reviewed journal. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>nil</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>North Terrace
5000
Adelaide
SA</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/12/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/13/RAH/444</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/10/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Raakhi Mistry</name>
      <address>Royal Adelaide Hospital
Level 5, North Wing Link
North Terrace
Adelaide 5000
SA</address>
      <phone>+61420970408</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>raakhimistry@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Raakhi Mistry</name>
      <address>Royal Adelaide Hospital
Level 5, North Wing Link
North Terrace
Adelaide 5000
SA</address>
      <phone>+61420970408</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>raakhimistry@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Raakhi Mistry</name>
      <address>Royal Adelaide Hospital
Level 5, North Wing Link
North Terrace
Adelaide 5000
SA</address>
      <phone>+61420970408</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>raakhimistry@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Raakhi Mistry</name>
      <address>Royal Adelaide Hospital
Level 5, North Wing Link
North Terrace
Adelaide 5000
SA</address>
      <phone>+61420970408</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>raakhimistry@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>