<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336743">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/04/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/04/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000347965</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An easy intervention to improve short-term adherence to medications in community-dwelling older outpatients. A pilot randomised controlled study.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of an easy intervention versus usual geriatric care in improving adherence to medications in community-dwelling older outpatients.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Adherence to medications among older outpatients</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A quick and easy intervention with the objective to improve adherence to pharmacological treatment. It was applied at the end of the outpatient visit to the person managing the medications (patient or caregiver) who was asked to write down on a sheet of paper the drug regimen that had been prescribed. This was dictated to him/her by the doctor to obtain a schedule of pharmacological treatment in which the times of administration of the drugs were noted along with their dosages. The doctor supervised the operation, making sure that the transcription was correct and clear, and the patient or caregiver was then given the schedule for use at home. This schedule of therapy was set to be used at home for at least 4 weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care, i.e. the standard procedure available at the outpatient geriatric service: the prescribed pharmacological treatment was stated at the end of the medical report and reviewed orally with the person in charge of medications.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Outcome of the study was taken to be the presence of at least one self-reported adherence error of any kind (i.e. occasional or persistent) at a one-month follow-up. Errors were evaluated by means of a semi-structured interview in which participants were asked to indicate for each of the drugs prescribed i) if it was generally taken/given regularly, ii) if it was occasionally not taken/given because of forgetfulness or temporary unavailability, iii) what were the dosages and times of administration. Moreover, patients/caregivers were asked if they were taking/giving drugs not included in the list they had written under the doctor's dictation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>One month after the geriatric outpatient visit.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Being living in the community, taking at least one drug a day, having been prescribed a change in pharmacological treatment during the visit (i.e. at least one drug was added or suspended by the doctor) and  in the case of patients dependent in the management of medications - having with them at the visit the caregiver who was in charge of the administration of drugs.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Being not living at home, not taking medications, not having been prescribed a change in pharmacological treatment during the visit, being dependent in the management of medications without the caregiver who was in charge of the administration of drugs.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/05/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Milan</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>via Pace 9, 20122, Milan, Italy</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Italy</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Milan</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>via Pace 9, 20122, Milan, Italy</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Italy</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Fondazione IRCCS Ca' Granda Ospedale Maggiore Policlinico</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Geriatric Medicine Unit, via Pace 9, 20122, Milan</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Italy</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Complex interventions to improve compliance to pharmacological treatment in older people have given mixed results and are not easily applicable in clinical practice. The aim of this study was to test the short-term efficacy on self-reported medication adherence of an easy intervention in which the patient or caregiver was asked to transcribe the pharmacological treatment while it was dictated to him/her by the doctor. We hypothesize that this kind of intervention can be valuable in improving patients adherence to therapy, at least in the short term. Such intervention has the potential to be effective both psychologically and organisationally. Psychologically because it can enhance the sense of empowerment of patients/caregivers by  allowing them to play a more active role in the health-care process. Organisationally because it results in a medication schedule in which the dosages and the times of administration of the prescribed drugs have been clearly noted under the doctors supervision.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Claudio Bilotta</name>
      <address>via Pace 9, 20129 Milan</address>
      <phone>0039 2 55035411</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>claudio.bilotta@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Claudio Bilotta</name>
      <address>via Pace 9, 20122 Milan</address>
      <phone>0039 2 55035411</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>claudio.bilotta@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>