<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363825">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/03/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/03/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000316707</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Randomised controlled trial of a combination of Dexamethasone and Adrenaline for infants with Bronchiolitis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised controlled trial of a combination of Dexamethasone and Adrenaline versus standard care to assess duration of positive pressure ventilation for infants admitted to intensive care with Bronchiolitis 
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>DAB</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Bronchiolitis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>While in intensive care, patients in the treatment group will receive 0.6 mg/kg dexamethasone intramuscular or intravenously as a loading dose, then 1 mg/kg of methylprednisolone intravenous or prednisolone nasogastric or orally 8 hourly for 9 doses (days1-3 of the study), then daily for three days (days 4-6).  The route of administration is determined by the presence of an intravenous cannula or tolerance of oral intake for drugs that can be administered by nasogastric tube. This will be determined by the treating clinician. Starting at the same time as the loading dose of dexamethasone, patients will be given adrenaline providing the resting heart rate is &lt;180 beats per minute: If eligible 5 doses of 0.05ml/kg of 1% adrenaline (or 0.5ml/kg of 1/1000 adrenaline) made up to 6ml with 0.9% saline and nebulised using 12L/min of 02 and repeated every 30 minutes to a total of 5 doses, then given 1-4 hourly depending on the patient response for 72 hours, and then as required for a further 3 days while in intensive care. These drugs were chosen as they are commonly used for other inflammatory diseases of the airway of children and have been used in a recent randomised controlled trial in Canadian emergency department for this condition</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard therapy for bronchiolitis usually comprises oxygen therapy, positive pressure respiratory support administered by a gas flow device or mechanical ventilator, nutritional support and sedation. Both arms will receive these therapies. Once recruited and randomised, patients will be given either a combination of corticosteroids plus nebulised adrenaline in addition to  standard therapy, or standard therapy alone as determined by their random allocation. Dexamethasone and adrenaline are medications that are commonly used in this age group for the treatment of other respiratory infections.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The studys primary outcome is the duration of non-invasive or invasive positive pressure support  required from the time of admission to the study until discharge from intensive care. Positive pressure ventilation includes therapies such as high flow nasal prong oxygen of 1 L/kg/min, nasopharyngeal continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) or invasive positive pressure ventilation (IPPV).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration of intensive care stay - only at the conclusion of the intensive care stay will this outcome be evaluated</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1	Duration of mechanical ventilation  these data are recorded and updated on an hourly basis in the intensive care observation charts which are part of the medical record</outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration of intensive care stay</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intensive care length of stay
	</outcome>
      <timepoint>at discharge from intensive care</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospital length of stay</outcome>
      <timepoint>at discharge from hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of intubation  the number of children admitted to the intensive care units that require endotracheal intubation
</outcome>
      <timepoint>end of intensive care stay</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pressure-rate product if a nasogastric tube tube is already in situ. The pressure-rate product is a way of measuring the strain on the lung. The pressure can be estimated by measuring the transmitted pressure through an existing routinely placed nasogastric tube and then multiplied by the patients respiratory rate. The Pressure-rate product will be measured within the first 24 hours of respiratory support.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>duration of intensive care stay</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>a clinical diagnosis of bronchiolitis, defined as a first or second episode of wheezing or respiratory distress associated with a respiratory tract infection plus either  radiological evidence of chest hyperinflation or clinical evidence of prolonged expiration 
greater than 37 weeks and less than 18 months of age
no previous admission to this study
admission to intensive care for respiratory distress (not apnoea alone)
recruitment and initiation of the study therapy within 4 hours  of admission to intensive care
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>37</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Weeks</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Months</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Corrected gestational age of less than 37 weeks at time of admission to the intensive care.
Clinical evidence of croup (laryngotracheobronchitis)
Immunosuppressive treatment, including any dose of corticosteroids in the last 7 days.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>When admitted to the intensive care unit with the clinical diagnosis of bronchiolitis patients will be screened for inclusion and exclusion criteria. If eligible for the study, consent will be sought from the family/guardian of the child. The consent process will emphasize the voluntary nature of participation and that participation will not benefit the family or child. In the first instance, recruitment will be undertaken by clinicians or researchers who are not clinically caring for the child. The primary investigators and associate investigators will be available to assist with recruitment. Attempts will be made to separate the recruitment process from the primary clinician however in the event that there is no alternative (in particular after hours)  this role may fall to the treating clinician.  Subjects will not be eligible if they are not recruited within the first four hours of admission. After consent has been obtained, randomisation will be performed using off site computer generated system administered centrally.  </concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation process will be facilitated by an online randomisation website created by Dr Brent McSharry with the guidance of Dr. Kate Lee (CEBU). Each site will have site specific passwords to enable access to the website and randomisation process. Randomisation will be in blocks and stratified by (i) unit (5 strata), (ii) level of respiratory support (none, non-invasive positive pressure, endotracheal intubation plus mechanical ventilation) at the time of randomisation, and (iii) the presence of a risk factor (either cyanotic congenital heart disease or chronic lung disease requiring oxygen therapy for more than 14 days in the last 6 months). Thus there will be a total of 5 x 3 x 2 = 30 strata.
The first two patients at each centre will be used as the run-in patients and will follow the trial protocol, including randomisation.  All case report forms (CRFs) will be completed within two weeks of discharge from intensive care, and the data will be reviewed by the study co-ordinating centre within two weeks of the receipt of data.  This audit will document the feasibility of the trial and the adherence to the management strategies proposed, and the principal investigator will contact the site investigators to discuss any protocol deviations/violations. The data from these participants will be used as part of the main study.
</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>The primary outcome (duration of support) will also be compared between treatment groups in the following subgroups:
1.	Participants with cyanotic congenital heart disease
2.	Participants born prematurely (defined as &lt;36 weeks gestation)
3.	Participants with RSV positive bronchiolitis
4.	Participants with chronic lung disease
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/03/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>306</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Childrens Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Princess Margaret Hospital - Subiaco</hospital>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
    <postcode>6008 - Subiaco</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Children's Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>flemington rd parkville Victoria 3052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Paediatric Intensive Care Unit (PICU) 
Royal Children/s Hospital(RCH) Melbourne</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>flemington rd parkville Victoria 3052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Frank Shann</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>flemington rd parkville Victoria 3052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Bronchiolitis is a common viral infection of the lungs. It is mostly seen in children less than 1 year old, but it does affect children up to 2 years of age. Each year an average of 100 children with severe bronchiolitis need to be admitted for treatment in the intensive care unit. These children experience significant breathing difficulty and many are ill enough to need a machine to help them to breathe. The standard treatment for these children is to support their breathing, and to give them adequate nutrition and fluids. There are no other medications that have been shown to benefit children with bronchiolitis.

Steroids and adrenaline are two medicines that are commonly used to treat children with severe croup or asthma, and recent research suggests that they may help children with mild bronchiolitis. Steroids are an anti-inflammatory medicine, and adrenaline helps to expand inflamed narrowed airways. It is possible that using a combination of these medicines may reduce the amount of respiratory support required for those children admitted to the intensive care unit with bronchiolitis. Some doctors already use this medicine in intensive care because they believe it works, but other doctors do not use this medicine because they do not think there is enough evidence that it works in intensive care patients. 

The purpose of this research project is to see whether dexamethasone (a type of steroid) and adrenaline makes a difference in the treatment of children with bronchiolitis in intensive care.  Adrenaline and dexamethasone are medicines that are approved for use in children by the Therapeutic Goods Administration, Australia.

We will compare a group of children who receive the standard treatment for bronchiolitis with a group of children who receive the standard treatment plus steroids and adrenaline. We will compare the amount of respiratory support needed, the duration of mechanical ventilation and the length of stay in intensive care and in hospital in both groups. We aim to study a total of 305 children from The Royal Childrens Hospital, Melbourne. This research will also take place at Princess Margaret Hospital for Children in Perth and the Starship Hospital and Middlemore Hopsital in New Zealand. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal children's Hospital HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>flemington rd parkville victoria 3052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/12/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>32119A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ben Gelbart</name>
      <address>PICU
Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Rd 
Parkville 
Victoria 3052</address>
      <phone>61 3 93455211</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ben.gelbart@rch.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ben Gelbart</name>
      <address>PICU
Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Rd 
Parkville 
Victoria 3052</address>
      <phone>61 3 93455211</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ben.gelbart@rch.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ben Gelbart</name>
      <address>PICU
Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Rd 
Parkville 
Victoria 3052</address>
      <phone>61 3 93455211</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ben.gelbart@rch.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ben Gelbart</name>
      <address>PICU
Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Rd 
Parkville 
Victoria 3052</address>
      <phone>61 3 93455211</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ben.gelbart@rch.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>