<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336415">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/01/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/01/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000055909</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Variability and Heart Rate Kinetics During the Six-Minute Walk Test in Morbidly Obese Women  Effect of Aerobic Exercise Training after Gastric Bypass Surgery</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Variability and Heart Rate Kinetics During the Six-Minute Walk Test in Morbidly Obese Women  Effect of Aerobic Exercise Training after Gastric Bypass Surgery</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>no secondary IDs</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obese women undergoing aerobic exercise after gastric bypass surgery</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All patients will undergo a clinical examination prior to the gastric bypass surgery (GBS) Roux-en-Y, which will be done by gastroenterologist and a cardiologist physician (anamnesis, resting 12-lead electrocardiogram, endoscopy and blood analysis used to determine hemoglobin, triglycerides, total cholesterol and fractions: low-density lipoprotein - LDL and high-density lipoprotein - HDL, fasting glucose and uric acid). In addition, anthropometric data, spirometric measurements, regular physical activity pattern, record of heart rate (HR) and R-R intervals during six-minute walk test (6MWT) will be collected 1 week before and 4 months after GBS. One month after surgery, the obese women will be randomly assigned to two groups: 1) trained (that will participate in a aerobic exercise training program for 3 months) and 2) untrained (will not participate in the exercise program). 
The aerobic exercise training program consist of five steps: 1) initial five minutes of stretching the upper and lower limbs (hamstrings, quadriceps, calves, shoulders) and diaphragmatic breathing and awareness of proper posture in front of a mirror in the position standing and sitting; 
2) five minutes of heating on a treadmill at 3 km/h; 
3) forty minutes of walking on treadmill with speed and inclination varying according to the behavior of HR. These forty minutes will be separated into four steps of 10 minutes each: 1 degree) intensity of exercise which the HR remained at 50% of HR maximal; 2 degrees) 60% of HR maximal; 3 degrees) 70% of HR maximal and 4 degrees) maintaining 70% of HR maximal; Note: Heart rate and blood pressure will be obtained at the end of each step;
4) recovery of one minute at 3 km/h and; 
5) last step of ten minutes of the same initial stretching and diaphragmatic breathing. 
HR and blood pressure will be obtained at the beginning of the session, at the end of each step, recovery and at the end of session. The sessions will be held during one hour on alternate days: 3 times per week, for 12 weeks, a total of 36 sessions, a period of 3 months. The sessions will be performed individually and supervisioned by physiotherapist.
The control group (eutrophic healthy women), will not perform the GBS and will not participate in the exercise program</interventions>
    <comparator>The group of eutrophic healthy women (that had not been previously submitted to bariatric surgery) will performe all the assessments (anthropometric data, spirometric measurements, regular physical activity pattern, record of HR and R-R intervals during 6MWT) and will be considered the control group, because , however, they do not carry out any intervention (will not perform the GBS and will not participate in the exercise program)</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The six-minute walk test will be performed to assess the heart rate kinetics and heart rate variability</outcome>
      <timepoint>In the obese group: 1 week before and 4 months after gastric bypass surgery.

In the control group: performed the same evaluation, only one time</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The heart rate and R-R interval will be measured using an cardiofrequencimeter</outcome>
      <timepoint>In the obese group: 1 week before and 4 months after gastric bypass surgery during the six-minute walk test.

In the control group: performed the same evaluation, only one time</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria wiil be: (1) obese group: BMI = 40 kg/m2 for more than 5 years who will undergoa Roux-en-Y GBS, (2) control group (CG): 18.5 &lt; BMI &lt; 24.9 Kg/m2, (3) sedentary lifestyle and (4) age from 20 to 45 years old.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(1) women with orthopedic or neurological conditions that would preclude participation in an exercise program, (2) a history of cardiac arrhythmias or potential ECG alterations, (3) past history consistent with heart disease, (4) uncontrolled hypertension and diabetes mellitus, (5) chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (evaluated by previous pulmonary function measurements), (6) beta-blocker use, (7) postmenopausal status and, (8) participation in a regular exercise program at the time of study enrollment</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>One month after GBS, the obese group was randomized by using sequentially-numbered, sealed, opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/02/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>31</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Sao Paulo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Sao Carlos</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Viviane Castello</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Laboratorio de Fisioterapia Cardiorrespiratoria, Nucleo de Pesquisa em Exercicio Fisico (NUPEF), Rodovia Washington Luis (SP-310), km 235, Sao Carlos - Sao Paulo. CEP 13565-905.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Brazil</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Universidade Federal de Sao Carlos</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Rodovia Washington Luis (SP-310), km 235, Sao Carlos - Sao Paulo. CEP 13565-905</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Brazil</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Rodrigo Polaquini Simoes</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Laboratorio de Fisioterapia Cardiorrespiratoria, Nucleo de Pesquisa em Exercicio Fisico (NUPEF), Rodovia Washington Luis (SP-310), km 235, Sao Carlos - Sao Paulo. CEP 13565-905.</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Brazil</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>the purpose of this study will be (1) evaluate whether morbidly obese women have alteration of responses of heart rate (HR) kinetics during transition from resting to six-minute walk test (6MWT) and alteration in the HR variability during this test when compared with eutrophic women; (2) to determine if 4 months after gastric bypass surgery improves the HR kinetics and the cardiac modulation during the 6MWT and (3) determine the impact of an aerobic exercise training program (12 weeks) after GBS on HR kinetics and cardiac autonomic modulation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Committee of Federal University of Sao Carlos</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Rodovia Washington Luis (SP-310), km 235, Sao Carlos - Sao Paulo. CEP 13565-905.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Brazil</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Rodrigo Polaquini Simoes</name>
      <address>Laboratorio de Fisioterapia Cardiorrespiratoria, Nucleo de Pesquisa em Exercicio Fisico (NUPEF), Rodovia Washington Luis (SP-310), km 235, Sao Carlos - Sao Paulo. CEP 13565-905.</address>
      <phone>(+55 16) 3351-8705</phone>
      <fax>(+55 16) 3361-2081</fax>
      <email>rpssimoes@yahoo.com.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Viviane Castello</name>
      <address>Laboratorio de Fisioterapia Cardiorrespiratoria, Nucleo de Pesquisa em Exercicio Fisico (NUPEF), Rodovia Washington Luis (SP-310), km 235, Sao Carlos - Sao Paulo. CEP 13565-905.</address>
      <phone>(+55 16) 3351-8705</phone>
      <fax>(+55 16) 3361-2081</fax>
      <email>vivianecastello@yahoo.com.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>