<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370463">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/04/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/04/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000453482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Smart phone based Problem Gambling Evaluation and Technology Testing Initiative (SPGETTI) Phase II</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Smart phone based Problem Gambling Evaluation and Technology Testing Initiative (SPGETTI) Phase II</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>SPGETTI-II</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Problem Gambling</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Provide a behavioral intervention program delivered by mobile phone app to problem gamblers to support their relapse prevention. This intervention is in addition to usual/standard care.

The intervention is multi-pronged with a set of standard structured messages that are aimed at strategies for avoiding risk triggers., maintaining wellness, etc.  The number and timing of these messages are participant selected to match when they believe that they are most at risk for relapsing and how much support (frequency of messages) they identify they need. the intensity can be between 1 - 5 messages a day..  Once this is selected the participant receives these and does not need to activate the app further unless they wish to adjust the frequency or timing.   Two additional strategies within the app program are 1. a GPS locator activated on the participants phone which has coordinates  mapped to gambling premises will be used to trigger an intervention that is more intensive and specific to that occasion - i.e. when they appear to be in a gambling venue.  These messages are currently being refined.  However, they will be specifically shaped to facilitate the recognition of immediate risk of being exposed to cues and triggers that could influence a gambling relapse along with some immediate and actionable strategies to resist and avoid these cues; 2. a rescue icon will also be able to be activated by the participant when they feel that they need additional help.  This will be linked to more tailored messages, the problem gambling line contact numbers, and  their counselor (if appropriate).  
The intervention will be implemented for 1 month in total.  
Some monitoring will be undertaken through the app. The app will have location technology activated, This will be used to assess potential exposure (triggers) to gambling venues.  Times spent in these locations will be captured to help with contextualizing abstinence and relapses.  Self reported abstinence or relapse will be collected at the 1 month end point. </interventions>
    <comparator>Control participants will receive:
 1. current standard care for problem gambling and
 2. a simple app. 

1. Standard care is through planned sessions with a counselor,  During the four weeks intervention, a total of 2 - 3 sessions are likely.  Sessions involve standard CBT, and other theory based interventions  that are the core of the different provider services.  No influence on these will be undertaken by the research. 

2. An app will be installed with the same GPS location for venues as the intervention minus the trigger alerts function activation,  if they enter these venue zones.  They will also have information on problem gambling contact numbers  accessible through the app.  

 In this way,all participants receive an app, albeit the control group's app is extremely limited. This design is to help avoid participants knowing what group they are assigned to. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Continuous abstinence from gambling. this will be measured by self report, and frequency of being in a gambling locaiton (as defined by GPS technology within app). </outcome>
      <timepoint> At one month from randomisation </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>We will measure the number of participants in both arms of the study who are continuously abstinent (as measured by no lapses, with a lapse defined as exceedance of the specified parameters of the GPS location venue zones. All lapses will be measured objectively using data collected by the app and by self report. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At one month from randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The acceptability of the app and its perceived usefulness in preventing relapse and in assisting with the goal of achieving abstinence..   The Unified Theory of Acceptance and Use of Technology  framework will be used to measure this outcome.  A brief survey that enables assessment to be collected from the participants on  1) performance expectancy, 2) effort expectancy, 3) social influence, and 4) facilitating conditions</outcome>
      <timepoint>at one month from randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants are classified into gambling subtypes based on their PGSI scores. 
Only those with a score of 5 and over. aged 18 years and above and own a mobile smart phone capable of downloading an app, will be invited to take part</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Not owning a smart phone capable of downloading an app. 
Significant mental health illness or other long term condition that precludes ability to give informed consent. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Research assistants not otherwise involved in the study will undertake the primary recruitment interview and implement the randomisation sequence.  No researcher will know the identify of who is in the intervention or control. </concealment>
    <sequence>A computer generated  randomisation sequence</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>All participants will be blinded as they will all receive an app with the GPS technology enabled. In the control group the app will just be very simple such as information on numbers to call regarding problem gambling servcies.   
</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The design and number of participants are sufficient to meet the primary outcome.  This is based on a previous feasiblity study.  The aim is to inform our planning for a signficiantly larger trial which would be powered to  confer 90% power, two-sided P=0.05, to detect a difference of 30% in the proportion of participants in the intervention group continuously abstinent at one month after randomisation compared with the control group, assuming 50% continuous abstinence in the control group and &gt;10% loss to follow-up. 

The data will be initially analysed using descriptive statistics with the proportions of abstinence presented as frequency and percentages first, with unadjusted relative risk. 
When two proportions are compared and tested, relative risk and associated 95% confidence intervals will be determined; hypothesis testing will be performed by Chi-square test. All statistical tests will be two-sided at 5% level of significance.
The primary outcome will be analysed using a logistic regression model with associated odds ratio on the probability of abstinence at the participant level (i.e. yes/no abstinence), controlling for important confounding factors.  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/11/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/06/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>130</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Chris Bullen </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>National Institute for Health Innovation (NIHI), 
School of Population Health
University of Auckland, 
Private Bag 92019,
Auckland 1142, 
New Zealand 
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ministry of Health </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Minimising Gambling Team 
Mental Health Service Improvement 
Sector Capability and Implementation
Ministry of Health
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6145
New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Problem gambling, whatever the medium, is associated with widespread negative socioeconomic, social and health effects in New Zealand, and the negative impacts on individuals, families and communities have been well documented.  Abnormal cue reactivity is a central feature of all addictions, including problem gambling, and is associated with increased activity in motivation to engage in the behaviour. While the advent of the personal smartphone has created new opportunities for gambling harm via online gambling, it has also created opportunities to intervene at various stages in the problem gambling continuum, from prevention to relapse prevention.  Our research uses as a starting point existing models of intervention for relapse prevention, then adds a level of sophistication with real-time targeting and personalisation using mobile phones. that has not yet been investigated in the gambling addictions field.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Presentation: Humphrey, G.,  Bullen, C., Newcombe, D., Rossen. F., Tooley, M., Chan, J.  (2016) SPGETTI: A Smart-phone based Problem Gambling Evaluation and Technology Testing Initiative  HINZ Conference Oct/No 2016</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>NZ health and disability ethics committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
 Ethics Department
 Freyberg Building
 Reception  Ground Floor
 20 Aitken Street
 Wellington 6011
New Zealand</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/06/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>16NTA86 </hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/06/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Chris Bullen</name>
      <address>National Institute for Health 
University of Auckland 
Private Bag 92019, 
Auckland 1142. 
</address>
      <phone> +64 21415267</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nihi@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Gayl Humphrey</name>
      <address>National Institute for Health Innovation
University of Auckland 
Private Bag 92019, 
Auckland 1142. 
</address>
      <phone>+64 211100901</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>g.humphrey@auckland</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Chris Bullen</name>
      <address>National Institute for Health Innovation
University of Auckland 
Private Bag 92019, 
Auckland 1142. </address>
      <phone> +64 21415267</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nihi@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Gayl Humphrey</name>
      <address>National Institute for Health Innovation
University of Auckland 
Private Bag 92019, 
Auckland 1142. </address>
      <phone>+64 211100901</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>g.humphrey@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>