<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362219">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/03/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/03/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000297820</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Early vs. late initiation of continuous renal replacement therapy in patient suffering from septic shock and acute renal failure</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Timing for initiation of continuous renal replacement therapy in patients with septic shock and acute kidney injury</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Septic shock</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Acute kidney injury</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The aim of this study is to investigate the impact of early versus late initiation of continuous renal replacement therapy (CRRT) as defined by using the simplified RIFLE classification, on organ dysfunction among patients with septic shock and acute kidney injury.  Medical records of those patients who were admitted into our intensive care unit from 2008 to 2011 and required CRRT were reviewed. Those fulfilled the inclusion criteria and without exclusion criteria are recruited for further data analysis.  The observation period started at the time of  CRRT initiation (time zero) to 6 months after started CRRT.</interventions>
    <comparator>Nil</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sequential Organ Failure Assessment (SOFA) score</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time 0, 24 and 48 hours after initiation of CRRT</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Vasopressor dosage (based on medical records charted vasopressor dosage)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time 0, 24 and 48 hours after initiation of CRRT</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>ICU mortality (based on medical records upon ICU discharge)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Upon ICU discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospital mortality (based on medical records upon hospital discharge)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Upon hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>ICU length of stay (based on medical records upon ICU discharge)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Upon ICU discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospital length of stay (based on medical records upon hospital discharge)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Upon hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mortality (based on medical records, cross cluster electronic patient records or direct telephone contact)</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days, 3 months and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Severe sepsis (defined based on ACCP/ SCCM criteria, ie Systemic Inflammatory Response Syndrome in the presence of suspected or known infection, leading to organ dysfunction), and
2.	Acute kidney injury (defined based on RIFLE criteria, Injury grade or above, who required CRRT), and
3.	Presence of shock (defined as mean arterial pressure &lt;=65mmHg and required vasopressor support), either at the start or during CRRT</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>90</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Presence of Chronic kidney disease stage 5 or on regular dialysis support, or
2.	Pregnancy</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Both</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/03/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>20/03/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>31/05/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Shum Hoi Ping</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of intensive care
Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital
3 Lok Man Road, Chai Wan</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Hong Kong</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Acute kidney injury (AKI) affects 5% to 7% of all hospitalized patients (1-2). Sepsis and septic shock remain the most important cause of AKI in critically ill patients and account for more than 50% of cases of AKI in the intensive care unit (3). The optimal timing for initiation of renal replacement therapy (RRT) in septic AKI remains controversial. The main reason is the absence of a clear and consensual definition of AKI to stratify patients according to the degree of renal impairment. The development of new system, like Risk, Injury, Failure , Loss of kidney function, and End -stage renal failure (RIFLE) classification represent a major step forward (4).  Recent meta-analysis showed that earlier initiation of RRT in AKI may have a beneficial impact on survival (5).  However, the conclusion is based on heterogeneous studies of variable quality.  Moreover, the causes of AKI differ between studies, with less than half of the included cases were due to sepsis. In fact, the author concluded that a definitive treatment recommendation on timing of RRT in AKI cannot be made.  The aim of this study is to investigate the impact of early versus late initiation of continuous renal replacement therapy (CRRT) as defined by using the simplified RIFLE classification, on organ dysfunction among patients with septic shock and AKI. We hypotheized that early CRRT in septic shock can decrease organ dysfunction.  Medical records of those patient who were admited into our intensive care unit from 2008 to 2011 and required CRRT support are reviewed.  Those fulfiled the inclusion criteria and without exclusion criteria are recruited for further data analyisis.  

1.	Uchino S, Kellum JA, Bellomo R, Doig GS, Morimatsu H, Morgera S, et al. Acute renal failure in critically ill patients: a multinational, multicenter study. JAMA. 2005 Aug 17;294(7):813-8.
2.	Nash K, Hafeez A, Hou S. Hospital-acquired renal insufficiency. Am J Kidney Dis. 2002 May;39(5):930-6.
3.	Silvester W, Bellomo R, Cole L. Epidemiology, management, and outcome of severe acute renal failure of critical illness in Australia. Crit Care Med. 2001 Oct;29(10):1910-5.
4.	Bellomo R, Ronco C, Kellum JA, Mehta RL, Palevsky P. Acute renal failure - definition, outcome measures, animal models, fluid therapy and information technology needs: the Second International Consensus Conference of the Acute Dialysis Quality Initiative (ADQI) Group. Crit Care. 2004 Aug;8(4):R204-12.
5.	Karvellas CJ, Farhat MR, Sajjad I, Mogensen SS, Leung AA, Wald R, et al. A comparison of early versus late initiation of renal replacement therapy in critically ill patients with acute kidney injury: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Crit Care. 2011;15(1):R72.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hong Kong East Cluster Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital
3 Lok Man Road, Chai Wan</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/03/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HKEC-2011-92</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/12/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Hong Kong</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Shum Hoi Ping</name>
      <address>Department of Intensive Care
Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital
3 Lok Man Road
Chai Wan</address>
      <phone>852-25956111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>shumhp@ha.org.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Shum Hoi Ping</name>
      <address>Department of Intensive Care
Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital
3 Lok Man Road
Chai Wan</address>
      <phone>852-25956111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>shumhp@ha.org.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Shum Hoi Ping</name>
      <address>Department of Intensive Care
Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital 
3 Lok Man Road, Chai Wan
Hong Kong SAR</address>
      <phone>+852-25956111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>shumhp@ha.org.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>