<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365809">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/02/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/05/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000530628</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomized controlled trial of a Neuro-linguistic Programming technique (Phobia Cure) for people with a fear of heights.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In people with a fear of heights does the Neurolinguistic Programming technique (Phobia Cure) compared with a control activity reduce the fear of heights on the Heights Interpretation Questionnaire (HIQ) at 8 weeks.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1153-4383</utrn>
    <trialacronym>NeuroLPC</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Fear of Heights (score &gt; 29 on the Heights Interpretation Questionnaire)</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Both the intervention group and the control group will get a neurolinguistic programming relaxation activity (known as the relaxation anchor). The technique asks the participant to think of a favourite place. They are asked to close their eyes and imagine what the place looks like, sounds like, feels like, smells like and tastes like. They are asked to repeat the experience and when they get to the change from seeing to hearing they are asked to touch their thumb to their index finger. They repeat this twice. Then they are asked to touch their thumb to their index finger and see if they can get back that pleasant sensation. This is known as a relaxation anchor. In addition the intervention group will get the the Phobia cure. This will be done by clinicians who will be trained in the technique. This requires the patient to relive an experience of when they were exposed to a height and felt  stressful. They are asked to make a movie of that experience in their head and to imagine they are watching the movie from a seat in the theatre and that they are watching themselves watching the movie from the projection box. They run the movie forward in real time but in black and white and far away. Once they get to the end they are asked to float up in to the screen and be in the movie. They then run it backwards, in colour, as fast as possible such that their voice sounds like Donald Duck and their arms are waving in the air. They are asked to pop out the end from where they started the movie. They are asked how they feel about heights and if they feel better. The intervention can stopped there but up to three cycles may be needed to be certain that a change has occurred. Each therapy session will last about 30 minutes and after 3 cycles have been administered there will be no more cycles on that day or there after. There is a moment called a "break state" when the participant is asked to look out a window (to clear their thoughts). Between each cycle.

</interventions>
    <comparator>The control intervention willget  the same NLP relaxation technigue (the anchor)as the intervention group in addition to a 20 minute meditation MP3 by Vidayamala to match the time spent doing the Phobia cure in the intervention group. This is to avoid a time co-intervention bias in the intervention group. As both group get the anchor the study is a comparison of the phobia cure versus a one time meditation MP3.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Change in average scores on the HIQ continuous outcomes between intervention and control.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Eight weeks after the intervention </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Five step outcome. completely gone, much less bothersome, no change, much more bothersome, fully present between intervention and control.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Eight weeks from intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self assessment of fear of heights on scale of 1 to 10 with 10 being very fearful of heights between intervention and control.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Eight weeks after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean difference on the GAD 7 general anxiety disorder questionnaire between intervention and control.</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>HIQ score &gt; 29
Able to read and write English
Healthy volunteers</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Intoxication, dementia and terminal illness.
2. Psychotic disorder.

</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Remote computer (Server name is - caseweaver.com)</concealment>
    <sequence>Patients are randomised to the control group or treatment arm by way of the standard built-in random number generator on the server. This produces a random number of  zero (assignment to the control group) or one (assignment the treatment arm). Each time the application launches, the random number generator is initialized with a random value, which is obtained from the system clock.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>If participants are completing their outcome forms in person the participants will be asked to sign a validation form to say they have not had any assistance from the interviewer in completing the forms. Where possible the outcome forms will be emailed or posted back to the trial.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The analysis will use a chi-squared analysis on the outcome measures and be controlled for any baseline differences. Participants withdrawing from the study will be encouraged to attend follow-up visits and their data included in an intention-to-treat analysis. The sample size is based on a 30% effect size from 60% residual fear of heights to a 30% fear of heights with an alpha of 0.05 and a beta of 0.2.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/05/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>96</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Auckland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142
New Zealand</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Oakley Mental Health Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 2, Building 505, 85 Park Road, Grafton, Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142

</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Oakley Mental Health Research Foundation</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Level 2, Building 505, 85 Park Road, Grafton, Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Anxiety disorders are the most common mental disorder in the developed world. Phobias are an anxiety disorder and are common in our community. The prevalence in general practice is approximately 13% (35.7% of patients in primary care have mental disorders). The morbidity associated with this has not been adequately quantified but anecdotally it can affect patient health care with a needle phobia interfering with blood testing and claustrophobia with an MRI scan. We plan to use the Phobia Cure to determine if it is effective in those with a fear of heights.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Commitee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>No 1 The Terrace
PO Box 5013
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>14/NTA/23</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/02/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Bruce Arroll</name>
      <address>Department of General Practice and Primary Health Care
University of Auckland
Physical Address
Tamaki Campus
261 Morrin Road 
Glen Innes
1072</address>
      <phone>64-9-9236978</phone>
      <fax>64-9-3737624</fax>
      <email>bruce.arroll@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Bruce Arroll</name>
      <address>Department of General Practice and Primary Health Care
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142
Physical Address
Tamaki Campus
261 Morrin Road
Glen Innes
1072</address>
      <phone>64-9-9236978</phone>
      <fax>64-9-3737624</fax>
      <email>bruce.arroll@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Bruce Arroll</name>
      <address>Department of General Practice and Primary Health Care
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142

Physical Address
Tamaki Campus
261 Morrin Road 
Glen Innes
1072</address>
      <phone>64-9-9236978</phone>
      <fax>64-9-3737624</fax>
      <email>bruce.arroll@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Bruce Arroll</name>
      <address>Department of General Practice and Primary Health Care
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142

Physical Address
Tamaki Campus
261 Morrin Road 
Glen Innes
1072</address>
      <phone>64-9-9236978</phone>
      <fax>64-9-3737624</fax>
      <email>bruce.arroll@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>