<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362078">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/02/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/02/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000186853</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Determining if a customised "in-home" computer gaming system can improve sensory function in the hands of children with cerebral palsy.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Assessing the prevalence of tactile sensory agnosia in the hands of children with cerebral palsy aged 5 to 15 years old, and investigating if a customised "in-home" computer gaming system can improve sensory function for those children who are known to have a sensory deficit compared to healthy, aged matched typically developing children.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1127-0623</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil.</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cerebral palsy (CP).</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Tactile sensory agnosia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is a customised computer gaming system, with a specialised joystick to enable and maximise access for children with cerebral palsy. The interactive gaming system provides haptic feedback to the user - the haptic feature can be enabled or disabled, depending on the group the child is randomised into. Children are asked to use the system for 1 hour per day, 7 days a week, for 6 weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants who are identified as having a tactile sensory loss in their hands (compared to healthy, age-matched, typically developing peers) will be randomised into either the active (haptic) group or the control group (which will not receive haptic feedback during game play). </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improved performance in the suite of sensory assessment measures. The assessment measures are: a test of stereognosis (using 12 everyday objects); a test of tactile discrimination; a test of proprioception (by moving the distal phalange either up or down); and a test of pressure sensitivity (using Semmes-Weinstein monofilaments).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At first baseline (entry to Stage 1), at second baseline (entry to Stage 2, week 1), at the conclusion of the 6-week computer gaming trial (10 weeks post second baseline), and at 4 weeks post trial (14 weeks post second baseline). The computer gaming trial begins in week 5 and concludes in week 10.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improved performance in the measure of hand function, as measured using the Jebsen Taylor Hand Function Test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At first baseline (entry to Stage 1), at second baseline (entry to Stage 2, week 1), at the conclusion of the 6-week computer gaming trial (10 weeks post second baseline), and at 4 weeks post trial (14 weeks post second baseline). The computer gaming trial begins in week 5 and concludes in week 10.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Children with a confirmed diagnosis of cerebral palsy who are aged 5-15 years, with no previous hand surgery, who have not received botulinum toxin A in the last 3 months, and who have the ability to follow and respond to verbal instructions.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>5</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>15</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Children with a neurological condition other than cerebral palsy; children who are younger than 5 years of age or older than 15 years of age; children who have had hand surgery; children who have received botulinum toxin A within 3 months of stage 1 or within 3 months of stage 2; children who cannot follow and/or respond to verbal instructions.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Stage 1 of the overall research project is a tactile sensory assessment and functional assessment of the hands of children with cerebral palsy aged between 5 and 15 years old. A sensory loss for participants in Stage 1 will be determined by comparing participants to healthy, age-matched typically developing peers. Recruitment for Stage 1 will be via the South Australian Cerebral Palsy Register in Adelaide. Participants who are identified as having a sensory loss will be invited to participate in Stage 2 - the intervention - which involves each participant using a customised in-home computer gaming system with a specialised joystick controller. Participants will be given the same computer gaming system and controller, receive instruction in it's use from the same researcher, and will be randomised into one of two groups: Group A, where the computer gaming system and controller has the haptic feature enabled, or Group B, where the computer gaming system and controller has the haptic feature disabled. Participants will be unaware that the other group has the haptic feature enabled or disabled. Allocation for the randomised controlled trial will be performed by a third party not involved with the study.</concealment>
    <sequence>All participants will be assessed prior to beginning Stage 2. This assessment order (first, second, third, etc) will determine the order for randomisation. Randomisation will occur via a computer generated sequence. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/06/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>16/05/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>28/07/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Women's and Children's Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>72 King William Road 
North Adelaide, SA, 5006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Women's and Children's Hospital Foundation (for Stage 1)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Ground Floor
55 King William Road
North Adelaide, SA, 5006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Channel 7 Children's Research Foundation of South Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 2438, 
Regency Park, SA, 5942</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Flinders University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Bedford Park Campus
Sturt Road, 
Bedford Park, SA, 5042</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of South Australia</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>City East Campus, 
North Terrace, Adelaide, SA, 5000</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to determine if children with cerebral palsy (CP) who have a known tactile sensory deficiency in their hands can have that sense of touch improved, hence improving their overall hand and arm function. The intervention uses a specialised joystick to play a range of custom-made computer games that are aimed at captivating the interest and motivation of children with CP while providing tactile feedback to their hands to increase the realism and sense of game-play. 

Our hypothesis for this project is that tactile sensory perception can be improved in children with CP through a computer-based program that couples a fun, engaging and motivational activity with an opportunity to experience a range of appropriate sensory inputs.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Journal: 

A.W. Walker &amp; D.A. Hobbs (2014). An Industrial Design Educational Project: Dedicated Gaming Controller Providing Haptic Feedback for Children with Cerebral Palsy, The International Journal of Designed Objects, Volume 7, Issue 3, pp.11-21. (http://ijgo.cgpublisher.com/product/pub.237/prod.45) 

Invited/Keynote presentations: 

David Hobbs, Invited speaker, "Did you feel that? Can a customised, accessible gaming system harness motivation and engagement to improve tactile sensory function in the hands of children with cerebral palsy?", the Cerebral Palsy Alliance NSW, 21 August 2014. 

David Hobbs, Invited speaker, "Good Vibrations  the design and development of a novel gaming controller for children with cerebral palsy who have impaired tactile sensation", AOPA National Congress, 23 August 2013, Melbourne, Victoria. 

David Hobbs, Keynote speaker, "Improving Tactile Sensory Function in Children with Cerebral Palsy  Can Technology Play an Important Role?", South Australian Rehabilitation Research Forum inaugural meeting convened by the Statewide Rehabilitation Clinical Network, 15 March 2013, Adelaide, SA. 

Peer-reviewed conference abstracts and presentations: 

D Hobbs, B Wilkinson, B Wesson, M Hughes, A Walker, S Hillier, R Russo &amp; K Reynolds (2014). Actively choosing fun! An accessible gaming system, proceedings of the Australian Rehabilitation and Assistive Technology Association (ARATA) National Conference, 20-22 August, Canberra, Australia. 

D Hobbs, K Reynolds, R Russo, &amp; S Hillier (2014). The Design and Development of a Novel Gaming System to Influence Tactile Sensation in the Hands of Children with Cerebral Palsy, the proceedings of the Australian Society for Medical Research (ASMR) SA Scientific Research Day presentation, pp. 60 (Wednesday 4th June 2014). 

D Hobbs, B Wilkinson, B Wesson, M Hughes, A Walker, S Hillier, R Russo &amp; K Reynolds (2014). The design of an accessible, engaging and haptic serious gaming system for tactile sensory training of children with cerebral palsy, Developmental Medicine and Child Neurology, Vol 56(S2) pp. 22, (7th Biennial Scientific Conference of the Australasian Academy of Cerebral Palsy and Developmental Medicine (AusACPDM), Hunter Valley, NSW, 11-14 March 2014). 

D.A. Hobbs, M.B. Hughes, B.G. Wilkinson, A.W. Walker, R.N. Russo, S.L. Hillier &amp; K.J. Reynolds (2013). The development, testing and evaluation of an accessible haptic gaming system and controller for children with cerebral palsy, proceedings of the ITAG: Interactive Technologies and Games  Education, Health and Disability Conference, 17-18 October 2013, Nottingham, UK. 
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Women's and Children's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee (for Stage 1)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>72 King William Road, 
North Adelaide, SA, 5006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/12/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>REC2441/12/14</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>SA Health Human Research Ethics Committee (for Stage 1)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 10, CitiCentre 
11 Hindmarsh Square
Adelaide, SA, 5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/02/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>480/11/2014</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Women's and Children's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee (for Stage 2)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>72 King William Road, North Adelaide, SA, 5006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/12/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>REC2530/12/15</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Dr Ray Russo</name>
      <address>Women's and Children's Health Network and Flinders University 
72 King William Road 
North Adelaide, SA, 5006</address>
      <phone>+ 61 8 8161 7220</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ray.russo@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>David Hobbs</name>
      <address>Flinders University 
School of Computer Science, Engineering and Mathematics (CSEM) 
Sturt Road, 
Bedford Park, SA, 5042</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8201 3167</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>david.hobbs@flinders.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>David Hobbs</name>
      <address>Flinders University 
School of Computer Science, Engineering and Mathematics (CSEM) 
Sturt Road, 
Bedford Park, SA, 5042</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8201 3167</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>david.hobbs@flinders.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>David Hobbs</name>
      <address>Flinders University School of Computer Science, Engineering and Mathematics (CSEM) Sturt Road, Bedford Park, SA, 5042</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8201 3167</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>david.hobbs@flinders.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>