<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371246">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001067460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Do donor white blood cells survive in patients who need multiple blood transfusions?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The incidence of donor white blood cell survival (microchimerism) in transfusion dependent patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Blood transfusion related outcomes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>microchimerism</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haematological diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a pilot observational study.  Haematology patients who require chronic blood transfusion will be recruited (preferably transfusion naive when they are recruited).  A research sample for testing will be collected at each time point during their current standard of care sample collections.  The timepoints will be patient dependent, some patients could have weekly samples taken others every 2-3 months.  The blood sample will be 3mL (1 teaspoon) in volume and will be taken prior to each blood transfusion and will be taken at the same time as other standard of care samples.  This means that up to, but not limited to, 10 samples will be collected over the recruitment period of 4 years.  No interventions will be applied the sample will be collected for research testing only.  </interventions>
    <comparator>No control group since patients will either be positive or negative for the presence of donor white blood cells after transfusion.  The incidence is patient dependent and comparisons with other patient types will not be effective for this study.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Early Detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine if donor white blood cells survive in chronic blood transfusion recipients.  This outcome will be tested using a sensitive genetic real time polymerase chain reaction test on specific non-coding DNA sequences.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Samples will be taken before transfusion (baseline)
and before each red blood cell unit is administered.  These samples will be taken at the same time as other routine standard of care samples are collected (these will be patient dependent timepoints but could be up to 10 samples per patient in total)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>None</outcome>
      <timepoint>N/A</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Male and female patients 18-80 years of age.
Patients with a haematological condition who require chronic RBC transfusions.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Minors under the age of 18 and patients over the age of 80.
Mentally impaired or individuals in dependent relationships who are not sound of mind to consent to participate in this study.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Directed measured outcomes.  Patients will either be positive or negative for an incidence of donor white cell survival (microchimerism).  The number of patients to be recruited is 200.  This recruitment target is achievable in the timeframe for the student project for which this study is being conducted under.  Since it is a pilot data gathering exercise, this number of patients will give  a good indication on whether an incidence is present given that 10% of trauma patients in Australia were found to have microchimerism.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/09/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/07/2021</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/07/2021</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Flinders Medical Centre - Bedford Park</hospital>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal North Shore Hospital - St Leonards</hospital>
    <postcode>5042 - Bedford Park</postcode>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>2065 - St Leonards</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australian Red Cross Blood Service</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Research and Development
17 O'Riordan St
Alexandria
Sydney NSW 2015</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Red Cross Blood Service</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Research and Development
17 O'Riordan St
Alexandria
Sydney NSW 2015</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Chronically transfused patients receive multiple units of blood products over the course of their treatment. Multiple red blood cell (RBC) unit transfusions may lead to adverse transfusion related outcomes including the production of antibodies directed against RBC surface markers (antigens), haemolytic diseases and potential long-term donor cell survival, which is termed microchimerism.
The phenomenon of microchimerism has been documented between a mother and her fetus during pregnancy or as a result of twin-to-twin transfer in utero. However, microchimerism could also occur following organ transplantation and blood transfusion. Transfusion-associated microchimerism (TAM) is hypothesised to result from the presence of donor leucocytes present within a RBC unit. Research from the Blood Service Research &amp; Development Team in Australia and from the Blood Systems Research Institute in the US has shown that long-term surviving donor leucocytes have been detected in up to 10% of transfused trauma patients following blood transfusion. However, it is currently unknown whether chronically transfused Australian patients could also be vulnerable to microchimerism. Therefore, chronic RBC transfusion recipients will be investigated for the incidence of microchimerism.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Sydney Local Health District HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Office
Kolling Building, Level 13
Reserve Road
Royal North Shore Hospital
St Leonards NSW 2065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/07/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>RESP/16/104</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/05/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rena Hirani</name>
      <address>Research and Development
Australian Red Cross Blood Service
17 O'Riordan Street
Alexandria NSW 2015</address>
      <phone>+61292342454</phone>
      <fax>+61292342411</fax>
      <email>rhirani@redcrossblood.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rena Hirani</name>
      <address>Research and Development
Australian Red Cross Blood Service
17 O'Riordan Street
Alexandria NSW 2015</address>
      <phone>+61292342454</phone>
      <fax>+61292342411</fax>
      <email>rhirani@redcrossblood.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rena Hirani</name>
      <address>Research and Development
Australian Red Cross Blood Service
17 O'Riordan Street
Alexandria NSW 2015</address>
      <phone>+61292342454</phone>
      <fax>+61292342411</fax>
      <email>rhirani@redcrossblood.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rena Hirani</name>
      <address>Research and Development
Australian Red Cross Blood Service
17 O'Riordan Street
Alexandria NSW 2015</address>
      <phone>+61292342454</phone>
      <fax>+61292342411</fax>
      <email>rhirani@redcrossblood.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>