<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364964">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/09/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/09/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001083785</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Randomised controlled trial of the effectiveness of Mental Health Guru, an internet-based workplace induction program for depression and anxiety. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial evaluating the effect of Mental Health Guru, an internet-based workplace mental health induction program, on mental health literacy, stigma and help-seeking in a workplace population. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Help-seeking intentions and attitudes
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Mental health literacy</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Mental illness related stigma</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study will test the effectiveness of a brief, internet-based, workplace mental health program- Mental Health Guru - using a randomised controlled trial design. 

The Mental Health Guru program is an online educational program currently comprising two modules: 1) depression and 2) generalised anxiety disorder each of which comprises information about mental illness and the myths associated with it, personalised feedback and consumer videos. Participants randomly allocated to the intervention condition will be asked to complete one module per week, with each module requiring approximately 30 minutes to complete. The program can be completed via home or work computers. 

Program usage data will be captured from the technology systems including program module access, number of site visits and an estimate of length of exposure derived from log analysis. </interventions>
    <comparator>Wait-list

Individuals randomised to the wait-list control condition will receive access to the intervention program directly after completion of the 6-month assessment. If the participant has not accessed the 6 month assessment within one month, it will be closed. If a participant logs in after this time they will be provided with access to the intervention program. The intervention program will be available for a minimum period of 3-months from the date of the 6-month assessment notification.  </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression and Anxiety Literacy scores as measured by the Depression Literacy Scale (D-Lit) and Anxiety Literacy Scale (A-Lit).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-test: Week 4 of the trial, one week after access is provided to the second module.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Personal Depression and Anxiety Stigma scores as measured by the Depression Stigma Scale (DSS) and Generalised Anxiety Stigma Scale (GASS) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-test: Week 4 of the trial, one week after access is provided to the second module.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Help-seeking intention scores for depression and anxiety as measured by the General Help-Seeking Questionnaire (GHSQ) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-test: Week 4 of the trial, one week after access is provided to the second module.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression and Anxiety Literacy scores as measured by the Depression Literacy Scale (D-Lit) and Anxiety Literacy Scale (A-Lit) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Follow-up: 6-months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Personal Depression and Anxiety Stigma scores as measured by the Depression Stigma Scale (DSS) and Generalised Anxiety Stigma Scale (GASS) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Follow-up: 6-months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Help-seeking intention scores for depression and anxiety as measured by the General Help-Seeking Questionnaire (GHSQ) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Follow-up: 6-months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Help-seeking attitude scores as measured by the Attitudes Toward Seeking Professional  Psychological Help Scale - Short Form (ATSPPH-SF) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-test: Week 4 of the trial, one week after access is provided to the second module.

Follow-up: 6-months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceived Workplace Depression and Anxiety Stigma Scores as measured by the Depression Stigma Scale (Perceived Workplace) and  Anxiety Stigma Scale (Perceived Workplace) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-test: Week 4 of the trial, one week after access is provided to the second module.

Follow-up: 6-months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Level of symptoms of depression as measured by the Center for Epidemiologic Studies Depression Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Follow-up: 6-months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Level of generalised anxiety disorder symptoms as measured by the Generalised Anxiety Disorder 7-item Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Follow-up: 6-months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Usability, Acceptability and Satisfaction data as measured by a number of Likert, dichotomous and open-response items designed specifically for this study. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-test: Week 4 of the trial, one week after access is provided to the second module.

</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants must be employed by an organisation that has provided written consent to participate in the trial.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>No exclusion criteria</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be recruited from organisations that have provided informed written consent. The trial will be advertised to employees via employer emails and other advertisement materials. All advertisement materials will contain a url address for the study, which provides detailed information about the scope, nature and potential outcomes of the trial. If they choose to proceed, employees will then be required to answer a series of questions to provide their informed consent. Only after this process is completed will the employee be enrolled into the trial and asked to begin the baseline assessment. After completion of the baseline assessment, participants will be randomised to the intervention or control condition by computer generated random number assignment and notified of their allocation. </concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be stratified by gender and by management/ general staff status, and will use block randomisation with randomly generated block sizes. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Analysis will be undertaken according to intention-to-treat principles, comparing outcomes from all participants allocated to the intervention group (regardless of whether they complete the intervention or not) with all participants in the wait-list control group. Emphasis in the statistical analyses will be on differences between the intervention and control group in terms of changes across time (i.e., baseline to post-intervention, baseline to 6-month follow-up, and post-intervention to 6-month follow-up). We will examine these differences using mixed models analyses. Additional analyses will be performed to compare outcomes for completers. Missing data patterns will be examined and analysis will be undertaken to identify any baseline differences between completers and non-completers.

For power calculations the effect sizes achieved for the primary outcomes of mental health literacy, stigma and help-seeking in the MH-Guru pilot trial were considered. Based on a power of 0.80, an alpha of 0.05, and an expected drop out rate of approximately 60% (based on the MH-Guru pilot trial), we aim to assign 440 employees to each condition to show an effect size of 0.30 (the smallest effect size achieved for a primary outcome in the MH-Guru pilot trial). Based on this determination the total sample size needed is 880.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/07/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>11/07/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/10/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>12/11/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>880</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Kathleen Griffiths</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>National Institute for Mental Health Research, The Australian National University, Acton, ACT 0200
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>ANU Connect Ventures </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>15 London Circuit, Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to test whether an internet-based workplace mental health induction program is effective in increasing mental health literacy, decreasing stigma and improving help-seeking attitudes and intentions for depression and anxiety when compared to a wait-list control group. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Australian National University 
Acton, ACT 0200
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/07/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2013/387</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Kathleen Griffiths</name>
      <address>National Institute for Mental Health Research, The Australian National University, Acton, ACT 0200</address>
      <phone>+61 2 61259723</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 6125 0733</fax>
      <email>ea.cmhr@anu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Neera Odhavji</name>
      <address>National Institute for Mental Health Research, The Australian National University, Acton, ACT 0200</address>
      <phone>+61 2 61250938</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 6125 0733</fax>
      <email>mhguru@anu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Neera Odhavji</name>
      <address>National Institute for Mental Health Research, The Australian National University, Acton, ACT 0200</address>
      <phone>+61 2 61250938</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 6125 0733</fax>
      <email>mhguru@anu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Neera Odhavji</name>
      <address>National Institute for Mental Health Research, The Australian National University, Acton, ACT 0200</address>
      <phone>+61 2 61250938</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 6125 0733</fax>
      <email>mhguru@anu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>