<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82304">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/09/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/10/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000506493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effectiveness of a higher intensity water-based exercise program: a randomized controlled trial following stroke (pilot)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effectiveness of higher intensity water- and gym-based exercise programs on gait speed: a randomised controlled trial following stroke (pilot)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A water-based intervention consisting of three pool sessions per week for a total of six weeks. Each session will be 40 minutes duration and consist of a standardised resistance program, the intensity of which will be varied according to each individual's ability, with progressive increase in load over the six week period.</interventions>
    <comparator>Group 1 will consist of a gym-based intervention consisting of three gym sessions per week for a total of six weeks. Each session will be 40 minutes duration and consist of a standardised resistance program, the intensity of which will be varied according to each individual's ability, with progressive increase in load over the six week period.

Group 2 will consist of attendance at a chronic disease self management course once a week for six weeks. Each session will be 2.5 hours duration and will consist of instruction on how to manage symptoms, effectively communicate with your doctor, lessen frustration, fight fatigue, make daily tasks easier, and get more out of life.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Six minute walk test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, immediately post intervention, 3 months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Modified Berg Balance Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, immediately post intervention, 3 months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bioelectrical Impedance</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, immediately post intervention, 3 months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional independence using the Modified Barthel Index</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, immediately post intervention, 3 months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Goal Attainment Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, immediately post intervention, 3 months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life using EuroQoL</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, immediately post intervention, 3 months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Motor Assessment Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, immediately post intervention, 3 months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Medical Outcomes Study (MOS) Sleep Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, immediately post intervention, 3 months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fatigue Assessment Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, immediately post intervention, 3 months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>6 months to 3 years since first stroke (ischemic stroke or primary intracerebral haemorrhage), community dwelling, independent ambulation with or without gait aids, Mini Mental State Exam score fo at least 18, ability to accept instruction and give consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>-2147483648</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Subsequent stroke, major medical complications following stroke, unstable cardiac conditions, urinary or faecal incontinence, open wounds, tinea, unstable epilepsy or seizures, other comorbid conditions that might contraindicate participation in gym- or water-based exercise, inability to carry out the ecercise program, current participation in an exercise program</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>45</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Maria Crotty</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Repatriation General Hospital
Daws Road
Daw Park SA 5041</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Flinders University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Flinders Drive
Bedford Park SA 5043</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In any year, there are approximately 48,000 stroke events amongst Australians. Most patients will experience severe cardiovascular de-conditioning after a stroke and around 21% will experience a decline in mobility which leads to a disruption in usual functioning and may affect social reintegration. For this reason, improving physical fitness may both counteract the deficits frequently resulting from a stroke and play a role in the secondary prevention of cardiovascular disease.  

While recent Australian clinical guidelines for rehabilitation after stroke have recommended that programmes should include interventions to improve cardiovascular fitness, they provide no information on the components of the most effective programme. Water-based exercise is possible for patients who are non-ambulatory or have balance issues and previous studies have demonstrated high levels of adherence to water-based programmes. 

The study will compare higher intensity water-based exercise with gym-based exercise of similar intensity for patients within three years of their first stroke. Given the susceptibility of this patient group to functional deterioration, this trial will inform the current debate on the optimal features of programmes designed to improve function and physical fitness following stroke. The current lack of scientifically rigorous research in this area ensures that its results would have immediate application to the content of rehabilitation programmes overall. It is anticipated that the water environment will allow patients to exercise at a higher level than would have been possible on land, translating into greater improvements to function.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Repatriation General Hospital Research and Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Daws Road
Daw Park Sa 5041</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/09/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>32/06</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Simon Gunn</name>
      <address>Repatriation General Hospital
Daws Road
Daw Park SA 5041</address>
      <phone>08 8275 1103</phone>
      <fax>08 8275 1130</fax>
      <email>simon.gunn@rgh.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Simon Gunn</name>
      <address>Repatriation General Hospital
Daws Road
Daw Park SA 5041</address>
      <phone>08 8275 1103</phone>
      <fax>08 8275 1130</fax>
      <email>simon.gunn@rgh.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Leah Couzner</name>
      <address>Flinders University
Department of Rehabilitation &amp; Aged Care
GPO Box 2100
Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>(08) 8275 1103</phone>
      <fax>08 8275 1130</fax>
      <email>leah.couzner@rgh.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>