<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82487">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/12/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/01/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000010392</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Improving glycaemic control of patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) through management by a community based, multidisciplinary, integrated primary care / specialist level care service.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Is glycaemic control of patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) improved through management by a community based, multidisciplinary, integrated primary care / specialist level care service relative to comparable patients receiving usual care at a specialist outpatient diabetes clinic.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ICDMS</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM)

Recognised complications of T2DM</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>There are 2 levels of the intervention: the patient level and the general practice level.

Patient level intervention: The Inala Chronic Disease Management Service (ICDMS) provides multidisciplinary, coordinated and comprehensive care appropriate to the needs of the individual patient based on a systematic assessment of glycaemic control, presence of recognised complications of T2DM, and lifestyle and behavioural considerations.  Patients will attend the ICDMS for management of acute complications of T2DM.  Once blood sugar levels and/or other complications have stabilised, the patient will be discharged back to their usual General Practitioner (GP).  Patients will be followed up for 12 months for the ICDMS evaluation.

General practice / primary care level  an education and training program for GPs and general practice nurses.

The education and training program for GPs consists of a number of different, inter-related activities, and will continue for at least 12 months.  Participation in any of the activities will enable the GPs to gain Professional Development points in the Royal Australian College of General Practitioners (RACGP) Quality Assurance and Continuing Professional Development (QA&amp;CPD) program.

One activity are the monthly, one hour Case Based Discussions. The program for these discussions is relatively informal, and is adapted according to the needs of the attending GPs, the patients seen at the ICDMS, and any "hot topics" in diabetes care.  

GPs can also participate in the more formal, eight week "clinical fellow" training.  Each session is 1.5 hours.  The clinical fellow training aims to provide GPs with advanced skills, knowledge and confidence in caring for patients with T2DM who have complex care needs eg. a number of co-morbidities.

GPs will also be able to undertake supervised clinical attachments.  These will consist of observing an endocrinologist over 10 hours of consultation time, and keeping a reflective diary of the experience.

The practice nurse education and training program will consist of a series (approximately 3) of 2 hour seminars that are aimed at enabling the practice nurse take a more active role in providing comprehensive, coordinated care for patients with T2DM.</interventions>
    <comparator>Patient level intervention  comparable patients from a diffferent geographical region receiving usual care at a specialist diabetes outpatients clinic.

Primary care level  GPs and general practice nurses whose patients are cared for at the ICDMS but have been randomised to be waitlisted for the education and training program</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction in glycosylated haemoglobin (HbA1c), measured by blood samples</outcome>
      <timepoint>measurement will occur at baseline and at 6 months post intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improved processes of care of patients with T2DM by the GPs (and practice nurses) participating in the education and training program measured by pre and post assessment of GPs' knowledge, attitudes and clinical practices associated with caring for patients with T2DM.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Only at 6 months after commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cholesterol levels (total, high density lipoprotein (HDL), low density lipoprotein (LDL), triglycerides), measured by blood samples</outcome>
      <timepoint>Only at 6 months after commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diastolic and systolic blood pressure</outcome>
      <timepoint>Only at 6 months after commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Smoking status, measured by patient self-report</outcome>
      <timepoint>Only at 6 months after commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body mass index (BMI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Only at 6 months after commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Level of physical activity, measured by patient self-report</outcome>
      <timepoint>Only at 6 months after commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Retinopathy, measured by interpretation of retinal photographs</outcome>
      <timepoint>Only at 6 months after commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Estimated Glomerular Filtration Rate (eGFR), measured by urine samples</outcome>
      <timepoint>Only at 6 months after commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Urinary albumin, measured by urine samples</outcome>
      <timepoint>Only at 6 months after commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Urinary albumin:creatinine ratio, measured by urine samples</outcome>
      <timepoint>Only at 6 months after commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Active foot ulcer</outcome>
      <timepoint>Only at 6 months after commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lower limb amputation</outcome>
      <timepoint>Only at 6 months after commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients on appropriate medication for prevention or minimisation of complications, particulary, proportion of patients with microalbuminuria on Angiotensin-Converting Enzyme (ACE) inhibitors or angiotensin 2 receptor antagonists (A2RB); proportion of patients with dyslipideamia on statins or fibrates (if indicated and tolerated); and proportion of patients on prophylactic aspirin</outcome>
      <timepoint>Only at 6 months after commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient quality of life (assessed using EQ-5D measure)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Only at 6 months after commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient diabetes self efficacy (assessed using Diabetes Self-Efficacy Scale)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Only at 6 months after commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression (intervention group only, assessed using PHQ-9 measure)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Only at 6 months after commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severe hypoglycaemic episodes requiring assistance, measured by patient self-report</outcome>
      <timepoint>Only at 6 months after commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acceptability of the ICDMS to participating GPs (qualitative assessement)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Only at 6 months after commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acceptability of the ICDMS to patients (qualitative assessment)</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 and 6 months after commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participation, satisfaction and impact of patient participation in self-management education program, measured by attendance records and outcome evaluation using a questionnaire and patient feedback about perceived accomplishments as a result of participating in the program.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Only at 6 months after commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relative cost and benefit of ICDMS, assessed by health economic modeling using comparative changes in quality of life, resource utilisation and clinical indicators.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Only at 6 months after commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. patients with T2DM referred by GPs in the Inala catchment area for specialist management of their diabetes.
2. 18 yrs or older
3. willing to provide informed consent
4. have intact cognition</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. patients on haemodialysis or renal transplant patients
2. patients with insufficient hypoglycaemic awareness
3. patients who are pregnant</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The patient level intervention is an open controlled trial.  A geographical control is being used to assess the impact of the intervention on a range of clinical and patient related outcomes (listed previously).

The general practice intervention is a clustered randomised control trial, only involving general practices from the intervention area who have patients receiving care at the ICDMS.  General practices were stratified according to the number of GPs, and randomised to either immediate or waitlisted participation in the GP and practice nurse education program.  Practices were divided into two strata (one or two GPs, and three or more GPs), coded, and randomly allocated to the two groups by a blinded assessor, using opaque sealed envelopes.  The impact of this intervention will be assessed by reviewing processes of care within the general practice of non-referred patients.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>250</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>4110</postcode>
    <postcode>4108</postcode>
    <postcode>4300</postcode>
    <postcode>4075</postcode>
    <postcode>4068</postcode>
    <postcode>4076</postcode>
    <postcode>4077</postcode>
    <postcode>4078</postcode>
    <postcode>4074</postcode>
    <postcode>4106</postcode>
    <postcode>4073</postcode>
    <postcode>4107</postcode>
    <postcode>4109</postcode>
    <postcode>4113</postcode>
    <postcode>4115</postcode>
    <postcode>4116</postcode>
    <postcode>4301</postcode>
    <postcode>4303</postcode>
    <postcode>4304</postcode>
    <postcode>4305</postcode>
    <postcode>4306</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Community &amp; Primary Health Services, Queensland Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Mr Glenn Bradley, Executive Director, Community and Primary Health Services, Southside Health Service District.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Commonwealth Safety &amp; Quality Team, Queensland Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 48 
Brisbane QLD 4001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Discipline of General Practice, University of Queensland</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Prof Claire Jackson
Discipline of General Practice
School of Medicine
University of Queensland
Herston Rd
Herston QLD 4006</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Princess Alexandra Hospital</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Dr Tony Russell
Diabetes and Endocrinology Department
Princess Alexandra Hospital
Ipswich Rd
Woolloongabba QLD 4102</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This research aims to improve quality of life in patients with type 2 diabetes by building the capacity of primary care and providing accessible, evidence based care in the community through multidisciplinary collaboration and integration across the primary and tertiary interface.

The primary objective of this research is to investigate if glycaemic control of patients with type 2 diabetes can be improved through management at the Inala Chronic Disease Management Service (ICDMS) relative to comparable patients receiving usual care at the PAH endocrinology outpatients clinic.
Other important objectives of the research include:
* To improve modifiable cardiovascular risk factors and microvascular complications of diabetes
* To increase the capacity and scope of primary care to manage patients with type 2 diabetes
* To restructure the organisation of care in order to improve the effectiveness of patient care
* To develop a sustainable model of care that is generalisable to other chronic diseases.
* To investigate the relative costs of the new model of care
* To assess the acceptability to GPs of the ICDMS caring for patients traditionally referred to the specialist outpatients clinic
* To assess the acceptability to patients of the ICDMS rather than usual care at a specialist outpatients clinic.

A key component of the ICDMS will be the staged devolution of diabetes services from tertiary care to primary care through increasing the capacity of primary care to meet the needs of patients who would otherwise use hospital outpatient clinic services. Initially, the tertiary level service providers (particularly the endocrinologist) will be heavily involved in training, support and service provision. Their involvement will gradually decrease to a virtual consultative function interspersed with limited patient contact.

The proposed research is a structured and rational approach to evaluating the efficaciousness and effectiveness of the ICDMS. To achieve this, an open controlled trial of patient care at the ICDMS compared with usual care at the PAH diabetes outpatient clinic is proposed. Additionally, a nested cluster randomized controlled trial is proposed to test the effectiveness of the upskilling component of the project  general practices will be randomised to either receive the upskilling immediately or to be a wait-listed control group.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Diabetes Self Management Education Program - it is making a difference?  Presented at 2008 GP &amp; PHC Research Conference.  Hobart, Australia.

Enhancing patient and practitioner skills for chronic disease management in an integrated primary &amp; specialist level diabetes service. National Health Care Reform Conference  2008.  Sydney, Australia</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Princess Alexandra Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Princess Alexandra Hospital
Ipswich Rd
Woolloongabba QLD 4102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/06/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2007/100</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Tony Russell</name>
      <address>Department of Diabetes and Endocrinology, Princess Alexandra Hospital, Brisbane, Australia
b Diamantina Institute, University of Queensland</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3240 2690</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.russell@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Deb Miller</name>
      <address>Inala Chronic Disease Management Service
1st Floor
Inala Community Health Centre
64 Wirraway Pde
Inala QLD 4077</address>
      <phone>0419 788 001</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Deborah_Miller@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Tony Russell</name>
      <address>Department of Diabetes and Endocrinology, Princess Alexandra Hospital, Brisbane, Australia
b Diamantina Institute, University of Queensland</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3240 2690</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.russell@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>