<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367652">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/01/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/06/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000623594</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A multi-centre prospective observational study of simultaneous pulse oximeter and arterial oxygen saturation recordings in Intensive Care Unit patients.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In Intensive Care Unit patients requiring an arterial blood gas, a comparison between arterial oxygen saturation and pulse oximetry saturation measurements.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1165-3894</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Any condition requiring measurement of arterial blood gas in the Intensive Care Unit</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Evaluation of simultaneous pulse oximetry (SpO2) and arterial blood gas (ABG) measured oxygen saturation (SaO2) values recorded in ICU patients. 

The paired SpO2 value will be recorded at least 2 hours after admission to ICU, to allow for adjustments in oxygen therapy to become in-line with standard ICU practice for oxygen administration. Where possible, paired measurements will be done during the earliest arterial blood gas (ABG) taken after at least 2 hours of admission.

A single set of paired measurements will be taken per patient.</interventions>
    <comparator>The SpO2 value recorded by the pulse oximeter will be paired with the ABG measured oxygen saturation (SaO2) value for comparison.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>SpO2, measured by pulse oximetry at the same time an ABG is performed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The SpO2 value will be the first value displayed by the pulse oximeter following visualisation of blood entering the collection vial for the ABG analysis.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>SaO2, measured by ABG (while the pulse oximeter is in place).
ABG is assessed by means of a blood sample taken from an artery.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Taken at time of the clinically indicated ABG.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Four hundred patients with routine oxygen saturation monitoring and routine ABG measurements as part of their clinical care at Wellington Regional Hospital and Austin Hospital ICUs.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Diagnosis of methaemoglobinemia or prior use of intravenous dye during this admission(e.g. methylene blue). 
2. Diagnosis of CO poisoning.
3. Age under 16 years.
4. Patients previously recruited to the study with paired SpO2 and SaO2 values successfully recorded.
5. Any other condition which, at the investigators discretion, is believed may present a safety risk or impact upon the feasibility of the study or the interpretation of the study results.  </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>STUDY OBJECTIVES:

1.	To describe the agreement between paired SpO2 and SaO2 measurements in terms of bias and limits of agreement. 
2.	To estimate the influence on bias of the paired SpO2 and SaO2 measurements by: 
a.	The mean oxygen saturation (average of SpO2 and SaO2)
b.	PaCO2 
c.	APACHE II score (&gt; 25 vs &lt;25)
d.	Inotrope administration at the time of ABG sample (yes or no)
e.	Vasopressor administration at the time of ABG sample (yes or no)
f.	Values immediately prior to ABG sample:
i.	Capillary refill (&lt;3 seconds vs &gt;3 seconds)
ii.	Last recorded axillary body temperature 
iii.	Temperature of hands (warm vs cool to touch)
iv.	Mean arterial blood pressure
v.	Pulse pressure
vi.	Identification of any local factor by the nursing staff as potentially impacting on oximetry probe recording (e.g. motion artefact) 
g.	Skin pigmentation (based on modified Fitzpatrick scale with patient skin colour classified as either: Light (Type I to Type II), Medium (Type III to Type IV) or Dark (Type V to Type VI))
h.	Pulse oximeter model (Philips IntelliVue MP70 or Mossimo TRAM-RAC 4A)
3.	To describe the diagnostic performance of SpO2 to detect clinically important boundaries of SaO2 (90 %) and arterial oxygen tension (PaO2) (60 mmHg).

STATISTICAL METHODS:
Objective 1: 	Bland-Altman plots and estimation of bias and limits of agreement.
Objective 2: 	Analysis of Covariance. Should important predictors of bias be identified Bland-Altman methods will be used to determine whether there is also an effect on limits of agreement.
Objective 3: 	Receiver Operating Characteristic curve estimation by logistic regression and associated prediction equations.


SAMPLE SIZE:
The planned sample size is based on three considerations. Firstly, for the analysis of variables that predict the size of the bias we seek to have between 20 and 40 participants for each degree of freedom in the ANCOVA.  Based on the thirteen variables, some of which have multiple levels, this requires between 200 and 400 participants.  Secondly, the estimates of paired SD for the SpO2 to SaO2 difference from the papers of Pu, Van de Leow and Wouters; were 0.55%, 2.1%, and 2.2% respectively.  We wish to detect a SpO2 to SaO2 difference of 2% for any of the variables that might predict bias.  If there were two equal sized groups of 42 participants, 21 in each group, there is 80% power, with a type I error rate of 5%, to detect this size difference.  This suggests that a minimum of 20 participants with a particular characteristic will provide greater than 80% power to detect a difference of 2% between groups for dichotomous variables (because the complement of a particular characteristic will have be more numerous than 20).  We consider  a sample size of 400 as being likely that each individual characteristic will have at least 20 participants. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/06/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>400</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Wellington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>MRINZ</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>MRINZ, 
Wellington Regional Hospital, 
Riddiford Street, 
Newtown, 
Wellington 6021</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Wellington Regional Hospital, 
Riddiford Street, 
Newtown, 
Wellington 6021</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Nil</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Michael Richards</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>MRINZ, 
Wellington Regional Hospital, 
Riddiford Street, 
Newtown, 
Wellington 6021</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Pulse oximetry is commonly used in the clinical setting to guide oxygen therapy
.
The purpose of this study is to investigate the level of agreement between pulse oximeter measured oxygen saturations and arterial blood gas measured oxygen saturations (the gold standard for oxygen saturation measurement) in Australian and New Zealand Intensive Care Units.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern A Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Health and Disability Ethics Committees
Ministry of Health
C/- MEDSAFE, Level 6, Deloitte House
10 Brandon Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/12/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>14/NTA/180</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/10/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Janine Pilcher</name>
      <address>MRINZ, Wellington Regional Hospital, Riddiford Street, Newtown, Wellington 6021</address>
      <phone>+64 4 8050241</phone>
      <fax>+64 4 3895707</fax>
      <email>Janine.Pilcher@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Janine Pilcher</name>
      <address>MRINZ, Wellington Regional Hospital, Riddiford Street, Newtown, Wellington 6021</address>
      <phone>+64 4 8050241</phone>
      <fax>+64 4 3895707</fax>
      <email>Janine.Pilcher@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Janine Pilcher</name>
      <address>MRINZ, Wellington Regional Hospital, Riddiford Street, Newtown, Wellington 6021</address>
      <phone>+64 4 8050241</phone>
      <fax>+64 4 3895707</fax>
      <email>Janine.Pilcher@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Janine Pilcher</name>
      <address>MRINZ, Wellington Regional Hospital, Riddiford Street, Newtown, Wellington 6021</address>
      <phone>+64 4 8050241</phone>
      <fax>+64 4 3895707</fax>
      <email>Janine.Pilcher@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>