<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371041">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/07/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000905460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Mixed dilution haemodiafiltration versus post dilution haemodiafiltration in adults with end stage kidney disease: a prospective randomised crossover trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Mixed dilution haemodiafiltration versus post dilution haemodiafiltration in adults with end stage kidney disease: a prospective randomised crossover trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Haemodiafiltration</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>End stage kidney disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Mixed dilution haemodiafiltration (HDF) is the intervention in this trial and post-dilution HDF is the control. Currently, dialysis patients are routinely managed with post-dilution HDF in the units in this study (which is consistent with other units who perform HDF in Australia and New Zealand). HDF involves large volumes of fluid convection (the primary mechanism of solute clearance) and, subsequently, large volumes of replacement fluid reinfusion. In post-dilution HDF, replacement fluid is reinfused after the dialysis membrane. In mixed-dilution HDF, replacement fluid is reinfused both before and after the dialysis membrane in a ratio that will allow the most efficient clearance of solutes while maintaining a safe transmembrane pressure (TMP, the pressure between the dialysis fluid and blood compartments). The ratio is controlled automatically by the dialysis machine to maintain TMP between 250 - 300 mmHg. Apart from the site of fluid replacement, no other dialysis parameters will differ from standard care (ie post-dilution HDF)

After screening, patients will be randomised 1:1 to arm A (mixed then post dilution HDF) or arm B (post dilution then mixed HDF). Following a 2 week run in period of post-dilution HDF, patients will commence the first of two 4 week intervention periods. These intervention periods will be separated by a 2 week washout period of post-dilution HDF.

In the intervention periods, patients will continue on their pre-trial dialysis session duration, treatment location and dialysis schedule (Monday/Wednesday/Friday or Tuesday/Thursday/Saturday). Dialysate composition will remain constant. Each session, convection volume, circuit clotting and peak transmembrane pressure will be recorded by dialysis nursing staff. In the final week of each intervention period, pre and post dialysis bloods (solute clearance, albumin and clotting) and a post-dialysis recovery time questionnaire will be performed.</interventions>
    <comparator>Each patient will serve as their own control in this randomised crossover design. Post-dilution HDF is the control as this is currently the standard practice in the study dialysis units. Patients will continue their standard dialysis location, hours, prescription and dialysate composition</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Convection volume
-this will be recorded each dialysis session during the intervention periods
-this figure is automatically reported by the dialysis machine
-this figure will be recorded in each patient's record by dialysis nursing staff</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 4 of intervention periods 1 and 2</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Solute clearance
-levels of small (urea), medium (B2 microglobulin), and large (retinol binding protein, cystatin C) solutes will be measured on blood samples taken before and after dialysis
-samples will be taken in the mid-week session 
-solute clearance will be reported as a reduction ratio e.g. urea reduction ratio = (pre dialysis urea - post dialysis urea) / pre dialysis urea. This calculation will be performed for each of the 4 measured solutes</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 4 of intervention periods 1 and 2</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Peak transmembrane pressure
-measured automatically by dialysis machine each session
-recorded in patient file by dialysis nursing staff</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 4 of intervention periods 1 and 2</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Post dialysis recovery time
-survey of time taken for patients to recover following dialysis (0hr, 0-2hr, 2-6hr, 5-12hr, &gt;12hr)
-recorded by patients and entered into patient file by dialysis nursing staff</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 4 of intervention periods 1 and 2</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>CIrcuit clotting
-scale from 0 to 4 according to EDTNA ERCA audit to evaluate clotting in dialysis circuit
-recorded by nursing staff each session </outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 4 of intervention periods 1 and 2</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients with end stage kidney disease on conventional in-centre haemodialysis with dialysis session duration 4-6hr, three times per week</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Incident haemodialysis patients (&lt;3 months),
Temporary vascular access (HD central venous catheter)
Life expectancy &lt;6 months
Medical instability altered response criteria (airway, breathing, circulation, neurology)
Blood flow rate (Qb) &lt;250mls/min 
Non-adherence to prescribed treatment hours
Unable to tolerate post-dilution HDF
Residual urine output &gt;500ml/day
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/08/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>3/10/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>25</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Princess Alexandra Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 2, Ambulatory Renal and Transplant Services Building
Princess Alexandra Hospital
199 Ipswich Road, Woolloongabba QLD 4102</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Princess Alexandra Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 2, Ambulatory Renal and Transplant Services Building
Princess Alexandra Hospital
199 Ipswich Road, Woolloongabba QLD 4102
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Bundaberg Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Bundaberg Renal Unit
271 Bourbong St, Bundaberg, QLD 4670</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Bundaberg Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Bundaberg Renal Unit
271 Bourbong St, Bundaberg, QLD 4670</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>End stage kidney disease is increasing in incidence and many patients in Australia and New Zealand require renal replacement therapy. In 2014, 9147 patients were managed with haemodialysis (HD), and an additional 2207 patients were on haemodiafiltration (HDF) (ANZDATA 2016).  Although the uptake of HDF relative to HD has increased considerably, HDF remains underutilized in Australia, especially when compared to uptake in Europe and some parts of Asia. HD performs solute clearance and volume removal by the process of diffusion, with minimal contribution from convection. HDF enhances small and middle molecule clearance through convection and diffusion, which may theoretically improve patient-level clinical outcomes. The safety of HDF has been confirmed by recently published meta-analysis. 

Solute clearance by convection requires substantial volumes of ultrafiltration, which in turn necessitates the administration of exogenous fluid replacement. This fluid has traditionally been reinfused either before (pre-dilution HDF) or after (post-dilution HDF) the dialyser. Post-dilution HDF is highly efficient in terms of solute clearance, but concerns have been raised regarding haemoconcentration with an increase in theoretical risk of clotting. Pre-dilution HDF minimizes the risk of haemoconcentration but provides less efficient solute removal. In recent years, two novel HDF techniques (mixed- and mid-dilution HDF) have been developed, which permit simultaneous pre- and post-dilution delivery.  Mixed-dilution HDF appears to offer the most optimal balance between solute clearance efficiency and haemoconcentration compared to other forms of HDF. However, its uptake has been limited in Australia in spite of its availability.

Few studies have assessed the clinical efficacy of mixed dilution HDF. Existing literature is limited by small patient numbers and limited outcome measures. This randomised crossover trial will compare convection volume, clotting, small/middle/large molecule clearance, circuit clotting and post dialysis recovery time between mixed and post dilution HDF</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Princess Alexandra Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 2, Ambulatory Renal and Transplant Services Building
Princess Alexandra Hospital
199 Ipswich Road, Woolloongabba QLD 4102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/09/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/QPAH/253</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/07/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Angela Henson</name>
      <address>Level 2, Ambulatory Renal and Transplant Services Building
Princess Alexandra Hospital
199 Ipswich Road, Woolloongabba QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61731761111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>angela.henson@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Emily See</name>
      <address>Level 2, Ambulatory Renal and Transplant Services Building
Princess Alexandra Hospital
199 Ipswich Road, Woolloongabba QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61731761111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>emily.see@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Emily See</name>
      <address>Level 2, Ambulatory Renal and Transplant Services Building
Princess Alexandra Hospital
199 Ipswich Road, Woolloongabba QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61731761111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>emily.see@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>