<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370303">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/03/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/03/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000347460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial of a scheduling of outdoor play intervention to increase physical activity in childcare</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The efficacy of scheduling three periods of outdoor play vs one continuous period in increasing the time children spend in moderate-to-vigorous physical activity during childcare</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Physical Activity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Specifically, within a six hour day (9am-3pm) the intervention will divide their usual total time of out-door play for children across three periods of at least 15 minutes' duration. The total daily duration of outdoor play will remain unchanged. There will be no prescribed timing for the scheduling of the outdoor play. Activities will remain unchanged.
The duration of the intervention period will be between approximately 3 months.
Services will be supported by a childhood physical activity consultant with experience working with childcare services to implement the intervention. Adherence will be monitored by the external consultant who will ensure the intervention is delivered as per protocol (unless inclement weather, special events or offsite activities) </interventions>
    <comparator>No Treatment, standard care  instructed to continue their one outdoor play period of the same duration (except during inclement weather across the year)</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Minutes children spend in moderate-to-vigorous physical activity from the time that children arrive at care until 3pm will be measured by accelerometers using recommended cut-points</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at the end of the intervention period (approximately 3 months after baseline) </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>% time in MVPA out of total activity in care assessed by accelerometers</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at the end of the intervention period (approximately 3 months after baseline) </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total volume of activity (assessed via counts per 5 sec epoch) will also be assessed using accelerometers</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at the end of the intervention period (approximately 3 months after baseline) </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse events. Child injuries requiring documentation assessed via the Nominated Supervisor survey.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at the end of the intervention period (approximately 3 months after baseline) </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Child care services (long day care and preschools)
For a service to be eligible it will be within the Hunter geographic region of NSW Australia and have a minimum total number of children enrolled aged 3-6 years of at least 25.
Children
For children within the service to be eligible to participate they will be aged 3-6 years, have parental consent and attend care during any of the days of designated data collection</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>3</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>6</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Child care services (long day care and preschools)
Services serving special needs populations will be excluded from participating in the trial given the specialist care required for such children and the likelihood of a differential effect in this population group. Services with more than one outdoor play periods within the core hours of 9am to 3pm will be deemed ineligible.
Children
Children at the service with special needs will be excluded from participating in the trial. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Long Day Care Services and Preschools
A current list of all long day care services (LDCS) and preschools in the Hunter region which have licensed places for 3 to 6 year olds will be obtained from the NSW Department of Health. The Nominated Supervisor of eligible LDCS and preschools will be sent a letter informing them about the study and requesting permission to recruit parents through their service. Within two weeks from the initial information letters being sent, a study research assistant will telephone a Nominated Supervisor to answer any questions they may have and to confirm their eligibility, consent or otherwise.</concealment>
    <sequence>A statistician with no other involvement in recruitment or data collection will allocate services to either the intervention or control condition in a 1:1 ratio using a computerised random number generator.
Randomisation of services will be stratified by the socioeconomic status of the area where the service is located, and on service type (long day care service or preschool)  based on evidence of an association between services locality and  physical activity policies and practices of services. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/04/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>8/04/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>11/11/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>600</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>419</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>11/11/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2264 - Morisset</postcode>
    <postcode>2291 - Merewether Heights</postcode>
    <postcode>2304 - Mayfield</postcode>
    <postcode>2286 - Holmesville</postcode>
    <postcode>2303 - Hamilton South</postcode>
    <postcode>2428 - Smiths Lake</postcode>
    <postcode>2350 - Armidale</postcode>
    <postcode>2380 - Gunnedah</postcode>
    <postcode>2388 - Wee Waa</postcode>
    <postcode>2337 - Scone</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Associate Professor Luke Wolfenden</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Hunter New England Population Health
Locked Bag 10 Wallsend NSW 2287</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421

Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Hunter New England Population Health </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Locked Bag 10, Wallsend NSW 2287 Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Newcastle School of Medicine and Public Health</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University Drive
Callaghan NSW 2308
Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Changing the scheduling of existing programs in childcare centres may represent an effective strategy which is suitable to scale-up for population-wide implementation. Unstructured outdoor free play (as opposed to structured, staff-guided play) has been consistently associated with greater child physical activity.
The study hypothesise when compared to children attending control services, where outdoor play is scheduled within a single continuous period, children attending intervention services will spend an additional 10 minutes in moderate-to-vigorous physical activity per day at childcare. An increase of 10 minutes of moderate-to-vigorous physical activity in preschool-aged children has been found to have clinically important effects on fat mass and peak bone mass.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Wolfenden, L., et al. (2016). "A randomised controlled trial of multiple periods of outdoor free-play to increase moderate-to-vigorous physical activity among 3 to 6 year old children attending childcare: study protocol." BMC Public Health 16(1): 926.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Hunter New England Health 
Locked Bag 1, New Lambton NSW 2305 
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/03/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>15/11/18/4.03</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/10/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/370303-Wolfenden 2016.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Luke Wolfenden</name>
      <address>Hunter New England Population Health
Locked Bag 10
Wallsend, NSW, 2287
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4985 5168</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>luke.wolfenden@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Lubna Abdul Razak</name>
      <address>Hunter New England Population Health
Locked Bag 10
Wallsend, NSW, 2287
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4924 6305</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lubna.abdulrazak@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Luke Wolfenden</name>
      <address>Hunter New England Population Health
Locked Bag 10
Wallsend, NSW, 2287</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4985 5168</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>luke.wolfenden@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Lubna Abdul Razak</name>
      <address>Hunter New England Population Health
Locked Bag 10
Wallsend, NSW, 2287</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4924 6305</phone>
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>