<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370271">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/03/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/03/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000313437</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can electrogastrography (EGG) detect abnormal activity of the stomach in babies with feeding difficulties</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Continuous wavelet analysis of postprandial EGGs suggests sustained gastric slow waves may be slow to develop in infants with colic</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1180-3170</utrn>
    <trialacronym>CBS (Colicky baby study)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Colic (gastric motility disorders) in infants </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Exclusively breast-fed, non-colicky babies and exclusively breast-fed babies diagnosed with infant colic were recruited by advertisement. The mothers of those with infant colic completed a questionnaire regarding symptomatology.
A respiratory belt (ADInstruments MLT1132; Sydney, Australia) was placed around the mid-thorax of the baby. EGG recordings were taken from an array of adherent bipolar silver/silver chloride electrodes (Ambu N-00-S/25; Copenhagen, Denmark) applied to the anterior surface of the stomach. A total of 6 electrodes (4 recording, 1 common, 1 earth) were applied and connected to an electrically isolated recorder (AD Instruments Octal Bioamp ML138 and 8/SP Powerlab A/D converter; Sydney, Australia). Voltage readings from the respiratory belt and EGG recordings were for 3.5 hours (one recording per baby), based on previous research, including whilst the baby was sleeping after feeding</interventions>
    <comparator>EGG recordings from 23 breast fed colicky infants would be compared with a control group of  26 breast fed non-colicky infants using wavelet analysis</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early Detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine whether analysis of the EGG signal by CWT, could detect abnormal electrophysiological activity in babies with infant colic. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Voltage readings from the respiratory belt and EGG recordings were taken for periods of up to 3.5 hours, including whilst the baby was sleeping after feeding.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>NA</outcome>
      <timepoint>NA</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Infants recruited had ongoing signs of colic as diagnosed by a clinician and were screened by questionnaire to ensure that the child exhibited one or more of the reported characteristics; paroxysmal crying of a higher pitch with more tenseness and irregularity, paroxysmal crying particularly in the evening, paroxysmal crying for periods of more than 3 hours per day, paroxysmal crying for more than 3 days per week and paroxysmal crying more than three weeks duration, paroxysmal crying commencing during the first week of life and peaking during the second month of life. Infants recruited in the control group had no signs of colic as diagnosed by a clinician and were screened by a questionnaire to ensure that the child did not exhibit any of the above reported charachteristics</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>1</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Months</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>4</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Months</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Infants who were mechanically unwell </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>No power calculations were done as no one has previously studies the condition in infants with colic. The number of subjects were chosen based on an initial pilot study conducted by the group to determine the incidence of colic in infants. The initial pilot study did show that there is an underlying disorder but higher numbers of subjects were needed to provide a suitable basis for a power analysis to predict numbers in the current experimental context.  Data was analysed by multivariate statistics 
Differences between overall means of frequency, overall standard deviations, numbers of frequency values that fell below one standard deviation of the overall mean frequency and numbers of frequency values that were above one standard deviation from the overall mean frequency in the colicky and non-colicky groups were each compared by ANOVA.The pattern of variation of the three parameters between the two treatment groups was also explored by multivariate (discriminant) analysis. Both classical linear and quadratic models for discriminant analyses were employed, the latter to account for any departure from bivariate normal distribution </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Case control</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>25/02/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>4/12/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>49</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Wellington, Hawkesbay, Rangitekei, Tararua, Manawatu</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Massey University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Massey University (Turitea), Tennent drive, Palmerston North 4474</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Fonterra Co-operative Group Limited</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Private bag 11029, Fitzherbert Dairy Farm Road, Palmerston North 4442</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aetiology of infant colic is poorly understood with little evidence regarding the development of gastric and intestinal motility.  Its occurrence is a common concern to nursing mothers particularly in view of the fact that there are currently no tests that can readily distinguish any underlying pathology. The aim of the current work was to determine the incidence of gastric rhythm disorders in infants by comparing electrogastrography (EGG) signals by continuous wavelet analysis, to compare EGG patterns of non colicky versus colicky infants. Post prandial EGG recordings were obtained from 1) 26 breast fed non-colicky infants and 2) 23 breast fed colicky infants. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>NA</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>The study was first approved by Massey University Human Ethics Committee: Southern A 09/80 on 01/03/2010. An amendment o the trial was resubmitted to MUHEC on the 10th of July 2013 and received approval on 10/07/2013 . </publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Massey University Human Ethics Committee: Southern A </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Ethics Research Office, Courtyard Complex, Manawatu Campus, Massey University, Private bag 11222, Palmerston North 4442</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/07/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>09/80</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Roger Lentle</name>
      <address>Massey University Massey Institute of Food Science and Technology, School of Food and Nutrition College of Health Private bag 11222 Palmerston North 4442,</address>
      <phone>+64 (0)6 350 81402</phone>
      <fax>+64 (0)6 350 5657</fax>
      <email>R.G.Lentle@massey.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Roger Lentle</name>
      <address>Massey University Massey Institute of Food Science and Technology, School of Food and Nutrition College of Health Private bag 11222 Palmerston North 4442,</address>
      <phone>+64 (0)6 350 81402</phone>
      <fax>+64 (0)6 350 5657</fax>
      <email>R.G.Lentle@massey.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Roger Lentle</name>
      <address>Massey University Massey Institute of Food Science and Technology, School of Food and Nutrition College of Health Private bag 11222 Palmerston North 4442,</address>
      <phone>+64 (0)6 350 81402</phone>
      <fax>+64 (0)6 350 5657</fax>
      <email>R.G.Lentle@massey.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>