<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365020">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/09/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/09/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001067763</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Nutritional interventions for depression: An open label trial for nonresponders to probiotic treatment using a micronutrient formula.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The efficacy of a probiotic supplement in the treatment of depressive symptomatology in volunteers with moderate to very severe depression:
An open label trial using a micronutrient formula in non-responders.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1148-2095</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Open label trial using a micronutrient formula called Daily Essential Nutrients, made by Hardy Nutritionals. The key ingredients of this micronutrient formula include Vitamin A (as retinyl palmitate) 1920IU, Vitamin C (as ascorbic acid) 200mg, Vitamin D (as cholecalciferol) 1000IU, Vitamin E (as d-alpha tocopheryl succinate) 120IU, Vitamin K (as phylloquinone and menaquinone-7) 40mcg, Thiamin (as thiamin mononitrate) 20mg, Riboflavin 6mg, Niacin (as niacinamide) 30mg, Vitamin B6 (as pyridoxine hydrochloride) 23.3mcg, Folic acid (50% as L-methylfolate calcium) 500mcg, Vitamin B12 (as methylcobalamin) 300mcg, Biotin 360mcg, Pantothenic acid (as d-calcium pantothenate) 10mg, Calcium (as chelate) 440mg, Iron (as chelate) 4.6mg, Phosphorus (as chelate) 280mg, Iodine (from Pacific kelp) 68mcg, Magnesium (as chelate) 200mg, Zinc (as chelate) 16mg, Selenium (as chelate) 68mcg, Copper (as chelate) 2.4mg, Manganese (as chelate) 3.2mg, Chromium (as chelate) 208mcg, Molybdenum (as chelate) 48mcg, and Potassium (as chelate) 80mg. More detailed information, as well as a full ingredient list for the product, can be obtained from the manufacturer's website - http://www.hardynutritionals.com . The intervention requires the oral intake of 15 capsules per day (in 3 doses of 5, mid meal), for 8 weeks. Participants will be asked to record any doses missed as well as any unusual events in their life, in a study diary.</interventions>
    <comparator>NA - This is an open label single group study</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>MADRS score - Montgomery Asberg Depression Rating Scale - clinician
rated</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 8 weeks (end of trial)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>iCGI- Improved Clinical Global Improvement Scale - clinician-rated, severity and improvement</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>QIDS - Quick Inventory of Depressive Symptomatology - patient-rated</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4 weeks, 8 weeks (end of trial)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>DASS - depression, anxiety and stress scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4 weeks, 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>DAS - Dysfunctional Attitude Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4 weeks, 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>ATQ - automatic thoughts questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4 weeks, 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Must have been a participant in a previous study: An intervention using probiotics for depressive symptoms (Trial ID ACTRN12613000438752).

Must be a "non-responder" to the probiotic treatment after the open label phase. A response is classified as &gt;50% change on MADRS (primary outcome measure).

Must have a MADRS score of &gt;19 (moderate depression) at beginning of trial.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Identical to exclusion criteria for probiotic trial, as no new participants will be recruited (Trial ID ACTRN12613000438752).

Neurological disorder involving brain or other central function (e.g., epilepsy, MS, narcolepsy). 

Any serious medical condition for which major medical interventions are anticipated during the duration of the trial.

Any patient known to be allergic to the ingredients of the intervention.

Pregnancy or breastfeeding.

Any other medication with primarily central nervous system activity, including mood stabilizers. Participants must have been off of these medications for a minimum of four weeks prior to the trial.

Patients will be excluded temporarily if they have taken an oral antibiotic in the previous 6 weeks. If an antibiotic is begun during the course of the trial, that patient will be withdrawn from the study.

Any subject judged clinically to be at serious risk for suicide or violence in the opinion of the researchers. 

Participants will be asked to minimize their intake of colas, tea, coffee, alcohol, cigarettes and illicit drugs. These substances will be monitored as part of the trial.

Participants will be excluded if they take any antidepressant herbal supplement, including St Johns Wort and 5-HTP.

Renal, hepatic, cardiovascular and respiratory diseases

Any person whose immune system is known to be weakened (e.g. by HIV/AIDS, a genetic defect, long-term use of corticosteroids or taking immunosuppressive medications).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Upon completion of the probiotic intervention trial, non-responders to that intervention will be invited to participate in this trial with a new intervention. A new informed consent process will be undertaken and all participants who consent will all be given identical treatment (the micronutrient formula).</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Analysis of the outcome measures will involve conducting a repeated measures ANOVA, comparing mean scores on outcome measures at baseline, 4 weeks and 8 weeks. 

Proportion of responders will also be analysed - a response is defined as &gt;50% change on the MADRS from baseline.

All analyses will be done on intent-to-treat basis - each patient who provides informed consent will be included in the analysis, regardless of compliance with treatment. If any patient drops out before the final eight week follow-up visit, the last-observation-carried-forward technique will be used to impute the missing values. Complete documentation will be kept on non-completers, and their reasons for dropping out of the study prematurely. 

The individual changes will be summarised with 95% confidence intervals derived from the r-ANOVA. A two-sided p-value &lt;0.05 will be taken to indicate statistical significance.

The target sample size of 15 participants was determined from previous open label studies using micronutrients, whereby 15 participants was an adequate number to show significant change from pre to post measurements. Our experience with these micronutrients is that they usually have a large effect size, and so 15 is an adequate number to show change in preliminary, uncontrolled studies. However, the final number of participants will be dictated by the number of non-responders to probiotic treatment in the previous trial who choose to enter this new open label trial, so we may have more or less participants than our target.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/10/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/11/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/05/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>30/05/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>15</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>8</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/08/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Canterbury</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Julia Rucklidge</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Canterbury
Private Bag 4800
Christchurch 8140</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Canterbury</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Private Bag 4800
Christchurch 8140</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Canterbury</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Private Bag 4800
Christchurch 8140</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to evaluate the effectiveness of a micronutrient supplement in the treatment of depressive symptoms, for non-responders to the initial probiotic intervention in a previous trial. This micronutrient formula (Daily Essential Nutrients; and it's predecessor EMPowerplus) has proven efficacy for mood in trials on many different subjects, from people suffering with stress post earthquake, to people with ADHD, and more. The aim of this research study is to ascertain whether the supplement is
effective in improving symptoms of depression, in people who have not responded to previous treatment. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://bit.ly/UCnutritionresearch</trialwebsite>
    <publication>None to date</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern HDEC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
No 1 The Terrace
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6145</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/09/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>URA/12/05/013</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/09/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Amy Romijn</name>
      <address>University of Canterbury 
Private Bag 4800 
Christchurch 8140</address>
      <phone>6433642987ext 7705</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>julia.rucklidge@canterbury.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Amy Romijn</name>
      <address>University of Canterbury Private Bag 4800 Christchurch 8140</address>
      <phone>6433642987ext 7705</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amy.romijn@pg.canterbury.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Julia Rucklidge</name>
      <address>University of Canterbury Private Bag 4800 Christchurch 8140</address>
      <phone>+64 3 364 2987 ext. 7959</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>julia.rucklidge@canterbury.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Amy Romijn</name>
      <address>University of Canterbury Private Bag 4800 Christchurch 8140</address>
      <phone>+64 3 364 2987 ext. 7705</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amy.romijn@pg.canterbury.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>