<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370162">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/02/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/04/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000553471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy and safety of  dihydroartemisinin+piperaquine for the treatment of uncomplicated Plasmodium falciparum malaria in  Bosaso, Puntland, Somalia.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy and safety of  dihydroartemisinin+piperaquine for the treatment of uncomplicated Plasmodium falciparum malaria in  Bosaso, Puntland, Somalia.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Malaria</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>To assess the efficacy and safety of Dihydroartemisinin+Piperaquine (4 mg/kg DHA and 18 mg/kg Piperaquine once a day for 3 days) for the treatment of uncomplicated P. falciparum infection. The treatment will be given in tablets by oral. Eligible subjects will be treated for three days and followed up for 42 days. The daily doses of the study medicine will be administered under direct supervision.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group. It is a single arm study.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percent of treatment failures (early treatment failure + late clinical failure +late parasitological failure). This is composite primary outcome.

Enrolled patients will be assessed for parasitological (using microscopy) and clinical responses and treatment outcomes will be classified according to the latest WHO protocol.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Primary outcome (treatment failures) will be assessed on Days 2, 3, 7, 14, 21, 28, 35, 42 following initiation of Dihydroartemisinin+piperaquine.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percent of adverse event will be documented.

Known adverse events of Dihydroartemisinin+Piperaquine are asthenia, cough, diarrhoea, fever, loss of appetite, nausea, vomiting.

Parents or guardians of all enrolled patients will be asked routinely about previous symptoms and about symptoms that have emerged since the previous follow-up visit. When clinically indicated, patients will be evaluated and treated appropriately. All adverse events will be recorded on the case report form.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Secondary outcome (adverse events) will be assessed on Days 1, 2, 3, 7, 14, 21, 28, 35, 42 following initiation of Dihydroartemisinin+piperaquine.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prevalence of artemisinin resistance molecular markers (K13).

Parasite DNA extracted from the dried blood spots will be analyzed by PCR and sequencing for the presence of K13 (molecular marker for artemisinin resistance).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Day 0 (prior to initiation of the treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. age between six months and 60 years with the exception of 12-17 years old female minors and unmarried females 18 years and above;
2. mono-infection with P. falciparum detected by microscopy;
3. parasitaemia of 500200,000/microliter asexual forms;
4. presence of axillary temperature greater or equal to 37.5 degrees C or history of fever during the past 24 h
5. ability to swallow oral medication;
6. ability and willingness to comply with the study protocol for the duration of the study and to comply with the study visit schedule;
7. informed consent from the patient or from a parent or guardian in the case of children aged less than 18 years.
8. informed assent from any minor participant aged from 12 to 18 years; and
9.. consent for pregnancy testing from married female of 18 years and above.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Months</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. presence of general danger signs in children aged under 5 years or signs of severe  falciparum malaria according to the definitions of WHO;
2. weight under 5 kg;
3. mixed or mono-infection with another Plasmodium species detected by microscopy;
4. presence of severe malnutrition defined as a child aged 6-60 months has a mid-upper arm circumference below 115 mm)
5. presence of febrile conditions due to diseases other than malaria (e.g. measles, acute lower respiratory tract infection, severe diarrhea with dehydration) or other known underlying chronic or severe diseases (e.g. cardiac, renal and hepatic diseases, HIV/AIDS);
6. regular medication, which may interfere with antimalarial pharmacokinetics;
7. history of hypersensitivity reactions or contraindications to any of the medicine(s) being tested or used as alternative treatment(s);
8. a positive pregnancy test or breastfeeding of married women aged 18 years and above; and
9. unable to or unwilling to take pregnancy test or to use contraception for women of child-bearing age and who are sexually active.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients aged between 6 month and 60 years with uncomplicated malaria who meet the study inclusion criteria will be enrolled, treated on site with Dihydroartemisinin+piperaquine and monitored for 42 days. The follow-up will consist of a fixed schedule of check-up visits and corresponding clinical and laboratory examinations.</concealment>
    <sequence>Not applicable</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>None</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Treatment failure rate to dihydroartemisinin+piperaquine in the area is estimated to 5%. At a confidence level of 95% and a precision around the estimate of 5%, a minimum of 73 patients will be included. With a 20% increase to allow loss to follow-up and withdrawals during the 42-day follow-up period, 88 patients will be included in the study. 

The WHO excel software programs will be used for data management and analysis. Data will be analysed by two methods: the Kaplan-Meier method and per-protocol analysis. Patients who were subsequently lost to follow-up, had reinfections, or unknown PCR, will excluded from the per-protocol analysis of treatment outcomes, but included in the Kaplan-Meier analysis until the day of withdrawal from the study.

The final analysis will include:

1. a description of all patients screened and the distribution of reasons for non-inclusion in the study;
2. a description of all the patients included in the study;
3. the proportion of adverse events and serious adverse events in all the patients included in the study;
4. the proportion of patients lost to follow-up or withdrawn, with 95% confidence intervals and a list of reasons for withdrawal;
5. the cumulative incidence of success and failure rates at day 42, PCR-uncorrected and PCR-corrected; and
6. the proportion of early treatment failure, late clinical failure, late parasitological failure and adequate clinical and parasitological response at day 42 with 95% confidence intervals, PCR-uncorrected and PCR-corrected.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>4/01/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>30/03/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>88</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>92</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Somalia</country>
      <state>Puntland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Ministry of Health of Puntland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Wadajir Garowe Puntland state of Somalia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Somalia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ministry of Health of Puntland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Wadajir Garowe Puntland state of Somalia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Somalia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Nil</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Title: Efficacy and safety of  dihydroaretemisinin+piperaquine for the treatment of uncomplicated Plasmodium falciparum malaria in  Bosaso, Puntland, Somalia.

Purpose: To assess the efficacy and safety of Dihydroartemisinin-Piperaquine for treatment of uncomplicated falciparum malaria

Objective: To assess the efficacy and safety Dihydroartemisinin-Piperaquine for the treatment of uncomplicated P. falciparum malaria infections

Study Sites: study will be conducted in Bosaso site, North East Zone (Puntland) of Somalia. 

Study Period: The study started in Janauary 2016  and will continue until March 2016

Study Design: Single arm prospective study.

Patient population: Febrile patients aged between 6 months and 60 years, inclusive, with confirmed uncomplicated P. falciparum infection. Female minors aged 12-17 years and unmarried females aged 18 years and above will be excluded as subjecting them to pregnancy testing is unacceptable according to the local customs and cultures.

Sample Size: 88 patients will be enrolled.

Treatments and follow-up: Dihydroartemisinin-Piperaquine (daily dose for 3 days) will be given. Clinical and parasitological parameters will be monitored over a 42-day follow-up period to evaluate drug efficacy and safety.

Primary endpoints: The proportion of patients with early treatment failure, late clinical failure, late parasitological failure or an adequate clinical and parasitological response as indicators of efficacy. Recrudescence will be distinguished from re-infection by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) analysis. Day 3 malaria positivity rate will determined.

Secondary endpoints: 
1. The frequency of adverse events.
2. Frequency of molecular markers for artemisinin resistance (K13)
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Nil</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ministry of Health, Puntland</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Wadajir Garowe Puntland state of Somalia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/11/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>MoH/PL/297/2015</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/10/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Somalia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Abdikarim Hussein Hassan       </name>
      <address>Ministry of Health, Puntland
Wadajir Garowe Puntland state of Somalia
</address>
      <phone>+252907782859</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Abdikarimpl@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Somalia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Abdikarim Hussein Hassan  </name>
      <address>Ministry of Health, Puntland
Wadajir Garowe Puntland state of Somalia</address>
      <phone>+252907782859</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Abdikarimpl@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Somalia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Abdikarim Hussein Hassan  </name>
      <address>Ministry of Health, Puntland
Wadajir Garowe Puntland state of Somalia</address>
      <phone>+252907782859</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Abdikarimpl@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Somalia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Marian Warsame</name>
      <address>Global Malaria Programme
World health Organization
20 Avenue Appia, 
1211 Geneva 27 Switzerland
</address>
      <phone>+41 22 791 5076</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>warsamem@who.int</email>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>