<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369352">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/09/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/10/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001095550</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect on Hospitalisation and Cost Effectiveness of a Respiratory Coordinated Care Program for patients with Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease.
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A study of COPD Patients undergoing a Respiratory Coordinated Care Program and its effect on hospitalisation and cost for the 12 months before and after joining the program. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>COPD</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Epidemiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is a Respiratory Coordinated Care Program. This is a multidisciplinary program for chronic respiratory disease patients involving regular outpatient follow ups by nurse specialists with liaison with physiotherapists, occupational therapists, respiratory registrars and consultants.  These visits involve one on one home visits, initially weekly, then fortnightly and then monthly at the discretion of the treating nurse and team. At each visit, the patient's clinical state is assessed, as well as compliance with treatment, equipment supply and patient understanding of proper usage e.g. inhaler and spacer technique, referral to pulmonary rehabilitation as needed, and recognition of early clinical deterioration prompting an action plan whereby the community nurse would directly contact a respiratory physician or senior registrar, and early community treatment such as antibiotics, bronchodilators and steroids could be implemented.  The service also provides close follow up of patients post discharge from hospital in order to facilitate ongoing recovery from their illness, and allow more rapid discharge from hospital. Missed visits are followed up with phone calls.</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator treatment is the standard of care for COPD patients involving GP and respiratory physician follow ups on an individually determined basis. As this was not a randomised study, the comparator treatment was determined by the care patients received prior to joining the intervention.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospitalisation rate
- measured by using hospital and database records for number of hospitalisations and length of stay in 12 month period</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost to hospital
- simple cost analysis of costs of program including staff salaries, motor vehicle costs, medications and medical equipment, and calculating a cost of the program per patient. This was offset against savings made from changes in hospital admission rates and bed days, with 1 hospital bed day of a COPD admission conservatively estimated at $AUD 568 ($USD 400) based on the available literature</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>COPD by GOLD criteria, FEV1 &lt; 50% predicted, Age greater than or equal to 60, psychosocial stability </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>other primary respiratory diagnosis</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Not randomised, all patients in the study are enrolled in the program.</concealment>
    <sequence>N/A</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The intervention and comparator groups were compared using paired t-test and multiple regression analysis to address the impact of confounding factors. No power calculations have been performed.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/01/2007</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>31/12/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>147</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St George Hospital - Kogarah</hospital>
    <hospital>The Sutherland Hospital - Caringbah</hospital>
    <postcode>2217 - Kogarah</postcode>
    <postcode>2232 - Sutherland</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Respiratory Department St George Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>St George Hospital, Gray St, Kogarah, NSW, 2217</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>COPD patients were enrolled into an RCCP coordinated multidisciplinary program aimed at improving health outcomes and decreasing hospitalisation. Data from 2007-2012 was prospectively collected in a database, and retrospectively reviewed. Patients were analysed as to rates of hospitalisation in the 12 months prior to and after joining the program. The cost of the program was analysed against savings from decreased hospitalisation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Poster presentation
Aslam P., Man J., Behary J., Riskallah J., Ansary S., Kwan B., "Outcomes and Cost of COPD RCCP Program", Thoracic Society of Australia and New Zealand Respiratory Education Meeting November 15, 2013 

</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Ethics approval was obtained after enrollment in the intervention study was complete, as although data was prospectively collected, the intervention was set up in its own right, and it was unclear if a study was to be formally performed on the collected data. When a decision was made that the data was to be retrospectively analysed in a study, ethics approval was then sought and obtained, and data analysis then occurred. </publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>SESLHD HUMAN RESEARCH ETHICS COMMITTEE (SOUTHERN SECTOR)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>St George Hospital
Gray St, Kogarah, NSW, Australia 2217</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/04/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>LNR/12/STG/55</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/03/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Johnathan Man</name>
      <address>Department of Respiratory Medicine
Sutherland Hospital
Kingsway, Caringbah, NSW 2229
</address>
      <phone>+61434098777</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>johnathanjman@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Benjamin Kwan</name>
      <address>Department of Respiratory Medicine
Sutherland Hospital
Kingsway, Caringbah, NSW 2229
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 95407111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ben.kwan@sesiahs.health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Benjamin Kwan</name>
      <address>Department of Respiratory Medicine
Sutherland Hospital
Kingsway, Caringbah, NSW 2229
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 95407111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ben.kwan@sesiahs.health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Johnathan Man</name>
      <address>Department of Respiratory Medicine
Sutherland Hospital
Kingsway, Caringbah, NSW 2229
</address>
      <phone>+61434098777</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>johnathanjman@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>