<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372567">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/03/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/04/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000497303</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A study to evaluate the viability and efficacy of integrating the BeyondNow suicide prevention smartphone app into a telephone support service for callers who are experiencing suicidal thoughts.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A study to evaluate the viability and efficacy of integrating the BeyondNow suicide prevention smartphone app into a telephone support service for callers who are experiencing suicidal thoughts.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known.</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Suicidal ideation and behaviours</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Suicide</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Callers to a telephone support service, who present with mild to moderate suicidal ideation, will be given the option of creating a personalised safety plan using the 'BeyondNow' smartphone app. Support service counsellors will guide callers through the app installation process over the phone. The counsellors will then spend 10 - 15 minutes assisting callers to develop a safety plan and teaching them how to use the app during the initial phone call. The BeyondNow app provides users with the ability to develop a structured, and personally useful list of coping and help-seeking strategies which can be used to help cope with suicidal ideation during times of distress or crisis. The app allows users to document personalised warning signs of an impending crisis, ways to keep their environment safe, reasons for living, coping and distraction strategies, socialisation strategies, social contacts and professional support services. Callers who consent to participate in the research study, agree to use the BeyondNow app at their discretion for 6-weeks following contact with the telephone support service. Naturalistic use of the app will be monitored. All telephone support service counsellors hold a tertiary degree in a relevant dscipline, or are registered nurses that have a minimum of ten-years experience in mental health nursing. Counsellors also have at least three months relevant counselling experience, have knowledge of depression, anxiety and associated issues, and have received training from the researchers on safety planning and use of the BeyondNow app. </interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Telephone support service counsellor opinions regarding the integration of the BeyondNow app into support service call. Counsellor opinions will be gathered via a brief (1-minute) survey following each call using a survey designed specifically for this study. A qualitative interview designed specifically for this study will be used to gather counsellors' overall impressions at the end of the trial. </outcome>
      <timepoint>The brief (1-minute) survey will be completed following each call in which the BeyondNow was offered to a caller. The qualitative interview will be conducted at the end of trial, following cessation of recruitment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Telephone support service caller opinions regarding the integration of BeyondNow app into phone support service call. Caller opinions will be gathered via qualitative interview designed specifically for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline assessment by researchers, which will occur within three days of contact with the telephone support service. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participant self-report ratings of confidence in coping with suicidal ideation (Suicide Related Coping Scale).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 6-weeks.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participant self-report ratings of suicidal ideation (Columbia Suicide Severity Rating Scale - Brief version), </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2-weeks, 4-weeks, and 6-weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>App usage - measured via electronic app usage data, 


</outcome>
      <timepoint>Captured daily from baseline to end of intervention (6-weeks).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hopelessness - Measured using Beck Hopelessness Scale (4-item)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 6-weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceived burdensomeness: Measured using Interpersonal Needs Questionnaire (10-item).  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 6 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Thwarted belongingness: Measured using Interpersonal Needs Questionnaire (10-item).  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 6 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Emotional and Physical pain: Measured using a 4-item rating scale designed specifically for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2-weeks, 4-weeks, and 6 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Mild to moderate suicidal ideation in past 2-weeks.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Individuals deemed to be at immediate risk of suicide such that safety planning is contraindicated.
Individuals who do not posses a compatible smartphone. 
Intellectual disability. 
Presence of marked psychotic symptoms.
Impairment limiting app usage (e.g. Language, sight) </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Qualitative analysis for app user / counsellor opinion. 
Random effects regression models for change in outcome variables (Confidence in coping with suicidal thoughts; Suicidal ideation) from baseline to end of trial. 
Moderation analysis for app use (dose effect) on change in outcome variables from baseline to end of trial. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/04/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>2/10/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>18/12/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Wellington Rd
Clayton, VIC, 3168</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Movember Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>233 Punt Road
Richmond
VIC, 3121</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Smartphone apps are an effective way to provide health services to the community. The current study will investigate the viability and efficacy of integrating the BeyondNow suicide prevention smartphone app into a telephone support service for callers who are experiencing suicidal thoughts. Participants will install and set up their safety plan using the BeyondNow app with a telephone support service counsellor. The app will remain installed on participants' phones for the subsequent 6-weeks. Opinions on the integration of the BeyondNow app into the telephone support service will be collected. How the participants use their apps, as well as measures related to suicide (suicide coping, hopelessness, perceived burdensomeness, and emotional and physical pain) will also be collected over the 6-week trial. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash Univeristy Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Monash Research Office
26 Sports Walk
Monash University
Wellington Road
Clayton
VIC, 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/01/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2017-1510-8486</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Glenn Melvin</name>
      <address>Monash University Centre for Developmental Psychiatry &amp; Psychology
Building #1
270 Ferntree Gully Road
Notting Hill
VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+613 9902 4562</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>glenn.melvin@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Daniel Gresham</name>
      <address>Monash University Centre for Developmental Psychiatry &amp; Psychology
Building #1
270 Ferntree Gully Road
Notting Hill
VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+613 9905 0163</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>daniel.gresham@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Glenn Melvin</name>
      <address>Monash University Centre for Developmental Psychiatry &amp; Psychology
Building #1
270 Ferntree Gully Road
Notting Hill
VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+613 9902 4562</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>glenn.melvin@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Daniel Gresham</name>
      <address>Monash University Centre for Developmental Psychiatry &amp; Psychology
Building #1
270 Ferntree Gully Road
Notting Hill
VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+613 9905 0163</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>daniel.gresham@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>