<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369488">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/11/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/02/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000210471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of Self-Efficacy Enhancing Program on Foot Self-Care Behaviour of Elderly with Diabetes in Old Folks Home, Peninsular Malaysia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of Self-Efficacy Enhancing Program on Foot Self-Care Behaviour of Elderly with Diabetes </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Foot self-care behaviour</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Design: Cluster Randomized Trial (CRT), two groups (interventions and controls), single blind 
The theoretical background of the education program is based from Albert Banduras Self-efficacy theory.
The intervention is in a group seminar of education regarding foot care (8-10 respondents/ group/ session)
The program encompasses of 20 minutes of a power point presentation covered the following topics: awareness of risk factors and its complications, foot self-care behavior including daily washing, inspecting foot for problems, moisturizing, wearing proper shoes and socks; toenail and feet care; and when to seek help from a healthcare professional. 
At the end of seminar, the researcher will encourage active role and leave the respondents to perform foot self-care behavior independently. A pamphlet regarding foot care will be given to the respondents. 
The local nurses (research enumerator) will receive a checklist reminder of foot self-care to continuously support the respondents to perform the behaviour. 
Respondents will be encouraged to establish realistic goals on new targets (tailored action plan) in performing foot self-care behaviour. They need to start work in small realistic steps so that they will be more focus, confidence and become motivated to perform the desired behaviour (mastery experience). Respondents will be given a hand-out (symbolic modelling) so that they will perform the foot self-care behaviour daily. In order to maintain their confidence level, a positive feedback and strong encouragement need to be given continuously (verbal persuasion). During follow-up visit (at week 4), the researcher (registered nurse) will discuss (one to one) with respondents, sharing experience and get feedback on goals, examination of obstacles and problem situations (self-appraisal). 
A routine visit to the respondents will be done weekly (to monitor adherence) till the end of the program (week-12). 
Frequency and duration of administration: The program will be carried out for 12 weeks and consisted of a total of 4 visits: 1) Baseline information (20 minutes), 2) the program (within 4 weeks after baseline information for selected clusters) (week 0; 20 minutes), 3) Follow-up (week 4; 20 minutes for one to one discussion and 20 minutes for answering the questionnaire) and 4) evaluation (week 12; 20 minutes for answering the questionnaire). </interventions>
    <comparator>The control group (approximately 3 clusters/old folks home) will receive a usual health care. 
Usual health care in this study is defined by a routine health care for diabetic patients received from the local health care provider in the old folks home 
After completion the program, the control group will receive the same program as the intervention group (waiting list) after 12 weeks. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Foot self-care behaviour, assessed using a modified version of the Diabetes Foot Self-Care Behaviour Scale (DFSBS) (Chin &amp; Huang, 2013)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 4 and 12 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Foot care efficacy expectation, assessed using a modified version of the Foot Care Confidence Scale (FCCS) (Sloan, 1998)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 4 and 12 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The foot care outcome expectation (FCOE). The score was designed specifically for this study</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 4 and 12 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The knowledge on foot care (KFC). The score was designed specifically for this study</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 4 and 12 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life, assessed using a modified version of the Neuropathy and Foot Ulcer Specific Quality of Life (FS-QOL) (Vileikyte et al., 2003)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 4 and 12 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Foot condition, assessed using a modified version of the foot score (Baba et al, 2015)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 12 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Program acceptability, assessed using a modified version of the Abbreviated Acceptability Rating Profile (AARP) (Tarnowski &amp; Simonian, 1992) </outcome>
      <timepoint> 12 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The respondent:
1)	aged 60 years or more
2)	have been diagnosed with diabetes (old or new)
3)	presented with or without diabetic foot problems
4)	Malaysian. 
5)	able to communicate sufficiently well (English or Malay) to understand the education program. 
6)	able to perform activity daily living independently (e.g., bathing, feeding, grooming etc.). 
7)	have no major complications which would interfere with foot self-care behaviour (such as blind, mute and deaf and stroke).
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1)	Respondents who are currently has been diagnosed with mental health problems (psychotic/ unstable conditions)
2)	Respondents who are having impaired in cognitive level. 
3)	Respondents who are having depression. 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation process will be concealed by numbered containers</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using "lottery/ fish-bowl" technique</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>4/01/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>4/03/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>152</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>76</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/07/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Associate Prof Dr Hejar Abdul Rahman</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Community Health Department
Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences
Universiti Putra Malaysia
43400, Serdang, Selangor
Malaysia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Malaysia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Universiti Putra Malaysia  </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Research Management Centre
Universiti Putra Malaysia
43400, Serdang, Selangor
Malaysia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Malaysia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A cluster randomized trial; two arms (intervention and control), single-blind study will be carried out. The intervention group will receive a self-efficacy enhancing program on foot self-care behaviour while the control group will receive a usual health care.
The aim of the program is, the improvement on foot self-care behaviour (primary outcome), foot efficacy expectation, foot outcome expectation, knowledge on foot care, quality of life and the foot score (secondary outcome) after completion of the program. 
The control group will receive the same intervention program at the end of the study.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethic Committee for Research Involving Human Subjects (Universiti Putra Malaysia)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ethic Committee for Research Involving Human Subjects,
Universiti Putra Malaysia, 43400 UPM Serdang,
Selangor, MALAYSIA
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/08/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>FPSK(FR15)P021</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/07/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Malaysia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Department of Social Welfare</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Department of Social Welfare
Aras 6, 9-18, No 55 Persiaran Perdana
Presint 4, 62100, Putrajaya, Malaysia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/11/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>JKMM 100/12/5/2: 2015 / 003</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/10/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Malaysia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Siti Khuzaimah Ahmad Sharoni</name>
      <address>Nursing Department,
Faculty of Health Sciences,
Universiti Teknologi MARA
Puncak Alam Campus,
42300, Puncak Alam,
Selangor, Malaysia </address>
      <phone>+60192119284</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sitik123@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Dr Hejar Abdul Rahman</name>
      <address>Community Health Department,
Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences,
43400, Universiti Putra Malaysia,
Serdang, Malaysia</address>
      <phone>+6012-2362351</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hejar@upm.edu.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Dr Hejar Abdul Rahman</name>
      <address>Community Health Department,
Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences,
43400, Universiti Putra Malaysia,
Serdang, Malaysia</address>
      <phone>+60122362351</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hejar@upm.edu.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>