<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369113">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/01/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/02/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000136404</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pilot, comparative, randomized, controlled trial assessing the safety and efficacy of manuka honey in the treatment of sinonasal bacterial infections in chronic rhinosinusitis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Pilot, comparative, randomized controlled trial assessing the safety and efficacy of manuka honey augmented with methylglyoxal targeting bacterial infections and biofilms in patients with Chronic Rhinosinusitis in a clinical setting  </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1173-1933</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic rhinosinusitis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients in the treatment group will receive 28 pre-prepared sinonasal flush bottles containing 240mL of 16.5% manuka honey and 1.3mg/mL methylglyoxal.  They will be asked to utilize the flushes twice daily for 14 days. They will also receive 20 encapsulated dextrose tablets and will be requested to take these orally twice a day for 10 days in parallel with the honey flushes.

Patients are asked to return any unused bottles and/or tablets at the end of the study to monitor treatment adherence.  </interventions>
    <comparator>Patients in the control group will receive 28 pre-prepared sinonasal flush bottles containing an isotonic saline solution.  They will be asked to utilize the flushes twice daily for 14 days. They will also receive 20 culture directed antibiotic tablets and will be requested to take these orally twice a day for 10 days.

The antibiotic to be employed will be selected by the treating doctor and will be culture directed, depending on the bacterial pathogen in question and the pathogens sensitivity to antibiotics.  Due to this the dosage will also vary and again this will be determined by the treating doctor.

Patients are asked to return any unused bottles and/or tablets at the end of the study to monitor treatment adherence.  </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Removal of active infection.  This will be assess through endoscopic evaluation of the nose as well as by taking a swab from the patients nose to identify if any pathogenic bacteria are present.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately post-treatment </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of endoscopic score.  This will be assessed by endoscopically examining the nasal passage of the patients and recording this examination.  The video will then be scored by a blinded observer using the Lund-Kennedy scoring system.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately post-treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessing the safety of the manuka honey flushes.  This will be done by having patients self report any discomfort, pain or health problems that occur during the treatment period. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately post-treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of symptom scores. This will be assessed by asking patients to fill in two questionnaires regarding their symptoms.  This will utilize the two validated questionnaires the SNOT-22 and Visual Analogue Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately post-treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prevention of future bacterial infections.  This will be assessed by having patients attend clinics 3 and 6 months post-treatment to assess if they have continued to experience active infections. The nasal passage will be visualised using endoscopic techniques and if signs of an active infection are present, a swab will be taken and sent for microbiological analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 and 6 months post-treatment
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Long term assessment of endoscopic score.  This will be assessed by endoscopically examining the nasal passage of the patients and recording this examination.  The video will then be scored by a blinded observer using the Lund-Kennedy scoring system.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 and 6 months post-treatment
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Long term assessment of symptom scores. This will be assessed by asking patients to fill in two questionnaires regarding their symptoms.  This will utilize the two validated questionnaires the SNOT-22 and Visual Analogue Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 and 6 months post-treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(1)	Those who have had symptoms of chronic rhinosinusitis (nasal discharge, postnasal drip, nasal obstruction, facial pain and pressure, lack of sense of smell) that has been previously persistent for greater than 3 months 
(2)	Have had at least one operation for their chronic rhinosinusitis 
(3)	Continue to have ongoing symptoms despite surgical management 
(4)	Have a positive sinonasal swab that indicates a bacterial infection
(5)	Over 18 years of age 
(6)	Are able to give written informed consent 
(7)	Are local patients who will be returning to this centre for postoperative follow-up care
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>90</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(1)	A diagnosis of cystic fibrosis 
(2)	Pregnant or breastfeeding
(3)	Immunocompromised patients
(4)	Patients actively taking oral steroids
(5)	Patients who have used antibiotics within 1 month prior to the trial.
(6)	Fructose intolerance/allergy
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The allocation will involve the investigator contacting the person who is the holder of the allocation schedule.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation will be employed.  This will be undertaken using the software excel</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Differences between the control and treatment group will be assessed statistically using un-paired T-tests.  This includes change in SNOT-22, VAS and Lund-Kennedy score. To compare the ability of control and manuka honey groups to remove the active bacterial infection, Fishers exact or chi-squared tests will be employed.

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>8/02/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/02/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital - Woodville</hospital>
    <postcode>5011 - Woodville South</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Adelaide University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Adelaide
SA 5005
AUSTRALIA</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Adelaide</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Otolaryngology
28 Woodville Rd
Woodville South 5011
South Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Department of Otolaryngology, The Queen Elizabeth Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of Otolaryngology
28 Woodville Rd
Woodville South 5011
South Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this project is to develop a clinically safe and effective treatment against bacterial infections in patients with chronic rhinosinustis (CRS). Current standard antibiotic therapy often fails to treat sinonasal infections, and we therefore need to develop novel, effective therapeutics.  Previous in vitro and in vivo work have found manuka honey augmented with additional active ingredient methylglyoxal (MGO) to be effective against a bacterial infections.  We hypothesis that manuka honey with augmented MGO will effectively treat infections in the sinonasal region of patients with CRS.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital, Lyell McEwin Hospital and Modbury Hospital HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital
Ethics: DX465101
Ground Floor, Basil Hetzel Institute
28 Woodville Road
WOODVILLE SOUTH  SA  5011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/08/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/TQEHLMH/165</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>13/07/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter-John Wormald</name>
      <address>The Queen Elizabeth hospital
28 Woodville Rd,
Woodville, 5011
South Australia</address>
      <phone>+61882227158</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peterj.wormald@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter-John Wormald</name>
      <address>The Queen Elizabeth hospital
28 Woodville Rd,
Woodville, 5011
South Australia</address>
      <phone>+61882227158</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peterj.wormald@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sarah Vreugde</name>
      <address>The Queen Elizabeth hospital
28 Woodville Rd,
Woodville, 5011
South Australia</address>
      <phone>+61882227158</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sarah.vreugde@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter-John Wormald</name>
      <address>The Queen Elizabeth hospital
28 Woodville Rd,
Woodville, 5011
South Australia</address>
      <phone>+61882227158</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peterj.wormald@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>