<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369461">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/10/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/10/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001084572</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparative assessment of the absorption of a generic formulation of anagrelide capsule against the innovator anagrelide capsule conducted under fasting conditions in healthy male and female volunteers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A single dose, randomized, blinded, bioequivalence study of a test formulation of anagrelide capsule in a 2 way crossover comparison against the innovator anagrelide capsule conducted under fasting conditions in healthy male and female volunteers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1174-8095</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Bioequivalence study conducted in healthy volunteers comparing two formulations of anagrelide with no health condition or problem studied. 

Although this study is being conducted in healthy volunteers who are not being treated for the condition to which the medicine is used, anagrelide is a platelet-reducing agent . It is used to decrease the risk of blood clots in patients who have thrombocythaemia (too many platelets in the blood). It works to decrease production of platelets in the blood.. </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Single dose, crossover study design whereby each participant receives the test formulation of anagrelide (1 x 0.5 mg) on one occasion and the innovator formulation of anagrelide (1 x 0.5 mg) on one occasion with each dose seperated by a one week washout period. The intervention for this trial is the test formulation of anagrelide.

No water is allowed for 1 hour prior to dosing until 1 hour after dosing (except for the water consumed with the dose). 
Participants are required not to eat for 10 hours before receiving each dose and to fast for approximately 4 hours after receiving each dose. Bathroom visits will be supervised to ensure no unauthorised water or food intake and for personal safety. Participants will be confined at the Clinical Site for 10 hours prior to dosing to ensure compliance and will be monitored and for 8 hours after dosing.

Standard meals will be consumed at the Clinical Site with no additional food intake allowed. Alcohol breath testing will be performed upon each participant reporting to the Clinical Site 10 hours prior to dosing.

Pre and post study laboratory tests will be completed to assess the health of participants along with HIV, Hepatitis and drugs of abuse testing. 

Each dose will be taken orally with 240 ml of water at ambient temperature. Medication must be swallowed whole and a mouth check will be conducted to ensure the medication has been taken as directed.</interventions>
    <comparator>Single dose, crossover study design whereby each participant receives the test formulation of anagrelide (1 x 0.5 mg) on one occasion and the innovator formulation of anagrelide (1 x 0.5 mg) on one occasion with each dose seperated by a one week washout period. The comparator/control for this trial is the innovator formulation of anagrelide.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the bioavailability of anagrelide (as summarised by Cmax and AUC) for the formulation. All plasma samples will be assayed for anagrelide using one fully validated LC/MS/MS method. Validation will be conducted to comply with EU and FDA guidelines.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 0.25, 0.5, 0.75, 1, 1.25, 1.5, 1.75, 2, 2.25, 2.5, 3, 3.5, 4, 4.5, 5, 6, 7 and 8 hours</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to maximum peak concentration (Tmax) will be determined by plasma sample analysis. Tmax will be the time where the maximum concentration occurred in the sample points.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 0.25, 0.5, 0.75, 1, 1.25, 1.5, 1.75, 2, 2.25, 2.5, 3, 3.5, 4, 4.5, 5, 6, 7 and 8 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy male and non-pregnant females
Aged between 18 and 55
Non-smoker
BMI between 18 and 33 inclusive
Normal, healthy individuals as determined by medical history, physical examination, ECG, blood pressure and laboratory tests
Able to provide written informed consent </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any history of recent recurrent attacks of bronchitis, asthma, migraine headaches
Concomitant drug therapy of any kind
Sensitivity to anagrelide or any other similar class of medicines, or the excipients of anagrelide
History of any conditions that might interfere with the absorption, distribution, metabolism or excretion of the drug
Females who are pregnant and/or are breastfeeding
Smoker (anyone who has smoked in the last 6 months)
History of alcohol or drug abuse or dependency
Participation in a drug study within 60 days of the start of the study or donated blood in the 60 days preceding the study.
Volunteers for whom the Clinical Investigator believes, for any reason, that participation would not be an acceptable risk </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All formulations will be labelled as Formulation A and B. The identification of each treatment will only be known to the Managing Director and the Section Head - Trials and Regulatory Affairs. 

Each participant will be identified by a 3 digit screening number and a 2 digit subject number. The screening number will be issued once the participant has given written consent to participate in the study and the two digit subject number (randomisation number) after acceptance into the study </concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation list will be prepared using a computer program for a balanced two-way crossover design.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Bio-equivalence</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/11/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>24</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Otago</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Zenith Technology Corp Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>156 Frederick Street
Dunedin 9016 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Southern Cross Pharma Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>56 Illabunda Drive
Malua Bay
NSW 2536</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The objective of this study is to evaluate the bioequivalence of the test (new) formulation of 1 x 0.5 mg against the reference formulation (innovator brand of 1 x 0.5 mg anagrelide capsule) following oral administration of a single dose of 0.5 mg in healthy male and female subjects under fasting conditions.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern A Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
1 the Terrace
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6145 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/10/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>15/NTA/139</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/09/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Noelyn Hung</name>
      <address>Zenith Technology Corporation Limited
156 Frederick Street (PO Box 1777)
Dunedin 9016</address>
      <phone>+6434779669</phone>
      <fax>+6434779605</fax>
      <email>noelyn.hung@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Linda Folland</name>
      <address>Zenith Technology Corporation Limited
156 Frederick Street (PO Box 1777)
Dunedin 9016</address>
      <phone>+6434779669</phone>
      <fax>+6434779605</fax>
      <email>linda.folland@zenithtechnology.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Cheung-Tak Hung</name>
      <address>Zenith Technology Corporation Limited
156 Frederick Street (PO Box 1777)
Dunedin 9016</address>
      <phone>+6434779669</phone>
      <fax>+6434779605</fax>
      <email>tak.hung@zenithtechnology.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>