<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343123">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/08/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/08/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000854932</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Randomised, Placebo Controlled, Double-Blind, Single Ascending Dose and Multiple Dose Study to Assess the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics of Subcutaneous Doses of ATL1103 in Healthy Adult Male Subjects</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomised, Placebo Controlled, Double-Blind, Single Ascending Dose and Multiple Dose Study to Assess the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics of Subcutaneous Doses of ATL1103 in Healthy Adult Male Subjects</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>ATL1103 is being developed as a potential treatment for diseases of excessive growth hormone and insulin-like growth hormone (IGF)-I action, including the condition acromegaly.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Subjects will receive ATL1103 (growth hormone (GH) receptor antisense oligonucleotide) as a sterile aqueous solution administered by subcutaneous injection.

Stage A is a single asending dose study.  Each subject receives only one dose level once during the study.  The safety data from each cohort is reviewed before dosing of the next cohort.  The dose of ATL1103 administrered is 25 mg for cohort 1, 75 mg for cohort 2, 250 mg for cohort 3 and 400 mg for cohort 4.   
For Stage B, six doses of ATL1103 will be administered on days 1, 3, 5, 7, 14 and 21 of the study.  The time between stages, and the dose per injection for stage B, is to be decided on review of the safety data from Stage A.  For Stage B, subjects will be monitored for a further two weeks after the completion of dosing.</interventions>
    <comparator>The placebo is an aqueous buffered saline solution colour-matched for ATL1103.  The placebo will be administered by a single subcutaneous injection in stage A, and on days 1, 3, 5, 7, 14 and 21 in stage B.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A primary objective of the study is to evaluate the safety and tolerability of a single and multiple subcutaneous doses of ATL1103 when administered to healthy adult male volunteers.  Safety and tolerability will be assessed by serum chemistry, haematology, urinalysis, physical exam, vital signs and electrocardiogram.</outcome>
      <timepoint>For Stage A: Subjects will receive the dose of ATL1103 and remain in the unit for 24 hours.  There are three follow up visits on days 3, 4 and 7.

For Stage B: Subjects will be confined in the unit for seven days then return for seven out-patient visits up to Day 35.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Single and multiple dose pharmacokinetic parameters including concentration-time profile of ATL1103.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Plasma and urine will be collected for ATL1103 assays at various timepoints pre- and post-dose.  

Stage A 
Plasma will be collected pre-dose, and for 10 timepoints in the 24 hours after administration of ATL1103, and again on days 3, 4 and 7.  Urine will be collected for 24 hours after the administration of ATL1103.

Stage B
Plasma will be collected pre-dose, then at 11 timepoints in the 48 hours after administration of ATL1103 on days 1 and 21.  Samples will also be collected on days 3, 5, 7, 14, 28 and 35.  Urine will be collected for 24 hours after the first dose of ATL1103, and again on days 7 and 21.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Investigation of the pharmacodynamic effect of ATL1103 will be assessed by measurement of serum insulin-like growth factor (IGF)-I levels.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Serum will be collected for IGF-I assay four times in the first week, then weekly to Day 35 of the study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Aged from 18 years up to 45 years (inclusive).
2. Male 
3.  Body Mass Index (BMI) BMI of 19 to 30 kg/m2 with body weight of between 70kg and 90kg.
4.  Healthy as determined by a medical history 
5.  Serum IGF-1 levels within the normal range 
6.  Adequate venous access 
7.  Fluent in the English language.
8.  Written informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Volunteers with any of the following criteria will not be eligible for participation in this study:
1. Hypersensitivity.  History of allergy and/or hypersensitivity to any of the stated ingredients of the formulations.  A known hypersensitivity to lidocaine or all surgical dressings which may be used in the study procedures.
2. Medical Conditions
a) History of clinically significant gastrointestinal, hepatic, renal, cardiovascular, dermatological, immunological, respiratory, endocrine, oncological, neurological, metabolic, psychiatric disease or haematological disorders.
b) Any history of clinically significant cardiac arrhythmias or the presence of clinically significant abnormalities on ECG at Screening. 
c) Any evidence or history of hypotension or hypertension in the opinion of the PI following repeat assessment.  
d) Any history of asthma during the last 10 years.
e) A calculated creatinine clearance of less than 75 mL/min.
f)  Any predisposing condition that in the opinion of the Investigator might interfere with the absorption, distribution, metabolism and/or excretion of drugs.
g) History of abnormal bleeding tendencies or thrombophlebitis unrelated to venepuncture or intravenous cannulation, or a history of Hepatitis B, a positive test for Hepatitis B surface antigen, a history of Hepatitis C, a positive test for Hepatitis C antibody, a history of HIV infection or demonstration of HIV antibodies.
h) Inability to tolerate repeated venepuncture.
3. Laboratory Status.  Any evidence of organ dysfunction, or any deviation in clinical laboratory values which is confirmed upon re-examination to be clinically significant (i.e., in the opinion of the PI would jeopardise the safety of the subject or impact on the validity of the study results), including a liver function test (LFT) &gt; upper limit of normal (ULN).  Total bilirubin levels &gt; 1.5 x ULN will be allowed if associated with Gilberts syndrome.
4. Ethanol Use. Regular drinkers of more than four (4) units of alcohol daily (1 unit = 300 mL beer, 1 glass wine, 1 measure spirit) or those who may have difficulty abstaining from alcohol during the 48 hours prior to dose administration and until completion of blood sampling on Day 2 for the single-dose cohorts (Stage A) or Day 7 for the multiple-dose cohorts (Stage B).
5. Drug and Alcohol Abuse.  History of, or current evidence of, abuse of alcohol or any drug substance, licit or illicit, or positive urine drug and alcohol screen for drugs of abuse and alcohol.
6. Smoking. Current smoker of not more than 5 cigarettes or equivalent per day prior to commencing the study, unable to completely stop smoking during the study.
7. Medication
a) Difficulty in abstaining from any prescription medications for 14 days prior to dose administration and for the duration of the study.
b) Difficulty in abstaining from over-the-counter (OTC) medications or herbal supplements for seven days prior to dose administration and for the duration of the study.
8. Administration site. Any tattoos in the anterior abdominal area which, in the opinion of the Investigator would preclude accurate local tolerance assessments of injection sites.
9. Xanthine Use. Difficulty in abstaining from food and/or beverages that contain caffeine or other xanthines 
(e.g., coffee, tea, cola and chocolate) during the 24 hours prior to dose administration and whilst confined at the clinical facility.
10. Psychiatric or Psychological Disorder.	History of any psychiatric illness or psychological disorder which may impair the ability to provide written informed consent or participate in the study.
11. Protocol Compliance. Poor compliers or those unlikely to attend the Unit.
12. Recent Study Participation.  Receipt of any drug as part of a research study within 30 days of initial dose administration in this study. 
13.  Blood Donation.  Standard blood donation (usually 550 mL) within the 12-week period before dose administration.
14.  Dietary Habits. Unusual dietary habits, including vegetarian diets and excessive or unusual vitamin intakes.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence>A randomisation schedule will be generated by a statistician using a computer program.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>28/06/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>36</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Antisense Therapeutics Limited</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>6 Wallace Avenue
Toorak  Vic  3142</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Antisense Therapeutics Limited</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>6 Wallace Avenue
Toorak  Vic   3142</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>ATL1103 is being developed as a potential treatment for diseases of excessive growth hormone and insulin-like growth hormone (IGF-I) action.  This is the first in man study for ATL1103, and is being conducted as a randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blind trial.  Thirty six healthy male subjects will participate in the study. In stage A, subjects will receive one dose of either placebo or ATL1103 (at a dose of 25 mg, 75 mg, 250 mg or 400 mg).  In stage B, subjects will receive 6 doses of placebo or ATL1103 (at a dose to be determined after review of the safety data from Stage A). All treatments will be administered by subcutaneous injection.  
The primary objectives of the study is to evaluate the safety and tolerability of single or multiple injections of ATL1103, and to investigate the pharmacokinetic profiles of ATL1103 after subcutaneous administration.  The effect of ATL1103 on serum IGF-I levels will also be monitored.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Henry Buck Building
Austin Hospital
145 Studley Road
HEIDELBERG  VIC  3084</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/06/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H2011/04315</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>21/04/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Lynne Atley</name>
      <address>6 Wallace Avenue
Toorak  VIC  3142</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9827 8999</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 98271166</fax>
      <email>lynne.atley@antisense.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sue Turner</name>
      <address>6 Wallace Avenue
Toorak  VIC  3142</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9827 8999</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 98271166</fax>
      <email>info@antisense.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sue Turner</name>
      <address>6 Wallace Avenue
Toorak  VIC  3142</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9827 8999</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9827 1166</fax>
      <email>susan.turner@antisense.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>