<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372132">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/01/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/02/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000190303</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Functional brain reorganization enhanced by a novel gait training  evidenced by brain connectivity during treadmill walking in chronic stroke</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Functional brain reorganization enhanced by a novel gait training  evidenced by brain connectivity during treadmill walking in chronic stroke</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Subjects in the experimental group received 30 minutes of turning-based treadmill training for 12 sessions in 4 weeks.

a)	A rotational treadmill was designed to provide turning-based treadmill training. This treadmill is similar to a regular treadmill except for its circular running motor belt (0.8-m radius), which forces patients to continually turn rather than walk straight. Safety features included front and side handrails around the walking area, a harness connected to an overhead suspension system, and an emergency stop button located on the side handrail. Participants were trained in both directions, with the affected leg as the inner limb for 15 minutes and then as the outer limb for 15 minutes with a 5-minute break in between. After completing the turning-based treadmill training, a 10-minute ambulation training was followed.
b)	The training session was performed as individual one-on-one sessions at the study site.
c)	During each training session, an experienced physical therapist stood bedside and encouraged participants to walk with large strides and upright posture. 
d)	As progressively faster speeds are needed to continue challenging the locomotor abilities of individuals with hemiparesis, the treadmill speed, which began as each individuals comfortable turning speed on level ground, was increased by increments of 0.05 m/s every 5 minutes as tolerated. The criteria for increasing speed was determined by the ability to remain an upright posture and a perceived exertion of somewhat hard or lower (ie, a Borg rating of perceived exertion &lt;13).
e)	The register of attendance at sessions was checked by physical therapist.

</interventions>
    <comparator>Subjects in the control group received 30 minutes of regular treadmill training for 12 sessions in 4 weeks.

Other than the type of treadmill, the training protocol was the same as that described for the experimental group. Training speed was initially set at the individuals comfortable walking speed on level ground and increased by increments of 0.05 m/s every 5 minutes as tolerated. Participants received 30 minutes of regular treadmill training, followed by a 10-minute ambulation training similar to the experimental group.  </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>One of the primary outcome is cortico-cortical connectivity during regular treadmill walking. EEG, EMG, and footswitch signals during treadmill walking were simultaneously recorded from Ag/AgCl electrodes using a 40-channel QuickAmp amplifier (32 EEG channels, 4 bipolar channels for EMG and 4 auxiliary channels for footswitch), and Brain Vision Recorder software (Brain Products, Gilching, Germany). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Cortico-cortical connectivity during regular treadmill walking was assessed before intervention and after completing the 12-session training.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Another primary outcome is cortico-muscular connectivity during regular treadmill walking. EEG, EMG, and footswitch signals during treadmill walking were simultaneously recorded from Ag/AgCl electrodes using a 40-channel QuickAmp amplifier (32 EEG channels, 4 bipolar channels for EMG and 4 auxiliary channels for footswitch), and Brain Vision Recorder software (Brain Products, Gilching, Germany). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Cortico-muscular connectivity during regular treadmill walking was assessed before intervention and after completing the 12-session training.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>One of secondary outcome is overground gait speed. The gait performance at comfortable walking speed were obtained from the GAITRite system (CIR system, Inc, Havertown, PS), which contains pressure-sensitive sensors. The walkway was 4.75 m long and 0.9 m wide, and the pressure-sensitive area was 4.30 m long and 0.61 m wide. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Gait performance was assessed before intervention and after completing the 12-session training.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Another secondary outcome is overground  temporal gait symmetry. The gait performance at comfortable walking speed were obtained from the GAITRite system (CIR system, Inc, Havertown, PS), which contains pressure-sensitive sensors. The walkway was 4.75 m long and 0.9 m wide, and the pressure-sensitive area was 4.30 m long and 0.61 m wide. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Gait performance was assessed before intervention and after completing the 12-session training.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants with stroke had to satisfy the following criteria: (a) 6 months post first-ever stroke with unilateral motor deficits, (b) ability to walk independently for at least 6 m with or without use of walking aids (to ensure they were able to complete the 5-m walk test used in the current study), (c) a Brunnstrom stage of affected lower extremity greater than 3, and (d) a score greater than 24 on the mini-mental state examination (MMSE).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>37</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>71</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria were (a) unstable medical conditions (eg, deep vein thrombosis, aspiration pneumonia, or superimposed sepsis) and (b) history of other diseases known to interfere with participation in the study (eg, heart failure, hemi-neglect, or diabetic neuropathy).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>13/09/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>31/05/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>18</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>28/06/2013</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>National Yang Ming University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>No.155, Sec. 2, Linong St., Beitou Dist., Taipei City 112, Taiwan (R.O.C.)</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname> National Health Research Institutes of the Republic of China</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>35 Keyan Road, Zhunan, Miaoli County 35053, Taiwan</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This was a randomized controlled trial with pre and post assessment study. Subjects in the experimental group received 30 minutes of turning-based treadmill training for 12 sessions in 4 weeks, and subjects in the control group received 30 minutes of regular treadmill training for 12 sessions in 4 weeks. Cortico-cortical connectivity and cortico-muscular connectivity during regular treadmill walking and overground gait performance (speed and temporal symmetry) were assessed before intervention and after completing the 12-session training. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Taipei City Hospital </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>No.145, Zhengzhou Rd., Datong Dist., Taipei City 10341, Taiwan (R.O.C.)</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/08/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ray-Yau Wang</name>
      <address>Department of Physical Therapy and Assistive Technology. No.155, Sec.2, Linong Street, Taipei, 112 Taiwan (ROC)</address>
      <phone>+886928231905</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rywang@ym.edu.tw</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>I-Hsuan Chen</name>
      <address>Department of Physical Therapy. No.452, Huanqiu Rd. Luzhu Dist., Kaohsiung City 82144 Taiwan (R.O.C.) </address>
      <phone>+886 7-6979374</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ihchen@ms.szmc.edu.tw</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>I-Hsuan Chen</name>
      <address>Department of Physical Therapy. No.452, Huanqiu Rd. Luzhu Dist., Kaohsiung City 82144 Taiwan (R.O.C.) </address>
      <phone>+886 7-6979374</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ihchen@ms.szmc.edu.tw</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>