<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83858">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/04/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/07/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000588291</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Study of new femoral artery closure device to assist haemostasis in patients following cardiac catheterisation.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Safety and feasibilty study of new arterial closure device in patients following a Cardiac compared with literature controls for safety and time to haemostasis.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>CAT VI</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Coronary Heart Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In the Catheterization lab, provided no bleeding around the introducer sheath is observed and appropriate sterile technique is used, the Boomerang Catalyst VI Wire will be inserted through the indwelling 6F or 7F introducer sheath at the puncture site according to the Instructions for Use. After temporary hemostasis is achieved, imaging of the vessel will be performed to confirm correct placement of the device disc immediately prior to deployment of the extravascular collagen patch; the puncture site will then be observed for oozing blood and or signs of hematoma formation. At some point after hemostasis and prior to discharge, another ultrasound of the vessel will be performed and a digital image recorded as a baseline for the appearance of the collagen patch in proximity to the arteriotomy site.</interventions>
    <comparator>time to haemostasis using manual compression. no control group. Compared with average times for manual compression. As this is a safety and feasibilty study, no comparision will be made with other closure device times for haemostasis. A further Randomised Controlled Trial (RCT) will then be undertaken.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary safety endpoint is the incidence of major adverse events of the image-guided investigational device did not exceed those of manual compression alone as reported in literature.</outcome>
      <timepoint>discharge and 30 days post procedure</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary effectiveness endpoint is to demonstrate a superior (reduced) hold time till haemostasis with the Boomerang Catalyst VI System image-guided, extravascular patch as compared to literature controls for manual compression alone.</outcome>
      <timepoint>discharge and 30 days post procedure</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>the successful imaging of deployed Boomerang Catalyst VI disc and collagen patch prior to deployment, by clinician assessment</outcome>
      <timepoint>post procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>device success rate, by clinician assessment and vascular ultrasound</outcome>
      <timepoint>post procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>time to ambulation eligibility, by clinicain assessment</outcome>
      <timepoint>post procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>time to discharge eligibility, by clinician assessment</outcome>
      <timepoint>discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>clinically scheduled for angiogram or angioplasty, able to ambulate &gt;20 feet,</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>current infection, femoral arteriotomy in &lt;30 days, femoral arrter closure device in past 180 days, low platelets, high international normalised ratio (INR), anaemia, intra-procedural bleeding, high activated clotting time (ACT), A suspected intraluminal thrombus, hematoma, pseudo-aneurysm, or AV fistula of the target artery or 'multiple wall' arterial puncture.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>6/11/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>16/11/2009</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>17</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Cardiva Medical Inc</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>2585 Leghorn Street
Mountain View, 
California 94043</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cardiva Medical Inc</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>2585 Leghorn Street
Mountain View, 
California 94043</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Christchurch Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Cardiology Department
Christchurch Hospital 
Private bag 4710 
Christchurch, 8140</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Auckland City Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Auckland
New Zealand</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The Boomerang Catalyst VI System is designed to help in controlling bleeding (gaining haemostasis) following an arterial puncture made for the purpose of completing a coronary angiogram or angioplasty (procedures done in the cardiac catheter laboratory to look for or treat narrowings in the coronary arteries).  This puncture is usually made in the femoral artery in the groin. Often haemostasis is gained by manual compression (using the fingers or hand) and the literature reported average time for this technique will be compared the time it takes to gain haemostasis using the wire and collagen patch components of the device, as well as compression. There are several other closure devices used in New Zealand, and more than 50% of procedures would now have these used. 

The device is placed into the femoral artery in the catheter laboratory once the angiogram has been completed, followed by a minimum of one minute of manual compression. 
 
100 consecutive patients at 5 sites (20 per site) will be enrolled. The time taken to control the bleeding, time till the participant can stand and walk around, and the time till they are fit for discharge will be recorded. Also adverse, serious adverse and device adverse events will be recorded. Participants will be seen prior to discharge and again at 30 days and at these time points ultrasound will be used to assess the position of the collagen patch to the puncture site.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Multi-Regional Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
133 Molesworth Street
Wellington 6145
New Zealand</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/07/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>MEC/09/05/055</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/05/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr James Blake</name>
      <address>Cardiology Department
Christchurch Hospital 
Private bag 4710 
Christchurch 8140</address>
      <phone>+64 3 3640 640</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>james.blake@cdhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Catherine Cruickshank</name>
      <address>Cardiology Department
Christchurch Hospital 
Private bag 4710 
Christchurch 8140</address>
      <phone>+64 3 3601096</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>catheric@cdhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>James Blake</name>
      <address>Christchurch Hospital
cardiology Department
Private bag 4710
Christchurch</address>
      <phone>+64 3 364 0640</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>james.blake@cdhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>