<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368888">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/07/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/08/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000803594</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Life Balance: A pilot study evaluating the efficacy of a group education program on self-management in older adults with multiple conditions.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised wait-list control pilot study evaluating the efficacy of group self-management education sessions on quality of life in older persons with multi-morbidity.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn> U1111-1171-9260 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Multi-morbidity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Four, two-hour weekly group-based education sessions.  Sessions cover topics of self-management, values and goal setting, healthy living, symptom management, problem solving and introduces several mindfulness strategies aimed at assisting with worry and stress. Participants receive a 130 page resource book containing a synopsis of the content, further resources and self-directed exercises.  The education sessions are presented by registered nurses, nurse practitioners, and a registered clinical psychologist. 

Participants randomised to the intervention group will start the education programme one month after baseline questionnaire, while the control group will start the programme six weeks after the intervention group commenced the programme (waitlist control).



</interventions>
    <comparator>Waitlist control group will be offered the intervention six weeks after the intervention group started the educational intervention. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported quality of life assessed by the SF-12 </outcome>
      <timepoint> 6 weeks after commencement of the intervention programme</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in self-reported quality of life assessed via the SF-12 </outcome>
      <timepoint>change from baseline to 12 weeks after commencement of the intervention programme</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disability assessed via the WHO Disability Assessment Schedule (WHODAS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 6 and 12 weeks after commencement of the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Medication adherence assessed by the Medication Adherence Questionnaire (MMAS-8)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 6 and 12 weeks after commencement of the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mindfulness capacity assessed via Mindful Attention Awareness Scale (MAAS) </outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and 6 and 12 weeks after commencement of the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Beliefs about medication assessed via the Beliefs About Medicines Questionnaire (BMQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 6 and 12 weeks after commencement of the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Illness Perception assessed via the Brief Illness Perception Questionnaire (BIPQ) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 6 and 12 weeks after commencement of the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health distress assessed by the Stanford Symptoms Health Distress Scale (SHD) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 6 and 12 weeks after commencement of the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression assessed by the Stanford Personal Health Questionnaire Depression Scale (PHQ-8) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 6 and 12 weeks after commencement of the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Satisfaction with education sessions assessed by Satisfaction with Education Sessions patient satisfaction survey designed specifically for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks after commencement of the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Independently living older persons (non-Maori aged 65+ or Maori aged 55+) diagnosed with more than one long-term condition, able to attend and participate in the intervention sessions and to understand/speak English. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>55</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Currently being treated for an acute exacerbation (i.e. hospitalised).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sequentially numbered sealed opaque envelopes containing treatment allocation according to the randomisation schedule will be prepared. The envelopes will be kept by a person outside of the study team and only opened once a subject has provided informed consent, completed registration, and been allocated a study identification number. </concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated sequence.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Wait list control. Those in the control group will start the intervention six weeks after the intervention group started the educational intervention. Both groups will provide further follow-up data 6 and 12 weeks after they have commenced the intervention.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Participant characteristics at baseline will be reported using simple descriptive statistics. The primary outcome will be assessed using linear regression adjusting for baseline scores. The study design allows for estimation of within- and between-group effects. Therefore changes in continuous outcome measures over time, and differences between treatment groups, will be modelled using linear mixed models or general estimating equations. Parameter estimates with 95% confidence intervals will be derived from models.  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>28/08/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Canterbury</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Centre for Postgraduate Nursing Studies, University of Otago, Christchurch</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Otago, Christchurch
PO Box 4345
Christchurch 8140 
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Canterbury Medical Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 3225 
Christchurch 8011 
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Beverley Burrell</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Centre for Postgraduate Nursing Studies
University of Otago, Christchurch
PO Box 4345
Christchurch 8140 
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Marie Crowe</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Centre for Postgraduate Nursing Studies
University of Otago, Christchurch
PO Box 4345
Christchurch 8140
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Jenny Jordan</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>C/- Centre for Postgraduate Nursing Studies
University of Otago, Christchurch
PO Box 4345
Christchurch 8140</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Virginia Jones</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>C/- Centre for Postgraduate Nursing Studies
University of Otago, Christchurch
PO Box 4345
Christchurch 8140</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Mandy Wilkinson</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>C/- Centre for Postgraduate Nursing Studies
University of Otago, Christchurch
PO Box 4345
Christchurch 8140</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Ms Deb Gillon</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>C/- Centre for Postgraduate Nursing Studies
University of Otago, Christchurch
PO Box 4345
Christchurch 8140</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Ms Shirley Harris</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>C/- Centre for Postgraduate Nursing Studies
University of Otago, Christchurch
PO Box 4345
Christchurch 8140</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Jonathan Williman</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>C/- Centre for Postgraduate Nursing Studies
University of Otago, Christchurch
PO Box 4345
Christchurch 8140</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>New Zealand is experiencing an ageing population and the social, economic, medical and political implications and challenges that accompany demographic change. Overall, New Zealanders are living more independently and for longer, resulting in an ageing population with an increased prevalence of long-term conditions and often multiple conditions (multi-morbidity). It is increasingly acknowledged that successful aging relies in part on the individuals ability to self-manage his or her life. The concept of self-management or self-regulation has usually been associated with the physical aspects of aging but other factors are just as important for aging successfully including maintaining social networks and resources, and acquiring or maintaining skills to cope with potential and future stressors. Given the increased recognition of those factors and of the prevalence of multi-morbidity, current interventions are increasingly targeting overall wellbeing and utilising strategies that are useful for trans-diagnostic  (across multiplie diseases) symptoms rather than a symptom /disease specific approach. Mindfulness strategies offer potential to enhance self-management and quality of life across physical conditions. 
The Life Balance Self-management Programme being evaluated here combines cognitive behavioural and mindfulness strategies, applying them across chronic diseases (trans-diagnostically) to help manage negative thoughts and emotions and to enhance the uptake of the education and self-management strategies. 
This randomised pilot study aims to test that participant recruitment and randomisation to groups, education sessions and data gathering via questionnaires run smoothly and to produce data from the outcomes of the education sessions to support undertaking a larger randomised controlled trial.
The study design is a randomised open-label controlled trial with a wait listed control group. A convenience sample will be recruited of 60 older adults (non-Maori aged 65+ or Maori aged 55+) living independently in the community diagnosed with one or more long-term conditions and able to attend and participate in the intervention sessions and to understand/speak English.
The Life Balance Self-management Programme entails attendance at 2 hour group education sessions for four consecutive weeks (8hrs in total).  Manualised education sessions include the following topics: Healthy living, Symptom management, medication management and Self-management, form the first hour each day and four sessions on Mindful coping skills (cognitive behavioural and mindfulness strategies) are presented in the second hour. Participants receive a 130 page resource book containing a synopsis of the content, further resources and self-directed exercises.  
Outcomes measures assessed at baseline, 6 weeks and 12 weeks include the primary outcome (quality of life) as well as measures assessing disability, medication adherence, mindfulness awareness, beliefs about medication, illness perception, health distress, depression and satisfaction with education sessions at end treatment.


</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Ethics Committee Research Ethics (Health)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Otago
PO Box 56 
Dunedin 9054 
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/01/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H15/003</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Beverley Burrell</name>
      <address>Centre for Postgraduate Nursing Studies
University of Otago, Christchurch
PO Box 4345
Christchurch 8140

</address>
      <phone>+64 3 364 3850</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>beverley.burrell@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Beverley Burrell</name>
      <address>Centre for Postgraduate Nursing Studies
University of Otago, Christchurch
PO Box 4345
Christchurch 8140</address>
      <phone>+64 3 364 3850</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>beverley.burrell@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Beverley Burrell</name>
      <address>Centre for Postgraduate Nursing Studies
University of Otago, Christchurch
PO Box 4345
Christchurch 8140</address>
      <phone>+64 3 364 3850</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>beverley.burrell@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>