<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368087">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/03/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/04/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000380594</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Description of Lung Ultrasound From Initial Neonatal Transition, The DOLFIN Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Capturing and evaluating lung ultrasound images, heart rate, and saturation of peripheral oxygen in term and late preterm (&gt;32/40 weeks) infants not expected to require respiratory support at birth to determine whether ultrasound images of lungs have predictable changes in the first few hours of life.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Neonatal resuscitation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Lung aeration at birth</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Childbirth and postnatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Complications of newborn</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the respiratory system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a prospective, observational study of spontaneously breathing term and late preterm infants in the delivery room. The primary outcome will be to determine if ultrasound images of the lungs have predictable changes during the first few hours of life. 

Antenatal consent will be obtained from the parents prior to enrolment after admission to birth suites and initial assessment of the obstetric team or during the final prenatal visit. Consent will only obtained if not in established labour. 

Ultrasound images will be obtained using the Vividi (GE Healthcare, Wauwatosa, USA). An investigator will perform serial lung ultrasound exams, recordings 3-5 second clips of the right and left lung fields using 2D imaging and M-mode. The lung ultrasound exams will be brief. We will use a timer to limit exams to 2 minutes or less from the time of placing the ultrasound gel on the babys skin. Lung ultrasound exams will be performed at 6 time points: less than 10 minutes of life, 10-20 minutes of life, 1 hour of life, 2 hours of life, 4-6 hours of life, and 24-72 hours of life (the final exam targeting the time frame closest to discharge). If the lungs appear to have reached full aeration on two consecutive exams by the ultrasonographer (bilateral presence of A-lines with normal lung sliding), the study will be considered complete and no further images will be obtained. Prior to application to the babys skin, the ultrasound gel will warmed by placing it on a clean gauze under the radiant warmer in the patients room. After the exam, the ultrasound gel will be removed from the babys skin. 

At the one hour exam, ultrasound images of the will be obtained from the anterior, axillary, and posterior chest of the baby. The purpose of obtaining additional images at the one hour exam will be to test if there is a difference in lung aeration and fluid clearance with the probe positioned at different areas of the chest. In a study of 154 term and late preterm babies, Raimondi and colleagues performed lung ultrasound exams at 1-2 hours of life. Nine percent, 30%, and 61% had type 1, 2, and 3 lung ultrasound findings respectively. Therefore, the one hour exam may be ideal to compare images in different sections of the chest because of the variety of lung aeration grades and less potential to interfere with maternal bonding. The information obtained from the additional images will help standardize the lung ultrasound exam. The one hour exam will be limited to 5 minutes.

Lung ultrasound clips will be independently collected by an investigator (DB). Two 2-D clips and 2 images captured with M-mode for each exam will be de-identified, coded, and blindly graded by 3 consultants with expertise in ultrasonography (LF, OK, SR). The degree of lung aeration will be assigned based on the grade of these images at type 1, 2, or 3 using a previously published grading system. In the event of a disagreement among the blinded consultants, if 2/3 consultants agree, that grade will be assigned. If all three consultants assign a different grade, we will review the images openly in a group discussion. We will test inter-rater reliability of characterizing lung ultrasound images as type 1, 2, or 3 by having the three blinded ultra-sonographers independently evaluate each ultrasound clip using a Spearmans rank-order test. 

Before the ultrasound exams, we will place a pulse oximetry sensor on the babys right hand or wrist to measure the babys heart rate and oxygen levels. These measurements can be obtained while the baby is on the mothers chest or being held by the family. Heart rate and SpO2 will be obtained using either an NM3 Respiratory Profile Monitor (Philips Respironics, The Netherlands) or Radical 7 pulse oximeter (Masimo, California, USA). The heart rate, and SpO2 will be converted from analog to digital signal for statistical analysis. Measurements recorded will be analyzed using Stata Software (StataCorp, College Station, Texas, USA) for statistical analysis. The pulse oximeter will be applied to the babys right hand or wrist at each prior to each of the ultrasound examinations and be removed after the ultrasound exam is finished. If available, we will also record the umbilical arterial cord blood gas for analysis. 

If the investigators observe any concerning findings on lung ultrasound (evidence of pneumothorax or effusion) or pulse oximetry, they will immediately notify the clinical team caring for the baby. 

Our goal is obtain the desired data without altering the experience of the parents as they introduce a new member to their family and to avoid any interference with the clinicians caring for the baby. The lung ultrasound exams may be performed on the warming bed with the agreement of the clinician caring for the baby. If the clinical team decides that the baby is well enough to be moved from the warming bed to be with the mother, lung ultrasound exams can also with the infant on the mothers chest or while being held by a family member. If the baby cannot be held by the mother (or other family member) but the baby can be positioned close to the mother, there will be a dedicated research trolley with a warming mattress available to place the baby as close as possible to the mother for lung ultrasound exams. The natural transition of the healthy newborn includes bonding with the mother after birth. The study should not preclude skin to skin contact of babies or breastfeeding with their mothers in the first ten minutes of life.

We will review the data collected after enrolling 10 and 50 babies. The purpose will be to review for adverse outcomes, quality of ultrasound images, efficacy of data collection and grading. Specifically, we will monitor the babys first temperature collected by the clinical team, the potential of interfering with patient care, review the quality of ultrasound images using different exam techniques and settings (like location of ultrasound probe, gain, and depth), and the inter-relater reliability. 

The research team has over 10 years of experience studying neonatal transition in the delivery room The measurements obtained from this cohort of babies constitutes an observational study. This data will provide valuable information on the appearance of the lungs on ultrasound from birth through the first day of life and may serve as crucial baseline data for future interventional studies intended to improve respiratory care of newborns. 

The measurements and images obtained from this cohort of babies constitutes an observational study. The data will provide valuable information on lung ultrasound in the first minutes to hours after birth. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Nil</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome will be to determine if ultrasound images of the lungs have predictable changes during the first few hours of life. Ultrasound images will be obtained using the Vividi (GE Healthcare, Wauwatosa, USA). </outcome>
      <timepoint>We will use a timer to limit exams to 2 minutes or less from the time of placing the ultrasound gel on the babys skin. Lung ultrasound exams will be performed at 6 time points: less than 10 minutes of life, 10-20 minutes of life, 1 hour of life, 2 hours of life, 4-6 hours of life, and 24-72 hours of life (the final exam targeting the time frame closest to discharge). If the lungs appear to have reached full aeration on two consecutive exams by the ultrasonographer (bilateral presence of A-lines with normal lung sliding), the study will be considered complete and no further images will be obtained. 
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the proportion of babies with aerated lungs at designated time points listed in the research plan. Ultrasound images will be obtained using the Vividi (GE Healthcare, Wauwatosa, USA). </outcome>
      <timepoint>We will use a timer to limit exams to 2 minutes or less from the time of placing the ultrasound gel on the babys skin. Lung ultrasound exams will be performed at 6 time points: less than 10 minutes of life, 10-20 minutes of life, 1 hour of life, 2 hours of life, 4-6 hours of life, and 24-72 hours of life (the final exam targeting the time frame closest to discharge). If the lungs appear to have reached full aeration on two consecutive exams by the ultrasonographer (bilateral presence of A-lines with normal lung sliding), the study will be considered complete and no further images will be obtained. 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the average time to a fully aerated lung based on ultrasound imaging. Ultrasound images will be obtained using the Vividi (GE Healthcare, Wauwatosa, USA). </outcome>
      <timepoint>We will use a timer to limit exams to 2 minutes or less from the time of placing the ultrasound gel on the babys skin. Lung ultrasound exams will be performed at 6 time points: less than 10 minutes of life, 10-20 minutes of life, 1 hour of life, 2 hours of life, 4-6 hours of life, and 24-72 hours of life (the final exam targeting the time frame closest to discharge). If the lungs appear to have reached full aeration on two consecutive exams by the ultrasonographer (bilateral presence of A-lines with normal lung sliding), the study will be considered complete and no further images will be obtained. 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To correlate the degree of lung aeration with the heart rate (HR) and saturation of peripheral oxygen (SpO2). Ultrasound images will be obtained using the Vividi (GE Healthcare, Wauwatosa, USA). HR and SpO2 will be obtained using an NM3 Respiratory Function Monitor (Philips, California USA) or a Radical-7 Pulse Oximeter (California, USA).</outcome>
      <timepoint>We will use a timer to limit exams to 2 minutes or less from the time of placing the ultrasound gel on the babys skin. Lung ultrasound exams will be performed at 6 time points: less than 10 minutes of life, 10-20 minutes of life, 1 hour of life, 2 hours of life, 4-6 hours of life, and 24-72 hours of life (the final exam targeting the time frame closest to discharge). If the lungs appear to have reached full aeration on two consecutive exams by the ultrasonographer (bilateral presence of A-lines with normal lung sliding), the study will be considered complete and no further images will be obtained. Prior to each lung ultrasound exam, we will place a pulse oximetry sensor on the baby's right wrist, then remove the sensor once the exam is completed.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the time needed to perform a lung ultrasound exam that yields clean images easily reviewed by blinded expert sonographers. Ultrasound images will be obtained using the Vividi (GE Healthcare, Wauwatosa, USA). </outcome>
      <timepoint>We will use a timer to limit exams to 2 minutes or less from the time of placing the ultrasound gel on the babys skin. Lung ultrasound exams will be performed at 6 time points: less than 10 minutes of life, 10-20 minutes of life, 1 hour of life, 2 hours of life, 4-6 hours of life, and 24-72 hours of life (the final exam targeting the time frame closest to discharge). If the lungs appear to have reached full aeration on two consecutive exams by the ultrasonographer (bilateral presence of A-lines with normal lung sliding), the study will be considered complete and no further images will be obtained. 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To document abnormalities of lung pathology using ultrasound. Ultrasound images will be obtained using the Vividi (GE Healthcare, Wauwatosa, USA). 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>We will use a timer to limit exams to 2 minutes or less from the time of placing the ultrasound gel on the babys skin. Lung ultrasound exams will be performed at 6 time points: less than 10 minutes of life, 10-20 minutes of life, 1 hour of life, 2 hours of life, 4-6 hours of life, and 24-72 hours of life (the final exam targeting the time frame closest to discharge). If the lungs appear to have reached full aeration on two consecutive exams by the ultrasonographer (bilateral presence of A-lines with normal lung sliding), the study will be considered complete and no further images will be obtained. 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All inborn infants greater or equal to 33/40 weeks gestation, who are not expected to require respiratory support at birth, are eligible for this study. Antenatal consent from the parents will be required for enrolment. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Hours</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Infants will be excluded from analysis if they have a congenital abnormality. Infants will be excluded if their parents decline to give consent to this study. If there are signs of respiratory compromise or distress after birth, data collection will be delayed and ventilatory support given according to the Australian Neonatal Resuscitation guidelines. Infants who receive respiratory support for a brief period of time may still be eligible with the agreement of the clinician in charge of the infants care. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Infants will be recruited over a period of 12 months. Approximately another month will be required to collect hospital data on all infants enrolled. Medical data on each infant will be collected on Case Report Forms (Patient Data Form, DOLFIN Study). De-identified information will be collected via the Vividi ultrasound machine and heart rate and SpO2 will be obtained using either an NM3 Respiratory Profile Monitor (Philips Respironics, The Netherlands) or Radical 7 pulse oximeter (Masimo, California, USA). All information will then be entered into Stata database for analysis. Measurements recorded will be analyzed using SPSS Statistics (Chicago, USA) for statistical analysis. 

Ultrasound images will be obtained using the Vividi (GE Healthcare, Wauwatosa, USA). An investigator will perform serial lung ultrasound exams, recordings 3-5 second clips of the right and left lung fields using 2D imaging and M-mode. The lung ultrasound exams will be brief. We will use a timer to limit exams to 2 minutes or less from the time of placing the ultrasound gel on the babys skin. Lung ultrasound exams will be performed at 6 time points: less than 10 minutes of life, 10-20 minutes of life, 1 hour of life, 2 hours of life, 4-6 hours of life, and 24-72 hours of life (the final exam targeting the time frame closest to discharge). If the lungs appear to have reached full aeration on two consecutive exams by the ultrasonographer (bilateral presence of A-lines with normal lung sliding), the study will be considered complete and no further images will be obtained. Prior to application to the babys skin, the ultrasound gel will warmed by placing it on a clean gauze under the radiant warmer in the patients room. After the exam, the ultrasound gel will be removed from the babys skin. 

This is the first study that attempts to characterize and define the appearance and movement of the neonatal lung using ultrasound in spontaneously breathing infants from birth through the first hours of life. As such, there is no preceding data from which a sample size calculation can be completed. Dr. Francesco Raimondi in Naples, Italy and colleagues published an article in 2012, in which LUS was conducted in 154 term and late preterm babies at 2 hours of life to investigate if LUS can be used to predict which babies will require admission to the NICU. Ninety-four of the 154 babies had fully aerated lungs at 2 hours of life and none of these babies were admitted for respiratory support. By 36 hours of life, 152/154 babies had fully aerated lungs. 

We plan to recruit a convenience sample of 150 infants, 100 term infants (&gt;37 weeks gestational age) and 50 late preterm infants (33-36 weeks gestational age). We believe that serial lung ultrasound on 150 term and late preterm babies will be an adequate sample size to perform basic statistical evaluations, like repeated measured ANOVAs, with a chance of a type 1 error &lt;0.05 and a power of 80%. The sample size is also adequate to test intra-relater reliability and inter-relater reliability. 

We will recruit 75 infants born via vaginal delivery (50 term infants and 25 late preterm infants) and 75 infants born via caesarean section (50 term infants and 25 late preterm infants), during a 12 month period of study. 

We hypothesis that the timing of clearance of lung fluid and the establishment of lung aeration may be different via different modes of delivery and may be different for different gestational ages. There is literature to support that babies delivered via elective caesarean section will have a higher risk of transient tachypnea of the newborn and babies delivered via caesarean section secondary to failure to progress will have a higher risk of respiratory distress syndrome.

We also feel that there we will be able to safely recruit and study late preterm babies without interfering with patient care. Babies born 33-36 weeks have an increased risk of NICU admission for respiratory distress. We hypothesize that the clearance of lung fluid and establishment of aeration will be slower in these babies as well. Recruitment of babies born between 33-36 weeks may be more challenging than term babies. We felt that starting with 50 instead of 100 babies in the lower gestational age range would allow us enough time to complete the data collection. 

According the RWH annual report, there were over 7,000 deliveries in 2013, over 5,000 of which would be eligible to approach for consent. We believe that obtaining serial lung ultrasound images of 150 patients will allow us to obtain sufficient data to describe the appearance and movement of the neonatal lung from birth to the completion of transition from the womb.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Convenience sample</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/03/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>4/03/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>3/03/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Women's Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Prof Peter Davis</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Royal Women's Hospital
Locked Bag 300
Cnr of Grattan Street and Flemington Road
Parkville, VIC 3052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council Program Grant
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra, ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Royal Women's Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Cnr Grattan Street &amp; Flemington Road
Locked Bag 300
Parkville, VIC 3052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Prof Stuart Hooper</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The Ritchie Centre
MIMR-PHI Institute of Medical Research
27-31 Wright Street
Clayton, VIC 3168</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Omar Kamlin</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>The Royal Women's Hospital
Locked Bag 300
Cnr of Grattan Street and Flemington Road
Parkville, VIC 3052</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Lisa Fox</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>The Royal Women's Hospital
Locked Bag 300
Cnr of Grattan Street and Flemington Road
Parkville, VIC 3052</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Sheryle Rogerson</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>The Royal Women's Hospital
Locked Bag 300
Cnr of Grattan Street and Flemington Road
Parkville, VIC 3052</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Graeme Polglase</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>The Ritchie Centre
MIMR-PHI Institute of Medical Research
27-31 Wright Street
Clayton, VIC 3168</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Before birth, while a baby is in the mothers womb, the babys lungs are filled with fluid and the baby gets oxygen from the placenta. Once the baby is born, the baby needs to transition to using the lungs to get oxygen. In the hours after birth, the babys body will reabsorb the lung fluid and the lungs will fill with air. The purpose of this study is to describe the normal filling of a newborn babys lungs with air over the first few hours of life using an ultrasound machine. We believe that with the knowledge gained in this study, we can improve our care for babies that need help breathing at birth.  

The lung ultrasound exams will be brief, limited to 2 minutes or less from the time of placing the ultrasound probe gently to your babys chest. The first two exams will be during the first 20 minutes after your baby is born and will be repeated when your baby is 1 hour old, 2 hours old, 4 to 6 hours old and 24 to 72 hours old. At 1 hour of life, the lung ultrasound exam will be slightly longer as we take images of the front, back and side of your babys chest to test if a specific location to place the probe is better than another.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Royal Women's Hospital Research and Human Research Ethics Committees</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Royal Women's Hospital
Locked Bag 300
Cnr of Grattan Street and Flemington Road
Parkville, VIC 3052
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/02/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>15/01</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/01/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368087-DOLFIN Study Protocol V4 26.02.2015.doc</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368087-DOLFIN Study Consent V4 26.02.2015.doc</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368087-DOLFIN Study Patient Data Form V4 26.02.2015.doc.docx</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Douglas Blank</name>
      <address>The Royal Women's Hospital
Locked Bag 300
Cnr of Grattan Street and Flemington Road
Parkville, VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61422305487</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>douglas.blank@thewomens.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Douglas Blank</name>
      <address>The Royal Women's Hospital
Locked Bag 300
Cnr of Grattan Street and Flemington Road
Parkville, VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61422305487</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>douglas.blank@thewomens.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Douglas Blank</name>
      <address>The Royal Women's Hospital
Locked Bag 300
Cnr of Grattan Street and Flemington Road
Parkville, VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61422305487</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>douglas.blank@thewomens.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Douglas Blank</name>
      <address>The Royal Women's Hospital
Locked Bag 300
Cnr of Grattan Street and Flemington Road
Parkville, VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61422305487</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>douglas.blank@thewomens.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>