<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83723">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/03/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/05/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000329268</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The efficacy of a Flurbiprofen drug intervention on the relief of sore throat due to upper respiratory tract infection.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A multi-centre, randomised, double-blinded, placebo-controlled, parallel group, multiple dose, study of the efficacy of 8.75 mg flurbiprofen micro granules in the relief of sore throat due to upper respiratory tract infection.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Sore throat due to upper respiratory infection</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Investigational treatment: 8.75mg flurbiprofen micro granules or placebo granules, granules are tipped from the sachet onto the tongue and dissolve instantly.  Each sachet will contain either 8.75mg of flurbiprofen or a placebo.  The granules are are administered at the participant's discretion every 3 to 6 hours so long as they do not exceed the maximum recommended dose of 5 sachets per day.  The participant will be provided with sufficient granules to last up to 3 days.
Rescue medication: Paracetamol 500mg, 2 tablets orally, every 4 hours as required up to a maximum of 8 tablets per day.  The participant will be provided with sufficient rescue medication to last up to 3 days.  The resue medication is consumed in conjunction with the investigational treatment.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo micro granule formulation (sugar micro granules). Each sachet will contain  8.75mg of placebo.  Granules are tipped from the sachet onto the tongue and dissolve instantly. The granules are are administered at the participant's discretion every 3 to 6 hours so long as they do not exceed the maximum recommended dose of 5 sachets per day.  The participant will be provided with sufficient granules to last up to 3 days.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The area under the change from baseline curve (AUC) in severity of throat soreness from 0 to 2 hours after the first dose of study medication.  This is assessed with a sore throat rating scale questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessments are performed at baseline and then at 1 minute after first dose, then every 5 minutes for the first 15 minutes, then every 15 minutes up to 3 hours.  Then  again at 4 hours, 5 hours and 6 hours post first dose.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The area under the change from baseline curve (AUC) in severity of throat soreness from 0 to 6 hours post first dose. This is assessed with a sore throat rating scale questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: 0 to 6 hours post first dose.
Assessments are performed at baseline and then at 1 minute after first dose, then every 5 minutes for the first 15 minutes, then every 15 minutes up to 3 hours.  Then  again at 4 hours, 5 hours and 6 hours post first dose.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in severity of throat soreness (using the 11 point throat soreness scale).</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 1, 5, 10, 15, 30, 45, 60, 75, 90, 105,120,135,150, 165, 180, 240, 300 and 360 minutes post first dose.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline (using 100mm visual analogue scale (VAS) sore throat pain intensity scale) in sore throat pain intensity (pain intensity difference (PID) VAS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 1, 5, 10, 15, 30, 45, 60, 75, 90, 105,120,135,150, 165, 180, 240, 300 and 360 minutes post first dose.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>sum of pain intensity difference (SPID) over 0-3, 0-6 hours (using the 100 mm VAS sore throat pain intensity scale)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessments are performed at baseline and then at 1 minute after first dose, then every 5 minutes for the first 15 minutes, then every 15 minutes up to 3 hours.  Then  again at 4 hours, 5 hours and 6 hours post first dose.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to first reporting 'moderate sore throat relief' (which is the mid point on the 7 point sore throat relief scale).</outcome>
      <timepoint>From the first treatment dose until first time reporting moderate sore throat relief occurs</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total sum of pain relief ratings (TOTPAR3): Defined as the AUC from baseline to 3 hours post first dose for sore throat relief.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessments are performed at 1 minute after first dose, then every 5 minutes for the first 15 minutes, then every 15 minutes up to 3 hours.  Then  again at 4 hours, 5 hours and 6 hours post first dose.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total sum of pain relief ratings (TOTPAR6): Defined as the AUC from baseline to 6 hours post first dose for sore throat relief.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessments are performed  at 1 minute after first dose, then every 5 minutes for the first 15 minutes, then every 15 minutes up to 3 hours.  Then  again at 4 hours, 5 hours and 6 hours post first dose.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sore throat relief
This is assessed by a sore throat relief rating scale questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 1, 5, 10, 15, 30, 45, 60, 75, 90, 105, 120,135,150,165,180,240,300 and 360 minutes post first dose.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>AUC from baseline to 3 hours post first dose for the change from baseline in difficulty in swallowing.  This is assessed by a difficulty swallowing rating scale questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessments are performed baseline, then at 1 minute after first dose, then every 5 minutes for the first 15 minutes, then every 15 minutes up to 3 hours.  Then  again at 4 hours, 5 hours and 6 hours post first dose.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in difficulty in swallowing (using 100mm VAS difficulty swallowing scale)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 1, 5, 10, 15, 30, 45, 60, 75, 90, 105 and 120,135,150,165,180,240,300 and 360 minutes post first dose.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to first reporting a change of 1 or more on the Throat Soreness scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From the first treatment dose until first time reporting change of 1 or more on the Throat Soreness scale</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall treatment rating assesses by rating scale in questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At three hours following first treatment dose, and at the end of Day 3 of treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall flurbiprofen micro granule sachet consumption as recorded in the patient diary up to the end of Day 3.</outcome>
      <timepoint>the end of Day 3.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall rescue medication (Paracetamol) consumption as recorded in the patient diary up to the end of Day 3.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at the end of Day 3.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Whether the patient was symptom free at the end of Day 1, at 24 hours post first dose and at the end of Days 2 and 3. Freedom from symptoms is defined as the patient giving a sore throat score of 0 or 1.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at the end of Day 1, at 24 hours post first dose and at the end of Days 2 and 3.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of patients that discontinued trial medication due to resolution of sore throat.  This is reported by the participant via questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the completion of treatment programs</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Age: 18 to 75. 
Both male and female patients may be included.
Primary diagnosis: Patients with sore throat of onset within the past 4 days
Patients who have a sore throat (greater than or equal to 6) on the Throat Soreness Scale at baseline. 
Objective findings that confirm the presence of tonsillopharyngitis (greater than or equal to 5 points on the expanded 21-point  Tonsillopharyngitis Assessment).
Patients who have given written informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any previous history of allergy or known intolerance to the study drug or the following formulation constituents xylitol, mannitol, carbomer 974P,  sodium bicarbonate, mint, peppermint, aspartame, citric acid, silicon dioxide
Those whose sore throat has been present for more than 4 days.
Those who have evidence of mouth breathing.
Those who have evidence of severe coughing.
Those who have any disease that can compromise breathing e.g. bronchopneumonia.
Those who have taken any medicated confectionary, throat pastille, spray, or any product with demulcent properties such as boiled sweets in the previous 2 hours.
Those who have used any sore throat medication containing a local anaesthetic within the past 4 hours.
Those who have used any analgesic, antipyretic or cold medication (e.g. decongestant, antihistamine, antitussive or throat lozenge) within the previous 8 hours.
Those who have used a longer acting or slow release analgesic during the previous 24 hours e.g. Piroxicam and Naproxen.
Those taking antibiotics during the previous 14 days
Those with any painful condition that may distract attention from sore throat pain e.g. mouth ulcers etc. 
Those with a history of severe renal impairment.
Those with a history of severe hepatic impairment
Those taking warfarin and other coumarins.
Those taking carbamezepine, phenobarbitone, phenytoin, primidone, rifampicin, St Johns Wort or other drugs that induce liver enzymes in the 14 days before enrolment into the study (i.e. before first dosing day).
Those with a history of alcohol abuse or state that they regularly consume alcohol in excess of the recommended amounts (excessive alcohol &gt;21 units per week for females and &gt;28 units per week for males.).
Those who are glutathione-deplete e.g. eating disorders, cystic fibrosis, HIV infection, starvation, cachexia.
Those with any painful condition that requires analgesic usage.
Those unable to refrain from smoking during their stay in the investigative site.
Women of childbearing potential , who are pregnant or lactating, seeking pregnancy or failing to take adequate contraceptive precautions, (i.e. an oral or injectable contraceptive, an approved hormonal implant or topical patch or an intrauterine device. A women of child bearing potential is defined as any female who is less than 2 years post-menopausal or has not undergone an hysterectomy or surgical sterilisation, e.g. bilateral tubal ligation, bilateral ovariectomy (oophorectomy).
Those previously randomised into the study.
Those who have participated in a clinical trial in the previous 30 days. Thirty days are calculated from time of last dosing in the prior trial to time of anticipated dosing in this trial.
Those unable in the opinion of the investigator to comply fully with the study requirements, e.g. such as those who cannot comprehend or correctly use the pain rating scales.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Drug supplies will be packed and labelled according to a computer produced randomisation schedule by site.  On randomisation, patients will be allocated a unique number in numerical sequence.  Issue of the drug in sequence will ensure randomisation.
The investigator will be provided with the randomisation code for each patient as a code break envelope.  The code will only be broken for an individual patient in an emergency case such as a serious adverse event that requires knowledge of what study drug was taken in order that the serious adverse event can be treated appropriately.</concealment>
    <sequence>SAS random code generator, will randomly assign patients to either placebo or active treatment.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/05/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>370</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Reckitt Benckiser Healthcare (UK)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Dansom Lane 
Hull, HU8 7DS</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United Kingdom</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Reckitt Benckiser Healthcare (UK)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Dansom Lane 
Hull, HU8 7DS</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United Kingdom</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Novotech (Australia) Pty. Ltd.</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Level 3, 19 Harris Street
Pyrmont, N.S.W. 2009</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is testing a new treatment for sore throat called flurbiprofen micro granules. 
Flurbiprofen lozenges are approved by the Australian health authority, the Therapeutic Goods Administration (TGA) for the relief of pain, swelling and inflammation due to severe sore throat. In this study, tiny granules of flurbiprofen will be tested to determine if they too are effective in the relief of sore throat.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/04/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Christopher Morris</name>
      <address>Reckitt Benckiser Healthcare
Dansom Lane, Hull,  HU8 7DS</address>
      <phone>+44 (0) 1482 582675</phone>
      <fax>+44 (0) 1482 582172</fax>
      <email>Christopher.Morris@ReckittBenckiser.com</email>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Christopher Morris</name>
      <address>Reckitt Benckiser Healthcare
Dansom Lane, Hull,  HU8 7DS</address>
      <phone>+44 (0) 1482 582675</phone>
      <fax>+44 (0) 1482 582172</fax>
      <email>Christopher.Morris@ReckittBenckiser.com</email>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Lyn Adams</name>
      <address>Novotech (Australia) Pty. Ltd.
PO Box 117
Carlton South, VIC. 3053</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9341 1922</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9341 1998</fax>
      <email>lyn.adams@novotech-cro.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>