<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373059">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/06/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/10/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001455358</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Assessing the appropriate dose and efficacy of bovine lactoferrin to correct iron deficiency anaemia in non pregnant women: A community-based randomized controlled trial in Mirpur, Dhaka</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Assessing the appropriate dose and efficacy of bovine lactoferrin to correct iron deficiency anaemia in non pregnant women: A community-based randomized controlled trial in Mirpur, Dhaka</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>SHONJIBON 2 Part 1</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Iron Deficiency Anemia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaemia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>We will conduct a non-inferiority, double blind, individually randomized controlled trial in non-pregnant women of reproductive age with iron deficiency anaemia (haemoglobin &lt;120 g/L &amp; serum ferritin &lt;30 µg/L) to assess the haemoglobin and iron status in response to i) 200mg oral bovine lactoferrin, ii) 400mg of oral bovine lactoferrin iii) standard oral iron supplements (60mg elemental iron). The intervention (each capsule once daily) will be continued for 3 months. Study personnel (field implementer and study physicians) will have monthly contacts with the enrolled women for monitoring compliance to intervention.</interventions>
    <comparator>Daily oral 60mg iron sulphate + placebo
Both comparators will be administered for the same duration as the intervention (i.e. 3 months). The placebo will contain sucrose -01.059mg, lactose-61.758mg, maize starch-92.18mg, heavy kaolin-2.467mg, povidone (5 30)-59.358mg, purified talc-52.622mg. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome will be the change in hemoglobin concentration from baseline to the end of the 12th week of treatment. Spot measurement of hemoglobin will be done at the site of primary screening using standard/validated hemocue device. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 week assessment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in haemoglobin concentration from baseline to 4th, 8th and 12th week of treatment. Spot test of Hemoglobin will be done using standard validated hemocue machine.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4 week assessment, 8 week assessment, 12 week assessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in serum ferritin concentration corrected with C-reactive protein (CRP) and Alpha 1 Glycoprotein (AGP) from baseline to 4th, 8th and 12th week of treatment. 5ml blood will be collected from each study participants. Serum ferritin will be measured using Chemiluminescence Immunoassay. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4 week assessment, 8 week assessment, 12 week assessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in serum hepcidin concentration from baseline to 12th week of treatment. Hepcidin will be measured using ELISA methods. </outcome>
      <timepoint>at Baseline and 12 week assessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prevalence of anaemia-related symptoms (fatigue, pallor, dyspnoea, nail disorders, loss of appetite, deterioration in cognitive functions and skin disorders). This data will be collected during the scheduled follow-up interview of the study participants. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4 week assessment, 8 week assessment, 12 week assessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of women reporting side effects including abdominal pain, nausea, vomiting, regurgitation, diarrhoea and constipation during the treatment. This data will be collected during the scheduled follow-up interview of the study participants.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4 week assessment, 8 week assessment, 12 week assessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of women who discontinued the study because of side effects of the trial treatment. This information will be available from the regular monitoring data throughout study period. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Continuously throughout the study period during the regular monitoring process. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria> Age 18 through 49 years
 Non-lactating and non-pregnant
 Haemoglobin &lt;120 g/L, &amp; serum ferritin level &lt;30 µg/L corrected with C-reactive protein (CRP) &amp; a1-acid glycoprotein (AGP) (1, 40).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>49</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria> Cases of severe anemia with haemoglobin &lt;70 g/L will be excluded and referred to Shaheed Suhrawardy Medical College Hospital which is the nearest tertiary level hospital for treatment
 Other iron supplements taken in the one month preceding enrolment
 Recent blood transfusion
 Women who are currently ill with fever
 History of chronic non-communicable diseases or history of TB
 Women intending to move from study area within 2 months of enrolment
 Reported allergy to milk proteins or to iron products</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Numbered containers</concealment>
    <sequence>i) Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation), and ii) Permuted block randomisation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The estimated sample size is for a non-inferiority two-sample comparison of means for each dose of lactoferrin. The null hypothesis is that the degree of inferiority of the haemoglobin response after one month of oral bovine lactoferrin (L) to standard oral iron supplements (I), I-L, is greater than the margin M thus ruling out a degree of inferiority greater than the margin M.
Ho: I-L = M (L is more inferior to I than M)
Ha: I-L &lt; M (L is less inferior to I than M)
Assumptions:
 Based on evidence from prior studies the response of iron compared to placebo is 10.0 g/L, and M, the largest clinically acceptable difference, is 2.5 g/L.
 Expected standard deviation = 0.80 (in each group)
 Power = 0.80
 Alpha = 0.025 (one-sided)
The estimated required sample size per group is 161, giving a total sample size of 483 for the 3 treatment groups.
Since 15% of subjects are expected to be lost to follow-up, the total sample size is adjusted to 556.
Calculation based on 'SSI': module to estimate sample size for RCTs in Stata version 14.

Analysis Plan
Participants who will receive at least one dose of supplement and at least one post-baseline efficacy assessment during the double-blind part will be included in the analysis. All analysis will be conducted at individual level. We will analyze patients categorized by the treatment group to which they will be allocated on an intention-to-treat (ITT) basis. The last day of follow up will be considered as outcome status for study participants who may be lost to follow-up without having the outcome of interest. To obtain the overall across-dose-range treatment (Lactoferrin and IFA supplements) effects, the average differences between log-dose slopes for percent changes from baseline in iron status and inflammatory biomarkers will be obtained in separate analyses (ANOVA) for all arms of part one. For safety analyses, descriptive statistics will be included for all parameters and an analysis of variance model (ANOVA) will be used for between-group (treatment arms) and within group (anaemic and mild anaemic) comparisons. For subgroup analyses, we will use Cox proportional hazard models (for mortality outcome), and other generalized linear mixed models (for preterm and low birth-weight outcomes) that will incorporate each of the major covariates. Statistical significance will be considered at p&lt;0·05. Models will be able to evaluate the impact of the interventions by testing for interactions over time in all intervention groups. Analysis will be conducted to identify covariates that influence the response to interventions (based on household wealth, maternal education, or income).</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>28/02/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>556</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/04/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Bangladesh</country>
      <state>Dhaka</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>International Centre for Diarrhoeal Disease Research, Bangladesh (icddr,b)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>68, Shaheed Tajuddin Ahmed Sarani, Mohakhali, Dhaka, 1212</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Bangladesh</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Medical Research Council (MRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1 Kemble St, London WC2B 4AN, United Kingdom</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United Kingdom</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Saving Lives at Birth</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Funds were received through Saving Lives at Birth. 
The partner organization funding this particular protocol is USAID. 
Address- 1300 Pennsylvania Avenue, NW. Washington, DC 20523.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Sydney</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Edward Ford Building (A27), Fisher Road, University of Sydney NSW 2006, Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Hypotheses:
 Oral bovine lactoferrin is at least as effective in correcting iron deficiency anaemia among non-pregnant women of reproductive age compared to standard iron supplements.

Objectives:
1. To determine the optimal dose of oral bovine lactoferrin for correction and prevention of iron deficiency anaemia in women of reproductive age.
2. To determine whether bovine lactoferrin is at least as effective as oral iron in treating iron deficiency anaemia among non-pregnant women of reproductive age.
3. To compare the side-effects of oral iron supplements and bovine lactoferrin
4. To compare the adherence of oral iron supplements and bovine lactoferrin

Methods:
We will conduct a non-inferiority randomized controlled trial (RCT), to compare different doses of oral bovine lactoferrin with standard oral iron supplements in non-pregnant anaemic women of reproductive age to determine the appropriate dose of bovine lactoferrin, and demonstrate it is safe and as effective as standard oral iron supplements in treating iron deficiency anaemia. 

Outcome measures/variables:
The primary outcome will be the change in haemoglobin concentration from baseline to the end of the twelfth week of treatment. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Institutional Review Board (IRB) of icddr,b</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>68, Shaheed Tajuddin Ahmed Sarani, Mohakhali, Dhaka 1212</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/01/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>PR-15116</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>17/11/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Bangladesh</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee of The University of Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Edward Ford Building (A27), Fisher Road, University of Sydney NSW 2006, Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/07/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016/148</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>21/01/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Michael J Dibley</name>
      <address>Professor in Global Public Health Nutrition
Sydney School of Public Health
Sydney Medical School
Edward Ford Building (A27), Fisher Road, 
University of Sydney NSW 2006, 
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61293515203</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michael.dibley@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tanvir Mahmudul Huda</name>
      <address>Research Associate and PhD Candidate 
Sydney School of Public Health
Sydney Medical School
Edward Ford Building (A27), Fisher Road, 
University of Sydney NSW 2006, 
Australia

and 
Project Coordinator
Maternal and Child Health Division (MCHD)
International Centre for Diarrhoeal Disease Research, Bangladeh (icddr,b) 
68, Shaheed Tajudddin Ahmed Sarani
Mohakhali, Dhaka 1212
</address>
      <phone>+61412735284</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>thuda@icddrb.org</email>
      <country>Bangladesh</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tanvir Mahmudul Huda</name>
      <address>Research Associate and PhD Candidate 
Sydney School of Public Health
Sydney Medical School
Edward Ford Building (A27), Fisher Road, 
University of Sydney NSW 2006, 
Australia

and 
Project Coordinator
Maternal and Child Health Division (MCHD)
International Centre for Diarrhoeal Disease Research, Bangladeh (icddr,b) 
68, Shaheed Tajudddin Ahmed Sarani
Mohakhali, Dhaka 1212
</address>
      <phone>+61412735284</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>thuda@icddrb.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Shahreen Raihana</name>
      <address>Research Investigator
Maternal and Child Health Division (MCHD)
International Centre for Diarrhoeal Disease Research, Bangladesh (icddr,b)
68 Shaheed Tajuddin Ahmed Sharani, Mohakhali, 
Dhaka 1212, Bangladesh.</address>
      <phone>+8801778148334</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>shahreenr@icddrb.org</email>
      <country>Bangladesh</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>