<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363636">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/02/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/02/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000209796</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effectiveness of psychostimulant and broader action antidepressant medications for patients with melancholic depression</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomized controlled trial of methylphenidate (either as a monotherapy or an adjunct treatment) compared to an antidepressant group (dual action or tricyclic antidepressants) for patients with treatment-resistant melancholic depression to see if effective in improvement in depression ratings and remission over an 8-week period. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1139-2174 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>TOMEDS_PS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil.</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Melancholic Depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The trial involves three treatment groups:
1. Methylphenidate (MPD) monotherapy (Group 1)
2. Antidepressant monotherapy (group 2)
3. MPD and antidepressant combination Group 3)

Administration of medication will be as follows for the three treatment groups:

Group 1: : MPD will be progressively titrated up from 10 mg (taken daily) and with the dose increase ceased if the subject reports (i) a full response or significant side-effects, or (ii) no improvement beyond that of previous dose increase, or (iii) mood worsens on dose increase. Maximum dose of 30 mg/day. The managing clinician will assess clinical progress, pulse rate and blood pressure on a fortnightly basis. 

Group 2:	Administration of a dual or broad-action antidepressant, with decision dictated by previous failed antidepressant drug classes. Subjects who have only trialed an selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor (SSRI) will be prescribed a dual action antidepressant (desvenlafaxine) while patients that have previously trialed a dual-action drug will be prescribed a tricyclic antidepressant (dothiepin). These medications will be administered and titrated in line with current clinical procedures and patients will be clinically reviewed fortnightly. 

Group 3: As above, for MPD. Antidepressant will be selected in line with previous antidepressants trialed by patient and titrated in line with standard clinician practice. 

MPD will be administered in tablet form (10mg tablets; Trade name: Ritalin) with approval for prescription sought from the Pharmaceutical Branch of NSW Health per standard clinical procedures. 

The antidepressant dose will be administered in line with standard clinical procedure and on a case by case basis with (as for MPD) the dose increase ceased if the subject reports (i) a full response or significant side-effects, or (ii) no improvement beyond that of previous dose increase, or (iii) mood worsens on dose increase. Maximum dose administered in line with standard clinical guidelines.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Comparator group is the antidepressant monotherapy group, with the choice of antidepressant dictated by previous medications trialled and respective responses.

</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvement in depressive severity (via responder and remission rates) on the Quick Inventory of Depressive Symptomatology (QIDS). . 


</outcome>
      <timepoint>QIDS: Baseline, weekly for 8 weeks after commencing trial medication, follow-up (at 8 weeks after commencing trial medication). 
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depressive symptom severity will be assessed by the Hamilton Depression Inventory (HAM-D).

 A trial responder is operationalized as an improvement of 50% or more and a remitter by having a Hamilton score of less than seven at the trials conclusion.</outcome>
      <timepoint>HAMD: Baseline, fortnightly for 8 weeks after commencing trial medication, follow-up (at 8 weeks after commencing trial medication). 
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>i. Improvement on other psychiatric constructs, such as anxiety (measured by the Depression and Anxiety Scale), life satisfaction and enjoyment (Quality of Life Enjoyment &amp; Satisfaction Questionnaire) , social and occupational functioning (Work Productivity and Impairment Questionnaire).

</outcome>
      <timepoint>i. These additional psychiatric constructs are measured at baseline, fortnightly (for 8 weeks) and 8-week follow-up. 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>ii. Rapidity of response: measured by speed of response on the primary measures.</outcome>
      <timepoint>ii. Speed of response refers to improvement on QIDS measure (administered at baseline, weekly for 8 weeks, and 8-week follow-up).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>iii. Tolerance and dependence rates in the MPD groups: as indicated by managing clinician responsible for the administration of the trial medication.</outcome>
      <timepoint>iii. Tolerance and dependence rates: from information provided to managing clinician (can be at any point in time over the trial)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>iv. Side-effect and drop-out rates: measured by the Side-effects Profile Form which is a list of the most common side-effects associated with the trial medications and which is completed by the researcher and managing clinician. This form was developed for the purpose of this study. </outcome>
      <timepoint>iv. Side-effect and drop-out rates: drop out rates measured at trial's conclusion and side-effects measured at week 1 (after commencing trial medication) and continuing weekly until week 8 of treatment (follow-up). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion Criteria:
1.	Aged 18-65 years
2.	Diagnosis of a unipolar melancholic depression according to a Black Dog Institute psychiatrist and DSM IV-TR criteria (measured by MINI)
3.	Currently depressed with depressive onset present for at least 4 weeks
4.	Score on HAM-D equal to or greater than 14 and score on QIDS equal to or greater than 11 (i.e.  moderately to severely depressed)
5.	Failed two or more SSRI or dual action antidepressants (but never trialed a TCA or monoamine oxidase inhibitor (MAOI)) 
6.	Willing to accept randomized assignment to one of the three treatment options. 
7.	Prepared to commit to fortnightly visits to the BDI and participate in weekly phone calls with the researcher who will complete the QIDS and monitor side effects. 
8.	Able to provide written informed consent.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion Criteria
1.	Under 18 years of age, or over 65.
2.	Poor written and/or spoken English.
3.	Pregnant or breastfeeding
4.	Medical condition which contraindicates any trial treatment groups (e.g. epilepsy, cardiovascular condition, resting pulse rate above 80, blood pressure above 140/100).
5.	Currently psychotic or acutely suicidal
6.	Current drug or alcohol problems
7.	Has previously trialed a psychostimulant or was a previous user of psychostimulant.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Once a patient is deemed eligible for the study they will be assigned a study enrollment number that will be used on all study documents and a randomly allocated treatment group (via a blocked randomization, which is computer-generated). 

Allocation is concealed from all subsequent raters (who are blind to treatment group of all patients) and this is ensured by using a sealed opaque envelope with the patients treatment group inside and which is only seen by the participant, the managing clinician and the study researcher. 

An independent (and blinded) research assistant will be rating the key outcome measures. 
</concealment>
    <sequence>A blocked randomization will be computer generated.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>NA. </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The primary analyses will be on an intention-to-treat (ITT) analysis. Secondary analyses on patients who complied with treatment are potentially informative and will be considered. For longitudinal outcomes, generalized linear mixed models will be preferred as they accommodate data that is missing at random. At individual time-points missing data will probably necessitate multiple imputation and such analyses will be examined under multiple approaches to examine for sensitivity to method.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>17/04/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/12/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>225</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Prince of Wales Hospital - Randwick</hospital>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of New South Wales</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of New South Wales
High St
Kensington, NSW 2052
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary aim of the study to evaluate the effectiveness of MPD as a monotherapy and adjunctive antidepressant treatment in patients with melancholic depression who have failed orthodox antidepressant options. 

Key Hypotheses:
1.	Those receiving MPD and an antidepressant will show superior responder and remission rates compared to those receiving an antidepressant only 
2.	Those receiving MPD monotherapy will show comparable remission and responder rates to those in Group 2 (a non-inferiority hypothesis).
3.	Those receiving MPD will improve more rapidly than those on antidepressants only
4.	Substantive side-effects and drop-out rates will be lowest for patients on MPD only.

</summary>
    <trialwebsite>None at present.</trialwebsite>
    <publication>None at present. </publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>None.</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ethics Secretariat
UNSW Grants Management Office
Rupert Myers Building, Level 3, South Wing
The University of New South Wales
SYDNEY NSW 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/10/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HC12503</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Gordon Parker</name>
      <address>Black Dog Institute.
Hospital Rd. Prince of Wales Hospital.
Randwick
2031, NSW, Sydney.</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9382 4372  </phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9382 4343</fax>
      <email>g.parker@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rebecca Graham</name>
      <address>Black Dog Institute.
Hospital Rd, Prince of Wales Hospital
Randwick
2031, NSW, Sydney.</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93829253</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rebecca.graham@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Dusan Hadzi-Pavlovic</name>
      <address>Black Dog Institute.
Hospital Rd, Prince of Wales Hospital
Randwick
2031, NSW, Sydney.</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93823716</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.hadzi-pavlovic@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rebecca Graham</name>
      <address>Black Dog Institute.
Hospital Rd, Prince of Wales Hospital
Randwick
2031, NSW, Sydney.</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93829253</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rebecca.graham@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>