<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308189">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/07/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/07/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000562279</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of Blacktown Australian Better Health Initiative Integration Project in Improving Continuity of Care in Chronic Cardiac, Respiratory and Aged Care Patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of Blacktown Australian Better Health Initiative (ABHI) Integration Project in Improving Continuity of Care in Chronic Cardiac, Respiratory and Aged Care Patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>The study aims to achieve continuity of care for chronic cardiac, chronic respiratory and aged patients in the areas of Blacktown, by integrating the services of the hospital, general practitioners and community health services.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Observational study. We will compare patient presentations and admissions to the emergency department at Blacktown hospital 12 months prior to enrollment into the ABHI Integration project and 6 months following. In particular we will evaluate the date of admission, duration of admission (i.e., bed-days) and discharge diagnoses.  We will also investigate the impact on health care in the community. The date of death of any patient participant who dies during the six months following enrollment will be recorded. At recruitment into the evaluation, and again one and six months later, each patient participant will be asked to complete the EQ-5D health status measure1. This is a generic measure of health status that is applicable to a wide range of chronic diseases.</interventions>
    <comparator>n/a</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To measure the rates of emergency department presentation and hospital admission amongst patients enrolled in the Blacktown ABHI Integration Project, prior to and following enrollment</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months prior to enrollment into the ABHI Integration project and 6 months following.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To explore patients', carers' and health professionals' accounts of how the Blacktown ABHI Integration project has influenced the care of enrolled patients, and develop a detailed, quantified account of the effect of the Blacktown ABHI Integration Project on the processes of care of enrolled patients, and in consequence on their rates of emergency department presentation and hospital admission.</outcome>
      <timepoint>We will conduct qualitative interviews once at approximately 6 months following enrollment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients who present to Blacktown hospital with chronic cardiac, chronic respiratory or aged care and are classed high-risk of re-presentation to hospital and have had some form of care co-ordination from a care navigator in the emergency department or ward during their admission. Patients must also reside in the greater Blacktown area.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients under 18 years of age that are not chronically ill or not requiring aged care.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>28/07/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>WentWest Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>20 Wentworth Street 
Parramatta NSW 2150</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>WentWest Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>20 Wentworth Street 
Parramatta NSW 2150</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of the outcome evaluation will be to describe changes in the rates of emergency department presentations and hospital admissions associated with the Blacktown ABHI Integration Project, and to explore changes in the processes of patient care in the community that may explain these. The specific objectives will be: 1. To measure the rates of emergency department presentation and hospital admission amongst patients enrolled in the Blacktown ABHI Integration Project, prior to and following enrollment; also to measure contacts with SWAHS Community Health Services durign this time; 2. To explore patients, carers and health professionals accounts of how the Blacktown ABHI Integration Project has influenced the care of enrolled patients; and, 3. To develop a detailed, quantified account of the effect of the Blacktown ABHI Integration Project on the processes of care of enrolled patients, and in consequence on their rates of emergency department presentation and hospital admission.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney West Area Health Service Human Research Ethics Committee, Westmead Campus</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Office
Westmead Hospital
Rm 2020, Clinical Sciences, 2nd Floor
WESTMEAD NSW 2145</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>HREC/09/WMEAD/157</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>17/06/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Joy Tripovich</name>
      <address>Joy Tripovich PhD
Research Evaluation Officer
Australian Better Health Initiative
WentWest Ltd

Department of General Practice
University of Sydney
PO Box 154
Westmead NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+612 9845 9215</phone>
      <fax>+612 9845 8166</fax>
      <email>j.tripovich@usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Joy Tripovich</name>
      <address>Joy Tripovich PhD
Research Evaluation Officer
Australian Better Health Initiative
WentWest Ltd

Department of General Practice
University of Sydney
PO Box 154
Westmead NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+612 9845 9215</phone>
      <fax>+612 9845 8166</fax>
      <email>j.tripovich@usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>