<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336187">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/11/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/11/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610001051033</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Stepping Stones Triple P for Parents of Children with Acquired Brain Injury</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy of a behavioural family intervention plus a stress management adjunct on parental adjustment and child behavioural and emotional outcomes in parents of children with acquired brain injury: A randomised controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acquired brain injury</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>There will be one treatment group in this study. Participants will receive a behavioural family intervention which aims to teach parents ways to manage children's behavioural and emotional difficulties, and to teach them new skills, while at the same time aiming to improve parents' confidence and parenting skills, and reduce stress. This program will be conducted as a group program with 5-10 families per group. 6 group sessions running for 2 hours each will be offered, with an additional 3 or 4 telephone consults each running for approximately 30 minutes. Participants will also receive an adjunct intervention targetting parental stress and coping prior to receiving the behavioural family intervention. This program will consist of 2 group sessions running for 2 hours each, and will be based in Acceptance and Commitment Therapy (ACT). The goal of ACT is to increase psychological flexibility, or the ability to persist or change in the service of chosen life values. The group program will address the following ACT processes: acceptance of negative cognitions and emotions, cognitive defusion, mindfulness or present moment awareness, values, and committed action. The total length of the intervention will be 10 weeks. All programs will be conducted by registered provisionally registered psychologists from the University of Queensland.</interventions>
    <comparator>The treatment group will be compared to a wait-list control group, who will receive the behavioural family intervention once both treatment groups have completed their interventions. The treatment groups will also be compared to one another, to determine whether the ACT adjunct provides additional therapeutic benefit.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Child behavioural outcome, as measured by the Eyberg Child Behaviour Inventory (ECBI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, Post-intervention, 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dysfunctional parenting style, as measured by the Parenting Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, Post-intervention, 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Child behavioural and emotional outcomes, as measured by the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire (SDQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, Post-intervention, 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parental adjustment (stress, anxiety and depression symptoms), as measured by the Depression Anxiety and Stress Scale (DASS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, Post-intervention, 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parenting confidence as measured by the Parenting Tasks Checklist</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, Post-intervention, 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parent psychological flexibility, as measured by an adapted Acceptance and Action Questionnaire specific for the ABI population, as well as the Parent Thoughts and Feelings Questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post-intervention, 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Family functioning, as assessed by the General Functioning scale of the Family Assessment Device (FAD).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post-intervention, 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parent relationship functioning, as assessed by the Relationship Quality Index (RQI), and the Parent Problem Checklists (PPC).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post-intervention, 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Parents will be able to participate in the study if they meet the following criteria: -their child is aged between 2 and 12 -their child has a diagnosis of an acquired brain injury -the injury occured at least 3 months prior to commencement of the intervention - the child is no longer acutely unwell -their child is displaying some behavioural, emotional, or developmental difficulties (based on parent self-report). - Parents speak adequate English to participate in the group program. Grandparents who are the primary carers for children meeting the above criteria will also be eligible to participate.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- child is participating in a concurrent research project targetting child behavioural or emotional difficulties (eg. anger management)
- child is not experiencing any ongoing behavioural, emotional, or developmental difficulties following the brain injury
-child is in the custody of the Department of Child Safety</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be assessed for eligibility and enrolled in the study as they volunteer. Informed consent for participation will be gained from parents. 

Prior to the intervention, participants will be asked to complete their baseline questionnaire packs. Once this is received back from a participant, they will be randomly assigned to a group and informed of their allocation and the dates and times of their group. The random allocation will be from sealed opaque envelopes.

Treatment allocation will be recorded on a piece of paper, folded and placed inside each envelope in a random, computer generated, order. Envelopes will be opened in order as each participant is to be allocated.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using computerised sequence generation will be employed.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This study has a treatment groups and a waitlist control group.  The wait-list control group will also receive the comprehensive behavioural family intervention once the treatment groups have concluded their intervention. </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>22/10/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>24/05/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>57</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>4029</postcode>
    <postcode>4072</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Assoc Prof Kate Sofronoff</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Psychology
University of Queensland
St Lucia
QLD 4072</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Queensland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PhD student funds for primary investigator:
Felicity Brown
School of Psychology
University of Queensland 
St Lucia, QLD 4072</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Queensland Children's Medical Research Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Scholarship support

Level 4, Foundation Building
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston Rd, Herston, QLD 4029</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Queensland Cerebral Palsy and Rehabilitation Research Centre</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>In-kind support such as providing a computer, desk, telephone, printing, and other minor costs.

Level 3, Foundation Building
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston Rd, Herston, QLD 4029</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Kate Sofronoff</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>(Primary supervisor of Felicity Brown)
School of Psychology
University of Queensland 
St Lucia, QLD 4072</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Koa Whittingham</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>(Associate supervisor of Felicity Brown)
Queensland Cerebral Palsy and Rehabilitation Research Centre
Level 3, Foundation Building
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston Rd, Herston, QLD 4029</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Assoc Prof Roslyn Boyd</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>(Associate supervisor of Felicity Brown)
Queensland Cerebral Palsy and Rehabilitation Research Centre
Level 3, Foundation Building
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston Rd, Herston, QLD 4029</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Lynne McKinlay</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>(Associate supervisor of Felicity Brown)
Director of Medicine 
Level 1, North Tower
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston Rd, Herston, QLD 4029</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>An acquired brain injury (or ABI) refers to an injury to the brain that has occurred after birth. Common causes of traumatic brain injury (the most common subtype of ABI) are motor vehicle accidents, falls, sporting injuries, or assaults. Other causes of brain injury include stroke, tumor, infection, or hypoxia. In children, brain injury can cause existing skills and abilities to be lost at least temporarily, and can also cause delays in the development of new skills. Some children recover very well, however it is quite common for children to experience some form of behavioural, social, academic, physical, emotional or developmental problems. It is recognised that acquired brain injury can impact on the entire family system. Not only do parents have to manage the stress associated with the difficulties that their child is experiencing, they are also often dealing with many emotions related to the ABI, attending many appointments for their child, and dealing with schools and various other agencies. This study aims to assess the efficacy of a behavioural family intervention, plus an ACT-based intervention addressing the emotional costs of ABI, tailored specifically for parents of children with ABI, with an emphasis on the difficulties that might be unique to these families. It is predicted that this intervention will lead to decreases in child problem behaviour and emotional difficulties, improvements in parenting style, and improvements in parental adjustment.  </summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://exp.psy.uq.edu.au/steppingstonesbraininjury</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Children's Hospital and Health Services District Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Department of Paediatrics and Child Health
Level 3, Foundation Building
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston Road, Herston QLD 4029</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/08/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/10/QRCH/67</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/07/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Queensland Medical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research and Innovation Division 
University of Queensland
St Lucia, QLD 4072</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/08/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2010001056</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/08/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Mater Medical Research Institute</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Mater Hospital, Raymond Tce, South Brisbane, QLD 4101</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/07/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1731C</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Education Queensland</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Education House
30 Mary St, Brisbane, QLD 4000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/02/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>550/27/1046</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Catholic Education QLD</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 1201 
Brisbane QLD 4001
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>2011/146</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/03/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Felicity Brown</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
University of Queensland
St Lucia, QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3346 7285 or +61 7 3636 1292</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3636 5538</fax>
      <email>f.brown@psy.uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Felicity Brown</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
University of Queensland
St Lucia, QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3346 7285 or +61 7 3636 1292</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3636 5538</fax>
      <email>f.brown@psy.uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Felicity Brown</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
University of Queensland
St Lucia, QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3346 7285 or +61 7 3636 1292</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3636 5538</fax>
      <email>f.brown@psy.uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Felicity Brown</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
University of QLD
St Lucia, QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 407 151 650</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>f.brown@psy.uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>