<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363182">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/10/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/11/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001161819</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A trial of the Tailored Activities Program (TAP) for reducing challenging behaviours in persons with dementia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The TAP program: Tailored activities to reduce challenging behaviours in persons with dementia - a randomized trial of effectiveness and cost effectiveness</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>TAP Tailored Activities Program for people with dementia and their carers</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Dementia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dementias</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The 8 session intervention program involves an occupational therapist identifying preserved capabilities, deficit areas, and previous interests of the person with dementia from which they prescribe specific activities. The 8 sessions run for around 1-1.5 hours each and occur over a 4 month period. Sessions involve both the person with dementia and their family caregiver. Family caregivers are then trained to use activities as part of daily care at home as a management strategy to reduce behavioural symptoms.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group is designed to control for the empathetic listening and targeted information received by caregivers in the experimental group. The carer will receive three telephone education sessions of between 15 to 30 minutes each over a 4 month period. The sessions will be based on selected chapters from a current book by Prof. Brian Draper about dementia.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of neuropsychiatric symptoms measured using the NPI-C- frequency of apathy, agitation, depression, sleep and irritibility domains.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of neuropsychiatric symptoms measured using the NPI-C- frequency and severity of the 14 domains.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 months and 8 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of function using the Disability Assessment for Dementia (DAD).</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 months and 8 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of carer quality of life using the Life Satisfaction Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 months and 8 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of carer burden using the Zarit Burden Inventory (ZBI).</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 months and 8 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of carer stress, anxiety and depression, using the Depression, Anxiety and Stress Scale (DASS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 months and 8 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of caregiver skill using the Task Management Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 months and 8 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of caregiver confidence in using activities using the Caregiver Confidence in Using Activities Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 months and 8 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of carer vigilance using the Vigilance Items Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 months and 8 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of carer work productivity and activity impairment using the Work Productivity and Activity Impairement Questionnaire: Specific Health Problem (WPAI-SHP).</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 months and 8 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of patient quality of life via proxy assessment with carer using the Euro Quality of Life (EQ-5D-3L Proxy).</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 months and 8 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of resource utilisation in dementia using the Resource Utilisation in Dementia (RUD-Lite).</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 months 8 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of health utilities using the proxy version of the Health Utilities Index (HUI).</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 months 8 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of carer willingness to pay for potential services using the Willingness to Pay questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Person with dementia must:
1.	Have a diagnosis of dementia by a specialist, or meet the DSM-V (Major Neurocognitive Disorder) criteria
2.	Be rated by the carer as having a frequency score of at least 2 or above on any item of the NPI-Q (Neuropsychiatric Inventory) over the past month.
3.	Have conversational English
4.	Be able to participate (independently or with some help) in at least two activities of daily living (ADLs; eg. bathing, dressing, grooming, toileting, transferring from bed to chair)
5.	If on psychotropic medication, be on a stable dose for the past 60 days
6.	If on dementia medication, be on a stable dose for the past 3 months. 
7.     Person with dementia should be living in the community.

Carer must:
1.	Report occurrence of one or more behaviours (eg. apathy, passivity, disruptive behaviours) in person with dementia over the past month
2.	Have conversational English
3.	Be a family member of at least 18 years old and living with person with dementia or have at least 4 days or 7hrs per week contact.
4.	Be accessible by phone
5.	Indicate a willingness to learn use of activities</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Person with dementia will be excluded if:
1.	They are currently involved in another clinical trial
2.	They have a history of schizophrenia or bipolar disorder
3.	Their dementia is secondary to head trauma, alcohol, brain tumour, HIV
4.	They are not responsive to their environment (eg. unable to understand short commands or recognise a person coming in/out of the room)
5.	They are bed bound
6.	If patient is within the last 3 stages (7d, e, f) on the FAST (Functional assessment staging of Alzheimers Disease) which include the patient being unable to sit up without assistance, unable to hold their head up or unable to smile.
7.	They do not have capacity for functional communication

Carers will be excluded if:
1.	They are currently involved in another clinical trial
2.	They are planning to place person in a nursing home within 8 months
3.	They are on a psychotropic or cholinesterase inhibitor medication, which has not been a stable dose for past 60 days. 
4.	They have an active psychiatric disorder and have been admitted to a psychiatric hospital related to this in the past 5 years.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomisation will be generated by an investigator not involved in data collection or intervention. Placed in opaque envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted blocks of various sizes.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Nil</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>8/11/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>198</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>2101</postcode>
    <postcode>2031</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Cumberland Campus
75 East St
Lidcombe 
NSW 2141</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
 16 Marcus Clarke Street
 Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of NSW</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Kensington Campus

The University of New South Wales
SYDNEY
NSW 2052
AUSTRALIA</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Neuroscience Research Australia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Barker St
Randwick
NSW 2031</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Behavioural disturbances associated with dementia are common amongst community-residing people with moderate to severe dementia and are associated with reduced quality of life for both the person with dementia and their caregiver. We propose a randomized trial to test the effectiveness and cost effectiveness of the Tailored Activities Program (TAP) to reduce the burden of behavioural and psychological symptoms of dementia. The 8-session intervention involves occupational therapists identifying preserved capabilities, deficit areas, and previous interests of the person from which they prescribe specific activities. Family caregivers are then trained to use activities as part of daily care at home as a management strategy to reduce behavioural symptoms.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee of The University of Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 6, Jane Foss Russell Building - G02
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006 AUSTRALIA</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/08/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>15018</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Lindy Clemson</name>
      <address>C42 - Cumberland Campus
The University of Sydney
Lidcombe
NSW 2141 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 9372</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351 9672</fax>
      <email>lindy.clemson@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Lindy Clemson</name>
      <address>C42 - Cumberland Campus
The University of Sydney
Lidcombe
NSW 2141 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 9372</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351 9672</fax>
      <email>lindy.clemson@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Claire O'Connor</name>
      <address>C42 - Cumberland Campus
The University of Sydney
Lidcombe
NSW 2141 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 9594</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351 9672</fax>
      <email>claire.oconnor@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>