<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="1365">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/03/2004</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/03/2004</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000472572</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Optimising very preterm infant outcomes: an evidence based screening and surveillance method</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The accurate identification of very preterm infant disability by general practitioners in the primary practice setting using screening and surveillance methods</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>OPIO</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Perinatal Trials Registry: PTR518</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Disability of very preterm infant</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Complications of newborn</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Children born very preterm-at a gestation less than 31 completed weeks- at approximately two weeks prior to discharge from the special care nurseries of Queensland tertiary maternity hospitals were randomised to either the preterm-targeted screening and surveillance group (which was a targeted screening program for disability) or to the National Health Medical Research Council screening program (which is the Australian routine and universal child health program for disability). Both groups screening programs were cordinated by the child's general practitioner. Screening was conducted over the child's first 12-months corrected age of life. General practitioners used the infomation from their respective programs to complete a questionnaire on disability which they returned to the coordinating centre at the Royal Brisbane Women's Hopsital.</interventions>
    <comparator>National Health Medical Research Council screening program (which is the Australian routine and universal child health program for disability).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Agreement (agreed status / disagreed and unsure status) on the primary classification of disability status between general practitioners in both groups (preterm-targeted and National Health Medical Research Council) and the tertiary centre neurodevelopmental assessment at 12-months corrected age conducted in the tertiary centre hospital.  Status=disabled will be defined by the neurodevelopmental assessment as the presence of any of: crebral palsy where a child has nonprogressive motor impairment characterized by abnormal muscle tone and movement, developmental delay where a child scored more than 1.0 SD below the standardised test mean assessed with the Revised Griffith Mental Development Scales or the Bayley Scales of Infant Development II - Mental Developmental Intelligence, bilateral blindness if visual acuity in both eyes was worse than 6/60 and deaf if they required aids. Clinicians performing the tertiary assessment were blinded to the childs trial treatment assignation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 12-months corrected age</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sensitivity analysis. 
There were three sensitivity analyses. 1) Agreement on a secondary classification of disability status (&lt;-2SD developmental quoitents, cerebral palsy, bilateral blindness or hearing requiring aids) correctly identified by general practitioner in both groups. 
The primary classification of disability was used to test the two general practitioner groups for 2) interrater agreement (agreed status / disagreed ststus)and as a 3) screening instrument. </outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1. The effect of the screening and surveillance programs on parental stress and parent-child interaction measured by the Edinburgh Postnatal Depression Scale and the Parenting Stress Index-Short Form</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 12-months corrected age of the child. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2. Families were asked to document the health services they used including rehospitalisations</outcome>
      <timepoint>Over the 12-month study period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3. A locally designed questionnaire on how helpful the assigned program was in assisting with child health was sent to parents and general practitioners</outcome>
      <timepoint>At completion of the study at 12-months corrected age of the child.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Infants who met the following criteria were enrolled two weeks prior to discharge from the special care nursery by research assistants from each of Queensland's three tertiary maternity hospitals (The Royal Brisbane Women's Hosiptal RBWH, Mater Mother's Hospital MMH, The Townsville Hospital TTH):Inclusion criteria included: infants (male and female) born at a gestation less than 31 completed weeks, whose family could nominate a general practioner and who would return for follow.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Not stated</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>31</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Weeks</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>none</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by phone</concealment>
    <sequence>Block randomisation with random even-numbers between ten and twenty inclusively, stratified for hospital, gestation and social risk factors (two or more of the following: indigenous, single parent, maternal education below school grade 10 or gross weekly household income less than $400.00) were used to assign infants to treatment groups. The first child of a multiple birth was randomised and its siblings automatically assigned to the same group through a central telephone randomisation service. The study investigators were unaware of the block sizes employed and had no access to either the computer or randomisation database.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>None</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/12/2002</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>202</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Queensland Health Golden Carsket</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Bonnie Babes</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Brisbane Women's Hospital Research Scholarship</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Queensland Health</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Studies in the United Kingdom have shown the feasibility of collecting a standardised core of data with specific criteria for defining disability in children born very preterm at two years of age from questionnaires completed by parents and health care clinicians.  Evaluation of outcomes for children born very preterm by questionnaires are very important for the purpose of providing global and epidemiologic information on outcomes, and for planning of services.  However, most of the available questionnaires are a subjective assessment of the child and liable to bias.  We are proposing the use of questionnaires to collect late morbidity and disability data from the primary health sector in children born very preterm with the support of a structured preterm clinical pathway for screening and surveillance.   The pathway has been designed to ensure standardised data collection providing a more objective and valid assessment of late morbidity and disability.  It is not designed to replace specialist assessment of a child.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Brisbane Women's Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>RBWH02/16</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Queensland</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>2002000895</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Townsville Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>40/02</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Mater Mothers' Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>540M</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Margo Anne Pritchard</name>
      <address>Perinatal Research Centre. University of Queensland. Ned Hanlon Building Level 6. The Royal Brisbane Women's Hospital. Herston QLD 4209</address>
      <phone>+61 7 36365172</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 36367169</fax>
      <email>mpritchard@somc.uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Margo Anne Pritchard</name>
      <address>Perinatal Research Centre
Level 6
Ned Hanlon Building
University of Queensland
The Royal Brisbane Women's Hospital
Herston QLD 4209</address>
      <phone>+61 7 36365172</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 36367169</fax>
      <email>mpritchard@somc.uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>