<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370786">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001168448</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A study to determine whether myalgia is due to statin use</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Protocol for a N-of-1 (Single-Patient) trial service to determine whether myalgia is due to statin use in a sample of patients with a history of statin-induced myalgia</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Statin-induced myalgia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Rosuvastatin 5mg once daily for 3 weeks followed by a wash-out period with a matching placebo for 3 weeks, and followed by matching placebo 3 weeks. Oral capsules</interventions>
    <comparator>matching placebo capsule</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the value of N-of-1 trials in determining statin induced myalgia by comparing measures of myalgia (through the Myalgia Score questionnaire, and CK levels in serum assay) in treatment versus control periods. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 6, 9, 12, 15, 18, 21, 24 and 27 weeks post randomisation
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To record the number of eligible patients screened and number of those consent to participate
</outcome>
      <timepoint>27 weeks  post randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the trial drop out rate and reasons for drop out

</outcome>
      <timepoint>27 weeks  post randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate resume rate to statin therapy after completion of N-of-1 trials
the number of participants that will continue statin therapy after completion of the study
</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The percentage of participants that are given a final diagnosis of statin-related myalgia at the conclusion of their participation in the N-of-1 service
</outcome>
      <timepoint>27 weeks post randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Has indication for statin therapy;
History of intolerance of both atorvastatin 10 mg AND rosuvastatin 5 mg monotherapy;
History of statin-related myalgia occuring within three weeks of starting statin therapy and consequently discontinued statin use;
Without clinically significant CK elevations, &lt;3x the upper limit of normal or &lt;3x times the baseline value
Willing to restart statin therapy.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnancy;
History of alcohol and/or drug abuse;
Hypothyroidism;
Renal function impairment; 
Liver obstructions, patients with elevated liver enzymes (up to 3 times)
History of rhabdomyolysis;
History of metabolic or inflammatory myopathy;
History of neuropathy;
Unlikely to comply with the demands of N-of-1 trial.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation involved contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who was "off-site" or at central administration site.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>N-of-1 single patient design</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>3/04/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>5/02/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>15</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>2</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/08/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The George Institue for Global Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 10, King George V Building Missenden Rd, Camperdown NSW 2050
Postal Address: PO Box: M201 Missenden Rd, NSW 2050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Heart Foundation Vanguard Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 3, 80 William Street, EAST SYDNEY New South Wales 2010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Level 11 KGV Building, Missenden Rd
Camperdown
2050 NSW </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>National Heart Foundation guidelines recommend long-term statin therapy in several major patient groups, but adherence rates are low, even following life-threatening events such as acute coronary syndrome. Muscle-related symptoms are the most commonly reported reason for statin discontinuation and about 1 in 5 patients taking statins report some degree of muscular pain. Placebo-controlled trials indicate overall in a treated population most symptoms are not due to the statin, but for an individual patient it is typically impossible to be certain. N-of-1 (single-patient multiple crossover) trials offer a simple, intuitive way to resolve this uncertainty. While N-of-1 trials have been used for more than 20 years, to date, few clinical services in Australia are conducting N-of-1 trials on a regular basis to improve the management of individual patient. Fewer studies have looked at the potential of using N-of-1 trials to determine statin tolerability.  A recently published study suggested that N-of-1 trials can improve the assessment of statin-related myalgia in selected patients from endocrinology clinics in Canada. However, the results were limited by its small sample size and the potential for expanded use of N-of-1 trials to improve the compliance of statin therapy among statin intolerant patients remains unclear. 
The study will include up to 15 N-of-1 trial participants. Patients with prior history of intolerance of both atorvastatin 10 mg AND rosuvastatin 5 mg monotherapy, had statin-related myalgia occurring within three weeks of starting statin therapy and consequently discontinued statin use will be invited to participate. Each person will go through 3 double-blind, crossover comparisons of statin versus matching placebo. Each treatment and control period will last for 3-weeks and there will be a 3-week placebo wash out period after each of the active statin treatment. The total trial period for each participant will be 27 weeks. Myalgia scores will be recorded on a weekly basis during the study period. Brief Pain Inventory Questionnaire will be completed and blood sample collection will be done at baseline and at the end of each active treatment and control period to measure serum CK, ALT, AST, FGF21 and creatinine levels. To avoid unblinding of treatment allocation during the trial period, additional blood samples will be stored to measure lipids levels upon study completion. Genotype analysis will also be done at the end of the study to determine if genotype is associated with statin-induced myalgia. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Local Health District</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>c/- Research Ethics and Governance Office (REGO)
 Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
 Missenden Road
 CAMPERDOWN NSW 2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/07/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>X15-0411 </hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/12/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nicole Li</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health
Level 10 KGV Building
Missenden rd
Camperdown
NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8052 4507 </phone>
      <fax>+61 2 8052 4502</fax>
      <email>nli@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Cindy Kok</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health
Level 10 KGV Building
Missenden rd
Camperdown
NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8052 4748</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 8052 4502</fax>
      <email>ckok@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Cindy Kok</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health
Level 10 KGV Building
Missenden rd
Camperdown
NSW 2050 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 8052 4748</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 8052 4502</fax>
      <email>ckok@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>