<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364060">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/04/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/04/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000434796</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Hyperbaric Oxygen Therapy and Insulin Resistance.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of one session of Hyperbaric Oxygen Therapy on insulin resistance in overweight men and women.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Insulin sensitivity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Visit 0 (Pre-clamp) and Visit 3 (Post-clamp) - Blood samples and subcutaneous adipose tissue biopsy:
Subject will be seated comfortably in a chair for a 2-hour period. An IV cannula will be inserted into a vein in the forearm, and blood will be taken for analysis of fasting glucose and insulin time (t) = 0 min, and for cytokines at t = 0, 60 and 120 mins. The adipose tissue biopsy will then be performed. After cleansing the skin on the abdomen lateral to the umbilicus with chlorhexidine solution, and placing a fenestrated drape, anaesthesia will be administered (5ml of Xylocaine 2%, no adrenaline) via subcutaneous injection. A 0.75cm incision is made in the skin using a #11 scalpel, and a 5mm Bergstrom needle inserted to collect approximately 250mg of adipose tissue with suction. Two or three passes will be used to obtain approximately 500mg of adipose tissue. The sample is washed in sterile 0.9% saline and snap frozen in liquid nitrogen. Upon completion of the biopsy, pressure is applied and the incision closed with a sterile 'Steri-strip'.

Visit 1 and Visit 2 - Hyperinsulinaemic euglycaemic clamp:
Two intravenous cannulae are inserted into veins in contralateral forearms using local anaesthetic (lignocaine 1%).  A baseline blood sample is taken to assess fasting glucose, and a primed insulin infusion is started for assessment of insulin sensitivity by hyperinsulinemic euglycemic clamp (80mU/m2/min) for 3.5 hours. Blood samples (&lt;2mls) are obtained at 5-10 minute intervals so that blood glucose can be maintained at 5mmol/L with a variable infusion of 25% Dextrose, and a trained individual will be present for the duration of the clamping procedure.  The steady state glucose infusion rate is calculated over the final 30 minutes of the clamp and adjusted for fat free mass by DXA. Immediately post-clamp, volunteers are given orange juice and high carbohydrate lunch, and the glucose infusion is maintained on a halving scale for 5 minutes each for at least 20 minutes. Blood sugar levels are monitored every 10-15 minutes for 45-60 minutes.

Visit 2 and Visit 3 - Hyperbaric oxygen (HBO) therapy:
Subject will be seated comfortably in a chair and wheeled into the chamber. The HBO session will involve compression to 2 atmospheres absolute, breathing 100% oxygen via a 'hood' gas delivery system for 90 minutes, and a linear decompression to 1 atmosphere absolute over 30 minutes. During visit 2, the 2-hour HBO treatment will occur during the second and third hours of the clamp. During visit 3, the HBO treatment will occur during the 2 hours immediately preceding the biopsy.

Visit 4 - Blood samples:
Subject will be seated comfortably, and a single blood sample will be taken for analysis of fasting glucose, insulin and cytokines. 

Visits 1 to 4 will occur on consecutive days, and visit 0 will occur 1 to 2 weeks beforehand.</interventions>
    <comparator>No treatment: Subjects will undergo the insulin clamp and adipose tissue biopsy without hyperbaric oxygen therapy.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Insulin sensitivity, as measured by the hyperinsulinaemic euglycaemic clamp.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The clamps will be used to measure insulin sensitivity on two separate days. The first clamp will occur without hyperbaric oxygen (HBO) treatment, and act as a 'basline' measurement, while the second clamp will occur the following day with a 2-hour HBO treatment starting after the first hour. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Inflammation and angiogenesis associated with insulin resistance, as measured by levels of various cytokine markers (CRP, MCP1, TNFa, IL-6, ICAM-1, VEGFa and PDGF) using various serum and plasma assays.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At t=0min, 60min and 120min of a 2 hour period with or without hyperbaric oxygen exposure.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gene expression related to inflammation and angiogenesis present in adipose tissue samples will be measured using Q-PCR.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, and after one 2-hour hyperbaric oxygen exposure.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Overweight and obesity (BMI 25-35kg/m2)
2. Assessed fitness to enter hyperbaric chamber</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Personal history of Diabetes or major psychiatric disorders,
2. Use of prescribed or non-prescribed medications which may affect glucose homeostasis (eg steroids) 
3. Uncontrolled asthma, current fever, upper respiratory infections
4. Individuals who regularly perform high intensity exercise (&gt;2 week)
5. Pregnancy, lactation (breast feeding), women who are planning to become pregnant.
6. Current intake of &gt; 140g alcohol/week
7. Current smokers of cigarettes/cigars/marijuana
8. Current intake of any illicit substance
9. Experience claustrophobia in confined spaces
10. Has donated blood within past 3-months
11. Has been involved in any other study within the past 3-months
12. Unable to comprehend study protocol
13. Any other contraindication to HBOT (eg Eustachian tube dysfunction making middle ear inflation ineffective)
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>9/04/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>David Wilkinson</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Hyperbaric Medicine Unit
Dept of Anaesthesia and Intensive Care
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Tce, Adelaide SA 5000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Adelaide Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>North Tce, Adelaide SA 5000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Leonie Heilbronn</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University of Adelaide
Discipline of Medicine
Eleanor Harrald Building
Frome Rd, Adelaide SA 5000</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In a recent series of studies performed by our group, we have shown that exposure to hyperbaric oxygen (HBO) leads to an increase in insulin sensitivity in male subjects and that this improvement can be measured in all men, not just those with diabetes. The aim of this study is to investigate the time course of this effect and explore the mechanisms involved when exposure to HBO induces an increase in peripheral insulin sensitivity. This study will also test whether the same thing happens in female subjects.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>David Wilkinson</name>
      <address>Hyperbaric Medicine Unit
Dept of Anaesthesia and Intensive Care
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Tce, Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61882225116</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>david.wilkinson@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Briohny Bartlett</name>
      <address>University of Adelaide
Discipline of Medicine
Level 6, Eleanor Harrald Building
Frome Rd, Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61882224130</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>briohny.bartlett@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>David Wilkinson</name>
      <address>Hyperbaric Medicine Unit
Dept of Anaesthesia and Intensive Care
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Tce, Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61882225116</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>david.wilkinson@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>