<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362227">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/05/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/05/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000512820</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A pilot safety and acceptability trial of moderated on-line social therapy (MOST) for first-episode psychosis.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot safety and acceptability trial of moderated on-line social therapy (MOST) for first-episode psychosis.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>First Episode Psychosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Psychosis and personality disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Our newly developed moderated on-line social therapy model (MOST) offers an ICT paradigm which has the potential to address important challenges in the engagement and treatment of young people recovering from early psychosis. We have pioneered and developed a new model for on-line behavioural interventions entitled Moderated on-line social therapy (MOST). The MOST model integrates on-line social networking with individually tailored interactive psychosocial interventions, with the involvement of expert mental health and peer moderators to ensure the effectiveness and safety of the intervention. MOST has been applied to a world-first program entitled Horyzons designed for the purpose of assisting young FEP patients in their recovery. Horyzons is a wesbite which has been designed as a supplement to traditional face-to-face biopsychosocial interventions for FEP, and has not been designed as a replacement for recommended treatments. The online intervention will be provided for a 4-week period. Participants will be asked to use Horyzons at their discretion.</interventions>
    <comparator>Uncontrolled: the same intervention will be applied to all participants in the study</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acceptability of the system will be considered achieved if 10 of the 20 participants log on more than once per week across each of the four weeks during the 1-month of the pilot.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Follow-up assessment post-trial (1 month follow-up)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The pilot will be considered to indicate safety of the Horyzons system if: (i) all participants report feeling adequately supported by moderators via the semi-structured interview, (ii) two or less participants experience relapse in psychosis during the 1 month of the pilot; (iii) no participants deliberately self harm during the course of the pilot; and (iii) if there are no unlawful entries into the Horyzons system.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Follow-up assessment post-trial (1 month follow-up)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(a) a first episode of a DSM-IV psychotic disorder or mood disorder with psychotic features; (b) aged 15-25 years inclusive; (c) less than or equal to 6 months treatment with an antipsychotic medication prior to registration with the early psychosis service; (d) remission on positive symptoms of psychosis which will be defined as 4 weeks or more of scores of 3 (mild) or below on the subscale items hallucinations, unusual thought disorder, conceptual disorganization, and suspiciousness on the expanded version of the Brief Psychiatric Rating Scale (BPRS). Additional inclusion criteria to ensure low level of risk within MOST include: (e) low aggressiveness which will be defined by a score of 5 or below (with the exception of evidence of threat to others) on the hostility subscale of the expanded version of the BPRS for the month prior to study entry; and, (f) low suicidal risk defined as a score of 4 or below on the suicidality subscale for the month preceding study entry.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>15</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>25</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(a) intellectual disability; (b) inability to converse in, or read English; (c) participation in previous CBT or pharmacological trials for psychosis; (d) a DSM-IV diagnosis of either antisocial personality disorder (ASPD) or borderline personality disorder (BPD); (e) pregnancy; (f) medical conditions requiring high level of care; (g) presence of acute psychotic symptoms above a mild level; (h) presence of moderate or above levels of suicidality or hostility.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>After providing informed consent participants the RA will administer the SCID, BPRS and Calgary Depression Rating Scale. In a separate meeting the moderator will then orient participants to the Horyzons system. There will not be a control comparison intervention and all participants will have full access to their usual array of treatments at EPPIC and any treatments they are accessing elsewhere.
Participants will then be able to participate in Horzons at their convenience over a period of 1 month if they meet the inclusion and exclusion criteria.</concealment>
    <sequence>Non-randomised</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/01/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Helen Macpherson Smith Trust</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Helen Macpherson Smith Trust 27 Windsor Place
Melbourne Victoria 3000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Telstra Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Locked Bag 5680
Melbourne VIC 3001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Melbourne University, IBES</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Level 5, Alan Gilbert Blding,
161 Barry St (Cnr Grattan St), 
3010 Carlton
Victoria</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In this study we will evaluate the acceptability, feasibility, safety and initial clinical benefits of an online intervention (HORYZONS) designed to maintain the benefits of early intervention services for psychosis over the long term.
We expect that HORYZONS will be well-received, safe and seen as a valuable treatment option by young people suffering from psychosis.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>N/A</trialwebsite>
    <publication>N/A</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Melbourne Health - Human Research and Ethics Commitee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office for Research
Level 6 East, Main Building
300 Grattan Street
The Royal Melbourne Hospital  VIC  3050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/01/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2011.231</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/12/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>John Gleeson</name>
      <address>School of Psychology /Faculty of Arts and Science
Australian Catholic University
115 Victoria Parade 
3065 Fitzroy (Victoria)</address>
      <phone>(+61) 3 99533108</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>john.gleeson@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mario Alvarez</name>
      <address>Orygen Youth Health Research Centre 
35 Poplar Rd 
3052 Parkville (Victoria)</address>
      <phone>(+61) 401772668</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>malvarez@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mario Alvarez</name>
      <address>Orygen Youth Health Research Centre 
35 Poplar Rd 
3052 Parkville</address>
      <phone>(+61) 401772668</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>malvarez@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>