<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368842">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/06/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/07/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000711516</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>RECHARGE: A Behavioural Regulation Program for Young Persons with Depression</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>RECHARGE: A Behavioural Regulation Program Targeting Circadian Desynchrony in Young Persons with Depression</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1171-6564</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The main objective of this study is to evaluate whether a behavioural regulation program called RECHARGE that targets desynchrony in circadian rhythms can reduce depressive symptoms in young persons with depression. Specifically, this study will aim to restore circadian rhythm synchrony using RECHARGE, and improve depression as a result of restored circadian rhythm synchrony.

For this pilot phase of the study, we aim to recruit 20 participants. This small sample size was chosen to study the success of this novel behavioural regulation program as a pilot for a future study with a larger sample size.

Before the commencement of the study, participants will be asked to wear a wrist activity and light monitor, called an actigraphy watch. This is like a small watch worn on your non-dominant wrist, and will be worn for approximately 14 days before the beginning of the program. Participants will also be asked to complete a series of questionnaires and tests of mental and physical health.
 
After two weeks of wearing the watch, the 8-week behavioural regulation program will begin. At Week 1 of the program, participants will attend a 2 hour introductory group learning and training workshop. This group workshop (four persons) will involve engaging in an interactive educational session about the 24 hour body clock, how it can become desynchronised, and strategies you can use to resynchronise it. Following this, training will be given on how to operate the iPhone application, Recharge, which will be used across the course of the study. This application creates a personalised six-week program to help resynchronise the 24 hour body clock, and monitors daily progress and provides participants with feedback over the six weeks. Recharge includes the development of a personalised day and night activity schedule, alarm clock that triggers fun activities to get you up and out of bed, reminders and tips to increase your exposure to daylight in the early hours of the day, physical exercise games to get you moving across the day, wellbeing guidebook providing information and tips on sleep basics, mood, exercise, eating well, and light exposure, daily check-ins to track mood, energy, exercise, and sleep, and graphs and charts to help monitor progress. At the end of the workshop, participants will be asked to wear the actigraphy watch for a further two weeks of monitoring.

At Week 3, participants will attend a 1 hour individual behavioural regulation session with the research investigator. This will involve a personalised analysis of the results from the Recharge app and actigraphy watch from the previous 14 days. Currently used behavioural regulation strategies (including those learnt in the initial group workshop) will be discussed for effectiveness and suitability, and novel personalised strategies will be taught depending on the Recharge app and actigraphy watch results. Finally, personalised goals for sleep, wake, exercise, and light exposure will be set for the following two weeks. At the end of the session, participants will be asked to wear the watch for a further two weeks of monitoring.

At Week 5, participants will attend a second 1 hour individual behavioural regulation session with the research investigator. Like the first individual session, this will involve a personalised analysis of the results from the Recharge app and actigraphy watch. Currently used behavioural regulation strategies will be discussed, and appropriate novel strategies will be taught. Finally, personalised goals for sleep, wake, exercise, and light exposure will be set for the following two weeks. At the end of the session, participants will be asked to wear the watch for a further two weeks of monitoring.

At Week 7, participants will attend a final 2 hour individual behavioural regulation session with the research investigator. In the final session, a personalised analysis of their full six-week Recharge app and actigraphy watch results will be conducted. Behavioural regulation strategies used throughout the program will be discussed and refined, and completed and non-completed goals for sleep, wake, exercise, and light exposure will be identified. During the last half of the session, a brief workshop on relapse prevention and management will be given. This will involve a brief education on lapses and relapses and how they occur, and training on specific skills needed to manage a lapse or relapse should one occur after the conclusion of the program. Finally, participants will be asked to fill out a series of questionnaires and tests on mental and physical health. At the end of the session, participants will be asked to wear the watch for a further two weeks of monitoring.

Two weeks after the end of the program, participants will be asked to complete a final follow-up assessment, including wearing the actigraphy watch for two weeks and completing a final series of questionnaires on mental and physical health to examine any changes post-study.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in depression score as assessed by total depression score on Hamilton Rating Scale for Depression (HAMD) and Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS).  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6-weeks (conclusion of behavioural regulation program), and 8-weeks (two weeks follow-up).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in cognitive-emotional regulation as assessed by total rumination score on Rumination Response Scale (RRS) and total cognitive-emotional score on Cognitive Emotion Regulation Questionnaire (CERQ). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6-weeks (conclusion of behavioural regulation program), and 8-weeks (two weeks follow-up).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in wellbeing as assessed by total wellbeing score on Quality of Life Enjoyment and Satisfaction Questionnaire -Short Form (Q-LES-Q-SF). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6-weeks (conclusion of behavioural regulation program), and 8-weeks (two weeks follow-up).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in circadian rhythm synchrony as assessed by total score on Morning-Eveningness Questionnaire (MEQ), total sleep-wake score on Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI), and score on circadian paramaters (amplitude, minimum, acrophase, and rhythmicity indices) derived from actigraphy watch results. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6-weeks (conclusion of behavioural regulation program), and 8-weeks (two weeks follow-up). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in manic symptoms as assessed by total mania score on Internal State Scale (ISS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6-weeks (conclusion of behavioural regulation program), and 8-weeks (two-weeks follow-up). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria:
1. Aged between 16 and 30.
2. Current diagnosis of major depression (as indicated by treating clinician according to current DSM-V criteria for Major Depressive Disorder (MDD).
3. Current circadian dysrhythmia (as indicated by pre-study actigraphy watch results).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>30</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria:
1. Not fluent in English
2. Has sleep apnoea
3. Has other primary psychiatric disorders associated with depression (e.g. schizophrenia)
4. Has other major neurological problems (e.g. stroke, epilepsy, head injury)
5. Is dependent on alcohol or illicit substances
6. Engages in regular shift-work
7. Has recently experienced jet lag (you will be required to wait three days for each jet lag hour before entering the study)
8. Does not have an iPhone or iPad</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Recruitment will be conducted via clinician referral. Clinicians from the Brain and Mind Clinic and Headspace at Camperdown will identify patients who may be eligible (is within the age range and has a current diagnosis of Major Depressive Disorder) and is interested in participating to this study.

The research team will then approach potential participants who consent to be contacted for study involvement. They will be called by the research investigator via telephone to inform them about the current study and ask questions addressing the inclusion/exclusion criteria.

Individuals who meet the inclusion and exclusion criteria will then be given an actigraphy watch to assess circadian rhythm desynchrony before commencement of the behavioural regulation program. 

Allocation is not concealed. </concealment>
    <sequence>Subjects will not be randomised. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Actigraphy data will be analysed using standard algorithms in GraphPad Prism to determine delayed sleep phase, total sleep time, sleep onset and offset, wake after sleep onset, and sleep efficiency. Other circadian parameters (amplitude, minimum, acrophase, and rhythmicity indices) will also be derived from this data using cosinor analysis.

These actigraphy measures, as well as questionnaire data collected from both the clinician-rated and self-report questionnaires will be compared across time points using SPSS v.23 statistical software. Changes in mood, circadian rhythm, cognitive-emotional functioning, and general well-being will be evaluated using repeated measures ANOVA. Mediational analyses will examine potential explanatory pathways, with questions focused on whether change in circadian parameters (derived from both actigraphy and questionnaire data) are causally related to mood outcomes, and if these occur at different time points (post-program compared to follow-up).</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/07/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Ian Hickie</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Brain and Mind Research Institute, The University of Sydney, 94 Mallett Street, Camperdown NSW 2050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The Brain and Mind Research Institute, The University of Sydney, 94 Mallett Street, Camperdown, NSW 2050</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Ashlee Hannon</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Brain and Mind Research Institute, The University of Sydney, 94 Mallett Street, Camperdown NSW 2050</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study, RECHARGE is an investigation of a novel 8-week behavioural regulation program targeting circadian rhythm desynchrony and its impact on depressive symptomology in young people with depression. It is the aim of the study to evaluate the 8-week behavioural regulation program and its impact on depression, and identify whether targeting circadian rhythm desynchrony (and its related improvements in circadian rhythm) are associated with improvements in depression.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee, The University of Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Ethics Office, Margaret Telfer Building (K07), The University of Sydney NSW 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/07/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ian Hickie</name>
      <address>Brain and Mind Research Institute, The University of Sydney, 94 Mallett Street, Camperdown, NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 0810</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ian.hickie@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Ashlee Hannon</name>
      <address>Brain and Mind Research Institute, The University of Sydney, 94 Mallett Street, Camperdown, NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9114 4000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ashlee.hannon@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Ashlee Hannon</name>
      <address>Brain and Mind Research Institute, The University of Sydney, 94 Mallett Street, Camperdown, NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9114 4000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ashlee.hannon@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Ashlee Hannon</name>
      <address>Brain and Mind Research Institute, The University of Sydney, 94 Mallett Street, Camperdown, NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9114 4000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ashlee.hannon@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>