<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335137">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/02/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/02/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000141044</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Assessment of the impact of nephrectomy on 
cardiovascular risk in living kidney donors: 
longitudinal follow-up. Focus on endothelial 
dysfunction, inflammation and oxidative stress.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Assessment of the impact of nephrectomy on 
cardiovascular risk in living kidney donors: 
longitudinal follow-up. Focus on endothelial 
dysfunction, inflammation and oxidative stress.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cardiovascular disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other renal and urogenital disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The aim of this study is to assess the impact of nephrectomy on cardiovascular risk factors and vascular function, with emphasis on early markers of vasuclar disease including endothelial dysfunction, oxidative 
stress and inflammation.  Specifically, we will scrutinize the following features of early vascular disease: 
Inflammation: hsC-reactive protein, Interleukin-6 (IL-6) 
Endothelial dysfunction: Brachial Artery Reactivity
Smooth muscle dysfunction: Pulse Wave Velocity 
Oxidative stress:Plasma, urinary 8-iso-prostaglandin 2 and oxidized low density lipoprotein (LDL) 
Vascular structure: Carotid intima-media thickness 
We will also collect data relevant to features of metabolic syndrome including triglyceride, High Density Lipoprotein, waist-hip ratio and fasting glucose, to determine the association between renal and cardiac function and traditional cardiovascular risk factors. All patients will be reviewed in outpatient clinic every 12 months for a total of 5 years. Data on vascular imaging studies will be collected at baseline and annually. Glomerular filtration rate will be estimated at baseline and annually using 24 hour urine collection,  Modification of renal diet (MDRD) and 51Cr-Chromium-51 Ethylenediamine Tetraacetic acid (EDTA) nuclear scan. 24 hour urine collection will be used to measure urinary protein and albumin excretion. All cardiovascular events, admissions, biochemical and clinical data will be recorded at specific annually at time of follow up.</interventions>
    <comparator>A control group already established within the Centre of Clinical Research and Excellence (CCRE), matched for age and gender will be approached for comparative purposes.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Carotid intima media thickness (ultrasound of vascular structure)</outcome>
      <timepoint>This study is planned for 5 years with baseline and subsequent review every 12 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Brachial artery reactivity (ultrasound of vascular function)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and every 12 months for 5 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients who fulfill the live donation selection process and successfully complete donor nephrectomy</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients from areas in Queensland where follow up vascular studies can not be carried out for logistic reasons.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>23/08/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Queensland Brisbane QLD 4072 Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC) (CCRE - Centres of Clinical Research Excellence)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The University of Queensland Brisbane QLD 4072 Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nephrology Department, Princess Alexandra Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Ipswich Road, Woolloongabba Qld 4102</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to assess the impact of nephrectomy on cardiovascular risk factors and vascular function, with emphasis on early markers of vasuclar disease including endothelial dysfunction, oxidative stress and inflammation. The follow-up studies of donor safety are flawed by being retrospective and with significant loss to follow-up. The numbers of patients who have died or have significant cardiovascular disease have not been adequately assessed. In the general population any degree of renal impairment, eGFR &lt; 60mls/min (Glomerular filtration rate) is independently associated with an increase in cardiovascular risk, death and hospitalization. Retrospective analysis or our cohort of live donors over the last 15 years (up till 2005) revealed that 39% of respondents had stage 2 (eGFR 15 -30mls/min) chronic kidney disease. We hypothesize that donors, post nephrectomy with the associated decrement in GFR may be at increased risk of future vascular disease. Specifically, we will scrutinize the following features of early vascular disease: 
Inflammation: hsC-reactive protein, IL-6 
Endothelial dysfunction: Brachial Artery Reactivity ) 
Smooth muscle dysfunction: Pulse Wave Velocity 
Oxidative stress:Plasma, urinary 8-iso-prostaglandin 2 and oxidized LDL 
Vascular structure: Carotid intima-media thickness 
We will also collect data relevant to features of metabolic syndrome including triglyceride, High Density Lipoprotein, waist-hip ratio and fasting glucose, to determine the association between renal and cardiac function and traditional cardiovascular risk factors. This is a 5 year longituidinal study of live donors. All patients will be reviewed in outpatient clinic every 12 
months. Data on vascular imaging studies will be collected at baseline and annually. Glomerular filtration rate will be estimated at baseline and annually using 24 hour urine collection, MDRD and 51Cr-EDTA nuclear 
scan. 24 hour urine collection will be used to measure urinary protein and albumin excretion. All cardiovascular events, admissions, biochemical and clinical data will be recorded at specific annually at time of follow up. A control group (already established within the CCRE), matched for age and gender will be 
approached for comparative purposes.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Princess Alexandra Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ipswich Road, Woolloongabba Qld 4102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>2007/078</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Nicole Isbel</name>
      <address>Nephrology department, Princess Alexandra Hospital, Ipswich Road, Woolloongabba Qld 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3240 5080</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3240 5480</fax>
      <email>nikky_isbel@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Nicole Isbel</name>
      <address>Nephrology department, Princess Alexandra Hospital, Ipswich Road, Woolloongabba Qld 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3240 5080</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3240 5480</fax>
      <email>nikky_isbel@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Mohd Kaisar</name>
      <address>Nephrology department, Princess Alexandra Hospital, Ipswich Road, Woolloongabba Qld 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3240 5080</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3240 5480</fax>
      <email>mokaisar@bigpond.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>