<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363103">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/10/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/10/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001067864</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Antidepressants to maintain remission and improve quality of life and mental health in Crohns disease (CD) patients: A pilot randomised controlled trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled pilot trial to evaluate the efficacy of fluoxetine in maintaining remission in Crohn's disease</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>inflammatory bowel disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Inflammatory bowel disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Fluoxetine was selected based on previous research showing its anti-inflammatory properties in humans, and in relation to IBD based on findings of studies examining animal models of colitis. Previous human studies have recommended a dose of 20mg daily (which is considered a low therapeutic dose when used in the treatment of depression) and the length of study to be at least 3 to 8 weeks in order to show fluoxetines efficacy. However, the present study was concerned with the longitudinal efficacy of fluoxetine as an agent modifying the course of IBD and psychological parameters, and thus treatment was provided for 12 months with the dose of 20mg daily administered orally. A Generic Health brand of fluoxetine was purchased from the RAH pharmacy and the placebo was an inactive tablet produced by Pharmaceutical Packaging Professionals as recommended by the same pharmacy. Treatment with fluoxetine is currently not part of standard practice in gastroenterology, however, in our case-note audit we demonstrated that a life-time use of antidepressants in our IBD patients is approx. 30% and thus many patients would have been exposed to antidepressants, including fluoxetine. In the audit, we did not identify any major adverse-events related to the use of antidepressants in IBD and the interview we conducted with IBD patients currently taking antidepressants demonstrated their acceptance by this population.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo (dummy tablet)</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome measure was a significant difference in means and proportions of participants in remission on the Crohn's Disease Activity Index (CDAI).</outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 6 and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome measure was a significant difference in means on the World Health Organisation Quality of Life measure (WHOQoL).</outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 6 and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary outcome measures was a difference in means on the fecal calprotectin test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 6 and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary outcome measures was a difference in means on the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 6 and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary outcome measures were differences in means of cytokine/chemokines (changes towards more anti-inflammatory balance) assessed on the serum assays.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 6 and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria
Patients had to meet ALL of the following criteria: 
1). Established diagnosis of CD; 
2). Remission or only mild symptoms of CD (CDAI &lt;150); 
3). Have flared CD in the last 12 months (as documented by their treating doctor and demonstrated by either raised inflammatory markers, augmented therapy, high CDAI or calprotectin); 
4). Be on stable dose of all their current CD therapies for 12 weeks;
5). Be 18 years old or older;
6). Have a sufficient knowledge of English to understand and answer questionnaires.
7). Have the ability to consent to the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria
Patients were excluded if they met ANY of the following: 
1). Have serious uncontrolled mental illness (e.g. schizophrenia) or are alcohol/substance dependant; 
2). Currently taking antidepressants; 
3). Currently receiving psychotherapy; 
4). Currently taking steroids &gt;15mg or equivalent;
5). Are allergic to fluoxetine or any component of placebo; 
6). Are pregnant or breastfeeding; 
7). Have cognitive impairment.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients meeting the inclusion criteria and providing consent to participate in the trial were randomly assigned to receive either fluoxetine 20mg daily or placebo. Patients in both treatment arms remained on their current IBD treatment. We used stratified randomisation where the strata were sex (male / female) and the Hospital Anxiety and Depression (HADS) score (&gt;7 or &lt;7 on either of the subscales). After initial screening, participants were assigned to one of 4 categories and within each, 13 participants were assigned to controls and 14 to the experimental group. Sealed envelopes with these allocations were prepared by the study’s statistician (AE) who had no patient contact. The randomisation scheme was generated by a computer program designed for this purpose. </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple computer-generated sequence involving a matrix of random numbers. Separate randomisation tables will be used for each hospital. Proportion 1:1.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/01/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>7/08/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>28/02/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>52</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>26</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>Flinders Medical Centre - Bedford Park</hospital>
    <postcode>5001</postcode>
    <postcode>5042</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of South Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Nursing and Midwifery
GPO Box 2471, Adelaide 5001, SA</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Broad Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>10900 Wilshire Boulevard Twelfth Floor
Los Angeles, California  90024</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Royal Adelaide Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>North Tce, Adelaide 5000, SA</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Flinders Medical Centre</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Flinders Drive  Bedford Park SA 5042</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Background: Studies have shown that antidepressants may reduce inflammation in animal models of colitis. The present trial aims to examine whether fluoxetine added to standard therapy for Crohns disease (CD) maintains remission, improves quality of life and/or mental health in humans with CD as compared to placebo. 
Methods / Design: A parallel randomised double-blind placebo controlled trial was conducted. Participants with clinically established CD, in remission or with only mild symptoms, were randomly assigned to receive either fluoxetine 20mg daily or placebo, and followed for 12 months. Participants provided blood and stool samples and answered questionnaires measuring mental health and quality of life. Linear mixed-effects models were used to compare groups on the outcome variables.
Results: Of the 26 randomised participants, 14 were randomised to receive placebo and 12 to receive fluoxetine for 12 months. Overall, 14 (53.8%) participants were male. The mean age was 37.4 (13.2) years. Fluoxetine had no effect on IBD activity measured using the CDAI (F(3, 27.5) =.064, p=.978) or the calprotectin (F(3, 32.5)= 1.08, p=.371) during the 12-month period of observation.  Similarly, there was no impact of fluoxetine on physical (p=.645), psychological (p=.884), social (p=.649), or environmental quality of life (QoL) (p=.992), on anxiety (p=.979) or depressive symptoms (p=.956) as compared to placebo.
Conclusion: 20mg of fluoxetine daily does not appear to improve the course of CD, QoL or mental health over 12 months of observation as compared to placebo. The trial documents the difficulty of conducting antidepressant trials with human subjects suffering from CD .
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Not yet available</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 3, Hanson Institute, RAH, North Terrace, Adelaide  SA  5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/11/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/10/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Antonina Mikocka-Walus</name>
      <address>School of Nursing and Midwifery
University of South Australia
GPO Box 2471
Adelaide 5001, SA</address>
      <phone>+61 8 83022468</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 83022168</fax>
      <email>antonina.mikocka-walus@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Antonina Mikocka-Walus</name>
      <address>School of Nursing and Midwifery
University of South Australia
GPO Box 2471
Adelaide 5001, SA</address>
      <phone>+61 8 83022468</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 83022168</fax>
      <email>antonina.mikocka-walus@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Antonina Mikocka-Walus</name>
      <address>School of Nursing and Midwifery
University of South Australia
GPO Box 2471
Adelaide 5001, SA</address>
      <phone>+61 8 83022468</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 83022168</fax>
      <email>antonina.mikocka-walus@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Antonina Mikocka-Walus</name>
      <address>School of Nursing and Midwifery University of South Australia GPO Box 2471 Adelaide 5001, SA</address>
      <phone>+61 8 83022468</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>antonina.mikocka-walus@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>