<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367831">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/06/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/07/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000793516</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Routine Monitoring and Evaluation of efficacy and safety of dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine  in Tasagn Health Centre (Battam Bang Province), in Promaoy Health Centre ( Pursat province), in Oral Health Centre (Kampong Speu province), and in Sandan health centre (Kampong Thom province) for the treatment of uncompleted Plasmodium falciparum malaria  in Cambodia.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Routine Monitoring and Evaluation of efficacy and safety of dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine  in Tasagn Health Centre (Battam Bang Province), in Promaoy Health Centre ( Pursat province), in Oral Health Centre (Kampong Speu province), and in Sandan health centre (Kampong Thom province) for the treatment of uncompleted Plasmodium falciparum malaria  in Cambodia.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>TES 2012 Cambodia</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>uncomplicated Plasmodium falciparum infection</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients with P. falciparum infection are orally treated with standard 3-day dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine (Duo-Cotecxin Registered Trademark, DHA 40 mg and PP 320 mg, Zhejiang Holley Nanhu Pharamaceutical Co. Ltd, Jiaxing, Zhejiang province, China). Supervised dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine is administered once daily for 3 days (D0, 24h, 48h) by the research team. Dosing is based on body weight, in accordance with the national treatment guidelines: (i) &lt; 19 kg, 1 tablet/day; (ii) 19-29 kg, 1.5 tablets/day; (iii) 30-39 kg, 2 tablets/day; (iv) &gt; or = 40 kg, 3 tablets/day. For children unable to swallow tablets, DHA-PP was dissolved in 5 ml of water.

Patients are  observed for one hour post-dosing and redosed full or half dose if vomiting occurred within 30 minutes or between 31 and 60 minutes, respectively. Those who vomited after the second dose are withdrawn from the study and given parenteral rescue treatment (intramuscular artemether). 

</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of patients with treatment failures. Patients will be classified as early late clinical failure, late parasitological failure or an adequate clinical and parasitological response. Recrudescence will be distinguished from re-infection by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 42</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The frequency and nature of adverse events. Clinical examination to detect blistering, peeling, loosening of skin, chills, convulsions, difficulty swallowing, fast heartbeat, joint or muscle pain etc...</outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 1, 2, 3, 7, 14, 21, 28, 35 and 42.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- age between 2 and 60 years except unmarried females between 12 and 18 years old (potential unpredicted pregnancy);
- mono-infection with P. falciparum detected by microscopy; P. falciparum parasitaemia of 500-200,000/microliter asexual forms;
- ability to swallow oral [by mouth] medication;
- ability and willingness to comply with the study protocol for the duration of the study and to comply with the study visit schedule

- Patients were evaluated clinically and parasitologically based on the specific inclusion criteria: over two years of age; fever (above 37.5 degrees Celsius) or history of fever in the last two days; P. falciparum mono-infection with parasite density between 500 to 200,000 asexual parasites/microliter and the exclusion criteria of the study;
- If a patient is eligible for the study the researcher asks if the patient can involve in the study by explaining all the process, procedure and all potential risks of drug side effects.
- If the patient agrees to participate in the study then the patient needs to sign in an inform consent.
- The patients are to stay at the health facilities for 3 or 4 days until the parasites completely clear from their bodies
- The patient has to come back to the study site for follow up on weekly basis over 42 days.
- During the follow up the patient receives the physical and parasitological examination (i.e, blood slide). </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>2</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>*presence of general danger signs in children aged under 5 years or signs of severe falciparum malaria according to the definitions of WHO;
*weight under 5 kg;
*mixed or mono-infection with another Plasmodium species detected by microscopy;
*presence of severe malnutrition (defined as a child whose growth standard is below 3 z-score, has symmetrical oedema involving at least the feet or has a mid-upper arm circumference &lt; 110 mm);
*presence of febrile conditions due to diseases other than malaria (e.g. measles, acute lower respiratory tract infection, severe diarrhea with dehydration) or other known underlying chronic or severe diseases (e.g. cardiac, renal and hepatic diseases, HIV/AIDS);
*regular medication, which may interfere with antimalarial pharmacokinetics;
*history of hypersensitivity reactions or contraindications to any of the medicine(s) being tested or used as alternative treatment(s);
*unmarried women 12-18 years old;
*a positive pregnancy test or breastfeeding;
*unable to or unwilling to take a pregnancy test or unwilling to take pregnancy test or contraceptives (for women of child-bearing age).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>- Patients were evaluated clinically and parasitologically.
- If a patient is eligible for the study the researcher asks if the patient can involve in the study by explaining all the process, procedure and all potential risks of drug side effects.
- If the patient agrees to participate in the study then the patient needs to sign in an inform consent.
- The patients are to stay at the health facilities for 3 or 4 days until the parasites completely clear from their bodies
- The patient has to come back to the study site for follow up on weekly basis over 42 days.
- During the follow up the patient receives the physical and parasitological examination (i.e, blood slide). </concealment>
    <sequence>Nil</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>- The primary outcome was evaluated by a per-protocol analysis with an exact two-side 95% confidence interval .
- Kaplan-Meier analysis with a log-rank test were applied for the comparison of the proportion of subjects with treatment failure among several groups enrolled in the 4 differents sites. 

As the treatment failure rate to DHA-­PIP in the area is 10%, 10% has been chosen. At a confidence level of 95% and a precision around the estimate of 8%, a minimum of 54 patients must be included. With a 10% increase to allow loss to follow-up and withdrawals during the 42-day follow-up period, 60 patients should be included in the study per site the 4 differents sites (Tasagn Health Centre, Promaoy Health Centre, Oral Health Centre and Sandan health centre).</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>9/08/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/04/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>21/03/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>240</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>158</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Cambodia</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Ministry of Health of Cambodia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>No. 151-153, Kampuchea Krom Blvd (128), 12252 Phnom Penh</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Cambodia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>World Health Organization</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>20 Av. Appia, 1211 Geneva 27</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Switzerland</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study is to evaluate the efficacy and safety of dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine for the treatment of uncomplicated P. falciparum in Cambodia</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>National Ethics Committee for Health Research</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress># 2 Blvd, KIM YL SUNG, Khan Tuol Kok, Phnom Penh
P.O. box 1062</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/01/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>0095 NECHR</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/12/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Cambodia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rithea Leang</name>
      <address>National Centre for Parasitology, Entomology and Malaria Control Cambodia #372, Monivong Blvd, Corner St. 322 Phnom Penh, Cambodia 
P.O. box 1062</address>
      <phone>+855 12 715 666</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rithealeang@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Cambodia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rithea Leang</name>
      <address>National Centre for Parasitology, Entomology and Malaria Control Cambodia #372, Monivong Blvd, Corner St. 322 Phnom Penh, Cambodia 
P.O. box 1062</address>
      <phone>+855 12 715 666</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rithealeang@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Cambodia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rithea Leang</name>
      <address>National Centre for Parasitology, Entomology and Malaria Control Cambodia #372, Monivong Blvd, Corner St. 322 Phnom Penh, Cambodia 
P.O. box 1062</address>
      <phone>+855 12 715 666</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rithealeang@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Cambodia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>