<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370545">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/04/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/04/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000525482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A preliminary investigation on the effects of intermittent exposure to hypoxia on glucose homeostasis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A preliminary investigation on the effects of intermittent exposure to hypoxia on glucose homeostasis in overweight adults with impaired fasting blood glucose</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1182-0446 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Impaired fasting blood glucose</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Pre-diabetes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Overweight</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants with impaired fasting blood glucose will be given intermittent exposure to hypoxic air from a hypoxicator via a breathing mask. The biofeedback mode of the hypoxicator will be used with the target hypoxia level set as blood oxygen saturation at 90% (corresponding oxygen level in the air at approximately 15%). The blood oxygen saturation is monitored by a pulse oximeter. Each intervention session is for 1 hour that includes four cycles of breathing hypoxic air for 10 minutes followed by normal air for 5 minutes. The intervention will be administered by research scientists and accredited exercise physiologists. Each intervention session will be delivered individually at the research laboratory in School of Health and Human Sciences, Lismore Campus of Southern Cross University.
The research has two phases. The first phase is a pilot investigation that will use a single system research design to examine the acute effects of 1 hour hypoxia or normoxia exposure on blood glucose. Each participant will be randomly allocated into two hypoxia and two normoxia sessions each is separated by one week. The phase two of the research will be a randomised controlled trial that uses a single-blind crossover design to investigate the effects of four weeks (three 1 hour sessions per week in non-consecutive days) hypoxia or placebo intervention on blood glucose homeostasis and insulin sensitivity. A 4-week wash-out period will be inserted between the two 4-week hypoxia or normoxia (placebo) intervention periods).</interventions>
    <comparator>Hypoxia group will be given normobaric hypoxic air and control group will be given normal air during the intervention sessions. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase 1: Acute changes in blood glucose (skin-puncture samples), assessed by a hand-hold glucometer.. 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Phase 1: Pre, 30 min and 60 min during, and 30 min, 1 hour and 24 hour post an intervention trial.

</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase 2: Changes in fasting blood glucose (veni-puncture samples), assessed by serum assay at an accredited pathology lab..</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre and post four weeks hypoxia and four weeks placebo intervention periods.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase 2: Changes in glucose tolerance (veni-puncture samples), assessed by serum assay at an accredited pathology lab..</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre and post four weeks hypoxia and four weeks placebo intervention periods.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase 2: Changes in blood insulin (veni-puncture samples), assessed by serum assay at an accredited pathology lab.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Phase 2: Pre and post four weeks hypoxia and four weeks placebo intervention periods.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase 2: Changes in HbA1c, assessed by ion-exchange high-performance liquid chromatography at an accredited pathology lab.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre and post four weeks hypoxia and four weeks placebo intervention periods.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood oxygen saturation (SpO2), monitored by a pulse oximeter in all intervention sessions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored continuously during each intervention session to provide biofeedback to the hypoxicator. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Heart rate, monitored by a pulse oximeter.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored continuously and recorded every 5 minutes during each intervention session. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure, monitored using a sphygmomanometer. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 15 minutes during each intervention session. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Fasting blood glucose greater than 6.0 mM
Body mass index &gt;25 (i.e. overweight or obese);  
No planned changes to medication regimen for hyperglycaemia (e.g. metformin, acarbose) or other metabolic diseases (e.g. lipid lowering drugs); and 
No planned major lifestyle changes during the testing period (i.e. commencement/ceasing of exercise regimen, pregnancy, etc.)
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Cardiovascular diseases; 
Anemia or blood donation within past 3 months; 
Severe chronic obstructive pulmonary disease; 
Smoking;
Alcohol consumption for more than 3 standard drinks per day;
Obstructive sleep apnea;
Uncontrolled asthma;
Inflammatory and/or infectious diseases; 
Intolerance to oxygen insufficiency; 
Disease with symptoms of decompensation; 
Terminal illness; 
Cancer; 
Pregnant; 
Neurological diseases; or
Mental illness.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed. </concealment>
    <sequence>A restricted randomization (blocking) method will be used. Participants will be randomly given a code number among 1 to 4 in Phase 1, or 1 to 20 In Phase 2, then a random pick of odd (or even) number will determine whether those having an odd (or even) number will start with treatment A – hypoxia, or B - normoxia, then change over to the alternate treatment at the designed time point. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Phase one of the trial is a pilot investigation that will use a single system research design. Each individuals responses to 1 hour hypoxia or placebo treatment will be visually demonstrated and inspected. Four participants with impaired fasting blood glucose and one healthy participant will be recruited and are thought sufficient in validating intervention procedures.  

The phase two of the trial is a randomised controlled trial that will use a single-blind crossover design to investigate the effects of four weeks (three 1 hour sessions per week) hypoxia or normoxia (as control) intervention. The number of participants is justified by a priori estimation. With assumptions of effect size of 0.4, power of 0.8, alpha level of 0.05, and two groups with three measures, the minimum number required is 12 (i.e. 6 in each group) for general linear model with repeated measures statistical analysis. Therefore, a total 20 participants (10 in each group) would be sufficient, with consideration of potential dropouts.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>27/04/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>22/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>25</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/04/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2480 - Lismore</postcode>
    <postcode>2478 - Ballina</postcode>
    <postcode>2470 - Casino</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Southern Cross University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Military Road 
Lismore, NSW 2480 

</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Southern Cross University </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Military Road
Lismore, NSW 2480</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Obesity and diabetes have become global epidemics. It is known that adequate physical activity and a healthy diet are among the key factors in weight control and management of type 2 diabetes. However, participation in regular exercise could be a challenge to some individuals with various capacities. There have been reports in the literature that hypoxia interventions, alone or combined with exercise, may have beneficial effects on weight control and blood glucose homeostasis in individuals with obesity and hyperglycaemia. With advancement of technology, hypoxia chambers and breathing devices (hypoxicators) have become available to provide air with various levels of oxygen. Whether hypoxia can be validated as an alternative or complementary intervention for obesity and diabetes requires further research. 

The aim of this research is to conduct a preliminary investigation on the effect of four weeks intermittent exposure to mild hypoxia (with the target blood oxygen saturation level at approximately 90%) on blood glucose homeostasis and insulin sensitivity in individuals with impaired fasting blood glucose. The participants responses (including blood oxygen saturation level, heart rate, and blood pressure) during the intervention sessions will be closely monitored, and their blood glucose, insulin and HbA1c levels, and glucose tolerance will be assessed pre and post the intervention period to determine the effects.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Cross University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Military Road
Lismore, NSW 2480</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/03/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>ECN-16-025</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/02/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Shi Zhou</name>
      <address>School of Health and Human Sciences
Southern Cross University
Military Road, Lismore NSW 2480</address>
      <phone>+61 2 66203991</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>shi.zhou@scu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Charl Neuhoff</name>
      <address>School of Health and Human Sciences
Southern Cross University
Military Road, Lismore NSW 2480</address>
      <phone>+61 2 66203868</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>g.neuhoff.10@student.scu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Shi Zhou</name>
      <address>School of Health and Human Sciences
Southern Cross University
Military Road, Lismore NSW 2480</address>
      <phone>+61 2 66203991</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>shi.zhou@scu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>