<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370381">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/03/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/04/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000518460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Clinical Trial of Group counselling and support online using Kids Helpline Circles on a secure social network.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy Trial of Kids Helpline Circles: A Secure Online Social Network for Young People

</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1181-1390</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>anxiety</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>stress</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention brief name: Group Solution Focused Counselling via Social Network + One-on-one solution focused counselling.

Control: One-on-one solution focused counselling.

For each intervention: Informational materials are provided to clients that relate to their mental health concern (e.g. depression, anxiety and stress). This is the psycho-education stage upon entrance to the trial, that is provided in both one-on-one online counselling and in group counselling via the social network.  Each week that a client voluntarily attends the intervention they will be provided with more support materials from written information, short YouTube videos on how to cope with mental illness and support counselling provided by a dedicated professionally trained counsellor at Kids Helpline. In all cases, only the professionally trained and accredited counsellor at Kids Helpline will provide the intervention counselling and support material. Each professional counsellor has a minimum of 2 years experience with delivering solution focused counselling by telephone or online. For this clinical trial, the mode of delivery will be a combination of online counselling (social network group counselling) and telephone or email support (one-on-one solution focused counselling. The number of times the intervention will be delivered is determined by the volunteer participant, but they can access the intervention for up to 4 years and may do so at their own frequency in any 24 hour period. The location where the intervention occurs is only online or via telephone or email.

For all trials the intervention is the same in the experimental condition - the provision of solution focused group counselling via social network, in addition to volunteer participants also attending individual, one-on-one solution focused counselling provided by telephone and/or email. Intervention adherence is completely determined by the volunteer participant as it is important they feel the service being provided is not enforced and is a choice for them to participate with.

Counselling Schedule: Counselling sessions in both conditions are available at 24/7 and are not scheduled. Kids Helpline is a 24/7 online and telephone counselling service, Given this, scheduled appointments are not necessary or required for the intervention.

Activities in Group Counselling: Each group counselling session follows the format of solution focused counselling. This form of counselling asks the group to set a topic/goal to discuss as a group and then problem solve the issues raised in the session (e.g. how to overcome self-esteem issues, bullying, loneliness, mood swings, aggression, etc). During the session the counsellor directs the group to helpful information (e.g. mental health self-help approaches, self-care, local, regional and urban services for mental health)  and asks them to share their thoughts on what they learn about these resources and rate how helpful they maybe in tackling their individual problems. The session/discussion usually closes with 'homework' for the group, asking group members to bring more information they find that helps them cope with their concerns to the next group session, regardless of what time or day they may choose to return. This allows subjects to interact and share their experiences of coping and problem based solution focused skills to the next group session they attend.

The Social Network being used for group counselling is a purpose built, privately owned and operated, social network platform called ELGG. https://elgg.org/ This custom built, secure and private social network platform can only be accessed by Kids Helpline clients invited to join. Before joining their details are recorded for counsellors to monitor client/subject engagement and adherence to the group counselling environment.

Monitoring of adherence is done through a number of means: i) log on frequency ii) downloaded content of mental health resources iii) comment posting and engagement one-on-one or in group with specific Kids Helpline counselors who monitor client/subject progress in the online environment.

'Sessions' are defined as approximately 5 min counsellor initiated discussions. Approximately, every 5 min the counsellor overseeing a group online will initiate solution focused topics to stimulate conversation and interest in the groups. These topics typically relate to what has been discussed in the previous 5 min. If the group is motivated in discussion, the counsellor will only watch the discussion and add comment if necessary. If the conversation is requires further in-put the counsellor will do so by promoting a positive and helpful prompting of discussion. This allows the group to remain free flowing for a period of time and also allows free access 24/7 to the group being monitored by the counsellor. A session can only be conducted with more than 2 participants present, but if only one participant is present the counsellor will engage them in one-on-one counselling until other participants join the discussion.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control intervention is determined by the participant as contact to Kids Helpline offers entrance choices through telephone or email.

Control duration is as long as the volunteer client wishes to engage - a minimum of 2 weeks up to 4 years. It is important the study determines natural attrition rates to the control (i.e. existing service offering) and to the intervention (i.e. adjunct service being trialed to supplement and enhance existing service offering).

For the control intervention: Counsellors talke one-on-one with the client about their problem of inquiry. Informational materials are provided to clients via verbal reference or online links that relate to their mental health concern (e.g. depression, anxiety and stress).  Each week that a client voluntarily attends one-on-one online or telephone counselling they may be provided with more support materials and ongoing support counselling provided by a dedicated professionally trained counsellor at Kids Helpline. In all cases, only the professionally trained and accredited counsellor at Kids Helpline will provide the intervention control condition counselling and support material. Each professional counsellor has a minimum of 2 years experience with delivering solution focused counselling by telephone or online. For this clinical trial the control intervention will be at the volunteer participants preference for either telephone or email support. The number of times the control intervention will be delivered is determined by the volunteer participant, but they can access the intervention for up to 4 years and may do so at their own frequency in any 24 hour period. The location where the intervention occurs is only online or via telephone or email.

For all trials the control intervention is the same for all volunteer participants - the provision of solution focused counselling via telephone or email.. Control intervention adherence is completely determined by the volunteer participant as it is important they feel the service being provided is not enforced and is a choice for them to participate with.

Counselling Schedule: Counselling sessions in both conditions are available at 24/7 and are not scheduled. Kids Helpline is a 24/7 online and telephone counselling service, Given this, scheduled appointments are not necessary or required for the intervention. 

Monitoring of adherence is done through a number of means: i) log on frequency ii) downloaded content of mental health resources iii) comment posting and engagement one-on-one or in group with specific Kids Helpline counselors who monitor client/subject progress in the online environment.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Center for Epidemiological Studies
Depression Scale for Children (CES-DC)</outcome>
      <timepoint>administered at entry and re-administered every 2 weeks for the duration of participation in the study (minimum 2 weeks up to 4 years).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Revised Childrens Manifest Anxiety Scale (RCMAS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>administered at entry and re-administered every 2 weeks for the duration of participation in the study (minimum 2 weeks up to 4 years).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rosenberg Self-Esteem Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>administered at entry and re-administered every 2 weeks for the duration of participation in the study (minimum 2 weeks up to 4 years).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Multidimensional Scale of Perceived Social Support</outcome>
      <timepoint>administered at entry and re-administered every 2 weeks for the duration of participation in the study (minimum 2 weeks up to 4 years).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Any client who contacts Kids Helpline for counselling is eligible, regardless of whether they are experiencing depression, anxiety or stress. All clients are informed about the study and are self-selected to voluntarily participate as a member for small group counselling via a secure social network owned by Kids Helpline (n=10 p/group). All clients are free to leave the study at anytime without penalty or prejudice.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>13</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>25</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Those clients upon entry to the study, or during the study, are assessed as being in great distress (e.g. suicidal thoughts) or require immediate medical or psychiatric help.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>N/A</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>A power analysis of with statistical error of 0.05 was used to calculate that a clinical sample effect size of .70 for N=40 was required across control and intervention. Method of analysis utilises correlation and regression to determine effect between control and intervention.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>29/04/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>23/03/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/04/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Sydney
Faculty of Health Sciences
75 East Street,
LIDCOMBE NSW 2141</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Yourtown - Kids Helpline</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Yourtown - Kids Helpline
Suite 5, Cordova Street
MILTON, QLD 4064</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Yourtown - Kids Helpline</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Yourtown - Kids Helpline
Suite 5, Cordova Street
MILTON, QLD 4064</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The research aims to provide evidence of efficacy of social support to young clients (13-25) who utilise the projects secure social network community site for peer-to-peer support supervised by a counsellor at Kids Help Line. This will validate that the best way to support and manage young peoples mental health issues is through extending solution focused one-on-one counselling practice to incorporate group counselling with peers, of the same age and problem, in a supportive, private and secure social network environment.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://kidshelpline.com.au/khl-circles-research-project/</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics Committee
Research Integrity
Research Portfolio
Level 6, Jane Foss Russell
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006 Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/03/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC 2016/132</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/01/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/370381-HEAppCatACond2016-132 (002).pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrew Campbell</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences
The University of Sydney
PO Box 170
LIDCOMBE NSW 1825</address>
      <phone>612415280495</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andrew.campbell@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrew Campbell</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences
The University of Sydney
PO Box 170
LIDCOMBE NSW 1825</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 9762</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andrew.campbell@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrew Campbell</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences
The University of Sydney
PO Box 170
LIDCOMBE NSW 1825</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 9762</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andrew.campbell@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrew Campbell</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences
The University of Sydney
PO Box 170
LIDCOMBE NSW 1825</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 9762</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andrew.campbell@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>