<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82920">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/06/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/07/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000356369</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Surgical Treatment of Rib Fractures: a Randomised Controlled Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Management of Multiple Rib Fractures with Open Reduction and Internal Fixation: a Randomised Controlled Trial to Investigate Effect on Morbidity and Quality of Life.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Rib Fractures</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fractures</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Open reduction and internal fixation of rib fractures.
Surgical approach: using thoracoscopy and muscle-sparing mini-thoracotomy incisions.
Surgical technique: fixation with an absorbable polylactide copolymer mesh and screw system and vicryl sutures.
Duration of surgery: 1.5 to 2.5 hours
Associated supportive treatment: intervention such as ventilation (other than for the duration of general anaesthesia), epidural or intravenous analgesia delivery and  physiotherapy determined by the patient's associated injuries and respiratory function. Patients will only be ventilated prior to surgery if they have respiratory failure. Duration of ventilation and duration of need for analgesia (other than oral analgesia) are variables that shall be measured and compared between groups.
Period of overall intervention: patients will be reviewed in clinic for a minimum of 6 months. Duration of other specific treatments (other than surgery) such as analgesia shall be determined by patient need.</interventions>
    <comparator>Treatment of patients with rib fractures using non-operative techniques including pain control, ventilatory support (invasive and non-invasive) and physiotherapy.
Duration: determined by patient need. Duration of ventilation and duration of need for analgesia (other than oral analgesia) are variables that shall be measured and compared between groups. Follow-up in clinic for a minimum of 6 months.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of Quality of Life (AQoL) instrument.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 3 months and 6 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain score: Numerical Rating Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>At discharge, 3 months and 6 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Respiratory complications: Pneumonia, empyema, and onset of ventilatory failure (requiring non-invasive or invasive respiratory support) after surgery or after cessation of initial ventilatory support.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At admission, 3 months and 6 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of ventilation support</outcome>
      <timepoint>At admission (from time of admission for chest injury to time of discharge from acute inpatient hospital care)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Spirometry: Forced expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV1) and Vital Capacity (VC) expressed as a percentage of predicted.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At discharge, 3 months and 6 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of need for epidural or intravenous analgesia</outcome>
      <timepoint>At admission (from time of admission for chest injury to time of discharge from acute inpatient hospital care)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients sustaining blunt chest trauma, with displaced fractures of two or more ribs</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>79</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with severe head injuries (GCS (Glasgow coma Score)&lt;9 on admission), abdominal, spinal or pelvic injuries prohibiting appropriate positioning for surgery, patients not expected to survive at 48 hours, pregnancy, patient or family decline to consent, no consent available, any other contraindication to surgery.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All eligible patients admitted into the trauma unit at the Royal Melbourne Hospital with blunt chest trauma, are interviewed by a researcher. After consent is given by the patient or the patient's next-of-kin, a sealed envelope with treatment group allocation is opened.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation table generated by a computer software programme.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>While the participant will not be blinded to the treatment allocation group, the follow-up with Quality of Life Questionnaires and Pain Scoring Systems will involve a blind assessor. The analysis of these outcomes shall then be assessed in a blind fashion.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>3052</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Phillip Antippa</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Cardiothoracic Surgery
Royal Melbourne Hospital
Gratten St, PARKVILLE.  VIC 3052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Melbourne Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Gratten Street
Parkville
VIC 3052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Katherine Martin</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>PO Box 305
FLEMINGTON
VIC 3031</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Rib fractures are a common injury. They can cause significant pain and lead to serious complications including death. Pain can affect the recovery from rib fracture, in particular how quickly a patient gets back to work or their activities of daily living. The aim of this study is to test the hypothesis that the operative management of patients with displaced (severe) rib fractures, via fixation of the fractures with an absorbable mesh plate, i) decreases the complications patients suffer from these injuries while in hospital, and ii) improves pain so that they can get back to work and normal activities quicker, and with an improved quality of life.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/08/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Katherine Martin</name>
      <address>PO Box 305
FLEMINGTON
VIC 3031</address>
      <phone>+61 3 93427000</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 93764532</fax>
      <email>katemartin@clause1.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Katherine Martin</name>
      <address>PO Box 305 
FLEMINGTON
VIC 3031</address>
      <phone>+61 3 93427000</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 93764532</fax>
      <email>katemartin@clause1.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Katherine Martin</name>
      <address>PO Box 305
FLEMINGTON
VIC 3031</address>
      <phone>+61 3 93427000</phone>
      <fax>+61 93764532</fax>
      <email>katemartin@clause1.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>