<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371260">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001092482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Gelatin supplementation around exercise and type 1 collagen synthesis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Vitamin C-enriched gelatin supplementation prior to intermittent activity in healthy active males augments collagen synthesis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Collagen Synthesis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal musculoskeletal and cartilage development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Healthy male subjects will complete a randomized double-blinded cross-over design. Subjects will randomly consume either 5, or 15 grams of gelatin or an isocaloric placebo control. Subjects will consume each treatment orally mixing the treatment from an opaque sachet in a Vitamin C enriched (48mg) flavoured beverage (400ml). Subjects will be instructed to mix the beverage in a opaque bottle and consume as quickly as possible. Each treatment will be consumed  1 hour prior to the completion of 6 minutes of self paced skipping.  Subjects will complete each treatment of the investigation and have a 4 day wash out period between crossing over to an alternate treatment.
In Lab acute ingestion and exercise phase
At baseline and 1 hour after the ingestion of the initial treatment (single dose prior to skipping) a large blood sample (50ml) will be taken, Sterile serum from these blood samples will be used for the  treatment of engineered ligaments. Measurements of collagen content and mechanical properties of the engineered ligaments will be undertaken. Blood samples will be taken at 0, 30min, 1, 1.5, 2 and 3hours post ingestion of each treatment for the  analysis of serum amino acids concentrations. Four hours post exercise a final blood sample will be collected for post exercise serum amino-terminal propeptide of collagen I (PINP) analysis before the subject will be allowed to leave the lab. 

Supplementation and exercise phase
Immediately following the above acute ingestion investigation phase subject will be required to repeat the intervention (treatment ingestion 1 hour prior to 6 minutes of self paced rope-skipping) 3 times a day with at least 6 hours between exercise bouts for 3 days. Subjects will return to the lab at 24, 48, and 72 hours post initial exercise and ingestion of treatment for determination of serum PINP concentrations. Subjects adherence to treatment ingestion and exercise will be completed at daily blood collection time points through verbal feedback and recorded by the researcher. As above subjects will have a 4 day wash out period before crossing over to on of the other randomly assigned treatments.</interventions>
    <comparator>Gelatin ingestion of 5 and 15g will be compared to placebo control group of 15g of isocaloric maltodextrin. All treatments will be consumed in a vitamin-c enriched  (48mg) beverage (400ml) 
All subjects will complete identical exercise protocols with the only difference being the amount of gelatin consumed</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in engineered ligament collagen content and mechanics. Engineered ligaments will be grown in serum taken a each time point for each treatment</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 1 hour post ingestion of treatment. This is assessed in arm 1 only.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in serum amino-terminal propeptide of collagen I (PINP) content over time in response to treatment and exercise</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre treatment ingestion (baseline), 4, 24, 48, and 72 hours. This outcome is assessed in arm 2 only</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in serum amino acid availability after the ingestion of the treatment</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre treatment (basleline), 30 minutes, 1, 1.5, 2 and 3 hours post ingestion of treatment. This outcome is in relation to arm 1.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Active individuals exercising 2-3x per week.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>History of recurrent connective tissue, tendon or ligament injury or current injury which prevents the exercise task being completed.
Known allergy to animal gelatin.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation will be controlled by a central researcher.
Subjects will receive numerically identified treatments in sealed opaque envelops and told to mix treatments in opaque bottles stirring and consuming treatments as quickly as possible.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size calculations
Arm 1
To detect a 2.4 ug change in engineered ligament collagen content assuming a SD of 1ug with 80% power at the 0.05 level a required sample size of 8 subjects was estimated.
Arm 2
To detect a 25 ng/mL change in the pre-post treatment serum PINP assuming a SD of the difference of 13 ng/mL with 80% power at the 0.05 level, a required sample size of 8 subjects was estimated.

Statistical analysis
Amino acid content and PINP levels will be  analyzed by two-way analysis of variance with one factor being time and the other being gelatin in the supplement. 
Post-hoc test using Tukey's multiple comparisons test will be utilised to determine the effect of the treatments. 
Engineered ligament data will be  analyzed by one-way ANOVA with Tukeys post hoc for the different gelatin levels in the supplement. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>13/07/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>5/10/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>8</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>8</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>18/09/2015</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>23/10/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australian Institute of Sport</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>AIS Nutrition
Building 19 
Leverrier St 
Bruce, 2616, Canberra, ACT.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Institute on Aging</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Building 31, Room 5C27
31 Center Drive, MSC 2292
Bethesda, MD 20892</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of California Davis</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>College of Biological Sciences
Hutchison Dr, 
Davis, CA 95616, United States</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Institute of Sport - Nutrition</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Leverrier St 
Bruce, 2616, Canberra, ACT</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of California Davis</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Hutchison Dr, 
Davis, CA 95616, United States</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>United States of America</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Monash University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Centre of Cardiovascular Research &amp; Education in Therapeutics, School of Public Health and Preventive Medicine,
Wellington Rd &amp; Blackburn Rd, Clayton VIC 3800</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>We intend to  test the hypothesis that consuming gelatin (a food derivative of collagen) and Vitamin C combined with exercise may increase collagen synthesis. To test this hypothesis, eight healthy males will complete a randomized cross-over design protocol where they will consume either a drink containing a isocaloric placebo, 5, or 15 grams of gelatin at a constant level of Vitamin C. Measurements of amino acid appearance in the blood over the first 3 hours will be measured in each condition and a larger blood draw will be taken at 1 hour to determine the effect of the nutritional supplement on engineered ligament collagen and mechanics. The subjects will perform six minutes of rope-skipping to stimulate collagen synthesis. This short bout of exercise will be repeated every six hours for the next three days and will be preceded by one hour with the appropriate drink containing placebo, 5, or 15 grams of gelatin. Over the 3-day training period, blood will be  taken for the analysis of the amino-terminal propeptide of collagen 1 (PINP), a byproduct of collagen synthesis. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Shaw G, Lee-Barthel A, Ross ML, Wang B, Baar K. (2017) Vitamin C-enriched gelatin supplementation before intermittent activity augments collagen synthesis. Am J Clin Nutr. 2017 Jan;105(1):136-143. doi: 10.3945/ajcn.116.138594. Epub 2016 Nov 16.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Australian Institute of Sport Ethics Comittee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Leverrier St 
Bruce, 2616, Canberra, ACT</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/04/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>20150401</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>17/03/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Gregory Shaw</name>
      <address>Australian Institute of Sport
Sport Nutrition 
PO Box 176 
Belconnen, 2617, ACT, 
</address>
      <phone>+61 412881541</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>greg.shaw@ausport.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Gregory Shaw</name>
      <address>Australian Institute of Sport
Sport Nutrition 
PO Box 176 
Belconnen, 2617, ACT, </address>
      <phone>+61 412881541</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>greg.shaw@ausport.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Gregory Shaw</name>
      <address>Australian Institute of Sport
Sport Nutrition 
PO Box 176 
Belconnen, 2617, ACT, </address>
      <phone>+61412881541</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>greg.shaw@ausport.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Gregory Shaw</name>
      <address>Australian Institute of Sport
Sport Nutrition 
PO Box 176 
Belconnen, 2617, ACT, </address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>