<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343412">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/08/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/08/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000933954</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A clinical trial to improve quality of life in aged care</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A cluster clinical trial in residential aged care facility (RACF) patients to determine whether care coordination is superior to usual care in reducing hospital transfer and improving resident quality of life.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1124-0819</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Primary/acute healthcare needs of residential aged care facility patients</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A coordinated care planning intervention with three key components
a. Comprehensive assessment which will incorporate an initial individual needs assessment focussing on current and likely future healthcare needs. The needs assessment will particularly focus on identifying patient preferences and goals (utilising informant perspectives where necessary) with respect to palliative care. It is anticipated the needs assessment will require at least two hour long sessions soon after enrolment.
b. Individualised care planning utilising six strategies that are most likely to impact on hospital transfer and quality of life. 
1. Patient +/- family education regarding diagnosis and prognosis. A research nurse will provide clear simple language verbal and written information regarding illness and expected clinical course.
2. An advanced care plan incorporating preferences of the patient and family for the setting of limits, if any, on hospitalisation, interventions, and resuscitation.
3. A palliative care plan for management of current and anticipated future symptoms. 
4. Primary care and assessment plan for the management of minor injury and illness tailored to the patient and RACF requirements. This may involve use of the patients regular general practitioner or other existing primary care services that augment general practice. 
5. Clinical practice guideline package for the management of major injury and illness. Tailored guidelines will be provided to deal with common acute complications requiring hospitalisation. 
6. Root cause analysis of all hospitalisations. We will use QI methodology to assess any hospitalisations in the intervention group and determine whether they were possibly avoidable and if so, what changes would be required to prevent a similar hospitalisation.
Whilst it is impossible to be proscriptive about how much contact will be required for each patient in the intervention arm, there will be minimum weekly contact with the patient and facility to manage the care planning.
c. Coordination of these strategies, and their systematic application, based on individual patient needs identified through comprehensive assessment. Each patient in the intervention arm will be assigned to a research nurse who will be directly responsible for providing key aspects of the intervention (including some primary care surveillance and service provision) and coordinate other aspects that require specialist and/or multidisciplinary involvement.
From enrolment, patients will be exposed to the intervention for a minimum period of eighteen months unless they die or return to live in the community on a permanent basis.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual (not specified) care, which for the purposes of the trial will be provided at the discretion of general practitioner/s and nursing staff within the RACF.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total number and rate of transfers to a hospital emergency department (ED) measured using hospital ED information surveillance supllemented by clinical records within each facility</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 18 months post enrolment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life (QoL) measured using the HUI2 and the EQ5D</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 3 months up to 18 months post enrolment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional status measured using the modified Barthel Index</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 6 months up to 18 months post enrolment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Death</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 18 months post enrolment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost effectiveness. The economic evaluation will take the perspective of the health care funder and will include analyses for health outcomes measured in terms of the primary clinical outcome (cost per ED transfer prevented) and secondary clinical outcomes (cost per life year saved, cost per quality adjusted life year gained).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 18 months post enrolment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient and care provider satisfaction. We will use discrete choice methods to quantify the aspects of care most valued by participants and others associated with the trial</outcome>
      <timepoint>Study completion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients will be eligible for inclusion if they are residents in a permanent high level care bed in an accredited RACF</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients will be excluded if they meet any of the following criteria
1. Not eligible for Medicare
2. Age &lt; 65 years
3. Patient not expected to survive more than 60 days after entry to the facility
4. Patient already resident within a low care facility with a support package to manage them as a high care patient</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Nonrandomized trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation to intervention versus control facility will occur. Within either facility, individual patients will be approached for recruitment.Potentially eligible patients will be enrolled by trained research staff. Because of the high (&gt;70%) rate of significant cognitive impairment in this population, it is recognised that a large number of patients will be incapable of providing informed consent. In these circumstances we will be guided by the NHMRC National Statement on Ethical Conduct in Human Research, in particular paragraphs 4.5.5 to 4.5.10.</concealment>
    <sequence>Non randomised cluster allocation</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>250</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Western Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>35 Stirling Hwy
Crawley
Western Australia
6009</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>JO &amp; JR Wicking Trust</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 389
Melbourne
Victoria
3001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>People living in residential aged care facilities (RACF) are amongst the most vulnerable Australians. Their acute healthcare needs are great yet we do not know whether the current system of providing much of this care in hospitals meets their interests or those of the broader community. This trial will test a new model of caring for people in RACF, to determine whether it can reduce hospital utilisation and improve quality of life.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Western Australia HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of WA (M459)
35 Stirling Hwy
Crawley
WA
6009</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/03/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>RA/4/1/5123</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Glenn Arendts</name>
      <address>Emergency Medicine, Royal Perth Hospital
GPO Box X2213
Perth WA 6847</address>
      <phone>61 8 92248458</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>glenn.arendts@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Roz Jaworski</name>
      <address>Emergency Medicine
School of Primary, Aboriginal and Rural Health Care
Level 2 R Block
QE II Medical Centre
Nedlands WA 6009</address>
      <phone>61 8 93464354</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>roz.jaworski@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Glenn Arendts</name>
      <address>Emergency Medicine, Royal Perth Hospital
GPO Box X2213
Perth WA 6847</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>glenn.arendts@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Glenn Arendts</name>
      <address>Emergency Medicine School of Primary, Aboriginal and Rural Health Care Level 2 R Block QE II Medical Centre, Monash Avenue, Nedlands WA 6009</address>
      <phone>61 8 92248458</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>glenn.arendts@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>