<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363355">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/12/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/12/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001289808</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The use of EmbryoGen in recurrent miscarriage and/or implantation failure patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The use of EmbryoGen to improve the clinical pregnancy and miscarriage rate in women who have recurrent miscarriage and/or implantation failure</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1137-7828</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Infertility</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Recurrent miscarriage</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Implantation failure</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fertility including in vitro fertilisation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients who have had greater than or equal to 1 miscarriage or at least three IVF cycles or FET cycles were embryos have failed to implant will be offered commercially avaliable EmbryoGen 'Registered Trademark' media by there clinician. The patient and partner will be provided with an information sheet and asked to sign a consent form prior to enrollment. They will be made aware of the risks, costs and benefits of the treatment as well as that their individualised IVF treatment plan will not be affected by participating in the trial

EmbryoGen 'Registered Trademark' media will be allowed to equilibrate for a minimum of 2 hours in 5-6% CO2 at 37 degrees celsius prior to use.

Recover oocytes as usual and prepare sperm according to preferred procedure.

Carry out fertilisation (Day 0) in pre- equilibrated EmbryoGen 'Registered Trademark'. Where ICSI is required  the sperm injection is performed in pre-equilibrated holding medium.

At 16-20 hours (Day 1) after insemination, IVF or ICSI, check for formation of pronuclei,  then carefully wash and transfer zygotes to fresh microdrops of EmbryoGen 'Registered Trademark' ( 10 micro litres). Cover with Liquid Paraffin.

Embryo transfer at Day 3. Patients will be made aware that they can only have a Day 3 transfer when using EmbryoGen

The embryos are prepared and transferred to the uterus in pre- equilibrated EmbryoGen 'Registered Trademark' (e.g. 20 to 30 micro litres).
Flush the transfer catheter with EmbryoGen 'Registered Trademark' prior to use.
 
We wish to continue the study until we have 400 oocytes in each arm where the confidence level is 95% and the confidence interval is 5%. Patients can have multiple cycles with EmbryoGen  'Registered Trademark'</interventions>
    <comparator>Historical data from previous IVF cycles the patients have had without EmbryoGen. Historical data will be collected from 2010-2012</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical Pregnancy Rate- number of clinical pregnancies (fetal heartbeat at 7 weeks U/S scan)/number of embryo transfers </outcome>
      <timepoint>One year</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Miscarriage rate- number of miscarriage/number of pregnancies (+ve hCG at pregnancy test)</outcome>
      <timepoint>One year</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Oocyte fertilisation rate- number of 2pn embryos/number of M2 oocytes inseminated</outcome>
      <timepoint>one year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Day 3 embryo quality- number of good quality day 3 embryos (grade 2.5/4 or above)/number of 2pn embryos</outcome>
      <timepoint>one year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Implantation rate- number of pregnancy sacs by ultrasound scanning/number of embryos transferred</outcome>
      <timepoint>one year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Live Birth Rate- number of live births/number of embryo transfers</outcome>
      <timepoint>one year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Congenital abnormality rates- number of abnormalities/number of live births</outcome>
      <timepoint>One year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Eligible patients must be 25-45 yrs old and have had greater than or equal to 1 miscarriage or at least three IVF cycles or FET cycles where embryos have failed to implant. They are required to have had at least 1 egg collection at PIVET without the use of EmbryoGen. The data collected from these cycles will act as the control. Patients who have a known reason for the miscarriage such as translocation or uterine pathology (fibroids, polyps) will be excluded. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>25</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>No history of miscarriage, First IVF cycle, Uterine factors (fibroids, polyps ect.), Translocations, Genetic causes other than aneuploidy
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients who fall within the inclusion criteria will be offered the use of EmbryoGen on their next IVF cycle at a consult with their clinician. The clinician will explain to the patients the advantages and disadvantages of EmbryoGen use. Patients will be provided with an information sheet as well as product brouchers. Patients will be required to read the information sheet and encourage to go away and digest the information before signing a consent to use EmbryoGen. The patients will have an opportunity to ask questions regarding EmbryoGen at their pre IVF embryology appointment.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Patients having EmbryoGen are required to have had at least 1 egg collection at PIVET without the use of EmbryoGen. The data collected from these cycles will act as the control.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Chi squared and students t-test</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>PIVET Medical Centre</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>166-168 Cambridge St Leederville WA 6007</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>PIVET Medical Centre</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>166-168 Cambridge St Leederville WA 6007</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Approximately 20-40% of all pregnancies end in miscarriage. In patients undergoing IVF treatment for infertility this rate is compounded by a high rate of embryo implantation failure. Based on data collated in the most recent ANZARD report, only 28% of the 50,495 embryo transfer cycles that took place in Australia/ New Zealand in 2008 resulted in a clinical pregnancy, and approximately 1 in 5 of these pregnancies ended in miscarriage. 
Despite numerous tests available to try and diagnose the cause of miscarriage (mostly involving the genetic diagnosis of chromosomal abnormalities), there are few treatment options available for this patient demographic.
EmbryoGen 'Registered Trademark'  is the first embryo culture media to show an improved live birth rate in women who have previously experienced miscarriage.
We wish to see if this applies to patients undergoing treatment at PIVET Medical Centre</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Research and Development
Curtin University 
GPO Box U 1987
Perth, Western Australia 6845</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/12/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>John Yovich</name>
      <address>PIVET Medical Centre
166-168 Cambridge St
Leederville WA 6007</address>
      <phone>+610894225400</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jlyovich@pivet.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Jason Conceicao</name>
      <address>PIVET Medical Centre
166-168 Cambridge St
Leederville WA 6007</address>
      <phone>+610894225400</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jconceicao@pivet.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Jason Conceicao</name>
      <address>PIVET Medical Centre
166-168 Cambridge St
Leederville WA 6007</address>
      <phone>+610894225400</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jconceicao@pivet.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Jason Conceicao</name>
      <address>PIVET Medical Centre
166-168 Cambridge St
Leederville WA 6007</address>
      <phone>+610894225400</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jconceicao@pivet.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>