<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368790">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/01/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/01/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000017426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Managing sleep with Zopiclone in acute low back pain. A feasibility study.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled feasibility study of managing sleep with Zopiclone in participants with acute low back pain and sleep disturbances.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>SLEEPain</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute mild-moderate Insomnia
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Acute low back pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is Zopiclone, considered an effective and safe, hypnotic medication with minimal adverse effects and mild chance of abuse, dependence, and tolerance and no withdrawal. 
Prior to enrollment each participant will be screened by their GP or a research physician at the Woolcock Institute of Medical Research or Neuroscience Research Australia (NeuRA).
The participant will be required to take the intervention every night for 14 nights. 
A standard single dose of 7.5mg will be taken shortly before bedtime for 14 days. 
The most commonly reported adverse event is bitter taste. Overall disturbances are rare and mild in intensity, however the participant will be reminded that they can withdraw at any time if they no longer feel comfortable taking the intervention.
The intervention will be given orally in a capsule form. 
The participants will be asked to return the empty drug packet to monitor adherence.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will receive placebo. Placebo is a substance that looks just like the intervention drug Zopiclone but has no therapeutic effect. 
It is composed of Avicel, in gelatine capsules.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean sleep quality, calculated from 14 nightly measures of the 11-point Numerical Rating Scale of sleep quality from the modified Pittsburgh Sleep Diary (PghSD). 

Monk, T.H, Reynolds III, C.F., Kupfer, D.J., Buysse, D.J., Coble, P.A., Hayes, A.J., Machen, M.A, Petrie, S.R., Ritenour, A.M., The Pittsburgh Sleep Diary. J. Sleep Res (1994) 3, 111-120</outcome>
      <timepoint>14 nights of the intervention period.  

</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean pain intensity measured by Pain Intensity Numerical Rating Scale. 

Childs, J. D., Piva, S. R. &amp; Fritz, J. M. Responsiveness of the numeric pain rating scale in patients with low back pain. Spine (Phila. Pa. 1976). 30, 13311334 (2005)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Average pain assessed at 14 days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Risk of chronic disability measure by the (Orebro Musculoskeletal Pain Screening Questionnaire (OMPSQ))

Hockings, R. L., McAuley, J. H. &amp; Maher, C. G. A systematic review of the predictive ability of the Orebro Musculoskeletal Pain Questionnaire. Spine (Phila. Pa. 1976). 33, E494E500 (2008).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at 2 weeks post commencement of intervention and 6 weeks post commencement of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Global recovery (The Patient Global Back Recovery Scale (GBRS))

Hush, J. M., Kamper, S. J., Stanton, T. R., Ostelo, R. &amp; Refshauge, K. M. Standardized measurement of recovery from nonspecific back pain. Arch. Phys. Med. Rehabil. 93, 849855 (2012).</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be completed at baseline, 2 weeks post commencement of intervention and 6 weeks post commencement of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression and Anxiety (DASS-21)

Ronk, F. R., Korman, J. R., Hooke, G. R. &amp; Page, A. C. Assessing clinical significance of treatment outcomes using the DASS-21. Psychol. Assess. 25, 110310 (2013).</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be completed at baseline, 2 weeks post commencement of intervention and 6 weeks post commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Insomnia (Insomnia Severity Index)

Alsaadi, S. M. et al. Detecting insomnia in patients with low back pain: accuracy of four self-report sleep measures. BMC Musculoskelet Disord 14, 196 (2013).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be completed at baseline, 2 weeks post commencement of intervention and 6 weeks post commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fatigue (The Flinders Fatigue Scale (FFS))

Gradisar, M. et al. The flinders fatigue scale: Preliminary psychometric properties and clinical sensitivity of a new scale for measuring daytime fatigue associated with insomnia. J. Clin. Sleep Med. 3, 722728 (2007).</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be completed at baseline, 2 weeks post commencement of intervention and 6 weeks post commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Drowsiness (Epsworth Sleepiness Scale)

Johns, M. W. Reliability and factor analysis of the Epworth Sleepiness Scale. Sleep 15, 376381 (1992).</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be completed at baseline, 2 weeks post commencement of intervention and 6 weeks post commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sleep Effort (The Glasgow Sleep Effort Scale)

Broomfield, N. M. &amp; Espie, C. a. Towards a valid, reliable measure of sleep effort. J. Sleep Res. 14, 401407 (2005).</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be completed at baseline, 2 weeks post commencement of intervention and 6 weeks post commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participant Satisfaction (Participant Satisfaction Questionnaire)</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be completed at 6 weeks post commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Objective Measure of movement intensity while asleep, using Actiwatch </outcome>
      <timepoint>14 nights of the intervention period.  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>DynaPort Move Monitor measuring movement and body position during the night</outcome>
      <timepoint>the first 7 nights of the intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.     Low back pain.
2.	Mild to moderate insomnia (Insomnia Severity Index score of between 7-21), of less than 6 weeks duration
3.	Sufficient understanding of written and verbal English language.

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Known allergy to sedative drugs 
2.     Diagnosed with sleep disorder including sleep apnea, primary hypersomnia, narcolepsy, circadian rhythm disorder, parasomnia or dyssomnia.
3.     Diagnosed with a psychiatric disorder 
4.	Diagnosis serious hepatic disorder
5.	Diagnosis severe myasthenia gravis
6.	Diagnosis acute narrow angle glaucoma
7.	Major surgery or blood donation in the past 12 weeks
8.	Pregnancy or expected pregnancy, or breastfeeding 
9.     Have a history of substance abuse or substance dependence subjects with alcohol abuse. 
10.    Weekly consumption more than 14 units (women) or 21 units (men) of alcohol.
11.	Daily consumption of more than the nicotine-equivalent of 15 cigarettes a day.
12.	Daily consumption of more than 5 caffeine-containing beverages a day/ caffeine consumption of &gt;500 mg/day
13.	Flew &gt;2 time zone in the past month or will have to do so during course of the study
14.   Working night shifts and unable or unwilling to discontinue this work pattern
15.	Presented with any condition that would prevent normal management of low back pain such as cancer.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Prior to initiation of the study, the Zopiclone and placebo pills will be encapsulated and placed into Webster packs by a compounding pharmacy. 
Both Zopiclone and placebo will be formulated such that the pills and packs appear identical.
Each Webster pack, whether Zopiclone or placebo, will be randomly assigned a number from 1-32, based on a computer generated random number sequence. Pack numbering was performed by two independent researchers otherwise uninvolved  in the study. The packs will be used in a consecutive manner as participants are enrolled. 

</concealment>
    <sequence>A block randomization schedule will be created using computer-generated random number table, </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The participants will also be asked to complete a participant satisfaction and devices utility questionnaire. </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Statistical analysis will be carried out on an intent-to-treat basis. Group comparisons will be made using ANOVA.  The overall survival/ resolution of symptoms rate will be calculated by nonparametric Kaplan-Meier method.  The median days to recovery will be calculated. Treatment effects will be represented by point estimates and confidence intervals of all outcome variables at all follow-up points.  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>21/12/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>20/09/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>32</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr. James McAuley</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Neuroscience Research Australia (NeuRA)
PO Box 1165
Randwick
NSW
2031</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Not funded</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>N/A</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Aims and research design
The aim of this pilot study is to assess the feasibility of a randomised controlled trial aimed to  improve sleep of patients with low back pain, using a hypnotic drug called Zopiclone, which is a currently available drug approved by the Therapeutic Goods Administration.
Methods
In accordance with recommendations for pilot studies this pilot will recruit thirty-two
participants. Participants will have acute low back pain and a co-existing sleep disturbance. Participants will be randomly allocated to one of two study groups of equal sizes. Patients in both groups will be encouraged to continue with their usual care, one group will receive placebo, while the other group also will receive Zopiclone over the course of 14 days.
Procedure
Participants who have sleep apnoea or severe insomnia will be excluded.
As this is a pilot study the primary aim of this study is to use the data obtained to refine recruitment, outcome measures and randomisation procedures for a larger trial. A secondary aim of this study is to estimate the effect of managed sleep on acute low back pain from the 95% confidence intervals. There have been no other studies to date that have evaluated the feasibility of controlling sleep as a way of improving low back pain. As this is a feasibility study the primary outcome measure has not yet been defined. The participants will be asked to complete a Pittsburgh Sleep diary and a numeric rating scale (NRS) to rate their average pain intensity daily for the first 14 days. During this time participants will be asked to wear an actiwatch overnight. The actiwatch measures movement during sleep and therefore it is an indirect measure of sleep quality. Participants will be asked to complete a Low back screening questionnaire and Global perception of change scale. These measures were selected because they are widely employed to assess persistence in low back pain. Psychological factors including depression and anxiety will be measured using the DASS. Participants will also be asked to rate next day effects using a Flinders fatigue scale and an Epsworth sleepiness scale.
Conclusion. 
This trial aims to conclude whether or not it is feasible to do a large scale randomised placebo controlled trial.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>None available as yet</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Local Health District</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Development Office
RPAH Medical Centre
Suite 210A, 100 Carillon Avenue
NEWTOWN NSW 2042 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/10/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>X15-0251</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/06/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368790(v10-11-2015-16-23-01)-Protocol 2.docx</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>James McAuley</name>
      <address>Neuroscience Research Australia (NeuRA)
PO Box 1165
Randwick
NSW
2031</address>
      <phone>+612 93991266</phone>
      <fax>+612 93991121</fax>
      <email>j.mcauley@neura.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>James McAuley</name>
      <address>Neuroscience Research Australia (NeuRA)
PO Box 1165
Randwick
NSW
2031</address>
      <phone>+612 93991266</phone>
      <fax>+612 93991121</fax>
      <email>j.mcauley@neura.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>James McAuley</name>
      <address>Neuroscience Research Australia (NeuRA)
PO Box 1165
Randwick
NSW
2031</address>
      <phone>+612 93991266</phone>
      <fax>+612 93991121</fax>
      <email>j.mcauley@neura.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>James McAuley</name>
      <address>Neuroscience Research Australia (NeuRA)
PO Box 1165
Randwick
NSW
2031</address>
      <phone>+612 93991266</phone>
      <fax>+612 93991121</fax>
      <email>j.mcauley@neura.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>