<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362543">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/05/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/06/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000620820</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of an online support program for Type 2 diabetes self-management and dysphoria (depression, anxiety, and diabetes-specific distress).</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised controlled trial of OnTrack Diabetes: An online support program to improve Type 2 diabetes self-management and dysphoria</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>N/A</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>N/A</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 diabetes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Dysphoria</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other public health</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>National randomised controlled trial of an automated, web-based program aimed to improve Type 2 diabetes self-management and dysphoria (depression, anxiety, and diabetes-specific distress) by primarily targeting physical activity, nutrition, health routines, and emotional well-being. 
Being a self-guided program, participants use the program at their own discretion. The Intervention group are sent an email reminder if they have not logged on in &gt;/= 2 weeks.
The prgoram has not set duration, as in, participants are free to access the program indefinitely, although the main trial period is 12 months (or, for participants who choose to be followed up in the future, 5 years).
There are three treatment arms in this trial, which involve the (i) usual care, (ii) wait-list control, and (iii) intervention arms. Usual care receives access to limited components of the full program throughout the trial (information resources, quizzes, and the health routines program module). The wait-list control arm receives access only to information resources and brief quizzes for the initial 3 months of participation, and then receives full program access. The intervention arm receives access to the full OnTrack Diabetes program. This includes information resources and brief quizzes on diabetes self-care (as accessible by treatment arms i and ii); self-monitoring tools and automated feedback graphs for physical activity and nutrition goal progress, blood glucose levels (daily highest and lowest), and mood (daily best and worst); access to My Diary, which is an electronic diary; and signposts for physical activity, eating, health routines, emotional wellbeing, and keeping ontrack, which each contain interactive tools based on cognitive behavioural therapy techniques of goal-setting, planning, problem-solving, etc, as well as mindfulness and meditation resources.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care: Limited access to online program content, including information resources and brief, self-administered diabetes self-care quizzes.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Glycaemic control (glyosylated haemoglobin level; HbA1c)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3, 6 and 12 months, and 5 years.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mood (depression, anxiety, diabetes-specific distress symptoms, asmeasured by the DASS-21, and two sub-scales of the Diabetes Distress Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3, 6, and 12 months, and 5 years.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diabetes self-care behaviours (physical activity participation, dietary intake, medication adherence...)
Physical activity participation is measured by the Active Australia Survey and Time Line Follow-back procedure (by phone interview); nutrition intake is assessed using the time line follow back procedure; and diabetes self-care is assessed by the Diabetes Self-care Activities Survey and the AusDiab Diabetes Self-Care Survey.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3, 6 and 12 months, and 5 years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-efficacy for diabetes self-care, as measured by Kavanagh et al.'s Diabetes Self-Efficacy Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3, 6, and 12 months and 5 years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life, as measured by the SF-36 Quality of Life Questionnaire and the EQ-5D.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3, 6, and 12 months and 5 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Qualitative outcomes - program acceptability, user satisfaction and acceptance, program usability, utility and implementation feasibility, as measured by the OnTrack Diabetes Evaluation survey - devised by Principal Investigator Kavanagh and CI Cassimatis, and by brief phone interview.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Program cost-effectiveness, as assessed using the Health Services Utilisation survey and self-reported medication intake.</outcome>
      <timepoint>End point result of baseline, 3-, 6-, 12-month and 5-year follow-up measures.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(a)Type 2 diabetes diagnosis &gt;/= 3 months; (b)aged 18-75; reside in Australia; (c)HbA1c &gt;/= 6.5%; (d)stable medication type &gt;/= 3 months; (e)stable medication dose &gt;/= 4 weeks; (f)access to computer with internet at least weekly.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(a)Mental condition other than depression/anxiety; (b)Psychological treatment for diabetes management; (c)Oral steroid medication; (d)Pregnancy or lactation; (e)Physical limitations preventing physical activity; (f)suicidal ideation.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>1. Individuals register interest via program homepage and book a time for screening call.
2. Researcher phones individual at appointed time and undertakes eligibility screening interview.
3. If eligible, a time is arranged in the following week for time line follow back phone interview on eating and physical activity, and participant is sent study's baseline survey to complete before the next call.
4. Following TLFB interview, Researcher actions participant into the program. Program sends out username and confidential password to participant, and the program randomly allocates them to an experimental condition when they sign in.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation is automated within the program. A 4 x 4 block randomisation schedule is used.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The intervention arm receives the full intervention from baseline throughout the trial; the wait-list control condition receives access to generic diabetes self-care information and brief self-care quizzes for the first waive of the trial and then receives full program access; and the usual care condition receives access to a modified (brief) version of the program which includes the generic information resources, brief quizzes and one program module (health routines).</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Queensland University of Technology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Institute of Health and Biomedical Innovation,
60 Musk Avenue, 
Kelvin Grove,
Brisbane,   QLD  4001</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Wesley Research Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The Wesley Health and Medical Research Institute
Level 8, East Wing, The Wesley Hospital,
451 Coronation Drive,
Auchenflower, 
Brisbane    QLD   4066</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Wesley Research Institute</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The Wesley Health and Medical Research Insitute,
Level 8, East Wing, The Wesley Hospital,
451 Coronation Drive,
Auchenflower,
Brisbane, 
QLD   4066</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study evaluates the efficacy of a novel, online support program that targets Type 2 diabetes self-management and dysphoria symptoms in aiming to improve glycaemic control and emotional well-being. Secondary aims of the program are to improve behavioural outcomes (physical activity, dietary intake, and medication adherence), self-efficacy for diabetes self-care, and quality of life. Program evaluations include cost-effectiveness and qualitative outcomes, for example implementation feasibility, user satisfaction, program usability and acceptability.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.ontrack.org.au/diabetes</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Poster (International Society for Research on Internet Interventions Conference, 2011):
Cassimatis, M., Kavanagh, D., Hills, A., Scuffham, P., Smith, A., &amp; Bauer, J. (2011). The OnTrack Diabetes Program: An Automated, Online Intervention for Type 2 Diabetes and Dysphoria Self-Management.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>UnitingCare Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>193 North Quay,
Brisbane QLD  4000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/06/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Cassimatis 9111</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/05/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Queensland University of Technology University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 4, 88 Musk Avenue,
Queensland University of Technology 
Kelvin Grove Campus,
Brisbane,  QLD  4001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/07/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1100000783</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/06/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor David Kavanagh</name>
      <address>Institute of Health and Biomedical Innovation,
Queensland University of Technology,
Kelvin Grove Campus
Level 4, 60 Musk Avenue,
Kelvin Grove,
Brisbane,  QLD  4001</address>
      <phone>+61 07 3138 6143</phone>
      <fax>+61 07 3138 6030</fax>
      <email>david.kavanagh@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mandy Cassimatis</name>
      <address>Wesley Research Institute,
Level 8, East Wing, The Wesley Hospital,
451 Coronation Drive,
Auchenflower
Brisbane   QLD   4066</address>
      <phone>+61 07 3721 1703</phone>
      <fax>+61 07 3721 1590</fax>
      <email>m1.cassimatis@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mandy Cassimatis</name>
      <address>Wesley Research Institute,
Level 8, East Wing, The Wesley Hospital,
451 Coronation Drive,
Auchenflower
Brisbane   QLD   4066</address>
      <phone>+61 07 3721 1703</phone>
      <fax>+61 07 3721 1590</fax>
      <email>m1.cassimatis@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>