<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371618">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/10/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/10/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001436460p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>CAPLA trial: Catheter Ablation for persistent atrial fibrillation: A Multicentre randomised trial of Pulmonary vein antral isolation (PVAI) vs PVAI with posterior left atrial wall isolation (PWI). </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>CAPLA trial: Catheter Ablation for persistent atrial fibrillation: A Multicentre randomised trial of Pulmonary vein antral isolation (PVAI) vs PVAI with posterior left atrial wall isolation (PWI). </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1188-4736</utrn>
    <trialacronym>CAPLA study </trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known </secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>atrial fibrillation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>1. name / Phrase: CAPLA trial: Catheter Ablation for persistent atrial fibrillation: A Multicentre randomised trial of Pulmonary vein isolation (PVI) vs PVI with post Left Atrial wall isolation (PWI).

2. Goal / Elements: Atrial fibrillation (AF) ablation also known as pulmonary vein isolation (PVI) has become standard practice and recommended for patients with symptomatic paroxysmal AF (PAF). However, the optimal ablation strategy for patients with persistent atrial fibrillation (PsAF) is not known. Current guidelines recommend use of PVI only in this patient population which we also know is ineffective. Recent evidence has shown that posterior wall isolation (PWI) in addition to PVI may offer benefit in patients with PsAF. Hence we have designed this randomised trial comparing PVI alone vs PVI + PWI and assess 12 month outcomes. 

3. Materials: This trial incorporates standard practice for patients with PsAF. All patients will be seen at our arrhythmia clinic with written information provided about atrial fibrillation and the management options available as per routine care. If they are selected for intervention based on clinical and standard management guidelines, they will then be offered enrollment in our trial. If they choose to, addition written information will be provided at that point about the interventions. All trial patients will be followed up closely at 3, 6 and 12 months after intervention. 

4. Procedures: Standard / Routine pulmonary vein isolation will be performed in all patients. The additional step in those randomised to the posterior wall isolation will involve a roof and inferior line that is also considered routine care in patients with persistent atrial fibrillation. The standard procedure involves minimally invasive procedure in which patient is taken to the cardiac catheter laboratory. Procedure performed under general anaesthesia. femoral venous access obtained through with catheters are advanced into the heart. The pulmonary veins in the left atrium are targeted with radio frequency ablation using special catheters that can deliver radiofrequency energy to the atrial tiuuse. At the end of the procedure, all sheaths and catheters removed from body. 

5. Care provided by Cardiologist and Electrophysiologists who will be looking after the patients regardless of whether they are part of the trial. 

6 &amp; 7. Modes of delivery locations: Care and intervention will be provided directly. Location will be tertiary hospitals. 

8. Intervention: Interventions will be performed once as part of the trial. Subsequent intervention will be based on patients clinical indication and the physician recommendation. Approximate duration of procedure in the PVI group is 2.5 hours. The PVI + PWI group is expected to be slightly longer at approximately 3 hours. 

9 &amp; 10. Tailoring or modification: During the ablation, the proceduralist will decide if any additional intervention is clinically necessary or recommended as part of patient care. Any intervention required for the benefit of the patient will be undertaken as needed.
</interventions>
    <comparator>The control arm will be standard pulmonary vein isolation only without the additional posterior wall isolation. The procedure is expected to take approximately 2.5 hours. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Single procedure success rate (i.e No documented AF &gt;30 seconds) off antiarrhythmic drugs at 12 months. 

This specific outcome of recurrence of AF is evaluated in all patients. If they require the use of anti arrhythmic therapy after their procedure, it reflects potential recurrence, hence it is a primary outcome. A new secondary outcome is added which reflects the other group: Single procedure success rate (i.e No documented AF &gt;30 seconds) on antiarrhythmic drugs at 12 months. 

Recurrence of AF for &gt;30 seconds, assessed by 7 day holter monitor or ECG</outcome>
      <timepoint>AF recurrence - assessed at 12 months post procedure </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Complication rates at 12 months (including pulmonary vein stenosis, perforation, tamponade, stroke)
 Complications will be documented immediately at the time of procedure and during the follow up visits at 3, 6 and 12 months. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Complications: Assessed at time of procedure and during follow up at 3,6 and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Procedural duration.

Documented in patient records. Assessed by review of medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>Procedural duration, assessed immediately following end of procedure.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fluoroscopy time

Documented in patient records at the time of procedure. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed immediately following end of procedure. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Requirement for antiarrhythmic medication beyond 3 months

Documented during the 3, 6 and 12 months follow up visits. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at 3, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Success after multiple procedures at 12 months off Anti arrhythmic drug (AAD)s

Success after multiple procedures refers to pateints who have more than one procedure for their atrial fibrillation either due to recurrence or due to new atrial flutter. 

This outcome is measured in all pateints undergoing multiple procedures. Whether it is with or without antiarrhythmic therapy is then further evaluated. 

Off antiarrhytmics refers to patients who do not have the need for AADs after their ablation procedures. 

Documented during the 3, 6 and 12 months follow up visits. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at 3, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Success after multiple procedures at 12 months on AADs

Success after multiple procedures refers to pateints who have more than one procedure for their atrial fibrillation either due to recurrence or due to new atrial flutter. 

This outcome is measured in all pateints undergoing multiple procedures. Whether it is with or without antiarrhythmic therapy is then further evaluated. 

Documented at 12 month follow up</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at 12 month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life (SF-36 questionnaire)

Documented at the initial review pre procedure and at 12months follow up visit</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed prior to ablation procedure and at 12 months follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>AF Severity Score (AFSS)

Documented at the initial review pre procedure and at 12months follow up visit</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed prior to ablation procedure and at 12 months follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Canadian Cardiovascular Society Severity in AF Score (CSS-SAF)

Documented at the initial review pre procedure and at 12months follow up visit</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed prior to ablation procedure and at 12 months follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Echocardiographic dimensions (LA dimensions and volume, left ventricular end-systolic and end-diastlic dimensions)

Documented in patient records at the routine pre procedure echocardiogram</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at the initial review prior to ablation procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Single procedure success rate (i.e No documented AF &gt;30 seconds) on antiarrhythmic drugs at 12 months. 

Recurrence of AF for &gt;30 seconds, assessed by 7 day holter monitor or ECG</outcome>
      <timepoint>AF recurrence - assessed at 12 months post procedure </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients aged 18 to 80 yeasr old with symptomatic documented persistent AF who have trialled and failed to antiarrhythmic therapy</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Paroxysmal AF. Patients with permanent or chronic persistent AF &gt; 18months. AF secondary to reversible cause such as thyrotoxicosis or severe untreated sleep apnoea. Patients with contra indication to anticoagulation. Ejection fraction of &lt;40% on echocardiogram. Creatinine &gt;200, End stage renal or hepatic failure. Severe valvular heart disease or cyanotic congenital heart disease.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The coin toss will be carried out only after the participant has been enrolled in the study, 
(At the time of enrolment it will not be known which group that participant would be allocated to)</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using coin-toss</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>We are planning a study of independent cases and controls with 1 control per case. Prior data, indicate that the failure rate among controls is 36.7%. If the true failure rate for experimental subjects is 16.7%, we will need to study 86 in each arm to be able to reject the null hypothesis that the failure rates for experimental and control subjects are equal with probability (power) 0.8. The Type I error probability associated with this test of this null hypothesis is 0.05. We will use a continuity-corrected chi-squared statistic or Fishers exact test to evaluate this null hypothesis. Assuming a modest drop out rate of 30%, we will need about 123 patients in each group. Comparisons between groups will be performed with either an unpaired Students T-Test or where a normal distribution cannot be assumed, the Mann Whitney U test. All statistical analyses will be performed using Stata (12 or higher), StataCorp LP, College Station, TX 77845</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/02/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/07/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>246</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/07/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - City campus - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Melbourne Private Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>3004 - Prahran </postcode>
    <postcode>3050 - Parkville</postcode>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Papworth Hospital, Cambridge</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Waikato Hospital, Hamilton</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Alfred Hospital </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>55 Commercial Rd, Melbourne VIC 3004, Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Alfred Hospital </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>55 Commercial Rd, Melbourne VIC 3004, Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Melbourne Hospital </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress> 300 Grattan St, Parkville VIC 3050, Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Melbourne Private Hospital </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Royal Parade, Parkville VIC 3052, Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Adelaide Hospital </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>North Terrace, Adelaide SA 5000, Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Papworth Hospital </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Papworth Everard, Cambridge CB23 3RE, United Kingdom</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United Kingdom</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Waikato Hospital </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Selwyn Street and Pembroke Street, Hamilton 3204, New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>What is known? 
PVAI for AF is the standard of care in people with symptomatic paroxysmal AF (class I indication) but the next step in ablation for people with persistent AF is unknown. A major international landmark trial has yielded neutral results with some forms of additional ablation but the effect of PWI + PVAI has not been formally assessed in a multicentre randomised trial. 

What this study adds? 
Multicentre randomised trial assessing the effect of adding PWI to PVAI in persistent AF on 12-month arrhythmia free survival. 

Primary Endpoints
Recurrence of AF for &gt;30 seconds. Single procedure success rate off antiarrhythmic drugs at 12 months. 
Complication rates at 12 months (including pulmonary vein stenosis, perforation, tamponade, stroke)

Secondary Endpoints
Procedural duration
Fluoroscopy time
Requirement for antiarrhythmic medication beyond 3 months
Success after multiple procedures at 12 months off AADs
Success after multiple procedures at 12 months on AADs
Quality of life (SF-36 questionnaire)27
AF Severity Score (AFSS)28
Canadian Cardiovascular Society Severity in AF Score (CSS-SAF)29
Echocardiographic dimensions (LA dimensions and volume, left ventricular end-systolic and end-diastlic dimensions)
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred hospital </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>55 Commercial road, Melbourne, Vic 3004 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/10/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Kistler</name>
      <address>Alfred Hospital
55 Commercial Road, Melbourne Vic 3004
&amp; 
Baker IDI Heart &amp; Diabetes institute 
75 Commercial Road, Melbourne Vic 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 2000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter.kistler@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hariharan Sugumar</name>
      <address>Alfred Hospital
55 Commercial Road, Melbourne Vic 3004
&amp; 
Baker IDI Heart &amp; Diabetes institute 
75 Commercial Road, Melbourne Vic 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 2000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hsugumar@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hariharan Sugumar </name>
      <address>Alfred Hospital
55 Commercial Road, Melbourne Vic 3004
&amp; 
Baker IDI Heart &amp; Diabetes institute 
75 Commercial Road, Melbourne Vic 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 2000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hsugumar@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>