<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="139">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/08/2005</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/09/2005</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12605000442606</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Phase II trial of cellular immunotherapy on CA-125 response with M-FP cancer vaccine in patients with epithelial ovarian carcinoma</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase II trial of cellular immunotherapy on CA-125 response with M-FP cancer vaccine in patients with epithelial ovarian carcinoma</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Ovarian Cancer cellular immunotherapy</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Ovarian Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ovarian and primary peritoneal</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a single centre, non comparative, open label, single arm phase II study.  The study will evaluate intradermal injection of autologous dendritic cells cultured ex vivo with M-FP Cancer vaccine comprising a portion (VNTR Region) of the MUC 1 protein fused to glutathione-S-transferase (GST) and conjugated to polymannose.  M-FP is delivered to the patient as vaccine loaded dendritic cells, three injections over a 10 week period, followed by booster injections every ten weeks for a total of seven treatments over 12 months. The aim will be to readminister a minimum of 25 x 106 M-FP loaded dendritic cells at each reinjection, into 6 to 8 sites.</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>None</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine whether cellular immunotherapy with M-FP cancer vaccine can lead to clinical responses or stabilisation of disease, as determined by serum CA-125, in patients with adenocarcinoma of the ovary. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured from visit 5 onwards for each patient.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>EFFICACY
- To estimate the duration of a CA-125 response or stabilisation.
- To estimate progression free survival (PFS), based on duration of CA-125 response or stabilisation.
- To determine whether treatment with M-FP cancer vaccine can lead to immunological responses in patients with adenocarcinoma of the ovary.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All secondary outcomes will be measured at the end of the trial for each patient.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>SAFETY
- To further characterise the safety profile of M-FP cancer vaccine in patients with adenocarcinoma of the ovary.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>All secondary outcomes will be measured at the end of the trial for each patient.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>EXPLORATORY
- To evaluate the relationship between clinical response and CA-125 response in patients with measurable or non-measurable lesions
- To evaluate the rate of change in serum CA-125 levels before and during treatment with M-FP cancer vaccine.
- To evaluate the relationship between MUC1 expression on archival tissue samples and clinical response.
- To evaluate the relationship between histological subtype and clinical response.
- To evaluate the relationship between HLA type and immunological and CA-125 response.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All secondary outcomes will be measured at the end of the trial for each patient.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Histologically or cytologically proven epithelial adenocarcinoma of ovarian or fallopian tube origin, or primary peritoneal carcinoma. - No options for curative therapy. - Rising CA-125, which is defined as an increase in CA-125 by at least 25% from a baseline reading within one month. A repeat CA-125 test must be done to confirm the increased value. At least one level must be greater than or equal to twice the upper limit of the normal range (ULNR). - No surgery, radiotherapy, chemotherapy, hormonal therapy for malignancy, immunotherapy or experimental therapy within the last 4 weeks. - Adequate bone marrow function (white blood cells &gt;3.0 x 109 per litre, haemoglobin &gt; 100 g/L, platelets &gt;100 x 109 per litre). - Adequate liver function (bilirubin &lt; 2 x ULNR, AST or ALT &lt; 5 x ULNR). - Adequate renal function (creatinine within normal ranges). - At least 18 years of age. - Life expectancy of at least 6 months. - ECOG Performance Status of 0 - 1 inclusive (Ambulatory and able to carry out activities of daily living). - Written informed consent given by the patient.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Coexisting or previous other malignancies unless in complete remission for not less than 2 years and excepting in situ carcinoma of the cervix or basal cell or squamous cell carcinoma of the skin. - Ovarian sarcoma / mixed Mullerian tumours. - Active uncontrolled infections. - Psychiatric, addictive or any (medical) disorder which compromises ability to give truly informed consent for participation in this study or comply with the requirements of the study. - Any serious medical condition that may prevent the participant from completing at least the first six months of the study. - Concurrent systemic steroid treatment. - Clinical autoimmune disease, eg rheumatoid arthritis, systemic lupus erythematosus, (except autoimmune thyroiditis). - Clinically significant ischaemic heart disease (unstable angina or acute myocardial infarction within the last 3 months) or cardiac failure (NYHA Class III or IV) - see Appendix A. - Infection with the Human Immunodeficiency (AIDS) Virus, hepatitis B virus or hepatitis C virus. - Pregnant or breast feeding, or planning to become pregnant during the course of the study. - Evidence of CNS metastases.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>19/07/2004</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Cancer Vac Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Commercial sponsor</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>see below</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>N/A</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary />
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress> Victoria</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Emma Ball</name>
      <address>Cancer Vac Pty Ltd
Unit 7
79-83 High Street
Kew VIC 3101</address>
      <phone>+61 3 98248166</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>eball@primabiomed.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Effie Skrinos</name>
      <address>Cancer Clinical Trials Centre
Austin Hospital
Austin Health
Level 3 Lance Townsend Building
145 - 163 Studley Road
Heidelberg VIC 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94963576</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Effie.Skrinos@ludwig.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>