<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371351">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/09/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001260415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A study to evaluate safety and tolerability of GS -5801 in healthy subjects</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 1 Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability,
Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics of GS-5801, and the
Effect of Food on GS-5801 Pharmacokinetics in Healthy Subjects</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>GS-US-405-2064</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hepatitis B Virus</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Cohort 1: 2 mg GS-5801 (1x 2 mg tablet) or placebo tablet. Fasted. Dosing Day 1, Day 2-7 Washout, Dosing Days 8 - 14.
Cohort 2: 6 mg GS-5801 (3x 2 mg tablets) or placebo tablets. Fasted. Dosing Day 1, Day 2-7 Washout, Dosing Days 8 - 14.
Cohort 3: 20 mg GS-5801 (1x 20 mg tablet) or placebo tablet. Fasted. Dosing Day 1, Day 2-7 Washout, Dosing Days 8 - 14.
Cohort 4-6: between 2mg and 100 mg GS-5801 or placebo tablet(s). Fed or fasted. Dosing Day 1, Day 2-7 Washout, Dosing Days 8 - 14. Dose will be determined based on available safety, PK, and PD data from cohorts 1-3 which informs on the effect of food on the PK and PD of GS-5801.
Cohort 7: Day 1: 2mg to 100 mg GS-5801, single dose. Fasted. Day 2-7 Washout. Day 8: up to 100 mg GS-5801, single dose. Fed

Fasted state: no food or drinks except water, for at least 10 hours.
Fed state: study drug(s) will be administered at approximately the same time each day and within 5 minutes of completing a specified moderate-fat-calorie breakfast (~600 calories, 25% to 30% fat).

The investigator will maintain an accurate inventory of all study drug(s). Each dose of the study drug(s) administered at the study center will be administered by qualified study center staff. The dose of study drug(s) administered to subjects in the clinic under the supervision of staff will be accurately recorded, which indicates the date and quantity of each dosage formulation dispensed to individual subjects.
Used and unused study drug supplies, including empty containers, are to be returned to the shipping facility from which it came for destruction following drug accountability and drug inventory reconciliation.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo-to-match (PTM) GS-5801 tablets are identical in size, shape, color and appearance to the corresponding active strength GS-5801 tablets. The PTM GS-5801 tablet cores contain commonly used excipients including lactose monohydrate, microcrystalline cellulose, croscarmellose sodium, and magnesium stearate.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the safety and tolerability of escalating single- and multiple- oral doses of GS-5801. The primary safety endpoints are the incidences of adverse events, vital signs and ECG measurements, and laboratory abnormalities assessments.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Safety will be evaluated throughout the study. 
Incidences of adverse events will be monitored continuously from screening to end of study. 
Vital signs: Screening, Day-1, Day1, 2, 3, 8, 9, 10, 12, 14, 16, 18, 21, 28, end of trial
ECG: Screening, Day-1, Day1, 2, 3, 8, 9, 10, 14, 28, end of trial
Lab assessments: Screening, Day-1, Day1, 2, 3, 8, 9, 10, 12, 14, 16, 18, 21, 28, end of trial</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To characterize the single- and multiple-dose pharmacokinetics (PK) of GS-5801 and its metabolite GS-698080. The primary PK endpoints are single- and multiple- dose plasma PK parameters: AUClast, AUCinf (single dose), AUCtau (multiple dose), % AUCexp (single dose), Ctau (multiple dose), and Cmax, of GS-5801 and its metabolite GS-698080.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Part A and B (Cohorts 1-6): Intensive PK sampling will occur relative to dosing of GS-5801 or placebo at the following time points for each cohort:
Day 1: 0 (predose, = 5 min prior to dose), 0.25, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 2.5, 3, 3.5, 4, 5, 6, 8, 10, 12, 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours postdose.
Days 8-13: 0 (predose, = 5 min prior to dose)
Day 14: 0 (predose, = 5 min prior to dose), 0.25, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 2.5, 3, 3.5, 4, 5, 6, 8, 10, 12, 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours postdose.
Part C (Cohort 7): Intensive PK sampling will occur relative to dosing of GS-5801 at the
following time points:
Days 1 and 8: 0 (predose, = 5 min prior to dose), 0.25, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 2.5, 3, 3.5, 4, 5, 6, 8, 10, 12, 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours postdose.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To perform a preliminary evaluation of the effect of concomitant food intake on the PK of GS-5801 and its metabolite GS-698080. The primary PK endpoints are single- and multiple- dose plasma PK parameters: AUClast, AUCinf (single dose), AUCtau (multiple dose), % AUCexp (single dose), Ctau (multiple dose), and Cmax, of GS-5801 and its metabolite GS-698080.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Part A and B (Cohorts 1-6): Intensive PK sampling will occur relative to dosing of GS-5801 or placebo at the following time points for each cohort:
Day 1: 0 (predose, = 5 min prior to dose), 0.25, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 2.5, 3, 3.5, 4, 5, 6, 8, 10, 12, 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours postdose.
Days 8-13: 0 (predose, = 5 min prior to dose)
Day 14: 0 (predose, = 5 min prior to dose), 0.25, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 2.5, 3, 3.5, 4, 5, 6, 8, 10, 12, 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours postdose.
Part C (Cohort 7): Intensive PK sampling will occur relative to dosing of GS-5801 at the
following time points:
Days 1 and 8: 0 (predose, = 5 min prior to dose), 0.25, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 2.5, 3, 3.5, 4, 5, 6, 8, 10, 12, 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours postdose.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>NA</outcome>
      <timepoint>NA</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Have the ability to understand and sign a written informed consent form (ICF), which must be obtained prior to initiation of study procedures.
2. Be aged 18 through 45 years of age, inclusive at screening
3. Be a nonsmoker. The use of nicotine or nicotine-containing products must be discontinued 90 days prior to the first dose of study drug
4. Have a calculated body mass index (BMI) of &gt;=19.0 and =&lt;30.0 kg/m2 at screening
5. Have a creatinine clearance (CLcr) =&gt;90 mL/min (using the Cockcroft-Gault method based on serum creatinine and actual body weight as measured at screening, ie,
Male: (140  Age [years]) x (Weight [kg]) / 72 x (Serum Creatinine [mg/dL]) = CLcr (mL/min)
Female: ((140  Age [years]) x (Weight [kg]) / 72 x (Serum Creatinine [mg/dL])) x 0.85 =  CLcr (mL/min)
6. Females of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test at screening and clinic admission
7. Male subjects and female subjects of childbearing potential who engage in heterosexual intercourse must agree to use protocol specified method(s) of contraception
8. Male subjects must refrain from sperm donation from clinic admission (eg, Day -1),
throughout the study period, and continuing for at least 90 days following the last dose of study drug
9. Subjects have not donated blood within 56 days of study entry or plasma within 7 days of study entry and must refrain from blood donation from clinic admission, throughout the study period, and continuing for at least 30 days following the last dose of study drug.
10. Screening laboratory and 12-lead ECG evaluations must be without clinically significant abnormalities as assessed by the investigator
11. Have liver disease or liver function tests such as alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alkaline phosphatase, and total bilirubin below the upper limit of normal at screening
12. Have either a normal 12-lead ECG or one with abnormalities that are considered clinically insignificant by the investigator in consultation with the sponsor
13. Must be willing and able to comply with all study requirements
14. Must, in the opinion of the investigator, be in good health based upon medical history and physical examination, including vital signs.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Be a pregnant or lactating female
2. Have received any study drug within 30 days prior to study dosing
3. Have current alcohol or substance abuse judged by the investigator to potentially interfere with subject compliance or subject safety
4. Have a positive test result for human immunodeficiency virus type 1 (HIV-1) antibody,
hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg), or hepatitis C virus (HCV) antibody
5. Have poor venous access that limits phlebotomy
6. Have taken any prescription medications or over-the-counter medications, including herbal products, within 28 days prior to start of study drug dosing, with the exception of vitamins, fish oil, protein powder, and/or paracetamol and/or ibuprofen and/or hormonal contraceptive medications
7. Have been treated with systemic steroids, immunosuppressant therapies, or chemotherapeutic agents within 3 months prior to screening or is expected to receive these agents during the study (eg, corticosteroids, immunoglobulins, and other immune- or cytokine-based therapies)
8. Significant serious skin disease, such as but not limited to rash, food allergy, eczema,
psoriasis, or uticaria
9. Significant drug sensitivity or drug allergy (such as anaphylaxis or hepatoxicity)
10. Known hypersensitivity to the study drugs their metabolites or to formulation excipients 
11. Significant cardiac disease (including history of myocardial infarction based on ECG and/or clinical history, any history of ventricular tachycardia, congestive heart failure, or dilated cardiomyopathy with left ventricular ejection fraction &lt; 40%), a family history of long QT syndrome, or unexplained death in an otherwise healthy individual between the ages of 1 and 30 years
12. Syncope, palpitations, or unexplained dizziness
13. Implanted defibrillator or pacemaker
14. Liver disease, including Gilbert disease
15. Severe peptic ulcer disease, gastroesophageal reflux disease, or other gastric acid
hypersecretory conditions requiring prolonged (&gt; 6 months) medical treatment.
16. Medical or surgical treatment that permanently altered gastric absorption (eg, gastric or intestinal surgery). A history of cholecystectomy is not exclusionary.
17. Have any serious or active medical or psychiatric illness (including depression) that, in the opinion of the investigator, would interfere with subject treatment, assessment, or compliance with the protocol. This would include renal, cardiac, hematological, hepatic, pulmonary
(including chronic asthma), endocrine (including diabetes), central nervous, gastrointestinal (including an ulcer), vascular, metabolic (thyroid disorders, adrenal disease), immunodeficiency disorders, active infection, or malignancy that are clinically significant or requiring treatment.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by phone/fax/computer.
Part A: (Cohorts 1-3): 10 per cohort (8 GS-5801, 2 placebo-to-match)
Part B: (Cohorts 4-6): 10 per cohort (8 GS-5801, 2 placebo-to-match)
Part C: (Cohort 7): 10 GS-5801</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerised sequence generation. Randomized 4:1 to receive either blinded GS-5801 (N=8) or matching placebo (N=2)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Part A (Cohorts 1-3): Randomized, blinded, placebo-controlled, single- and multiple-doses with staggered pre-specified dose escalations
Part B (Cohorts 4-6): Randomized, blinded, placebo-controlled, single- and multiple-doses with adaptive dose selection, and fed or fasted administration of GS-5801.
Part C (Cohort 7): Open-label, two-treatment, fixed-sequence, food effect with adaptive dose selection of GS-5801.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>3/10/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>70</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Gilead Sciences, Inc.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Gilead Sciences, Inc.
333 Lakeside Drive, Foster City, CA 94404</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Gilead Sciences, Inc.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Gilead Sciences, Inc.
333 Lakeside Drive, Foster City, CA 94404</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>NA</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>NA</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will proceed in three parts, governed within and between parts by reviews of safety data and application of stopping rules. Based on safety and available pharmacokinetic (PK) and pharmacodynamic (PD) data, and at the discretion of the sponsor in consultation with the investigator, the adaptive cohorts may be repeated at the same dose level, be held until further data are available, or not be initiated at all.
Part A will proceed in 3 staggered pre-specified cohorts. Within each cohort, 10 unique subjects will be randomized 4:1 to receive either blinded GS-5801 (N=8) or matching placebo (N=2). All study drugs in Part A will be administered in a fasted state.
Part B: Based on available safety, PK, and PD data from cohorts in Part A,
doses for Part B (Cohorts 4 - 6) will be selected between 2 and 100 mg. Within each cohort, 10 unique subjects will be randomized 4:1 to receive either active GS-5801 (N=8) or matching placebo (N=2). Within each cohort, subjects may be administered up to 100 mg
GS-5801 once daily in either the fed or fasted state.
Part C: The dose of GS-5801 selected for evaluation in Cohort 7 will be determined based on review of available safety, PK, and PD data from Cohorts in Part A and/or B and will not exceed a dose previously evaluated in Parts A or B. 10 unique subjects will receive a single dose of GS-5801 (up to 100 mg) administered in the fasted state on Day 1, followed by a 6-day washout, and a second single dose of GS-5801 (up to 100 mg)
administered with a moderate-fat-calorie breakfast.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committee (HDEC), NZ</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Ethics Department
Freyberg Building
Reception  Ground Floor
20 Aitken Street, Wellington 6011
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/09/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/08/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Edward Gane</name>
      <address>Auckland Clinical Studies Limited
3 Ferncroft Street, Auckland 1042
</address>
      <phone>+64 9 373 3474</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>edgane@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Anuj Gaggar</name>
      <address>Gilead Sciences, Inc.
333 Lakeside Drive
Foster City, CA 94404
</address>
      <phone>+1 650 358 1090</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>anuj.gaggar@gilead.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Anuj Gaggar</name>
      <address>Gilead Sciences, Inc.
333 Lakeside Drive
Foster City, CA 94404</address>
      <phone>+1 650 358 1090</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>anuj.gaggar@gilead.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Wayne Paul</name>
      <address>Gilead Sciences Pty Ltd
Level 6, 417 St Kilda Road, Melbourne, Victoria 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9272 4451</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9272 4435</fax>
      <email>wayne.paul@gilead.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>