<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370229">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/02/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/03/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000328471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparison of the mini sling or retropubic sling in the treatment of women with severe  (Intrinsic Sphincter Deficiency -ISD) stress urinary incontinence (SUI)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Objective cure rate of mini sling or retropubic sling in women with Intrinsic Sphincter Deficiency - a RCT study (Mini RISD)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1180-1666 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>Mini RISD</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Stress Urinary Incontinence</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Intrinsic sphincter deficiency</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other renal and urogenital disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants with SUI will be referred for urodynamics examination routinely to assess for urodynamic stress incontinence (USI). Once urodynamic stress incontince associated with ISD has been comfirmed, participants will be randomized to the minisling or retropubic sling.
Intervention  - Insertion of a mini-sling for treatment of female urodynamic stress incontinence &amp; intrinsic sphincter deficiency. The minisling is a single incision sling system with small integrated self-fixating tips that anchor into the obturator internus muscle.This operation will be performed by a urogynaecologist or urgynaecology fellow with at least 3 years experience and the procedure will take approximately half an hour. The outcome is to assess the objective cure rate (negative clinical cough stress test) at 6 months post-surgery.</interventions>
    <comparator>Comparator - Retropubic sling 
 A retropubic sling involves tunneling the sling from the suburethral region, in close contact to the bladder in the retropubic space (behind the pubic bone), to the lower abdominal wall.  This sling will treat stress incontinence by providing support to the urethra to prevent urinary leakage during times of increased abdominal pressure. This operation will be performed by a urogynaecologist or urgynaecology fellow with at least 3 years experience and the procedure will take approximately half an hour. 
.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the objective cure rate (negative clinical cough stress test) of the minisling against the retropubic sling at 6 months post-surgical treatment of female urodynamic stress incontinence &amp; intrinsic sphincter deficiency

</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess composite outcome of  immediate complications of the minisling against the retropubic sling eg number of passes of sling ( if bladder perforation was noted), bladder or urethral perforation, bowel perforation. These complications will be noted on the operating report by the surgeon and will be collected from the operation sheet.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Intra-operative</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess  composite outcome of short term post-operative complications of the minisling against the retropubic sling eg number of pain days, supra-pubic pain, urinary tract infection. 
Tools used to assess pain
Pain Score (VAS 0  10) &amp; Intensity (0 - 3) at 6 hours and discharge
Additional analgesia if pain score &gt;5 or intensity greater than or equal to 2.
Tools used to assess for UTI
1 mid stream urine sample with a single colony count of &gt; 10 power of 5</outcome>
      <timepoint>The pain score and intensity will be collected at 6 hours and at discharge and the incidence of supra-pubic pain and urinary tract infection 6 weeks post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the incidence of urinary urgency after both slings based on symptoms of urgency ( rushing to void) and frequency defined as a score &gt;3 on the patient perception of intensity of urgency scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the incidence of voiding dysfunction after both slings based on symptoms of hesistancy, difficulty voiding, incomplete emptying of the bladder OR  need for on-going use of a catheter to drain the bladder after 6months OR return to theatre for sling loosening or sling division.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post surgery
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the subjective outcomes using validated symptoms questionnaire -Incontinence impact questionnaire - overactive bladder (ICIQ-OAB)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the subjective outcomes quality of life using the incontinence impact questionnaire (IIQ7)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine global improvement using a patient global impression of improvement questionnaire (PGI -I)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the change in sexual function using pelvic organ prolapse/urinary incontinence sexual questionnaire (PISQ-12), following both slings.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare cost effectiveness between the minisling against the retropubic sling using a cost utility approach to measure changes in QALY, using EQ5D13</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the impact of urinary incontinence using the Incontinence impact questionnaire - urinary incontinence (ICIQ UI SF)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All participants between the ages of 18-80 with urodynamic stress incontinence and intrinsic sphincter deficiency. (USI/ISD)
Capable of providing informed consent and able to return for follow up.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Untreated Detrusor overactivity
Significant voiding dysfunction 
Lower urinary tract anomaly (congenital)
Neurogenic bladder disorders
Previous radiation therapy to pelvis
Past history of any form of fistula involving the vagina
Allergy to polypropylene or local anaesthetic
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Recruiting surgeons will call a central telephone number and the urogynaecology nurse consultant who holds the randomization codes will notify surgeon of allocation. Patients are blinded to type of sling inserted. Sham dressing will be placed on the suprabubic area for participants with mini-sling
Blinding of the surgeon performing the surgery is not possible.
</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomized with equal probability to minisling or  retropubic sling using a central computer-generated random allocation. Subjects will be randomised in order of entry into the study. 
Balanced baseline characteristics would minimise influence on potential confounders.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Assuming an objective cure rate of 79% from the retropubic sling with power of 80%, a sample size of 66 in each arm would be required to detect a clinical difference of 20%, using a one sided alpha of 0.05. Allowing for an attrition rate of 15%, we propose to recruit a total of 152 subjects for the trial
An interim analysis after the first 30 patients in each arm have completed 6 months of follow up: cessation of ongoing recruitment if minisling has greater than 25% difference in subjective cure rate compared with retropubic sling at 6months
Intention to treat analysis
Outcomes were compared with Pearson x2 test for categorical data and Student t test or Wilcoxon rank-sum for continuous data as appropriate. 2 sided 95% confidence intervals will be used
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/03/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>21/04/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>152</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Mercy Hospital for Women - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Moorabbin campus - East Bentleigh</hospital>
    <postcode>3165 - Bentleigh East</postcode>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Lin Li Ow</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Monash Moorabin Hospital, Level 2 Urodynamics room,
823-865 Centre Road Moorabin Victoria 3165</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Monash Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Pelvic Floor Unit
Monash Health
823-865 Centre Road, Bentleigh East, Vic 3165
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Mercy Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>163 Studley Road
Heidelberg Vic 3084</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>A/Prof Anna Rosamilia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Suite 48, Cabrini Hospital 
181-183 WAttletree Road
Malvern Vic 3144</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Stress incontinence (SUI) is defined as urinary leakage with activities that increase intra-abdominal pressure (e.g. cough, sneeze, laugh and exercise). SUI is a prevalent condition with high burden of suffering. Midurethral slings (MUS) have become the operation of choice for treatment of female stress urinary incontinence. MUS are synthetic tapes that are implanted transvaginally to support the urethra. The urethra is a tube that connects the bladder to the outside of the body and removes urine from the body.


Midurethral slings can be deployed in a retropubic or transobturator fashion. A retropubic approach involves tunneling the sling from the suburethral region, in close contact to the bladder in the retropubic space (behind the pubic bone), to the lower abdominal wall. In contrast, the transobturator approach involves the passage of a sling through the obturator membrane which is further away from the bladder. This approach has been shown to have a reduced rate of intra-operative bladder perforation.

Recent systematic reviews of retropubic or transobturator midurethral tapes suggest equivalent efficacy, at least in the medium term. Both midurethral systems continue to have clinically significant complications such as bladder injuries, vagina mesh exposures, voiding difficulty, denovo (new onset) urgency and groin/thigh pain reported. Retropubic slings have more hematoma, bladder perforations, whereas transobturator slings have less over active bladder symptoms and less voiding difficulties. 

The minisling is a single incision sling system with small integrated self-fixating tips that anchor into the obturator internus muscle. This potentially avoids complications associated with trocar passage through retropubic or transobturator route. Comparative trials of retropubic against transobturator slings have shown retropubic slings to be superior in the cure rates of women with intrinsic sphincter deficiency (a severe form of stress urinary incontinence  ISD) .

Randomised trials of minislings against transobturator slings have shown similar results,  with the added advantage of less overactive bladder symptoms and voiding difficulties. The self-fixating tips of the minislings allow them to be placed under more tension, whilst retaining the advantages of the transobturator sling. 

The retropubic sling comes with superior efficacy, but has higher risks of pelvic hematoma, bladder perforations, denovo urgency and voiding dysfunction. Minislings, placed under more tension, may provide equivalent or better results than retropubic slings in patients with ISD, whilst retaining the advantages of transobturator slings. 

We seek to examine if the minisling is as efficacious as the retropubic sling for women with urodynamic stress incontinence (USI) and intrinsic sphincter deficiency (ISD) and compare their clinical outcomes. 

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash Health </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Support
Services
Monash Health
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Road
Clayton Victoria 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/04/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/01/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Mercy Health </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>163 Studley Road
Heidelberg Victoria 3084</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>18/04/2016</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/01/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Anna Rosamilia</name>
      <address>Monash Health Pelvic Floor department 
Suite 48, 183 Wattletree Rd, Malvern VIC 3144</address>
      <phone>+6139509 6500</phone>
      <fax>+613 95096376</fax>
      <email>annarosamilia@urogyn.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Alison Leitch</name>
      <address>Pelvic Floor Unit
Obstetrics and Gynaecology
Monash Medical Centre Moorabbin
823-865 Centre Road
Bentleigh East Vic 3165</address>
      <phone>+613 99288588</phone>
      <fax>+613 99288338</fax>
      <email>Alison.Leitch@monashhealth.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lin Li Ow</name>
      <address>Pelvic Floor Unit
Obstetrics and Gynaecology
Monash Medical Centre Moorabbin
823-865 Centre Road
Bentleigh East Vic 3165</address>
      <phone>+613 99288588</phone>
      <fax>+613 99288338</fax>
      <email>owlinli@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lin Li Ow</name>
      <address>Pelvic Floor Unit
Obstetrics and Gynaecology
Monash Medical Centre Moorabbin
823-865 Centre Road
Bentleigh East Vic 3165</address>
      <phone>+613 99288588</phone>
      <fax>+613 99288338</fax>
      <email>owlinli@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>