<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371566">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/09/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/10/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001425482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of Pharmacist Charting at Admission to Residential Care</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of Pharmacist Charting at Admission to Residential Care</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>PPMC Residential Care</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hospital admission</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Pharmacist generated interim medication charts to facilitate the transfer of medication information when patients are transferred from an inpatient hospital admission to a
residential care facility. 

On discharge from General Medical units, a seven (7) day interim medication chart generated by partnered pharmacist medication charting and authorised by a medical officer will be supplied along with the discharge summary and discharge prescriptions. This chart is to be used by the residential care facility until the patient is seen by their usual provider.

This intervention will begin approximately three months after data collection begins (in order to gather baseline/pre-implementation data) and run for 3 months.</interventions>
    <comparator>Patients discharged from General Medical units to residential care facilities before the interim medication charts are implemented. These patients are supplied with a discharge summary with a medication management plan and discharge prescriptions as per standard care.

Data will be collected prospectively beginning mid-October 2016, for a 3 month period, before the intervention is implemented.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of medication errors as identified by comparing intended medication management plans on discharge with patients' care facility medication charts </outcome>
      <timepoint>10 days post hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients with an updated medication administration chart in the 7 days post-admission to the RCF (either interim or long term medication administration chart)
identified by reviewing medication charts</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days post discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients for whom locum medical practitioner attendance was required within 7 days of transfer for the purpose of writing or updating a medication chart identified by reviewing medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days post hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of medication administration errors identified in the 7 days post-admission to the RCF identified by reviewing medication charts</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days post hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of significant medication administration errors identified in the 7 days post-admission to the RCF as determined by a blinded expert panel identified by medication record review</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days post hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of patients readmitted to hospital within 7 days and 30 days of discharge to a RCF due to medication administration errors at the RCF identified by medical record review</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 and 30 days post hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Hospital admission and discharge from Alfred Health
A current patient of the following residential aged care facility on admission to hospital (ie not a new patient to facility following discharge): Royal Freemasons, Jewish Care, Aged Care Services Australia, Emmy Monash Aged Care, Abberfield Aged Care Facility, Menarock Aged Care Services</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients discharged to residential care facilities not listed above. 
Patients discharged outside pharmacist working hours (7am to 9pm, Monday to Sunday)
Patients who attend the Emergency Department but are not admitted as inpatients
Patients who are returning to a RCF and have had no medication changes made during hospitalisation
Children and/or young people (&lt;18 years of age)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Pre/post</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Comparisons between the pre and post standard of care will be performed using commercially available statistical software. Continuous variables will be compared using means (plus standard deviation) or medians (plus inter-quartile range) depending on the underlying distribution of the data. Where appropriate, a Student t-test will be used for normally distributed continuous variables or a Mann-Whitney U test where data is found to be non-normally distributed. The Wilcoxon rank-sum test will be used for ordinal variables and chi-square or Fishers exact test as appropriate for categorical variables. A two sided p-value of 0.05 will be considered to be statistically significant.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/10/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>28/04/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/05/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
    <postcode>3004 - Prahran </postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Alfred Health Pharmacy Department</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Pharmacy Department
55 Commercial Road
Melbourne Victoria 3004</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Health and Human Services (DHHS)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>50 Lonsdale Street
Melbourne Victoria 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Alfred Health has implemented a partnered pharmacist medication charting (PPMC) model which has been in place since November 2012. A randomised trial conducted in 2015 demonstrated that PPMC significantly reduced medication errors on admission compared to a standard medical model.
As part of a Department of Health Workforce Innovation Grant, the PPMC model is being extended as a standard of care to patients on admission to residential aged care following discharge from an inpatient admission.
The specific aim of this project is to evaluate whether a pharmacist generated interim medication chart facilitates the transfer of medication information when patients are transferred from an inpatient hospital admission to a residential care facility. Aiming to reduce the proportion of missed medication doses and the number of locum medical officer visits in the first 7 days postadmission to the residential care facility. And improving the communication and continuation of hospital medication plans onto long term residential care medication charts.
A pre and post methodology will involve visiting the 10 most utilised residential care facilities (RCF) in the Alfred Health catchment to collect data.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>55 Commercial Road
Melbourne Victoria 3004</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/09/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/Alfred/117</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>31/08/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Michael Dooley</name>
      <address>Pharmacy Department
Alfred Hospital
55 Commercial Road
Melbourne Victoria 3004</address>
      <phone>+61390762061</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.dooley@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Erica Tong</name>
      <address>Pharmacy Department
Alfred Hospital
55 Commercial Road
Melbourne Victoria 3004</address>
      <phone>+61390762061</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.tong@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Erica Tong</name>
      <address>Pharmacy Department
Alfred Hospital
55 Commercial Road
Melbourne Victoria 3004</address>
      <phone>+61390762061</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.tong@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Ria Hopkins</name>
      <address>Pharmacy Department
Alfred Hospital
55 Commercial Road
Melbourne Victoria 3004</address>
      <phone>+61390762061</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.hopkins@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>