<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83963">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/05/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/06/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000436279</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised phase II study comparing the activity and toxicity profiles of Carboplatin plus pegylated Liposomal Doxorubicin (CLD) versus Carboplatin plus Paclitaxel (CP) in potentially platinum sensitive ovarian cancer patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised phase II study comparing the clinical response and toxicity of Carboplatin plus pegylated Liposomal Doxorubicin (CLD) vs Carboplatin plus Paclitaxel (CP) in potentially platinum sensitive ovarian cancer patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>HE4B99  {issuing authority: Hellenic Cooperative Oncology Group (HeCOG)}</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>platinum sensitive ovarian cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ovarian and primary peritoneal</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>chemotherapy with Carboplatin plus pegylated Liposomal Doxorubicin (CLD): pegylated Liposomal Doxorubicin was administered as an intravenous infusion of 90 min at a dose of 45 mg/m2 followed by an intravenous infusion of 1 hour of Carboplatin at Area Under the Curve (AUC) 5, on day 1. Cycles were repeated every 28 days. Premedication included 20 mg dexamethasone, 4mg dyphenidramine, 150 mg ranitidine  administered intravenously immediatelly prior to pegylated Liposomal Doxorubicin  administration. The dose of carboplatin based on AUC was calculated by the estimated creatinine clearance using Calverts formula. Six cycles of chemotherapy were administered unless evidence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity occurred.</interventions>
    <comparator>chemotherapy with Carboplatin plus Paclitaxel (CP):Paclitaxel was administered at 175 mg/m2 as a 3hr intravenous infusion followed by an 1hour intravenous infusion of Carboplatin at an AUC5, on day 1. Cycles were repeated every 21 days. All patients received standard premedication of dexamethasone, dyphenhydramine and ranitidine prior to paclitaxel (20 mg dexamethasone, 4mg dyphenidramine, 150 mg ranitidine were administered orally 12 hours prior to paclitaxel and the same doses intravenously again immediatelly prior to paclitaxel administration). Patients in the intervention group received the above premedication only immediately prior to liposomal doxorubicin intravenously .  The dose of carboplatin based on AUC was calculated by the estimated creatinine clearance using Calverts formula. Six cycles of chemotherapy were administered unless evidence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity occurred.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>response was assessed clinically, and by imaging of measurable disease sites, ie by Computerised Tomography (CT) scans of chest, abdomen/pelvis as indicated and tumour marker measurements. Standard World Health Organisation (WHO) criteria were applied for assessment of response, as these were commonly used prior to the broad introduction of Response Criteria In Solid Tumours (RECIST) criteria, by our group and others, and at the time when this study was initiated. For patients without measurable disease, response was determined based on repetitive Cancer Antigen-125 (CA125) measurements using the algorithm proposed by Rustin and according to CA-125 Rustin's criteria.</outcome>
      <timepoint>response was assessed at the completion of every second cycle, i.e at the beggining of cycle 3, at the beggining of cycle 5 and then after completion of cycle 6.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Toxicity criteria were those adopted by the World Health Organization.</outcome>
      <timepoint>toxicity was assessed on day 1 of each cycle, detailing toxicity-related events of each previously completed cycle</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Women at least 18 years old, with histologically confirmed recurrent ovarian cancer (OC), 6 months or more after platinum-based chemotherapy, patients with bidimensionally measurable disease or only elevated serum tumour marker CA125 (more than twice the upper limit of normal), with Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 02 and life expectancy of at least 3 months were eligible. Adequate bone marrow, hepatic and renal functions were required.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with a history of malignancy other than completely excised in situ carcinoma of the cervix or basal carcinoma of the skin, prior or recurrent central nervous system metastases, serious cardiac disease, other serious medical illness or inability to comply with the treatment plan and follow-up visits were excluded. Also patients with residual neurotoxicity from previous platinum and/or taxane chemotherapy were excluded.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/1999</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>201</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Hellenic Cooperative Oncology Group</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Hatzikonstanti street No 18, Athens 11524</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Greece</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Hellenic Cooperative Oncology Group</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Hatzikonstanti street No 18, Athens 11524</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Greece</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Platinum-based combinations are standard 2nd-line treatment for platinum-sensitive ovarian cancer. This randomized phase II study was conducted to evaluate the efficacy and safety of a carboplatin-based combination with pegylated LD versus the standard combination of carboplatin with paclitaxel in patients with ovarian cancer relapsing at least 6 months after 1st-line platinum-based therapy. It is hypothesised that the combination of carboplatin-pegylated LD will be at least as effective with a more favourable toxicity profile than the standard combination with paclitaxel.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>H. Linardou</name>
      <address>Hatzikonstanti street No 18, Athens 11524</address>
      <phone>+30 210-4809852</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>elinardou@metropolitan-hospital.gr</email>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>D. Bafaloukos</name>
      <address>Hatzikonstanti street No 18, Athens 11524</address>
      <phone>+30 210-4296620</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dbafaloukos@metropolitan-hospital.gr</email>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>