<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364210">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/05/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/05/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000536763</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Optimising immune responses to vaccination in Australian Hajj Pilgrims</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In Hajj pilgrims, does dTpa given before the co-administration of MCV4 and PCV 13 conjugate vaccines illustrate priming or suppression of immune response</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1142-8250</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Immune response to vaccines</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Knowledge, attitude and perception regarding vaccines and vaccination uptake</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the immune system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be randomly assigned by a computer into one of 3 groups

Group 1: Will be initially vaccinated intramuscularly against diphtheria/tetanus/pertussis in July followed by pneumococcal and meningococcal vaccines a month later.


Group 2 : Will be vaccinated intramuscularly in July against diphtheria/tetanus/pertussis, pneumococcal and meningococcal disease at the same time

Group 3: Will be initially vaccinated intramuscularly in July against pneumococcal and meningococcal diseases followed, by diphtheria/tetanus/pertussis vaccine a month later.

The dose of the vaccines will be the same standard dose in all the groups : dTp =0.5mL, MCV4= 0.5 mL and PCV13= 0.5 mL

Knowledge, attitude and practice (KAP survey). This survey will be in the form of self administered questionnaire that will be distributed before vaccination. The questions will explore the pilgrims attitude and knowledge regarding vaccines and Hajj diseases.</interventions>
    <comparator>There is no control group here as there is no standard practice for this. The three groups will compared against each other to find out which group will gain a better immune response</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Immune response to MCV4 will be assessed by measuring human serum bactericidal assay hSBA.


</outcome>
      <timepoint>3-8 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>IGg antibodies for diphtheria; pertussis and tetanus will be measured by ELISA. </outcome>
      <timepoint>3-8 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Immune response to pneumococcus will be measures by OPA, a functional assay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3-8 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Knowledge attitude and Practice regarding vaccines and vaccine uptake will be assessed via a self administered questionnaire.

This questionnaire is designed specifically for this study. Data from pilgrims demographics and their KAPs towards travel-vaccines in general, and pneumococcal, influenza and pertussis vaccines in particular, will be assessed via self-administered questionnaire, barriers to vaccination will be evaluated through appropriate questions. </outcome>
      <timepoint>the survey will take place in July immediately before vaccination</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Australian pilgrims attending Hajj and/or Umrah for 2013, 2014 and 2015</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>64</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>People with  a previous history of allergic reaction to any of the study vaccines.
People previously vaccinated with any of the  (13 valent pneumococcal vaccine, 4 valent meningococcal vaccine,diphtheria, pertussis and tetanus vaccine) in the past 3 years</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Potential participants will be recruited through various methods such as radio announcements and distributed flyers.

The investigator will determine who is eligible by checking the eligibility checklist. Eligible participants will be consented after reading the (Information Statement). After they sign the consent form, the will be randomly assigned by an onsite computer into one of 3 groups. Neither the study investigator nor the study participant can decide in which group the participant will be.



Group 1: Will be initially vaccinated against diphtheria/tetanus/pertussis followed by pneumococcal and meningococcal vaccines a month later.
Group 2: Will be vaccinated against diphtheria/tetanus/pertussis, pneumococcal and meningococcal disease at the same time 
Group 3: will be initially vaccinated against pneumococcal and meningococcal diseases followed, by diphtheria/tetanus/pertussis vaccine a month later.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be generated via an on-site computer</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Studies with various meningococcal conjugate vaccines have shown that a minimum 4 fold response to serogroup (Y) to be as low as 74%. With power of 80% and a two sided a=0.025, a sample size of 72 participants per group will give the power to detect a 25% relative increase from 74% to 92.5% (with the same power, this will also detect an increase from 80% up to 96%). (We will be also able to detect a reduction in response from 74% to 49.5% [and from 80% to 56%]). To account for 5% loss to follow-up, approximately 76 per group are required i.e. a total of 227 participants in the three groups. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>8/07/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>8/07/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>24/06/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>227</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>276</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Children's Hospital at Westmead - Westmead</hospital>
    <postcode>2145 - Westmead</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Children's Hospital, Westmead (Prof.Robert Booy)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Kerry Packer Research Building
The Children's Hospital at Westmead
Cnr Hawkesbury Rd &amp; Hainsworth St.
Westmead, NSW, Postcode: 2145</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>This study is self funded by the investigators at the  National Centre for Immunisation Research and Surveillance NCIRS</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Kerry Packer Research Building
The Children's Hospital at Westmead
Cnr Hawkesbury Rd &amp; Hainsworth St.
Westmead, NSW, Postcode: 2145</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Robert Austrian Research Award</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The 9th International Symposium on Pneumococci and Pneumococcal Diseases (ISPPD 2014).
Address: ISPPD Administrative Office
c/o Marcel Dekker at Kenes Assocations Worldwide
Rue François-Versonnex 7,
1207 Geneva, Switzerland</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Switzerland</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Pfizer</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Pfizer Vaccine. 401 N Middletown Rd. Building 222. Pearl River, NY 10965. USA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>GSK</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GlaxoSmithKline Australia
Level 3, 436 Johnston Street, Abbotsford, Victoria, 3067.
PO Box 18095, Melbourne, Victoria, 8003.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Research suggests that carrier proteins may unpredictably enhance or reduce immune response to the polysaccharide antigens; therefore administering dTpa before, with, or after MCV4 is an important matter with regard to immune response to vaccines. 
There are no data Adults on whether the receipt of dTpa before, after or concomitantly with MCV4 and PCV13 would enhance or suppress immune response. Therefore, we would like to explore further means in order to optimise immunity and maximise immunogenicity of these vaccines in Hajj or Umrah pilgrims.
In addition to optimising the immunogenicity of the recommended vaccines, this study will also explore the pilgrims pre-travel health seeking behaviour and assess their Knowledge Perception and Attitude (KAP) towards the recommended vaccines.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.ncirs.edu.au/assets/research/clinical/Hajj-pilgrims-study.pdf</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/05/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>13/05/15/3.05</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/04/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Robert Booy</name>
      <address>Kerry Packer Research Building
The Children's Hospital at Westmead
Cnr Hawkesbury Rd &amp; Hainsworth St.
Westmead, NSW,
 Postcode: 2145.
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61298451433</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>robert.booy@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mohamed Nagmi Tashani</name>
      <address>Kerry Packer Research Building
The Children's Hospital at Westmead
Cnr Hawkesbury Rd &amp; Hainsworth St.
Westmead, NSW,
 Postcode: 2145.
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61435752969</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>toshani2003@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Robert Booy</name>
      <address>Kerry Packer Research Building
The Children's Hospital at Westmead
Cnr Hawkesbury Rd &amp; Hainsworth St.
Westmead, NSW,
 Postcode: 2145.
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61298451433</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>robert.booy@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mohamed Nagmi Tashani</name>
      <address>Kerry Packer Research Building
The Children's Hospital at Westmead
Cnr Hawkesbury Rd &amp; Hainsworth St.
Westmead, NSW,
 Postcode: 2145.
Australia</address>
      <phone>61435752969</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>toshani2003@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>