<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369239">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/09/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/09/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000984594</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Phase I study of orally inhaled PB01 in healthy male participants following single and repeat administration.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled Phase I study to evaluate the safety, tolerability and pharmacokinetics of single and multiple doses of orally inhaled PB01 administered to healthy subjects.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Airway inflammation and fibrosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>PB01 solution for oral inhalation is administered using a nebuliser and consists of PB01 in 20mM sodium phosphate buffer and 500 mM sodium chloride, pH 7.  

Stage 1 (Single Ascending Dose)
PB01 will be administered via oral inhalation as a single dose.  The starting dose level is 3 mg (Cohort 1) with provision to escalate to 9 mg (Cohort 2), 20 mg (Cohort 3) and 30 mg (Cohort 4) subject to Safety Review Committee assessment of each preceding dose level Cohort. 

Study medication will be administered by an Aerogen Aeroneb Go vibrating mesh nebuliser which delivers 3 mL of study medication in approximately 7 minutes and 6 mL of study medication in approximately 13 minutes.  Participants will be admitted to the study unit on Day -1 (the day prior to administration of study medication) and trained on the use of the Aeroneb Go nebuliser. Participants will be required to fast (from food) for at least 10 hours prior to administration of study medication on Day 1. On Day 1, study medication will be administered by inhalation under the supervision of the clinical site personnel and participants will be confined to the study unit for a further 24 hours.   On Day 2, participants will be discharged from the study unit after completion of all study procedures.  Participants will attend the study unit on Day 5 (+2) for an End of Study Evaluation. Pharmacokinetic (PK) sampling for PB01 PK determination will be included in this Stage.  

Stage 2 (Multiple Ascending Dose)
Dose levels to be determined from results of Stage 1. Up to three dose levels are planned. PB01 will be administered via oral inhalation once a day for 14 consecutive days. 

Eligible participants will be admitted to the study unit on Day -1 (the day prior to administration of study medication) and trained on the use of the Aeroneb Go nebuliser.  Prior to administration of study medication on Day 1 and Day 14, participants will be required to fast (from food) for at least 10 hours.  On Day 1, study medication will be administered by inhalation under the supervision of the clinical site personnel. Dosing will continue once daily on Days 2-14 inclusive, under supervision. Participants will be confined to the study unit throughout the 14 day dosing period and will be discharged from the study unit on Day 15.  On Day 21(+2) participants will attend the study unit on an End of Study Evaluation.  PK sampling for PB01 PK determination will be included in this Stage.

Participants from Stage 1 will not be used for Stage 2. For both Stages, the investigator is responsible for maintaining accurate study medication accountability records throughout the study. Drug accountability will be performed by the monitor during monitoring visits to reconcile the number of study medication syringes dispensed with that used/returned.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo solution for oral inhalation contains vehicle only, which consists of 20mM sodium phosphate buffer and 500 mM sodium chloride, pH 7.  

Participants will be randomised in a ratio of 3:1 to receive either PB01 or Placebo, with the exception of the first two participants (i.e. the sentinel participants) within each dose level cohort who will be randomised in a ratio of 1:1 to ensure that one participant receives PB01 and one participant receives Placebo.  </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the safety and tolerability of orally inhaled PB01 in healthy male participants following single (Stage 1) dose administration.</outcome>
      <timepoint>For Stage 1 (Single Ascending Dose) a single orally inhaled dose of PB01 will be administered on Day 1 of the study for each dose level cohort. Participants will be confined to the study centre from Day -1 and will be discharged on Day 2. Participants will then return on Day 5 (+2) for an End of Study Evaluation.  During this time vital signs, physical examination, clinical laboratory determinations (haematology, clinical chemistry, liver function tests, coagulation, urinalysis, Follicle stimulating hormone (FSH) levels), 12 lead electrocardiogram (ECG) reading and spirometry will be performed.  Blood samples for determination of the production of antibodies to PB01 will be collected but not assayed unless clinically indicated. All participants will be monitored for adverse events and concomitant medications for the duration of the study and all information received between consent and final visit (Day 5 (+2)) will be recorded in the case report form.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the safety and tolerability of orally inhaled PB01 in healthy male participants following repeat (Stage 2) dose administration.</outcome>
      <timepoint>For Stage 2 (Multiple Ascending Dose), PB01 will be administered once daily for 14 consecutive days. Participants will be confined to the study centre from Day -1 and will be discharged on Day 15. Participants will then return on Day 21(+2) for an End of Study Evaluation.  During this time vital signs, physical examination, clinical laboratory determinations (haematology, clinical chemistry, liver function tests, coagulation, urinalysis, Follicle stimulating hormone (FSH) levels), 12 lead electrocardiogram (ECG) reading and spirometry will be performed.  Blood samples for determination of the production of antibodies to PB01 will be collected but not assayed unless clinically indicated. All participants will be monitored for adverse events and concomitant medications for the duration of the study and all information received between consent and final visit (Day 21(+2)) will be recorded in the case report form.
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the pharmacokinetics of orally inhaled PB01 in healthy male participants following single (Stage 1) dose administration.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pharmacokinetic parameters for PB01 in serum include Cmax, Tmax, T1/2, AUC(0-t), and AUC (0 - infinity).  Blood samples will be collected at pre-dose, immediately after completion of dosage administration, and at 20 minutes (only if dosing has been completed prior to the 20 minute time point), 30 minutes, 45 minutes and at 1, 1.5, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 12 hours on Day 1 and 24 hours (Day 2) after commencement of PB01 administration.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the pharmacokinetics of orally inhaled PB01 in healthy male participants following repeat (Stage 2) dose administration.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pharmacokinetic parameters for PB01 in serum include Cmax, Tmax, T1/2, AUC(0-t), and AUC (0 - infinity).  Blood samples will be collected at pre-dose, immediately after completion of dosage administration, and at 20 minutes (only if dosing has been completed prior to the 20 minute time point), 30 minutes, 45 minutes and at 1, 1.5, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 12 and 24 hours after commencement of PB01 administration.

Blood sampling will be done for the first dose of study medication administered on Day 1 and for the last dose of study medication administered on Day 14 for this stage (Stage 2) of the study.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Able to speak, read and understand English sufficiently to understand the purposes and risks of the study and to provide written informed consent.
Healthy males aged 18 to 55 years inclusive at the time of consent.   
Body Mass Index (BMI) of greater than or equal to 18 to less than or equal to 30.0 kg/m2
Normal pulmonary function and performance on pulmonary function tests, defined as Forced expiratory volume measured in one second, expressed in litres (FEV1), and Forced vital capacity, expressed in litres (FVC) both greater than or equal to 80% of their predicted value for age, ethnicity, sex and height.  
Participants must be willing and able to comply with scheduled visits, treatment plan, laboratory tests and other study procedures.
Participants must be willing to comply with the medically acceptable contraceptive requirements of the study from Screening to at least 30 days after the last IMP administration.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants will not be eligible to participate in the study if they meet any of the following criteria:
Clinically significant disease including airway inflammation, haemoptysis or other respiratory disease (except for completely-resolved childhood asthma and symptom free for greater than 5 years).
Participants who have a positive urine cotinine test at Screening or Day -1.
Smokers (i.e. cigarette or tobacco use at any time within the last 18 months).
Use of caffeine-containing foods/beverages/dietary supplements, decaffeinated beverages or alcohol within 48 hours prior to all visits and/or unable to refrain from their use during the study.
Use of prescription or non-prescription (over-the-counter) or complementary medicines, within 14 days prior to Day -1, except occasional use of paracetamol (up to 2g per day).
Respiratory tract infection within the previous four weeks or any infection within 7 days prior to Day -1. 
Any clinically significant abnormalities on clinical chemistry, haematology, urinalysis, physical examination, medical history, 12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG), or vital signs as judged by the investigator or sponsor (at Screening and/or Day -1).
Clinically significant abnormality of renal function, defined as Cockcroft Gault creatinine clearance less than 70 ml/min.
Clinically significant abnormality of hepatic function defined as AST or ALT greater than 1.5 times the upper limit of normal.
History or evidence of, or positive test for HIV, hepatitis B or hepatitis C.
Positive urine drug screen or alcohol test during Screening or on-study, or history of drug or alcohol abuse and/or dependence within the past year prior to Day -1.
Participation in another clinical trial or administration of any investigational agent within 8 weeks or 5 half-lives (whichever is longer) prior to Day -1.
History of clinically significant allergic disease requiring medical treatment with medications as judged by the investigator or sponsor.
History of hypersensitivity to follistatin or drugs of the same pharmacological class.
Surgical or medical conditions which could significantly alter drug absorption, distribution, metabolism or excretion.
Major surgery within 3 months prior to Day -1 or anticipated surgery in the study period.
Blood or plasma donation of more than 500 mL during the 3 months prior to Day -1.
History of or current clinically-significant gastrointestinal, hepatic, renal, cardiovascular, respiratory, endocrine, oncological, immunological, neurological, ophthalmological, haematological or psychiatric disorder or any other condition, which in the opinion of the investigator or sponsor would jeopardize the safety of the participant or the validity of the study results.
Unable to refrain from strenuous activity for 48 hours prior to all visits and for the duration of the study.
Unable to use nebuliser.
An employee of the sponsor or research site personnel directly affiliated with this study or their immediate family members defined as a spouse, parent, sibling, or child, whether biological or legally adopted.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>22/09/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>22/09/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>23/02/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>30/03/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>56</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>48</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Paranta Biosciences Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>189-191 Balaclava Road, Caulfield North, Victoria 3161</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Paranta Biosciences Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>189-191 Balaclava Road, Caulfield North, Victoria 3161</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is designed to assess the safety, tolerability and pharmacokinetic profile of orally inhaled PB01 when administered to healthy male volunteers (aged between 18 and 55 years) as a single dose (Stage 1 component of the study) and 14 consecutive once daily doses (Stage 2 component of the study) at dose levels up to 30 mg.
Stages 1 and 2 will be conducted in Australia. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Limited</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>129 Glen Osmond Road, Eastwood SA 5063
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/07/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nicholas Farinola</name>
      <address>CMAX, A Division of IDT Australia Ltd, Royal Adelaide Hospital, Level 5, East Wing, North Terrace, Adelaide 
South Australia 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 3928</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Nicholas.Farinola@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Ross Barrow</name>
      <address>Paranta Biosciences Ltd, 189-191 Balaclava Road, Caulfield North, Victoria 3161
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9526 0021</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ross.barrow@parantabio.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Nuket Desem</name>
      <address>Paranta Biosciences Ltd, 189-191 Balaclava Road, Caulfield North, Victoria 3161
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9526 0021</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nuket.desem@parantabio.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Nuket Desem</name>
      <address>Paranta Biosciences Ltd, 189-191 Balaclava Road, Caulfield North, Victoria 3161
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9526 0021</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nuket.desem@parantabio.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>