<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83507">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/01/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/02/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000089235</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An Investigation of the efficacy of single photon emission computed tomography (SPECT) ventilation/perfusion (V/Q) scintigraphy in diagnosing pulmonary embolism</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An investigation of the sensitivity and specificity of single photon emission computed tomography (SPECT) ventilation/perfusion (V/Q) scintigraphy for the diagnosis of pulmonary embolism in 100 patients with suspected pulmonary embolism.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pulmonary Embolism</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All patients to receive the following: One planar ventilation/perfusion (V/Q) scintigraphy using Technegas and 185MBq (5mCi) Tc-99m-Macro Aggregated Albumin (MAA) (Pulmolite CIS-US Inc Bedford MA USA) acquired on dual head Picker Prism 2000 (Cleveland Ohio) or Siemens eCam (Knoxville Tennessee) gamma cameras using low energy high-resolution collimators on the Tc-99m photopeak of 140kEv +/-10% for 60 stops 15 (10) seconds/stop 360 degrees; one SPECT ventilation/perfusion (V/Q) scintigraphy using Technegas and 185MBq (5mCi) Tc-99m-Macro Aggregated Albumin (MAA) (Pulmolite CIS-US Inc Bedford MA USA) acquired on dual head Picker Prism 2000 (Cleveland Ohio) or Siemens eCam (Knoxville Tennessee) gamma cameras using low energy high-resolution collimators on the Tc-99m photopeak of 140kEv +/-10% for 60 stops 15 (10) seconds/stop 360 degrees; one 16-row multidetector computed tomography pulmonary angiography (CTPA) extended from 1 cm above the aortic arch to the diaphragm, using contrast (120ml of Iomeron 300) injected intravenously at a rate of 3.5 ml/sec, and Philips MX8000 IDT model (Philips Healthcare Andover MA USA) or Toshiba Aquilion 16 model (Toshiba Minato-ku Tokyo, Japan) scanners operating with 16 times 0.75 mm collimation at pitch 0.9 and 0.5 second rotation and time and exposure factors of 120 kVp and 230 mA. with dose modulation software and automated bolus tracking software; Xray; d-dimer; respiratory physicians' diagnosis based on clinical measures and observations, Xray, CTPA, XDPVTE (d-dimer) and 3 month follow up. The information provided for the physicians' diagnosis specifically excludes the planar and SPECT ventilation/perfusion images and reports. Planar and SPECT ventilation and perfusion scintigraphy and CTPA are to be performed within 24 hours of each other, with the first scan commencing as soon as possible after recruitment, and the order of tests determined by the treating clinician. The scheduling and number of other diagnostic tests is also determined by the treating clinician, according to his/her clinical management plan. The physicians' diagnosis is separate from the treating clinician's diagnosis, and is reached at least three months after the completion of scans, and after retrospective review of the clinical information, CTPA scan report and three-month follow-up.</interventions>
    <comparator>Uncontrolled</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sensitivity and specificity of SPECT ventilation/perfusion (V/Q) scintigraphy, when compared with a respiratory physicians' diagnosis based on clinical measures and observations, Xray, computed tomography pulmonary angiography (CTPA), d-dimer and 3 month follow up.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of final diagnosis</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Agreement (proportion and Kappa) of SPECT ventilation/perfusion (V/Q) scintigraphy with diagnosis by computed tomography pulmonary angiography (CTPA)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At completion of scan reporting</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diagnostic quality of scans as assessed by two radiologists (in the case  of computed tomography pulmonary angiography) or two nuclear medicine specialists (in the case of ventilation/perfusion scintigraphy) reporting the scans, who grade each scan as diagnostic or non-diagnostic. Discrepant gradings (one "diagnostic", one "non-diagnostic") were referred to a reference panel of three radiologists (in the case  of computed tomography pulmonary angiography) or three nuclear medicine specialists (in the case of ventilation/perfusion scintigraphy) to reach a consensus decision.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At completion of scan reporting</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Under investigation for presumed acute pulmonary embolism (PE), glomerular filtration rate above the lowest quartile for age group, ability to give informed consent, willingness to undergo all scans, screening completed before the scheduled time of first scan</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Critical illness
Current haemodynamic instability with shock or hypotension
Sustained ventricular tachycardia or ventricular fibrillation in the previous 24 hours
Myocardial infarction in the previous month, with ongoing instability
Chronic pulmonary hypertension
Renal impairment or on dialysis
Mechanical ventilatory support
Pregnancy
Allergy to intravenous contrast or iodine or lung scan agents
Severe thyroid disease
Previous pulmonary emboli
Inferior vena caval filter
Likelihood of receiving thrombolysis within 24 hours
Evidence of an alternative source of thromboemboli other than the pelvic veins and lower extremities
Institutionalised patient or prisoner
Likelihood of discharge before completion of study scans</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/03/2004</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Michael Hensley</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The School of Medicine and Public Health, 
University of Newcastle, 
Callaghan, NSW, 2308
Australia

Hunter Region Mail Centre NSW 2310 Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>John Hunter Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Locked Bag 1
Hunter Region Mail Centre
NSW 2310 Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Barry Soans</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Clinical Director
Hunter New England Imaging,
Locked Bag 1,
Hunter Region Mail Centre, NSW, 2310,
Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Pulmonary emboli (PE) are common and overlooking the diagnosis can result in serious harm and death. Various imaging modalities including ventilation-perfusion (V/Q) scanning and Computed Tomography Pulmonary Angiography (CTPA) are used.  These imaging tests are imperfect and, even when combined with pretest stratification, often leave the clinician uncertain as to the presence or absence of PE.  
Initial studies have suggested that Single Photon Emission Computed Tomography  (SPECT) V/Q scintigraphy may be more sensitive and specific than planar V/Q scintigraphy, and have higher intra-observer reproducibility and fewer non-diagnostic studies.  Studies also suggest that SPECT V/Q scintigraphy may be safer than CTPA for patients with contrast allergy and for young or pregnant women.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>John Hunter Hospital
Locked Bag 1
Hunter Region Mail Centre NSW 2310
Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/11/2003</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>03/10/15/3.08</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Michael Hensley</name>
      <address>The School of Medicine and Public Health, 
University of Newcastle, 
Callaghan, NSW, 2308
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 2 49217776</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Susan.Miles@mater.health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Susan Miles</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine
Calvary Mater Newcastle
Locked Bag 7 
Hunter Region Mail Centre NSW 2310 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 2 49211211</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Susan.Miles@mater.health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>