<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362391">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/04/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/04/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000447853</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>How effective are the drugs pregabalin and celecoxib in relieving pain after laparoscopic gall bladder surgery?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of pregabalin and celecoxib on the analgesic requirements after laparoscopic cholecystectomy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1130-0146</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>pain after laparoscopic cholecystectomy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>premedication 1 hour before the surgery with 

Group pregabalin: pregabalin 150 mg + matched celecoxib placebo orally

Group celecoxib: celecoxib 400 mg + pregabalin placebo orally

Group pregabalin/celecoxib: pregabalin 150 mg + celecoxib 400 mg orally

Group placebo: pregabalin placebo + celecoxib placebo orally

Matched celecoxib and pregabalin placebos are identical in shape, size and colour to celecoxib and pregabalin tablets, but they differ from the original tablets in that they contain no active ingredients. 
12 hours after the premedication, second dose of study drugs (pregabalin 150 mg/ celecoxib 200 mg/ combination/ placebo) given.</interventions>
    <comparator>Matched celecoxib and pregabalin placebos are identical in shape, size and colour to celecoxib and pregabalin tablets, but they differ from the original tablets in that they contain no active ingredients.  All the groups do get patient controlled analgesia with fentanyl as the routine care.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>postoperative pain and PCA fentanyl requirements are assessed. Assessment of pain at rest &amp; with movement with verbal rating scale 0-10 with 0 representing no pain and 10 the worst imaginable pain</outcome>
      <timepoint>1,2,4,8,12,24 hours postoperatively,</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>assessment of preoperative anxiety  with the  verbal rating scale 0-10.</outcome>
      <timepoint>once before premedication and once before induction</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>sedation scores as assessed by  4 point ordinal scale
0-	none ,completely awake
1-	mild, occasional drowsy, easy to rouse
2-	moderate, arousable, but not able to stay awake
3-	severe, difficult to rouse or unarousable</outcome>
      <timepoint>1,2,4,8,12,24 hours postoperatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nausea &amp; vomiting assessed with the 4 point ordinal scale 
 
0-	no N +V
1-	mild N+V
2-	moderate N+V
3-	severe N+V</outcome>
      <timepoint>1,2,4,8,12,24 hours postoperatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Other side effects-headache/light headedness/dizziness/visual disturbance- diplopia/pruritus/difficulty in walking or concentrating/drowsiness &amp; difficulty in staying awake/itchiness/drymouth/confusion. The above side effects are noted with yes/no ordinal scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 1,2,4,8,12,24 hours postoperatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>satisfaction with pain relief by scale of 0-10, 0, completely dissatisfied; 10- completely satisfied</outcome>
      <timepoint>assessed at 24 hours postoperatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>ASA I/II patients, 18-70 years, undergoing laparoscopic cholecystectomy with minimal or no health issues.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. patients with significantly established IHD( angina, MI, heart failure) /peripheral arterial disease/cerebrovascular disease, patients with NYHA II-IV functional capacity classification of heart failure, uncontrolled DM, Hypertension.
2. ASA&gt;2
3. patients with dizziness
4. history of peptic ulcer
5. pregnancy or lactation
6. patients on anticonvulsants, antidepressants
7. impaired kidney, liver  function
8. obese( patients&gt; BMI 40)
9. psychiatric disorders, drug/alcohol abuse
10. history of aspirin sensitive asthma,  known hypersensitivity to celecoxib or sulphonamides, history of allergic-type reactions after aspirin or NSAIDs.
11. history of epilepsy
12. patients receiving analgesics/sedatives ( opioids incl. tramadol, acetaminophen, NSAIDs) within 24 hours preoperatively
13.Conversion to open cholecystectomy, bile spillage, insertion of drain.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A randomisation list will be created by our hospital pharmacy using a computer program. Patients who meet the inclusion/exclusion criteria, and give informed consent, would be randomly allocated to four groups based on computer generated codes.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using a randomization table created by a computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Factorial</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3 / Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/05/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Prince Charles Hospital - Chermside</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Usha Gurunathan</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Anaesthesia, The Prince Charles Hospital, Rode Road, Chermside, Brisbane, QLD-4032</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Prince Charles Hospital foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Rode Road, Chermside, Queensland- 4032</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Pain is inadequately treated in many of the surgical procedures. Postoperative pain is the main reason for the prolonged convalescence after laparoscopic (key hole) gall bladder surgery. Severe postoperative pain after  gall bladder surgery can cause significant long standing pain, if not adequately treated initially. 

Postoperative pain has been traditionally treated with opioids, non steroidal anti-inflammatory agents and paracetamol. Opioids are associated with significant side effects and constant search for an alternative agent with similar potency and minimal side effects has been on for a very long time.

Pregabalin and Gabapentin have recently elicited a lot of interest as being useful drugs for postoperative pain relief. Pregabalin has got a lot of pharmacokinetic advantages over Gabapentin as being more potent and    more bioavailable with very minimal side effects. When combined with drugs like celecoxib, which are the 
safer versions of anti-inflammatory drugs as of current evidence, Pregabalin is likely to exhibit synergistic 
effect. This project evaluates the efficacy of Pregabalin, Celecoxib and their combination to treat postoperative pain in patients undergoing laparoscopic gall bladder surgery. 

This will be a randomized, double blind study. Selected participants will be given pregabalin, celecoxib or their combination or their placebo before and after surgery. They will be given standard general anaesthesia according to protocol. Their pain scores after surgery, demand for pain killers, anxiety levels, satisfaction with pain relief and other side effects will be recorded by a nurse.

Statistical analysis will be made with the above observations to evaluate the efficacy of the study drugs.

If this research yields positive result, it can add on to the evidence for using a different group of drugs for relief of acute postoperative pain as opposed to conventional pain relief with opioids. Also, the same group of drugs may be trialled in future for minimising the occurrence of chronic pain after surgery.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr.Usha Gurunathan</name>
      <address>The Prince Charles Hospital, Rode Road, Chermside, QLD 4032</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3139 4000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>usha_gurunathan@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr.Usha Gurunathan</name>
      <address>The Prince Charles Hospital, Rode Road, Chermside, QLD-4032</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3139 4000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>usha_gurunathan@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr.Usha Gurunathan</name>
      <address>The Prince Charles Hospital, Rode Road, Chermside</address>
      <phone>07 3139 4000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>usha_gurunathan@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>