<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366463">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/07/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/08/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000833662</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can provision of ambulatory nutrition services to patients discharged from acute care improve health outcomes at an acceptable cost?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of Dietary modification versus no dietary modification on length of hospital stay, hospital re-admission rate, mortality, quality of life and associated costs in hospitalised malnourished patients.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1157-9341 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Malnutrition in Hospitalized patients</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients admitted in General Medicine ward will be screened for malnutrition by a member of research team, using Malnutrition Universal Screening tool(MUST) and those found to be malnourished will be stratified according to cognitive status into two groups - cognitively normal and cognitively impaired and will be referred to a dietitian who will perform a detailed nutritional assessment using PG-SGA(Patient Generated Subjective Global Assessment) tool and patients will be randomized to intervention and control group. Patients in the intervention group will receive nutritional intervention which may include dietary modification or nutritional supplements and will be followed every month by a telephone call to check compliance for two months and at the end of three months will be seen in dietary clinic for repeat nutritional assessment and cost benefit analysis will be calculated and patients in the control group will follow usual care which does not include prolonged ambulatory dietary intervention.
Nutrition Intervention:
The dietitian will set realistic goals negotiated with the patient in an effort to prevent decline in nutritional status. The PG-SGA and calculation of estimated requirements will provide guidance on areas of potential nutritional inadequacy and the diet intervention will be tailored to address these. The duration of nutritional intervention will be single one hour session at the baseline and thirty minutes reviews.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group includes malnourished admitted patients who will receive the standard care of treatment being followed in the hospital which does not routinely include  dietary intervention over extended period of time after hospital discharge.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvement in Patient Generated Subjective Global Assessment (PG-SGA) score.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at three months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>European5 Quality of Life(EQ5D) Score</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and then at three months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospital Re-admission rate
This will be determined by data linkage to patient medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At three months as compared to control group</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost-benefit analysis
The evaluation will be  based on a primary outcome of cost per unit reduction in the PG-SGA( Patient generated Subjective Global Assessment) during the intervention period. That is, how much savings can be attributed to one unit of improvement in nutritional status. Utility-based outcomes will be incorporated into the analysis allowing a secondary outcome to be cost per QALY gained (based on the EQ5D level values). This will be determined using European Quality of Life Questionnaire(EQ5D) and Quality adjusted Life years(QALY) will be calculated.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of three months as compared to control group.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mortality</outcome>
      <timepoint>At three months as compared to control group.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients admitted to general medicine ward aged sixty years or above, Ability to provide written consent or consent obtained from legal guardian if cognitively impaired, Identified as malnourished according to a standard malnutrition screening instrument-Malnutrition Universal Screening Tool (MUST).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Resides outside metropolitan Adelaide, Inability to obtain consent, non-english speaking, Aborigines, palliative patients.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All patients admitted under general medicine will be screened by research associate using Malnutrition Universal Screening Tool(MUST) and Allocation concealment will be done by sealed opaque envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation schedule will be created by an independent statistician using ralloc.ado version 3.6.1 in Stata version 11.1. Treatment allocations will be randomly permuted and balanced within blocks and stratified according to cognitive status (history of dementia/delirium vs no cognitive impairment). Numbered opaque envelopes will conceal allocation until baseline assessments have been completed. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Primary analysis for this study will be undertaken using intention to treat principles. Stratified randomisation by cognitive status (history of dementia/delirium vs no cognitive impairment) will be utilised. Central tendency and distribution will be determined and data presented as appropriate. Conditional upon fulfilling required statistical assumptions and on measurement level of the variables Independent samples t-tests, Mann-Whitney U tests or Chi-square test of association will be used to compare groups at baseline. Any identified variables that are different despite applying randomisation will be investigated and if required entered into subsequent models as confounders. To determine differences between the groups, repeated measures ANOVA with one between and one within factor and their interaction will be considered. If amount of missing data due to death or withdrawal will make a list wise approach to dealing with absent responses inappropriate, linear mixed models (LMM) will be utilised instead. Finally, if severe violation of the LMM statistical assumptions regarding PG-SGA and EQ-5D distributions occurs then generalized linear mixed models will be used. Survival analysis will be undertaken to compare groups for length of stay, time to first hospital readmission or presentation to emergency department and time to death. Statistical analyses will be undertaken using relevant software including SPSS and STATA. 

For the primary outcome of nutritional status as measured by the scored PG-SGA, it has been recommended that a shift of three points is clinically meaningful. Literature using scored PG-SGA in similar populations indicates an average SD of approximately 4.3. This estimate was used in the estimate of sample size resulting in a standardized effect size of f=0.35. Repeated measures between factor ANOVA sample size estimation procedure available in software G*Power3 was used to calculate the sample size for this project. Assuming an effect size f=0.35, alpha=0.002, power 80%, with two levels for between factor and two repeated measurements (correlated at 0.5 level) the estimated required sample size is 86 (43 per group). To allow for deaths and withdrawals (15% each), a total of 112 participants will be recruited (56 per group). A sample size of 86 will be sufficient to detect the difference of 0.18 units in EQ-5D quality of life scale as based on a theoretical SD value for EQ-5D  equal to 0.25. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>28/11/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>24/06/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>112</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>148</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>4/10/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Flinders Medical Centre - Bedford Park</hospital>
    <postcode>5042 - Bedford Park</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Yogesh Sharma</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of General Medicine
Flinders Medical Centre
Flinders Drive
Bedford Park SA 5042</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>A/Prof Michelle Miller</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of Nutrition and Dietetics
Flinders University
Flinders Drive
Bedford Park SA 5042</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Malnutrition is common in hospitalized patients and is associated with adverse health outcomes including prolonged length of stay, increased risk of pressure sores and increased re-admission rates and proves costly for the hospitals. Diagnosis of malnutrition is often missed due to a number of factors including lack of awareness among clinicians and low priority given other medical conditions. The main purpose of this study is to find out whether nutrition supplementation started early in hospital and extending for three months after discharge has any beneficial effects on health outcomes of patients and whether this intervention is a cost-effective strategy.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Adelaide Clinical Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Flats G5  Rooms 3 and 4
Flinders Drive
Flinders Medical Centre, Bedford Park SA 5042
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/07/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>273.14 - HREC/14/SAC/282 </hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/06/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Yogesh Sharma</name>
      <address>Department of General Medicine
Flinders Medical Centre
Flinders Drive
Bedford Park SA 5042</address>
      <phone>+61882046694</phone>
      <fax>+61882046255</fax>
      <email>Yogesh.Sharma@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Yogesh Sharma</name>
      <address>Department of General Medicine
Flinders Medical Centre
Flinders Drive
Bedford Park SA 5042</address>
      <phone>+61882046694</phone>
      <fax>+61882046255</fax>
      <email>Yogesh.Sharma@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Yogesh Sharma</name>
      <address>Department of General Medicine
Flinders Medical Centre
Flinders Drive
Bedford Park SA 5042</address>
      <phone>+61882046694</phone>
      <fax>+61882046255</fax>
      <email>Yogesh.Sharma@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>