<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336900">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/05/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/05/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000488909</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The role of Vitamin C in managing type 2 diabetes: Vitamin C, Thiazolidinediones and their combined effect on
Adiponectin</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>People with Type 2 diabetes currently treated with thiazolidinediones supplemented with Vitamin C and the combined effect on adiponectin as a therapeutic for metabolic disease.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Dose escalation of Vitamin C supplementation, twice daily oral tablets, (500, 1000, 1500 and 2000 mg) for two weeks at each dose with no washout period in between. Vitamin C supplementation will be taken in addition to participants' existing thiazolidinedione treatment which will continue as usual.</interventions>
    <comparator>None</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Increase in high molecular weight adiponectin assessed using a blood test and subsequent laboratory analysis of the sample.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the start of the trial, fortnightly after each increase in Vitamin C dosage and then a fortnight after the final Vitamin C dosage is complete.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Female or male participants between the ages of 18 and 70 with non insulin dependent type 2 diabetes under TZD treatment (either rosiglitazone 4  8 mg or piogitazone greater than or equal 30 mg) with or without metformin.
HbA1C level 7  8.5 %.
Participant on stable diabetic therapy for three months prior to the intervention.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>HbA1C level greater than 8.5 %
Participants must have a stable body weight (&lt; 5% selfreported weight loss/gain) within last 3 months prior to enrolment.
Participants taking iron supplements.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/05/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>18/11/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>10</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Princess Alexandra Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>199 Ipswich Road Woolloongabba, Brisbane, Queensland, 4102</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Queensland Department of Employment, Economic Development and Innovation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Queensland Government
PO Box 15168,  City East, Qld,  4002</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Queensland</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The University of Queensland
Brisbane QLD 4072 Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Thiazolidinediones (TZD) are a class of drug commonly prescribed to manage type 2 diabetes. While the exact
mechanism of action is unknown, efficacy of the drug is closely correlated with improved circulating concentration of
a protein, adiponectin, secreted by fat tissue. Adiponectin is decreased in many diseases states including type 2
diabetes. Adiponectin is secreted as multimers of different sizes, termed low molecular weight (LMW) and high
molecular weight (HMW), and while an increase in circulating adiponectin is beneficial, it is more specifically an
increase in the HMW multimers that is correlated with improvement in health. An improvement in adiponectin profile refers to an increase in the proportion of the multimers present as HMW and may also be concomitant with an increase in total adiponectin.

Previous studies have demonstrated that high dose Vitamin C alone can improve glucose control in obese and
diabetic patients. Researchers involved with the proposed research project have demonstrated that combining
Vitamin C with TZD treatment has a synergistic effect on adiponectin profile in vitro in a human adipose cell line.
Vitamin C alone improves adiponectin profile 1.7 fold, while improvements are 5 fold over baseline when in
combination with TZD. Combining the evidence from previous studies and these in vitro observations
demonstrates a potential for combining TZD with high dose Vitamin C to get an improved treatment for managing
type 2 diabetes.

Research Design and Methods: Patients will have a two week wash out period to control vitamin c levels, and then
two weekly intervals on escalating doses of oral vitamin C for 8 weeks (4 doses, 500 mg / day, 1000 mg / day, 1500
mg / day and 2000 mg / day). Each patient will serve as their own control, with assessment of total and HMW
adiponectin at the beginning and end of the trial and at dose escalation points in between as primary endpoints.
Other indicators of improvement in metabolic parameters will also be monitored.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Metro South Health Service District Human Research Ethics Committee (EC00167)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Centres for Health Research Level 2, Building 35
Princess Alexandra Hospital
Ispwich Road WOOLLOONGABBA QLD 4102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/04/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00167</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Associate Professor Anthony Russell</name>
      <address>Department of Diabetes and Endocrinology, Ground Floor
Building 1, Princess Alexandra Hospital
199 Ipswich Road
Woolloongabba QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3240 5914</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.russell@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Associate Professor Anthony Russell</name>
      <address>Department of Diabetes and Endocrinology, Ground Floor
Building 1, Princess Alexandra Hospital
199 Ipswich Road
Woolloongabba QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3240 5914</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.russell@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Felicity Rose</name>
      <address>Translational Research Institute
Level 4 37 Kent Street
Woolloongabba QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3443 7665</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>frose@mmri.mater.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Anthony Russell</name>
      <address>Department of Diabetes and Endocrinology, Ground Floor Building 1, Princess Alexandra Hospital 199 Ipswich Road Woolloongabba QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3240 5914 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.russell@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>