<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336875">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/05/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/05/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000538943</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Colorectal cancer screening and early detection in people with Chronic Kidney Disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A diagnostic test accuracy study for colorectal cancer screening using immunochemical faecal occult blood testing in a chronic kidney disease population</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1121-1269</utrn>
    <trialacronym>DETECT Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Bowel cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Kidney Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Bowel - Back passage (rectum) or large bowel (colon)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All eligible participants will receive an imunochemical faecal occult blood test (IFOBT) kit (EIKEN brand) containing the test and instructions, with additional explanation provided by study staff, as required. A sample is then collected from two separate bowel motions. All samples will be self-collected. 

All completed kits will be sent and processed in a designated central laboratory and analysed according to the companys standardised specifications. The results of this test can be positive, negative or inconclusive. All results will be sent via mail to the corresponding treating physicians, the participants and the research assistants at the Centre for Kidney Research. The screen is considered positive when one of the samples contains at least 50ng/ml of haemoglobin. Negative results are not followed up in the study but these patients are advised to continue with annual screening with their health practitioner. If the results are inconclusive, the participants will be contacted by phone and asked to repeat the test. 

Only participants with positive IFOBT findings will be referred for a diagnostic colonoscopy at a designated colonoscopic service. Study staff will track participants with positive IFOBT results and will ensure the referral process is scheduled effectively and efficiently for a colonoscopy. The participants will not be required to pay for the IFOBT kit or the diagnostic colonoscopy. Other clinical significant pathologies such as polyps, adenomas, vascular lesions will be documented and recorded. Wherever possible, they will be resected and sent for pathology. Depending upon the stage of initial diagnosis, further treatment may be required for participants with malignant polyps and cancers. All cancer diagnoses, including stage, histological types, treatment effect, will be reported to the National Bowel Screening Program Register, the Central Cancer Registry of New South Wales (located within the Cancer Institute of NSW) and the Australian and New Zealand Dialysis and Transplant Registry (ANZDATA). Study staff will ensure the treatment plans and follow-up are taking place efficiently and effectively. </interventions>
    <comparator>The reference standard should ideally be performed in all patients regardless of the screen test results and health status to avoid verification bias, but it would be medically and ethically unjustified to subject all patients (with and without positive screens) to receive the diagnostic colonoscopic procedure. Instead, all participants with positive screens, with or without a cancer, will be followed up clinically, with a phone-call for up to a period of 4 years. All negative FOBT screens will also be followed up clinically with a phone call, at the end of 2 and 4 years. For validation of such a procedure, we will also compare results of patients who had diagnostic colonoscopies and the standard diagnoses based upon clinical follow-up. To ensure adequate follow-up and accurate calculation of diagnostic test accuracies, we will compare our cancer records with that of the Central Cancer Registry of N.S.W. and the ANZDATA Registry. The ANZDATA Registry contains one of the largest and the most comprehensive databases of patients with renal replacement therapy in the world. The ANZDATA Registry collects all cancer records (stage, histological types and treatment) except for squamous and basal cell carcinomas of the skin. </comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prevalence of a positive screening result (defined as positive IFOBT with at least one of the two stool samples containing at least 50ng/ml of haemoglobin) in people with chronic kidney disease in stages 3-5, dialysis and kidney transplant populations using the immunochemical faecal occult blood test. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Five years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prevalence of colorectal cancer as determined with diagnostic colonoscopy, in people with chronic kidney disease in stages 3-5, dialysis and kidney transplant populations.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Five years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Test performance characteristics of immunochemical faecal occult blood screening, including: test specificity, positive predictive values and negative predictive value for colorectal cancers. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Five years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stage distribution and disease progression of screened detected colorectal cancers as determined by diagnostic colonoscopy. To ensure adequate follow-up and accurate calculation of diagnostic test accuracies, we will compare our cancer records with that of the Central Cancer Registry of N.S.W. and the ANZDATA Registry.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Five years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stage distribution and disease progression of interval cancers as determined by diagnostic colonoscopy. To ensure adequate follow-up and accurate calculation of diagnostic test accuracies, we will compare our cancer records with that of the Central Cancer Registry of N.S.W. and the ANZDATA Registry.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Five years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse outcomes from screening, diagnosis, and treatment of colorectal cancers, including bleeding, infection, perforations and anxiety related to positive test results. Clinical assessment and management of these will include blood tests and CT scans.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Five years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>* Australian citizens or permanent residents who are holders of Medicare cards and/or DVA gold cards
* Aged 35  74
* People with chronic kidney disease in stages 3  5 (defined as estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) of less than 60ml/min/1.73m^2)
* People with kidney alone or kidney and pancreas transplants 
* People on dialysis 
* Average risk for colorectal cancer (Average risk is defined as no personal history of colorectal cancer or adenomatous polyps, no family history of colorectal cancer in a first-degree relative and no history of inflammatory bowel disease)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>35</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>74</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>* Active gastrointestinal bleeding
* Previous gastrointestinal bleeding
* Previous colonoscopies in the past 2 years
* Current pregnancy
* A personal history of colorectal cancer or adenomatous polyps, a family history of colorectal cancer in a first-degree relative and a history of inflammatory bowel disease.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All patients with chronic kidney disease in stages 3-5, dialysis or transplant populations will be recruited from the Sydney West Area Health Service. All eligible patients from each of these area health services will be identified and the researchers will consent the patients, if necessary, with a health care interpreter. All eligible participants will receive an IFOBT kit containing the test and instructions, with additional explanation provided by study staff, as required. All participants with positive IFOBT findings will be referred to a diagnostic colonoscopy at a designated colonoscopic service. Study staff will track participants with positive IFOBT results and will ensure the referral process is scheduled effectively and efficiently with no more than four weeks waiting time for a colonoscopy.</concealment>
    <sequence>Not applicable</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>28/05/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>28/05/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>30/11/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>1700</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>1707</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>29/11/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2145</postcode>
    <postcode>2747</postcode>
    <postcode>2148</postcode>
    <postcode>2800</postcode>
    <postcode>2065</postcode>
    <postcode>2050</postcode>
    <postcode>2138 - Concord West</postcode>
    <postcode>2250 - Gosford</postcode>
    <postcode>2153 - Bella Vista</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Toronto</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Christchurch</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Germaine Wong</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Public Health
Edward Ford Building (A27)
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006 
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council - Screening and Test Evaluation Program (STEP) grant (691626)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Jeremy Chapman</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Director of Acute Interventional Service
Department of Renal Medicine
Westmead Hospital
Cn Hawkesbury and Darcy Roads
Westmead NSW 2145
Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to assess the health benefits, harms, and costs of early detection for colorectal cancer in people with chronic kidney disease.

Who is it for?
You can join this study if you are aged 35-74 years and have chronic kidney disease in stages 3-5, have had a kidney transplant, or are on dialysis. You must be an Australian citizen or permanent resident who holds a Medicare and/or DVA gold card. You should have no personal or family history of colorectal cancer, no previous or current gastro-intestinal bleeding, no inflammatory bowel disease, and have not had a colonoscopy within the last two years.

Trial details
In this study, all participants will receive a home testing kit, called the immunochemical faecal occult blood test (IFOBT) kit. This will contain instructions, and additional explanation will be provided by study staff as required. The test will require participants to collect a sample from two of their separate bowel motions. The completed test kits will then be sent and processed in a laboratory to determine whether the result is negative, positive, or inconclusive. Participants with positive findings will be referred for a diagnostic colonoscopy. All diagnoses are recorded and communicated to participants. All participants will be followed up for a period of four years. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.kidney-research.org</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney West Area Health Service Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Westmead Hospital
PO Box 533
Wentworthville NSW 2145</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/03/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC2010/2/4.5(3101)AU RED HREC/10/WMEAD/13</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/02/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>NSW Population &amp; Health Services Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 9, 8 Central Avenue, Australian Technology Park, Eveleigh NSW 2015
PO Box 41, Alexandria, NSW 1435</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/05/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/13/CIPHS/13</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Dr Germaine Wong</name>
      <address>University of Sydney
School of Public Health
Edward Ford Building (A27)
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61298451473</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>germaine.wong@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Dr Germaine Wong</name>
      <address>University of Sydney
School of Public Health
Edward Ford Building (A27)
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61298451473</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>germaine.wong@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Dr Germaine Wong</name>
      <address>University of Sydney
School of Public Health
Edward Ford Building (A27)
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61298451473</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>germaine.wong@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Germaine Wong</name>
      <address>University of Sydney School of Public Health Edward Ford Building (A27) The University of Sydney NSW 2006 Australia </address>
      <phone>+61298451473</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>germaine.wong@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>