<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83177">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/09/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/11/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000557336</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of lens wear on bacterial adhesion to lens surfaces</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A prospective, randomised, open label, parallel group, cross-over design clinical trial to investigate protein and lipid deposition that mediate bacterial adhesion on the surface of silicone hydrogel contact lenses with use of different lens care solutions during daily and extended wear.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Effect of lens wear on bacterial adhesion to lens surfaces</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Protein and lipid deposition on the surface of silicone hydrogel lenses during daily wear and extended wear of contact lenses</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal eye development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Lens care solution crossover during 2 months daily wear (i.e. wear lenses during the day and remove lenses prior to sleep) of silicone hydrogel lenses. 1 month extended wear (continuous wear during the day and night) of silicone hydrogel lenses. There is a 1 calender day washout between treatments. At start of daily wear, each group will be randomly assigned to use either Optifree-Replenish (Alcon, USA) or Menicare Soft (Menicon, Japan) lens care solution. After one month daily wear, subjects will be dispensed with the alternate lens care solution. Subjects will continue with this solution for the duration of the trial (i.e. one further month of daily lens wear and 1 month of extended lens wear).</interventions>
    <comparator>Active control - crossover study</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To identify the proteins and lipids that deposit on a lens surface and to determine which proteins and lipids mediate bacterial adhesion to the lens surface. Extracted proteins to be separated by nano-Liquid Chromatography (LC) and Mass Spectrometry (MS). Concentration of each protein determined by Enzyme-Linked ImmunoSorbent Assay (ELISA). Extracted lipids to be separated by Thin Layer Chromatography (TLC) and amounts of lipids measured using standard curves on TLC plates.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 1 month, 2 months and 3 months from the baseline visit</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>N/A</outcome>
      <timepoint>N/A</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Be able to read and comprehend English and give informed consent as demonstrated by signing a record of informed consent;
Be at least 18 years old;
Be willing to comply with the wearing and clinical trial visit schedule as directed by the Investigator;
Have ocular health findings considered to be 'normal' and which would not prevent the participant from safely wearing contact lenses; 
Have experienced an ocular adverse event that is not considered to be severe by the Investigator (Investigator discretion) or that is temporary in nature;
Is correctable to at least 6/12 (20/40) or better in each eye with contact lenses;
Be experienced or may be inexperienced at wearing contact lenses</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pre-existing ocular irritation, injury or condition that would preclude contact lens fitting and safe wearing of contact lenses;
any systemic disease that adversely affects ocular health; active corneal infection or any active ocular disease that would affect wearing of contact lenses;
previously experienced a severe contact lens related adverse event (Investigator discretion), that is likely to affect their contact lens wear experience or present a significant safety risk during the trial;
any prescribed systemic medication or topical medications which may alter normal ocular findings/are known to affect a participants ocular health/physiology or contact lens performance either in an adverse or beneficial manner;
previous corneal refractive surgery;
contraindications to contact lens wear;
currently enrolled in another clinical trial;
participation in a clinical trial within the previous 2 weeks;pregnant or lactating women who are not able to complete the study (Investigator discretion).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be randomly assigned to one of two different lens types, followed by a within group design (solution allocation). Allocation will be concealed and done by central randomisation by computer.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation plan will be generated by computer</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/10/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Institute for Eye Research</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 5, North Wing, Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14, Barker St
Kensington NSW 2052
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Institute for Eye Research</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 5, North Wing, Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14, Barker St
Kensington NSW 2052
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To identify the proteins and lipids that deposit on a lens surface and to determine which proteins and lipids mediate bacterial adhesion to the lens surface.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Vision Cooperative Research Centre and Institute for Eye Research Human Ethics Committee (VIHEC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 4, Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14 Barker St
University of New South Wales (UNSW), Kensington NSW 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/07/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>08/06</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/06/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Mark Willcox</name>
      <address>Institute for Eye Research
Level 4, Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14 Barker St
University of New South Wales (UNSW), Kensington NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93857516</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93857401</fax>
      <email>m.willcox@ier.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mr Jerome Ozkan</name>
      <address>Institute for Eye Research
Level 5, Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14 Barker St
University of New South Wales (UNSW), Kensington NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93857516</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93857401</fax>
      <email>j.ozkan@ier.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mr Jerome Ozkan</name>
      <address>Institute for Eye Research
Level 5, Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14 Barker St
University of New South Wales (UNSW), Kensington NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93857516</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93857401</fax>
      <email>j.ozkan@ier.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>