<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83245">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/07/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/08/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000685213</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The acute effects of moderate intensity aerobic, resistance and combination exercise on components of the metabolic syndrome in overweight and obese individuals.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Overweight and obese individuals and the acute effects of moderate intensity aerobic, resistance and combination exercise on components of the metabolic syndrome.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Metabolic syndrome risk factors in overweight and obese individuals</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study was a randomized cross-over design examining the postprandial effects of different types of exercise in the evening prior to a breakfast meal. Subjects were randomized on four occasions, each one-week apart, to each intervention, either no exercise (control), 30 minutes of aerobic exercise on a treadmill, 30 minutes of resistance exercise (leg press, leg curl, leg extension, bench press, rear deltoid row) or a combination of 15 minutes of aerobic exercise and 15 minutes of resistance exercise. A postprandial response was measured following the breakfast meal.</interventions>
    <comparator>No exercise</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood lipids and lipoprotein status as well as glucose and insulin sensitivity the day after the exercise intervention.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples taken at baseline, then 30 mins, 1 hr, 2.5 hrs, 4 hrs, 5 hrs, 6 hrs and 8 hrs after a standard meal.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Endothelial function measured via Sphygmocor pulse wave analysis (PWA).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1 hr, 2 hrs, 3 hrs, 4 hrs, 6 hrs and 8 hrs</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resting energy expenditure and fat oxidation measured via indirect open-circuit calorimetry.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 30 mins, 1.5 hrs, 2.5 hrs, 3.5 hrs and 5.5 hrs</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Overweight or moderately obese postmenopausal women and men who were sedentary.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>67</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Diabetes mellitus, pre-existing heart conditions, pregnant or lactating, smokers, gastrointestinal tract surgery, any other major illness.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subjects were allocated to the randomly generated sequence of control, aerobic, resistance or combination exercise in the order they were recruited.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer program generated randomization plan.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/11/2004</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>16</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Curtin University of Technology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth WA 6845</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The metabolic syndrome (MS) is a term used to describe the clustering of metabolic risk factors, such as abdominal obesity, insulin resistance, dyslipidaemia and elevated blood pressure. It is estimated that 20-25% of the worlds adult population have the metabolic syndrome. Having the risk factors associated with the MS leads to an increased risk of developing cardiovascular disease (CVD) and such individuals are also five times more likely to develop Type 2 diabetes. The root causes of the MS are described as being a combination of being overweight or obese, physical inactivity and genetic factors. Cardiovascular disease is a major cause of death in Australia and most industrialized countries. Atherosclerosis is the main cause of CVD. The initiation of atherosclerosis is the accumulation of lipid deposited by circulating lipoproteins within the arterial wall. Postprandial lipaemia (after meal blood lipid appearance) induced by eating a fatty meal increases circulating levels of lipid. Increased postprandial lipid levels have the potential to deposit into the arterial wall and develop into an atherosclerotic lesion. However, exercise decreases postprandial lipaemia as an acute (short-term) effect after a single bout. The aim of this study was to investigate whether a single 30-minute bout of resistance, aerobic or combined exercise at moderate intensity would decrease postprandial lipaemia, glucose and insulin levels of a high fat meal consumed 14 hours after the exercise bout, as well as increase resting energy expenditure and increase fat oxidation in overweight and obese individuals compared to no exercise. We also compared the effects of the different exercise modalities.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin University Ethics Commitee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>GPO Box U1987 Perth WA 6845</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/07/2004</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HR 75/2004</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Assoc Prof Sebely Pal</name>
      <address>Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 4755</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.pal@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Assoc Prof Sebely Pal</name>
      <address>Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 4755</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.pal@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Suleen Ho</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>suleen.ho@postgrad.curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>