<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335925">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/09/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/09/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000746033</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Determining the resistant starch content of new barley varieties prepared as muffin bars in volunteers with ileostomy.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Determing the resistant starch content of new barley varieties prepared as muffin bars in volunteers with ileostomy.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>no secondary ID</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Development of an assay that predicts resistant starch in new cereals by relating in vitro and in vivo determinations.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>There are four treatments (three test foods and one control) to be consumed by participants as well as the specified breakfast each day on four consecutive days.
Throughout the trial period (four consecutive days) participants consume a basal diet which contains specially selected foods known to be low in resistant starch content. Since the participants are required to consume the same restricted basal diet for four consecutive days all foods are provided by the Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation (CSIRO). The participants are free to select their basal diet from a list of suitable foods provided by CSIRO and the these foods are required to be eaten at the same times each day of the four day trial period.
On top of these basal diets the participants will consume a muffin bar (one bar for each day and ~50g per bar) prepared from each of the three test flours under investigation. One day will be a control day in which the participants will consume only the basal diet (no muffin bar).
The study is a randomised crossover design where each participant consumes each of the test muffin bars and has a control day in the four day trial period. A test day spans a 24 hr period from the consumption of breakfast at 7.30 am one day to the final ileal digesta collection taken at ~7am the following day. 
On the first day of the study the participants empty their stomal bags at 7 am (this sample is discarded) and then collect and freeze digesta samples every 2 hrs until 11pm. Their final collection for day 1 is at 7 am on day 2. this pattern of digesta collection continues until the final collection at 7 am on day 5 at which point the trial is complete. There are 9 digesta samples in each test period and they are frozen immediately after collection and remain frozen until analysed.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control is a low starch diet only with very little resistant starch(&lt; 0.5g /day. This is made possible by participants selecting their daily food from a list of foods that are known to contain minimal resistant starch and CSIRO providing all the foods for the trial period to each participant.
As this is a crossover designed study each participant acts as their own control</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determination of the starch in the various muffin bars (and therefore the test flours) that is resistant to digestion.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Ileal samples collected at 7am on day 1 and there after at 2 hr intervals until 11 pm at night. This collection pattern is repeated on each of the 4 days in the trial period ie a total of 9 collections for each day from Monday 7 am to Friday 7 am.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>comparison of the in vivo resistant starch determination with the in vitro resistant starch (RS) determination on the same food products</outcome>
      <timepoint>Ileal samples collected at 7am on day 1 and there after at 2 hr intervals until 11 pm at night. This collection pattern is repeated on each of the 4 days in the trial period ie a total of 9 collections for each day from Monday 7 am to Friday 7 am.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>conventional and well-functioning permanent ileostomy</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Use of any form of drug therapy or medication or supplements that may interfere with bowel function eg antibiotics.
Definite or suspected personal history or family history of adverse events or intolerance of plant-based foods being tested in this study
persons considered by the investigator to be unwilling, unlikely or unable to comprehend or comply with the study protocol and restrictions 
Persons unwilling or unable to collect ileal effluent as required
Participants taking any supplements which could interfere with study parameters</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subject were enrolled from a pool of volunteers who have well functioning, permanent ileostomy and who have expressed an interest on participating in such studies on   presious occasions.</concealment>
    <sequence>Treatments for each day are prepared by drawing each of the four test foods from a box for each volunteer.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Bio-availability</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>13/09/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>8</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>National Research Flagship- Cereal and metabolic health stream</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>CSIRO Food and Nutritional Sciences
PO Box 10041
BC Adelaide
SA 5000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Food Futures National Research Flagship- Cereal and metabolic health stream</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>CSIRO Food and Nutritional Sciences
PO Box 10041
BC Adelaide
SA 5000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to determine the RS content of finely milled new varieties of barley (in muffin bars) using ileostomy participants.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>CSIRO Food and Nutritional Sciences Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 10041
Adelaide BC
SA 5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/04/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Tony Bird</name>
      <address>CSIRO Food and Nutritional Sciences
PO Box 10041
Adelaide BC
SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8303 8902</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tony.bird@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Tony Bird</name>
      <address>CSIRO Food and Nutritional Sciences
PO Box 10041
Adelaide BC
SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8303 8902</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tony.bird@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jenny McInerney</name>
      <address>CSIRO Food and Nutritional Sciences
PO Box 10041
Adelaide BC
SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8303 8838</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jenny.mcinerney@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>