<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308260">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/07/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/07/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000630213</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial of enhanced cognitive therapy and family education for youth depression, anxiety, and substance abuse</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial of enhanced cognitive therapy and family education for youth depression, anxiety, and substance abuse</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>DFO</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Behavioural Exchange Systems Training (BEST) Plus - Parents receive 16 hours of parent sessions in a group with other families. Siblings are invited to join the group for the final 4 sessions of BEST Plus. The BEST Plus program will run for 8 weeks in total. The program will be administered as 1 x 2hr session per week. The BEST Plus intervention will be administered by 2 clinical facilitators: either clinical masters students or clinical staff from youth services at JIGSAW or Drummond Street Relationships Center. All facilitators will receive specialist training and supervision in the BEST Plus model.
Self Help for Alcohol/Other Drug Use and Depression for Young people (SHADEY)- The young person receives 10 individual sessions of a Cognitive Behavioural Therapy (CBT) based intervention. The program will run for a duration of 10 weeks. The SHADEY program will be administered in 1 x 90 minute sessions per week. The SHADEY program will be administered by trained clinical masters students or clinical staff from youth services at JIGSAW or Drummond Street Relationships Center. All SHADEY clinicians will receive specialist training and supervision in the SHADEY model.
Combined SHADEY and BEST Plus- Following the BEST intervention for the family, the young person is invited to complete the SHADEY intervention. The total duration of the combined condition is 18 weeks. The parents receive 8 x 2hr, weekly sessions, and siblings are invited to join their parents for the final 4 x 2hr sessions. One week following the conclusion of the BEST Plus program the young person will be invited to complete 10 x 1.5hr weekly sessions. This order of administration cannot be reversed.</interventions>
    <comparator>3 treatments compared in Randomized Controlled Trial (RCT)
- BEST Plus
- SHADEY
- SHADEY and BEST Plus
In addition, outcomes for participants in the RCT will be compared with others who: 
- Refuse to participate (receive treatment as usual)
- Are on a wait list for treatment
however these conditions are not randomly assigned.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Revised Hamilton Depression Rating Scale score</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, completion of intervention and 6 months after intervention completion by young person</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Beck Scale for Suicidal Ideation score</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, completion of intervention and 6 months after intervention completion by young person</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Youth Self Report/Adult Self Report score. Both include scales for adaptive functioning, empirically based syndromes, substance use, Internalizing, Externalizing, and Total Problems. In addition, both profiles feature American Psychiatric Association Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM-IV-TR)-oriented scales, for Depressive Problems; Anxiety Problems and other diagnostic categories.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post intervention and 6 month follow up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Parenting Relationship Questionnaire score</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, completion of intervention and 6 months after intervention completion by parent</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Millon Clinical Multiaxial Inventory-III (MCMI-III) scores. The MCMI-III assesses Axis I (clinical syndromes e.g. depressive and anxious disorders) and Axis II (e.g. personality disorder) symptoms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, completion of intervention and 6 months after intervention completion by parent</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Mean Adolescent Substance Abuse Subtle Screening Inventory score</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, completion of intervention and 6 months after intervention completion by young person.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Working Alliance Inventory (WAI) score. The WAI gives an overall indication of the quality of the therapeutic working relationship between therapist and client.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Completed twice, three weeks and eight weeks from the start of the intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Using the Youth Self Report/Adult Self Report
1) a score in the clinical or subclinical range for Anxiety and/or Depression symptoms
2) a score in the clinical or subclinical range for Substance Misuse
Have a parent or carer willing to enter the evaluation
Parent/Carer and Youth must be able to speak and understand English (must not require an interpreter)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>12</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>25</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Has an intellectual disability or autism
Has parent/s who do not wish to participate
Young person or parent has a severe mental illness requiring inpatient treatment
There is insufficient address for follow-up or unwillingness to return for follow-up</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation involves contacting the holder of the allocation schedule (research fellow) who is “off-site” at central administration site.</concealment>
    <sequence>Subjects will be allocated through simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software. This will be generated by a statistician in the School of Psychology, who is external to the research team.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>13/07/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>20/10/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>16/01/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>102</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>3000</postcode>
    <postcode>3220</postcode>
    <postcode>3053</postcode>
    <postcode>3121</postcode>
    <postcode>3125</postcode>
    <postcode>3214</postcode>
    <postcode>3011</postcode>
    <postcode>3030</postcode>
    <postcode>3850</postcode>
    <postcode>3217</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Associate Professor Andrew Lewis</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Psychology Deakin University 
Waterfront campus, Level 3, DCP Building, 
27 Brougham Street, Geelong, VIC, 3217</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Beyond Blue (independent not for profit organisation)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 6100
Hawthorn West VIC 3122</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor John Toumbourou</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Psychology Deakin University 
Waterfront campus, Level 3, DCP Building, 
27 Brougham Street, Geelong, VIC, 3217</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Associate Professor Lina Ricciardelli</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Psychology Deakin University 
221 Burwood Highway
Burwood VIC 3125</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Tess Knight</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Psychology Deakin University 
221 Burwood Highway
Burwood VIC 3125</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Melissa O'Shea</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Swanston Centre
Corner Swanston &amp; Myers Streets
Geelong VIC 3220</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Melanie Bertino</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Psychology Deakin University 
Waterfront campus, Level 3, DCP Building, 
27 Brougham Street, Geelong, VIC, 3217</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The trial is aimed at families where a young person aged 16-25 has mental health (depression / anxiety) and/or substance use problems. We intend to test the relative benefits for reducing parent and youth depressive symptoms, by comparing two psychological treatments. These include a family substance abuse education program (BEST), and a one-on-one youth intervention (SHADEY). A third group of families will receive both of these treatments, to determine if they are more effective when they are combined. We predict that all treatments will produce reductions in: (1) the youth self-reported rate of depressive and anxiety symptoms; (2) the level of youth substance use and risk of substance abuse; and (3) that the combined therapy will be more effective than either in isolation. We further predict (4) that the family program will result in greater reductions in parent and sibling mental health symptoms, and reduced youth substance use, than the one-on-one cognitive therapy (SHADEY), while (5) the SHADEY cognitive therapy will produce greater reductions in youth depressive symptoms.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Lewis, A.J., Bertino, M.D., Robertson, N., Knight, T., &amp; Toumbourou, J.W. (2012). Consumer feedback following participation in a family-based intervention for youth mental health. Depression research and treatment, Open Access Online Special Issue Article ID 235646, 8 pages, 2012. doi:10.1155/2012/235646.

Bertino, M.D., Richens, K., Knight, T., Toumbourou, J.W., Ricciardelli, T. &amp; Lewis, A.J., (2013). Reducing parental anxiety using a family based intervention for youth mental health: A randomized controlled trial. Open Journal of Psychiatry, Special Issue on Anxiety Research, Publication Date: February 2013. doi: 10.4236/ojpsych.2013.31A013

Bertino, M.D., Connell, G. &amp; Lewis, A.J. (2012). The association between parental personality patterns and internalising and externalising behaviour problems in children and adolescents. Clinical Psychologist, 16 (3), 110-117.

Lewis, A., Bertino, M.D., Knight, T., Ricciardelli, L., Shand, L., &amp; Toumbourou, J. (under review). Parent mental health impacts of family based therapy for adolescent mental health: The Deakin Family Options randomized controlled trial. Journal of Family Psychology.

Bertino, M., Lewis, A., Toumbourou, J., Ricciardelli, L., &amp; Knight, T. Family therapy and cognitive-behavioral therapy for youth with depression, anxiety and substance disorders. In V. Mrowinski, M. Kyrios and N. Voudouris (Eds), Abstracts of the 27th International Congress of Applied Psychology. Paper presented at ICAP Symposium, Melbourne, Convention Centre, 11-16 July 2010 (pp 232 -233). Retrieved 8 October 2010, from http://icap2010.eproceedings.com.au/icap2010.pdf

Danaher, J., Lewis, A., Toumbourou, J., Ricciardelli, L., Knight, T., &amp; Bertino, M. Prevention and Early Intervention Work with Australian Families. Presented at the University of Utah First International Conference on Parenting and Family Skills, Bangkok, Thailand December 17 and 18 2010. 

</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Deakin University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Ethics Office, Research Services Division, Deakin University, 221 Burwood Hwy, Burwood VIC 3125</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/06/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC 205-2008</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Barwon Health Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Barwon HREC, Kitchener House, 285 Ryrie Street, Geelong, VIC, 3220</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/02/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>09/42</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>8/05/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Associate Professor Andrew Lewis</name>
      <address>School of Psychology, Deakin University, 221 Burwood Highway Burwood VIC 3125</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9244 6774</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Andrew.lewis@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Associate Professor Andrew Lewis</name>
      <address>School of Psychology, Deakin University, 221 Burwood Highway Burwood VIC 3125</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9244 6774</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Andrew.lewis@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Associate Professor Andrew Lewis</name>
      <address>School of Psychology, Deakin University 
Waterfront campus, Level 3, DCP Building, 
27 Brougham Street, Geelong, VIC, 3217.</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9244 6774</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 5227 8621</fax>
      <email>Andrew.lewis@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Andrew Lewis</name>
      <address>School of Psychology, Deakin University, 221 Burwood Highway Burwood VIC 3125</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9244 6774</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andrew.lewis@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>