<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362609">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/06/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/06/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000652875</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Study of the Drug BTD-001 in Young Adults and Adolescents with Down Syndrome</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase IB, Double-blind, Randomized, Placebo-Controlled, Parallel Group Study of the Safety, Tolerability, Preliminary Efficacy and Pharmacodynamics of BTD-001 in Young Adults and Adolescents with Down Syndrome</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>The COMPOSE Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>BTD-001 DS102</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Down syndrome</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human genetics and inherited disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Down's syndrome</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants (13 to 35 yrs in age) will be enrolled. Following screening, a visit prior to first dose will establish baseline measurements of cognitive function, adaptive behaviour scoring and evoked response measurements. Eligible participants will be randomised to one of the following treatments: Treatment A - 50mg BTD-001 taken orally twice daily, as oral solution. Treatment B - 100mg BTD-001 taken orally twice daily, as oral solution. Treatment C - Placebo taken orally twice daily, as oral solution All study treatments will be made up as a flavoured drink solution. Study drug will be given for 12 weeks. </interventions>
    <comparator>Sterile purified water will be used as placebo made up as a flavoured drink and taken as oral solution.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and tolerability of BTD-001 twice daily oral as assessed by: physical and neurological examinations; laboratory safety tests; ECG; vital signs; adverse event collection. Adverse events are any untoward medical occurrences in study participants administered study treatment. 
Based on animal studies and the experience of other people who have received the active ingredient in BTD-001, side effects that may occur include feelings of anxiety and difficulty with sleeping. At very high doses, seizures (fits) and gastrointestinal effects (nausea and vomiting) have been reported to occur. Please note that these side effects have occurred at doses 10-20 times greater than those being tested in this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 2 weeks, 4 weeks, 8 weeks, 12 weeks and 16 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive, and behavioural/functional effects of BTD-001 in persons with Down syndrome as assessed by psychometric and functional measures. Psychometric measures include standardise tests assessments for functional and adaptative behavior and language. These include: Vineland adaptive behavior scale (VABS-II), Behavior rating inventory of executive function (BRIEF), and Clinical Evaluation of Language Functions (CELF4). Cognitive test assessments will be performed using a computer based testing system [CANTAB(Registered Trademark)].  </outcome>
      <timepoint>At 4 weeks, 12 weeks, 16 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Effects of BTD-001 on auditory event related potentials (ERP) in persons with Down syndrome. Auditory ERP  will be assessed by electroencephalography (EEG).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 4 weeks, 12 weeks, 16 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Males and females, age 1335 years with Down syndrome 2. Body weight greater than 40 kg AND BMI less than 40.0 kg/m2 3. Ability to cooperate and complete required tests and procedures. 4. Capable of undergoing the cognitive test battery and evoked response potential testing. 5. Negative pregnancy test AND non-lactating (females only) 6. If sexually active and female, the person with DS must be surgically sterile OR using reliable contraception 7. Laboratory findings, vital signs and ECG within normal limits or any abnormalities judged clinically not significant 8. Stable medical condition For Parents/Guardians 1. Parents or guardians of the person with DS must understand the study, give written and dated informed consent/assent, and successfully complete behavioural assessment interviews. 2. Parent or guardian agree to accompany the subject to all visits, be capable of supervising and reporting study drug use and adequately reporting the subjects functional status. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>13</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>35</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Current use of anti-epileptics, focal seizure disorder, syncope, unexplained loss of consciousness at any time OR seizure in the past 3 years.
2. History of or concurrent neurological disorders interfering with cognition.
3. History or  diagnosis of clinically significant psychiatric or neurological disease.  
4. Neuroleptic agent, bilobalide-containing product OR benzodiazepine use in last 4 weeks
5. Significant endocrine abnormality
6. Subjects with hypothyroidism are excluded unless they have received a stable dose of medication. 
7. Significant hepatic impairment 
8. Significant renal impairment 
9. History of porphyria
10. History of leukemia or other malignancy  
11. Participation in a clinical drug trial within 4 weeks 
12. Severe sleep apnea or excess daytime sleepiness
13. Recent or anticipated use of prohibited medications
14. Have any other condition which, in the Investigators opinion, would put the person with Down syndrome at risk by participating in this study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients and their carers who consent to take part in the study will be allocated a unique subject number. After screening, eligible patients who meet the inclusion and exclusion criteria will be randomised to 1 of 3 blinded treatments, 

An automated system will administer the randomization process and provide the Investigator codes used to assign study drug packaging to subjects.</concealment>
    <sequence>An automated system will administer the randomization process and provide the Investigator codes used to assign study drug packaging to subjects.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/08/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>3/08/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>29/08/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>27/01/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>90</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>88</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3168 - Notting Hill</postcode>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>6008 - Subiaco</postcode>
    <postcode>2522 - University Of Wollongong</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Broadway Nedlands</postcode>
    <postcode>7250 - Launceston</postcode>
    <postcode>4215 - Southport</postcode>
    <postcode>5034 - Clarence Park</postcode>
    <postcode>3122 - Hawthorn</postcode>
    <postcode>4101 - South Brisbane</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Novotech (Australia) Pty Limited</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 3, 235 Pyrmont Street
Pyrmont NSW 2009</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Balance Therapeutics, Pty Ltd.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Balance Therapeutics, Pty Ltd 2/1518 Nepean Highway, Mount Eliza VIC 3930 Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>BTD-001, has been used for several decades around the world as a treatment for dementia, a respiratory stimulant and as an ingredient of a cough medication. Studies in a mouse model of Down syndrome (DS) (Ts65Dn transgenic mouse) have demonstrated that chronic administration of the product improved cognition on a number of behavioural assessments. These improvements were sustained months after discontinuation of drug administration, indicating that BTD-001 may cause long-lasting synaptic changes supporting improved cognition. These data indicate that BTD-001, may improve function and cognition in persons with DS and has the potential to improve educational and quality of life outcomes for this population.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>1st floor, Building 3e, Monash Research Office, Clayton Campus, Monash University, Wellington Road, Clayton, VIC 3800</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/03/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CF11/3234 - 2011001763</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Rhoshel Lenroot</name>
      <address>Neuroscience Research Australia
Barker Street
Randwick, NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9399 1089</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.lenroot@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Sasita Sophia</name>
      <address>Novotech (Australia) Pty Ltd
Level 3, 235 Pyrmont St
Pyrmont, NSW 2009</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8569 1400</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 8569 1498</fax>
      <email>Sasita.sophia@novotech-cro.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Annette Madrid, MD</name>
      <address>1250 Bayhill Drive
San Bruno, CA 94066</address>
      <phone>+1650 741 9100</phone>
      <fax>+1650 741 9104</fax>
      <email>annette.madrid@balance-therapeutics.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Rhoshel Lenroot</name>
      <address>Neuroscience Research Australia
Barker Street
Randwick, NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9399 1089</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.lenroot@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>