<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367299">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/10/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/11/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001160628</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pregnancy Outcomes after Pre-pregnancy weight loss in obese women (POP Study)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Does substantial pre-conception weight loss, achieved using a 12-week program of a Very Low Energy Diet, improve pregnancy outcomes compared to modest weight loss achieved using a diet and exercise program in obese women?   </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>POP Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known </secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Pre-pregnancy weight loss</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fetal medicine and complications of pregnancy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>12 week program which consists of:

1) Optifast meal replacement for 2 meals per day. The third meal consisting of a serve of protein (meat, chicken, egg, tofu approximately the size of the palm of the hand), 2 cups of non-starch vegetables and a salad dressed with oil. Patients will meet with a dietician at the start of the study for 30 minutes to discuss implementation of the diet. They will then prepare meals themselves. Participants will be seen every 2 weeks during the intervention phase. Blood pressure, weight, waist circumference and hip circumference will be measured. 

2)Exercise according to national guidelines. Patients will be asked to complete the 'Australia Active Survey' prior to commencing the study. They will then be provided with an information booklet "Australia's Physical Activity and Sedentary Behaviour Guidelines for Adults". These guidelines recommend accumulating 150 to 300 minutes (2 ½ to 5 hours) of moderate intensity physical activity or 75 to 150 minutes (1 ¼ to 2 ½ hours) of vigorous intensity physical activity, or an equivalent combination of both moderate and vigorous activities each week.  Subjects will be provided with a Pedometer (Yamax 700S). Daily step count will be recorded for 7 consecutive days (week 2 of study). This is for the purposes of ensuring there is not a significant difference in activity level between our two study groups. 

3) Pre-pregnancy vitamin supplement including high dose folate. Folate 5mg orally, by mouth daily is recommended in accordance with the RANZCOG 'Obesity in Pregnancy' guidelines. In addition, participants will be asked to take a multi-vitamin suitable for a woman planning pregnancy (eg. Elevit).

Blood tests will be performed at the start and end of the intervention period. A food diary will be performed to ensure compliance with the diet. However, the amount of weight on on Optifast should be approximately 10-15% of body weight in 12 weeks based on the results of previous trials. 

*Optifast products vary slightly but an example of the components of an Optifast product are listed below. Optifast products include soups, bars, desserts, shakes. 

INGREDIENTS
Fructose glucose syrup (sugar beet), Soy crisp (Soy protein isolate, tapioca starch, salt), Milk chocolate (17%) [Sugar, Cocoa solids (6.5%), whole Milk powder, Emulsifier (Soy lecithin), Flavour], Soy nuts, Soy protein isolate, Minerals (Tripotassium citrate, Calcium phosphate, Sodium phosphate, Magnesium phosphate, Trisodium citrate, Magnesium carbonate, Ferric pyrophosphate, Potassium iodate, Zinc oxide, Sodium selenate, Copper sulphate, Manganese sulphate), Inulin, Fruit preparation [ Sugar, Raspberry (0.6%), Apple puree (0.4%),Raspberry (0.6%) and Cherry (0.2%) juice concentrate, Fructose syrup, Lactose (9%) (Milk), Vegetable fat, Flavour, Vegetable gum (440), Food acid (330)], Vegetable oil (Rapeseed), Vitamins (Ascorbic acid, Vitamin E acetate, Nicotinamide, Biotin, Vitamin A acetate, Calcium pantothenate, Folic acid, Cholecalciferol, Pyridoxine, Riboflavin, Thiamin, Cyanocobalamin), Food acid (330), Flavour, Emulsifier (Soy lecithin). Contains Milk and Soy. Made on equipment that also processes products containing tree nuts, peanuts and oats.

NUTRITIONAL INFORMATION
Servings per package	6
Serving size	60g

Unit of measure	Quantity per serve
Energy	kJ	950
Cal	228
Protein	g	18.3
Fat, total	g	6.9
- Saturated fat	g	2.6
Carbohydrates	g	20.8
- Sugar	g	19.3
Dietary fibre	g	4.5

VITAMINS
Thiamin	mg	0.69
Riboflavin	mg	1.02
Niacin	mgNE	9.6
Pantothenic acid	mg	1.9
Vit B6	mg	1
Biotin	microgram	67
Folic Acid	microgram	126
Vit C	mg	63
Vit E	mgTE	6

MINERALS
Sodium	mg	390
Calcium	mg	270
Copper	mg	0.9
Iodine	microgram	66
Iron	mg	9.1
Magnesium	mg	150
Manganese	mg	0.70
Phosphorus	mg	588
Selenium	microgram	36
Zinc	mg	5.4
Potassium	mg	732
</interventions>
    <comparator>12 week program based on the best practice care for an obese woman planning pregnancy which consists of :-

1) Diet according to the Australian Guide to Healthy Eating with a goal of weight loss. A 24 hour food recall will be performed with a dietician. The calorie content will then be calculated and a meal plan designed with the current calorie content minuss 500 calories per day. A food diary will then be completed and weight measured to ensure weight loss is achieved. Participants will be seen fortnightly during the intervention period. Blood pressure, weight, waist circumference and hip circumference will be measured. 

2) Exercise according to national guidelines. Patients will be asked to complete the 'Australia Active Survey' prior to commencing the study. They will then be provided with an information booklet "Australia's Physical Activity and Sedentary Behaviour Guidelines for Adults". These guidelines recommend accumulating 150 to 300 minutes (2 ½ to 5 hours) of moderate intensity physical activity or 75 to 150 minutes (1 ¼ to 2 ½ hours) of vigorous intensity physical activity, or an equivalent combination of both moderate and vigorous activities, each week. Subjects will be provided with a Pedometer (Yamax 700S). Daily step count will be recorded for 7 consecutive days (week 2 of study). This is for the purposes of ensuring there is not a significant difference in activity level between our two study groups. 

3) Pre-pregnancy vitamin supplement including high dose folate. Folate 5mg orally, by mouth daily is recommended in accordance with the RANZCOG 'Obesity in Pregnancy' guidelines. In addition, participants will be asked to take a multi-vitamin suitable for a woman planning pregnancy (eg. Elevit).

Blood tests will be performed at the start and end of the intervention period. A food diary will be performed to ensure compliance with the diet as outlined by dietician.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In obese (BMI &gt;30kg/m2) non-diabetic women, does substantial pre-conception weight loss (10-15% body weight) result in a =/&gt;10% reduction in maternal fasting plasma glucose (in mmol/L) at 26-28 weeks gestation when compared with maternal fasting plasma glucose (in mmol/L)from women who achieve modest pre-conception body weight (&lt;3% body weight). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Fasting maternal glucose at 26-28 weeks gestation will be used as the primary outcome. Therefore, the primary outcome timepoint will be 26-28 weeks gestation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In obese women (BMI &gt;30kg/m2), does substantial pre-conception weight loss (10-15% body weight) when compared with modest pre-conception weight loss (&lt;3% body weight) result in a reduction in the composite end-point of maternal gestational diabetes (IADPSG definition), large-for-gestational age, macrosomia, pre-eclampsia, intra-uterine growth restriction (IUGR), delivery prior to 37 weeks, caesarean section, shoulder dystocia/birth injury, neonatal hypoglycaemia, neonatal hyperbilirubinemia, neonatal intensive care or special care nursery admission. </outcome>
      <timepoint>End of pregnancy. 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In obese women (BMI &gt;30kg/m2), does substantial pre-conception weight loss (10-15% body weight) when compared with modest pre-conception weight loss (&lt;3% body weight) reduce the time (in days) between the end of the weight maintenance phase and conception? </outcome>
      <timepoint>Date of conception (based on the earliest ultrasound or Last Menstrual Period if no ultrasound is available). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In obese women (BMI &gt;30kg/m2), does substantial pre-conception weight loss (10-15% body weight), when compared with modest pre-conception weight loss (&lt;3% body weight), result in a distinct pattern of DNA methylation in cells (cord blood and/or buccal mucosa) derived from the offspring?</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of pregnancy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>4) Neonatal anthropometery

Length will be measured in centimetres using a measuring board.

Birth weight will be taken in grams within 72 hours of delivery using calibrated digital scales. 

Head circumference will be measured using a tape measure. Measurements will be taken be the same examiner.  

Skin fold thickness will be measured at each of three sites- left triceps, left sub scapular region and left flank. Each will be recorded in centimetres using Harpenden calipers. Measurements will be taken be the same examiner.  

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 72 hours of delivery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>5) Maternal mean length of hospital stay
</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of hospital stay based on hospital record.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neonatal mean length of hospital stay</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of hospital stay based on hospital record. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In obese women (BMI &gt;30kg/m2), does substantial pre-conception weight loss (10-15% body weight) when compared with modest pre-conception weight loss (&lt;3% body weight) result in a reduction in rate of large-for-gestational age infants (birth weight &gt;90th gentile for gestational age)? </outcome>
      <timepoint>End of pregnancy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In obese women (BMI &gt;30kg/m2), does substantial pre-conception weight loss (10-15% body weight) when compared with modest pre-conception weight loss (&lt;3% body weight) result in a reduction in the end-point of macrosomia (birth weight &gt;4000g)?  </outcome>
      <timepoint>End of pregnancy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In obese women (BMI &gt;30kg/m2), does substantial pre-conception weight loss (10-15% body weight) when compared with modest pre-conception weight loss (&lt;3% body weight) result in a reduction in the rate of pre-eclampsia (defined as persistent hypertension that develops in pregnancy with involvement of one or more maternal system)? </outcome>
      <timepoint>End of pregnancy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In obese women (BMI &gt;30kg/m2), does substantial pre-conception weight loss (10-15% body weight) when compared with modest pre-conception weight loss (&lt;3% body weight) result in a reduction in rate of intra-uterine growth restriction (IUGR) (defined as an estimated fetal weight &lt;10th percentile for gestational age)? </outcome>
      <timepoint>End of pregnancy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In obese women (BMI &gt;30kg/m2), does substantial pre-conception weight loss (10-15% body weight) when compared with modest pre-conception weight loss (&lt;3% body weight) result in a reduction in the rate of neonates born prior to 37 completed weeks gestation?   </outcome>
      <timepoint>End of pregnancy </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In obese women (BMI &gt;30kg/m2), does substantial pre-conception weight loss (10-15% body weight) when compared with modest pre-conception weight loss (&lt;3% body weight) result in a reduction in the rate of primary caesarean section?
</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of pregnancy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In obese women (BMI &gt;30kg/m2), does substantial pre-conception weight loss (10-15% body weight) when compared with modest pre-conception weight loss (&lt;3% body weight) result in a reduction in the shoulder dystocia/birth injury?
</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of pregnancy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In obese women (BMI &gt;30kg/m2), does substantial pre-conception weight loss (10-15% body weight) when compared with modest pre-conception weight loss (&lt;3% body weight) result in a reduction in the rate of neonatal hypoglycaemia (neonatal blood glucose &lt;2.6mmol/L within the neonatal period)? </outcome>
      <timepoint>End of pregnancy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In obese women (BMI &gt;30kg/m2), does substantial pre-conception weight loss (10-15% body weight) when compared with modest pre-conception weight loss (&lt;3% body weight) result in a reduction in the rate of clinically diagnosed neonatal hyperbilirubinemia?
 </outcome>
      <timepoint>End of pregnancy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In obese women (BMI &gt;30kg/m2), does substantial pre-conception weight loss (10-15% body weight) when compared with modest pre-conception weight loss (&lt;3% body weight) result in a reduction in rate of neonatal intensive care or special care nursery admission?</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of pregnancy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In obese women (BMI &gt;30kg/m2), does substantial pre-conception weight loss (10-15% body weight) when compared with modest pre-conception weight loss (&lt;3% body weight) result in a reduction in the rate of maternal gestational diabetes (IADPSG definition)?</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of pregnancy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Planning pregnancy in the next 6 months
BMI equal or greater than 30 and equal or less than 55kg/m2
Living in Victoria Australia </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>38</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Type 2 Diabetes
Physical or psychiatric illness that would preclude the use of Optifast
Currently pregnant or lactating
Currently undergoing reproductive technology treatment
Irreversible infertility</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Recruitment wil occur through:-
1. Social media (Facebook advertising linked to a website)
2. Radio and newspaper advertisement
3. Through University of Melbourne affiliated hospital clinics (Weight Control clinic at The Austin, Bariatric Clinic at RMH, Healthwise Clinic at RWH). 

Once the patient has completed a 'Registration of Interest' form or has made contact with the trial site, the trial co-ordinator will phone screen the woman. They will then make an appointment at a mutually agreeable time. 

They will then attend a full screening visit and if the patient is eligible and agreeable, the consent forms will be signed. 

Patients will then be allocated to treatment groups as below. 
 
</concealment>
    <sequence>Patients will be stratified based on age, BMI and parity. Computer generated random assignment of groups will occur within strata. 

Allocation concealment occurs by central allocation of randomisation by computer. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>As we hypothesised, individuals from our pilot study in group B had reduced glucose levels of approximately 10% (actual 9.12%, SE = 1.83, n = 24) compared to just 1.24% for those in Group A (SE = 1.40, n = 14).  Of the 24 individuals who completed the weight loss phase, 10 have fallen pregnant and reached the 12 week gestation phase (Group A: n = 3; Group B = 7).  Excitingly, the findings from the 7 women in Group B suggest that glucose reductions can be maintained at 12 weeks (mean 7.7% less glucose levels than at the beginning of the weight loss phase, SE = 1.74).  On average, the change in glucose for these women between the end of the weight loss phase and 12 weeks gestation was a small reduction of 0.14 mmol/L.  While we only have three women at 12 weeks gestation in group A, they too maintained similar glucose levels from the end of the weight loss phase (small average increase of 0.07mmol/L.  The SD of percentage change at the end of the weight loss phase was 8.6 and then 9.9 for those measured at 26 weeks gestation.  Allowing for at least a moderate effect size of 0.6 for difference in percentage decrease in glucose at 26 weeks gestation (i.e difference in means = 6, SD = 10; or slightly larger difference in means and larger SD) we require 60 women in each group to achieve 90% power.  Allowing for 45% dropout (20% drop-out during the weight loss phase as indicated in our pilot data, plus an additional 25% drop-out to allow for women who fail to become pregnant or who experience a pregnancy loss &lt;20 weeks gestation), we require approximately 218 individuals.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/11/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>5/11/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>5/11/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>218</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>19/03/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - City campus - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Mercy Hospital for Women - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <hospital>The Royal Women's Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Melbourne
Grattan St
Parkville, VIC 3051</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Melbourne
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of Melbourne
Grattan St,
Parkville, VIC 3051
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Norman Beicher Medical Research Foundation Reserarch Funding</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>459 Toorak Rd
Toorak, VIC 3142</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Joe Proietto
Sir Edward Dunlop Chair of Medicine</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Centre for Metabolic Disease
Heidelberg Repatriation Hospital
Level 2 Boronia Building
Waterdale Rd
Heidelberg Heights VIC 3081</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>A/Professor Alison Nankervis</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Diabetes and Endocrinology
Level 4
Royal Melbourne Hospital
Grattan St
Parkville VIC 3052</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Michael Permezel</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Medicine, University of Melbourne
Level 4
Mercy Hospital for Women
Studley Rd
Heidelberg, VIC 3084</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>A/Professor Jeff Craig</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Epigenetics Department
Murdoch Childrens Research Institute
50 Flemington Rd, 
Parkville, VIC 3052</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Luke Prendergast</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Mathematics
Latrobe University
Plenty Rd,
Bundoora, Victoria 3086</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Priya Sumithran</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Metabolic Medicine
University of Melbourne
Repatriation Hospital
Heidelberg Heights, Victoria 3081</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Helen Skouteris</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Psychology
Deakin University
221 Burwood Highway
Burwood, Victoria 3151</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Kate Stern</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Melbourne IVF
344 Victoria Parade
East Melbourne
Victoria, 3002</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a two arm parallel group randomised controlled trial to determine if substantial weight loss is superior to modest weight loss in reducing maternal glucose at 26-28 weeks gestation and therefore preventing adverse maternal and neonatal pregnancy outcomes. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.popstudy.com.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Melbourne Health HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office for Research
Royal Melbourne Hospital
Grattan St
Parkville, VIC 3052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/06/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/MH/71</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/04/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office for Research
Austin Health
Studley Rd
Heidelberg, VIC 3084</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/07/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/MH/71</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/06/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Women's Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research and Ethics
Crn Grattan St and Flemington Rd
Parkville, VIC 3052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>31/07/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/MH/71</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/06/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Mercy HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Mercy Health HREC
Level 6
Mercy Hospital for Women
Studley Rd
Heidelberg VIC 3084</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/09/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>R14/19, HREC/14/MH/71</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/07/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Melbourne IVF</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Melbourne IVF
344 Victoria Parade
East Melbourne, 
Victoria, 3002</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/04/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Project 38/14 MIVF</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>22/03/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/367299-Leaflet Version 2, August 2014.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Joseph Proietto</name>
      <address>Centre for Metabolic Disease
Boronia Building
Repatriation Hospital
Austin Health
Waterdale Rd
Heidelberg Heights VIC 3081</address>
      <phone>61 3 9496 2250</phone>
      <fax>61 3 9497 4554</fax>
      <email>j.proietto@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sarah Price</name>
      <address>Centre for Metabolic Disease
Boronia Building
Repatriation Hospital
Austin Health
Waterdale Rd
Heidelberg Heights, VIC 3081</address>
      <phone>+ 61 3 9496 6221</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sarah.price@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Joseph Proietto</name>
      <address>Centre for Metabolic Disease
Boronia Building
Repatriation Hospital
Austin Health
Waterdale Rd
Heidelberg Heights, VIC 3081</address>
      <phone>61 3 9496 2250</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9497 4554</fax>
      <email>j.proietto@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sarah Price</name>
      <address>Centre for Metabolic Disease
Boronia Building
Repatriation Hospital
Austin Health
Waterdale Rd
Heidelberg Heights
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 6221</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sarah.price@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>