<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372922">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/05/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000699369</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Outcomes of a therapeutic program with children and adolescents with Autism using trained assistance dogs</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Outcomes of a therapeutic program using trained assistance dogs in relation to reducing behavioural symptoms and promoting play engagement in children and adolescents with Autism. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>N/A</utrn>
    <trialacronym>N/A</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Autism</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Occupational therapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Autistic spectrum disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will take part in an occupational therapy session designed to promote engagement in play activities to meet behavioural and social goals set by the parents and occupational therapist. The assistance dogs will be used in the sessions at a variety of levels depending on the responses on the participant: at a basic level the dog will just be in the room, or the dog may sit close or next to the participant, or the dog may be actively involved in an activity (such as brushing the dog, or touching it in some way) or the dog may be fully involved such as putting a lead on the dog and walking it through an obstacle course, or taking the dog for a walk outside.  
Each session will last for an hour, and participants will be offered five weekly sessions.
An Occupational Therapist will run the sessions
Sessions are run on an individual basis with the dog trainer and a parent present, and will take place in a treatment room at the Assistance Dogs Australia centre. 
Records will be kept of participant's attendance </interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Achievement of goals for the five session program using Goal Attainment Scaling and a non standardised parent survey focused on social interaction, language and communication, engagement and calmness.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Five weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Social Responsiveness Scale scores
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and five weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Behavioural observations of session recordings. These will be assessed using a non standardised observation sheet that is being developed as part of this study, and will be scored by someone who was not part of the therapy session using video-recordings. This will include notes and simple counts of positive behaviours: Verbal behaviour towards the dog or therapist, Nonverbal behaviour towards the dog or therapist, Spontaneous language use, Spontaneous behaviour towards the dog or therapist, Play with the dog or therapist, Visual contact with the dog or therapist, Smiling towards the dog or therapist, or Imitating the therapists actions, as well as Negative behaviours such as Self-stimulatory activities or behaviours, Self-play or self-absorption, 
Hand flapping, Repetitive behaviours (hand posturing, humming, clicking, spinning objects), etc
Disruptive or aggressive behaviours/tantrums

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Five weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants aged between 5 and 20 years
Participants to have had a diagnosis of ASD for over 12 months
Parents and participants to have attended a PAWS workshop (run by Assistance Dogs Australia)
Participants to be comfortable around dogs and to have a positive view of dogs. 
Parents/caregivers to be available to attend all sessions. 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>5</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>20</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants who do not fit the inclusion criteria
Participants who do not wish to participate in the session/s
Participants or parents that do not communicate in English</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>N/A</concealment>
    <sequence>N/A</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Simple pre-post study design</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Descriptive analysis of baseline assessment and follow up assessment data
Paired t-tests of continuous outcome measure scores
Qualitative analysis of video recordings of participant behaviour and engagement during sessions
A sample of 75 participants has been set by Assistance Dogs Australia who have already recruited participants for this study through their PAWS workshop program consisting of families who are interested in applying for an assistance dog.
Qualitative analysis of parent interviews</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/06/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>6/11/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>75</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>8/12/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2233 - Engadine</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Assistance Dogs Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 455
Engadine NSW 2233</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Scentre Group Grant - Westfield</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Administered through Assistance Dogs Australia
PO Box 455
Engadine NSW 2233</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Sydney, Faculty of Health Sciences</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>75 East Street
Lidcombe
NSW 2141</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project will explore the use of assistance dogs as the primary therapeutic tool in occupational therapy sessions for children and young persons with autism spectrum disorder (ASD).  Five individual therapy sessions with an occupational therapist, an assistance dog and an assistance dog trainer will be conducted with 75 individuals with ASD. The content of the therapy sessions will be analysed to investigate the assistance dog as a tool to facilitate social engagement, communication and play in children and young persons with ASD. Interviews will be conducted with parents and caregivers of those involved in the sessions to understand their perceptions of their childs experiences and outcomes of the sessions. This process will develop a shared understanding of the role of assistance dogs in supporting individuals to engage in the social and practical tasks that they want to, and are expected to, achieve. Enhanced insight into the unique role of assistance dogs will enable the development of occupational therapy sessions targeting the specific needs of children and young persons with ASD. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Jane Foss Building
University of Sydney
Camperdown
NSW 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/01/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016/984 </hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>13/12/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Lynette Mackenzie</name>
      <address>Discipline of Occupational Therapy
Faculty of Health Sciences
University of Sydney
75 East Street
Lidcombe, NSW 2141</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93519832</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Lynette.Mackenzie@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Claire Dickson</name>
      <address>Assistance Dogs Australia
PO Box 455
Engadine NSW 2233</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9548 3355</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>CDickson@assistancedogs.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Lynette Mackenzie</name>
      <address>Discipline of Occupational Therapy
Faculty of Health Sciences
University of Sydney
75 East Street
Lidcombe, NSW 2141</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 9832</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Lynette.Mackenzie@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Lynette Mackenzie</name>
      <address>Discipline of Occupational Therapy
Faculty of Health Sciences
University of Sydney
75 East Street
Lidcombe, NSW 2141</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 9832</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Lynette.Mackenzie@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>