<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335402">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/04/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/05/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000352000</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Bell-van Riet test of the acromio-clavicular (AC) Joint</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Clinical evaluation of acromioclavicular joint pathology: Sensitivity of the Bell-van Riet (BvR) test</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>BvRTest</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Localised acromioclavicular pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The patient stands facing the examiner and the shoulder is passively elevated to 90 degrees, and then fully adducted. The elbow is then extended, with the shoulder in internal rotation (IR) and the forearm pronated. During this manoeuvre, the examiner supports the arm of the patient with his opposite hand, while resting the other hand on the patients opposite shoulder to maintain adduction and to prevent rotation of the patients upper body. If pain is present, this is considered to be a positive cross arm adduction sign. The patient is then asked to resist the examiners downwards force on the forearm . In a positive BvR test, this results in pain and the inability of the patient to maintain the arm in the adducted and elevated position. As a further assessment in this study the test was then repeated with the adducted arm in external rotation (ER).  This test is performed once only for diagnostic purposes and takes approximately 7 seconds to complete</interventions>
    <comparator>Nil</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>If pain is present, this is considered to be a positive cross arm adduction sign. The patient is then asked to resist the examiner's downwards force on the forearm . In a positive BvR test, this results in pain and the inability of the patient to maintain the arm in the adducted and elevated position.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All patients undergo 5 shoulder impingement tests including the BVR test. These are used in random order to avoid the influence of fatigue. Each test is performed once only pre-operatively for diagnosis.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the efficacy of the BvR test compared with cross body adduction, O'Brien's active compression test, Paxinos test and  Jacob's test. These clinical examination tests  are evaluated by the clinician by palpation, performance of  controlled movement of the arm across the chest, and response to resisted movement</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-operatively once only</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>NIL</outcome>
      <timepoint>NIL</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>ALL patients with isolated AC (acromio clavicular ) joint symptoms were included sequentially in this study, INCLUSION CRITERIA were defined as  the presence of localised AC joint tenderness or at least one positive AC joint compression tests. In addition, all post-injection tests had to be negative for patients to be included.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria included; previous surgery to the AC joint or rotator cuff, diminished rotator cuff strength or positive impingement signs, diminished passive glenohumeral movement, and patients with a known allergy to local anaesthetics or previous adverse reactions to corticosteroid injections elsewhere in the body</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sequential patients with isolated AC joint symptoms were included in this study This was assessed by the presence of localised AC joint tenderness or at least one positive AC joint compression test.</concealment>
    <sequence>Sequential- non randomised</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2005</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>58</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>A/Prof. Simon Bell</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Melbourne Shoulder and Elbow Centre
31 Normanby St.,
Brighton 3186
Vic</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress>Nil</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Acromioclavicular (AC) joint pathology is a common cause of shoulder pain. The location of pain originating from the AC joint can be diverse and patients are often not able to identify the exact location. In most patients the pain will be located in an area bounded by the mid-part of the clavicle and the deltoid insertion, but the pain has also been shown to radiate to the radial side of the forearm into the thumb.
AC joint pathology can occur in isolation, but is often associated with other causes of shoulder pain, such as subacromial impingement or rotator cuff pathology. Surgical treatment of other causes of shoulder pain can affect the AC joint, and arthroscopic acromioplasty may have detrimental effects on an already compromised AC joint. Conversely, residual AC joint pathology has been shown to have a negative effect on the outcome of surgery to the rotator cuff. Detection of AC joint pathology is therefore crucial in the treatment of patients with any type of shoulder problem and various clinical tests have been described to asses AC joint pathology. The primary aim of this study was to assess the diagnostic sensitivity of the  BvR (Bell-van Riet) test, when compared with other tests.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>There was no Ethics permission required as this was a comparative assessment of standard diagnostic techniques currently used by clinicians. All patients gave signed informed consent and were de-identified.</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/09/2005</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1/08/2005</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/08/2005</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Professor Simon Bell</name>
      <address>Melbourne Shoulder and Elbow Centre
31 Normanby St.,Brighton 3186. Vic</address>
      <phone>61 3 95928028</phone>
      <fax>61 3 95929612</fax>
      <email>snbell@optusnet.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Jennifer Coghlan</name>
      <address>Melbourne Shoulder and Elbow Centre
31 Normanby St.,Brighton 3186. Vic</address>
      <phone>61 3 95923775</phone>
      <fax>61 3 95929612</fax>
      <email>coghlan@bigpond.net.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Jennifer Coghlan</name>
      <address>Melbourne Shoulder and Elbow Centre
31 Normanby St.,Brighton 3186. Vic</address>
      <phone>61 3 95923775</phone>
      <fax>613 95929612</fax>
      <email>coghlan@bigpond.net.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>