<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320959">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/12/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/02/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000100099</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial of three forms of psychosocial early intervention for borderline personality disorder in youth.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>MOBY: A randomised controlled trial of specialised early intervention with individual Cognitive Analytic Therapy, specialised early intervention without individual psychotherapy, and standard youth mental health care for first-presentation borderline personality disorder in youth.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Monitoring Outcomes of Borderline personality disorder in Youth (MOBY).</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Borderline personality disorder</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Youth mental health</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Psychosis and personality disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Three interventions will be compared. Two of the interventions are two forms of the Helping Young People Early (HYPE) specialised early intervention for borderline personality disorder. The third intervention is youth mental health care. The three study arms will be: i) HYPE + individual Cognitive Analytic Therapy (HYPE+CAT); ii) HYPE + Befriending (HYPE+Bef); iii) Youth mental health care + Befriending (YMH+Bef).  

HYPE+CAT is an integrated, multidisciplinary team-based early intervention service model for borderline personality disorder. It uses a shared psychosocial model of borderline personality disorder and a common language for communication with patients, families and carers, team members and the wider service system. HYPE+CAT includes: i) rigorous diagnosis of BPD and other personality pathology; ii) up to 16 x 50-minute individual Cognitive Analytic Therapy (CAT) sessions delivered over approximately 26 weeks; iii) assertive case management integrated with the delivery of psychotherapy; iv) developing a collaborative model of the individual patients difficulties that is shared with the patient, HYPE team, family and relevant others and is used for intra- and extra-service liaison; v) active engagement of families or carers, with psychoeducation and up to four sessions of family intervention; vi) general psychiatric care, with specific assessment and treatment of co-occurring psychiatric syndromes (comorbidity), including the use of pharmacotherapy (where indicated), while minimising polypharmacy; vii) access to the shared elements of Orygen Youth Health  crisis team, inpatient care, activity group program; viii) with a clear model of brief and goal-directed crisis and inpatient care; ix) individual and group supervision of staff; and x) a quality assurance program.

HYPE+Bef will comprise all of the elements of HYPE+CAT except that individual Cognitive Analytic Therapy will be substituted with up to 16 x 50-minute individual sessions of Befriending delivered over approximately 26 weeks. Befriending is a manualised intervention that consists of talking about neutral topics that interest the participant (e.g. music, sport, books). If the participant finds verbal interaction difficult, activities such as board games, walking, or playing sport, can be used with a view to using the activity as a tool to engage the participant in further neutral conversation during and after the activity. The therapists primary goals are to keep the participant engaged for the full duration of therapy and to keep the conversation or activity as close to a neutral pleasant chat as possible.</interventions>
    <comparator>YMH+Bef includes individual practice by specialist youth mental health clinicians within a government-funded multidisciplinary group practice setting. Clinicians carry a diagnostically mixed patient load. They diagnose mental disorders, develop a management plan, offer psychoeducation, conduct assertive case management and offer general psychiatric care. General practitioner and/or psychiatric referrals and pharmacotherapy are initiated as clinically indicated. Crisis and inpatient services are accessed from the state-based mental health system, as needed. In addition, participants in this group will receive up to 16 x 50-minute individual sessions of Befriending delivered over approximately 26 weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Interpersonal problems measured by the Inventory of Interpersonal Problems Circumplex Version (IIP-C)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months and 18 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Social Adjustment measured by the Social Adjustment Scale Self Report (SAS-SR)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months and 18 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Client satisfaction measured by the Client Satisfaction Questionnaire (CSQ-8)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months and 18 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Suicidal Ideation as measured by the self-report Beck Suicidal Ideation Scale (BSS) and Mobiletype, a mobile phone program that asks open and closed questions about affect, suicidal ideation and parasuicidal behaviour.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The BSS will be completed at the Baseline, 3 month, 6 month, 12 month and 18 month assessments.  Mobiletype will be completed 6 times per day for 6 days after each assessment at Baseline, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months and 18 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parasuicidal Acts as measured by the Suicide Attempt and Self-Injury Interview (SASII) and Mobiletype, a mobile phone program that asks open and closed questions about affect, suicide ideation and parasuicidal behaviour.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months and 18 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Affective Instability as measured by the 10-item self-report Short PANAS (Positive and Negative Affect Schedule), administered with Mobiletype.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Mobiletype is administered six times per day for six days following the Baseline, 3-month, 6-month, 12-month and 18-month assessments.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Borderline Personality Disorder Symptoms as measured by the Borderline Personality Disorder Severity Index (BPDSI-IV).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3-month, 6-month, 12-month and 18-month assessments.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression as measured by the self-report Center for Epidemiologic Studies Depression Scale - Revised (CESD-R) and the semi-structured interview and rating scale of the Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale (SIGMA).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3-month, 6-month, 12-month and 18-month assessments.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Substance Use as measured by the self-report Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test (AUDIT) and the interview measure, the Opiate Treatment Index (OTI - Section II).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3-month, 6-month, 12-month and 18-month assessment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Therapeutic Alliance as measured by the Working Alliance Inventory (WAI).</outcome>
      <timepoint>In the HYPE+CAT arm, after the first, sixth and final CAT sessions.  In the HYPE+Bef and YMH+Bef arm, after the first, sixth and final befriending sessions and after the first case work/case management session, after two months of case work/case management, and after the final case work/case management session.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life as measured by the Assessment of Quality of Life (AQoL-8D).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3-month, 6-month, 12-month and 18-month assessment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Social and Occupational Functioning as measured by the Social and Occupational Assessment of Functioning Scale (SOFAS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3-month, 6-month, 12-month and 18-month assessment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Emotion Regulation as measured by the Difficulties in Emotion Regulation Scale (DERS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3-month, 6-month, 12-month and 18-month assessment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Broad inclusion criteria to capture the "real world" clincial environment.  These are: (1) Age 15-25 inclusive, (2) Ability to give informed consent and comply with study procedures, (3) Fluency in English, (4) Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-IV axis II disorders BPD.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>15</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>25</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(1) First episode psychosis within the 12 months prior to entering the study, (2) Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-IV Axis 1 Bipolar I or II Disorder, (3) Psychiatric condition due to a medical condition, (4) Severe disturbance, such that the person is unable to comply with the requirements of informed consent or the protocol, (5) A Schizophrenia Spectrum Disorder, (6) prior evidence-based BPD treatment, (7) does not meet the clinical services' eligibility criteria (e.g. catchment area).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Potential participants will be identified through the Orygen Youth Health triage system and the headspace Sunshine intake systems using the 15 BPD items from the SCID-II PQ or the SCID-II BPD module. Written informed consent will be obtained from all participants and for minors, from a parent or guardian. Following baseline assessment, participants will be assigned randomly and consecutively in a ratio of 1:1:1 to one of the three interventions.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation sequence will be computer-generated by an independent statistician. Treatment allocation will use randomised permuted blocking and participants will be stratified by age (&lt;18 years old/= 18 years old), sex and CESD-R score (cut point=37).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>No</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The main analysis will be based on the intent-to-treat principle. To determine whether there are group differences on the primary and secondary outcome measures at 6, 12 and 18 months a series of mixed effects model repeated measures analysis of variances models (MMRM) will be employed.  The within groups factor will be time and group will serve as the between subjects factor.  MMRM is a preferred method for analysing clinical trial data in psychiatry, compared with more traditional repeated measures analysis of variance (ANOVA) and analysis of covariance (ANCOVA models). The advantages of MMRM over these traditional models include: 1) all existing data are included in the model; 2) there is no imputation or substitution of missing data; and 3) dispersion and correlation of data at all occasions can be modelled. Planned comparisons and sensitivity analysis can also be successfully conducted with this technique.  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/03/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>17/03/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>30/09/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>135</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>139</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/06/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>7/07/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
    <postcode>3011 - Footscray</postcode>
    <postcode>3020 - Sunshine</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>National Health and Medical Research Council</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Borderline Personality Disorder (BPD) is a severe mental disorder that arises during adolescence and young adulthood. This study investigates the most effective form of early intervention for young people (15-25 years old) presenting for treatment of BPD for the first time.  It is a randomised controlled trial comparing three interventions: two forms of the specialised HYPE early intervention (one with and one without 16 sessions of individual Cognitive Analytic Therapy), along with an intervention of the same duration comprising general youth mental health care. The primary outcomes are improvement in interpersonal problems and social adjustment. It is expected that at the 12- and 18-month time points after enrolment that participants who receive HYPE plus individual Cognitive Analytic Therapy will have better outcomes on these measures than those who receive HYPE without individual Cognitive Analytic Therapy, and that both these groups will have better outcomes than those who receive general youth mental health care.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Melbourne Health Research and Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Royal Melbourne Hospital
Parkville Victoria 3050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/06/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2010.055</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/02/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Melbourne Helath Human Research and Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office for Research
Level 6 East, Main Building
Grattan Street
The Royal Melbourne Hospital  VIC  3050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>2010.055</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/02/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Andrew Chanen</name>
      <address>Locked Bag 10 
Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9342 2800</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andrew.chanen@orygen.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Andrew Chanen</name>
      <address>Locked Bag 10 
Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9342 2800</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andrew.chanen@orygen.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Jennifer Betts</name>
      <address>Locked Bag 10 
Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9342 2800</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jennifer.betts@orygen.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Andrew Chanen</name>
      <address>Orygen, The National Centre of Excellence in Youth Mental Health
35 Poplar Rd, (Locked Bag 10), Parkville, VIC, 3052</address>
      <phone>+61393422800</phone>
      <fax>+61393873003</fax>
      <email>andrew.chanen@orygen.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>