<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363659">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/02/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/02/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000164796</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Peak Heart Rate during Upright Treadmill and Supine Cycling.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In healthy volunteers what is the heart rate response to supine bicycle exercise compared to upright treadmill exercise.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1138-9650</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>cardiovascular disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will initially undergo an upright treadmill exercise assessment. A modified protocol will be used consisting of a 2 minute warm-up period at slow walking pace, followed by ramped increase of both treadmill speed and inclination to reach maximum age predicted heart rate in 5-8 minutes. Once maximum heart rate is reached participants will step to the side of the treadmill for 15 seconds rest, before starting again for another 30 seconds. This is repeated 8 times to simulate the pauses needed during the MRI assessment.
During a second clinic session 2-14 days later, participants will be placed in an MRI and undergo a resting scan, followed by a scan during exercise where they will be asked to pedal in the supine position while still in the scan position. The exercise protocol begins with a 2 minute warm-up period pedalling at 60-90 rpm with no resistance. The resistance is then increased to achieve maximum exercise in 5-8 minutes. Once maximum exertion is reached participants stop pedalling for 10 seconds for MRI image acquisition and then begin pedalling again for a further 30 seconds before stopping again for another acquisition. This is repeated 8 times to acquire all required images. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>The control method for this study exercises participants on an upright treadmill using a modified protocol will be used consisting of a 2 minute warm-up period at slow walking pace, followed by ramped increase of both treadmill speed and inclination to reach maximum age predicted heart rate in 5-8 minutes. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome is to achieve a heart rate response during supine bicycle exercise increases to 80% of that obtained during upright treadmill. The heart rate is monitored by ECG during both treadmill and MRI and pulse-ox as a secondary measurement during MRI.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Heart rate is recorded throughout each test and comparisons made at peak exercise capacity.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>acquisition of ventricular function using MRI during supine exercise</outcome>
      <timepoint>MRI image acquisition occurs within seconds of reaching the exercise target as participants are pedalling while in the scan position.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>healthy controls aged 20-75</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnancy, contraindication to MRI, atrial fibrillation, physical limitations preventing treadmill or cycle exercise, known cardiovascular disease - especially CAD, hypertensive (treated or untreated) - resting blood pressure (supine) above 160/100 mmHg.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/03/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>7/03/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>10/04/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>8</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Auckland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences
85 Park Rd Grafton
Auckland 1023</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Auckland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences
85 Park Rd Grafton
Auckland 1023</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>N/A</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is a pilot to measure the maximum heart rate possible cycling in the supine position to gain experience to plan future cardiac magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) studies using exercise stress for the assessment of patients with coronary artery disease (CAD).  Typical exercise stress tests are often conducted walking upright using treadmills. Imaging at peak heart rates are limited by delays as participants are moved from the treadmill into the image position. Supine exercise removes this delay. However it is not well known what heart rates are possible in this position as fewer muscle groups are engaged. In this study heart rate data from the supine position will be compared against that obtained by treadmill for each participant and the hearts function will be assessed using MRI. Ventricular function and aortic pulse wave velocity (PWV) and distensibilty measurements will be assessed, both at rest and peak heart rates.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committees</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
No 1 The Terrace
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6145</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/02/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/02/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Alistair Young</name>
      <address>University of Auckland
Faculty of Medical and Healthy Sciences
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1023</address>
      <phone>+64 9 373 7599</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.young@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Paul Roberts</name>
      <address>Auckland Bioengineering Institute
The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 9 373 7599</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>prob114@aucklanduni.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Paul Roberts</name>
      <address>Auckland Bioengineering Institute
The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 9 373 7599</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>prob114@aucklanduni.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>