<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370114">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/04/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000982415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparison between pain education and tendinopathy education both combined with a eccentric exercises program in sports players with chronic patellar tendinopathy.
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparison between pain education and tendinopathy education both combined with a eccentric exercises program for the reduction of pain and the improvement of life quality in sports players with chronic patellar tendinopathy.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1179-6217 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None
</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Patellar tendinopathy</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Pain </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Arm 1: Program with explanation of pain (theoretical class about the pain, neuroscience, physiology of pain and how it works the pain) combined with eccentric exercise in a 25 degrees decline board which the participants have to perform for 3 weeks at home.
Arm 2: Program with explanation of tendinopathy (theoretical class about the physiology of the tendon, the function of the patellar tendon, what is the tendinopathy and how it works) combined with eccentric exercise in a 25degrees decline board which the participants have to perform for 3 weeks at home..
Both groups made with sports players from athleticism, volleyball and basketball with chronic patellar tendinopathy.
The programs of explanation consist in a group theoretical 1 hour class with the support of a PowerPoint.
The programs of eccentric training consist in a first group class of 30 minutes for explain the exercises and the progress of them, and then the participants do the exercises twice a day during 3 weeks with the 25 degrees decline board at home. The exercise consist of 3 sets of 15 repetitions performed during 15 minutes twice daily of a single leg squat stand on the 25 degrees declined board while performing the exercise.
The intervention consist in 4 sessions: session 1 complete the test and explanation of pain/tendinopathy, session 2 explanation of the exercise and start of home exercises completed within 1 week of session 1, session 3 occurs three weeks following session 2, and the participants complete the final test, session 4 occurs 1 month following session 3, and the participants complete the monitoring test.
All the interventions are executed by experienced physical therapists in a sports center.
In order to monitor the adherence when the patients complete the exercises they have to send an okey sign in a message to the physical therapist.
</interventions>
    <comparator>The program with explanation of pain combined with eccentric exercise will act as the control.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome 1: Found the changes in the pain in chronic patellar tendinopathy after the intervention, assessed using MPQ-SV questionaire short version with a VAS.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: Baseline and when the intervention finishes and 1 month after the intervention commencement.
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome 2: Found the changes in the quality of life in chronic patellar tendinopathy after the intervention, assessed using SF-36 questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: Baseline, and when the intervention finishes and 1 month after the intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcome 1: Amount of change, in case that it happened, in pain in sport players with chronic patellar tendinopathy after the intervention assessed by MPQ-SV questionnaire short version with a VAS..</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: when the intervention finishes and 1 month after the intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcome 2: Amount of change in the quality of life, in case that it happened, in sports players with chronic patellar tendinopathy, assessed by SF-36 questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: when the intervention finishes and 1 month after the intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcome 4: (composite secondary outcome) Investigate what are the factors (changes in the understanding of pain, changes in the tendon, changes in the understanding of the pathology) that can influence the results after the application of this intervention. Each component will be assessed by the SF-36 and MPQ-SV short version questionnaires. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: Baseline and when the intervention finishes.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcome 5: Identify which aspects of quality of life of the sport players with chronic patellar tendinopathy are the most affected. This outcome will be assessed using the SF-36 test in Spanish Version.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: when the intervention finishes.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Minimum of exercise that each participant must be completing in a normal week: 3 trainings of his/her sport (athletics, basketball, volleyball)  per week of 45 minutes each one, chronic patellar tendinopathy, no meniscus injury or muscular injury or articular injury and no pharmacological, medical or physical therapy treatment during the intervention.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>46</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Less than 3 trainings/week of less than 45 minutes each one, no chronic patellar tendinopathy, with meniscus injury or muscular injury or articular injury and with pharmacological, medical or physical therapy treatment in the moment that the intervention begins.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed opaque envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>This is a pilot study, the number of participants needed for the investigation was determined by the number used in similar studies.

To evaluate the data first of all the data quality will be examinate, the outliers will be searched with Mahalanobis distance.
After that Shapiro-Wilks will be use to see the normality of the dependent variables.
The analysis will continue with the descriptive analysis of the cualitative ordinal variables, the median and quartiles first and third will be shown.
The initial homogeneity of the groups will be checked with the U of Mann-Whitney.
After that, an analysis will be done to see the differences between the different measures (Pre-test, Post-test and Post-test1). Each group will be considered isolated for the analysis. For it, it will be used the K test for related samples and the ANOVA of Friedman and the analysis will be completed with the test of comparison by pairs of measurements.
Finally the contrast of the efficacy of both groups will be done by comparing the values of the differences variables by the U of Mann-Whitney test. And this test will be completed by the calculation of the effect size.
Every test will be done with a confidence interval of 95% and a signification level of a=0'05.
The analysis will be done by intention of treatment.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>15/02/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>31/05/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>10</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>18/07/2016</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>18/07/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Valencia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Alcala de Henares</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Colegio de San Ildefonso, Plaza de San Diego s/n
 28801 Alcala de Henares (Madrid)</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Spain</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Elena Mendez</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Avda. Comunitat Valenciana 99, 46770, Xeraco (Valencia), SPAIN
University of Alcala de Henares</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Spain</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The main purpose of the study is to compare a pain education program with a tendinopathy education program both combined with eccentric exercises to determine which decrease most the pain and increase the most the life quality in sports players with chronic patellar tendinopathy.
The study hypothesize that a combined program of education with eccentric exercises will provide better results than an eccentric exercise program alone, and as the chronic patellar tendinopathy is a dysfunctional pain and not exactly a chronic pain, it's been hypothesize that a tendinopathy education program will give better results than a pain education program.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Comite de Etica de Investigacion y Experimentacion Animal (CEI) de la Universidad de Alcala</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Plaza de San Diego, s/n
28801 Alcala de Henares
Madrid</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/02/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CEIH/HU/2015/32</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/12/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Spain</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Elena Mendez Meri</name>
      <address>Avenida Comunitat Valenciana, 99, 2 floor, door A 
46770 Xeraco
Spain
University of Alcala de Henares</address>
      <phone>+34666900645</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>elenamendezmeri@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Elena Mendez Meri</name>
      <address>Avenida Comunitat Valenciana, 99, 2 floor, door A 
46770 Xeraco
Spain
University of Alcala de Henares</address>
      <phone>+34666900645</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>elenamendezmeri@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Elena Mendez Meri</name>
      <address>Avenida Comunitat Valenciana, 99, 2 floor, door A 
46770 Xeraco
Spain
University of Alcala de Henares</address>
      <phone>+34666900645</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>elenamendezmeri@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Elena Mendez Meri</name>
      <address>Avenida Comunitat Valenciana, 99, 2 floor, door A 
46770 Xeraco
Spain</address>
      <phone>+34666900645</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>elenamendezmeri@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>