<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370716">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/07/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000899448</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy of using Fitbits to promote physical activity in inactive Victorian adolescents
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy of using Fitbits to promote physical activity in inactive Victorian adolescents: Technological revolution or fad?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>RAW-PA: Raising Awareness of Physical Activity Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Physical inactivity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Sedentary behaviour</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The aim of this intervention is to evaluate the effectiveness of the Fitbit Flex (and accompanying app) combined with digital behaviour change resources to promote physical activity in inactive adolescents. The intervention is grounded in Social Cognitive Theory and Behaviour Choice Theory. Following the completion of baseline measures, schools will be randomised to either the intervention or wait-list control group. The 12-week intervention will include a Fitbit Flex and accompanying app, weekly individual and/or team missions to complete, and digital behaviour change resources accessed via social media (e.g. infographics, social forums, short videos etc.). Alerts to new missions and content will be delivered via email or text message 2-3 times per week. Participants will be asked to wear the monitor as much as possible throughout the 12 weeks. Adolescents will access the resources and be encouraged to participate in 12 missions (delivered at the start of each week) in their own time. Examples of weekly missions include Break it up, where adolescents will be asked to identify share ideas on how to move more and sit less, Buddy up, where participants will try to identify and implement ways to help others (e.g. family) to be more active, and Build it up, where participants will be asked to think about changing one thing that could help them to be more active. The accompanying resources match the weekly themes (e.g. how to set SMARTER goals), will step participants through the behaviour change process and target behaviour change techniques in an interactive, flexible way. The focus of the intervention is the accumulation of physical activity across the day. 

Adherence to the intervention will be monitored by documenting engagement with the intervention elements (e.g. numbers reporting engagement with resources, social media contributions etc.).</interventions>
    <comparator>Wait-list control group for 6 months. The wait-list control group will be offered the intervention after the 6 month assessment. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Objectively-measured physical activity (students)

Students will wear accelerometers for 8 consecutive days at each time point.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention, and 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Objectively-measured sedentary time (students)

Students will wear accelerometers for 8 consecutive days at each time point.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention, and 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of steps taken per day (students)

Assessed using wrist-worn Fitbit monitors.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed during 12-week intervention </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Leisure time physical activity (students)

Assessed using validated questionnaires including brief moderate-to-vigorous self-report measure and M-SPAN student survey. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention, and 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anthropometric assessments (height, weight, waist circumference) - students

Height - assessed using portable stadiometer (cm)
Weight - assessed using calibrated electronic scales (kg)
Waist circumference - measured using flexible steel tape at the narrowest point around the waist (cm)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention, and 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity enablers and barriers - assessed via self-report questionnaires (students)

Self-efficacy - measured using Social Cognitive Measures related to Adolescent Physical Activity Scale
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention, and 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Demographic survey (e.g. employment status, highest level of schooling, country of birth etc.) completed by parents/guardians</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intervention acceptability and enjoyment (students)

Information concerning adolescents' enjoyment and acceptability of the intervention components will be assessed via purpose-designed questions (e.g. Which aspects of the program did you enjoy etc.). 
Focus groups will also be conducted to examine adolescents' perspectives on the intervention program using purpose-designed questions. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility - engagement with the intervention

Measured via engagement with social media and weekly missions</outcome>
      <timepoint>During 12-week intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intervention feasibility and acceptability (teachers)

Interviews will be conducted with teachers to examine their thoughts on the intervention program using purpose-designed questions from an organisational perspective. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Leisure time sedentary behaviour (students)

Assessed using validated questionnaires including M-SPAN student survey. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention, and 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity enablers and barriers - assessed via self-report questionnaires (students)

Social support - measured using Social Cognitive Measures related to Adolescent Physical Activity Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention, and 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity enablers and barriers - assessed via self-report questionnaires (students)

Behavioural strategies - measured using Social Cognitive Measures related to Adolescent Physical Activity Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention, and 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity enablers and barriers - assessed via self-report questionnaires (students)

Barriers to physical activity - measured using Adolescent Physical Activity Perceived Barriers Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention, and 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity enablers and barriers - assessed via self-report questionnaires (students)

Physical activity enjoyment - measured using Physical Activity Enjoyment Scale (PACES)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention, and 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity enablers and barriers - assessed via self-report questionnaires (students)

Neighbourhood safety - measured using Neighbourhood Environment Walkability Scale for Youth</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention, and 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adolescents are eligible to participate in this study if they:
- Are in Year 8 
- Attend a secondary school located in a socioeconomically disadvantaged area
- Have access to the internet
- Do not meet current physical activity recommendations for youth
- Do not engage in regular organised physical activity outside of school
- Do not own and/or have not used a wearable activity tracker before</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>13</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>15</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Adolescents will not be eligible to participate if they are:
- Aged 12 years at the time of first baseline assessments
- Have used and/or own a wearable activity tracker</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation will not be concealed. Schools are eligible to participate if they are located within a socioeconomically disadvantaged area of Melbourne. Voluntary, written informed organisational consent will be obtained for schools to participate. Participants (students and teachers) will then be recruited through schools. Year 8 students who meet the minimum age criteria will receive a recruitment pack containing Plain Language Statements and Consent Forms to take home to their parents, In order to participate, students will be required to return signed parental consent forms, which will also include student assent to participate, to their school for collection by the research team. Once baseline assessments have been completed, schools will be randomised into either the intervention or wait-list control group. </concealment>
    <sequence>The project will use a group randomised controlled trial design. Schools will be randomly allocated to intervention or wait-list control groups for the duration of the study. 

Schools will be match-paired based on their size and then randomly allocated to either the intervention or control using a computer-based random number generator. Participants attending schools in the intervention group will receive the 12 week physical activity program. Participants attending schools in the wait-list control group will not receive the physical activity program during the study period. However, at the conclusion of the final assessments, participants will receive the information and resources. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>8/08/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>13/06/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>280</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/05/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Nicola Ridgers</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Institute for Physical Activity and Nutrition (IPAN),
Deakin University,
221 Burwood Highway,
Burwood,
VIC 3125.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Victorian Health Promotion Foundation (VicHealth)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Ground Floor,
1531 Pelham St
Carlton, VIC 3053</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to examine the effectiveness of a wearable activity tracker combined with digital behaviour change resources to promote physical activity in inactive adolescents attending schools in socioeconomically disadvantaged areas. This 12-week intervention will include a commercially available wearable activity tracker and accompanying app, digital behaviour change resources delivered via social media, weekly individual and/or team 'missions', and alerts to new content and 'missions' delivered via emails and text messages. Physical activity, sedentary time, leisure time behaviours and potential mediators of behaviour change will be assessed. Assessments will be undertaken at baseline, post-test and at 6-month follow-up. Process evaluation assessments will also be undertaken. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Ridgers, N.D., Timperio, A., Brown, H., Ball, K., Macfarlane, S., Lai, S.K., Richards, K., Ngan, W. &amp; Salmon, J. (2017). A cluster-randomised controlled trial to promote physical activity in adolescents: The Raising Awareness of Physical Activity (RAW-PA) Study. BMC Public Health, 17, 6.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Deakin University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Locked Bag 20000,
Geelong, VIC 3220</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/07/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016-179</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/06/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nicola Ridgers</name>
      <address>Institute for Physical Activity and Nutrition (IPAN),
Deakin University,
221 Burwood Highway,
Burwood,
VIC 3125.</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9244 6718</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nicky.ridgers@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Samuel Lai</name>
      <address>Institute for Physical Activity and Nutrition (IPAN),
Deakin University,
221 Burwood Highway,
Burwood,
VIC 3125.</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9246 8350</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.lai@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nicola Ridgers</name>
      <address>Institute for Physical Activity and Nutrition (IPAN),
Deakin University,
221 Burwood Highway,
Burwood,
VIC 3125.</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9244 6718</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nicky.ridgers@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nicola Ridgers</name>
      <address>Institute for Physical Activity and Nutrition (IPAN),
Deakin University,
221 Burwood Highway,
Burwood,
VIC 3125.</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9244 6718</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nicky.ridgers@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>