<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369563">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/11/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/11/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001266550</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Corticosteroid injections compared to foot orthoses for plantar heel pain</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>For adults with plantar heel pain, is an ultrasound-guided corticosteroid injection more effective than foot orthoses for reducing pain and increasing function.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1176-1291</utrn>
    <trialacronym>SOOTHE Heel Pain Trial</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Plantar heel pain</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Plantar fasciitis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A single corticosteroid injection.

1 mL betamethasone (Celestone Chondrose) mixed with 1 mL bupivacaine (Marcaine 0.5%) injected perifascially by a radiologist under ultrasound guidance. As this is a single injection, adherence will be monitored by attendance at the appointment with the radiologist, Adverse events associated with this intervention will be documented.

In addition, participants will perform plantar fascia and calf stretches prior to standing each morning, by holding the stretch for a period of 10 seconds, repeated 10 times for each foot/leg (total daily stretch session of approximately 7 to 8 minutes each morning for 12 weeks). Adherence will be monitored by recording the number of days per week the participant has performed their stretches, assessed via questionnaire at each four-weekly timepoint. </interventions>
    <comparator>Prefabricated foot orthoses (Formthotics manufactured by Footscience Christchurch, New Zealand).

The foot orthoses will be a full-length arch contouring device, manufactured from a single-density polyethylene closed cell foam that will support the arch of the foot. Participants will be advised to use the foot orthoses in their footwear for as much time as they can during the day, for the 12 weeks of the trial. Adherence will be monitored by recording the average days per week, plus the average number of hours per day the participant has worn the foot orthoses, assessed via questionnaire at each four-weekly timepoint. Adverse events associated with this intervention will be documented.

In addition, participants will perform plantar fascia and calf stretches prior to standing each morning, by holding the stretch for a period of 10 seconds, repeated 10 times for each foot/leg (total daily stretch session of approximately 7 to 8 minutes each morning for 12 weeks). Adherence will be monitored by recording the number of days per week the participant has performed their stretches, assessed via questionnaire at each four-weekly timepoint. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The foot pain domain of the Foot Health Status Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4, 8 and 12 weeks </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severity of first step pain after rising in the morning on a 100mm visual analogue scale (VAS) 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4, 8 and 12 weeks </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severity of 'average' pain today on a 100mm visual analogue scale (VAS) 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4, 8 and 12 weeks </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The foot function domain of the FHSQ</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4, 8 and 12 weeks </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plantar fascia thickness measured sonographically</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4 and 12 weeks </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health-related quality of life assessed by the Short Form 36 (SF-36)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4, 8 and 12 weeks </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The 7-day Physical Activity Recall Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4, 8 and 12 weeks </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fear-avoidance beliefs measured using the Fear-avoidance Components Scale (FACS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4, 8 and 12 weeks </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Days of work lost measured by self-report questionnaire at each four-weekly time-point</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4, 8 and 12 weeks </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sessions of sport or exercise lost measured by self-report questionnaire at each four-weekly time-point.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4, 8 and 12 weeks </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Co-interventions used for plantar heel pain measured by self-report questionnaire at each four-weekly time-point.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4, 8 and 12 weeks </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health-related quality of life assessed by the EuroQol (EQ-5D)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4, 8 and 12 weeks </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Global perceived rating of change measured with a 15-point Likert scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>4, 8 and 12 weeks </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(i)	Aged 18 years and over 
(ii)	Have a clinical diagnosis of PHP in accordance with the clinical practice guidelines linked to the International Classification of Function, Disability and Health from the Orthopaedic Section of the American Physical Therapy Association, which includes:
a.	Pain the plantar medial heel region that is aggravated by weightbearing activities or worse in the morning and/or after a period of rest
b.	Pain upon palpation of them medial calcaneal tubercle
(iii)	A duration of PHP for at least 4 weeks
(iv)	Report their average pain over the last seven days as at least 30 mm on a 100 mm visual analogue scale
(v)	Be willing to regularly wear foot orthoses for the duration of the trial
(vi)	Be willing and have no contraindications to receive a corticosteroid injection in the plantar heel
(vii)	Be willing not to implement any other forms of treatment during the trial (with the exception of paracetamol 4g/day)
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(i)	Unable to understand the English language
(ii)	Unable to walk household distances unaided
(iii)	Have received treatment for PHP in the last four weeks
(iv)	Have received a corticosteroid injection in the previous six months
(v)	Have a history of surgery to the heel
(vi)	Have a systemic medical condition such as a connective tissue disease, degenerative neurological disorder or inflammatory disorder
(vii)	Unwilling to wear footwear that can accommodate foot orthoses
(viii)	Have regularly worn foot orthoses within the previous six months
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be allocated to groups using an interactive voice response telephone service provided by the National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC) Clinical Trials Centre at the University of Sydney, New South Wales, Australia. A secondary investigator who is not involved with any other part of the trial will advise participants of their allocation</concealment>
    <sequence>The sequence will be generated by an interactive voice response telephone service provided by the National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC) Clinical Trials Centre at the University of Sydney, New South Wales, Australia. Permuted block randomisation with uneven random block sizes will be undertaken. Minimisation will be undertaken by stratifying participants based on their sex, BMI and the duration of symptoms.  </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The sample size has been calculated a priori based on being able to detect a minimal important difference of 13 points on the pain domain of the Foot Health Status Questionnaire, the primary outcome measure. Using a standard deviation derived from previous research of 21, a power of 0.8, alpha level of 0.05 and a conservative drop out of 10%, a sample size of 46 participants per group will be required to provide sufficient power. To allow for unforeseen circumstances we aim to recruit a total of 100 participants who will be randomised to one of two groups (i.e. approximately 50 participants per group)

Where appropriate continuous data will be analysed using parametric statistical tests. To achieve this, data will be checked for normality. If data is not normally distributed, it will be transformed if appropriate, otherwise non-parametric tests will be conducted. If normally distributed, primary and secondary outcomes will be compared using the linear regression approach to analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) with baseline severity included as a covariate.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>28/04/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>6/05/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/03/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Glen Whittaker</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Discipline of Podiatry
School of Allied Health
La Trobe University
Bundoora, 
Victoria 3086</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>La Trobe University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>La Trobe University
Bundoora, 
Victoria 3086</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Our primary aim is to compare the effectiveness of ultrasound-guided corticosteroid injections to foot orthoses (shoe insoles) for individuals with plantar heel pain, using an assessor-blinded randomised trial. Our hypothesis is that corticosteroid injections will be more effective in the short-term (0-4 weeks), while foot orthoses will be more effective in the longer term (5-12 weeks). 
Our secondary aims are to compare the effectiveness of corticosteroid injections to foot orthoses on: foot function; general health; plantar fascia thickness; work, sport and recreation; and fear-avoidance beliefs. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.heelpaintrial.com</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Whittaker, G. A., Munteanu, S. E., Menz, H. B., Elzarka, A., &amp; Landorf, K. B. (2017). Corticosteroid injections compared to foot orthoses for plantar heel pain: protocol for the SOOTHE heel pain randomised trial. Contemporary Clinical Trials Communications, 5, 111. doi: 10.1016/j.conctc.2016.11.003.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>La Trobe University Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>La Trobe University
Bundoora, 
Victoria 3086</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/01/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>15-120</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/11/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/369563-1-s2.0-S2451865416300357-main.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Glen Whittaker</name>
      <address>Discipline of Podiatry
School of Allied Health
La Trobe University
Bundoora, Victoria, 3086</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9479 5785</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9479 5415</fax>
      <email>g.whittaker@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Glen Whittaker</name>
      <address>Discipline of Podiatry
School of Allied Health
La Trobe University
Bundoora, Victoria, 3086</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9479 5785</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9479 5415</fax>
      <email>g.whittaker@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Glen Whittaker</name>
      <address>Discipline of Podiatry
School of Allied Health
La Trobe University
Bundoora, Victoria, 3086</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9479 5785</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9479 5415</fax>
      <email>g.whittaker@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Glen Whittaker</name>
      <address>Discipline of Podiatry
School of Allied Health
La Trobe University
Bundoora, Victoria, 3086</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9479 5785</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9479 5415</fax>
      <email>g.whittaker@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>