<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369569">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/11/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/11/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001246572</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>'THE MANAGING EMOTIONS (ME) PROGRAM'
The development of an 8 Week Dialectical Behaviour Therapy (DBT) Informed Skills Training Program including Creativity/art making exercises for the treatment of people who have difficulty managing their emotions.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The development of an 8 Week Dialectical Behaviour Therapy (DBT) Informed Skills Training Program including Creativity/art making exercises for the treatment of people who have difficulty managing their emotions.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Emotion Dysregulation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Impulsive behaviour</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Research is based on the attendance of Skills Training Groups only, no individual therapy. Each Weekly session is 2.5 hours in duration. At each session Diary cards are discussed, a mindfulness exercise is experienced by all attendees and then skills are taught, handouts are supplied and group discussion follows.
 In the 8 Week DBT Skills Training only program the final half hour of each weekly group will involve verbal discussion on when and where these skills will help individuals in the groups 
 In the 8 Week DBT skills training plus art making the final half hour is dedicated to making an art exercise that specifically relates to the skills taught and a small discussion is conducted in sharing images at the end of group.  

8 to 10 participants will attend an 8 week Dialectical Behaviour Therapy (DBT) Skills training course.  
WEEK
ONE -Introduction to Dialectical Behaviour Therapy-What is Wise Mind
TWO -Concentration on the skill of Distress Tolerance Wise Mind Accepts
THREE -Distress Tolerance skills of Improving the Moment
 FOUR - Mindfulness
Observing, describing and participating in a non-judgmental, one-mindfully and effective manner -Mindfulness exercises  circuit . Identifying what we need to do to practice the options we have to improve and enjoy the moment mindfully using our 5 senses.
FIVE - Reality Acceptance- Willingness and Willfulness
SIX -Understanding our emotions and Chain analysis
Identifying and describing the difference between primary and secondary emotions and their functions
SEVEN - Goals of Interpersonal Effectiveness and How to communicate effectively.
EIGHT - Review of all diary cards and the skills you feel could assist you

8 to 10 participants will attend an 8 week Dialectical Behaviour Therapy (DBT) Skills training course plus tailored art exercises.

Dialectical Behaviour Therapy Informed Skills Training and Art Exercises 8 week program
WEEK	
ONE - Introduction to Dialectical Behaviour Therapy-What is Wise Mind. 
ART EXERCISE - How Skills could help build frame around us. What would Wise Mind look like? Coloured pencils  
TWO - Concentration on the skill of Distress Tolerance Wise Mind Accepts	
ART EXERCISE - To identify what kind of distress tolerance strategies may help 
 create 7 tools before action  Texters and collage
THREE - Distress Tolerance skills of Improving the Moment
ART EXERCISE - Creating an object or image of the cheerleader within to keep one safe whilst practicing the skills- clay
FOUR - Mindfulness - Observing, describing and participating in a non-judgmental, one-mindfully and effective manner.  Mindfulness exercises  circuit . Identifying what we need to do to practice the options we have to improve and enjoy the moment mindfully - using our 5 senses
ART EXERCISE - What did it feel like to be mindful? ' watercolours'
FIVE - Reality Acceptance- Willingness and Willfulness
ART EXERCISE - Creating a representation of Willingness  what can you accept right now?- texters, oil pastels, collage.
SIX - Understanding our emotions and Chain analysis
Identifying and describing the difference between primary and secondary emotions and their functions
ART EXERCISE - After experiencing a primary emotion, how many secondary emotions d you experience represented by Acrylic paints on canvass
SEVEN - Goals of Interpersonal Effectiveness and How to communicate effectively.
ART EXERCISE - When I communicate well How do I look  - construction found materials
EIGHT - Review of all diary cards and the skills you feel could assist you	Review of all artwork. Creating an image that represents a tool box full of the skills you find most useful


A key component of DBT is teaching a client to stay a little longer than before with feeling emotional pain, validating and accepting their experience whilst moving towards changes in behaviours.  The skill of managing difficult emotions is paramount to being able to gain or maintain balance in a life that has meaning and fulfilment, free from self-harm, anxiety, depression and a sense of emptiness.  Adding the experience of creating images can help patients learn skills in two very different ways, verbally and experientially. Patients leave group with a concrete, original item or object to remind themselves of the skills they have learned..

Facilitators of Groups - All facilitators will receive a 74 page Manual prepared by the Prinicpal Researcher. The facilitators will attend the training free of charge and will receive a 'Certificate of Attendance' that provides 14 professional development hours with the following organizations who have endorsed the training for professional development points.
Australian and New Zealand Arts Therapy Association ANZATA
Australian Association of Social Workers AASW
Australian Counselling Association ACA
Australian Council of Mental Health Nurses ACMHN
The training is also listed on Australian Psychological Society webpage APS (APS does not endorse any training by private organizations)  

Group Facilitators may already have sufficient training in DBT or may have attended the Principal Researcher's 2 Day Intensive DBT Training.  The Principal Researcher will be responsible for checking this requirement and approving all facilitators are qualified and experienced group facilitators.

Group facilitators will be currently practicing Health Care Professionals, Art Therapists, Psychologists, Social Workers, Occupational Therapists, Counsellors etc. having experience in facilitating Mental Health Groups and being current members of a Professional Association relevant to their professional qualifications. DBT training will be offered to all facilitators. Facilitators must have over 12 months experience in conducting group work. Two people are required to be present for DBT Groups and it is estimated that the maximum number of  DBT Trained Facilitators required would be 16 and the total number of co-facilitators (not necessarily trained in DBT would also be 16). The facilitators can be male or female. 

An Outline of the Training is below:
2 DAY INTENSIVE DIALECTICAL BEHAVIOUR THERAPY TRAINING

 Dialectical Behaviour Therapy (DBT) was developed by Prof. Marsha Linehan, Ph.D.,at the University of Washington in the late 1970s. She added acceptance, dialectics and validation strategies to cognitive-behavioural treatment for patients diagnosed with borderline personality disorder (BPD) who often presented with chronic patterns of suicidal or other severe dysfunctional behaviours and named the therapy Dialectical Behaviour Therapy (DBT).  In her 2nd Edition DBT Skills Training Manual 2015 she has explained how useful DBT is for many other client groups and has given examples of how DBT can be modified to assist these patients. She has also added a variety of new skills to the original modules for skills training.
 It is not unusual for individuals diagnosed with BPD to also struggle with other problems -- depression, bipolar disorder, post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD), anxiety, eating disorders, or alcohol and drug problems. Its important to note that DBT is an empirically-supported treatment. for BPD sufferers.  DBT skills are extremely useful for people in assisting in the management of impulsive behaviours, mood changes, emotional dysregulation, anxiety, depression and urges to use substances, food, gambling etc. to avoid or get rid of uncomfortable or intense emotions. DBT gives patients concrete skills and strategies to manage disruptive emotional experiences.
This 2 day Intensive Dialectical Behaviour Therapy Training is designed to assist practitioners gain knowledge of how to work with DBT as individual therapists and also as skills group facilitators. Training can be tailored to specific regions needs and information on how to set up a DBT program including Therapists Consult groups is also detailed.
DAY 1
Biosocial Therapy of Borderline Personality Disorder, DSM1V/V, Description of Dialectical Behaviour Therapy and Statistics
5 Functions of Treatment, Standards and Modes of Treatment, Researched Model of DBT description
Dialectics and Validation
Strategies of Encouragement, Genuineness, DBT Styles of communication
Pre-Treatment Stage, Orienting and Commitment Strategies, Goals, Patients and Therapists Agreements
Stages and Targets of Treatment
Individual DBT Therapy, Crisis Intervention, Suicide Risk Assessment, Phone Coaching, Treating Wilfullness, Diary Cards, Chain Analysis
Implementing DBT in a System, DBT Consultation Team Agreements
DAY 2
Changes in 2nd Edition DBT Skills Training 2015
DBT For Adolescents and suggested Skills Training for non BPD patients in a variety of settings
Skills Training Group, Group Rules, Four skills of DBT
Mindfulness, States of Mind  Art Exercise
Distress Tolerance 
Emotional Regulation
Interpersonal Effectiveness
Assumptions of DBT, Resources
Training Objectives:
Participants will:
-
1. gain knowledge of the philosophy of DBT, the structure of the therapy and statistical information on the researched model. Discussion of latest research for the use of DBT in a variety of settings. 
2. gain knowledge of how to teach crisis survival techniques and address suicide ideation, self-harm and impulsive destructive behaviours of patients
3. gain knowledge in how to work dialectically using validation and acceptance strategies with patients.
4. gain knowledge in how to look after oneself as a clinician and gain supportive supervision within the DBT frame to help assist in working with patients who present with high levels of emotional dysfunction.
5. gain knowledge of all four skills of DBT, Mindfulness, Distress Tolerance, Emotional Regulation and Interpersonal Effectives, including the additions of new skills added in 2nd Edition DBT Training 2015 (Prof Marsha Linehan)
6. gain knowledge in how to teach a skills training group
7. gain knowledge in working with many client groups that experience emotional dysregulation and working with DBT with adolescents 

Expressive Therapy Clinic's Trainings are endorsed by AASW, ACMHN, ACA, ANZATA an listed on APS Website for Professional Development..

</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group is the 8  to 10 participants who attend the DBT Skills only training program</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Facilitator confidence in using DBT, measured using a numerical rating scale (0-5) 


</outcome>
      <timepoint>The question on the assessment/evaluation is one question at the end of the 2 Day Intensive DBT Training as follows: 

How do you rate your confidence to use DBT in your practice/work from 0 - 5?
0 - No confidence 5 - A lot of confidence</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The aims of the research are to test a DBT-Art approach along side a standard DBT control for efficacy 

Data will be collected from both the DBT only 8 week Skills Training program and the DBT 8 week program with art making.  The following data will be measured:
DBT Ways of coping checklist .
A Detailed Questionnaire representing ways that the participant has coped with stressful events in your life.  The questionnaire measures the use of 59 coping strategies from 'Never used, Rarely used, Sometimes used, Regularly used.






 


</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measure will be taken in the first week of the 8 Week Skills Training Programs and again at the end of the programs.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome 3 - Outcome Rate Scale (ORS) - Assessing how participant feels in the following areas. Personal well-being, Interpersonally with family/close relationships, Socially - work, friendships, Overall - general sense of well-being</outcome>
      <timepoint>Primary outcome timepoint 3
Data collected at end of each weekly group.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcome 1
Confidence in control of Emotions scale developed by Principal Investigator</outcome>
      <timepoint>Secondary outcome timepoint 1
Pre scale at beginning of both 8 week programs and Post at the end of the 8 week programs</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcome 2
Participant's Diary Card - Measuring urges to act on behaviours and actions taken.  Also measure of emotional response. This is a composite secondary outcome.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Secondary outcome timepoint 2
This information is recorded by the participants on a daily basis in both programs for the duration of 8 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcome 3
A focus group will be held at the end of both 8 week programs to assess the satisfaction rate of all participants in both groups.

The participants in the 8 week DBT skills training group with art exercises attached will also be asked the following.
What did you feel about using Creativity/art making alongside DBT Skills? Did in add value to the program  Yes or No?</outcome>
      <timepoint>Secondary outcome timepoint 3
This satisfaction question will be conducted at the end of the week of the programs.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants referred to attend both 8 week programs will have a history of mental health issues specifically related to difficulty in managing or regulating emotions.  They will be referred from a variety of mental health sources.  They will have presented to General Practitioners, Psychiatrists or Psychologists or other mental health providers with a history of emotional dysregulation. Facilitators will be asked to complete a 'DERS' Difficulties in Emotion Regulation Scale, Gratz,K.L. &amp; Roemer, L. (2004) with potential participants.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>17</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>The exclusion criteria for the study would be any participants exhibiting the following:
1.	Marked degree of cognitive deficit which would prevent participation in essential treatment components (e.g. diary card. Specific behavioural deficits = unable to read, focus, recall, verbally communicate)
2.	Actively psychotic  i.e. thought-disordered; responding to auditory hallucinations, delusional beliefs.
3.	Specific behaviours: to an extent that they:
(a) Interfere with setting, being able to assess or provide treatment, or
(b) Make the individual unable to behaviourally attend/participate in assessment/treatment.
4.	Using substances/alcohol  at diagnostic level of severity (such that it largely obstructs therapy)
5.	Bingeing/disordered eating to point of 
(a) Behaviour requiring current inpatient care and/or
 (b) Inability to cope with therapy tasks

</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will attend the programs when they are scheduled to be piloted.  Participants will not be given a choice as to attend 8 Week DBT Skills training program or the 8 week DBT plus art making program.  Participants therefore will not necessarily have a preference for either group. 

 Simple randomisation using procedures like coin-tossing will be used to select participants for groups</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>In total of 4 separate sites will be identified to conduct the pilot programs.
Two of the sites are planned to be set up in the community and the other two sites are planned to be conducted in two separate private or public hospitals outpatient settings. Approaches are currently being made to two private hospital sites. 
It is envisaged that all 4 sites will conduct at least two series of both 8 weeks skills training programs. 
Up to 8 Health Care Professionals will conduct the DBT only 8 Week skills based program twice. 
Up to 8 other Health Care Professionals will conduct the DBT and creativity/art making  8 Week skills based program twice. 
The total maximum number of facilitators will be 16.  The total maximum number of co-facilitators will be 16.
There will be 8 participants in each group.  A total of 128 participants for the total study

Each group will be conducted for 2.5 hours except the final group. This group will be a 3 hour group.
</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>sample size was calculated to identify the numbers of participants required to detect an effect for outcome and process measures set at p=.05 on a two tailed repeated measures test. Standard deviations and mean outcome scores from published research using the same or similar measures in brief psychological treatment approaches were included to refine the sample size calculation. The calculation set the sample at 120 participants.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>19/02/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>23/03/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>128</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Currumbin Clinic - Currumbin</hospital>
    <hospital>The Sydney Clinic - Bronte</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Megan Shiell</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Expressive Therapy Clinic, 51 Hillcrest Avenue, TWEED HEADS SOUTH  NSW  2486</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Megan Shiell</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Expressive Therapy Clinic
51 Hillcrest Avenue
TWEED HEADS SOUTH  NSW  2486</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This research is aimed at evaluating two Dialectical Behaviour Therapy (DBT) informed skills based programs.. One Program is stand alone DBT Skills and the other DBT skills plus art making. There is a growing body of evidence that suggests DBT is a very effective treatment for many other disorders for example, addiction, depression and anxiety, eating disorders.  Standard DBT comprises five approaches to assist patients.  One of those approaches is a DBT Skills training group. There is also evidence that DBT Skills Training programs alone are effective in reducing impulsive behaviour and depression. (Linehan, M. 2nd Edition DBT Skills Training Manual 2015 Guilford NY). 
People who suffer the symptoms of emotional dysregulation are often considered to be unpredictable, unreliable and likely to experience problems with relationships both in community, work and in their family relations.  
As a Registered Art Therapist, the principal researcher has integrated creativity/art making within a standard 8 Week DBT Skills Training Program for many years. Repeated group evaluation of this approach has been positive on measures of both outcome and satisfaction with treatment.  As a result the approach has now been standardised and is ready for evaluation in a clinical setting.   The aims of the research are to test a DBT-Art approach along side a standard DBT control for efficacy 
Outcome measures will be symptom improvement and interpersonal function and participant satisfaction with treatment. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Institutional Human Research Ethics Committee, University of Queensland</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>School of Medicine
University of Queensland
288 Herston Road
Herston Qld4780</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>31/08/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2015001113</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/07/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/369569-Assessment 2 Day Intensive DBT Training.docx</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Megan Shiell</name>
      <address>Expressive Therapy Clinic
51 Hillcrest Avenue,
TWEED HEADS SOUTH  NSW 2486</address>
      <phone>+61 417 084 846</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.shiell@expressivetherapyclinic.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Megan Shiell</name>
      <address>Expressive Therapy Clinic
51 Hillcrest Avenue
TWEED HEADS SOUTH  NSW  2486</address>
      <phone>+61 417 084 846</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.shiell@expressivetherapyclinic.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Megan Shiell</name>
      <address>Expressive Therapy Clinic
51 Hillcrest Avenue
TWEED HEADS SOUTH  NSW  2486</address>
      <phone>+61 417 084 846</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.shiell@expressivetherapyclinic.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Megan Shiell</name>
      <address>51 Hillcrest Avenue
TWEED HEADS SOUTH  NSW  2486</address>
      <phone>0417 084 846</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.shiell@expressivetherapyclinic.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>