<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369310">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/09/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/10/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001097538</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Randomized trial of the efficacy and rate of relapse of bacterial infections using standard versus symptom-based antibiotic duration in primary-care patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomized trial of the efficacy and rate of relapse of bacterial infections using standard versus symptom-based antibiotic duration in primary care patients.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>None</utrn>
    <trialacronym>None</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Skin infections</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Pneumonia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Sinusitis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cystitis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The antibiotic course will be stopped when the patient's symptoms have substantially subsided.  The investigators will advise the patient when to stop antibiotics, based on symptoms scores assessed daily while taking antibiotics.  The criteria for stopping antibiotics, based on a symptom severity score of 1 (very mild) to 10 (most severe) will be all of the following:
1. More than 3 days after onset of symptoms
2. Symptom score 2 or less for feverishness (chills, sweats) and pain
3. Symptom score 3 or less or back to baseline for loss of appetite, body ache, skin symptoms/signs (redness, heat, swelling - if skin infection), urinary symptoms (dysuria, frequency - if urinary infection), cough improving (if chest infection), less than 50% volume of purulent sputum (if chest infection), less than 50% volume of nasal discharge or post-nasal drip (if sinus infection)
4. The patient feels ready to stop antibiotics. 

Adherence will be checked each day during antibiotic treatment. </interventions>
    <comparator>Antibiotic course will be of standard duration</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Response to antibiotic treatment, assessed by daily symptom score.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>End of treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relapse of infection, assessed by symptom score at follow up, by restarting of antibiotics and for urine infection by relapse or persistence of positive urine culture. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 5 to 7 after treatment stopped and day 14 to 21 after treatment stopped</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Treatment-emergent adverse events, such as nausea, vomiting, diarrhoea or skin rash.  The patient will be asked about TEAE by the study team at each contact.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Each day during the period of antibiotic treatment and at each follow-up assessment (between days 5 to 7 after treatment finishes and between days 14 and 21 after treatment finishes).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total consumption of antibiotic doses, assessed by telephone questioning</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily phone call during antibiotic treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Outpatients only
Skin infection - surface area &gt; square 75 cm
Pneumonia - using scoring system from local acute cough algorithm
Sinusitis - criteria for antibiotic treatment from Australian Therapeutic Guidelines 2014
Bladder infection - compatible symptoms plus bacteruria</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Severe infections or hospitalised patients. 
Substantial immune compromise
Treatment failure for same infection in past 3 months
Other antibiotic treatment within 4 days of enrolement. 
Infection found to be caused by bacteria resistant to those prescribed
Skin infection requiring more complex or prolonged treatment, such as necrotising infection, diabetic foot infections or infection complicating severe peripheral vascular disease, decubitus ulcer infection, animal or human bite infection, infection complicating fresh water or salt water trauma, or infection associated with a vascular, enteric or urinary catheter site, underlying osteomyelitis or septic arthritis, or a recent deep surgical wound.
Chest infections requiring more complex or prolonged treatment, such as infective exacerbations of bronchiectasis or cystic fibrosis, empyema. 
Sinus infection involving the orbit or intra-cranial structures
Pyelonephritis, prostatitis or indwelling urinary catheter</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The GP or ED doctor will contact the study team with a possible recruit.  The doctor will prescribe antibiotics according to local protocols (which are highlighted and promoted for patients treated during the study period).  Patients interested in being included in the study will be given written information then contacted and visited to discuss being in the trial.  Subjects will be randomised to either symptom-based or standard antibiotic duration according to pre-generated sequences.  Allocation will be performed by the principal investigator and will be concealed from the GP, patient and research assistant until it has been determined that the patient meets the criteria for the trial and has consented to being part of the trial. </concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation in blocks, stratified by infection type.  Used www.random.org – integer sets.  </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Two arms</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>9/11/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>20/11/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>27/01/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>71</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Stopped early</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>21/02/2016</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>21/02/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis>Data collected is being analysed</dataanalysis>
    <withdrawnreason>Lack of funding/staff/facilities</withdrawnreason>
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Nelson Bays Primary Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 1776
Nelson 7040</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Nelson Medical Research and Education Trust Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>c/o Dr Bruce King
Medical Outpatients Department
Nelson Hospital
Private Bag 18
Nelson 7010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nelson Medical Research and Education Trust</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>c/o Dr Bruce King
Medical Outpatient Clinic
Nelson Hospital
Private Bag 18
Nelson 7010</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>When a doctor prescribes antibiotics, the usual advice is to finish the course.  Instead, patients often stop taking the antibiotics when they feel better.  This trial is designed to find out which strategy is better for a variety of mild to moderate infections treated in the community.  
More and more information now shows that shorter courses of antibiotics work as well as longer courses for many mild to moderate infections and that success can be predicted by certain symptoms of infection going away.  A shorter course of antibiotics is likely to cause fewer side effects and less resistance.  A longer course of antibiotics, in those who are slow to get better, may prevent the infection coming back.  
This is the first randomised trial we are aware of that formally tests whether it is best to finish a course of antibiotics or stop when the symptoms have substantially gone away.  we hypothesise that a symptom-based duration of antibiotic treatment will be equal or more effective than a standard course, with equal or less antibiotic consumption and treatment-emergent adverse effects.   
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committees</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Ethics Department
Freyberg Building
20 Aitken St
Wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/11/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/10/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Richard Everts</name>
      <address>Nelson Bays Primary Health 
PO Box 1776
Nelson 7040</address>
      <phone>+64 274633284</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>richard.everts@nbph.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Richard Everts</name>
      <address>Nelson Bays Primary Health 
PO Box 1776
Nelson 7040</address>
      <phone>+64 274633284</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>richard.everts@nbph.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Richard Everts</name>
      <address>Nelson Bays Primary Health 
PO Box 1776
Nelson 7040</address>
      <phone>+ 64 274633284</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>richard.everts@nbph.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>