<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369575">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/11/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/11/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001267549p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A multicentre, randomised controlled pilot trial comparing performance of direct laryngoscopy versus videolaryngoscopy for endotracheal intubation in surgical patients (MAC-V trial)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A multicentre, randomised controlled pilot trial comparing performance of direct layngoscopy versus videolaryngoscopy for endotracheal intubation in achieving successful first-pass intubation in patients undergoing general anaesthesia for surgery.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1176-3641 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>MAC-V</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil known
</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>patients undergoing surgery who require endotracheal intubation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients will be randomised to be intubated using either a direct laryngoscopy or videolaryngoscopy. The intervention (intubation using either direct laryngoscopy or videolaryngoscopy) will be a single event utilising standard intubating techniques (induction of anaesthesia and muscle relaxation) at the start of surgery requiring intubation. The sole difference between the groups will be the laryngoscopy technique used.
Duration of intervention will be less than 15 minutes </interventions>
    <comparator>Direct laryngoscopy</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of first pass endotracheal intubation.
First pass endotracheal intubation is defined as successful intubation during a single apnoeic episode. Airway adjuncts such as bougie or stylet may be used as can assistance with optimal external laryngeal manipulation (OELM) or suctioning. Curtailing the attempt for bag-mask ventilation, repositioning, assistance or additional equipment to those already specified will be deemed failure. This a binary outcome (pass or fail).</outcome>
      <timepoint>at intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to first pass endotracheal intubation.
Time to first-pass intubation is defined as the time taken from when the intubator takes the laryngoscope  to when endotracheal tube placement is confirmed and end tidal CO2 is recorded on capnography waveform. This will be timwed using a stopwatch.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at intervenion. This is from when the intubator takes the laryngoscope  to when endotracheal tube placement is confirmed and end tidal CO2 is recorded on capnography waveform. Please see specific definition above.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>performance of techniques measured by intubation difficulty score (IDS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>immediately following intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>patient harm measured by composite of airway bleeding, mucosal injury and sore throat reported in post anaesthetic care unit </outcome>
      <timepoint>immediately after intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adult patient scheduled for surgery requiring asleep endotracheal intubation
No contra-indication to direct laryngoscopy or videolaryngoscopy
Laryngoscopy for endotracheal intubation is required
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Known or predicted difficult bag-mask ventilation
Requires  rapid sequence intubation
Any language or cognitive problems that preclude adequate informed consent being obtained.
Anaesthetist does not have enough clinical experience to use direct laryngoscopy or videolaryngoscopy without in-theatre supervision.
Clinical scenarios where awake or asleep fibreoptic inbutation is the technique of choice
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Those meeting inclusion criteria and lacking exclusion criteria will be invited to participate in the study.
Following provision of informed consent subjects will be allocated to one of the two treatment groups . Group assignment will be by random concealed allocation, this will be carried out using sealed opaque envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted block randomisation
</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>We estimate a total of 200 patients will be adequate to test feasibility endpoints but not adequate for the primary endpoint. We estimate from previously published data that the first-pass intubation rates will be approximately 85%. We believe a clinically important absolute difference would be 5%. 
To find a 5% absolute difference between the performances of laryngoscopy blades we calculated that the sample size of 1480 (alpha= 0.05 and beta= 0.2) or 1940 (alpha=0.05 and beta 0.1) would be needed. Please refer to table in attachments section on page 9 to see calculations. 
Responses will be collected and collated using Microsoft Excel and statistical analysis will be carried out using SAS v9.3 for Windows. Categorical variables will be compared using the X^2 analysis; and continuous variables using Students t-test or ANOVA for normally distributed variables; non-normally distributed variables will be transformed or analysed using non-parametric statistics as appropriate.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/01/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Auckland District Health Board</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Anaesthesia
Level 8 Support Building
Auckland City Hospital
2 Park Road, Grafton
Auckland
1023</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Auckland District Health Board</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Anaesthesia
Level 8 Support Building
Auckland City Hospital
2 Park Road, Grafton
Auckland
1023</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Approximately half of patients having general anaesthesia require endotracheal intubation to allow muscle relaxation, control ventilation or protect the airway. Historically, this has been achieved mostly by direct laryngoscopy with a laryngoscope. In the last 20 years, videolaryngoscopy has been used increasingly with many anaesthetists favouring its use. The two techniques are in widespread use and anaesthetists are expected to be familiar with both. There is increasing evidence that videolaryngoscopy provides superior view of the glottic opening. However, this is a surrogate endpoint and there seems to be a poor relationship between view and intubation success with many videolaryngoscopic devices. A large, pragmatic clinical trial powered for intubation success has never been performed. Current randomised control trials comparing these methods are small, use different endpoints, and specific populations, making results less generalisable. Furthermore meta analyses comparing these devices have rarely collected data relating to harm that could be consequent to their use. We believe the most meaningful endpoint to determine the performance of these devices is first pass intubation, that is, the first attempt to intubate being successful. This multicentre study aims to compare direct larygoscopy with videolaryngoscopy using first pass intubation success as the primary endpoint. We aim to test the feasibility of a large, multicentre effectiveness trial by recruiting 200 trial participants across 3 sites in 3 months. We aim to compare the relative harms of the different laryngoscopic techniques. The results of this trial will provide improved guidance for current airway algorithms
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/11/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/369575-Study design.docx</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alice Loughnan</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia
Level 8 Support Building
Auckland City Hospital
2 Park Road, Grafton
Auckland
1023</address>
      <phone>+6493670000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alice.loughnan@btinternet.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Ellen Waymouth</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia
Level 8 Support Building
Auckland City Hospital
2 Park Road, Grafton
Auckland
1023</address>
      <phone>+6493670000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>EWaymouth@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Douglas Campbell</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia
Level 8 Support Building
Auckland City Hospital
2 Park Road, Grafton
Auckland
1023</address>
      <phone>+6493670000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dcampbell@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Carolyn Deng </name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia
Level 8 Support Building
Auckland City Hospital
2 Park Road, Grafton
Auckland
1023</address>
      <phone>+6493670000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>CarolynD@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>