<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372241">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/01/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/02/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000175370</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Impact of binocular vision disorders on contact lens dissatisfaction in non-presbyopic adult contact lens wearers.
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A prospective study in a population of myopic non-presbyopic adult contact lens wearers to determine a suitable measure of contact lens dissatisfaction and to determine the extent to which binocular vision disorders contribute to contact lens dissatisfaction.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Contact lens dissatisfaction</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Binocular vision disorders</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This will be a prospective study in a population of myopic non-presbyopic adult contact lens wearers. On successful enrollment, participants will complete two validated questionnaire comprising the Convergence Insufficiency Syndrome Survey (CISS) and the Contact Lens Dry Eye- Questionnaire-8 (CLDEQ-8). The CISS assesses symptoms arising from binocular vision disorders and the CLDEQ-8 assessed symptoms arising from contact lens dryness. Each participant will complete questionnaires according to a pre-determined randomization plan to minimize potential bias arising from completing questionnaires in the same order. Participants will be given the second questionnaire only after completing and returning the first questionnaire.
A standard, optometric binocular vision assessment will be performed and participants will be classified as either having a binocular vision disorder or not having a binocular vision disorder.
Participants will be sent a set of three contact lens dissatisfaction questionnaires after completing the standard, optometric binocular vision assessment. These questionnaires comprise the Contact Lens Impact on Quality-of-life (CLIQ), the Ocular Surface Disease Index (OSDI) and the Ranked Symptom Survey (RSS). The CLIQ is a validated quality-of-life questionnaire aimed specifically at non-presbyopic contact lens wearers. The OSDI is a validated questionnaire comprising three subscales assessing assess vision-related function, ocular symptoms and environmental triggers. The RSS comprises three subscales assessing discomfort, vision dissatisfaction and lens handling dissatisfaction. On completion and return of the questionnaires, a second set of the same questionnaires will be sent within 5-7 days. Participants will complete and return the second set of questionnaires. Each participant will complete each set of three questionnaires according to a pre-determined randomization plan to minimize potential bias arising from completing questionnaires in the same order.
</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will be participants diagnosed as not having a binocular vision disorder</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The utility of the Contact Lens Impact on Quality-of-life (CLIQ), the Ocular Surface Disease Index (OSDI) and the Ranked Symptom Survey (RSS) questionnaires to measure contact lens dissatisfaction in myopic, non-presbyopic adults, as assessed by correlations between the Convergence Insufficiency Syndrome Survey and each of the three questionnaires (CLIQ, OSDI, RSS). </outcome>
      <timepoint>On the day of enrolment (completion of the CISS), 2-3 days following enrolment (completion of first set of CLIQ, OSDI, RSS) and 7-9 days (completion of second set of CLIQ, OSDI, RSS).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The utility of the CLIQ, OSDI and RSS questionnaires to measure contact lens dissatisfaction in myopic, non-presbyopic adults, as assessed by correlations between the Contact Lens Dry Eye Questionnaire-8 (CLDEQ-8) and each of the three questionnaires (CLIQ, OSDI, RSS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>On the day of enrolment (completion of the CLDEQ-8), 2-3 days following enrolment (completion of first set of CLIQ, OSDI, RSS) and 7-9 days (completion of second set of CLIQ, OSDI, RSS).
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The utility of the CLIQ, OSDI and RSS questionnaires to measure contact lens dissatisfaction in myopic, non-presbyopic adults, as assessed by repeatability of each of the three questionnaires (CLIQ, OSDI, RSS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>2-3 days following enrolment (completion of first set of CLIQ, OSDI, RSS) and 7-9 days (completion of second set of CLIQ, OSDI, RSS</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Presence of a binocular vision disorder as determined by standard optometric testing comprising monocular and binocular high contrast visual acuity and 6 m and 40 cm, dissociated heterophorias at 3 m and 40 cm, fixation disparity at 40 cm, accommodative facility at 40 cm, near point of accommodation, near point of convergence, stereopsis at 40 cm, vergence ranges at 6 m and 40 cm, positive and negative relative accommodation at 40 cm, near autorefraction and contact lens dissatisfaction as determined from the primary outcome (either the CLIQ, OSDI, RSS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>On the day of enrolment (completion of the standard optometric testing), 2-3 days following enrolment (completion of first set of CLIQ, OSDI, RSS) and 7-9 days (completion of second set of CLIQ, OSDI, RSS).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants must:
*Be able to read and comprehend English and give informed consent as demonstrated by signing a record of informed consent.
*Be between 18-40 years old, male or female.
*Have less than or equal to 1.00 D cylindrical power in either eye.
*Achieve at least 0.20 LogMAR (6/9.5) or better in each eye with no more than a one-line difference (0.10 LogMAR) between eyes with current contact lenses.
*Willing to comply with the clinical trial as directed by the Investigator.
*Have ocular health findings considered to be normal and which would not prevent the participant from safely wearing contact lenses.
*Be an experienced spherical contact lens wearer with current contact lens prescription at least one week old. 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants must not have:
*Any pre-existing ocular irritation, injury or condition (including infection or disease) of the cornea, conjunctiva or eyelids that would preclude contact lens fitting and safe wearing of contact lenses.
*Any systemic disease that adversely affects ocular health e.g. diabetes, Graves disease, and auto immune diseases such as ankylosing spondylitis, multiple sclerosis, Sjogrens syndrome and systemic lupus erythematosus. Conditions such as systemic hypertension and arthritis do not automatically exclude prospective participants.
*Use of or a need for concurrent category S3 and above ocular medication at enrolment. 
*Eye surgery within 12 weeks immediately prior to enrolment for this trial.
*Previous corneal refractive surgery.
*Previous surgery on the extra ocular muscles.
*Contraindications to contact lens wear.
*Currently enrolled in another clinical trial.
*Pregnancy. Formal testing of pregnancy is not required. A participants verbal report is sufficient.
The Investigator may, at his/her discretion, exclude anyone who they believe may not be able to fulfil the clinical trial requirements or it is believed to be in the participants best interests.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>The two objectives of this trial require different sample sizes, with the objective of determining the extent to which binocular-vision disorders contribute to CL dissatisfaction requiring the larger sample. The sample size will therefore be based on this objective.

Previous data suggests the mean difference +/- SD in the ocular surface disease index scores between participants identified as symptomatic on either the convergence insufficiency symptoms survey or contact lens dry eye questionnaire-8 = 9 +/- 11 and 27% of participants have a binocular vision disorder. Therefore 15 participants with a binocular vision disorder and 56 participants without a binocular vision disorder (71 participants in total) are required to reject the null hypothesis at the 5% level of significance and 80% power.

Participants will be enrolled until the required numbers in each category are achieved, to a maximum of 100 participants.
Participants who have commenced the clinical trial will be included in the analysis dataset.
 
Questionnaires will be scored as per published instructions. The correlation of dissatisfaction questionnaires with binocular vision questionnaires will be assessed using non-parametric Spearman Correlation. Repeatability of dissatisfaction questionnaires will be assessed using paired non-parametric tests, Bland-Altman plots and by estimating the co-efficient of repeatability.

Data will also be summarised as means +/- standard deviations. No transformation is likely to be required. Scores between questionnaires will be compared using student t-tests.

Participants will be categorised into two trial groupsthose with a binocular vision disorder and those without a binocular vision disorder. The level of dissatisfaction will be compared between participant groups using non-parametric group tests such as Wilcoxon or Mann-Whitney tests and parametric tests such as t-test based on the assumptions of normality. The level of dissatisfaction will be determined as item totals for each questionnaire.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/02/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>13/04/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>19/02/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>71</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>26/02/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Brien Holden Vision Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 5, Rupert Myers Building 
Gate 14, Barker Street University of New South Wales, 
NSW 2052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Brien Holden Vision Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 5, Rupert Myers Building 
Gate 14, Barker Street University of New South Wales, 
NSW 2052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>School of Optometry and Vision Science, University of new South Wales</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Level 3, Rupert Myers Building 
Gate 14, Barker Street University of New South Wales, 
NSW 2052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Contact lens dissatisfaction is a major problem for contact lens wearers. Most research efforts have concentrated on contact lens discomfort as a source of contact lens dissatisfaction, but binocular vision disorders among contact lens wearers has not been researched as a potential source of contact lens dissatisfaction. This study aims to identify a questionnaire which measures dissatisfaction due to symptoms from binocular-vision disorders and discomfort in myopic non-presbyopic adult contact lens  wearers and to determine the extent to which binocular-vision disorders contribute to contact lens dissatisfaction.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Limited</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>129 Glen Osmond Road
Eastwood 
South Australia 5063
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/02/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2017-01-069</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/01/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Daniel Tilia</name>
      <address>Brien Holden Vision Institute
Level 5, Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14 Barker St, University of New South Wales
NSW  2052</address>
      <phone>+61293857516</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.tilia@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Daniel Tilia</name>
      <address>Brien Holden Vision Institute
Level 5, Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14 Barker St, University of New South Wales
NSW  2052</address>
      <phone>+61293857516</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.tilia@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Daniel Tilia</name>
      <address>Brien Holden Vision Institute
Level 5, Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14 Barker St, University of New South Wales
NSW  2052</address>
      <phone>+61293857516</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.tilia@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Daniel Tilia</name>
      <address>Brien Holden Vision Institute
Level 5, Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14 Barker St, University of New South Wales
NSW  2052</address>
      <phone>+61293857516</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.tilia@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>