<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83796">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/04/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/05/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000319279</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Control of Diabetes through Weight Loss in Indigenous Diabetes</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of lapband surgery on weight loss in diabetic Indigenous Australians.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Laparoscopic gastric banding surgery is a minimally invasive surgery lasting 60-90 minutes, in which a band is fastened around the upper stomach to create a small pouch which restricts the amount of food that can be consumed.</interventions>
    <comparator>Active group. Standard care: health education and self administered questionnaire to assess their perception of diabetes. It would take approximately 30 minutes to complete. Following, a discussion with them would be held (lasting 2-3 hours) to address their concerns and refresh aspects of diabetes education identified in the questionnaires.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The central aim of the study is to achieve a substantial and durable weight loss. The principal outcome is the frequency of remission of type 2 diabetes in response to this weight loss. Additional outcomes would include measure of side effects and complications, compliance, acceptability and costs. 
Weight loss and frequency of diabetes remission will be measured by clinical assessments (weight lost via full medical history, examination by health professional), collection of tissue/ fluid (blood results indicating diabetes status)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Each participant would be engaged in a process of care for their diabetes which would begin with a detailed clinical assessment (including baseline data collection). There would be an operative procedure involving an overnight hospital stay and then data would be collected fortnightly over a two year period.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compliance (subjects band compliance and acceptance) - via questionaires, focus groups</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data would be collected fortnightly over a two year period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients must:
-1. Be Indigenous people who suffer obesity and type 2 diabetes 
-1. Agree to comply with the procedures of the study including questionnaire assessment
2.Have no history of previous abdominal surgery which would potentially preclude laparoscopic placement of the band. 
3.Be free of medical issues which contra-indicated the proposed treatments.   These may include acute myocardial infarction within the past 6 months, dementia, active psychosis, concurrent experimental drug use, pregnancy or intending to conceive in the next two years, lactation, severe alcohol or  drug abuse, use of drugs known to affect body composition, cytotoxic drugs, internal malignancy, or major organ failure.
4.Be able to understand the Lapband (LAGB) procedure and its potential for benefit and risk.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients would be excluded from entry  -:
1.	If there was lack of acceptance of the procedures of the study including questionnaire assessment
2.	If there was a history of previous abdominal surgery which would potentially preclude laparoscopic placement of the band. 
3.	If there were medical issues which contra-indicated the proposed treatments.   These may include acute myocardial infarction within the past 6 months, dementia, active psychosis, concurrent experimental drug use, pregnancy or intending to conceive in the next two years, lactation, severe alcohol or  drug abuse, use of drugs known to affect body composition, cytotoxic drugs, internal malignancy, or major organ failure.
4.	If there was an inability to understand the LapBand (LAGB) procedure and its potential for benefit and risk or were unable to understand or agree to the aftercare process.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/04/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>210</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Centre for Obesity Research and Education (CORE)
School of Public Health &amp; Preventive Medicine
Monash University
The Alfred Hospital, Commercial Road
Melbourne Victoria 3004 Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The hypothesis of this study is that the LAGB procedure and the aftercare program would be acceptable and feasible and engender sufficient compliance that a group of Indigenous people with type 2 diabetes will benefit from the weight loss with remission of type 2 diabetes equal to that observed in a Caucasian group of the Melbourne RCT trial. To ascertain success-factors for the LAGB procedure and give appropriate health education with a view of improving their compliance to obtain the hypothesised results the study would assess the perceptions and beliefs of diabetes patients and their health care service providers.        

The central aim of the study is to achieve a substantial and durable weight loss. The principal outcome is the frequency of remission of type 2 diabetes in response to this weight loss. Additional outcomes would include measure of side effects and complications, compliance, acceptability and costs.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash University Human Research Ethics Committee (SCERH)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Ethics
Monash Research Office
Building 3E, Room 111
Monash University, Clayton 3800</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/05/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kristine Egberts</name>
      <address>Centre for Obesity Research and Education (CORE)
School of Public Health &amp; Preventive Medicine
Monash University
The Alfred Hospital, Commercial Road
Melbourne Victoria 3004 Australia</address>
      <phone>+613 99030686</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Kristine.Egberts@med.monash.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kristine Egberts</name>
      <address>Centre for Obesity Research and Education (CORE)
School of Public Health &amp; Preventive Medicine
Monash University
The Alfred Hospital, Commercial Road
Melbourne Victoria 3004 Australia</address>
      <phone>+613 99030686</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Kristine.Egberts@med.monash.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>