<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373003">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/05/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000783325</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Probiotics to reduce infection in patients admitted to the Intensive Care Unit  </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Restoration Of gut miCroflora in CrITical Illness (The ROCIT trial): A multicentre Randomised controlled trial of probiotic therapy to reduce nosocomial infection and increase days alive and out of hospital in critically ill patients admitted to the intensive care unit. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ROCIT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>hospital acquired infection</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention 
Participants randomised to probiotics will receive a once daily administration of a single capsule of probiotic therapy containing 20 billion colony forming units of Lactobacillus plantarum strain 299v. Participants receiving oral antibiotics will not receive administration of the study drug within two hours of a dose of oral antibiotics.  In vitro testing of the product has been completed locally confirming viable bacteria at a colony count within 0.1 log10 of the expected value. Participants will be discouraged from initiating any additional probiotic therapy after discharge from index hospitalisation until study completion (day-60). All other treatment will remain at the discretion of the treating team. Minimisation of contamination by development of an SOP for the handling and administration of probiotics based on published standard.
Participants will be provided a study drug diary to record adherence and requested to return study drug bottles at the end of the study period for pill counts and reconciliation. 

</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo
The trial will be placebo-controlled. Participants randomised to placebo will receive an identically packaged capsule and will not receive any probiotic therapy whilst hospitalised. Participants will be discouraged from initiating any additional probiotic therapy after discharge from index hospitalisation until study completion (day-60). All other treatment will remain at the discretion of the treating team. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Days alive and out of hospital</outcome>
      <timepoint>day 60</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>* All-cause nosocomial infection to hospital discharge. Assessed by two independent blinded infectious diseases clinicians review of medical records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>hospital discharge, censored at day 60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>* ventilator-associated pneumonia. Assessed by two independent blinded infectious diseases clinicians review of medical records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>ICU discharge, censored at day 60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>* hospital-acquired pneumonia. Assessed by two independent blinded infectious diseases clinicians review of medical records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>hospital discharge, censored at day 60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>* urinary tract infection. Assessed by two independent blinded infectious diseases clinicians review of medical records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>hospital discharge, censored at day 60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>* surgical site infection. Assessed by two independent blinded infectious diseases clinicians review of medical records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>hospital discharge, censored at day 60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>* blood stream infection. Assessed by two independent blinded infectious diseases clinicians review of medical records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>hospital discharge, censored at day 60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>* clostridium difficile infection. Assessed by two independent blinded infectious diseases clinicians review of medical records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>hospital discharge, censored at day 60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>* Antibiotic free days. Blinded assessment of medical records.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>hospital discharge, censored at day 60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>* Composite out come of antibiotic, antiviral and antifungal free days. Blinded assessment of medical records.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>to hospital discharge, censored at day 60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>* Ventilator-free days. Blinded assessment of medical records.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>ICU discharge, censored at day 60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>* Vasopressor-free days. Blinded assessment of medical records.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>ICU discharge, censored at day 60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>* Incident renal replacement therapy.Blinded assessment of medical records.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>ICU discharge, censored at day 60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>* Renal replacement-free days. Blinded assessment of medical records.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>ICU discharge, censored at day 60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>* ICU mortality. Blinded assessment of medical records.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>icu discharge, censored at day 60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>* Hospital mortality. Blinded assessment of medical records.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>hospital discharge, censored at day 60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>* day 60 mortality. Blinded assessment of medical records and phone contact where necessary.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>day 60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>* Quality of life via EQ5D5L. Phone contact. </outcome>
      <timepoint> at day 60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>* Per protocol analysis of days alive and out of hospital  including those with &gt;80% compliance to daily administration of study drug. Blinded assessment of medical records.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>day 60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>* Per protocol analysis of all cause nosocomial infection including those with &gt;80% compliance to daily administration of study drug. Blinded assessment of medical records.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>day 60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>* Admitted to the ICU or high dependency area for less than 48 hours
* Anticipated to require intensive care or high dependency area care beyond the next calendar day
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. less than 18 years of age
2. Absolute contraindication to receiving medication via the enteral route
3. Known to be receiving probiotic therapy at time of index hospitalisation
4. Acute pancreatitis as a cause or complication of current admission
5. Immunosuppressed, e.g. chemotherapy within four weeks of admission, receiving greater than or equal to 1.5mg/kg methylprednisolone daily or equivalent for more than four days
6. Neutropenia (neutrophil count less than 1x109/L)
7. Prosthetic heart valve or permanent pace maker
8. Death is deemed to be inevitable as a result of the current acute illness AND either the treating clinician, the patient, or the substitute decision maker are not committed to full active treatment
9. Enrolment not considered in the patients best interest
10. Previously enrolled in the ROCIT study
11. Unlikely to be residing in the Perth Metropolitan area in 60 days time
12. Participating in a competing interventional study
13. Pregnancy
14. Admitted to hospital from a high level nursing facility or rehabilitation facility
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>sequentially numbered, otherwise identical vials of study drug and placebo</concealment>
    <sequence>central, variable block size via online randomisation engine</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Normally and non-normally distributed data will be presented as mean and standard deviation (SD), and median and interquartile range (IQR), respectively. Between-group comparison of parametric data will be provided as mean difference and confidence interval and analysed using Students t test. Between-group comparison of non-parametric data will be presented at median difference and analysed using the Mann-Whitney U test. For dichotomous data, frequencies and percentages will be presented and between-group analysis will use Fischers Exact or Chi-squared test as appropriate. The numbers at risk in each group and the number and proportion of events observed will be reported, as well as the equivalent absolute risk difference, relative risk ratio and corresponding 95% confidence intervals. Survival time from randomisation until day 60, according to treatment group will be displayed as Kaplan-Meier curves and analysed using a log-rank test.  Estimates of hazard ratios for survival, with corresponding 95% CI and P values, will be obtained from the Cox proportional hazards models incorporating treatment group alone, and independent covariates used in the multivariate models. Secondary analysis will also be conducted adjusting the primary outcome variable for prespecified baseline covariates (age, gender, APACHE-II score, IVAB therapy) in a transformed multivariable linear regression model including baseline univariate variables with a p&lt;0.25. For all outcome analyses a two-sided P value of &lt;0.05 will be considered significant.  

Pre-specified subgroups will be: 
1. Antibiotic therapy vs no antibiotic therapy at enrolment
2. Emergency vs Elective admission
3. Surgical vs medical admission
4. Microbiota diversity (Shannon Index&lt;4 vs Shannon Index &gt;4)
5. Trauma vs non trauma admission

Subgroup analyses will be performed on the pre-specified subgroups of interest irrespective of whether there is evidence of a treatment effect. Heterogeneity between subgroups will be determined by fitting an interaction between treatment and subgroup. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>23/07/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>28/07/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>3/07/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>220</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>16</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>3/09/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Fiona Stanley Hospital - Murdoch</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Perth Hospital - Perth</hospital>
    <hospital>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital - Nedlands</hospital>
    <hospital>St John of God Hospital, Subiaco - Subiaco</hospital>
    <hospital>St John of God Hospital, Murdoch - Murdoch</hospital>
    <postcode>6150 - Murdoch</postcode>
    <postcode>6000 - Perth</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
    <postcode>6008 - Subiaco</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Fiona Stanley Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Murdoch Drive, Murdoch, WA, 6065</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>State health Research Advisory Council Research Translation Project, Department of Health, government of Western Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Health, Perth, 189 Royal St, East Perth, Western Australia, 6004</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of this study is to determine whether probiotic therapy in critically ill patients admitted to an ICU reduces hospital-acquired infection, and hence reduces risk of death and time in hospital. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Metropolitan Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Fiona Stanley Hospital, Murdoch Drive, Murdoch, Perth, WA, 6065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/04/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>RGS000000004</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/12/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Edward Litton</name>
      <address>Intensive Care Unit
Fiona Stanley Hospital
Murdoch Drive
Murdoch
Perth 
WA 
6065</address>
      <phone>+61415293281</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ed_litton@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Edward Litton</name>
      <address>Intensive Care Unit
Fiona Stanley Hospital
Murdoch Drive
Murdoch
Perth 
WA 
6065</address>
      <phone>+61415293281</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ed_litton@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Edward Litton</name>
      <address>Intensive Care Unit
Fiona Stanley Hospital
Murdoch Drive
Murdoch
Perth 
WA 
6065</address>
      <phone>+61415293281</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ed_litton@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Edward Litton</name>
      <address>Intensive Care Unit
Fiona Stanley Hospital
Murdoch Drive
Murdoch
Perth 
WA 
6065</address>
      <phone>+61415293281</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ed_litton@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>