<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336402">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/01/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/01/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000057987</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Genetic and environmental influences on taste receptors in the prevention of obesity</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Genetic and environmental influences on taste receptors in the prevention of obesity amongst individuals who are hyper (more) and hypo (less) sensitive to prototypical taste stimuli as measured via the evaluation of taste function and taste receptor gene expression, prior to, and following four weeks consumption of a standardised (DASH) diet.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1119-0014</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>During this study, subjects will be evaluated for their taste sensitivity to a number of prototypical taste stimuli including sucrose (sweet taste), citric acid (sour taste), sodium chloride (salty taste), caffeine (bitter taste), oleic acid (fatty acid taste) and monosodium glutamate (umami taste). Individuals who are hyper- or hypo- sensitive to any of these taste stimuli, as defined by a score greater than, or less than 2 standard deviations from the mean, will be asked to participate in the study, which will involve consumption of a standardised diet, the Dietary Approaches to Stop Hypertension (DASH) diet. Whilst this diet was developed to reduce sodium intake, it is accepted as a suitable diet for general health, due to the high levels of fruits and vegetables, as well as whole grains that comprise the diet, and limitations on sugars and fats. The DASH diet will be customized to each participant. For this, all participants will receive recipe cards for cooking DASH style meals and information on how much of each specific food or food group (vegetables, fruits etc) they will be required to consume. In general, the DASH diet recommends the following 1) 7-8 serves of whole grains (whole wheat breads, pasta, cereals etc), 2) 4-5 serves of vegetables (where 1 serve is equal to 1 cup of raw vegetables, or 1/2 cup cooked vegetables), 3) 4-5 serves of fruit (where 1 serve is equal to 1 medium fruit, 1/4 cup dried fruit or 1/2 cup canned fruit), 4) 2-3 serves of low-fat or fat free dairy (where 1 serve is equal to 200 g yoghurt or 200 mls milk), 5) 2-3 serves of oils and fats (where 1 serve is equal to 1 teaspoon of unsaturated oil, low-fat salad dressing, or mayonnaise) per day. To account for differences in body size and energy needs, all diets will be customized for each participant. Taste sensitivity as well as taste receptor gene expression will be measured prior to and following the diet intervention, which will run for four weeks. For this, all participants will complete 4 X 30 minute taste tests, two prior to the intervention, and two during week four of the intervention, as well as 2 x 30 minute testing sessions where tongue tissue will be collected, once prior to, and the other following the intervention. The DASH diet will be consumed by all participants for 4 weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>no control - all subjects will consume the diet</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome in this study will be taste sensitivity, which will be measured via determining the detection threshold, which is the lowest amount of tastant required for it to be detected, for the following tastants sucrose (sweet taste), citric acid (sour taste), sodium chloride (salty taste), caffeine (bitter taste), oleic acid (fatty acid taste) and monosodium glutamate (umami taste).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Taste thresholds will be established prior to the intervention and during week four of the dietary intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The second primary outcome will be taste receptor gene expression, which will be measured via collecting micrograms of tongue tissue, by gently scraping the tongue with a cell scrapper or cell brush. Tongue tissue will be combined with commercially available gene probes, which are used to measure the expression of taste receptor genes</outcome>
      <timepoint>Taste receptor gene expression will be established prior to the intervention and during week four of the dietary intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dietary intake changes as a result of the intervention will be captured by use of 24 hour food recalls.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Repeat 24 hour food recalls will be collected prior to initiating the diet, to measure recent food intake. During the intervention, one 24 hour food recall will be collected per week, to measure dietary changes whilst consuming the DASH diet</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Adults over the age of 18 years
- Adults living in the Sydney metropolitan area
- Adults with good written and spoken English
-Adults who can attend testing sesions between 9:00am - 5:00pm Monday to Friday</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-Adults with medical conditions known to influence weight
-Adults who are currently, or have been within the past 3 months on a diet, or consuming a special diet
-Adults whose weight has fluctuated by more than 3 kilograms in the past 3 months
-Adulst older than 55 years
-Adults who are restrained eaters
-Adults who are allergic to, or do not wish to consume dairy based products
-Adults with impaired taste, or those consuming medication known to affect taste
-Smokers</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All subjects will participate in the dietary intervention</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/04/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Conor Delahunty</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>CSIRO Food and Nutritional Sciences
Riverside Corportae Park
11 julius Avenue
North Ryde
2113
NSW</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation (CSIRO)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Riverside Corportae Park
11 julius Avenue
North Ryde
2113
NSW</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation (CSIRO)</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>CSIRO Food and Nutritional Sciences
Riverside Corportae Park
11 julius Avenue
North Ryde
2113
NSW</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will evaluate the influence of diet on taste sensitivity and taste receptor gene expression in healthy subjects</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>CSIRO Food and Nutritional Sciences Human Research Ethics Commitee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>CSIRO Food and Nutritional Sciences
Kintor Road
Adelaide
5000
South Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>31/01/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Jessica Stewart</name>
      <address>CSIRO Food and Nutritional Sciences
Riverside Corporate Park
11 Julius Avenue
North Ryde
2113</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 9490 8363</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jessica.stewart@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Jessica Stewart</name>
      <address>CSIRO Food and Nutritional Sciences
Riverside Corporate Park
11 Julius Avenue
North Ryde
2113</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 9490 8363</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jessica.stewart@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Jessica Stewart</name>
      <address>CSIRO Food and Nutritional Sciences
Riverside Corporate Park
11 Julius Avenue
North Ryde
2113</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 9490 8363</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jessica.stewart@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>