<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371767">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/11/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/01/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000072314</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of chitosan-dextran (Chitodex) gel with budesonide and mupirocin in chronic rhinosinusitis patients post endoscopic sinonasal surgery</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of chitosan-dextran (Chitodex) gel with budesonide and mupirocin in chronic rhinosinusitis patients post endoscopic sinonasal surgery</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1189-3972</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Rhinosinusitis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other inflammatory or immune system disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients who meet ALL of the inclusion/exclusion criteria will be offered participation in this study and will be randomised into treatment and control group after informed consent has been obtained. 

After patient has given consent, they will be randomised into one of three groups:
1. Test group 1: To receive Chitodex (10ml of succinyl chitosan + 300mg of dextran aldehyde) + Budesonide (Pulmicort) 2mg/4mL + Mupirocin 20mg OR
* Budesonide and Mupirocin is incorporated into the gel complex
2. Test group 2: Chitodex (10ml of succinyl chitosan + 300mg of dextran aldehyde) + Budesonide (Pulmicort) 2mg/4mL with oral antibiotics OR
* Budesonide is incorporated into the gel complex
3. Control group: Oral antibiotics and will not receive any test gel post op (current standard practice)

Oral antibiotics prescribed are as per standard post operative practice of investigator unless guided by previous swab results and contraindications (ie. adverse reactions). 

All patients will have 2 swabs taken by the surgeon under direct visualisation with rigid nasoendoscopy prior to their endoscopic sinus surgery for both bacterial culture as well as nasal microbiome analysis. At the end of the sinus surgery while the patient is still under general anaesthetic, the gel will be applied as a once-off prodedure by the operating surgeon. The gel is injected into the sinonasal cavity as post operative wound dressing using a luer lock pressure control syringe. 

All post operative and follow up instructions remain the same for patients in all cohorts.
The patients will then be asked to return to the outpatient department at 2 weeks, 6 weeks and 6 months post operation (none different to usual practice). At each review they will have 2 sinus swabs taken and a recording of their endoscopic sinus examination. The endoscopic video examination will then be scored by a blinded clinician for infection (pus), oedema, granulation tissue, and crusting using validated Lund Kennedy Scale. In addition, patients will be asked to complete a self-directed symptom and comfort questionnaire at each time-point SNOT22 and Visual Analogue Scale.

If on review visits any recruited patients have clinical signs and symptoms of sinus infection patient will be prescribed a rescue course of antibiotic (as per standard practice).</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group patients are treated based on current standard practice which is to receive a course of oral antibiotics post endoscopic sinus surgery</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary endpoint will be eradication of infection, indicated by a negative microbiology swab of the sinuses, clinical scores on endoscopy and symptom scores on patients self-directed questionnaires pre and post treatment.

The outcomes will be assessed by both the patient and an independent blinded clinician.

Pre and post treatment endoscopic scores will be performed by an independent blinded clinician using a scoring sheet specific for this study which consists of the validated Lund-Kennedy Endoscopic Score (LKES).

The patient will be scoring their pre and post symptoms using the VAS and SNOT-22 scoring sheet.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Sinus swab, endoscopy score and patient symptom scores will be assessed at baseline D0 of enrolment (pre-treatment) and at 2 weeks, 6 weeks and 6 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To observe the changes in nasal microbiome post endoscopic sinus surgery. 
Nasal swabs are performed and uses culture-independent bacterial DNA sequencing techniques to identify the microbiome of sinonasal cavity</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 week post operation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Selection/inclusion criteria:
Patients who meet ALL of the following criteria will be offered inclusion in the study:
(1)	Patients undergoing ESS for CRS AND
(2)	Have who have had symptoms of chronic rhinosinusitis (nasal discharge, postnasal drip, nasal obstruction, facial pain and pressure, lack of sense of smell) that has been previously persistent for greater than 3 months AND
(3)	are over 18 years of age AND
(4)	are able to give written informed consent AND
(5)	are local patients who will be returning to this centre for postoperative follow-up care
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(1)	allergy to shellfish, steroids or mupirocin
(2)	pregnant or breastfeeding
(3)	immunodeficient patients (patients on any immunosuppressive or immunomodulatory agent)
(4)	on other CYP450 inhibiting drugs (e.g. ketoconazole, ritonavir, atazanavir, clarithromycin, indinavir, itraconazole, nefazodone, nelfinavir, saquinavir and telithromycin)
(5)	liver disease</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomised by GraphPad Quickcalcs software (http://www.graphpad.com/quickcalcs/index.cfm) to be a part of either the test group 1, test group 2 or control group</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>We will be recruiting a total of 57 patients for this study. 

Power analysis estimates a sample size of 19 patients per arm would be required to achieve statistical significance (80%, p = 0.05), based on response rates of 25% in control group and 70% in treatment group, as well as accounting for a 10% drop out rate.

This 70% treatment response rate may represent an underestimation as previous study conducted showed 88.9% of patients were culture negative following mupirocin sinus rinses (Jervis-Bardy et al, 2012). We have done this because it would be the first time we would be using Chitodex gel as a drug vehicle for Mupirocin and by doing so it would increase our probability of detecting smaller clinical responses.  For the control group, the 25% response rate estimation is based on clinical observation that chronically infected patients have responded poorly to conventional therapy. 


All results will be statistically analysed at the completion of the study. The proposed statistical test will be 2-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) and Students t-test, with a significance value set at p&lt;0.05. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1 / Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/11/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/11/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>57</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/05/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital - Woodville</hospital>
    <hospital>Memorial Hospital - North Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>5011 - Woodville</postcode>
    <postcode>5006 - North Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital
28 Woodville Rd,
Woodville South, 5011
South Australia, Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Adelaide</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department Otorhinolaryngology 
3C Level 3 Main Building, The Queen Elizabeth Hospital, 28 Woodville Road, Woodville 5011, South Australia, Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This research is aimed at improving outcomes for patients with chronic rhinosinusitis post endoscopic sinus surgery. A dissolvable dressing Chitodex (CD) gel has already been known to be beneficial to postoperative bleeding and healing after endoscopic sinus surgery. We aim to further improve its effects by combining the current formulation with budesonide (a steroid solution) and mupirocin (an antibacterial agent). 

We have specifically targeted patients in the immediate post endoscopic sinus surgery setting because in previous studies, we have found that biofilm-positive patients compared to biofilm-negative patients have worse outcome post surgery in both symptoms and nasoendoscopy scores, requiring repeated courses of antibiotic treatment and extra postoperative visits (Singhal et al 2008). 

Therefore in this study we hope to investigate if the eradication of biofilms combined with the improved wound healing properties of using Chitodex gel incorporated with mupirocin and budesonide (CBM gel) could prevent patients from progressing to the subset of recalcitrant disease.

The specific aims of this study is to 
1. To investigate the effects of Chitodex + Budesonide + Mupirocin (CBM) gel in post sinonasal surgery patients with chronic rhinosinusitis (CRS)
2. Compare the change in nasal microbiome post endoscopic sinus surgery

The primary end point is measured by:
1) Eradication of bacteria confirmed with microbiological swab
2) Independently scored video endoscopic examination of sinuses pre and post treatment
3) Patient's symptoms score pre and post treatment

The secondary end point is to:
1. Compare the change in nasal microbiome post endoscopic sinus surgery
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>	The Queen Elizabeth Hospital, Lyell McEwin Hospital and Modbury Hospital HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital
Ethics: DX465101
Ground Floor, Basil Hetzel Institute
28 Woodville Road
WOODVILLE SOUTH SA 5011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>31/10/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec> HREC/15/TQEH/174  Q20161009</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/09/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter John Wormald</name>
      <address>Department of Otorhinolaryngology
The Queen Elizabeth Hospital
28 Woodville Rd,
Woodville South 5011
South Australia
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 7158</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peterj.wormald@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mian Ooi</name>
      <address>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital
28 Woodville Rd,
Woodville South 5011
South Australia
Australia</address>
      <phone>+618 8222 7158</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mianli.ooi@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mian Ooi</name>
      <address>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital
28 Woodville Rd,
Woodville South 5011
South Australia
Australia</address>
      <phone>+618 8222 7158</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mianli.ooi@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mian Ooi</name>
      <address>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital
28 Woodville Rd,
Woodville South 5011
South Australia
Australia</address>
      <phone>+618 8222 7158</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mianli.ooi@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>