<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362557">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/05/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/06/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000613808</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Planning, timing and quit success: A randomised controlled trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In smokers using a web-based intervention to quit, does a recommendation to implement the quit attempt immediately and/or adherence to a structured planning protocol increase the likelihood of achieving 6-month sustained abstinence?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1131-2505</utrn>
    <trialacronym>QIPT (Quitting Immediately and/or Planning Trial)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Tobacco use, addiction and abstention</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study is a 2x2 crossover trial, with participants allocated to intervention or control on both of the following arms:

Arm 1: Immediate implementation: In this arm smokers will be encouraged (recommended) to quit immediately, or as soon as practically possible (e.g., if they need to obtain medication or use it for a period before actually quitting). Those who have already decided to quit will be encouraged to implement their decision immediately. Others will be encouraged to take the next step toward quitting as soon as possible (this may involve getting medication), and implement the quit attempt immediately they have done so.  These recommendations will take place via questions in the automated QuitCoach assessment, each time the participant completes the assesment. The control aspect of this is to quit in their own time, without any systematic encouragement to bring it forward.

Arm 2: Structured Planning intervention: The structured planning augmentation of the QuitCoach will consist of highly prescriptive instructions for planning a quit attempt. Key aspects of the structured planning intervention are informed by the theory of implementation intentions.  It will be delivered via modifications and additions to the basic QuitCoach tailored advice, and through a section of the QuitCoach website containing a set of tools to facilitate implementation. The control condition will receive the basic QuitCoach.

Participants can be randomised to either: No immediate implementation nor structured planning; no immediate implementation but receiving structured planning; receiving recommendation to quit immediately but no structured planning; or receiving both interventions.

Regardless of to which of the four possible study arms the participant has been randomised, frequency of use of the QuitCoach is at the discretion of the participant. Thus, there is no set endpoint for delivery of the intervention. All participants will be reminded to return via emails sent periodically over several weeks and scheduled according to their readiness to quit, but we anticipate that most will complete the assessment only once (when they join the study). It is possible that those allocated to receive the structured planning intervention will return more frequently, as for this group the QuitCoach will include a greater selection of tools potentially motivating return.</interventions>
    <comparator>Active control  standard treatment (public version of QuitCoach program and associated resources)</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sustained abstinence, reported having quit for 6 months and no reported smoking at all in last week. Assessed via a web-based questionnaire following an emailed invitation to complete; failures to respond will be phoned to complete the assessment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>TP: 6 months after quit date</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Making a quit attempt. Assessed via a web-based questionnaire following an emailed invitation to complete; failures to respond will be phoned to complete the assessment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The initial (2-week) follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Point prevalence (7 days) quit. Assessed via a web-based questionnaire following an emailed invitation to complete; failures to respond will be phoned to complete the assessment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The initial (2-week) follow-up, and at 6 months follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Smokers who want to quit, who are using the QuitCoach, and at recruitment have not committed to a quit attempt in the next day.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Non-smokers, ex-smokers, people not ready to quit (defined as reporting not planning to make a quit attempt in the next month), or who are on the brink of quitting (&lt;24 hours), and those reporting a mental health condition for which they are taking medication.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All participants will be recruited from users of the QuitCoach. QuitCoach users complete a 10-minute assessment of their smoking and quit intentions and on this basis receive a detailed personalised quit plan. We will be recruiting via a question inserted into the QuitCoach assessment, on interest in participating in a study designed to improve the program and to better understand what determines the likelihood of quit attempts succeeding. Randomization is via a hidden binary number generator in the on-line recruitment survey. Following randomization this the questionnaire varies somewhat, including most of the elements of the Immediate Implementation arm and some elements of the Structured Planning arm which are delivered to those eligible. Participants know what they are receiving, but not about the alternatives.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation is via a hidden binary number generator in the on-line recruitment survey which is activated after the person consents, allocating a code of 0 or 1 for each arm of the study (i.e., 0,0 = neither immediate implementation nor structured planning; 0,1 = no immediate implementation, receiving structured planning; 1,0 = receiving recommendation to quit immediately but no structured planning; 1,1 = receiving both interventions.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Factorial</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>23/05/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>2400</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Ron Borland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Cancer Council Victoria, 1 Rathdowne St, Carlton Vic 3053</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council, GPO Box 1421, Canberra ACT 2601, Australia.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>James Balmford</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Cancer Council Victoria, 1 Rathdowne St, Carlton Vic 3053</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Elena Swift</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Cancer Council Victoria, 1 Rathdowne St, Carlton Vic 3053</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>It is currently unclear whether there is a benefit for smokers to act immediately on impulses to quit smoking, and if so, whether delay is detrimental in its own right, or only if the time is not used productively for appropriate planning. It is also unclear whether planning can effectively be carried out after quitting, allowing smokers to quit spontaneously yet still effectively plan for the maintenance of their attempt. The study is designed to untangle these issues, specifically exploring the benefit of structured support and the possible positive effects of recommending immediate implementation, apart from any delay required by the help to be used (e.g., medications that need to be used for a period before quitting).

We hypothesize that among smokers who seek help, 6-month sustained abstinence assessed on an intention-to-treat basis will be greater among:     
1. Those encouraged to quit immediately as compared with those encouraged to quit to their own timetable; 
2.  Those who are provided with a structured planning program based around the development of implementation intentions (if-then statements designed to increase the likelihood that a goal is attained), as compared with those only provided motivational messages and general encouragement to plan; 
3.  And that these two effects will be independent. 
We will also explore the outcomes as a function of compliance with the recommended strategies, and whether the trial outcomes differ for different outcome measures (e.g. point-prevalence cessation, different imputation strategies for dealing with missing cases).</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Cancer Council Victoria Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Cancer Council Victoria, 1 Rathdowne St, Carlton VIC 3053</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>1108</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ron Borland</name>
      <address>Cancer Council Victoria, 1 Rathdowne St, Carlton, VIC, 3053</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9635 5185</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9635 5440</fax>
      <email>Ron.Borland@cancervic.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ron Borland</name>
      <address>Cancer Council Victoria, 1 Rathdowne St, Carlton, VIC, 3053</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9635 5185</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9635 5440</fax>
      <email>Ron.Borland@cancervic.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ron Borland</name>
      <address>Cancer Council Victoria, 1 Rathdowne St, Carlton, VIC, 3053</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9635 5185</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9635 5440</fax>
      <email>Ron.Borland@cancervic.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>