<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368259">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/03/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/05/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000415505</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A pilot study of inferential comprehension intervention for children with specific language impairment.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>For pre-primary age children with specific language impairment, does an oral inferential comprehension programme lead to improved oral inferential comprehension skills compared to a control phonological awareness treatment.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1168-7660 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Specific Language Impairment</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Speech therapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The participants will be randomly allocated to one of two intervention groups (the oral inferential comprehension (OIC) intervention or the comparison intervention targeting phonological awareness (PA)). The participants will then take part in the intervention, implemented by the researcher.
The intervention will run over an 8 week period during Term 3, 2015, from Week 2 to Week 9. During this time, the intervention will be provided to each group of four children two times per week, for sessions of approximately 30 minutes. The interventions will be run by the researcher (a qualified speech pathologist) and will be included as a part of the weekly classroom activities for the participants involved. 
The OIC intervention sessions will focus on the explicit instruction and practice of narrative macrostructure (drawing on components of a commercial programme: Braidy the StoryBraid (Trademark) ) (Moreau &amp; Zagula, 2002) and narrative microstructure concepts. The intervention has been designed based on the intervention principles pertaining to the large body of research in speech pathology journals regarding interventions for children with specific language impairment (e.g. duration and intensity of intervention sessions, appropriacy of intervention activities, etc).  As such, the activities involved in the intervention will be appropriate for the age and the population and will be highly engaging and rewarding for the participants (e.g. small group interactive reading of storybooks, role-playing with puppets, etc).</interventions>
    <comparator>The PA intervention will focus on the explicit instruction and practice of phonological awareness skills (such as rhyme, phoneme identity, segmentation and blending) based on the Gillon Phonological Awareness Training (PAT) Programme (Gillon, 2008).
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pre- and post treatment data collection will include measures of:
Inferential and literal comprehension of narrative using the Squirrel Story Narrative Assessment on iPad (Carey, Leitao, &amp; Allan, 2006) which includes the Narrative Comprehension of Picture Books questions (NC task) (Paris &amp; Paris, 2003). 


</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment will be carried out in the week prior to intervention commencing and post-treatment will be carried out in the week following intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pre- and post treatment data collection will include measures of:
Phonological awareness skills as measured by the Preschool and Primary Inventory of Phonological Awareness (PIPA) (Ozanne et al, 2000).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment will be carried out in the week prior to intervention commencing and post-treatment will be carried out in the week following intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>N/A</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The participants in this study will be recruited from a Language Development Centre (LDC) in metropolitan Perth and therefore have a diagnosis of specific language impairment. Participants will be both male and female and will be in pre-primary (aged 4;6 to 5;6, years;months). 
The study will recruit a minimum of 40 children as participants. In addition to their current enrolment in pre-primary at an LDC, participants will meet the following selection criteria:
1.	English as a primary language (identified by parents on the consent form). 
2.	Intelligible speech at discourse level</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>4</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>6</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria = evidence of significant hearing, vision, behavioural, language and educational or medical issues.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by computer will be used to allocate participants, once consent has been received, to two equally sized groups . Allocation will be determined by the Random Sequence Generator at www.random.org</concealment>
    <sequence>Following consent, each participant will complete an initial assessment session (20-30 minutes, including breaks) with the researcher. 

The participants then will be randomly allocated to one of two intervention groups (the inferential comprehension intervention or the comparison intervention targeting phonological awareness). 

Randomisation to two equally sized groups will be determined by the Random Sequence Generator at www.random.org</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>This research aims to evaluate the effectiveness of an intervention created to improve oral inferential comprehension (based on the findings of Study 1 which was a descriptive profiling study) in young children with specific language impairment.  Study 2 will involve developing and piloting an intervention targeted at improving oral inferential comprehension in a small randomised controlled trial of children with specific language impairment. Participants will be randomly allocated to the oral inferential comprehension treatment (OIC) or the comparison phonological awareness treatment (PA) conditions.

There will be a significant Group x Condition interaction between T1 and T3 such that: 
Hypothesis 2a: Compared to the PA control group, the OIC intervention group will show significantly greater T1 to T2 increase in oral inferential comprehension scores. 
Hypothesis 2b: The intervention groups T1 to T2 increase in oral inferential
comprehension scores will be maintained at T3.
Hypothesis 3a:  The proportion of individuals showing a positive reliable 
change in oral inferential comprehension score between T1 and T2 will be significantly greater for the OIC intervention group.
Hypotheses 2a  2b will be tested using a Generalised Linear Mixed Model (GLMM). The GLMM will be implemented through SPSSs (Version 22) GENLINMIXED procedure. The GLMM will include one nominal random effect (participant), one categorical fixed effect (group: intervention versus control), one ordinal fixed effect (time: T1  T3), and the Group x Time interaction. Violations of sphericity (associated with multiple assessments of the same individuals) will be accommodated by changing the covariance matrix from the default of compound symmetry to autoregressive. Twenty participants in each of the two groups should provide an 80% chance of capturing moderate (f = .19) intervention effects at an alpha-level of .05.
Hypothesis 3a will be tested by computing a T1-T2 reliable change (RC) score for each participant on the outcome measures. The RC score is the degree to which the participant changes on the outcome variable (oral inferential comprehension score) divided by the standard error of difference between the T1 and T2 scores (Jacobson &amp; Truax, 1991). When the absolute value of the RC score is greater than 1.96, it is likely that the post-test score reflects a real or reliable change. It has been argued that this value can be reduced in some situations (Wise, 2004). The proportion of individuals showing a reliable T1-T2 change in the intervention group will be compared to the proportion of individuals showing such a change in the control group. The statistical significance of the comparison will be estimated with a binary logistic GLMM model which will include the fixed nominal predictor (group: intervention, control) and the binary outcome (reliable change: yes, no).  Computation of the RC score for a particular outcome will require estimates of the outcomes reliability and variability for a population of individuals similar to the target population sampled. The Cronbachs alpha and standard deviation from Study 1 will be used as an estimate of reliability and variability. These analyses will be used to address the third research question. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>25/05/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Curtin University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth
WA
6845</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Curtin University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth
WA
6845
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There is currently a lack of research investigating interventions which target oral inferential comprehension in children with specific language impairment (SLI). This is despite the knowledge that children with SLI demonstrate poor oral inferential comprehension, and the evidence showing the importance of this skill for later reading comprehension and learning.

Therefore, this study will involve developing and piloting an intervention targeted at improving oral inferential comprehension in a small randomised controlled trial of children with specific language impairment. The intervention is evidence-based, designed based on the intervention principles pertaining to the large body of research in speech pathology journals regarding interventions for children with specific language impairment . The findings will therefore add to the evidence-base of interventions and effective practice in the area of language comprehension, leading to improved long-term language and literacy outcomes for children with specific language impairment.
The participants will be randomly allocated to one of two intervention groups (the inferential comprehension intervention or the comparison intervention targeting phonological awareness). The participants will then take part in the intervention, implemented by the researcher. The intervention will involve small group (4 children) activities, for approximately 30 minutes, twice per week for 8 weeks over the course of one Term.
It is anticipated that the participants receiving the inferential comprehension intervention will demonstrate a significant improvement in their oral inferential comprehension compared to the participants receiving the phonological awareness intervention. It is also anticipated that the participants receiving the phonological awareness intervention will demonstrate a significant increase in their phonological awareness skills compared to the participants receiving the inferential comprehension intervention.
This finding will provide preliminary support for the effectiveness of oral inferential comprehension intervention with this age group and population, and inform the practice of speech pathologists and educators working with children with SLI.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin University HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics Committee
Office of Research &amp; Development
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth
WA 6845</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/03/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Suze Leitao</name>
      <address>School of Psychology &amp; Speech Pathology 
Curtin University GPO Box U1987
Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+ 61 8 9266 7620</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>S.Leitao@Curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Suze Leitao</name>
      <address>School of Psychology &amp; Speech Pathology 
Curtin University GPO Box U1987
Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+ 61 8 9266 7620</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>S.Leitao@Curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Suze Leitao</name>
      <address>School of Psychology &amp; Speech Pathology 
Curtin University GPO Box U1987
Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+ 61 8 9266 7620</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>S.Leitao@Curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Suze Leitao</name>
      <address>School of Psychology &amp; Speech Pathology 
Curtin University GPO Box U1987
Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+ 61 8 9266 7620</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>S.Leitao@Curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>