<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373453">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/08/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/08/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001180303</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Abdominal Functional Electrical Stimulation To Assist Ventilator Weaning In Critically Ill Patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Abdominal Functional Electrical Stimulation To Assist Ventilator Weaning In Critically Ill Patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1200-4986</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Critical Illness</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Sepsis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Traumatic Brain Injury</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The abdominal muscles are the primary muscle group used during forced exhalation. We have shown that surface Functional Electrical Stimulation (FES) of the abdominal muscles, termed Abdominal FES, can improve respiratory function and assist weaning from mechanical ventilation in spinal cord injury. A pilot study of 11 ventilated critically ill patients found Abdominal FES maintained abdominal muscle thickness and decreased ventilation duration, however the sample size was too small to achieve statistical significance. We hypothesise that Abdominal FES in critically ill patients will reduce diaphragm and abdominal muscle atrophy, with the long term goal of this project to demonstrate reduced mechanical ventilation duration.

Twenty critically ill patients being treated in the Intensive Care Unit (ICU) of the Prince of Wales Hospital, Sydney, will be recruited to this randomised, placebo controlled pilot trial. Participants will be recruited who are mechanically ventilated and are expected to remain that way for at least 48 hours. Ten patients will be randomly allocated to receive Abdominal FES and 10 will receive a placebo. In the Abdominal FES group, Abdominal FES will be applied for 30 minutes, twice per day, 5 days per week, until the patient is  discharged from the ICU.

Specifically, Abdominal FES will be delivered, via electrodes placed over the surface of the abdomen, at a frequency of 30 Hz and a pulse width of 350 µs. These settings are based on previous trials. The stimulation amplitude will initially be set to 60 mA, which corresponds to 90% of the maximum amplitude that was tolerated by healthy volunteers in a previous study. If this amplitude results in discomfort to the patient (based on clinical judgement) then it will be reduced as necessary. In addition, the stimulation amplitude will be evaluated five and 20 minutes after the start of each session to ensure that stimulation is still tolerable and causing a suitable muscle contraction. Ultrasound will be used to verify whether stimulation results in a contraction of the abdominal muscles during the first Abdominal FES session.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants in the placebo group will receive sham Abdominal FES for 30 minutes, twice per day, five days per week, until discharge from the intensive care unit. Placebo Abdominal FES will be similar to active FES in all respects except for the simulation intensity, which will be kept to a level which does not cause a muscle contraction.

Specifically, stimulation pulses will be delivered at a frequency of 10 Hz, a pulsewidth of 50 µs and at a low current amplitude that does not cause abdominal muscle contraction, verified with ultrasound. These settings were chosen so that participants experience the sensation of Abdominal FES without an abdominal muscle contraction. Initially, 10 mA of current will be applied and, if necessary, will be lowered in steps of 2 mA until no muscle contraction is seen with ultrasound.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Thickness of the abdominal muscles as measured by ultrasound</outcome>
      <timepoint>48 hours after initiation of mechanical ventilation compared to when breathing independently of mechanical ventilation for 24 hours</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility as measured by patient compliance, time needed to recruit patients, time needed to collect data, proportion of eligible patients of total ICU population, withdrawal rate and effectiveness of blinding</outcome>
      <timepoint>Final day of patient enrolment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Thickness of the diaphragm as measured by ultrasound</outcome>
      <timepoint>48 hours after initiation of mechanical ventilation compared to when breathing independently of mechanical ventilation for 24 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Echogenicity of the abdominal wall muscles as measured by ultrasound</outcome>
      <timepoint>48 hours after initiation of mechanical ventilation compared to when breathing independently of mechanical ventilation for 24 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximum expiratory pressure (MEP) measured using spirometry</outcome>
      <timepoint>when breathing independently of mechanical ventilation for 24 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximum inspiratory pressure measured using spirometry</outcome>
      <timepoint>when breathing independently of mechanical ventilation for 24 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Peak expiratory flow measured using spirometry</outcome>
      <timepoint>when breathing independently of mechanical ventilation for 24 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Vital capacity measured using spirometry</outcome>
      <timepoint>when breathing independently of mechanical ventilation for 24 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time spent dependent on mechanical ventilation</outcome>
      <timepoint>when breathing independently of mechanical ventilation for 24 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Systemic inflammatory markers (IL-6, IL-1, IL-8) as measured by blood test</outcome>
      <timepoint>48 hours after initiation of mechanical ventilation compared to after 3 days of Abdominal FES</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time in Intensive Care Unit (ICU)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At ICU discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Re-intubations in intensive care</outcome>
      <timepoint>Discharge from Intensive Care Unit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life during and after mechanical ventilation as measured by SF-36 questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours after extubation and at ICU discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>mechanical ventilation dependence due to critical illness</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>pregnancy
expected to be ventilated for &lt; 24 hours (based on clinical judgement)
ventilated for &gt; 72 hours (to avoid excessive muscle atrophy)
non-pharmacological paralysis (e.g. spinal cord injury or Guillain-Barré syndrome)
physical obstacles that prevent Abdominal FES (e.g. severe abdominal trauma, pacemaker)
terminal illness
no response to Abdominal FES (e.g. lower motor neuron impairment)
recent abdominal surgery within four weeks prior to study inclusion
no clearly visible separate layers of the abdominal muscles (external oblique, internal oblique and transverse abdominal muscles), assessed with ultrasound during routine care</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Each participant will be randomly assigned to active or placebo Abdominal FES in a 1:1 ratio using a random, secure, web-based program (SecureTrial) by an independent investigator</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomised computerised sequence generation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Study results will first undergo descriptive level statistical analyses. For continuous variables, Two-way, Students t-tests will then be carried out using unequal variances where the variables are normally distributed. Tests for normality will be carried out using the Shapiro-Wilk method. Variables that are not normal in distribution that also cannot be log transformed to a normal distribution curve will be analysed using the Mann-Whitney U test or other non-parametric methods to be determined based on actual data distributions. For repeated measures, analysis of variance will be considered where methodologically appropriate.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/08/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/08/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Prince of Wales Hospital - Randwick</hospital>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Neuroscience Research Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>139 Barker Street 
Randwick 
NSW 2031</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Liberate Medical LLC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>6400 Westwind Way, Suite A
Crestwood, KY 40014</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Academy of Technology and Engineering</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1 / 1 Bowen Crescent, Melbourne Vic 3004</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary objective of this study is to investigate whether Abdominal Functional Electrical Stimulation (Abdominal FES) can prevent abdominal muscle atrophy during mechanical ventilation in critically ill patients. If feasible, data will be used to design a second, larger trial on clinically relevant endpoints. The secondary objectives of this study are to analyse whether this intervention also affects: (1) the thickness of the diaphragm, (2) respiratory function, (3) ventilation duration, (4) markers for systemic inflammation, (5) Intensive Care Unit (ICU) length of stay, (6) ICU and hospital representations, (7) re-intubations, (8) mortality and (9) quality of life.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Eastern Sydney Local Health District Human Research Ethics Committe</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Support Office
G71, East Wing 
Edmund Blacket Building
Prince of Wales Hospital
Randwick NSW 2031 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/07/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>17/050</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/05/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Euan McCaughey</name>
      <address>Neuroscience Research Australia
139 Barker Street
Randwick
NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9399 1827</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.mccaughey@neura.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Euan McCaughey</name>
      <address>Neuroscience Research Australia
139 Barker Street
Randwick
NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9399 1827</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.mccaughey@neura.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Euan McCaughey</name>
      <address>Neuroscience Research Australia
139 Barker Street
Randwick
NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9399 1827</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.mccaughey@neura.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>