<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373232">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/07/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001035314p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>CyFiT Telerehabilitation: Technology based physiotherapy for peer driven participation in therapy, and quality of life.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>CyFiT Telerehabilitation:  Investigation into the efficacy of a telehealth physiotherapy intervention on quality of life and community participation for school-aged children with cystic fibrosis, a randomised controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>CyFiT = CyFiT Telerehabilitation Trial</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>N/A
</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cystic Fibrosis
</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human Genetics and Inherited Disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Cystic fibrosis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All participants 
Participants will be randomised to either the Standard Control group or the CyFiT Telerehab Group.  All participants will partake in four one hour assessment sessions taking place on a six monthly basis from the commencement of the study: initial (0 months), 6 months, 12 months, and 6 months follow up (i.e. 18months post initial commencement).  During this time, reassessment of outcome measures will be completed with research clinicians.  For patient convenience, reassessments will be scheduled on the day of multi-disciplinary clinic reviews.  Participants and families will be notified of their group allocation prior to the initial assessment session.  

CyFiT Telerehab Group
Children will be provided with a consumer-based activity tracker to wear every day, including sleeping.  A patient login to the CyFiT Telerehab Online Portal (website) will also be provided to families.  During the initial assessment, the research clinician will demonstrate how to use the activity tracker as well as navigating the website. 
Data collected by the activity tracker will be aggregated to a secure database where summaries are presented via an online dashboards available for patients and treating clinicians.  This portal will provide information to the treating clinician to assist them in determining if further physiotherapy intervention is required. Data will be retrieved from activity trackers on a daily bases, however frequency can be increased to every 30 seconds if required.  Increased frequency enables clinicians to have access to near-real-time physiological data during real-time video-conference consultations.  Additional physiotherapy follow up will be protocol triggered as per standard practice.  Common rationales that would indicate a need for further follow up includes: post-inpatient follow-up, equipment reviews post equipment prescription (e.g. changes to positive expiratory pressure mask settings), and adherence based sessions.  An additional option for clinician initiated consultation to at-risk patients based on deteriorating physiological data aggregated from activity trackers.  This information is available to clinicians through a computer based dashboard.  Physiotherapy consultations will be delivered via real-time video conferencing into the home with the same rationale as standard care.   Intervention group's exercise diary will be replaced by wearable consumer based activity trackers, allowing participants and clinicians to review recent activity progress through online web based portals.   
Children deemed appropriate will also be referred to a weekly supervised group exercise class where children of similar age and function will undertake group physiotherapy sessions over a multi-point video conference into the home.  A physiotherapist will be constantly supervising a class of no more than 6 participants in these classes and providing individualised therapeutic advices during this time.  Each session will be 1 hour in duration, and frequency will vary from classes to classes based on individual patient needs via the same rationales for additional physiotherapy follow up. 
A moderated virtual exercise room is also available for patients of similar ages and physical function on a weekly basis to attend.  These unstructured sessions are designed to prompt social interaction and peer-driven therapy where the group collectively work towards a common goal (e.g. attain a total of 100,000 steps per week) or through a workout regime.  Duration of exercise room will vary based on the current goal/task (formulated by treating physiotherapist), instead the rooms operate more towards an "open/closing" time, where participant can freely join/exit and re-join during this period.  For example, longer activities (e.g. 100,000steps/week) rooms may be open every afternoon from 3pm to 5pm for a week.  Whereas shorter activities (e.g. a workout routine taking 20minutes), rooms may be open from 3pm to 4pm on Monday each week.  Clinicians will not directly supervise these open times, but rather review statistics such as attendance rate, % of task completed as well as responding to feedback from users through a short web survey.
Children in the intervention arm will be provided with a wrist-based consumer activity tracker, and is expected to have access to a mobile, tablet, or computer device with access to internet and audiovisual recording capabilities.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Children allocated to the control group will receive current standard of physiotherapy care from Lady Cilento Children's Hospital

Standard Control Group
Children and family will participate in the initial assessment by research clinician.
Additional physiotherapy follow up outside these clinics will be provided at Lady Cilento Children's Hospital if a child's condition warrants additional physiotherapy interventions.  A home exercise program will be performed independently and recorded via a self-reported paper-based exercise diary.  Further physiotherapy follow up will be indicated to families during 3-monthly multi-disciplinary reviews, or follow up consultations post inpatient stay; rationale for frequency, dose and care plan will be individually reasoned by treated clinician on individual patient-to-patient basis.   Common rationales that would indicate a need for further follow up includes: post-inpatient follow-up, fine-tuning of home therapy sessions, equipment reviews when new equipment is prescribed (e.g. changes to positive expiratory pressure mask settings), and adherence based sessions.  </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Modified Shuttle Walk Test a standardised functional exercise capacity test for young people with CF </outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 6 Months for 18 months, Baseline (0 month), 6 months, 12 months and 18 months post-intervention commencement, etc.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cystic Fibrosis Questionnaire - Revised (CFQ-R) a quality of life measure for young people and families with CF</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 6 Months for 18 months, Baseline (0 month), 6 months, 12 months and 18 months post-intervention commencement,.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospitalisation Rate:
Number of inpatient days spent during the 12 months period of intervention.  This will be accessed by the review of medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 12 months post intervention commencement </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self Reported Exercise Diary, self reported amount of exercise over past week</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weekly across 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure of Processes of Care (MPOC) assessment will be used to assess quality of care provided by the health service from a patient's perspective</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 6 Months for 18 months, Baseline (0 month), 6 months, 12 months and 18 months post-intervention commencement,. This is a standardized questionnaire which patients will fill out on re-assessment sessions for the trial</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>CAPE-PAC Assessment measures the quantity of participation in activities of daily living.  This outcome will complement Outcome 5 to provide quality and quantity of social participation</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 6 Months for 18 months, Baseline (0 month), 6 months, 12 months and 18 months post-intervention commencement,.  This is a standardized questionnaire which patients will fill out on re-assessment sessions for the trial</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Life-H Assessment assessing the quality of social participation of patient in daily living.  The assessment is designed to complement Outcome 4 (CAPE-PAC) to enable both quality and quantity of social participation.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 6 Months for 18 months, Baseline (0 month), 6 months, 12 months and 18 months post-intervention commencement,.  This is a standardized questionnaire which patients will fill out on re-assessment sessions for the trial</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Economic Feasibility will be assessed using medical record, as well as patient information such as time off work/school for clinical visit, travel costs, cost of equipment/connection costs to determine an overall cost of service, this will then be analyses in context of all other outcome measures such as quality of life (Cystic Fibrosis Questionnaire - Revised), physical function (Modified Shuttle Test), and participation (CAPE-PAC and Life-H Assessment)  to enable the calculation of quality-adjusted life years and enable cost-utility and/or cost-benefit statistical analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 12 months post intervention commencement </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence to exercise therapy, clinical consultation visits.
Data from activity trackers, medical record, and record generated from clinical consultations will be used to determine patient adherence to physiotherapy exercises, and adherence to physiotherapy consultations</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 12 months post intervention commencement </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Computer System Usability Questionnaire and NASA task load Index will be used to assess the user friendliness of the software component.,</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 6 Months for 18 months, Baseline (0 month), 6 months, 12 months and 18 months post-intervention commencement,.  This is a standardized questionnaire which patients will fill out on re-assessment sessions for the trial</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Medically Diagnosed with Cystic Fibrosis</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>8</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Co-morbidity with CF that would otherwise be unsuitable fore telehealth
Intellectual disability
Neurological conditions e.g. Cerebral palsy
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Once eight participants in the same age bracket is recruited, each participants will be randomly assigned to either CyFiT Telerehab arm or the Standard Control Arm via drawing of one of the opaque envelopes. This process will continue until 110 participants are recruited.</concealment>
    <sequence>A random sequence will be generated via a computer-based random numbers generator (Microsoft® Excel® 2013 15.03.4927.1000) by chief investigator using the default rand() function to generate a value between 0 and 1. The outcome are as follow: 
 	&lt;0.5	=	CyFiT Telehealth Intervention
 	=0.5	=	Standard Control Group 
The outcome (above) will be written in a piece of paper and concealed inside a sequentially numbered, opaque envelope and stored securely offsite.
Consenting participants will be randomised into either the CyFiT Telerehab intervention group or the Standard Control group. To ensure an equal number of participants in either intervention group, a random permuted block design with a fixed size of 8 will be utilized with participant stratification on age as follow:
	Primary 		(8 to 11 years old)
 	Middle 		(12 to 15 years old) 
  	Senior		 	(16 to 18 years old)
</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Statistical analysis will be performed by the chief investigator using SPSS statistical software.  Primary analysis will use the intention to treat principle, using the last observation recorded for participants who withdraw from the program. Baseline data will be statistically analysed through a linear model to establish any difference between the groups at baseline.  If characteristics are not comparable at baseline, they will be modelled as covariates in subsequent analyses in order to adjust their possible confounding effects. Linear mixed models will be used to evaluate the effectiveness of the CyFiT intervention compared to the standard care control on the primary outcome (e.g. Modified Shuttle Test and Cystic Fibrosis Questionnaire  Revised). Linear mixed models take into account variation in individuals over time, are able to manage missing data without excluding participants for further analysis and examine changes in the outcomes over time as well as across the two groups. Significance will be set at p&lt;0.05. Residuals of the fitted models will be examined to ensure that all required assumptions are met.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/07/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>110</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/07/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Lady Cilento Children's Hospital - South Brisbane</hospital>
    <postcode>4101 - South Brisbane</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
Building 84A
The University of Queensland
Queensland, St Lucia 4072</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Health Practitioner Research Scheme 2017 Funding Round - Department of Health Allied Health Professions' Office of Queensland (Queensland Health)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1, 15 Butterfield Street
Herston Qld 4006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Lady Cilento Children's Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>501 Stanley Street 
South Brisbane, QLD,  4101</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Children with cystic fibrosis (CF) need to spend a lot of time on physiotherapy. Families have very busy lives, and using telehealth may reduce the burden of management, and contribute to improved quality of life.  Telehealth offers home management with reduced travel requirements, saving time and money for families, and reducing the risk of hospital-acquired infections. Standards of care recommend that there are no interactions between people with CF due to cross infection risks.  Telehealth allows young people with CF to connect with each other, and safely do physiotherapy in a fun &amp; socially supportive environment. 
Aim: to investigate the clinical effectiveness &amp; impact of a purpose-designed telehealth service (CyFiT) in physiotherapy management of CF.  Our proposed research will investigate the comparison between CyFiT Intervention Group and standard outpatient physiotherapy for CF.  We hypothesise that there will be no difference in functional activity capacity, hospitalisation rate, or increased cost to health providers between the two groups, but there will be significant differences in quality of life and patient satisfaction measures.  
Research Design: Randomised controlled trial comparing CyFiT Intervention Group and standard outpatient physiotherapy. Balanced block design; 110 participants. All participants will receive the same physiotherapy care, at the same time that would otherwise occur. The difference is that participants will be randomly assigned to physiotherapy delivered face to face (standard outpatient physiotherapy), or at home through telehealth consultations and online group exercise classes (CyFiT Intervention Group).  Participants allocated to the CyFiT Intervention Group will be provided with a Garmin activity tracker. The tracked information will guide clinicians during individual and group sessions, and help identify deteriorations. The trial period will continue for 12 months, after which children will return to standard outpatient physiotherapy care. 
Methods: All participants in this study will receive 4x1 hour reassessment sessions (at 0, 6, 12, and 18 months post commencing the trial).  Appoints will align with their regular multi-disciplinary clinics every three monthly to minimise inconvenience for families.  Any additional follow-up physiotherapy will be delivered according to allocation to telehealth or control group. Outcome measures are:
-	Functional Exercise Capacity 
-	Quality of Life 
-	Quality &amp; Quantity of Social Participation 
-	Adherence to physiotherapy 
-	Hospitalisation Rate 
-	Cost Effectiveness/utility 
-	Perception of Service 
Previous researchers have commented on the efficacy of telehealth in managing CF.  
No researchers have directly replaced face to face physiotherapy with a comprehensive telehealth equivalent in an operating CF clinic.  Through this trial, researchers will investigate the effectiveness of CyFiT Telehealth to integrate into a contemporary and family centred clinic.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Children’s Health Queensland </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics Committee
Level 7, Centre for Childrens Health Research
Lady Cilento Childrens Hospital Precinct
62 Graham Street
South Brisbane QLD 4101</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/06/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Ray Lang</name>
      <address>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
Building 84A
The University of Queensland
St Lucia, QLD, 4072</address>
      <phone>+614 22 193 168</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lei.lang@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Ray Lang</name>
      <address>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
Building 84A
The University of Queensland
St Lucia, QLD, 4072</address>
      <phone>+614 22 193 168</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lei.lang@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Ray Lang</name>
      <address>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
Building 84A
The University of Queensland
St Lucia, QLD, 4072</address>
      <phone>+614 22 193 168</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lei.lang@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Ray Lang</name>
      <address>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
Building 84A
The University of Queensland
St Lucia, 4072</address>
      <phone>+614 22 193 168</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lei.lang@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>