<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363076">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/10/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/10/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001064897</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Lifestyle Engagement and Activity Program (LEAP) for Life project in community aged care</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of the Lifestyle Engagement and Activity Program (LEAP) for Life project on client engagement in community aged care</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>LEAP for Life</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Geriatrics</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Dementia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dementias</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>LEAP for Life will train case managers or coordinators over 3 hours on incorporating individualized activities into care plans.  Care workers will be trained on how to engage clients and implement individualised activities.  Skills will include improved conversation and listening skills, reminiscence, humour and play, Montessori, music and planning for special events.  Care workers will receive 9 hours of training in 4 sessions delivered quarterly.In addition, a change champion with lifestyle, occupational or diversional therapy experience, will be appointed within each site to assist case managers and care workers in preparing activities, and encourage incorporation of the newly learned skills into usual care.  This change champion, will be also be available to consult with case managers on care planning, and to work a buddy shift with care workers.</interventions>
    <comparator>This is a repeated measures single-arm within-subject design, across five aged care community service outlets.  Clients will be assessed at 6 months pre intervention (time -6), immediately before the start of training (time 0), 6 months after commencement of the training (time 6) and 12 months after commencement of the training (time 12).  All sites will receive the LEAP for Life training.  The change in outcome measures from prior to treatment to the start of treatment will be utilised as a within-subjects control.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The effects of LEAP on increasing engagement of clients by care workers.

Measure 1: An engagement questionnaire developed for the study based on the Cohen-Mansfield's Observational Measure of Engagement (2009), to be completed by care workers (see below): 
1)What proportion of times when you offer the client a social activity or social interaction does he/she accept? 
- Almost never accepts 
- Accepts about 25% of the time 
- Accepts about 50% of the time 
- Accepts about 75% of the time 
- Accepts most of the time

2)When you are with the client, what proportion of the time are they occupied or involved with you in an activity or conversation? By occupied and involved we mean that they are participating in, or watching what is happening.
- Almost none of the time 
- About 25% of the time 
- About 50% of the time
- About 75% of the time
- Most of the time

3)When the client is involved with you in conversation or social activity how much attention are they paying to you or the activity? 
- Not attentive 
- Somewhat attentive 
- Attentive 
- Very attentive

4) Is the client's attitude positive or negative towards your interactions?
- Very negative 
- Negative 
- Somewhat negative 
- Neutral 
- Somewhat positive 
- Positive 
- Very positive

5 a) How much of the time does the client interact appropriately and meaningfully with you? 
- None of the time 
- A little of the time 
- Some of the time 
- Most or all of the time

b) How appropriate is this engagement? 
- Very inappropriate 
- Inappropriate 
- Somewhat inappropriate 
- Neutral 
- Somewhat appropriate 
- Appropriate 
- Very appropriate

6. When the client interacts with you what proportion of the time do they actively participate by talking or physically joining in, and what proportion are they more passive and just watch or make very brief responses to questions? 
- Almost always passive 
- occasionally active, usually passive 
- active about half the time, 
- passive about half the time
- usually active, occasionally passive
- almost always active


Measure 2: A researcher rated questionnaire developed for the study on amount of engagement based on interviews with the client and family.  The researcher will ask questions such as: 
-What do you talk about with the care workers during their visits?
-When the care worker is doing the housework what do you do? Do you join in or talk to them while they are cleaning? 
-When the care worker is looking after your personal care, do you talk together? 
-When the care worker takes you out, do you talk together? What do you talk about? 
-Do you sometimes do something social or recreational together such as have a cup of tea or go for a walk?
When you and your care worker spend time talking together, how much do you enjoy this?
-When you and your care worker spend time doing things together, how much do you enjoy this?
-How much do you value the company of your care workers? Do you look forward to their company?
-Do you feel like the care workers take an interest in you and your life?  Do they ask you about yourself?
-How would you describe your care workers? 
-How well do you get on with your care workers?  Do you think of your care workers as friends?
-How do you feel after your care workers visits? Do you feel pretty happy, a bit annoyed, or no different really?
-Does time pass quicker when your care workers are around? 

Based on this interview, the researcher will rate the following questions on a Likert scale 1-5: 
1.Rate the amount of social conversation that client /family report experiencing
2.Rate the amount of recreational activities that client/family report experiencing?  
3.Based on both client/family report, rate how the client seems to feel  about any social conversation with their care workers
4.Based on both client/family report, rate how the client seems to feel  about any recreational activities with their care workers</outcome>
      <timepoint>Both measures at all timepoints: at 6 months pre training (time -6), immediately before the start of training (time 0), 6 months after commencement of the training (time 6) and 12 months after commencement of the training (time 12).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The effects  of LEAP on client satisfaction with  care.

Assessed by the Homecare satisfaction measure - care worker and case manager subscales (Geron SM, Smith K, Tennstedt S, et al. The Home Care Satisfaction Measure. The Journals of Gerontology Series B: Psychological Sciences and Social Sciences. 2000; 55: S259-S70).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At all timepoints: at 6 months pre training (time -6), immediately before the start of training (time 0), 6 months after commencement of the training (time 6) and 12 months after commencement of the training (time 12).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The effects of LEAP on client dysphoria/depression, for clients rated as depressed at baseline.

Measure 1: Geriatric Depression Scale ( J A Yesavage Geriatric Depression Scale Psychopharmacology Bulletin (1988) 24:4;709-711)

Measure 2: Dysphoria subscale of the Neuropsychiatric Inventory (de Medeiros et al. (2010). International Psychogeriatrics. 22(6): 984-994.)</outcome>
      <timepoint>All measures at all timepoints: at 6 months pre training (time -6), immediately before the start of training (time 0), 6 months after commencement of the training (time 6) and 12 months after commencement of the training (time 12).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The effect of LEAP on client loneliness, on clients assessed as lonely at baseline

Assessed by UCLA Loneliness Scale (Russell D, Peplau LA, Cutrona CE. The Revised UCLA Loneliness Scale: Concurrent and Discriminant Validity Evidence. J Pers Soc Psychol. 1980; 39: 472-80)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At all timepoints: at 6 months pre training (time -6), immediately before the start of training (time 0), 6 months after commencement of the training (time 6) and 12 months after commencement of the training (time 12).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The effect of LEAP on client agitation, on clients assessed as agitated at baseline

Measure 1: Agitation subscale of the Neuropsychiatric Inventory (de Medeiros et al. (2010). International Psychogeriatrics. 22(6): 984-994.)

Measure 2: Cohen-Mansfield Agitation Inventory - Relative (Cohen-Mansfield J. A description of agitation in a nursing home. J Gerontol. 1989; 44: M77-84)</outcome>
      <timepoint>All measures at all timepoints: at 6 months pre training (time -6), immediately before the start of training (time 0), 6 months after commencement of the training (time 6) and 12 months after commencement of the training (time 12).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The effect of LEAP on client apathy on clients assessed as apathetic at baseline

Measure 1: Apathy subscale of the Neuropsychiatric Inventory (de Medeiros et al. (2010). International Psychogeriatrics. 22(6): 984-994.)

Measure 2: Apathy Evaluation Scale - self and proxy versions (RS Marin, RC Biedrzycki, S Firinciogullari: Reliability and Validity of the Apathy Evaluation Scale, Psychiatry Research, 38:143-162, 1991).</outcome>
      <timepoint>All measures at all timepoints: at 6 months pre training (time -6), immediately before the start of training (time 0), 6 months after commencement of the training (time 6) and 12 months after commencement of the training (time 12).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Clients receiving services from the five partner sites in New South Wales (Baptist Community Services - Liverpool; Baptist Community Services - Central Coast; Australian Nursing Home Foundation; Multicultural Community Care Service; and the Whiddon Group - Glenfield.  
- Clients receiving community aged care packages: CACP, EACH or EACH-D.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Clients will be ineligible if they are; 
- foreshadowed to stop accessing the service, 
- acutely unwell, 
- under public guardianship with no person responsible to consent on their behalf.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>NA</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>8/10/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>268</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>2178</postcode>
    <postcode>2171</postcode>
    <postcode>2170</postcode>
    <postcode>2168</postcode>
    <postcode>2162</postcode>
    <postcode>2176</postcode>
    <postcode>2256</postcode>
    <postcode>2257</postcode>
    <postcode>2250</postcode>
    <postcode>2251</postcode>
    <postcode>2165</postcode>
    <postcode>2166</postcode>
    <postcode>2136</postcode>
    <postcode>2134</postcode>
    <postcode>2194</postcode>
    <postcode>2200</postcode>
    <postcode>2007</postcode>
    <postcode>2194</postcode>
    <postcode>2167</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dementia Collaborative Research Centre, University of New South Wales</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>FAO: Dr. Lee-Fay Low,
Room 302, Level 3
AGSM Building (G27)
The University of New South Wales
UNSW SYDNEY NSW 2052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Encouraging Better Practice for Aged care (EBPAC), Department of Health and Ageing</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 9848,
Canberra ACT 2601, Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of Sydney</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>FAO: Associate Professor Yun-Hee Jeon,
Sydney Nursing School, Room A5.13, MO2, 88 Mallett Street, Camperdown, NSW, 2050</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Arts Health Institute</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>FAO: Dr. Maggie Haertsch,
Arts Health Institute, PO Box 1772, Newcastle, NSW, 2300.</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other Collaborative groups</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Centre for Applied Research in Dementia</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>FAO Dr. Cameron Camp,
34208 Aurora Road, #182 Solon, OH 44139.</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>United States of America</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>LEAP for Life is a training package for packaged community care staff which aims to improve engagement of clients by providing more individualised conversation and activities. This single arm trial will follow staff and their clients for 18 months, 6 months before the training begins, and across 12 months of training. Staff will be trained on how to incorporate engagement strategies and activities into care plans, and how to deliver these strategies and activities into practice. They will be supported by a change champion over 12 months.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of New South Wales Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>UNSW Grants Management Office
Rupert Myers Building, Level 3 (M15)

The University of New South Wales NSW 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>31/07/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HC12383</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr. Jess Baker</name>
      <address>Dementia Collaborative Research Centre
Room 304,  Level 3 AGSM Building 
University of New South Wales,
Sydney, NSW, 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 (0) 2 9385 2605</phone>
      <fax>Fax: + 61 (0)2 93852299</fax>
      <email>jessica.baker@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr. Jess Baker</name>
      <address>Dementia Collaborative Research Centre
Room 304,  Level 3 AGSM Building 
University of New South Wales,
Sydney, NSW, 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 (0) 2 9385 2605</phone>
      <fax>Fax: + 61 (0)2 93852299</fax>
      <email>jessica.baker@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Jess Baker</name>
      <address>Dementia Collaborative Research Centre
Room 304,  Level 3 AGSM Building 
University of New South Wales,
Sydney, NSW, 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 (0) 2 9385 2605</phone>
      <fax>Fax: + 61 (0)2 93852299</fax>
      <email>jessica.baker@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lee-Fay Low</name>
      <address>Dementia Collaborative Research Centre, Room 303, Level 3 AGSM Building, University of New South Wales, Sydney, NSW, 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 (0) 2 9385 2599</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lf.low@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>