<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347473">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/09/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/09/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000979954</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of meals rich in carbohydrate and fat on metabolism and inflammation</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Postprandial effect of carbohydrate and fat mixed meals on the regulation of metabolism, inflammation and immune function in healthy subjects with or without a family history of type 2 diabetes and in type 2 diabetes patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>St Vincent's Hospital Research Ethics Reference H06/147</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 diabetes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Family history of type 2 diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Meals:
High carbohydrate
High fat
Mixed high carbohydrate and high fat

Meal composition:
High carbohydrate:
130 g of Heinz canned spaghetti in tomato sauce and cheese, 140 g of white bread, 40 g toasted Muesly, 30 g jam, 40 ml of cordial concentrate in 250 ml water, 150 g plain fat free yoghurt, 5 g sugar (950 kcal, 12.6 g fat, 158 g carbohydrate, 51 g protein).

High fat meal:
100 g eggs fried in 15 ml canola oil, 30 g Ryvita crisp-bread, 10 g butter, 52.5 cheddar cheese, 30 g mixed nuts, 125 g strawberries, 40 g whipping cream, 4 g sugar (1066 kcal, 81 g fat, 25 g carbohydrate, 59 g protein).

High carbohydrate high fat meal:
100 g eggs fried in 15 ml canola oil, 160 g bagel, 7 g butter, 40 g jam, 21 g cheddar cheese, 20 g mixed nuts (1169 kcal, 75 g fat, 79 g carbohydrate, 45 g protein).

Research Plan and procedures:
Each subject attends the Clinical Research unit in the morning after an overnight fast (10-12 hours) for five visits:	

Screening Visit (visit 1):
Detailed information, informed consent.
Medical history, clinical check, blood pressure, weight, height, oral glucose tolerance test (OGTT).
At the end of screening, if eligible to participate in the study, the clamp visit (visit 2) and meal visits (visits 3-5) will be scheduled.
The clamp visit will be booked 7-14 days after the screening visit and the first meal visit (visit 3) will be scheduled 14 days after visit 2. 

Clamp visit (visit 2): 
Fasting blood samples 
Indirect calorimetry 
Heart rate variability at resting and during the intravenous glucose tolerance test (IVGTT) and hyperinsulinaemic euglycaemic clamp (see detailed procedure below).
Dual X-ray absorptiometry (DXA) and computerized tomography (CT).

Visit 3,4 and 5 are identical and performed 7-14 days apart:
Baseline (fasting) indirect calorimetry, heart rate variability
Test meal 1/2/3 in a randomized order. Specifically, the subjects will be randomized for the first meal and will then have the 2 other meal types in a randomized order.

Blood samples are taken before and 30, 60, 120, 180 and 240 min after the meal for measuring cytokines, glucose, insulin, hormones, triglyceride.
Indirect calorimetry is repeated at 3.5-4.0 hours to evaluate postprandial fat and carbohydrate oxidation. 
Heart rate variability at 30-min intervals in the postprandial state.

Subjects undergo the following procedures:
Oral Glucose Tolerance Test (OGTT)- A 75g glucose drink is given and blood glucose is measured at -10, 0, 30, 60, 90 and 120 minutes.

Intravenous Glucose Tolerance Test (IVGTT) is performed to assess B-cell function and the heart rate variability response to endogenous insulin. Blood is drawn at -10, 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8, 10, 20, 30, 40, 50, 60 min after infusion of 0.3 g/kg dextrose 25% (maximum 25 g or 100 ml).


Hyperinsulinaemic euglycaemic clamp is performed to assess whole-body insulin sensitivity and heart rate variability response to supra-physiological hyperinsulinaemia. Insulin is infused intravenously at 60 mU/m2 body surface area/min. Glucose is infused at a rate sufficient to maintain blood glucose at about 5 mmol/L (euglycaemia). The steady state glucose infusion rate (GIR) is defined as the average rate of glucose delivery during the last 30 min period of the clamp. Two venous cannulae will be needed, one at each forearm. The antecubital vein is usually used. Before the insertion of the cannulae the usual antiseptic procedures are applied. Blood is drawn every 10 minutes during the clamp.
 
Indirect calorimetry will be performed fasting and at clamp steady stae (from 90-120 min) or at 3.5-4 h post meal. This technique is used to evaluate resting energy expenditure and the carbohydrate and fat oxidation rate. A transparent plastic hood is connected to the measuring device and placed over the subjects head for a 30 min period. Calculations of O2 consumption and CO2 production are done by continuous measurements of inspired and expired air diluted in a constant air flow. Subjects will be asked to remain motionless and awake.

Dual X-ray absorptiometry (DXA) is performed to quantify body fat, central fat and lean body mass. Lunar Prodigy (Lunar Radiation Corporation, software version 7.51) whole body scanner at St Vincents Hospital is used. The scanner emits low energy X-rays. The scan takes about 5 minutes and the radiation dose is less than 1 mrem (equal to about 12 h background radiation).

CT scan - Cross-sectional CT slices (at L2/3 and L4/5) to evaluate visceral and subcutaneous abdominal fat. Liver fat content will also be evaluated (1 slice).</interventions>
    <comparator>Non</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The effect of hyperinsulinamia on the autonomic nervous system

The autonomic nervous system activity will be assessed using a heart rate sensor (SphygmoCor, AtCor Medical Inc., Australia). Heart rate (HR, bpm) and both time and frequency domain measures of heart rate variability, root mean square of successive differences (RMSSD) between adjacent R-R intervals, low frequency (LF) power (0.04 - 0.15 Hz), high frequency (HF) power (0.15 - 0.4 Hz), and the LF/HF ratio will be derived. Power spectral density for the LF and HF components of heart rate variability are calculated using fast Fourier transformation. RMSSD is sensitive to vagal cardiac control, both sympathetic and vagal activity are considered to be the main determinants of the LF component, whereas the HF component is thought to predominantly reflect vagal activity. The LF/HF ratio is therefore considered to be an indicator of sympatho-vagal balance.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 30 min rest, HRV will be assessed in 2 lots of 8-10 min. During IVGTT, clamp and meals, HRV will be assessed every 30 min for 10 min.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The effect of meal composition on the function of immune cells and inflammatory markers


Immune cell preparation and flow cytometry analysis:
Fresh whole blood sample will be stained with fluorochrome-conjugated antibodies to various cell surface markers purchased from BD Biosciences (San Diego, CA) at baseline and every 1-hour post meal. All analyses will be performed on a BD FACSCaliburTM (BD Biosciences, San Diego, CA) with an excitation laser line Argon (488nm) and Red diode (635nm), and running CellQuest software (version 3.3 from BD Biosciences). Data Analysis software FlowJo version 7 from TreeStar Inc will be used. For comparative quantification of surface activation marker expression, the mean fluorescence intensity (MFI) of the marker will be divided by the MFI of the unstained control to give relative MFI (rMFI). For quantification of Th1/Th2 cells we use intracellular cytokine staining for the key cytokines interferon-gamma (for Th1) and IL-4 (for Th2) (BD Bioscience Pharmingen, San Diego, CA). Briefly, peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) will be activated with PMA (160ng/ml) and Ionomycin (1000ng/ml) for 4 hours at 37C in the presence of GolgiPlug (BD Bioscience, San Diego, CA), allowing the identification of T-helper cell subsets. After surface staining for CD4+ and CD8+, cells will be permeabilized using BD Cytofix/Cytoperm? reagents (BD Bioscience Pharmingen, San Diego, CA), stained for intracellular cytokines and analysed immediately by flow cytometry.

Circulating inflammatory markers:

High sensitivity C-reactive protein (hsCRP) will be measured using a Beckman Coulter Synchron LX system Chemistry Analyser, with reagents and calibrators supplied by Beckman Coulter Inc. (Sydney, Australia). 
Interleukin (IL)6, monocute chemoattractant protein (MCP)1 and soluble intercellular adhesion molecule (sICAM)-1 will be measured using commercial high sensitivity ELISA (R&amp;D Systems, Minneapolis MN, USA).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immune cell surface markers and Th1/Th2 will be evaluated at fasting and every hour post meal for 4 hours and inflammation markers at fasting and at 3-h postprandially</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy men and women or type 2 diabetes patients</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Type 2 diabetes patients:
HbA1c&gt;10% or insulin treatment
Cardiovascular disease, cancer.
Healthy individuals:
Any underlying disease</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>The subjects will be randomized for the first meal and will then have the 2 other meal types in a randomized order based on a randomization list. 

Research Randomizer (Version 3.0) http://www.randomizer.org/</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/02/2007</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>1/02/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>21</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Garvan Institute of Medical Research</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>384 Victoria Street
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Diabetes Australia Research Trust</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO BOX 3156 
CANBERRA  ACT   2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Neuro Science Research Pfeizer Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>P O Box 57
West Ryde NSW 2114</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Type 2 diabetes is an increasingly common disorder characterized by a poor response of the bodys tissues to insulin and impaired secretion of insulin from the insulin producing cells in the pancreas. The mechanisms causing these two defects are still poorly understood. Moreover, there are signs of chronic inflammation in the body, but its role in diabetes and the contribution of the immune system to this process is not known. We believe that studying the metabolic responses to glucose and insulin in subjects with or without a family history of diabetes will advance our understanding of early underlying impairments, possibly contributing to the development of diabetes.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Viardot A, Heilbronn LK, Samocha-Bonet D, Mackay F, Campbell LV, Samaras K (2012) Obesity is associated with activated and insulin resistant immune cells. Diabetes Metab Res Rev 28:447-454

Jenkins AB, Batterham M, Samocha-Bonet D, Tonks K, Greenfield JR, Campbell LV (2013) Segregation of a latent high adiposity phenotype in families with a history of type 2 diabetes mellitus implicates rare obesity-susceptibility genetic variants with large effects in diabetes-related obesity. PLoS One 8:e70435</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Office
Level 6, de Lacy Building
St Vincent's Hospital
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/01/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H06/147</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dorit Samocha-Bonet</name>
      <address>384 Victoria Street
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61292958309</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.samochabonet@garvan.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Lynne Schofield</name>
      <address>384 Victoria Street
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61292958230</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>l.schofield@garvan.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dorit Samocha-Bonet</name>
      <address>384 Victoria Street
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61292958309</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.samochabonet@garvan.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dorit Samocha-Bonet</name>
      <address>384 Victoria Street, Darlinghurst, NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61292958309</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.samochabonet@garvan.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>