<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372328">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/04/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/04/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000572369</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised evaluation trial of the LIFE FLeX digital health and wellbeing program for anxiety and depression.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised evaluation trial of the LIFE FLeX digital health and wellbeing transdiagnostic program, offer through the My Digital Health platform, for reducing anxiety and depression and improving emotional regulation in adults.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Depressive symptoms</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A transdiagnostic, cognitive behavioural and biopsychosocially-based digital health program, offered through the My Digital Health platform, for decreasing symptoms of anxiety and depression (called LIFE FLeX), will be evaluated using a randomised control design. People who consent to participate will be given access to the LIFE FLeX digital health program immediately but will be randomly allocated to one of two groups: 1) LIFE FLeX digital program A (immediate access to all of the program modules) or; 2) LIFE FLeX program B (weekly, sequential release of the program modules).

LIFE FLeX is designed to provide people with information and strategies to address their anxiety and depressive symptoms and contains six core modules, plus an Introduction module delivered over 7 weeks. There will also be a short two page Booster module three weeks following the post-intervention assessment. The booster module will release at that time and participants will be notified by email that it has been released. 


The six core LIFE FLeX digital health program modules are: 

1. Increasing Biological Flexibility: Looks at the biology of the stress response, understanding what biological flexibility is and what techniques to use to increase biological flexibility (e.g., increasing physical activity, breathing control).
2. Increasing Emotional Flexibility: Looks at what emotions are, increasing emotional awareness, and use of emotional regulation strategies. 
3. Increasing Thinking Flexibility: Looks at the role of thoughts in depression and anxiety and how to increase thinking flexibility (e.g., identifying and challenging unhelpful thoughts). 
4. Increasing Behavioural Flexibility: Looks at how what we do influences how we think and feel and how to increase behavioural flexibility through reducing avoidance through gradual exposure (for anxiety) and increasing activity through behavioural activation (for depression). 
5. Increasing Wellness (positive affect) Flexibility: Looks at wellness and positive affect and how to increase wellness through various strategies (e.g., acts of kindness, openness to experience, social connectedness). 
6. Increasing Life FLeX-ability: Recaps the entire program, reflects over progress and discusses relapse prevention. 

Each module will take approximately 25 minutes to complete. In addition, in order to reinforce the module-based information, there are 20-30 minutes of offline activities each week. Offline activities include applying the concepts / techniques discussed in the modules such as self-monitoring depressive and anxiety symptoms, undertaking one of the increasing biological and wellness flexibility intervention strategies, monitoring emotions and thoughts and undertaking the gradual exposure or behavioural activation activity. Participants will also receive automated emails (e.g., to remind them to log on, when to complete during, post/follow-up intervention questionnaires) and will be asked several questions at the beginning of each module to help gauge their progress. Modules include text, graphics, audio, video, editable forms, interactive games (e.g., brain training) and downloads. Modules can be accessible via web, mobile or tablet devices. 

The LIFE FLeX program is housed within the participant's My Digital Health dashboard. My Digital Health is the parent platform that houses a variety of digital health programs. Via the participants dashboard, they are able to access several resources. This includes: My Dashboard, My Inbox, My Daily Monitoring, My Progress Graphs, My Timeline, My Profile and My Tutorial. 

Participants will be asked to complete a pre-intervention assessment (Week 0), during intervention (Week 3 and Week 5) assessments, post-intervention assessment (Week 8) and a 1- and 3-month follow-up assessment (Week 12 &amp; Week 20 respectively) and they will be able to access the LIFE FLeX program for the entire trial period. However, while the during, post-intervention and follow up assessments are scheduled, participants will not be able to access the program until they have completed the scheduled assessments (or after the expiry time to complete the scheduled assessment has lapsed). Participants will retain access to the program until Week 27.

Participant engagement with the program will be obtained through by passive analytic data (e.g., what pages / strategies they visited / used and when), as well as reviewing the completion of daily mood and lifestyle event survey data and the scheduled intervention assessments.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants in both conditions will be asked to complete the same questionnaires and be provided with the exact same content. However, one condition will be able to access all of the program content from their first log in and the other condition will be provided with a 'scheduled release' of the program modules. That is, each week one new module will be made available to them.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depressive symptoms using the PHQ-9</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, during intervention (Week 3 and 5), post and 1 and 3 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety symptoms using the GAD-7 </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, during intervention (Week 3 and 5), post and 1 and 3 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Emotional dysregulation by using the DERS-Brief</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post and 1 and 3 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>General psychological distress levels using the K10</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post and 1 and 3 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mental wellness using the MHC-SF</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post and 1 and 3 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life using the EQ-5D</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post and 1 and 3 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Affective styles using the ASQ</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post and 1 and 3 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Optimism using the LOT-R</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post and 1 and 3 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time perception using the Time Dilation Test (self-developed)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post and 1 and 3 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Treatment credibility using the TCS</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Personality traits using the TIPI</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Treatment satisfaction, including engagement, will be measured using the TSQ</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity levels using single item questions (self developed)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post and 1 and 3 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Social Connectedness Rating question using a 5 point scale (self developed)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre, post and 1 and 3 month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Alcohol consumption levels (self-developed questions) and followed up with CAGE-AID questions if high alcohol consumption is indicated.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre, post and 1 and 3 month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Drug use (self-developed questions) and followed up with CAGE-AID questions if high use of drugs is indicated.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre, post and 1 and 3 month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sleep quantity and quality questions (self-developed and 4 ISI items used). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre, post and 1 and 3 month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Chronic physical illness diagnosis questions (self developed)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mental health condition diagnosis questions (self developed)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Current use of prescribed medication(s) question (self-developed)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre, post and 1 and 3 month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Use of services for a physical health condition questions (self developed) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre, post and 1 and 3 month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Use of mental health services questions (self developed)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre, post and 1 and 3 month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life Rating question - 6 point scale (self developed)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre, post and 1 and 3 month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mental Health Rating question - 6 point scale (self developed)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre, post and 1 and 3 month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical Health Rating question - 6 point scale (self developed)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre, post and 1 and 3 month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety subtype questions (self developed)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre, post and 1 and 3 month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants must be 18 years or older and concerned about their anxiety and or depressive symptoms.

LIFE FLeX has been developed for people with depressive and anxiety symptoms and therefore recruitment will focus on people with depression and anxiety. However, those without symptoms are able to register if they wish too. The program is also preventative in nature and therefore non-anxious and/or depressed participants may also benefit from some of the information within the program (e.g., increasing wellness flexibility).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>No internet access, does not create a My Digital Health account (requires the provision of a valid email address), does not provide consent to study conditions.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be invited to register for the study on the LIFE FLeX child website (or via the parent website - My Digital Health) following ‘My Digital Health’ account creation. Once an account is created, they will be required to provide their informed consent after reading through the LIFE FLeX evaluation study Plain Language Information Statement. Following informed consent, participants will then be presented with the pre-intervention assessment questionnaires. Once completed the participant will then be informed as to which condition they have been randomly allocated to (on screen and also sent an automated email). The My Digital Health platform software randomly allocates participants.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated block design method.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Pre-, post- and follow-up variables will be subjected to mixed methods repeated measures to determine significant changes over time.

Overall medium to large effect sizes are obtained when providing people with fully automated self-help transdiagnostic programs. However it is currently unknown what difference one might expect when varying how the modules are delivered. Therefore, assuming a conservative small effect (i.e. GPower f(v) test = 0.20), significance set at 5% (p = .05), power at 80%, a sample of 277 will be required to demonstrate statistical significance on the primary analysis. However, allowing for a 50% attrition rate, we will be required to recruit 416 participants.  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/05/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>31/05/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>416</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>6</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>17/12/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Federation University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University Drive, Mt Helen Campus, Victoria, 3350</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Federation University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University Drive, Mt Helen Campus, Victoria, 3350</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A transdiagnostic, cognitive behavioural and biopsychosocially-based digital health program for decreasing symptoms of anxiety and depression (called LIFE FLeX) will be evaluated. LIFE FLeX digital health is one of the digital health programs offered through the My Digital Health platform. People who consent will be given access to the LIFE FLeX program immediately but are randomly allocated to one of two groups: 1) LIFE FLeX digital health program A (immediate access to all of the program modules) and; 2) LIFE FLeX program B (weekly, sequential release of the program modules). 

LIFE FLeX is designed to provide people with information and strategies to address their anxiety and depressive symptoms and contains six core modules, plus an Introduction module delivered over 7 weeks. There will also be a short Booster Module released in Week 10. 

Each module will take approximately 25 minutes to complete. In addition, in order to reinforce the module-based information, there are 20-30 minutes of offline activities each week. Participants will also receive automated emails (e.g., to remind them to log on, when to complete post/follow-up questionnaires) and will be asked to self-monitor their mood and daily lifestyle events (e.g., sleep) and asked several questions at the beginning of each module, to monitor their progress. 

Participants will complete a pre-intervention assessment (Week 0), during intervention (Week 1-7) assessments, post-intervention assessment (Week 8) and a 1 and 3-month follow-up assessment (Week 12 &amp; Week 20 respectively). 

It is expected that people who undertake LIFE FLeX will show reductions in anxiety and / or depressive symptoms at post-intervention assessment and follow-up assessment time points, as well as increases in positive affect and emotional regulation.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://lifeflex.mydigitalhealth.org.au (direct, child website)
https://www.mydigitalhealth.org.au (parent site)</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>LIFE FLeX is globally accessible via the web.</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Federation University Higher Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Federation University Australia. Office 218, Building F, Mt Helen Campus. 
PO Box 663, Ballarat VIC 3353</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/02/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>A15-005</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/02/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Britt Klein</name>
      <address>Federation University.
University Drive, Mt Helen Campus, 3350, Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 5327 6717</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>b.klein@federation.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Britt Klein</name>
      <address>Federation University.
University Drive, Mt Helen Campus, 3350, Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 5327 6717</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>b.klein@federation.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Britt Klein</name>
      <address>Federation University.
University Drive, Mt Helen Campus, 3350, Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 5327 6717</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>b.klein@federation.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Britt Klein</name>
      <address>Federation University
University Drive, Mt Helen Campus, 3350, Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 5327 6717</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>b.klein@federation.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>