<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="342982">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/06/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/06/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000595910</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy of oral antibiotic prophylaxis in prevention of surgical site infection following skin lesion excisions at high risk of infection in general practice</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A primary care study of skin lesions excisions from the lower limb and groin and excisions from any site in diabetics comparing the effect of a 2g oral dose of cephalexin administered 30-60 minutes prior to the operation and a placebo in the prevention of subsequent surgical site infection</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1121-7889</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Surgical site infections following skin lesion excisions from the lower limb or groin in general practice</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Surgical site infections following skin lesion excisions from any site in diabetics in general practice</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>2 g oral dose cephalexin (administered in 4 x 500mg capsules) 30-60 minutes prior to skin lesion excisions from the lower limb or groin or any site from diabetics</interventions>
    <comparator>Inert gel capsule, identical to that containing cephalexin.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Presence or absence of wound infection defined as:
Purulent discharge from the wound must be present 
OR
Atleast one of the following signs and symptoms of infection 
Pain/Tenderness
Localised swelling
Heat
Erythema &gt;1cm</outcome>
      <timepoint>When patients return for suture removal (10 days for excisions from back and shin, 7 days for all other sites) or earlier if patients re-present due to perceived infection (date which wound is assessed at will be recorded)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Wound grade
1. No infection or erythema 
2. Stitch abscess
3. Less than 1cm of erythema with no pain, heat or swelling 
4. Less than 1 cm erythema from the wound margin with pain, heat or swelling
5. Greater than 1 cm erythema from the wound margin with no pain, heat or swelling
6. Greater than 1 cm erythema from the wound margin with  pain, heat or swelling
7.Deep infection or systemic symptoms (including lymphangitis, regional lymphadenopathy)</outcome>
      <timepoint>When patients return for suture removal (10 days for excisions from back and shin, 7 days for all other sites) or earlier if patients re-present due to perceived infection (date which wound is assessed at will be recorded)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prescription of antibiotics for wound infection</outcome>
      <timepoint>When patients return for suture removal (10 days for excisions from back and shin, 7 days for all other sites) or earlier if patients re-present due to perceived infection (date which wound is assessed at will be recorded)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Additional consultations required for wound to be reviewed or re-dressed due to infection</outcome>
      <timepoint>Recorded each time patients re-presents primarily in order to have wound reviewed or re-dressed due to diagnosed infection at time or suture removal or earlier for up to 30 days after skin lesion excision</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. &gt;18 yrs old
2. Capable of informed consent
3. Presenting for excision of a minor skin lesion from lower leg  or groin OR Diabetic presenting for skin lesion excision from any site</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Currently taking antibiotics or clinically indicated for antibiotic treatment following excision 
Repair of lacerations or lesion considered contaminated/infected prior to surgery
Excision not requiring sutures (E.g. shave biopsy or curette)
Excision of sebaceous cyst
Patient unable to return for suture removal
Penicillin or cephalosporin allergy</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Consecutive patients presenting at participating general practices are eligible for the trial provided the meet inclusion/exclusion criteria
Practices doctors and nurses responsible for recruiting patients to the trial
If interested in participating, patient will be asked to give signed consent before being allocated a consecutive number by the enrolling nurse or doctor
This number will correspond to a numbered container containing the capsules the patient will receive upon returning to have their skin lesion/s excised. The contents of the capsules held within each numbered container will be determined using a computer generated random sequence and will be blinded to all parties directly involved in allocation, administration of capsules and outcome assessment. In the event that an adverse event occurs the trial coordinators will inform the treating doctor of the contents of the capsule and the participant will be removed from the trial.</concealment>
    <sequence>A sequence of consecutive numbers randomised to either intervention or control will be generated using a computer randomisation. This sequence will be used to create numbered containers which will containing identical capsules filled with either the intervention or control substance depending on the group to which the number was allocated during computer randomisation. Each enrolled patient will be assigned a consecutive number and will receive the capsules from the corresponding numbered container upon return for skin lesion excision.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>4/10/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>31/05/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>James Cook University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Medicine and dentistry
Mackay Base Hospital
Bridge Rd
Mackay QLD 4740</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>James Cook University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>School of Medicine and dentistry
Mackay Base Hospital
Bridge Rd
Mackay QLD 4740</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Certain risk factors are known to be associated with a predictably high rate of surgical wound infection following minor dermatological procedures such as skin lesion excision. The use of oral antibiotic prophylaxis has been suggested as one way of reducing this risk of infection. This project seeks to test the efficacy of such recommendations in the form of a double blind randomised control trial. For the purposes of this trial the high risk group was defined as patients undergoing skin lesion excisions from the lower limb and groin and diabetics having skin lesion excisions from any site. The intervention will consist of a 2g oral dose of cephalexin administered 30-60 minutes prior to the excision while the control will be an identical placebo. Wounds will be assessed for infection using a standardised criteria when patients return for suture removal or earlier if participants re-present due to perceived infection. A wound grading system will also be used and other information which may correlate with infection will also be recorded. This project aims to enrol 100 patients and is a pilot for a large scale multi-centre trial currently in planning.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>James Cook University Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Ethics and Grants Administrator
Research Office
Room 021 A
Ground Floor
Kevin Stark Research Building (DB019)
James Cook University 
Townsville, Qld 4811</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/05/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H4113</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Samuel Smith</name>
      <address>Student Accommodation
School of Medicine and dentistry
Mackay Base Hospital
Bridge Rd
Mackay, QLD 4740</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)407256136</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 4885 7111</fax>
      <email>samuel.smith@my.jcu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Samuel Smith</name>
      <address>James Cook University
Unit 29
159 Riverside Boulevard 
Douglas, QLD 4814
</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)407256136</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 4885 7111</fax>
      <email>samuel.smith@my.jcu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Samuel Smith</name>
      <address>Student Accommodation
School of Medicine and dentistry
Mackay Base Hospital
Bridge Rd
Mackay QLD 4740</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)407256136</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 4885 7111</fax>
      <email>samuel.smith@my.jcu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Samuel Smith</name>
      <address>Unit 29
159 Riverside Boulevard 
Douglas, QLD 4814
</address>
      <phone>+61407256136</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>smith.samuelcharles@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>