<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363723">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/02/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/03/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000262707</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Clinical Study of New Intraocular Lens Design in Participants requiring Bilaterial Cataract Removal 
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Prospective, Non-randomised, Technician-masked, Parallel group (40-50 subjects), Dual site, Clinical Investigation of a new Intraocular Lens (model XRA03) when compared to the Control, Tecnis 1-piece Monofocal Lens (ZCB00) in participants requiring Bilaterial Cataract Removal to Assess Binocular Distance Vision Acuity and Incidence of Dysphotopsias. 
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U111-1139-5832</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cataract extraction and artificial lens implantation for vision acuity restoration for far, intermediate and near vision with reduced need for further spectacle correction/dependence.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In Model XRA03, the spherical diffractive posterior surface of the lens optic  has been modified to provide an increased range of vision and partially corrects for chromatic aberrations. After phacoemulsification/removal of a cataractous lens, the study device is implanted  using a manual "Platinum 1" screw style Unfolder/handpiece through a minimally invasive (~2.4mm) corneal incision.  A standard operative time is 30-40min. Once implanted, the design benefits are intended to be permanent.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control lenses are an approved monofocal hydrophobic acrylic Intraocular lens. Surgical approach for control device is identical to the study lens via phacoemulsification /extraction of the natural cataracterous lens followed by lens insertion through a minimally invasive (~2.4mm) corneal incision using a  "Platinum1 " screw style Unfolder/ handpiece.   A standard operative time is 30-40min.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Binocular range of vision. Subjects will read an eye chart situated at a various distances using both eyes. 













</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three months post-operative second lens implantation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sponsor developed Questionnaire assessment of patient satisfaction of vision quality, optical visual syptoms and spectacle usage administered by clinical staff.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Same as primary 3 months post operative second lens replacement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Monocular and binocular uncorrected and best-corrected distance visual acuity. Subjects will read an eye chart situated at a far distance with and without spectacle correction using one eye at a time and both eyes.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Same as primary 3 months post operative second lens replacement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Monocular and binocular distance-corrected intermediate  visual acuity.  Subjects will read an eye chart situated at an intermediate distance with correction using one eye at a time and both eyes.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Same as primary 3 months post operative second lens replacement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Monocular and binocular distance corrected and best-corrected near visual acuity with minimum/threshold add. Subjects will read an eye chart situated at a near distance with correction using one eye at a time and both eyes.  This will also be tested with correction that is equivalent to reading glasses.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Same as primary 3 months post operative second lens replacement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Monocular best-corrected distance contrast sensitivity. Subjects will look at a contrast sensitivity eye chart (consisting of dark to light-colored lines) with correction and report what they see using one eye at a time.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Same as primary 3 months post operative second lens replacement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidences of optical/ visual symptoms. Subjects will be asked whether they have experienced any specific types of visual symptoms and the observed intensity, if any since surgeries.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Same as primary 3 months post operative second lens replacement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Bilateral cataracts for which phacoemulsification extraction     and posterior IOL implantation have been planned for both eyes

Visual potential of Decimal 0.8 (Snellen 20/25) or better in   each eye after cataract removal and IOL implantation 

Signed informed consent
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Use of systemic or ocular medications that may affect vision (the use of any miotic agent is specifically contraindicated)

Acute or chronic disease or illness that would increase the operative risk or confound the outcome(s) of the study (e.g., uncontrolled, insulin-dependent diabetes, immunocompromised (including current or anticipated use of immunosuppressants), connective tissue disease, etc.)

 Surgery that is not resolved/stable or may affect vision

Prior refractive surgery (LASIK, LASEK, RK, PRK, etc.)

Corneal abnormalities such as stromal, epithelial or endothelial dystrophies

 Intraocular inflammation or recurrent ocular inflammatory condition

Known pathology that may affect visual acuity; particularly retinal changes that affect vision (macular degeneration, cystoid macular edema, proliferative diabetic retinopathy, etc.) 
 
Capsule or zonule abnormalities that may affect postoperative IOL centration or tilt, including pseudoexfoliation, trauma, or surgical complications (e.g. zonular rupture, eccentric anterior capsulorhexis)
 
Requiring an intraocular study lens power outside the available range of +16.0 to +28.0 D
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Enrolment via recommendation from PI/CI and meeting the acceptance criteria. Informed consent form provides detailed information on the potential benefits and risks associated with selection to participant in the trial.
Allocation of study lens not concealed. Subject can select to have the experimental lens implanted in both eyes.</concealment>
    <sequence>Non- randomized</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Technician masked to prevent bias in post-operative measurements / lens performance. Investigator or designated trained clinician shall perform the  biomicroscopic slit-lamp exam.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods> For visual acuity data, descriptive statistics will be the focus  including mean, standard deviation (SD) and the 95% confidence intervals (C.I.) of the mean.  All data will be reported by IOL group. Although some statistical comparisons will be performed between IOL groups, it is noted that statistical power is  somewhat limited in this study due to the control group being small in size, thus the study focus is primarily to describe the performance of the study IOL. A statistical comparison between lens groups will also be performed using a one-sided, two-sample, t-test with an alpha set at 0.05. The null hypothesis is that the mean defocus range for Model XRA03 subjects is less than or equal to that for control subjects. For questionnaire data, the frequency and proportion of subjects with a given response will be reported by IOL group. For comparisons between IOL groups, for ordinal data, the Wilcoxon rank sum test will be used with the Fishers exact test used for categorical data. For questionnaire data two-sided testing will be used with alpha set at 0.05.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/04/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>13/05/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>16/06/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>30/07/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>North Island</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Abbott Medical Optics Inc</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>1700 E. Saint Andrew Place
Santa Ana,
California 92705
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Abbott Medical Optics Inc
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1700 E. Saint Andrew Place
Santa Ana,
California 92705
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname> Dr Dean Corbett BSc, MBChB, FRANZCO</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Auckland Eye
8 St. Marks Road
Remuera 1050
Auckland.</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Neil Murray</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>71 Fairy Springs Road, 
Rotorua 3010
New Zealand</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this clinical trial is to evaluate the binocular clinical performance of a design modification to the Tecnis Monofocal IOL, Model XRA03.  Results will include descriptive statistics on the visual performance of Model XRA03 in bilaterally implanted subjects (post phacoemulsification of cataracts) over distance, intermediate and near vision. This study is a prospective, non-randomized, technician-masked, parallel-group study of 40-50 subjects across up to two investigative sites. Clinical Hypothesis: The study IOL, Model XRA03 will achieve a mean binocular distance visual acuity of  20/40 or better at each defocus point through -1.5 diopters with minimal levels of clinically significant dysphotopsias (night glare/halos) and potentially provide improved uncorrected intermediate to near vision compared to currently marketed monofocal acrylic lenses.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>1.    Koretz J.F., Kaufman P.L, Neider M.W. Goeckner P.A.          Accommodation and Presbyopia in the Human Eye  Aging of the Anterior Segment.  Vision Res. 1989, Vol. 29, No. 12, pages 1685-1692.
2.    Benjamin, William, J., Borish, Irvin M. Borishs Clinical         Refraction, Philadelphia: 1998, W.B. Saunders, pg 109.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Results of this study will help determine the design for a larger clinical study that can support market approval and claims for Model XRA03 IOL. </publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname> Northern A Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Venue: Novetel Ellerslie
72-112 Greenlane Rd East
Auckland 
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/04/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>13/NTA/30</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/02/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dean Corbett BSc MBChB, FRANZCO</name>
      <address>Auckland Eye
8 St. Mark's Road
Remuera 1050
Auckland.</address>
      <phone>+64 9 529 2480</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 529 2481</fax>
      <email>dlcorbett@xtra.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dean Corbett BSc MBChB, FRANZCO</name>
      <address>Auckland Eye
8 St. Mark's Road
Remuera 1050
Auckland.</address>
      <phone>+64 9 529 2480</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 529 2481</fax>
      <email>dlcorbett@xtra.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Eugenia Thomas </name>
      <address>Senior Manager Clinical Research
Abbott Medical Optics Inc
1700 E. Saint Andrew Place
Santa Ana, California 92705
</address>
      <phone> +1 (714) 247-8723</phone>
      <fax>+1 (714) 247-8784</fax>
      <email>Eugenia.Thomas@amo.abbott.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Dale Lambert</name>
      <address>Abbott Medical Optics Australia
level 3, Building 2
20 Bridge Street
Pymble 2073
Sydney NSW</address>
      <phone>+61 2 98550120</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 98550190</fax>
      <email>dale.lambert@amo.abbott.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>