<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363496">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/03/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/04/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000480785</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of an online parenting programme for parents of 3-4 year-old children.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomized controlled trial evaluating the efficacy of Triple P Online with parents of preschool children with hyperactive/ inattentive behaviour difficulties.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hyperactive child behaviour</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Inattentive child behaviour</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Parenting practices</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Triple P Positive Parenting Program is a multilevel parenting and family support strategy that aims to prevent behavioural, emotional and developmental problems in children. Triple P Online is a self-administered, interactive parenting programme, delivered via the internet. The programme aims to teach parents the use of 17 core child-management strategies. There are eight sequenced modules: 1) What is positive parenting?; 2) Skills for encouraging behaviour you like; 3) Teaching new skills; 4) Managing misbehaviour; 5) Dealing with disobedience; 6) Preventing problems by planning ahead; 7) Making shopping fun; and 8) Raising confident, capable kids.

Triple P Online incorporates elements designed to engage participants and improve knowledge acquisition, positive self-efficacy, and behaviour activation. These elements include: 1) user-friendly navigation; 2) video-based modelling of parenting skills, and diverse parent voxpops describing their experiences; 3) personalized content including goal setting, review and feedback; 4) interactive exercises to prompt parental problem solving, decision making and self-regulation; 5) downloadable worksheets and podcasts to review session content; and 5) automated text messaging and email prompting to increase the likelihood of programme completion. The programme also provides parents with a customizable and printable workbook that records programme content, parents goals and responses to exercises.

The programme will take 30 minutes per week for a period of eight weeks. 
 

Two telephone consultations with a Triple P practitioner will be added to the programme in order to maximize participation in the programme and enhance parental problem-solving and self-regulation skills. These telephone sessions will take at least ten minutes, but not more than 30 minutes and willl take place in week two and four of the study. A randomised controlled trial design will be used to evaluate the effects of participation in the online parenting programme in comparison with a wait-list control group.

</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will receive no treatment during the trial. Participants allocated to the control group will be offered access to the Triple P Online programme six months after the intervention group has finished the programme, after the trial has finished and all data have been collected.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A decrease in hyperactive/ inattentive child behaviour.
- Measured by the Conners Early Childhood Behaviour questionnaire (Conners EC-BEH) Inattention/ Hyperactivity subscale, completed by the primary caregiver.


</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post-intervention and at 6-month follow-up (i.e. 6 months after completion of treatment).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A decrease in hyperactive/ inattentive child behaviour.
- Measured by the Conners EC-BEH short form Inattention/ Hyperactivity subscale, completed by the secondary caregiver.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post-intervention and at 6-month follow-up (i.e. 6 months after completion of treatment).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction of less optimal parenting practices as measured by  the Parenting Scale (PS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post-intervention, and at 6-month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Increase in self-reported authoritative parenting as measured by the Parenting Styles and Dimensions Questionnaires (PSDQ) authoritative parenting scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post-intervention, and at 6-month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Increase in parent satisfaction and efficacy. Measured by the Parenting Sense of Competence Scale (PSOC).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post-intervention, and at 6-month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Decrease in symptoms of depression, anxiety and stress reported by parents. Measured by the Depression Anxiety Stress Scales (DASS-21). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post-intervention, and at 6-month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A decrease in teacher reported hyperactive/ inattentive child behaviour.
- Measured by the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire-Hyperactivity scale (SDQ). 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post-intervention, and at 6-month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>An improvement in the child's social functioning measured by preschool teacher ratings on the Child Behaviour Scale (CBS). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post-intervention, and at 6-month follow-up.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Client satisfaction as measured by the Client Satisfaction Questionnaire, completed by the primary caregiver. </outcome>
      <timepoint>6-month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Parent has a child of 3- or 4-year old.
- The target child has an elevated level of hyperactivity and/ or inattention according to following measures:
'Werry-Weiss-Peters questionnaire' (score of 14 or higher) and the preschool version of the clinical interview 'Parental Account of Child Symptoms (PACS)' (score of 16 or higher), and parental concern over impairment based on a score of 1 or more on the PACS perceived severity scale or impact scale
- Parent has access to a computer and broadband internet.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>19</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Parent who is currently seeing a professional for the childs behaviour difficulties (rationale: if the target child is receiving support from another service, then it will be difficult to disentangle potential benefits gained from the provided programme from those gained by this external support).

- Parent/s is currently seeing a health professional for emotional or psychological problems (rationale: if parents are receiving support from another service, then it will be difficult to disentangle potential benefits gained from the provided programme from those gained by this external support).

- Parents with a child suffering from a developmental disability, i.e., autism, intellectual disability, or chronic illness (rationale: the self-help version of Triple P is designed for children with behavioural problems that are otherwise normally developing. A modified version of Triple P, Stepping Stones Triple P, has been specifically designed to meet the unique needs of parents who have children with a developmental or health disability.

- Parents who are not able to read an English newspaper without assistance (rationale: the written online materials of this programme are not suitable for parents who cannot read a newspaper without assistance). 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Parents interested in participating in the study are asked to self-refer to the researcher. Information about the study protocol is explained and a screening interview is conducted to determine participant eligibility. Written informed consent is collected and pre-intervention measures are then administered. Randomization to condition is conducted at the level of individual children in sequence of completion of pre-intervention measures. 

The holder of the allocation schedule is off-site and emails the result.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer generated list of random is used to allocate to condition. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>- the experimental group receives the intervention straight after completing the first set of questionnaires;
- the control group receives no intervention during the trial. The control group receives the intervention after all three sets of questionnaires at the three different time points have been completed, after all data have been collected.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/02/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>11/02/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/09/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>65</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Auckland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Faculty of Education, University of Auckland
Private Bag 92601, Symonds Street
Auckland 1150
New Zealand
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Auckland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Faculty of Education, University of Auckland
Private Bag 92601, Symonds Street
Auckland 1150
New Zealand
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A randomized controlled trial design will be used to evaluate the effectiveness of the online version of the self-help Triple P Positive Parenting Program (TPOL) in comparison to a waitlist control group, in a sample of parents of preschool children with hyperactive/ inattentive behaviour problems. Parents will also receive two telephone support calls from a Triple P Practitioner, 
in order to maximize programme participation and enhance parental problem-solving and self-regulation skills.

Pre-intervention, post-intervention and 6-month follow-up assessment will be collected on a range of parenting and child behaviour measures. The waitlist control group will gain access to the online programme after the assessments on all three time points are completed.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Auckland Human Participants Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Integrity Unit
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92601, Symonds Street
Auckland 1150
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/11/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2012/8376</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Louise Keown (Nike Franke's main supervisor)</name>
      <address>School of Learning, Development, and Professional Practice
Faculty of Education,
Epsom Campus,
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92601
Symonds Street Auckland 1150</address>
      <phone>64 (0)9 623 8899 ext 86435</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>l.keown@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Nike Franke</name>
      <address>Faculty of Education, University of Auckland
Private Bag 92601, Symonds Street
Auckland 1150
</address>
      <phone>64 (0)9 623 8899 Ext. 48788</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>n.franke@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Nike Franke</name>
      <address>Faculty of Education, University of Auckland
Private Bag 92601, Symonds Street
Auckland 1150
</address>
      <phone>64 (0)9 623 8899 Ext. 48788</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>n.franke@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Nike Franke</name>
      <address>Faculty of Education, University of Auckland
Private Bag 92601, Symonds Street
Auckland 1150
</address>
      <phone>64 (0)9 623 8899 Ext. 48788</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>n.franke@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>