<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366157">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/04/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/04/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000420640</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>RAndomised controlled trial to imProve depressIon and the quality of life of people with Dementia using cognitive bias modification (RAPID)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>RAndomised controlled trial to imProve depressIon and the quality of life of people with Dementia using cognitive bias modification (RAPID)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>RAPID</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>depression
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Alzheimer's disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Alzheimer's disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be asked to attend the WA Centre for Health and Ageing, Royal Perth Hospital, on a daily basis for a total of 10 sessions of cognitive bias modification (CBM) (2 weeks  excluding weekends). Each session will be delivered on a 24 high-resolution screen using a local PC station, and will last approximately 30 minutes: 15 minutes each for CBM-Attention (CBM-A) and for CBM-Interpretation (CBM-I). 

In the CBM-A session, participants will be shown pairs of emotionally discrepant photos for 500 ms (sad or neutral/happy faces). Each pair will then be replaced by a small probe (square or circle) appearing in the screen position previously occupied by one of the photos. Participants will be instructed to use a response box with a square and a round button to indicate the shape of the probe that appeared on the screen. The probe will then disappear and will be replaced, after 1 second, by another pair of photos to initiate the next trial. The time to discriminate probe identity (square or circle) will be recorded automatically. In the active CBM condition, designed to reduce attention to negative information, probes will always appear in the position of neutral/happy faces. 

In the interpretative CBM sessions (CBM-I), single ambiguous cue-words that permit a negative and benign interpretation (e.g., BEAT) will first appear in the top half of the screen for 1s. Then two words will appear on the bottom half of the screen: one on the left and the other on the right hand side. This word-pair will consist of one target word that is semantically related either to the negative or benign meaning of the ambiguous cue-word (e.g., VICTORY or PUNISH), and one word that is unrelated to either meaning of the ambiguous cue-word (e.g., CLOUD). Participants will be asked to identify which is the target word and use the response box to indicate whether the semantically-related word appeared on the left or right-hand side of the screen (by pressing the left or the right hand side button on the response box, respectively). The time required to accurately identify the target word will be recorded automatically. In the active CBM condition, designed to reduce negative interpretations of ambiguity, target words always will be associated with the benign meanings of the cue-words, discouraging their negative interpretation.

</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator control intervention will follow the same procedures described for the active intervention group, except that in the CBM-A control condition the probes will appear 50% of the time in the position of neutral/happy faces and 50% of the time in the position of the sad faces. In the CBM-I control condition 50% of the target words will be associated with the benign meaning and 50% with the negative meanings of the cue-words.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>We will use the Cornell Scale for Depression in Dementia (CSDD) to establish the presence of clinically significant symptoms of depression (CSDD greater or equal 8), measure changes in the severity of symptoms, and ascertain the remission of symptoms (CSDD less than 8).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Two weeks after the baseline assessment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Quality of Life AD (QoL-AD) scale will be this studys measure of quality of life. It consists of 13 items that assess behavioural competence, psychological status, physical functioning and interpersonal environment that is of relevance to older adults. Each item offers four answers that range from poor (1) to excellent (4), with the total possible score ranging from 13 to 52. Higher scores indicate better quality of life. The QoL-AD has the added advantage of offering patient and carer versions. The QoL-AD has robust psychometric propertie. Changes in QoL-AD scores from baseline represent another outcome of interest of this trial.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Two weeks after the baseline assessment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in CSDD scores.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Twelve weeks after the baseline assessment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in QoL-AD scores.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Twelve weeks after the baseline assessment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Negative attentional bias will be indexed by degree of relative speeding to discriminate probes appearing in the position of sad faces compared with the happy/neutral faces.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Two and twelve weeks after the baseline assessment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Negative interpretative bias will be indexed by degree of relative speeding to identify words associated with negative compared with the benign meaning of the ambiguous word.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Two and twelve weeks after the baseline assessment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change of scores on the Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Two and twelve weeks after the baseline assessment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>We will recruit 80 people with depression in mild to moderate severity Alzheimers disease according to the following inclusion criteria:
1.	Diagnosis of probable AD according to NINCDS-ADRDA criteria, which is largely consistent with DSM-V diagnosis of major neurocognitive disorder due to probable AD,
2.	Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE) score equal or greater than 15,
3.	Cornell Scale for Depression in Dementia (CSDD) equal or greater than 8,
4.	Fluent in written and spoken English (preferred language for at least 10 years).
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>100</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>We will exclude from participation people who have:
1.	One or more diseases likely to compromise ongoing participation in the trial (for example, severe visual impairment),
2.	A weekly alcohol consumption greater than 28 standard drinks (&gt; 4 drinks per day) or 6 or more standard drinks on any one day of the week,
3.	Active suicidal intent,
4.	No health practitioner who is able to provide ongoing clinical care,
5.	Changed antidepressants during the preceding four weeks,
6.	Not given informed consent to participate.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>We will recruit community-dwelling participants from the Perth metropolitan area who are in contact with our clinical services (including Memory Clinics and Memory Services of the Royal Perth, Bentley and Swan Hospitals). These services assess 8-10 new referrals with the diagnosis of dementia per week (about 5 or 6 with AD) and review twice as many ongoing cases. If necessary, we will contact local primary care practices and other mental health services for older adults to assist with recruitment. Volunteers who meet the study entry criteria will be asked to complete all further assessments and study procedures at the WA Centre for Health and Ageing, located at the Royal Perth Hospital.

Eligible participants will be automatically assigned to one of the two treatment groups by a computer. Allocation will be concealed from both the participant and the research team.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomly assigned to control and active CBM according to a list of random numbers generated by computer in blocks. The allocation ratio will be 1:1. Group allocation codes will then be linked to random id numbers that will be assigned to each participant when they log on for their first CBM session. Neither the participant nor research staff will be aware of the independently controlled randomisation code. Participants will be advised about the study’s aims and procedures (which will be exactly the same for all participants), but not about the details characterising the control and the active intervention. In addition, the research person supervising the CBM sessions will not be involved in the collection of any outcome data. Group assignment codes will only be open after the last endpoint of interest of the last participant in the trial is collected. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Study size:
Data from the placebo-controlled trial of mirtazapine and sertraline indicate that people with DAD treated with placebo improved, on average, 6 points (standard deviation, SD = 4) after 13 weeks (Banerjee et al., 2011). We estimate that people treated with CBM should improve an additional 3 points (9 in total, SD = 4). A sample size of 76 people with DAD (38 per group) would give the study 90% power to declare this difference as significant (alpha &lt; 5%, two-tailed). We plan to recruit 80 participants with DAD (40 randomly assigned to each treatment group) and anticipate that 15% of them will be lost during the study. In this case, the trial would be completed by 68 participants and would still have 87% power. We further anticipate that loss to follow up will be minimal during the initial two weeks of treatment, although changes in scores may also be smaller at that point in time (3 points for controls and 6 for intervention participants). If we lose 10% of our sample during the initial two weeks, primary outcome data would be available for 72 participants (36 per group) and the study would have 89% power to declare as significant such a difference between the groups. Furthermore, a sample of this size would give the study 84% power to declare as significant changes in QoL-AD scores of 1 point for controls and 4.5 points for active CBM participants over three months (SD=5 for both groups; positive changes indicate expected improvement). The changes in response bias (measured in milliseconds) are expected to be associated with a minimum effect size of 0.4 (Cohens d)(See et al., 2009), which would require about 50 trials per participant (within group comparison). As each CBM session includes 96 trials for attention (faces) and 96 trials for interpretive bias (words), the study will have ample power to investigate this outcome. 

Statistical analyses:
We will use means and standard deviations to describe continuous variables with normal distribution, medians and inter-quartile ranges for ordinal variables, and frequency tables for categorical variables. We will use t-tests to compare the change in CSDD and QoL-AD scores between baseline and week 2. If statistical adjustments are required because of unbalance in other study measures (e.g., gender distribution), we will use analysis of co-variance. We will use multilevel mixed models to analyse changes in CSDD, QoL and attentional and interpretative biases from baseline to week 2 and 12. We will investigate the interaction between group and time effects (statistical adjustments will be made, if necessary). This analysis is intention to treat. Multiple imputation (imputed chain equations) will be employed for the analysis of week 2 data, if necessary.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/06/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>2/06/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>14/09/2020</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>29/09/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Suspended</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>15/12/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Perth Hospital - Perth</hospital>
    <hospital>Bentley Health Service - Bentley</hospital>
    <hospital>Swan Districts Hospital - Middle Swan</hospital>
    <hospital>Osborne Park Hospital - Stirling</hospital>
    <hospital>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital - Nedlands</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - City campus - Parkville</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>WA Centre for Health &amp; Ageing</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 6
48 Murray Street
Perth, WA 6000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>WA Centre for Health &amp; Ageing</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>48 Murray Street
Perth, WA 6000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Depressive symptoms are common and undermine the quality of life of people with Alzheimers disease (AD). Cholinesterase inhibitors and antidepressants have all but no effect on the mood of patients, and their use is associated with greater risk of adverse events compared with placebo. The use of traditional psychotherapeutic interventions, such as cognitive behavioural therapy, is hindered by the presence of cognitive impairment. Cognitive bias modification (CBM) is a novel, simple and safe intervention that targets attentional and interpretative biases associated with anxiety, dysphoria and depression. CBM operates through implicit learning systems, which are spared until late in the course of the dementia illness. CBM is effective at reducing depressive symptoms in adults without cognitive impairment and our pilot data indicate that this is a feasible and, most likely, efficacious treatment for people with depression in AD (DAD). Moreover, CBM is safe and unlikely to be associated with significant adverse events in this vulnerable population. RAPID will evaluate this innovative intervention in a carefully designed trial that brings together an accomplished team of investigators with expertise in ageing research, depression, dementia, CBM, randomised trials and translation of research findings into clinical practice. This study will produce definitive high quality evidence for the benefits of CBM in improving the quality of life of people with DAD.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Almeida, O.P., MacLeod, C., Flicker, L., Ford, A.H., Grafton, B. &amp; Etherton-Beer, C. (2014). RAndomised controlled trial to imProve depressIon and the quality of life of people with Dementia using cognitive bias modification: RAPID Study Protocol. BMJ Open, 4, e005623.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Perth Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 5 Colonial House
Royal Perth Hospital
GPO Box X2213
Perth, WA 6001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/04/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>REG 14-036</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/03/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Osvaldo P. Almeida</name>
      <address>School of Psychiatry &amp; Clinical Neurosciences (M573)
University of Western Australia
35 Stirling Highway
Crawley, WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61-8-92242855</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>osvaldo.almeida@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Varsha Hirany</name>
      <address>School of Psychiatry &amp; Clinical Neurosciences (M573)
University of Western Australia
35 Stirling Highway
Crawley, WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61-8-92242855</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>varsha.hirani@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Osvaldo P. Almeida</name>
      <address>School of Psychiatry &amp; Clinical Neurosciences (M573)
University of Western Australia
35 Stirling Highway
Crawley, WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61-8-92242855</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>osvaldo.almeida@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Osvaldo P. Almeida</name>
      <address>School of Psychiatry &amp; Clinical Neurosciences (M573)
University of Western Australia
35 Stirling Highway
Crawley, WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61-8-92242855</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>osvaldo.almeida@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>