<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320951">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/12/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/01/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000019000</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Safety and immunogenicity of Helicobacter pylori clinical isolates in  healthy volunteers.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Safety and immunogenicity of Helicobacter pylori clinical isolates in  healthy volunteers.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>This study will evaluate the safety and immunogenicity of selected Helicobacter Pylori (H.pylori) clinical strains in healthy human volunteers that have not been previously exposed to H. pylori.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study will evaluate the safety and immunogenicity of selected H. pylori clinical strains in healthy human volunteers that have not been previously exposed to H. pylori. The study will include 5 clinical isolates and a placebo group. Subjects will be randomised into 6 groups of 6, totally 36 subjects in total.
Each participant will only receive either a single oral dose (30 mls) of one of the five H. pylori strains, or the placebo.
 The H. pylori inoculum or placebo will be administered 90 days after screening, and eradication  therapy commenced 30 days after inoculum or placebo administration.
The eradication therapy consists of NEXIUM Hp7 (Esomeprazole 20mg, amoxycillin  trihydrate 1000mg, and clarithromycin 500mg); the tablets are taken twice a day for one week.</interventions>
    <comparator>The placebo group will relieve a single oral  administered dose of soup broth.  All participants will undergo eradication therapy.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To observe the clinical effect of Helicobacter pylori infection.

1.Live Helicobacter pylori  are administered
   to healthy subjects
  a.Symptom diary cards are completed
  b.Infection status is determined at the
     2-week gastroscopy

 2.The subject completes the follow-up
     period
      a. The final endoscopy is completed
      b. Eradication treatment is completed
         by the patient
       c. Follow-up breath tests confirm
          eradication of Helicobacter pylori

    Selected H. pylori strains will be administered to naive (sero-negative) healthy subjects. Infection status will be determined by histological assessment of gastric tissue (biopsies taken at 0, 2 and 12 weeks after infection), blood profiles, liver function test (LFT), cell counts, pH, acid, and the daily diary and telephone follow-up for adverse events.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The primary timepoints are: 
   a). Gastroscopy at week 2
   b). Gastroscopy at week 12
   c). Eradication therapy at  week 16
  Diary cards will be distributed at Screening Visit (V 1) - 14 day Baseline diary card; post-inoculum (V4, week 5) - 21 days diary card; and post-eradication (V9, week 15) - 7 days diary card.
  Blood profiles will be collected at Screening (V1), Day 0 (V2), Wk4 (V5), Wk6 (V6), Wk8 (V7), Wk12 (V8), Wk16 (V10), and Wk 20 (V11).
  Urease Breath Tests (UBT)  will be conducted at Baseline (V1),  two weeks post-inoculum (Wk6), pre-gastroscopy (Wk12), and post-eradication therapy (Wk16).
  A baseline gastroscopy will be conducted at V2 (Day 0).
  Telephone follow-up post-inoculum (V4) will take place at V4 + day 1, V4 + day 2, and V4 + day 3.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the immunogenicity and metabolites of H. pylori in naive (sero-negative) healthy subjects

1.	Immunogenicity will be determined by measuring H. pylori specific immunoglobulin responses and serum cytokine responses in the blood at intervals during the study. Urine samples will be assessed for the presence of H. pylori metabolites.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The secondary outcome of this Study is to determine the immunogenicity of the H. pylori strains (ability of host to mount an immune response against H. pylori). Serum will be collected from blood samples at 2, 4, 8, and 12 weeks after the infection step.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion Criteria
1.	Healthy men and women
2.	Aged 18-70 years inclusive
3.	Use their own mobile phone 
4.	Sero-negative for H. pylori
5.	Asymptomatic with regard to dyspepsia. Mild symptomatic but endoscopy negative gastro-oesophageal reflux disease is not an exclusion providing the condition does not require the regular use of Proton Pump Inhibitors or H2 blockers (occasional use permitted). However the participants with the following medical conditions will be excluded:
   a.)Peptic Ulcer Disease
   b.)History of major gastrointestinal surgery e.g. gastric banding
6.	No known allergy to principal medications / antibiotics used to treat 
H. pylori in this study (esomeprazole, amoxycillin, clarithromycin and tinidazole). No known intolerances or allergy to 2nd and 3rd line medications /antibiotics used to treat H. pylori, including macrolides, tetracycline, fluoroquinolones, furazolidone, colloidal bismuth subcitrate.
7.	Living in Australia for duration of trial (approximately 12 months) 
8.	Provide written informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion Criteria
1.	Pregnant or breast feeding women; women who are less than 2 years postmenopausal; or women of child bearing potential not using adequate contraception for the duration of the study (adequate contraception is the use of oral contraceptives, contraceptive injections, intra-uterine device, contraceptive patches or the use of a double barrier contraception method e.g. use of condom and spermicidal cream simultaneously). Women of child bearing potential will be required to have a negative serum Beta Human Chorionic Gonadotropin (BHCG) pregnancy test before continuing in the study.
2.	Current or probable requirement to use any of the following medications: anticoagulants, aspirin, clopidogrel, antibiotics, regular use of proton pump inhibitors (occasional use permitted) or regular use of non steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (more often than twice weekly).
3.	Positive Helicobacter pylori serology at visit 1
4.	Current enrolment in another clinical trial involving a medication or device.
5.	Living with or having daily contact with children aged 12 years or younger at home, school, day care or equivalent facilities.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants are pre-screened to ensure that they meet the Inclusion/Exclusion criteria. A copy of the Patient Information and Consent (PICF) is then emailed to prospective participants for their consideration. If the participant wishes to continue they contact the Trial Coordinator, and come into the hospital clinic for formal discussion, counselling on the Trial, and signing of the PICF. The participant then undergoes a medical review by the Principal Investigator, and baseline data and biologic sampling is collected as per Protocol. Allocation to control and experimental groups is randomised by a randomisation generator with central randomisation by computer. </concealment>
    <sequence>All participants are given a Trial Number generated from a random number generator. This is provided by the Trial Statistician through a central randomisation by computer. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/12/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>15/12/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>27/07/2010</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>36</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Ondek Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>19A Boundary Street
Rushcutters Bay
NSW   2011</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ondek Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>19A Boundary Street
Rushcutters Bay
NSW   2011</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Hospital Ave
 Nedlands
 WA 6009.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Helicobacter pylori (H. pylori) infection is a common stomach infection affecting ~50 % of people worldwide. In most cases, patients have no symptoms. H. pylori infection does induce immune responses, however they are not protective. For these reasons Ondek Pty Ltd is developing H. pylori as a live bacterial delivery system for vaccines and other therapeutic agents.

The aim of this study is to find strains of Helicobacter pylori which can be safely used as a vehicle for the delivery of vaccines such as that used to treat Influenza in humans. Here we would like to assess the suitability of H. pylori strains as a live bacterial vector, and identify clinical isolates with a safe profile in humans.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sir Charles Gairdner Group</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Hospital  Ave.
Nedlands
WA 6009</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/10/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2009-062</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr. Hooi Ee</name>
      <address>Principal Investigator
 Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
 Endoscopy Suite, G75
 Hospital Ave.
 Nedlands
 WA 6009</address>
      <phone>(+61) 8  93463677</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Hooi.Ee@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Jim Blanchard</name>
      <address>Clinical Trials Coordinator
 Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
 Endoscopy Suite, G75
 Hospital Ave.
 Nedlands
 WA 6009</address>
      <phone>(+61) 8 93464036</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Jim.Blanchard@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hooi Ee</name>
      <address>Principal Investigator Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital Endoscopy Suite, G75 Hospital Ave. Nedlands WA 6009</address>
      <phone>(+61) 8 93463677</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Hooi.Ee@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>