<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367578">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/12/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/04/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000306516</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Chronic back pain rehabilitation in small groups: pain, disability and function a quasi-randomized trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In patients with chronic back pain is rehabilitation in small groups following the international guidelines as good or better than classic approach with back school (postural education, strengthening exercises, stretching exercises) for relief of pain, reduction of disability, and increase of function</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none
</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>chronic back pain
</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>2-week exercise rehabilitation program. Back School based exercise involving stretching of back muscles, exercise of abdomen strenghtening, postural education, floor based exercise. Back School home-based exercises (the same exercises performed during treatment sessions) are reported in a book given at the end of the treatment. Evidence based exercise involving progressive exposure (with a progressive increase in repetitions and coordination and decrease of balance till fatigue), aerobic global exercise (involving the muscles of both legs and of the back in the way to increase the heart beat from the one at rest). Evidence based home-based exercises involves global aerobic exercises floor based exercises and auto-mobilization of peripheral nervous system, those exercises will be taught to the patients during the treatment sessions.
Prescription is 5 x 1/2 hours sessions per week for 2-weeks. All directly supervised from the physiotherapist in a group format (5 people per group session). All sessions will be performed in a outpatient service of the public health system. No intervention group will completes both the back and evidence based exercises. Adherence to the intervention will be assessed through the presences to the treatment sessions and an adherence scale at follow-up assessment.</interventions>
    <comparator>Evidence based exercise involving progressive exposure (with a graded increment of range of motion, repetitions, and balance), aerobic global exercise (using both arms and legs muscles in the way to increase the heart beat from the one at rest), neurodynamic exercise (with auto-mobilization techniques of the peripheral nervous system). Sessions will be supervised by the physical therapist. 
Prescription is 5 x 1/2 hours sessions per week for 2-weeks. All directly supervised in a group format (5 people per group session).

Waitlist control group will be treated in one of the two groups above (Back school group or Evidence based group) in not more than 12 month. they will be assigned to the group they will choose (blinded from the type of treatment) during reservation of the rehabilitation cycle. None of the control group will perform any type of rehabilitation program including home based exercises. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain intensity (Verbally administred Numerical Pain Rating Scale)

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (pre), 2-weeks (post program) and 3 month (follow up)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disability (Roland Morris Disability Questionnaire)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (pre), 2-weeks (post program) and 3 month (follow up)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functioning (SF-36)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (pre), 2-weeks (post program) and 3 month (follow up)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adeherence to the Physical therapist indications on home exercises (SIRAS) </outcome>
      <timepoint>3 month  (follow up)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>number of exercise remembered will be assessed during the administration of the scales at follow up in a written form.

"Report here how many exercises you remeber from those learnt during the treatment sessions_________"</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 month  (follow up)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>other health system access for unresolved back pain will be assessed during the administration of the scales at follow up in a written form.

"Report here how many other accesses to the health system you have done for your unresolved back pain after the treatment sessions_________"

</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 month (follow-up)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Male and female participants with chronic back pain. This group excludes those with oncological disease or neurological progressive diseases and dementia(as assessed from described history of participants), because of possible interaction with diseases problems related , which introduces confounding factors for interpretation of the results.
Participants will have had LBP for at least 12 weeks and have provided written informed consent confirming
their participation.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>90</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants will be excluded for the following reasons: presence of severe postural abnormality or neuromuscular disorder, previous diagnosis of pathology (confirmed by previous magnetic resonance imaging or radiograph).
Participants must not have engaged in any specific rehabilitation program in the last 3-months, and
must not be regularly seeing a physiotherapist or any spinal manipulation practitioner.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Effect size expected (d of Cohen) was a strong clinical effect ( d = 0.80).
Sample size was estimated with a alpha = 0.05 (5% chance of type I error) and 1- beta =0.80 (power 80%). This provided an estimated total sample size of n = 52. Allowing for a 20% dropout rate increased the sample size required to n = 64 (n = 32 in each group of tretment) plus n = 32 waitlist control group. 

Variations in responses will be assessed through a Generalised Multinomial Model  (GLM) to assess the impact that can have time or rehabilitation or the interaction between them in the modification of those values. Statistical analysis will be performed through correlation assessment in changes of she scale scores using Student T test and Spearman's Rho test. also the impact of adherence to the physical therapist's indication on exercise to be performed at home will be assessed through a GLM</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/05/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>96</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Milano</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Giacomo Carta</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Isituti Clinici di Perfezionamento 

Viale Andrea Doria 52

Milano

20122</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Italy</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>None</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>the aim of the study is to assess the impact of rehabilitation in small groups (2-5 people) on chronic back pain. In particular we want to assess the changes on pain intensity, disability and functioning. A comparison will be made between classic treatment (Back School approach), waiting list and guidelines on chronic back pain follower.
We also want to assess the changes during time.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Isituti Clinici di Perfezionamento</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/01/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Italy</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Giacomo Carta</name>
      <address>Isituti Clinici di Perfezionamento 

Viale Andrea Doria 52

Milano

20122</address>
      <phone>+39 3405950493</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>giacomo.carta@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Giacomo Carta</name>
      <address>Isituti Clinici di Perfezionamento 

Viale Andrea Doria 52

Milano

20122</address>
      <phone>+39 3405950493</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>giacomo.carta@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Giacomo Carta</name>
      <address>Isituti Clinici di Perfezionamento 

Viale Andrea Doria 52

Milano

20122</address>
      <phone>+39 3405950493</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>giacomo.carta@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Giacomo Carta</name>
      <address>Via Luca Signorelli 9</address>
      <phone>3405950493</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>giacomo.carta@gmail.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>