<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336442">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/01/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/01/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000081910</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>ManUp Gladstone Project: an Internet and Mobile Phone Delivered Physical Activity and Nutrition Intervention.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy Testing of an Internet and Mobile Phone Delivered Physical Activity and Nutrition Intervention for Men aged 35-54 years.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1119-1840</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>The aim of this research is to test the efficacy of an internet and mobile phone delivered physical activity and nutrition intervention in a two-armed randomised control trial for men aged 35-54 years.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be recruited and randomised into two intervention groups with the help of various partner organisations that form part of the community consortium and local media.

The two intervention groups will consist of the 'Control' group and the 'IT' (Information Technology) group.

The 'Control' group will receive a print logbook with all ManUp intervention material.

Participants in the 'IT' Group will be provided with access to both the website and the mobile phone application. Participants are not required to have a mobile phone that is compatible with the application that we have developed, however in that case they will not be able to access this 'extra' component of the intervention. Participants with access to the IT group will receive regular challenge progress emails and SMS.

Dependant on the length of challenges that participants choose, they will either receive an email/SMS weekly or fortnightly. Challenges opt from three to twelve weeks in length, and participants can complete as many challenges as they like during the duration of the project.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants in the 'Control' group will not have access to an internet or mobile intervention, receiving only print-based information only. 

A sub-sample group will comprise of both 'Control' and 'IT' group members. Those in the sub-sample will have objective measures taken of their height and weight.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants wll be asked to complete the following survey instruments and have the following measurements taken at each data collection time point.

Physical Activity Questionnaire
Nutrition/Food Questionnaire
Physical Activity Literacy Questionnaire
Nutrition Literacy Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 3 and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase 1 - Control Group and IT Group.

All individuals will be provided with a detailed information sheet and an informed consent form. They will have their data recorded at a time convenient for them. Participants will complete the survey instruments (Surveys mentioned in Primary Outcome 1) and will have their height and weight measured at each time point.

Phase 2 - Sub-sample group.

All individuals will be fitted with an accelerometer and will have objective measures taken of their height and weight whilst completing the same intervention as Phase 1 participants.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 3 and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be screened by a member of the research team either in person, phone conversation or electronic communication and meet the following criteria to be included in the study.

- Male
- Aged 35-54 years
- Own a mobile phone
- Have regular access to the internet
- Not have a condition where physical activity is contraindicated
- Have completed a pre-exercise screening assessment and have a low or moderate risk for exercise related complications, or if high risk have approval from medical professional to participate in exercise. (http://sma.org.au/wp-content/uploads/2009/05/new_pre_screening.pdf)

Participants will be deemed healthy volunteers by completing the pre-exercise screening assessment.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>35</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>54</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Female
- Outside of 35-54 year age bracket
- Without a mobile phone
- Without regular access to the internet
- Have a condition where physical activity is contraindicated</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Interested participants are asked to complete an online registration form which details whether or not they are eligible, contact information and how they found out about ManUp Gladstone.

Once eligibility is assessed, participants are enrolled into the project and assigned to an intervention group. 

Those who are in the sub-sample group are asked to visit our ManUp Gladstone Project Officer for an Actigraph appointment. Those not in the sub-sample are sent an e-mail asking them to complete an online survey, completing the first stage of the intervention.

Allocation is not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomization.com was used to determine how the 504 participants would be allocated to the two intervention groups, as well as a the small sub-sample group.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>25/10/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>504</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>4680</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>CQUniversity Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Institute for Health and Social Science Research
CQUniversity Australia
Rockhampton Queensland 4702</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Queensland Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
15 Butterfield Street
HERSTON Queensland 4006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University Of Western Sydney</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Biomedical and Health Sciences
Campbelltown Campus
Penrith South DC NSW 1797</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Government body</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>CSIRO</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>The Australian E-Health Research Centre
CSIRO Human Nutrition
PO BOX 10041
Adelaide BC SA 5000

Level 7 - UQ CCR Building 71/918
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
HERSTON Q 4029</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>ManUp is a physical activity and healthy eating project for men and is conducted in the Gladstone region. In this project we will use the Internet to help men to achieve their physical activity and healthy eating goals and challenges.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.recruit.manup.org.au
www.manup.org.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office Of Research
Building 32
CQUniversity
Rockhampton Queensland 4701</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/09/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H10/07-131</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mitch Duncan</name>
      <address>Building 18
CQUniversity Australia
Rockhampton Queensland 4701</address>
      <phone>+61 7 49306977</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.duncan@cqu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mitch Duncan</name>
      <address>Building 18
CQUniversity Australia
Rockhampton Queensland 4701</address>
      <phone>+61 7 49306977</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.duncan@cqu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Cindy Hooker</name>
      <address>Building 18
CQUniversity Australia
Rockhampton Queensland 4701</address>
      <phone>+61 7 49306537</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c.hooker@cqu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>