<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373751">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/10/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/10/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001429347p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can a behavioural smartphone application decrease sedentary behaviour in cardiac rehabilitation?: the ToDo-CR feasibility study.
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Can a behavioural smartphone application decrease sedentary behaviour in cardiac rehabilitation?: the ToDo-CR feasibility study.
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1202-9862 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>ToDo-CR</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>sedentary behaviour</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>coronary heart disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Study design
The feasibility study will be conducted over 6-months within the Canberra Hospital Cardiac Rehabilitation (CR) program. Participants will be assessed on admission and at the end of the 6-week traditional phase II hospital-based CR program. They will also complete a follow-up assessment post discharge from the CR program, approximately 6-months post admission to the CR program.

 Intervention
On entry into the CR program, eligible participants will be given a Fitbit Flex, shown how to install the ToDo and Moves apps on their smartphone and how to use them by an exercise physiologist. Participants will be required to wear the Fitbit Flex for the 6-month study period and will be able to keep the Fitbit Flex on completion of the study.

ToDo is a cloud-based behaviour change service delivered through a smartphone application created by Onmi in collaboration with Do Something Limited and is currently being trialed in Europe. The ToDo program helps people learn new behaviours so they have more choice over how they react to different situations. The system suggests micro behavioural alternatives that gradually change peoples habits. This is based on evidence that these small behavioural changes effect health outcomes. Each program is personalised and consists of different types of Dos: Core Dos and Data Driven Dos. CORE Dos address the individuals psychology and the factors that often prevent healthy changes. DATA DRIVEN Dos, address their everyday context that traps them in habitual behaviour, fusing data from the Fitbit Flex (acceleration) and the Moves app (GPS) to create a comprehensive digital profile of the individual, with near real-time analysis algorithms. 

At the intake of the program a set of diagnostic questions will be answered by the patient on the Do Something Different website. The unique program of behavioural prompts (Dos) will be based on the persons answers to the diagnostic questions. For a duration of one week baseline measurements will be collected. This is used to calibrate the program triggers for sending Data driven Dos. The calibration uses absolute and relative behaviour (i.e. actual amount of steps and relative increases or decreases). The system computes variable scores based on the persons behaviour. When the system identifies a need for improvement, an appropriate Do is sent. By combining technology, evidence-based guidelines and psychology, the program aims to increase the patients self-efficacy, with the goal to decrease their sedentary behaviour and increase their moderate-vigorous physical activity. 

</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sedentary behaviour. Sedentary behaviour will be measured using an accelerometer. The raw data collected by the accelerometer, counts, will be used to obtain the time spent in
sedentary behaviour, which will be defined as less than 100 counts per minute while awake..</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 6 weeks and 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility measures. This includes the standard deviation of the main outcome measure (sedentary behaviour) to estimate the sample size for a larger randomised controlled trial, the number of eligible participants, and the follow-up rates and response rates to questionnaires.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Moderate - vigorous physical activity (MVPA; accelerometer). MVPA will be measured using an accelerometer. The raw data collected by the accelerometer, counts, will be used to obtain the time spent in different physical activity intensities while awake. We will use the Freedson Combination energy expenditure algorithm to determine the intensity cut-points.</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 6 weeks and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body mass index (BMI). BMI (kg/m2) will be recorded using a calibrated set of scales and a stadiometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Waist-to-hip ratio (WHR).Waist circumference and hip circumferences will be measured in centimetres
using a tape measure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure. Blood pressure levels will be obtained using a mercury sphygmomanometer on the right
arm of seated subjects.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Exercise Capacity.The 6-minute walk test (6MWT) is a commonly used objective measure of functional exercise capacity in cardiac rehabilitation. The distance an individual is able to walk along a flat 25-30 m walkway over a 6 minute period, with breaks as required, is recorded. The test is a self-paced, submaximal test of exercise capacity, and has been found to have a moderate-to-high reliability and validity.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks and 6 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health-related quality of life. The MacNew questionnaire will be used for the assessment of heart disease specifc health-related quality of life.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety. The Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale questionnaire will be used for the assessment of anxiety.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression. The Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale questionnaire will be used for the assessment of depression.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks and 6 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Smartphone Application Usability. The Unified Theory of Acceptance and Use of Technology (UTAUT2) questionnaire will be used to assess the usability of the Vire DoCHANGE app and ToDo-CR program</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sedentary behaviour (self-reported).Self-reported sedentary behaviour will be assessed using the Past-Day Adults Sedentary Time (PAST) questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks and 6 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Moderate-vigorous physical activity (self-reported). Self-reported physical activity will be assessed using the Active Australia Survey.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks and 6 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Attending a phase II (outpatient) cardiac rehabilitation program, with stable coronary heart disease and receiving optimal medical treatment +/- revascularisation, that is, coronary artery bypass graft surgery, percutaneous coronary intervention or another transcatheter procedure, or have had a myocardial infarction. Eligible participants must also have a smartphone.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants will be excluded if they have New York Heart Association class II-IV symptoms of heart failure (or documented signs and symptoms of chronic heart failure, with ejection fraction &lt; 45%), uncontrolled arrhythmias, severe chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, uncontrolled hypertension, symptomatic peripheral artery disease, unstable angina, uncontrolled diabetes, are unable to perform a submaximal walking test (6-minute walk test), or are unable to wear an accelerometer due to disability, for example, if they are confined to a wheelchair.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>No control group</concealment>
    <sequence>No control group</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This is a feasibility study.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>All participants who completed the baseline assessment and attended at least one session within the 6-week acrdiac rehabilitation (CR) program will be included in the evaluation sample. Quantitative analysis of outcome measures will be conducted. A p-value of less than 0.05 will be considered statistically significant. Qualitative thematic analysis of feedback from CR participants on the usage of the behavioural app (ToDo-CR) may be used.

The number of minutes per day spent in sedentary behaviour will be calculated using standard countbased intensity threshold values of counts per minute: &lt; 100 for sedentary behaviour (&lt;1.5 MET). Four
further summary measures of sedentary behaviours will calculated per day and averaged over valid days:
(a) percentage of the wear-day spent in sedentary behaviour (b) number of sedentary bouts (defined as a
period of consecutive minutes where the accelerometer registered &lt;100 counts/minutes) (c) average duration of sedentary bouts and (d) number of sedentary breaks (defined as at least 1 min where the
accelerometer registered &gt;= 100 counts/minute following a sedentary bout). The Freedson Combination
energy expenditure algorithm will be used to determine the intensity cut-points for MVPA. This outcome variable will be used to investigate whether participants have reached the World Health Organisation physical activity guidelines.

Additional analyses will be completed with a one-way repeated measures analysis of variance (ANOVA) to
test for differences in physical activity and sedentary behaviour (with a 95% confidence interval (CI)) within
the sample over 6 months. Intention-to-treat analysis will be used at 6-weeks, 6-months where data is missing, bringing the last value forward. A maximum of three attempts will be made to contact participants so outcome measures can be obtained, making the analysis more complete.

Sample size
As this project is a feasibility study a formal sample size calculation has not been completed. The aim is to recruit a minimum of 30 participants.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/02/2018</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>4/06/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>3/12/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Canberra Hospital - Garran</hospital>
    <postcode>2605 - Garran</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Nicole Freene </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Canberra, University Drive, Bruce, ACT, 2617</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Canberra</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Bruce
ACT
Australia
2617</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Sander van Berlo</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Onmi Design
Torenallee 30-10, Eindhoven, NL</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Netherlands</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Prof Rachel Davey</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University of Canberra, University Drive, Bruce, ACT, 2617</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Cardiac rehabilitation (CR) is a secondary prevention program for cardiovascular disease. Physical activity (PA) is considered a core component of cardiac rehabilitation programs. Despite this, studies have found that PA levels are low in CR participants and sitting time is high. The aim of this study is evaluate the feasibility of a behavioural smartphone application (ToDo-CR) to decrease sedentary behaviour (SB) in CR participants. A secondary objective will be to determine whether the smartphone application increases MVPA in CR.  Studies have identified that CR patients are interested in support via the internet and mobile phones.  Yet, few studies have investigated the efficacy of smartphone applications in CR. To our knowledge this will be the first study to investigate the use of a smartphone application in CR and its effect on SB. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Nil currently</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>ACT Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Canberra Hospital, Yamba Drive, Garran, ACT, 2605</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/10/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nicole Freene</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy
University of Canberra
University Drive
Bruce
ACT 2617</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6201 5550</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nicole.freene@canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nicole Freene</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy
University of Canberra
University Drive
Bruce
ACT 2617</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6201 5550</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nicole.freene@canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nicole Freene</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy
University of Canberra
University Drive
Bruce
ACT 2617</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6201 5550</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nicole.freene@canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nicole Freene</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy
University of Canberra
University Drive
Bruce
ACT 2617</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6201 5550</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nicole.freene@canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>