<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372252">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/01/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/02/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000185369</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Metabolic effects of cross-sex hormone treatment</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Metabolic effects of cross-sex hormone treatment in transgender individuals</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1192-2161</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Metabolic Health</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal metabolism and endocrine development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Potential participants will be invited to the study if they are scheduled to commence male-to-female (feminising) or female-to-male (masculinising) cross-sex hormone treatment. Cross-sex hormones are used to facilitate the gender affirmation process in transgender individuals. Feminising therapy initially begins with administration of androgen blockers, with oestrodiol (oral or transdermal) added after 6 - 12 weeks, with the dose titrated to maximal dose or until biochemical targets are met. Masculinisng therapy involves adminstration of transdermal testosterone, beginning at 1/4 dose on alternating days and titrated up over 8-12 weeks until maximal dose is reached. After biochemical treatments are met, transition to injectable testosterone treatment may be considered. Treatments are individualised and may vary according to individual response.
Study appointments will be before commencing treatment (baseline), 3 months, 6 months and 12 months. Each appointment will take 40-60 minutes to complete, and will be scheduled alongside the routine appointments with the Endocrinologist, At each time-point routine clinical measurements will be recorded (fasting glucose, blood lipid profile, FBC, LFT, &amp; UEC ). In addition to these, the following outcomes will be measured:  Body composition using biometric impedance analysis and dual-energy xray absorpiometry (DEXA); dietary intake, physical activity, and self-perceived health &amp; wellbeing will be measured using questionnaires; and a small blood sample will be collected to measure fasting insulin, erythrocyte and plasma fatty acid profile, adipokines and inflammatory markers.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in eicosapentaenoic acid and docosahexaenoic acid content of erythrocyte membranes, measured using gas chromatography from a fasted blood sample</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 3, 6, &amp; 12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anthropometric measurements 
Height (baseline only), weight, waist circumference, hip circumference</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 3, 6 &amp; 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body fat distribution, measured using biometric impedance analysis and dual x-ray absorpiometry (DEXA)</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 3, 6 &amp; 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Insulin Resistance, as measured by HOMA-IR (fasting glucose x fasting insulin / 22.5), measured by commercial pathology using standardized techniques.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 3, 6, &amp; 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma Inflammatory Markers (IL-6, TNF-alpha), measured using ELISA assays</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 3, 6, &amp; 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Routine clinical measurements of metabolic health (LFT, FBC, UEC, blood lipid profile [total cholesterol, LDL-cholesterol, HDL-cholesterol, fasting triglycerides, fasting glucose, &amp; HbA1c), measured by hospital pathology services using standardized methods</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 3, 6, &amp; 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dietary Intake, measured using a validated online food frequency questionnaire (Australian Eating Survey)</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 3, 6, &amp; 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-perceived health and well-being, measured using self-administered questionnaire (SF-36)</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 3, 6, &amp; 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical Activity, measured using a validated self-administered questionnaire (International Physical Activity Questionnaire, long version)</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 3, 6, &amp; 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasting serum insulin, measured by commercial pathology using standardized methods</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 3, 6, &amp; 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma adipokines (adiponectin, leptin), measured using ELISA assays </outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 3, 6, &amp; 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in plasma eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA) and docoshexaenoic acid (DHA) levels, measured using gas chromatography from a fasted blood sample</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 3. 6, &amp; 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be invited to join the study if they are:
- Aged 18 years or older
- Commencing cross-sex hormone treatment at John Hunter Hospital</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>The following people will be excluded from volunteering from the study:
- Children and young people  less than 18 years
- People who regularly consume more than 2 serves / week (250g) oily fish or taking fish oil capsules
- People with an intellectual or mental impairment who cannot give informed consent</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Sample Size: A 23% increase in Omega-3 Index (%EPA+DHA content of erythrocyte membranes) has been determined to reduce the risk of sudden cardiac death by approximately 50%. Previous studies in transgender individuals and early pregnancy have reported changes to plasma DHA levels, with no changes to EPA levels . Eighteen people in each group will give 80% power to detect a 20% change in DHA content of erythrocyte membranes, assuming a standard deviation in the response to treatment to be 30%, with alpha set at p=0.05. In order to account for withdrawals we will recruit 20 participants from each group (i.e. 20 trans-males and 20 trans-females).
Treatment effects: All the data will be tested for normality and expressed as mean +/- SEM or median (IQR) as appropriate. The effect of CSH on outcome measures will be determined using paired t-tests. Alpha will be set at p=0.05. Significance (P-value set at 0.05) indicates the changes from the baseline values. Changes from the baselines over all time-points will be determined using one-way ANOVA using repeated measures.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>True</patientregistry>
    <followup>12</followup>
    <followuptype>Months</followuptype>
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/02/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>John Hunter Hospital - New Lambton</hospital>
    <postcode>2305 - New Lambton</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Newcastle</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University Drive,
Callaghan, NSW, 2308</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Newcastle</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University Drive,
Callaghan, NSW, 2308</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Hunter Medical Research Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1/1 Kookaburra Circuit,
New Lambton Heights
NSW, 2305</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>John Hunter Hospital</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Locked Bag 1
New Lambton
NSW, 2305</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Biological differences between males and females are well known in terms of reproductive functioning. However, it is becoming increasingly well recognised that non-communicable chronic diseases, such as diabetes, cardiovascular disease, and many neurological and mental health disorders display sexual dimorphisms in their pathogenesis and presentation. Females are somewhat protected against both the development of insulin resistance and cardiovascular disease compared with males of a similar age. However, this difference between sexes diminishes after women reach menopause. Much of this sexual dimorphism has been attributed to the regulatory effects of the steroid sex hormones testosterone, oestrogen and progesterone. 
Cross-sex hormones (CSH) are a treatment option used to treat gender dysphoria (DSM V) and facilitate transition from their natal sex (i.e. sex assigned at birth) to their identified gender. Feminisation typically requires administration of androgen-blockers and co-administration of oestrogen hormones, whereas masculinisation requires administration of testosterone treatment. Treatment with CSH is usually lifelong. 
Evidence shows that transgender persons are at an increased risk of mental distress and chronic disease. In addition to the physical changes induced by cross-sex hormone therapy commonly associated with puberty (such as changes to body hair, skin appearance), cross-sex hormones have been shown to influence factors such as body composition. The overall effect of cross-sex hormone treatment on cardiovascular and diabetes risk is still unclear. Cross-sex hormone treatment has been reported to both improve and impair various CVD risk factors, such as fasting glucose and insulin levels, plasma docosahexaenoic acid (DHA) levels, adipokines and C-reactive protein. 
Studying the effect of cross-sex hormones on DHA status and other risk factors for CVD and diabetes in transgender persons undergoing hormone therapy allows a unique opportunity to investigate the contribution of sex hormones to the sexual dimorphisms apparent in both these conditions. Furthermore, investigating metabolic changes in response to cross-sex hormone treatment may help to inform dietary and/or pharmaceutical strategies for minimizing the health risks associated with receiving CSH in this at risk group. Therefore the aim of this observational study is to measure the effect of cross-sex hormone therapy on metabolic risk factors for both diabetes and CVD in transgender individuals undergoing hormone therapy.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Locked Bag 1
New Lambton, NSW, 2305</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/12/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016/12/14/4.03</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Newcastle Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics Officer
Research Office,
The Chancellery,
The University of Newcastle
University Drive,
Callaghan, NSW, 2308</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/01/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H-2017-0011</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/01/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Katie-Jane Wynne</name>
      <address>John Hunter Hospital
Locked Bag 1
New Lambton, NSW, 2305</address>
      <phone>+61 2 49213000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>katie-jane.wynne@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kylie Abbott</name>
      <address>305B Medical Sciences Building
University of Newcastle
University Drive, 
Callaghan, NSW, 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 49215638</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kylie.abbott@uon.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kylie Abbott</name>
      <address>305B Medical Sciences Building
University of Newcastle
University Drive, 
Callaghan, NSW, 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 49215638</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kylie.abbott@uon.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kylie Abbott</name>
      <address>305B Medical Sciences Building
University of Newcastle
University Drive, 
Callaghan, NSW, 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 49215638</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kylie.abbott@uon.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>