<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372877">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/06/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000887370</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle> Percutaneous Neuromodulation Therapy on Hamstring Flexibility in Subjects with Short Hamstring Syndrome </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Immediate Bilateral Effects of Percutaneous Neuromodulation Therapy on Hamstring Flexibility in Subjects with Short Hamstring Syndrome </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Short Hamstring Syndrome </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Hamstring Flexibility </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>There are 3 different groups receiving one of each treatment:
1. Percutaneous Electrical Stimulation (PES group). Subjects in the PES Group received the PES thecnique in the perineurium of the sciatic nerve. Specifically, this intervention consisted in the application of an asymmetric biphasic rectangular current of 150 microseconds and 10 Hz using a specifically developed medically certified device (Physio Invasive, Enraf Nonius, Prim, SPAIN). The subject lay prone with his feet outside the table. The sciatic nerve was located at 50% of the distance between the greater trochanter and interlinear articular knee by ultrasound machine (cross-section) (Logiq, GE Healthcare, USA) and then, a needle (0.30mm x 0.40mm) was inserted, perpendicular to the surface of the skin, until the perineurium of sciatic nerve. Prior to inserting a needle, the underlying skin was cleaned with isopropyl alcohol. The intensity of the current was necessary to cause an exacerbated muscle contraction, according to the Valera and Minaya protocol´s: once-off 1.5 mins session, current was applied every 4 times cycle for 20 s.
The intervention will be performed in the department of Physicaltherapy in the University of Seville by a sports physiotherapist with an experience of more than 5 years.
2. Passive Stretching Technique. Subjects in the Stretching group received passive stretching of the hamstring muscles in their dominant leg. While lying supine, a researcher who was blinded to SLR test measures would passively position the subject into the SLR position (hip in flexion, knee in extension, and ankle in neutral) without pain/discomfort to the point where resistance to movement was first noted. This position was then maintained for 20 seconds  and repeated further 4 times. During the 20 second stretches, the therapist monitored the subjects to ensure they did not make any compensation that could modify the stretching position. Each subject had a total of 1.5 minutes of stretching on their lower extremity. 
3. Neurodynamic Sliding Technique. Subjects in the Neurodynamic group received sciatic neurodynamic sliders, performed in supine. The objective of the technique is to produce a sliding movement of neural (sciatic) structures relative to their adjacent tissues . Sliders involve the application of movement/stress to the nervous system proximally while releasing movement/stress distally and then reversing the sequence. Recent research has shown that sliders actually result in greater excursion than simply stretching the nerve. Subjects were supine with their neck and thoracic spine supported in a forward flexed position. Concurrent hip and knee flexion were alternated dynamically with concurrent hip and knee extension. The therapist alternated the combination of movement depending on the tissue resistance level. This combination of movements was performed for 1.5 minutes on their dominant lower extremity. </interventions>
    <comparator>Mechanical Stimulation (Needle group). Subjects in the Needle Group received mechanical stimulation in the perineurium of the sciatic nerve through a needle. The sciatic nerve was located at 50% of the distance between the greater trochanter and interlinear articular knee by ultrasound machine (cross-section) (Logiq, GE Healthcare, USA) and then, a needle (0.30mm x 0.40mm) was inserted, perpendicular to the surface of the skin, until the perineurium of sciatic nerve. Prior to inserting a neddle, the underlying skin was cleaned with isopropyl alcohol. This intervention was performed during 1.5 min.
Every interventions will be performed in the department of Physicaltherapy in the University of Seville by a sports physiotherapist with an experience of more than 5 years.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The range of hip motion, assessed by passive straight leg raise test (SLR)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and after intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>muscular activity assessed by tensiomyography</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and after intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Young people, SLR test&gt;70 degree</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>30</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria were hamstring injury within the past year, a Personal Psychological Apprehension Scale (PPAS) score &gt;37.5, verbal report of performing regular lower extremity muscle stretching exercises, history of neck trauma (whiplash), neck symptoms, history of fracture in any part of the body, history of growth disorders, history of neurological or orthopedic disorders, diagnosis of herniated disk, low back pain in the last 6 months, and body mass index (BMI) lower than 20 Kg/cm2 or higher than 30 Kg/cm2, commonly accepted contraindications to invasive phsyiotherapist technique including chronic joint disease, surgery, prosthesis or osteosynthesis in the area of intervention, cardiac disease, neoplasia, coagulopathy, and use of certain drugs (fluoroquinoles, anticoagulants, corticosteroids or non-steroidal anti-inflammatories), any contraindications to needling per se including unsurmountable fear of needles, history of adverse reaction to needling, immunocompromise, difficulty expressing feelings appropriately and/or allergy to metals, and  epilepsy</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>sealed opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using dice-rolling</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>26/06/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>28/07/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>28/07/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Seville</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Seville</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Avicena street, s/n, 41009, Seville, Spain</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Spain</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Seville</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Avicena street, s/n, 41009, Seville, Spain</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Spain</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Injuries to the hamstring musculature are commonplace in many mainstream sports and occupations involving physical activity. Many predisposing factors for hamstring injury have been suggested within the literature, including insufficient warm- up, poor flexibility, muscle imbalances, neural tension, fatigue. 
Inadequate flexibility within the posterior thigh compartment appears to be one of the more commonly accepted causes of hamstring injuries. There are several studies in which manual therapy is applied to improve the flexibility of the hamstrings: stretching, eccentric exercises; and/or neural therapy. All these procedures caused a short-term increase in hamstring flexibility.
Stretching and eccentric exercises are local and homolateral therapy. However, we believe that neural therapy may be local but have a distant effect. Therefore, the aim of this study will be to examine the immediate effects of a technique of hamstring stretching, neurodynamic sciatic sliding, percutaneous electric stimulation and mechanical stimulation with needle on  sciatic nerve in asymptomatic subjects with short hamstrings syndrome. We hypothesized that the classical stretching technique would improve the homolateral range of motion, as assessed by the passive straight leg elevation test (SLR), while sliding neural techniques would lead to short-term bilateral improvement. Muscle activity could be affected.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University Hospital Virgen Macarena-Virgen del Rocio.</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Dr. Fedriani, Street 3, 41009 Seville, Spain</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/05/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/02/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Spain</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Blanca De la Cruz Torres</name>
      <address>Avicena street, s/n, 41009, Seville, Spain
Department of Physical Therapy
University of Seville</address>
      <phone>+34 666676870</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bcruz@us.es</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Blanca De la Cruz Torres</name>
      <address>Avicena street, s/n, 41009, Seville, Spain
Department of Physical Therapy
University of Seville</address>
      <phone>+34 666676870</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bcruz@us.es</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Blanca De la Cruz Torres</name>
      <address>Avicena street, s/n, 41009, Seville, Spain
Department of Physical Therapy
University of Seville</address>
      <phone>+34 666676870</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bcruz@us.es</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Blanca De la Cruz Torres</name>
      <address>Avicena street, s/n, 41009, Seville, Spain
Department of Physical Therapy
University of Seville</address>
      <phone>+34 666676870</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bcruz@us.es</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>