<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308064">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/07/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/08/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000660280</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Lifestyle Outcomes of Absolute cardiovascular risk Feedback project</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial to test the effect of providing absolute cardiovascular feedback, tailored lifestyle information and telephone counselling and support on lifestyle behaviours and cardiovascular risk factors in participants at risk of cardiovascular disease</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>LOAF</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cardiovascular disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Group1. Face to face feedback (once only 45 minute session ) of absolute cardiovascular risk to patient with advice on risk factor profile and lifestyle changes to improve risk, together with individualised written materials.
Group 2. Face to face feedback (once only 45 minute session) plus telephone support and counselling (monthly phone calls for  6 months and then bi-monthly phone calls for 6 months - 9 phone calls of 10-12 minutes duration)`
Group 3. Control group - usual general practice care</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will receive their usual general practice care. General Practitioners (GP) will receive their pathology results for ethical reasons.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To measure the decrease in the proportion of their energy coming from saturated fats by asking participants to complete the Dietary Questionnaire for Epidemiological Studies (DQESv2) - Cancer Coucil of Victoria</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and 1 year after intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess dietary salt intake using DQESv2</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and 1 year after intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To monitor physical activity using The Lifescripts questionnaire and using accelerometers(Actigragh GT1M) for seven consecutive days</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and 1 year after intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Urinary Sodium Excretion will be measured in a single, timed, overnight, non-fasting urine collection- not by 24 hour urine collection. Aliquots of each sample will be measured in duplicate for sodium and potassium using indirect ion selective electrodes and for creatinine by the Abbott Jaffe reaction, all in an Abbott Architect analyser. Urinary sodium will then be converted to daily excretion rates using the multipliers of 8 hour urinary excretion.</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and 1 year after intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess waist-hip ratio using Figure Finder Tape Measure. Measurements are to taken twice,  directly over the skin and at the level of the tape. Waist measurement is taken at the level of mid-point between the inferior margin of the last rib and the iliac crest in the mid axillary plane. Hip measurement is taken at the level of the greatest posterior protuberance of the buttocks which usually corresponds anteriorly with the level of the symphysis pubis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and 1 year after intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2. Blood pressure will be measured using an OMRON office digital blood pressure HEM-907 monitor after participants have been seated for 3 minutes. Three measurements will be taken two minutes apart and an average of the last two measurements calculated.</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and 1 year after intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>body mass index (BMI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline and 1 yr following randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>fasting blood glucose levels.
Blood samples will be collected after a 12 hour fast using Glucose List No 7D66</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and 1 year after intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>total cholesterol to high density lipo-protein (HDL) cholesterol ratio 
Blood samples will be taken after a 12 hour fast using the Abbott Architect c8000 analyser. The 3K33 Ultra HDL reagent kit will be used to analyse HDL cholesterol and the Cholesterol Kit List No. 7D62 for cholesterol.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline and 1 yr following randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Absolute cardiovascular risk(ACR) of &gt;10%
Minimum age of females = 45yrs
Minimum age for males = 55yrs</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. ACR &lt;10%
2. A history of cardiovascular morbidity(myocardial infarction, stroke, peripheral vascular disease, angina, transient ischaemic attack, &gt;50% carotid stenosis, carotid endarterectomy or stenting, coronary artery angioplasty or stenting, coronary artery bypass grafting)
3. Serious intercurrent illness likely to cause death within the next 2 years
4. Current participation in another clinical trial
5. Not literate in English
6. GP considers them unsuitable for the study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>GPs and their practices are recruited by invitational letter.
Once recruited, potential participants are identified using a data search of  the GPs client database.
A list of patients is generated and given to the GP for review regarding eligibility and contraindications to participation.
Invitational letter sent to potential participant from the practice, including project description and reply slip.
On reply the participant is issued with an ID number, participant information is sent out, an appointment is made to sign consent forms and perform the baseline assessment.
If the partcipant is assessed as having a ACR of &gt; 10% they are allocated into either the two intervention groups or the control group by cluster randomisation by general practice, based on computer generated random numbers and performed by a person not directly  involved in implementation to ensure allocation concealment.</concealment>
    <sequence>computer generated random numbers</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Factorial</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>90</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>7000</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Menzies Research Institute (UTAS)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level2/199 Macquarie St
Hobart 7000
Tasmania</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Heart Foundation of Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Heart Foundation, Level 12, 500 Collins Street, Melbourne VIC 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Much cardiovascular disease could be prevented if GPs could encourage their patients to improve their diet, physical activity and smoking behaviour. Communication of risk to patients may change their behaviour but the effectiveness of individualised cardiovascular risk feedback in general practice is not yet known.  This study aims determine whether feedback of their cardiovascular risk to patients in general practice can improve lifestyle behaviours associated with cardiovascular disease.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Commitee (Tasmania) Network</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>HREC(Tasmania)Network
Office of Research Services
University of Tasmania
Private Bag 01
HOBART TAS 7001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/06/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H0010492</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/05/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Tania Winzenberg</name>
      <address>Menzies Research Institute
Private Bag 23
Hobart 7001
Tasmania</address>
      <phone>+61 3 62267700</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 62267704</fax>
      <email>Tania.Winzenberg@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Helen Steane</name>
      <address>Menzies Research Institute
Private Bag 23
Hobart 7001
Tasmania</address>
      <phone>+61 3 62267758</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 62267704</fax>
      <email>hrsteane@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Helen Steane</name>
      <address>Menzies Research Institute
Private Bag 23
Hobart 7001
Tasmania</address>
      <phone>+61 3 62267758</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 62267704</fax>
      <email>hrsteane@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>