<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320642">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/12/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/01/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000074099</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An evaluation of a computerised cognitive behavioural therapy programme  for depression among young people who are outside of mainstream education.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of a computerised Cognitive Behavioural Therapy programme on depressive symptoms in young people who have mild to moderate depression and are outside of mainstream education.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1112-8752</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Computerised cognitive behavoural therapy (CBT) intervention.  Participants are asked to complete 1 or 2 30 minute levels per week; there are  7 levels in total which should be completed within 5 weeks as suits the individual.  The topics covered include psycho-education, relaxation techniques, social skills training, activity scheduling,  problem solving, recognition and restructing of cognitive disortions, hopefulness and helpseeking.  

A crossover study design is used: all participants are screened at baseline and then randomised to treatment now (to be completed over the following 4-5 weeks) or delayed start (start after 5 weeks).  All participants are reassessed at 5 weeks (after those randomised to 'start now' have completed the intervention and before those randomised to 'delayed start' begin) and at 10 weeks (after all participants have completed the programme), 50% of participants randomised to 'delayed start' are reassessed at 15 weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>Delayed treatment.  
1.All participants are assessed (assessment 1)
2. Then all participants are randomised to beginning the treatment straight away (group 1) or beginning the treatment after assessment two in 5 weeks time (group 2).
3.  Over the following 4-5 weeks intervention  takes place for group 1, no intervention for group 2.
4. At week 5 assessment 2 takes place for all participants (this is post intervention for group 1 but still pre intervention for group 2. 
5. Then group 2 does the intervention, group 1 has no intervention.
6. At week 10 -11 all participants have a 3rd assessment (this is post intervention for group 2 and follow up for group 1. 
7.  At week 15-16 half of group 2 participants have a fourth (Follow up) assessment (not all are asked to do this due to timing of the school term and finishing dates for this involved sites)</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>At each assessment the primary measure is depressive symptoms as measured by the Childrens Depression Rating Scale, Revised (CDRS-R)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre treatment (for all participants)
At 5 weeks (post intervention for group 1 and pre intervention for group 2)
At 10 weeks (this is a follow up point for group 1 and post intervention for group 2).
At 15 weeks (follow up point for 50% of those in group 2 only).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life as measured by the Paediatric Quality of Life Enjoyment and Satisfaction Questionnaire (PQ-LES-Q).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre treatment (for all participants)
At 5 weeks (post intervention for group 1 and pre intervention for group 2)
At 10 weeks (this is a follow up point for group 1 and post intervention for group 2).
At 15 weeks (follow up point for 50% of those in group 2 only).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Locus of control as measured by the Childrens Nowicki Strickland Internal External Locus of control scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre treatment (for all participants)
At 5 weeks (post intervention for group 1 and pre intervention for group 2)
At 10 weeks (this is a follow up point for group 1 and post intervention for group 2).
At 15 weeks (follow up point for 50% of those in group 2 only).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self reported depressive symptoms as measured by the Reynolds Adolescent Depression Scale (RADS-2)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre treatment (for all participants)
At 5 weeks (post intervention for group 1 and pre intervention for group 2)
At 10 weeks (this is a follow up point for group 1 and post intervention for group 2).
At 15 weeks (follow up point for 50% of those in group 2 only).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety symptoms as measured by the Spence Anxiety Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre treatment (for all participants)
At 5 weeks (post intervention for group 1 and pre intervention for group 2)
At 10 weeks (this is a follow up point for group 1 and post intervention for group 2).
At 15 weeks (follow up point for 50% of those in group 2 only).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hopelessness as measured by the Kazdin Hopelessness Scale (HPLS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre treatment (for all participants)
At 5 weeks (post intervention for group 1 and pre intervention for group 2)
At 10 weeks (this is a follow up point for group 1 and post intervention for group 2).
At 15 weeks (follow up point for 50% of those in group 2 only).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Satisfaction with treatment - short questionnaire and interview for young people who have completed the intervention.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 5 weeks (for group 1 )
At 10 weeks (for group 1 and group 2).
At 15 weeks (follow up point for 50% of those in group 2 only).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>young people aged 12-18 years who are in an Alternative Education, youth transition or intensive youth programmes for young people who are disengaged or at risk of being disengaged from mainstream education.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>12</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Young people who are already recieving CBT, Interpersonal Therapy or Selective Serotonin Reuptake Inhibitors (SSRI's) for depression.

Young people who have severe depression, current sucide risk or other severe mental health issue which may mean that they are unsafe on this programme.

Young people who have a disablity or insufficent english language that would result in them being unable to use the computer programme.

Young people who are not expected to be enrolled in the participating site for a 10 week period.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>students are invited to participate in the study by their tutor.  Those who consent take part in a baseline interview.  Once this is completed the participant opens a sealed envelope allocating them to treatment now or treatment delayed.  Students who have symptoms of mild to moderate depression on the CDRS are the target participants.   We aim to recurit 30 participants in this group.  Interested students who have no or minimal depressive symptoms are able to participate if they wish. Outcome data for this group will be analysed separately from that of students with depressive symptoms. Students who have severe depression or safety issues are reffered for additonal assistance.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using a randomization table created by a computer software (i.e., computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Assessments at week 5 and week 10 are recorded for 20% of participants and coded by a research assistant who is blind to their allocation.  The outcome scores obtained by this research assistant are compared to those obtained by the main reseracher (who is not blinded).  The checking of scores will be carried out an independent statistican and analysed for any systematic difference in results between the reseachers by participants treatment allocation.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/07/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Theresa Fleming</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Dept of Psychological Medicine
University of Auckland
PO Box 92019
Auckland Mail Centre 
Auckland 1142.
New Zealand</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ministry of Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Great South Road
Penrose
AUCKLAND 1061</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Tertiary Education Commission</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The Tertiary Education Commission - Te Amorangi Matauranga Matua 
Service Centre
1 Ash Road, Wiri
Private Bag 76928
Manukau City 2241</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Auckland</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Ths is supervised PhD work from the 
Dr Sally Merry
Dept of Psychological Medicine
University of Auckland
PO Box 92019
Auckland Mail Centre 
Auckland 1142. 
New Zealand</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Sally Merry</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Dept of Psychological Medicine
University of Auckland
PO Box 92019
Auckland Mail Centre 
Auckland 1142. 
New Zealand</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a trial of a computerised cognitive behavioural therapy (c-cbt) programme for young people who outside of, or poorly engaged with, mainstream education.  The programme is designed to reduce depressive symptoms.  Participants are randomised to the c-cbt programme now, or beginning in 5 weeks time.  The programme has 7 levels which take 20-30 minutes each.  Participants usually do 2 levels per week.  Participants are re-assessed at 5 and at 10 weeks time.  Fifty percent of students who are in the delayed start group are reassessed at 15 weeks time.  Measures include depressive symptoms (CRDS and RADS) anxiety symptoms (Spence), Quality of Life (PQLS), Hopelessness (HPLS) and locus of control.  Satisfaction with treatment and beliefs about treatment and the intervention are explored using semi structured interviews before, after the intervention and at 4 weeks follow up. Parents and tutors are invited to give feedback too, via semi structured interviews.  The target number of participants is 30 young people who have symptoms of mild to moderate depression.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.sparx.org.nz</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Y Regional Ethics committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 1031 Hamilton, 
Hamilton 3204</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/07/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/03/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Theresa Fleming</name>
      <address>Dept of Psychological Medicine
University of Auckland
PO Box 92019 
Auckland Mail Centre 
Auckland 1142.</address>
      <phone>64 9 3737599 extn 87891</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>t.fleming@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Theresa Fleming</name>
      <address>Dept of Psychological Medicine
University of Auckland
PO Box 92019 
Auckland Mail Centre 
Auckland 1142.</address>
      <phone>64 9 3737599 extn 87891</phone>
      <fax>64 9 3737013</fax>
      <email>t.fleming@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Theresa Fleming</name>
      <address>Dept of Psychological Medicine
University of Auckland
PO Box 92019 
Auckland Mail Centre 
Auckland 1142.</address>
      <phone>64 9 3737599 extn 87891</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>t.fleming@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>