<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="113">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/08/2005</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/08/2005</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12605000167662</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A  double blind randomised placebo-controlled   intervention trial to determine the efficacy of the probiotic VSL #3  in reducing the incidence and or frequency of diarrhoea in enterally-fed critically ill patients.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A  double blind randomised placebo-controlled   intervention trial to determine the efficacy of the probiotic VSL #3  in reducing the incidence and or frequency of diarrhoea in enterally-fed critically ill patients.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Diarrhoeal illness and infection in critically ill patients</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>VSL#3 is a commercially available probiotic and helps to replenish the "good" bacteria in the small intestine, ensuring that the digestive system works efficiently and effectively. It is safe, easily digestible and freely available to all consumers and has demonstrated health benefits in clinical trials. Participants will be randomly assigned to a treatment or placebo group with in 48 hours of admission to the intensive care unit. Study participants will remain in the study for a maximum period of 21 days or until tube feeding is ceased by the patient's attending physician or the patient is discharged from hospital. At this point data collection would cease.
Study participants, intensive care nurses and attending  physicians will be blinded to group membership. All critically ill patients who are unable to consume normal oral diet will be fed via a feeding tube utilising the ICU enteral feed algorithm.
The probiotic/placebo will be prepared in pharmacy and packaged in a 50 ml syringe and delivered to the intensive care unit (or ward) daily and matched with the participants study identification number. The VSL#3/VSL#3 placebo syringe will be administered to each study participant twice daily at 0900 hours and 2100 hours. The probiotic/placebo preparation will be administered by the intensive care nurse responsible for each patients care and delivered to the patient's digestive tract via either a nasogastric or nasojejunal feeding tube. Information relative to the record of stool output (time of episode, frequency of output, consistency and volume of stool output using the King's College Stool Chart  will be entered on a 24 hour Data Collection Sheet.  Permission has been sought and granted from the King's College Faculty of Dietetics [London] in reference to using the instrument for the purposes of this study. Information from the Daily Data Collection Sheet will be secured on a computer locked database in the intensive care unit.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the effect of the probiotic VSL #3 versus placebo administration of  VSL#3  in intensive care patients receiving enteral feed.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the effect of VSL #3 versus placebo administration of VSL #3 on the markers of infection of critically ill patients receiving enteral feeding. Data collection relevant to bacteriological markers of infection include routine testing of Central Access Devices tip assays, blood, tracheal aspirates and urine cultures. Data collection relevant to the biochemical markers of inflammation include the routine testing of immunoglobulins (IgG, IgM and IgA), 'C' Reactive Protein and Interleukin 6 and 10 assays.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All prospective adult participants that may require tube feeding as part of their routine management of their illness while a patient admitted to the ICU will be screened preoperatively in the pre-admission clinic or on admission to the ICU. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with the following characteristics would be excluded from the study;  &lt; 18 years Likely to be tube fed &lt; 48 hours Allergy to milk preparations Present with special dietary requirements (other than diabetic or renal considerations) requiring Total Parenteral Nutrition (TPN) Present with any condition that might interfere with the delivery of enteral feeds such as obstruction of the gastrointestinal tract.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Consecutively numbered envelopes which are not opened until a subject is enrolled. Envelopes are only opened in Pharmacy so that the appropriate treatment can be supplied.</concealment>
    <sequence>Random number generation function in Excel was used. No restrictions</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>8/08/2005</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Department of Health and Human Services (Tasmanian Government)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Launceston General Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>no secondary sponsor</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>It is not clearly understood why some critically ill patients develop diarrhoea while being fed by stomach tube.  Diarrhoeal illness has been linked to infection and treatment by antibiotics which can disrupt the normal functioning of the gastrointestinal tract. Excessive diarrhoea may cause patients not to digest the essential nutrients they need to overcome illness.   Severe cases of diarrhoea may also lead to discomfort and loss of dignity for the patient. Health professionals continually seek new therapies to remedy the onset of diarrhoea and the potential discomforts associated with it.
The aim of this study is to find out whether commercially available probiotic preparations (like yoghurt type foods) have the ability to reduce the frequency of diarrhoea in patients receiving their nourishment by feed tube in the intensive care unit. A secondary aim of this study is to find out whether probiotic preparations can decrease infection rates in seriously ill patients. Probiotics are not drugs and through out the world they are considered to be very safe. They represent a range of food ingredients or supplements which can be bought from health food shops and supermarkets. These foods contain live microbes many of which normally reside in the intestines. Research suggests that these foods improve intestinal health by restoring the normal balance of microbes in the gastrointestinal tract.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee (Tasmania) Network</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>GRIFFITH UNIVERSITY HUMAN RESEARCH ETHICS COMMITTEE</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr John Gowardman</name>
      <address>Launceston General Hospital
Charles Street
Launceston TAS 7250</address>
      <phone>+61 3 63487496</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 63487495</fax>
      <email>john.gowardman@dhhs.tas.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mr Terry Frohmader</name>
      <address>1066 Lilydale Road
Underwood TAS 7268</address>
      <phone>+61 3 63951277</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>et_frohmader@bigpond.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>