<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347483">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/09/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/10/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611001055998</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Wellbeing6 Program for Anxiety and Depression - A Randomised Controlled Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial comparing clinician-assisted Internet based treatment for Generalised Anxiety Disorder (GAD) and/or depression vs. a waitlist control condition on severity of symptoms of GAD and depression.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>The Wellbeing6 Program - A Randomised Controlled Trial</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Major Depressive Disorder</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Generalised Anxiety Disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be randomly assigned to one of two groups: 1) Treatment with clinician-assisted Internet based Cognitive Behavioural Therapy for Generalised Anxiety Disorder (GAD) and/or depression, or 2) Waitlist control. All participants will meet Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders 4th Edition (DSM-IV) criteria for GAD and/or Major Depressive Disorder. All group 1 participants will separately complete 6 lessons of Internet based treatment about the management of symptoms of GAD and depression. One lesson will be completed every 7 to 14 days (it will become available after the preceding lesson has been completed, with a minimum of 7 days between lessons and a maximum of 14 days). Each lesson will take about 15 minutes to complete. Group 1 participants will have access to summaries of each lesson, homework exercises, extra resources, weekly reminder emails, and one-on-one contact with the Clinician (Clinical Psychologist) by telephone or email in the first 2 weeks, then as required. The duration of the program is 8-10 weeks, but participants will be contacted 3 months post program and asked to complete follow-up questionnaires. Study questionnaires will be administered at application, pre-treatment, mid-treatment, post-treatment, at 3 months post-treatment, and the K10 pre-each lesson. These will take about 20 minutes to complete. The treatment materials are based on cognitive behavioural techniques.</interventions>
    <comparator>Waitlist control group. These participants remain on the waitlist until the treatment groups have completed their treatment (10 weeks). At that time (10 weeks) the waitlist group will receive the same treatment as Treatment Group 1.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptoms and severity of depression is measured by the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at application, pre-treatment, mid-treatment, post-treatment, and at 3 months post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Generalised Anxiety Disorder is measured by the Generalized Anxiety Disorder - 7 Item (GAD-7) questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at application, pre-treatment, mid-treatment, post-treatment, and at 3 months post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychological distress is measured by the Kessler-10 (K-10).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered before each lesson, at pre-treatment, mid-treatment, post-treatment, and at 3 months post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptoms and severity of depression is measured by the Beck Depression Inventory - II (BDI-II).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-treatment and post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Temperament is measured by the NEO-Five Factor Inventory, Neuroticism scale (NEO-FF-I, N scale).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-treatment and post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety is also measured by the Penn State Worry Questionnaire (PSWQ).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-treatment and post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disability is measured by the WHO Disability Assessment Scale (WHODASS-II).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-treatment and post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rumination (or repetitive thinking) is measured by the Repetitive Thinking Questionnaire (RTF) and the Positive Beliefs about Rumination Scale-Adapted Version (PSRS-A).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-treatment and post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient satisfaction questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-treatment and post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence to lessons and homework.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre- each lesson (lesson must be completed and homework downloaded before patient advances to next lesson).

The slides of a lesson must be clicked through from start to finish before the homework for that lesson can be downloaded, and the next lesson will not become available until the homework has been downloaded. Our admin system will notify us whether or not the homework has been downloaded.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Meet Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of the American Psychiatric Association-4th Edition (DSM-IV) criteria for Generalised Anxiety Disorder and/or Major Depressive Disorder, Internet access + printer access, Australian citizen.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Current substance abuse/dependence, Psychotic mental illness (Bipolar or Schizophrenia), Current or planned psychological treatment during study duration, Change in medications during last 1 month or intended change during study duration, use of Benzodiazepines, Suicidal.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants apply on line, followed by a telephone interview to confirm diagnosis via the Mini-International Neuropsychiatric Interview (MINI 5.0.0), a structured diagnostic interview. Participants will be randomized using a list generated prior to the study. Allocation concealment will occur in the following way: A staff member not involved in the clinical trial will generate the sequence using computer software, and place each choice in a sequentially numbered, opaque, sealed and stapled envelope.</concealment>
    <sequence>A randomisation list will be generated prior to the study using computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/10/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>10/10/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>18/03/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>99</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>18/09/2012</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>We recently completed an RCT pilot study of an internet-based transdiagnostic treatment for anxiety disorders and for GAD, panic, social phobia and depression. Adherence throughout the program was roughly equivalent to that of our previous internet-based disorder-specific programs (76%), and post-treatment results finalised in January 2010 support the efficacy of this initiative.

We are interested in further investigating the efficacy of internet-based treatments for a population of people suffering from GAD and/or depression.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.virtualclinic.org.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Newby J, McKenzie A, Williams, AD, McIntyre K, Watts S, Wong N, Andrews G: Internet-based cognitive behavioural therapy for mixed anxiety and depression: Results from a RCT and effectiveness in primary care settings. Psychological Medicine. 2013, 43(12): 2635-2648.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>St Vincent's Hospital HREC 
390 Victoria Street
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/08/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>11/SVH/95</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Gavin Andrews</name>
      <address>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney
390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+612 8382 1400</phone>
      <fax>+612 8382 1401</fax>
      <email>gavina@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Gavin Andrews</name>
      <address>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney
390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+612 8382 1400</phone>
      <fax>+612 8382 1401</fax>
      <email>gavina@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Anna Mackenzie</name>
      <address>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney
390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+612 8382 1400</phone>
      <fax>+612 8382 1401</fax>
      <email>a.mackenzie@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Gavin Andrews</name>
      <address>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney 390 Victoria St Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+612 8382 1400</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gavina@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>