<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370601">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/05/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/05/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000662460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can lifelike baby dolls provide a positive therapeutic response for people living with
dementia?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A parallel-randomised controlled trial to examine the effect of a Lifelike Baby Doll intervention on anxiety, agitation and aggression symptoms in people with dementia.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Dementia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Behavioural and psychological symptoms of Dementia (BPSD)</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Agitation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Aggression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dementias</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants in the intervention group will receive three individual non-facilitated doll sessions per week, for 30 minutes (Mon, Wed, Fri), anytime outside of meal and rest times, for a period of 3 weeks (dose = 4.5 hrs).When given the Lifelike Baby Doll and the research assistant will read a short script, such as Here is a doll. It looks a lot like a real baby but its not. I will leave the doll here with you for a short time. Adherence to the intervention will be monitored via a GoPro Hero camera.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants in the usual care group will not receive any intervention. Usual care in nursing homes, randomised to the usual care arm, no intervention (Lifelike Baby Doll), training or support will be provided by the study team. The level, duration and type of service provider initiatives in relation to BPSD will be documented so these can be controlled for as potential confounders.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A composite primary outcome to compare a Lifelike Baby Doll Intervention with Usual Care in terms of reducing anxiety, agitation and  aggression. These symptoms are frequently referred to as behavioural and psychological symptoms of dementia (BPSD).

Facility staff will complete the revised Neuropsychiatric Inventory  Nursing Home (NPINH) to measure BPSD exhibited in the previous 2 weeks. Based on Carer report, the NPI-NH is a valid and reliable instrument to assess frequency (0 = never to 4 = very frequently) and severity (0 = none to 3 = marked) of 14 behavioural domains.

Video recordings via a GoPro Hero camera and will be used to measure BPSD and reflect the persons interaction or non-interaction with the doll. Recordings will take place in a naturalistic setting, i.e. where the participant is given the doll. Similar scheduled times will be organized for the usual care control,</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Post-intervention (end of Week 3) - Facility staff will complete the revised Neuropsychiatric Inventory  Nursing Home (NPINH) to measure BPSD.
Week 0 (Baseline), 1 and 3 - 5 minutes of video recordings before the intervention, 30 minutes during the intervention and 5 minutes following the intervention to measure BPSD and reflect the persons interaction or non-interaction with the doll.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the acceptability of the Lifelike Baby Doll for people with
dementia. 40 minutes of video recordings during the intervention will be used to observe acceptability.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0 (Baseline), 1 and 3 - 5 minutes of video recordings before the intervention, 30 minutes during the intervention and 5 minutes following the intervention to observe acceptability of the Lifelike Baby Doll. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the acceptability of the Lifelike Baby Doll for families of people with
dementia and associated staff within the facility. Semi-structured interviews will be conducted to evaluate acceptability by families and staff.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) Participants will be recruited from Australian government approved Residential Aged Care Facilities (RACFs) within a 60km radius of Brisbane CBD in SE Queensland.
2) Have a confirmed or probable diagnosis of dementia
3) A documented history (within last 4 weeks) of anxiety, agitation or aggression.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>55</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Residents who are already using dolls or other plush toys.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealment will be done by a central randomisation by computer, at central administration site.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>In line with outcomes observed in another RCT study of an individualised non-pharmacological intervention for improving BPSD in people with dementia (Moyle W, Cooke ML, Beattie E, Shum DH, O'Dwyer ST, Barrett S., 2014), a total sample size of 72, (36 in each group), will be required (power of 0.90, a = .05 &amp; 20% attrition).

Descriptive statistics will be computed for participant demographics and outcome measures. Where data is not normally distributed, transformations will be conducted. Where transformation is unsuccessful or inappropriate, equivalent non-parametric analyses will be conducted. Baseline variations between intervention and control groups will be examined using Chi squared tests for categorical variables, t-tests for the normally distributed continuous variables and Kruksal Wallis tests for continuous variables with skewed distributions. STATA software programs will be used. Pre- and post- intervention effect will be assessing using repeated analysis of variance with any significant baseline variables as covariates. Effect sizes of statistically significant differences will also be calculated. An Intention-To-Treat (ITT) approach will be adopted. Multiple imputations will be used to manage missing data. Qualitative interview data will be analysed thematically to capture
the key elements of the doll intervention on perceptions and attitudes.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>72</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Griffith University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Menzies Health Institute Queensland 
Griffith University
Parklands Drive
Southport
QLD 4222.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Griffith University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Menzies Health Institute Queensland 
Griffith University
Parklands Drive
Southport
QLD 4222.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>People with dementia often have complex health and social needs that do not always receive appropriate attention. This can result in the person exhibiting symptoms such as anxiety, agitation and aggression. These are referred to as behavioural and psychological symptoms of dementia (BPSD) and are often related to the person having a need that has not been fulfilled. Pharmacological treatments have been the preferred treatment to alleviate such symptoms. As a result of a greater understanding about the adverse side effects of pharmacological treatments, a number of psychosocial interventions have been trialled. One psychosocial intervention that is increasingly being used to comfort, occupy and care for people with dementia is Lifelike Baby Dolls even though there is limited evidence for their use. It is imperative that we understand if these dolls are beneficial, harmful or indeed worthless in helping to comfort people with dementia. This parallel-randomised controlled trial will compare a Lifelike Baby Doll intervention with Usual Care in reducing anxiety, agitation and aggression symptoms in people with dementia. Participants will be assessed pre-and post- intervention for BPSD using the Neuropsychiatric Inventory and video recordings. Post intervention interviews with staff and family will evaluate the impact and perceptions of the doll.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Griffith University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>170 Kessels Road
Nathan
QLD 4111</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/05/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>GU Ref No: 2016/281</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>31/03/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Wendy Moyle</name>
      <address>Menzies Health Institute Queensland 
Griffith University
Parklands Drive
Southport
QLD 4222.</address>
      <phone>+61 (0) 7 3735 5526</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>w.moyle@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Wendy Moyle</name>
      <address>Menzies Health Institute Queensland 
Griffith University
Parklands Drive
Southport
QLD 4222.</address>
      <phone>+61 (0) 7 3735 5526</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>w.moyle@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Wendy Moyle</name>
      <address>Menzies Health Institute Queensland 
Griffith University
Parklands Drive
Southport
QLD 4222.</address>
      <phone>+61 (0) 7 3735 5526</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>w.moyle@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Shirley Wee</name>
      <address>Menzies Health Institute Queensland 
Griffith University
Parklands Drive
Southport
QLD 4222.</address>
      <phone>+61 (0) 7 55529540</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.wee@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>