<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320804">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/11/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/02/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000142033</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Development of youth friendly family medicine services in Bosnia and Herzegovina: a cluster randomized controlled trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Transforming family medicine services into youth friendly services: a cluster randomised controlled trial evaluating family medicine team training and organisational restructuring in Bosnia and Herzegovina</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1112-4542</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Youth friendly health services</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>training of the family medicine team and organisational changes in the family medicine services in order to transform them into youth friendly health services. Family medicine teams in the intervention arm will attend two one-day training sessions at 3 months interval and complete assignments between the two training sessions. Training will take place in interactive sessions involving 10 teams at a time. Three trainers experienced in adolescent medicine and family medicine will provide the training.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual continuous medical education (CME) program and no organisational changes in the control family medicine services, wait list design. The CME program in Bosnia &amp; Herzegovina does not usually include modules in adolescent health but the theme may be presented in lectures in paediatrics, which the family medicine are welcome to attend if they wish. There is no specific duration for the CME program but family doctors are required to acquire a certain number of points each year by attending lectures and training sessions</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>improved scores on the "Youth Friendly Health Services-World Health Organization Plus" (YFHS-WHO+) questionnaire, a validated questionnaire measuring youth friendliness in family medicine services</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline and 3-4 months post intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>proportion of young people between the ages of 15 and 24 years consulting in these family medicine services, as extracted from the daily electronic list of patients consulting the service</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline and 6 months post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>proportion of young people between the ages of 10 and 14 years consulting in these family medicine services, as extracted from the daily electronic list of patients consulting the service. This will also be assessed as we expect the intervention to have effects on the consulting behaviour of younger adolescents as well.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline and 6 months post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Young people (15-24 years) consulting in participating family medicine services.
Only young people from the age of 15 years will be included for the evaluation of the services, although the aim is to provide services that are friendly also to younger adolescents. From the age of 15, young people are considered mature enough to provide consent on their own for participation in the study. The YFHS-WHO+ has been validated for completion by young people aged 15 years and older</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>15</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>24</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>acute illness or injury requiring immediate attention of the physician, severe mental disorder such as psychosis or suicidal thoughts requiring treatment in a specialised setting, intellectual disability, inability to understand questions in the language of Bosnia &amp; Herzegovina.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Family medicine services from 10 municipalities in the region of Zenica in Bosnia &amp; Herzegovina will participate in the study. The unit of randomisation will be the municipalities. Patients will be recruited in the participating practices to complete the YFHS-WHO+ questionnaire shortly after their consultation. They will be blind to intervention allocation. The services however will not be blind to their allocation as they will be participating in specific CME activities as part of the intervention. Allocation involved contacting a stastician not involved in the study.</concealment>
    <sequence>computer generated stratified sequence (stratified by size of municipality, large and small) by a statistician not involed in the study</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>cluster randomized trial with municipalities as the unit of randomization, family medicine services as targets for the intervention and patients as subjects to measure the outcomes of the intervention</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>2/12/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>15/12/2010</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>600</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Bosnia and Herzegovina</country>
      <state>Zenica canton</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Geneva</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Dr Dagmar Haller
4 rue Gabrielle-Perret-Gentil
1211 GENEVE 14</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Switzerland</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Geneva University Hospitals</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>4 rue Gabrielle-Perret-Gentil
1211 GENEVE 14</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Switzerland</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Foundation fami</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Dr Dejan Sredic
Nemanjina 18, 74000 Doboj</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Bosnia and Herzegovina</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Public Health Institute</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Doboj-Zenica canton
74000 Doboj</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Bosnia and Herzegovina</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>The University of Melbourne</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Dr Lena Sanci
Department of General Practice, 
200 Berkeley Street
Carlton 3053
Victoria</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Background: More evidence is needed on the effectiveness of developing youth-friendly services that address the barriers adolescents face in accessing care. Responding to the needs of young people is one of the priorities of Foundation fami, an organisation working in collaboration Geneva University Hospitals to rebuild family medicine services in post-war Bosnia &amp; Herzegovina. 
Working hypothesis: Services exposed to an intervention to improve their youth-friendliness will be assessed as more youth-friendly by adolescent clients and will fulfil a higher number of youth-friendly standards as control services that are on a wait-list to receive the intervention.
This will be a cluster randomised trial involving 10 municipalities and 60 health services of the canton of Zenica in Bosnia &amp; Herzegovina: 5 municipalities will be randomised to the intervention arm and 5 to a wait-list control arm. Family medicine teams in the intervention arm will be invited to participate in an interactive training program about youth-friendly service principles and change processes within their service. The main outcome measures at baseline (before randomisation) and 6 months follow-up will be the score on the YFHS-WHO+ questionnaire, a recently validated tool which young people aged 15 to 24 years complete following a family medicine consultation.
The results of this trial will provide much awaited evidence about the development of youth-friendly primary care services and inform their further development both in Bosnia &amp; Herzegovina and worldwide.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>1. Haller DM, Meynard A, Pejic D, et al. YFHS-WHO+ Questionnaire: validation of a measure of youth-friendly primary care services. J Adolesc Health 2012;51(5):422-30</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Comite departemental d'ethique de medecine interne et medecine communautaire, HUG</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Rue Gabrielle-Perret-Gentil 4
1211 GENEVE 14</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/10/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>protocole 09-199</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/08/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Switzerland</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dagmar M Haller</name>
      <address>Primary Care Unit, Geneva University
9 avenue de Champel, 1211 GENEVE</address>
      <phone>+41 22 372 96 79</phone>
      <fax>+41 22 372 96 00</fax>
      <email>dagmar.haller-hester@hcuge.ch</email>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dagmar M Haller</name>
      <address>Primary Care Unit, Geneva University
9 avenue de Champel, 1211 GENEVE</address>
      <phone>+41 22 372 96 79</phone>
      <fax>+41 22 372 96 00</fax>
      <email>dagmar.haller-hester@hcuge.ch</email>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dagmar M Haller</name>
      <address>Primary Care Unit, Geneva University
9 avenue de Champel, 1211 GENEVE</address>
      <phone>+41 22 372 96 79</phone>
      <fax>+41 22 372 96 00</fax>
      <email>dagmar.haller-hester@hcuge.ch</email>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dagmar M Haller</name>
      <address>Primary Care Unit, Geneva University
9 avenue de Champel, 1211 GENEVE  </address>
      <phone>+41 22 372 96 79</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dagmar.haller-hester@hcuge.ch</email>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>