<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366034">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/03/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/04/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000355673</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Investigating the effect of Rasagiline on freezing of gait in Parkinsons disease using accelerometry and functional MRI.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Can Rasagiline alleviate symptoms of freezing of gait in patients with Parkinson's disease?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Freezing of gait in Parkinson's disease </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Parkinson's disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study is aimed to determine whether Rasagiline reduces the frequency and severity of freezing of gait (FOG) in Parkinsons disease (PD). PD patients suffering from FOG will be randomized to either Rasagiline, 1mg once a day, orally ingested, or an oral placebo capsule for 12 consecutive weeks. After the 12 week intervention, the patients' gait variables will be evaluated and compared to their gait variables prior the treatment. To monitor adherence to treatment, participants must return their left over drug tablets at their last visit to enable pill count. </interventions>
    <comparator>Patients in the control group will receive oral placebos (capsules identical to those with medication in the intervention groups, containing glucose and lactose), once daily for 12 consecutive weeks.
All patients will continue their usual treatment. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blinded assessment of time spend frozen during the Timed Up and Go assessment analyzed using accelerometry and video recordings at the end of the study compared to prior to treatment and to placebo. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed within the final 2 weeks of the treatment period and compared to the assessment prior to the investigation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in the BOLD response on functional MRI at the end of the study compared to prior to treatment and to placebo.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed within the final 2 weeks of the treatment period and compared to the assessment prior to the investigation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in the performance on the Trail Making Test part A and B; clinician-administered tests of processing speed and flexible thinking</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed within the final 2 weeks of the treatment period and compared to the assessment prior to the investigation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients diagnosed with PD according to the United Kingdom Brain Bank clinical criteria and confirmed by a trained neurologist.
Age over 18
Mini-Mental State Examination&gt;/=24	
Screening questionnaire criteria (FOG-Q) with a positive score on item 3.
FOG determined by the TUG prior to randomisation.
Stable medications for 1 month prior to randomisation.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Significant psychiatric disorder or cognitive impairment (MMSE&lt; 24) 
Current use of Rasagiline or medications that should be avoided with the concurrent use of Rasagiline, unless washout of more than four weeks.
Galactose intolerance, LAPP lactase deficiency or glucose-galactose malabsorption.
Any significant liver, kidney or autoimmune disease. 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be approached via telephone based on previous medical and neuropsychological assessments at the PD Research Clinic to see if they are interested in taking part in the trial. Other participants may approach the clinic based on advertisement of the trial. Participants will then be sent out detailed information regarding the project in addition to consent forms. Participants will be allocated to groups using a blocked randomisation method conducted by a member of the clinical research team who is not in any way involved in the recruitment, assessment or training in the study.
After baseline assessments, participants will receive the tablets (either Rasagiline or placebo) prepared by a person who is not involved in the assessment or training in the study.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomized at the time of the baseline assessment using a simple randomization table created by computer software and allocated by a blinded researcher not involved in trial recruitment, data gathering, assessments or training. Randomization will occur in 1:1 ratio in random blocks. Patients will be allocated a unique ID code in sequential, ascending chronological order.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A mixed model design will be used. The trial will be analysed on an intention-to-treat basis (Placebo or 1mg Rasagiline). Drug randomisation and time will be the fixed factors. Event rates from the first week prior treatment and week 12 after treatment will be used in the mixed model analysis of variance to help characterise individual patients variability (individual patients will be random factors). For the primary test of efficacy in the model we will test whether Rasagiline causes a reduction in time spend frozen than placebo over the last 12 weeks of the treatment period. Twenty patients will be randomised in each strata to have sufficient completers in this efficacy trial assuming a dropout rate of 10% to detect a reduction in the average amount spend frozen of 30%. With 18 completers in each strata, we will have 90% power with alpha set at 5% to detect this 30% relative improvement.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>A/Prof Simon Lewis</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Brain &amp; Mind Research Institute,
100 Mallett Street,
Camperdown, Sydney, 
New South Wales, 2050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Lundbeck Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1 Innovation Road 
North Ryde, Sydney,
New South Wales, 2113 

</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>We will evaluate whether Rasagiline is an effective treatment to alleviate symptoms of freezing of gait (FOG) in Parkinsons disease. 40 patients with FOG will be randomised to either Rasagiline or placebo arms. Treatment response will be assessed by video recordings and accelerometry of specific walking tasks (Timed up and Go test), taken before and after the intervention. In addition, functional brain imaging whilst patients perform a validated virtual reality gait paradigm will be used to determine the brain activation patterns associated with improvements in FOG. The use of brain imaging will also allow us to see why patients might have differential responses to therapy. Identifying the nature of these relationships will hopefully advance our understanding of freezing.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Chen, J. J. &amp; Ly, A-V. Rasagiline: A second-generation monoamine oxidase type B-inhibitor for the treatment of Parkinson's disease. Am J Health-Syst Pharm. 2006; 63: 915-928.

Parkinson Study Group. A controlled trial of rasagiline in early Parkinson disease: the TEMPO Study. Arch Neurol. 2002; 59:1937-43.

Parkinson Study Group. A controlled, randomized, delayed-start study of rasagiline in early Parkinson disease. Arch
Neurol. 2004; 61:561-6.

Rascol O, Brooks DJ, Melamed E et al. Rasagiline as an adjunct to levodopa in patients with Parkinsons disease and
motor fluctuations (LARGO, Lasting effect in Adjunct therapy with Rasagiline Given Once daily, study): a randomised, double-blind, parallel-group trial. Lancet. 2005; 365:947-54.

Parkinson Study Group. A randomized placebo-controlled trial of rasagiline in levodopa-treated patients with Parkinson disease and motor fluctuations. The PRESTO Study. Arch Neurol. 2005; 62:241-8.

Lewis, S. J. G. &amp; Barker, R. A. A pathophysiological model of freezing of gait in Parkinson's disease. Parkinsonism Rel Disord. 2009; 15(5): 333-8

Shine, J. M., Matar, E., Ward, P. B., et al. Exploring the cortical and subcortical functional magnetic resonance imaging changes associated with freezing in Parkinsons disease. Brain. 2013; 136(4): 1204-1215

</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee, University of Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 6 
Jane Foss Russell Building G02
University of Sydney, 
New South Wales, 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>2013/1030</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Simon Lewis</name>
      <address>Brain &amp; Mind Research Institute
100 Mallett Street, 
Camperdown, Sydney, 
New South Wales, 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 0702</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>simonl@med.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Simon Lewis </name>
      <address>Brain &amp; Mind Research Institute
100 Mallett Street, 
Camperdown, Sydney, 
New South Wales, 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 0702</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>simonl@med.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Simon Lewis </name>
      <address>Brain &amp; Mind Research Institute
100 Mallett Street, 
Camperdown, Sydney, 
New South Wales, 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 0702</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>simonl@med.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>