<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367446">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/08/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/09/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001011572</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Patient adherence to physiotherapy exercise programs: effect of a web-based exercise programming system compared to usual physiotherapy exercise delivery. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of a web-based exercise programming system on exercise adherence levels compared to usual exercise delivery in people receiving physiotherapy for a musculoskeletal condition</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1164-1937 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>PANTHER study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Neck pain </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Trunk pain </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Back pain </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Upper limb pain </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Lower limb pain </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Sports Injuries</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Osteoarthritis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Rheumatoid Arthritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A 3-week intervention of usual physiotherapy treatment with Physitrack: individualised care according to the participant's presenting diagnosis including an exercise program delivered using the web-based exercise programming system (Physitrack). 

The Physitrack group receives their exercise program through the physitrack web based programming system. 

Physitrack is a web based programming system with an extensive library of videos of a range of exercises. The treating physiotherapist determines the appropriate exercises for each of their patients, including the number of repetitions and sets, frequency, duration and exercise progression. The patients can then access their exercise program through the web page or via an App. It can be updated accordingly by the physiotherapist. 

The patients physiotherapist will be able to monitor their adherence to the exercises as the patient can interact with the app or online, and their exercise program and indicate how many repetitions they did of the exercise. Plus the patient can also view their adherence online and via the app.</interventions>
    <comparator>A 3-week intervention of usual physiotherapy treatment: individualised care according to the participant's presenting diagnosis including an exercise program delivered according to usual non web-based methods of the treating physiotherapist. For example, this could take the form of individualised hand written instructions, semi-structured/individualised typed handouts, or standardised/general handouts.

The patients physiotherapist will monitor their adherence as per their usual practice. This will depend upon the physiotherapist.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence level to an exercise program. Self-reported adherence level to the prescribed exercise program in the previous 3 week period; 11-point numeric rating scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient satisfaction with the delivery of the exercise program - 11-point numeric rating scale </outcome>
      <timepoint>3 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient-perceived confidence to perform exercises - 11-point numeric rating scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 weeks </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Newly presenting patient

Aged 18 years and over

Any musculoskeletal condition (e.g. back and neck pain, osteoarthritis, inflammatory arthritis such as rheumatoid, sports injuries, other injuries) that the treating physiotherapist (on initial assessment) expects to require at least a 3-week exercise program as part of the physiotherapy treatment

Current email address and access to a computer, tablet device or smart phone

Adequate level of written and spoken English to be able to complete online surveys and access a website written in English
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>On the waiting list, planning, or likely to require (in the opinion of the treating physiotherapist) surgery in the next 3 weeks</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All patients over 18 years of age with a musculoskeletal condition attending an initial session with a participating physiotherapist will be asked to complete a screening survey in reception before they are seen by the treating therapist. Eligible consenting participants will complete baseline measures and following will be randomised into the study at the initial consult by the treating physiotherapist using the National Health and Medical Research Council’s Clinical Trials Centre Randomisation interactive voice response system. Allocation concealment will be obtained using this. The schedule will be prepared using minimisation stratified for physiotherapist and the affected body region to be treated (upper limb, lower limb, and spine).</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation schedule will be prepared by the NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre. Randomisation will be by minimisation. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>All potential participants will be informed that their physiotherapist is participating in a study that will compare different ways of delivering exercise programs to determine which is better. They will not be specifically informed about the nature of the web-based program and thus will remain blinded to the different treatment arms of the study as well as the specific hypothesis of the study. </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Measured at 3 weeks post-intervention. Given the number of factors that affect adherence, and that Physitrack will only target some of these factors, we expect that Physitrack will have a small effect on patient adherence. Thus, to detect an effect size of 0.35 with 80% power and a significance level of 0.05, and controlling for stratifying variables of physiotherapist and body region we require 129 patients per arm (258 in total). To allow for 15% attrition, 152 per arm (304) in total will be recruited. 

Data will be analysed in a blinded manner with p values less that 0.05 considered significant. Demographic characteristics will be inspected to assess comparability of treatment groups. These variables will also be examined for those participants who withdraw from the study and those who remain. 
Descriptive statistics will be presented for each group as means or medians (standard deviation, inter-quartile ranges). Continuous outcomes will be compared between the two groups using between group analysis of variance (ANOVA) controlling for stratifying variables of physiotherapist and body region with significant level set at 0.05. Proportional odds models will compare improvement between groups based on perceived ratings of change. Model diagnostic checks will utilise residual plots. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/09/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>15/10/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>26/05/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>304</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>305</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>4/08/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Grattan Street,
Parkville
Victoria 3010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Physitrack Limited</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>100 Church Street 
Brighton, BN1 1UJ 
United Kingdom</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United Kingdom</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council
Program Grant 631717</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Exercise is an integral component of the conservative management of most musculoskeletal conditions. However, adherence to exercises is often low and this impacts on treatment effectiveness. The aim of this randomised controlled trial is to evaluate whether the addition of a web-based system, Physitrack, to usual physiotherapy treatment improves patient adherence levels to exercises compared to the usual non web-based methods physiotherapists use to deliver exercise programs to people with musculoskeletal conditions. Secondary aims are to evaluate whether Physitrack improves patient satisfaction with the delivery of an exercise program and whether patient confidence changes with Physitrack. 

The primary hypothesis is: The level of patient-reported adherence to a prescribed exercise program will be greater in the group receiving Physitrack in addition to usual physiotherapy treatment (Physitrack group) than in the group receiving non web-based usual physiotherapy treatment alone (Usual care group) after 3 weeks. 

Secondary hypotheses are: i) The level of patient satisfaction with the delivery of the prescribed exercise program will be greater in the Physitrack group than in the group receiving non web-based usual care after 3 weeks; and ii) The level of patient confidence with exercises will be greater in the Physitrack group than in the group receiving non web-based usual care after 3 weeks.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Melbourne Human Research Ethics Commitee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Melbourne Research
The University of Melbourne
Level 5 Alan Gilbert Building
241-255 Grattan Street,
Parkville
VIC 3010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/09/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1442773.1</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Kim Bennell</name>
      <address>Centre for Health, Exercise and Sports Medicine 
Department of Physiotherapy 
University of Melbourne 
Alan Gilbert Building 
161 Barry Street
Parkville
VIC 3010</address>
      <phone>+ 61 3 83444135</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.bennell@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Charlotte Marshall </name>
      <address>Centre for Health, Exercise and Sports Medicine 
Department of Physiotherapy 
University of Melbourne 
Alan Gilbert Building 
161 Barry Street
Parkville
VIC 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 83440485</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c.marshall@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Kim Bennell</name>
      <address>Centre for Health, Exercise and Sports Medicine 
Department of Physiotherapy 
University of Melbourne 
Alan Gilbert Building 
161 Barry Street
Parkville
VIC 3010</address>
      <phone>+ 61 3 83444135</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.bennell@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Charlotte Marshall</name>
      <address>Centre for Health, Exercise and Sports Medicine 
Department of Physiotherapy 
University of Melbourne 
Alan Gilbert Building 
161 Barry Street
Parkville
VIC 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 83440485</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c.marshall@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>