<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365485">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/12/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/01/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000065695</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Adaptation to resistance and endurance training with antioxidant supplementation</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Does vitamin C and E supplementation alter cellular and physiological adaptation to endurance training and strength training in healthy, young and elderly participants? A double-blind randomized controlled trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1151-4959 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>SARA</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Vitamin C and E supplementation in healthy, young (18-45 yr) and elderly (&gt;60 yr) participants</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Strength training in young and elderly (&gt;60 yr) participants</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Endurance training in Young (18-45 yr) participants</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Supplements (pills) are administrated orally. All participants take 4 x 250 mg vitamin C and 58,5 mg vitamin E daily for 10-12 weeks. The participants get supplements for 2 weeks at the time, and the participants are to return the empty pill bottles when getting new supplies. The participants confirm consumption of supplements in a diary regularly controlled by the investigators.

The study comprises 3 experiments with similar vitamin/placebo supplementation:
Young participants (18-45 yrs.) train either endurance or strength training; two different experiments. Volunteers are recruited separately to each experiment. The participants are in each experiment allocated, randomly to the receive C and E vitamin or placebo supplements.  
The endurance training combined with C and E vitamin/placebo supplementation intervention lasted for 11 weeks. The strength training combined with C and E vitamin/placebo supplementation intervention lasted for 10 weeks. 

The third experiment is conducted with elderly volunteers (&gt;60 yrs.), and they trained strength and consumed with C and E vitamin/placebo supplementation for 12 weeks.

Supplements (pills) are administrated orally. The participants get supplements for 2 weeks at the time, and the participants are to return the empty pill bottles when getting new supplies. The participants confirm consumption of supplements in a diary regularly controlled by the investigators.
 
The training programs:
The endurance training program (only young participants): 3-4 sessions per week (primarily running), divided into high intensity interval sessions (4-6x4-6 minutes; &gt;90% of maximal heart rate (HRmax)) and steady state continuous sessions (30-60 minutes; 70-90% of HRmax). The participants have the opportunity to be supervised (by an exercise physiologist) during training, but can also train unsupervised. Supervised training is organized as small groups (3-5 participants). Introduction sessions in use of heart rate monitor (Polar RS400/800CX) and a scale of perceived exertion (Borgs scale) are given to all participants, so that the training intensity can be controlled.

The strength training program#1: Young participants follow a traditional strength training program with four sessions per week. During the first six weeks the loads are 3 x 9-11 RM, whereas in the four lasts weeks the loads are 3-4 x 6-8 RM. The inter-set rest periods are 1-1.5 min. Exercises for all the major muscle groups are included in a split routine: two upper body and two lower body sessions per week. The exercise sessions last for 40-70 min. The young, strength training experienced participants, have the opportunity to be supervised during training (experienced strength coaches), but can also train unsupervised. Introduction sessions in order to learn the exercises are conducted before the intervention. 

The strength training program#2: Elderly participants follow a 3 full-body sessions per week, emphasizing free weight exercises where all the major muscle groups are included. Two of the sessions each week are moderate (8-10 rep, with 1 min rest between sets), and one varied between heavy (3-5 rep, with 2 min rest between sets) and light (13-15 rep, with 45 seconds rest between sets) every second week. The exercise sessions last for 30-60 min. The elderly participants are supervised during all sessions by experienced strength coaches.
</interventions>
    <comparator>The vitamin C and E and placebo pills were produced under Good Manufacturing Practice (GMP) requirements at Petefa AB (Vastra Frolunda, Sweden). Each vitamin pill contained 250 mg of ascorbic acid and 58.5 mg DL-alpha-tocopherol acetate (all-rac-alpha- tocopheryl acetate); in addition to cellulose, di/tri-calsium phosphate and magnesium stearate. Similar appearing placebo pills contained the same ingredients, except the vitamins, were produced by the same manufacturer. 

The placebo administration is identical to the C+E vitamin administration. The placebo groups follow the same training programs as the vitamin C and E groups.
</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>For the participants that follow the endurance training program: Maximal oxygen uptake during running (direct measurements of oxygen in the in and out breathe: mixing chamber; Jaeger Oxycon Pro, Hoechberg, Germany; treadmill: Woodway ELG 90/200 Sport, Weil am Rhein, Germany)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>2-4 days after the 11-weeks intervention period</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>For the participants that follow the strength training program: Lean mass (measured by DXA; Hologic Discovery, Waltham, MA, USA)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>2-4 days after the 10-12-weeks intervention periods</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>For the participants that follow the endurance training program: Mitochondrial proteins (measured in muscle biopsies by western blotting) 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>2-4 days after the 11-weeks intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>For the participants that follow the strength training program: Maximal strength (1 repetition maximum)</outcome>
      <timepoint>2-4 days after the 10-12-weeks intervention periods</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy individuals with no injuries that inhibit them from following the training programs.
Young participants: 18-45 years.
Elderly participants: &gt;60 years.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>90</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Musculoskeletal injuries and cardiovascular diseases    </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All volunteers undergo a medical screening and pre-tests before randomization. 

Allocation involved contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who was "off-site" or at central administration site
</concealment>
    <sequence>The volunteers were stratified on gender and the randomization was conducted by applying the Graphpads Random number generator (http://graphpad.com/quickcalcs/randomN1.cfm)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Data will be checked for normalization. A two-tailed, unpaired T-test will be used to test for statistical differences in the changes between vitamin C and E supplementation and placebo. Alternatively the Mann-Whitney test will be applied.

For the endurance experiment: If we expect a standard deviation (SD) of 5% we will have 80% power to detect a true mean group differences of approx. 4% with 25 subjects in each group (alpha: 0.05; two-tailed; StatMate, Graphpad software). 

For the strength experiment: With an expected gain of 1.5 kg in lean mass and a standard deviation of 0.7. Sixteen volunteers in each group would give 80% power to detect a difference of approximately 0.7 kg. (alpha: 0.05; two-tailed; StatMate, Graphpad software).</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>26/07/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>20/09/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>10/09/2012</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>10/09/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>140</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Norway</country>
      <state>Oslo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Norway</country>
      <state>Lillehammer</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Norway</country>
      <state>Ostfold</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Norway</country>
      <state>Kristiansand</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Norwegian School of Sport Sciences</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Norwegian School of Sport Sciences
PB. 4014 Ulleval stadion
0806 Oslo, Norway</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Norway</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Norwegian School of Sport Sciences
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PB. 4014 Ulleval stadion 0806 Oslo, Norway</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Norway</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Agder
</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University of Agder
PB: 422, 4604 Kristiansand, Norway</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Norway</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In this study we explore how intake of antioxidants affects the adaptation to exercise, both endurance training and resistance training. Theoretically, antioxidant supplementation could both facilitate and inhibit cellular adaptations to exercise, because there seems to be optimal level oxidative stress  hence, both high and low levels may be unfavorable.

We hypothesize that vitamin C and E (1000 mg and 235 mg per day, respectively) will shut down some of the redox-sensitive signaling pathways associated with adaptation to training. The supplement will therefore inhibit the improvement in maximal oxygen uptake after endurance training and inhibit muscle growth after strength training in young participants.

In elder participants (&gt;60 years), who have increased oxidative stress levels in their muscle cells, we hypothesize that vitamin C and E (1000 mg and 235 mg per day, respectively) will augment the adaptation to strength training.


</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Regional Committees for Medical and Health Research Ethics</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PB: 1130, Blindern, 0318 Oslo</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/06/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Norway</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Goran Paulsen</name>
      <address>Norwegian School of Sport Sciences
PB: 4014 Ulleval stadion
0806 Oslo, Norway</address>
      <phone>+4793429420</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>goran.paulsen@nih.no</email>
      <country>Norway</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Goran Paulsen</name>
      <address>Norwegian School of Sport Sciences
PB: 4014 Ulleval stadion
0806 Oslo, Norway</address>
      <phone>+4793429420</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>goran.paulsen@nih.no</email>
      <country>Norway</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Truls Raastad</name>
      <address>Norwegian School of Sport Sciences
PB: 4014 Ulleval stadion
0806 Oslo, Norway</address>
      <phone>+4791368896</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>goran.paulsen@nih.no</email>
      <country>Norway</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Goran Paulsen</name>
      <address>Norwegian School of Sport Sciences
PB: 4014 Ulleval stadion
0806 Oslo, Norway</address>
      <phone>+4793429420</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>goran.paulsen@nih.no</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>