<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371642">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/10/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/10/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001453471p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Funded pharmacy vaccination of pregnant women: uptake and views and experiences</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Funded pharmacist-delivered pertussis and influenza vaccination of pregnant women. The effect on vaccine uptake and views and experiences of women and health professionals</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1188-6022</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Vaccination</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Pertussis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Influenza</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Pregnancy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Antenatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is to fund influenza vaccine and pertussis vaccine through community pharmacies in one specific area of New Zealand. 
Drugs and dose: Combined diphtheria-tetanus-acellular pertussis vaccine (funded for a single delivery between week 28 and week 38 of pregnancy) and influenza vaccine (funded for a single delivery at any stage of pregnancy), both vaccines will be delivered by intra-muscular injection. The intervention period will be 12-24 months depending on study funding.
Any pregnant woman in the intervention area will be able to present to a pharmacy (or traditional areas ie general practice or hospitals) for the funded vaccinations. </interventions>
    <comparator>Selected comparable areas in New Zealand will continue with the current situation (funding in general practice and hospitals but not pharmacy) to provide the control. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of influenza vaccinations in pregnant women both overall and by delivery location (general practice, hospital, pharmacy). Measured through vaccination data collected in National Immunisation Record and claims data</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months or 24 months after starting vaccination delivery depending on funding</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of pertussis vaccinations in pregnant women both overall and by delivery location (general practice, hospital, pharmacy). Measured through vaccination data collected in National Immunisation Record and claims data</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months or 24 months after starting vaccination delivery depending on funding</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of influenza vaccinations in pregnant women who are of Maori ethnicity, and/or in high deprivation areas, both overall and by delivery location. Measured through vaccination data collected in National Immunisation Record and claims data</outcome>
      <timepoint>12-24 months after starting funding these vaccinations in pharmacy, depending on funding</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of pertussis vaccinations (Tdap) in pregnant women who are of Maori ethnicity, and/or in high deprivation areas, both overall and by delivery location. Measured through vaccination data collected in National Immunisation Record and claims data</outcome>
      <timepoint>12-24 months after start of intervention depending on funding</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To ascertain the views and experiences of women eligible for the vaccination during pregnancy (some who used the intervention and some who did not) regarding the intervention using semi-structured qualitative interviews. Note: these women will be invited to participate in the study and only with informed consent will the interview occur. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Approximately 12 months after start of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To ascertain the views and experiences of health professionals regarding the intervention using semi-structured qualitative interviews</outcome>
      <timepoint>Approximately 12 months after the study starts</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Women who were pregnant at the time of the intervention, are NZ residents, were eligible for the vaccinations during the study period, and have a surviving fetus beyond 27 weeks.
Note: women will not be enrolled as such for the primary outcome, and data will only be used for women who had the vaccinations and had a surviving fetus beyond 27 weeks. Women will be eligible for the vaccinations if pregnant but if they do not have a surviving fetus beyond 27 weeks will not be included. 
For the secondary qualitative research, women will be invited to participate in an interview and only with informed consent will the interview progress. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Women who deliver before 27 weeks, or who do not deliver a live baby. Women who are not eligible for funded vaccines (e.g. not NZ residents).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>N/A</concealment>
    <sequence>N/A</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Women living in the intervention group will have the option of using the pharmacy for free delivery of influenza vaccination or Tdap vaccination, in addition to usual sources of free vaccination. 
Women living outside of the intervention area will not have the option of using the pharmacy for free delivery of influenza or Tdap vaccinations, but only usual sources of free vaccination.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>10000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Natalie Gauld</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Dept of General Practice and Primary Health Care
Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences
Tamaki Campus
The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Waikato District Health Board</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Population Health
Waikato District Health Board
Hugh Monckton Trust Building  L5 
Cnr. Rostrevor &amp; Harwood Streets 
Private Bag 3200 
Hamilton 3240
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>A/P Cameron Grant</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Dept of Paediatrics
The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Helen Petousis Harris</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Immunisation Advisory Centre
Dept of General Practice and Primary Health care
Tamaki Campus
The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Low uptake of influenza vaccine and pertussis vaccine in pregnancy in New Zealand needs to be addressed. The hypothesis we seek to test is that providing funded pertussis and influenza vaccinations in pregnancy through community pharmacy will increase uptake in pregnant women, including those living in areas of higher household deprivation, and in women of Maori ethnicity. 
In one area of NZ (intervention area) these vaccinations will be funded through community pharmacies as well as the traditional areas (general practice and hospitals). In geographically comparable areas (controls) funding remains standard (general practice and hospital). 
The study will measure uptake overall and by location of vaccine delivery in women, and a further analysis will examine uptake in Maori and high deprivation populations,</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern B</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/10/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Natalie Gauld</name>
      <address>Department of General Practice and Primary Health CAre
Tamaki Campus
The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+6421336685</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>n.gauld@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Natalie Gauld</name>
      <address>Department of General Practice and Primary Health CAre
Tamaki Campus
The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+6421336685</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>n.gauld@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Natalie Gauld</name>
      <address>Department of General Practice and Primary Health CAre
Tamaki Campus
The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+6421336685</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>n.gauld@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>