<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369860">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/04/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/05/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000670471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of Functional Electrical Stimulation-cycling Plus Progressive Resistance Training on Muscle Strength After Incomplete Spinal Cord Injury: A Randomized Controlled Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of Functional Electrical Stimulation-cycling Plus Progressive Resistance Training on Muscle Strength After Incomplete Spinal Cord Injury: A Randomized Controlled Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1177-9811</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Spinal Cord Injury</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention group will receive 12 weeks Functional Electrical Stimulation (FES)-cycling (twice a week) plus progressive resistance training (once a week) which will be conducted by physiotherapist at research lab, University Malaya Medical Center, Kuala Lumpur. Each session for FES-cycling will be in a small group in 1 hour in duration which include electrodes to the quadriceps, hamstring, tibialis anterior and gastrocnemius while using Motomed cycling model VIVA 2 Parkinson which synchronize with Hasomed Rehamove 2 a FES machine during gait cycling. The parameters will be set with 300 microsecond pulse width, 30 Hz frequency, 35 rpm speed and 70-140 mA intensity. The participant will be register for attendance every training session.

The progressive resistance training involve electrodes on quadriceps, hamstring, tibialis anterior and gastrocnemius while using biodex isokinetic machine model no 850-230 which synchronize with Rehastim a portable FES. The resistance training on biodex machine will be based on manufacturer program which consist of 3-4 sets of resistance training with 10 repetitions at 50% RM and 5-10 second hold each repetition for 30 minutes.  The number of sets will be progress at 70% RM at 6 weeks then to 100% RM at 10 weeks as determined by physiotherapist.
</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will receive 12 weeks FES-cycling 3 times per week. Each session for FES-cycling will be 1 hour in duration which include electrodes to the quadriceps, hamstring, tibialis anterior and gastrocnemius while using Motomed cycling model VIVA 2 Parkinson which synchronize with Hasomed Rehamove 2 a FES machine during gait cycling. The parameters will be set with 300 microsecond pulse width, 30 Hz frequency, 35 rpm speed and 70-140 mA intensity.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>voluntary quadriceps, hamstring, tibialis anterior and gastrocnemius strength  (Nm) by using biodex isokinetic machine. This is a composite primary outcome.</outcome>
      <timepoint>before training, post 6 weeks training and post 12 weeks training</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximum voluntary contraction of quadriceps, hamstring, tibialis anterior and gastrocnemius by using EMG</outcome>
      <timepoint>before training, post 6 weeks training and post 12 weeks training</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>limb girth of the thigh (5 cm, 10 cm and 15 cm from based of patella) and calf muscle by using measurement tape.</outcome>
      <timepoint>before training, post 6 weeks training and post 12 weeks training</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>heart rate by using portable pulse oximetry</outcome>
      <timepoint>before training, post 6 weeks training and post 12 weeks training</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Oxygen saturation uptake by using portable SPO2 machine</outcome>
      <timepoint>before training, post 6 weeks training and post 12 weeks training</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>over six month incomplete SCI. ASIA C and D only
Level of injury C4-T12
Have at least 90 degree knee range of motion
Able to response to FES
Able to follow command
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Had recent history of trauma to the lower limb
Severe of infected skin pressure sore on weight-bearing skin areas
Uncontrolled spasticity or pain
History of cardiovascular problem
History of cardiorespiratory problem
Metal implants in femur or tibia bone</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The rehabilitation medicine physician will screen all participants for inclusion and exclusion criteria. Then they will be randomly picked by uninvolved person from the list name based on the sample size needed. </concealment>
    <sequence>a simple random sampling will be used to allocate participants into intervention group and control group using simple coin toss by a person uninvolved with the study.  </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The G-Power 3 software will be used to determine the sample size for this study. The effect size is 0.25. Based on the results an estimated sample of 28 participants could provide 80% power with  risk of type 1 error of 0.05.

The descriptive analysis (mean and standard deviation) of demographic data and maximum voluntary contraction will be recorded. Meanwhile means differences between the baseline within group factor of pre-exercise, 6 weeks and 12 weeks will be analyzed using ANOVA repeated measures. Post-hoc Bonferroni comparison will be used to analyze the baseline that is most significant.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/04/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/08/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>28</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <state>kuala lumpur</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>High Impact Research Grant, University Malaya, Kuala Lumpur</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department Biomedical Engineering, 
Faculty Of Engineering, 
University Malaya,
Jalan University
50603, Kuala Lumpur,
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Malaysia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>High Impact Research Grant, University Malaya, Kuala Lumpur</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department Biomedical Engineering,
Faculty Of Engineering,
University Malaya,
Jalan University,
50603, Kuala Lumpur

</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Malaysia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A spinal cord injury (SCI) is a chronic health condition in which the individual loses certain functions, no longer being able to exercise them in the same way as before the injury (Vall, Mauricio, Costa, Pereira, &amp; Friesen, 2011). SCI can induce prolonged inactivity and subsequent secondary complications such as muscle atrophy, pressure ulcers, and demineralization of the lower limb bones (Yoshida et al., 2013). Patients who survive with SCI often left with considerable residual disability that require longterm care for hospitalization, rehablitation and home care services (Wyndaele &amp; Wyndaele, 2006).
In United states, the incidence of SCI is approximately 40 cases per million population per year. The average age at time of injury is 31.7 years, with teenagers and young adults having the greatest risk (Livecchi, 2011). However, in Malaysia among all survivors of SCI about 50% of the patients experienced severe SCI (ASIA A or B), mainly involving patients in the age group 16 to 45 and experiencing traumatic SCI (Ibrahim et al., 2013).
Musculoskeletal atrophy is a serious complication of SCI which contributes to the development of secondary impairements in spinal cord injured individuals. Although better medical care of persons with SCI has helped to progressively improve their health and life expectancy over the last six decades, gains in mobility and self-care skills have remained relatively stagnant because further improvements in these areas are dependent on advancements in basic science that may lead to reversal of the neurological loss (Ragnarsson, 2008). Thus, it is well accepted among healthcare professionals and now diplomats worldwide that regular physical activity is a cornerstone of physical and psychologic well-being. 
Since the 1960s, FES-induced muscle contractions have been widely used as a rehabilitation therapy or an exercise regimen for the paralyzed lower limbs of people with SCI. With FES, paralyzed legs can be artificially evoked to produce otherwise unattainable dynamic movements, such as cycling, rowing, knee extension, standing, and stepping (Davis, Hamzaid, &amp; Fornusek, 2008). On the basis of this observation, FES cycle ergometers have been designed and extensively tested and prescribed for persons with SCI based on established clinical benefits. It can be performed either as static muscle contractions and dynamic knee extension (Hettinga &amp; Andrews, 2008).
FES-LCE did improve muscular strength and endurance, increase exercise Performance, and improve cardiovarcular response (Thrasher, Ward, &amp; Fisher, 2013 ; Davis et al, 2008). However, the persistance of the result from the exercise training still unknown. Therefore, in this study the objective is to investigate the effects of FES-cycling ergometer plus progression resistance exercise on muscle strength and cardiovascular response among incomplete SCI patient.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University Malaya Medical Center Medical ethics committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>university Malaya Medical Centre,
jalan university,
59100, kuala lumpur</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/08/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1003.14(1)</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Malaysia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Nurhaida Rosley</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy
Faculty of Health Sciences
Universiti Teknologi MARA
42300, Puncak Alam
Selangor
</address>
      <phone>+60136220157</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nurhaida.rosley@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Haidzir Manaf</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy
Faculty of Health Sciences
Universiti Teknologi MARA
42300, Puncak Alam
Selangor
</address>
      <phone>+60126615246</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>haidzirmanaf@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Nazirah Hasnan</name>
      <address>Department of Rehabilitation Medicine,
Faculty of Medicine, 
University Malaya, 
50603, Kuala Lumpur</address>
      <phone>+6012-3286844</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nazirah@ummc.edu.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>