<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367974">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/02/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/03/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000215527</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effects of fructose intake on acute serum uric acid level and blood pressure</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of consuming foods and beverages containing fructose by healthy young adults on serum uric acid and blood pressure</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1167-2639</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hyperuricaemia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Blood pressure</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Hypertension</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is an acute dietary intervention study in which healthy adults will be randomised to one of four groups. Group 1 - apples; Group 2 - apple juice; Group 3 a commercially available sucrose sweetened beverage (fizzy drink); Group 4 - a fructose drink and a glucose drink. Two serves of food will act as a crossover. For Groups 1 to 3, participants will consume either one serve (one apple; one glass of apple juice; or one can of fizzy drink) or two serves of the respective foods. One serve (one apple, a 250ml glass of juice or a 355ml can of fizzy) are commonly consumed items although a double serve (two apples, two glasses of juice or a 600ml bottle of fizzy) are within the realms of normal consumption for some people. The fructose content of one serve of each of those test foods will be within the range 15-20 g. The order of consumption will be randomised with a two week washout between tests. For Group 4, participants will consume a fructose beverage on one occasion and a glucose beverage on the other, again in randomised order. These are the control foods. The amount of fructose and glucose will be matched to that of the double food serve. At baseline and for one hour after consumption blood samples will be taken for uric acid analysis and blood pressure will be taken at baseline and 70 minutes.  </interventions>
    <comparator>A fructose solution will be made using pure fructose and carbonated water. It will be matched for fructose content to the double serve of test foods. This will control for effects of other nutrients in the test foods. A second control will be a glucose beverage. Glucose does not have uric acid raising potential and this will be used to control for time effects on uric acid during the experiment. Glucose also has a minimal effect on blood pressure and heart rate, so this will be used to control for time effects when assessing the fructose test foods.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum uric acid concentrations using capillary blood obtained by a finger prick </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and 30 and 60 minutes following ingestion of the test food</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure will be assessed as the mean of three determinations using an automatic sphygmomanometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and seventy minutes following ingestion of the test food</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Heart rate will be assessed as the mean of three determinations using an automatic sphygmomanometer. The Omron sphygmomanometer displays pulse rate (beats per minute) after each blood pressure determination.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 70 minutes following ingestion of the test food</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood glucose will be assessed with a Hemocue blood glucose meter using capiliary blood obtained by finger-prick</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 30 and 60 minutes following ingestion of the test food</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Satiety will be assessed using 100mm visual analogue scales</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 30 and 60 minutes following ingestion of the test food</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>University students</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>People diagnosed with chronic disease including diabetes mellitus, cardiovascular disease, cancer, and diseases of the digestive system; and women who are pregnant. 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be allocated to a test food and to an order of
consumption (single or double the amount of food) using a computer generated random number list. The person who will determine if a subject is eligible for inclusion in the trial will be unaware, when this decision is made, to which group the subject will be allocated. Allocation will be concealed from the research personnel conducting the study up to the time of the start of the intervention.</concealment>
    <sequence>Block randomisation to balance males and females into each of the four intervention groups. Simple randomization for order of treatment. All randomization will be done using a randomisation table created by computer software</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>There will be four treatment groups in parallel (apples; fruit juice; sugary beverage; control). Within each of the four intervention groups, each participant will consume in a crossover design (with a two week washout), either a single serve or a double serve of the foods.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>A total of 20 participants per group would be required to detect a difference of 50 micromol/L in plasma uric acid with 80% power and a two-sided significance level of 0.05. This was determined using a mean of 340 micromol/L and a standard deviation of 80 micromol/L. A two-sided paired t-test will be used to compare baseline and final uric acid levels for each test. Twenty participants per group will be ample to detect a change in blood pressure of 3 mmHg over the course of the experiment. ANCOVA will be used to test for differences in the primary outcomes among the groups.  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>27/02/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>27/02/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>27/03/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Otago</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Otago</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Otago</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Gout, hyperuricemia and hypertension are prevalent in New Zealand. In animal experiments and human studies involving large intakes of free fructose, fructose has been linked to increasing serum uric acid concentrations and elevated blood pressure. More studies are required to test whether uric acid and blood pressure are raised acutely when more realistic fructose intakes contained in real foods are consumed. The objective of this study is to test whether consuming fructose from commonly consumed foods in realistic serving sizes has an affect on acute post-ingestion serum uric acid concentration and blood pressure. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Otago Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/11/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Bernard Venn</name>
      <address>University of Otago
Department of Human Nutrition
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</address>
      <phone>+6434795068</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bernard.venn@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Bernard Venn</name>
      <address>University of Otago
Department of Human Nutrition
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</address>
      <phone>+6434795068</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bernard.venn@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Bernard Venn</name>
      <address>University of Otago
Department of Human Nutrition
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</address>
      <phone>+6434795068</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bernard.venn@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Bernard Venn</name>
      <address>Department of Human Nutrition
PO Box 56
Dunedin</address>
      <phone>+6434795068</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bernard.venn@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>