<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371386">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/09/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001259437</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A study using non-expanded stem cells for the treatment of early osteoarthritis of the knee (focal chondral defects) in comparison to standard conservative management.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A proof-of-concept study on the safety and efficacy of autologous stromal vascular fraction and platelet rich plasma for the treatment of symptomatic focal chondral lesions of the knee in comparison to accepted conservative management.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1186-4118 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Focal chondral lesions of the knee</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study will look to assess the safety and response of focal chondral lesions of the knee  to  injection protocols of stromal vascular fraction (SVF) and platelet rich plasma (PRP) in comparison to accepted conservative mangement. Thirty two participants will be enrolled in the study and randomly separated into 2 study groups.

Group 1: [SVF (IA) + PRP (IA)] at Day 0 + PRP (IA) at Days 7, 14 &amp; 28
Group 2: accepted conservative management including: simple analgesics, weight loss education, regular exercises, biomechanical adjustment

Autologous non-expanded SVF from adipose (fat) will be used due to the ease of harvest (liposuction) and safety. On average 100 million cells are injected into the joint. Adipose tissue is removed by lipo-aspiration (about 60 minutes). The fat is processed on-site to isolate the cells (this process takes up to 40 mins). The suspension of stromal stem cells is injected into the knee joint under ultrasound guidance. The PRP (3ml) process involves separating out platelets with plasma from a small amount of blood taken, and takes about 15 mins.

The harvesting of adipose and the PRP processing will be performed on the same day as the injection of SVF and PRP, respectively.</interventions>
    <comparator>Comparator treatment: accepted conservative management including: simple analgesics, weight loss education, regular exercises, biomechanical adjustment. Conservative management will be by face to face meeting with the doctor on Days 0, 180 and 365.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and tolerability of autologous stromal vascular fraction (SVF) and platelet rich plasma (PRP) for the treatment of focal chondral lesions of the knee. Adverse Events will be graded by the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events v 4.0 (CTCAE) and coded according to MedDRA terminology. Loco regional Adverse Events will be monitored (e.g. knee swelling, infection). Systemic Adverse Events will monitored by. laboratory parameters including [blood tests: Complete Blood Count (CBC), Comprehensive Metabolic Panel (CMP), and pregnancy test for female patients], and vital signs (temperature, heart rate, blood pressure, respiration rate and weight),</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at Days 0, 7, 14, 28, 56, 180, 365.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The KOOS (Knee Injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score) questionnaire will assess the patients opinion about their knee and associated problems.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at Day 0,28, 56, 90, 180,365</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The AQoL (Australian Quality of Life) questionaire is a health-related multi-attribute utility quality of life instrument.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at Day 0,28, 56, 90, 180,365</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The SF-36 (Short Form Health) survey is used as a patient-reported survey of patient health.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at Day 0,28, 56, 90, 180,365</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rescue medication consumption (e.g. analgesics). This outcome is assessed by self reported changes in the daily use and dosage of an individuals medication, along with data linkage to patients medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at Day 0,28, 56, 90, 180,365</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>MRI findings (cartilage mapping) will be used to assess disease modification. Cartilage mapping of the knee will indicate if a patient has improved cartilage volume or not.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at Day 0, 180,365</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Focal chondral lesions of the knee (as evidenced by MRI scan) with symptomatic pain and less than or equal to 6 cm2 in size.
2. Greater than 6 months knee pain with the index side (left or right) predominately on one side
3. A KOOS pain score greater than or equal to 65
4. Adequate blood chemistry and hematopoietic, renal, cardiovascular, respiratory, immunological function</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Subjects who have received investigational agents within 4 weeks (or 5 half-lives) of SVF/placebo infusion.
2. Presence of clinically significant acute or unstable cardiovascular, cerebrovascular (stroke), renal, gastrointestinal, pulmonary, immunological (viral hepatitis, or cirrhosis), endocrine, or central nervous system disorders.
3. Subjects who have had active neoplastic disease in the previous 3 years.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerised sequence generation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The study safety results will be analysed by descriptive statistics, as rigorous inferential statistics will not be feasible due to the small treatment group sample size. The primary analysis for safety will report all subject adverse events.

All efficacy analyses will be performed using the Intention to Treat (ITT) population. The chosen sample size of 32 patients allows for 16 patients per treatment cohort which is sufficient to detect a difference between the comparison group and SVF (with PRP) group in the mean percentage change over time in KOOS scores of 20% with a standard deviation of 10% or difference of 10% with a much larger standard deviation of 20%.

The endpoints for the MRI will be to assess disease modification following cartilage mapping of the MRI scans. The reviewer will indicate whether a participant has improved cartilage volume and the degree or not, or that degeneration has slowed in comparison to the placebo control. No formal statistical tests will be undertaken.

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/11/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>32</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/11/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2298 - Georgetown</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Cell-Innovations Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 7342
Warringah Mall
Brookvale NSW 2100</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cell-Innovations Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 7342
Warringah Mall
Brookvale NSW 2100</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary objective of this study is to determine the safety and tolerability of autologous stromal vascular fraction (SVF) and PRP in comparison to standard conservative management of patients with focal chondral lesions of the knee.

Secondary objectives are intended to measure differences between standard treatment and SVF based therapies including improvement of pain and mobility, quality of life and MRI to assess disease modifying activity.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.cell-innovations.com.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Sydney Local Health District</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Kolling Bld, level 13
Royal North Shore Hospital
St leonards NSW 2065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/07/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/HAWKE/484</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/12/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>David Mathers</name>
      <address>Hunter Regenerative Medicine
71 Georgetown Rd
Georgetown NSW 2298</address>
      <phone>+61 (02) 49601933</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>davidmathers@tpg.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Wayne Thomas</name>
      <address>Cell-Innovations
PO Box 7342
WARRINGAH NSW 2100</address>
      <phone> +61 1300 738 025 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>trials@cell-innovations.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Wayne Thomas</name>
      <address>Cell-Innovations
PO Box 7342
WARRINGAH NSW 2100</address>
      <phone> +61 1300 738 025 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>wthomas@cell-innovations.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>