<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372094">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/02/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/02/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000273381p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluating the relationship between response to an olfactory stress test and level of cognitive decline in older adults. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluating the relationship between response to an olfactory stress test and level of cognitive decline in older adults.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>OST Study Phase 2</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>ALZHEIMER'S DISEASE</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cognitive Impairment, Cognitive decline</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Alzheimer's disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study is designed to determine the extent to which olfactory testing, performed conventionally, and also the change in olfaction following an intranasal anticholinergic challenge, is associated with cognitive decline. 
Study participants returning to Phase 2 of the study will be assessed for cognitive change now that 4 years has passed.
Participants will receive two mail out surveys used in Phase 1. 
Participants who are eligible will participate in two visits.
Visit 1 (duration 3-3.5 hours): Like Phase 1, participants will complete the Audio Recorded Cognitive Screen (ARCS), complete a series of questionnaires regarding medical history and cognition, and complete two smell tests. 
Smell Test 1: University of Pennsylvania Smell Identification Test (UPSIT). Participants are asked to identify odours from a scratch and sniff booklet.   Twenty items of the UPSIT will be administered prior to atropine being administered. After 45 minutes we will test with the remaining 20 items of the UPSIT. 
Smell Test 2 (following Smell Test 1): Sniffin sticks are used as a test of nasal chemosensory performance that is based on pen-like odour-dispensing devices.  Participants will be presented with 16 pens at an interval of 30 seconds. Each participant is provided with a sheet of paper which describes 16 lists with 4 items each. Participants have to identify the item that best describes the presented odour. Test repeated at 45 minute interval, following atropine administration.  Upon completion participants will be asked to complete a sleep diary for 1 week and wear an accelerometer during that period.

Visit 2 (within 7 days of visit 1, duration  1.5 hours): Participants will attend a clinic appointment for a Neuropsychological Test Battery (NTB). The NTB is comprised of the following tests: California Verbal Learning Test (CVLT), WMS IV Visual Reproduction Test, WAIS IV Block Design, Similarities and Digit Span, WAIS IV Symbol Search &amp; Coding, Colour Word Interference Task and the test of Premorbid Functioning.
 
The major implication and novelty of this study lies in the new technique for administering 1% atropine during Visit 1. . This involves using a soft narrow tube attached to a syringe that the study participant gently inserts into their left nostril until they feel the end touching the inside of their nose, which occurs as it reaches the olfactory cleft, where we wish to deposit atropine. The participant then squirts the syringe to deposit a measured dose (0.05 ml) of the atropine.
 </interventions>
    <comparator>In Phase 1, eligible participants completed a variety of assessments between 1/3/2013 - 20/11/2014. The Hunter New England Human Research Ethics committee granted ethical approval on 18/05/2012 reference number HNEHREC 12/04/18/5.05.  University of Newcastle  Research Office Reference number: G1100221
  
Assessments included: 
Postal Surveys - Informant Questionnaire, Functional Activities Questionnaire
Smell Tests conducted pre and post (UPSIT, Sniffin Sticks) 1% atropine administration 
Audio Recorded Cognitive Screen (ARCS) 
Medical Assessment 
Blood Tests
Physical Exercise Assessment via Accelerometers. 

At Phase 1
Diagnoses (normal/cognitive impairment, aetiological) was based on clinical assessment, ARCS performance (worse than 1.5 SD below norms defining abnormality for any cognitive domain), and history of functional impairment due to cognitive problems,  We applied DSM V and 2011 McKhann et al. criteria for AD, and NINDS-AIREN criteria for vascular dementia. Imaging evidence of vascular disease from MRIs was considered in assigning diagnoses.
</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive decline on the Audio Recorded Cognitive Screen (ARCS)

</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Visit 1 the Audio Recorded Cognitive Screen (ARCS) is administered as a single assessment prior to olfactory stress test. These results are compared to Phase 1 ARCS results. From the ARCS administered at Phase 1 and Phase 2 we will derive cognitive change scores.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>
Phase 2
The Neuropsychological Test Battery will be used to inform Phase 2 diagnosis of incident dementia.  Phase 2 will thus constitute a gold standard diagnostic appraisal and in this way we will also avoid concerns of circularity when we assess the predictive properties of ARCS measures at Phase 1 for incident dementia/AD at Phase 2.

Definition of incident dementia due to Alzheimer's disease will be based on McKhann et al. 2011 criteria  (Alzheimers &amp; Dementia 7 (2011) 263269).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Regular weekly consensus diagnostic conference, following Visit 2 Neuropsychological assessment. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in olfactory (smell) performance on the Olfactory Stress Test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Visit 1, the olfactory stress test comprised of the University of Pennsylvania Smell Identification Test (UPSIT) and the Olfactory Sniffin Sticks.  We will be using the two tests of Olfaction in this study. In both parts of the Olfactory Stress test, the UPSIT will be administered BEFORE the Sniffin Sticks. The smell performance of returning participants will be compared to Phase 1 results.  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diagnosis of Incident cognitive impairment will be made by consensus diagnostic conference. 

Neuropsychological Test Battery (NTB) will be used to inform Phase 2 diagnosis of incident cognitive impairment (blind to ARCS scores).  Phase 2 will thus constitute a gold standard diagnostic appraisal and in this way we will also avoid concerns of circularity when we assess the predictive properties of ARCS measures at Phase 1 for incident cognitive impairment at Phase 2. 

The diagnosis of Incident Cognitive Impairment will be based on the criteria outlined by Albert et al. (Alzheimers &amp; Dementia 7 (2011) 270279). 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Consensus diagnostic conference, following Visit 2 Neuropsychological assessment. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be drawn from the Hunter Community Study (HCS), an established cohort of 3500 older individuals (aged 55-85 years old) randomly selected from the electoral roll, and recruited between 2004 and 2008.  </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>*Does not have a minimum of grade 7 education
*Less than 65 years and older
*Inability to write. 
*Inadequate visual acuity (5/36 or worse)
*Recent clinical stroke (within the last 6 months).
*Past history of severe traumatic brain injury
*Past olfactory tumour 
*Active nasal/sinus disease 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Univariate and multivariate analyses will be conducted to assess the association of olfactory performance and change in olfactory performance with cognitive change, and incident dementia and incident cognitive impairment.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>20/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>280</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>22/12/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Calvary Mater Newcastle - Waratah</hospital>
    <hospital>John Hunter Hospital - New Lambton</hospital>
    <postcode>2298 - Waratah</postcode>
    <postcode>2305 - New Lambton</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr. Peter Schofield</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Hunter New England Local Health District Mental Health
Neuropsychiatry Services
5th Floor McAuley Centre
Calvary Mater Hospital Campus
Waratah, NSW 2298</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health &amp; Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor John Attia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Hunter Medical Research Institute
Level 3 - the Pod
1 Kookaburra Close
New Lambton Heights
NSW 2305</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Alzheimer's disease (AD) has a long preclinical phase as characteristic brain changes accumulate before obvious symptoms and signs appear. The availability of a simple test to detect AD during this stage would have considerable value. Current tests or 'biomarkers' under evaluation for early AD detection are expensive (PIB PET imaging), invasive  (CSF amyloid), or require a high level of skill and technology (MRI volumetric analyses). An inexpensive, low tech, minimally invasive, easily administered test for preclinical AD would therefore be especially valuable. We hypothesize that a small dose of an anticholinergic drug (atropine) given by 'nasal squirt' would reach the olfactory bulb (smell centre) and reduce -smell performance more in individuals with Alzheimers disease (AD), including those with early AD in whom poorer smell performance can also be expected, than in those without AD. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Locked Bag No 1
New Lambton NSW 2305</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Peter Schofield</name>
      <address>Hunter New England Local Health District Mental Health
Neuropsychiatry Service
PO BOX 833
Newcastle NSW 2300</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4033 5739</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4033 5606</fax>
      <email>Peter.Schofield@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Laura Miles</name>
      <address>Hunter New England Local Health District Mental Health
Neuropsychiatry Service
PO BOX 833
Newcastle, NSW 2300</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4033 5701</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4033 5606</fax>
      <email>Laura.Miles@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Laura Miles</name>
      <address>Hunter New England Local Health District Mental Health
Neuropsychiatry Service
PO BOX 833
Newcastle, NSW 2300</address>
      <phone>+61 02 4033 5701</phone>
      <fax>+61 02 4033 5606</fax>
      <email>Laura.Miles@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Laura Miles</name>
      <address>Hunter New England Local Health District Mental Health
Neuropsychiatry Service
PO BOX 833
Newcastle, NSW 2300</address>
      <phone>+61 02 4033 5701</phone>
      <fax>+61 02 4033 5606</fax>
      <email>Laura.Miles@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>