<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="1264">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/05/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/05/2006</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000187549</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An Open-Label Extension Trial of UT-15C SR in Subjects with
Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An Open-Label Extension Trial of Treprostinil Diethanolamine Sustained Release (UT-15C SR) in Subjects with Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension to assess the long-term safety of UT-15C SR in study subjects and the effect of continued therapy with UT-15C SR on exercise capacity after one year of treatment.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>TDE-PH-304</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension (PAH)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Hypertension</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a multi-center, open-label study for eligible patients who participated in Protocol TDE-PH-301 and TDE-PH-302. The estimated study duration for each subject is up to 36 months from the point of transition from protocol TDE-PH-301 or TDE-PH-302 to the end of the open-label study. Treprostinil Diethanolamine Sustained Release (UT-15C SR) will be provided as 1, 5, and 10 mg tablets and will be labeled and packaged for open-label
administration. 
Subjects who were randomized to UT-15C SR treatment group in the previous trial will begin open-label therapy at the same dose they were receiving at the final (Week 12/16) visit in the previous trial, and subsequent dose adjustments will be made based on symptoms of PAH and AEs.</interventions>
    <comparator>For subjects who were randomized to placebo in either protocol TDE-PH-301 or TDE-PH-302, treatment will be initiated at 1 mg twice daily (every 12 hours +/- 1 hour) with dose escalation of an additional 1 mg twice daily every 5 days if clinically indicated based upon adverse events and symptoms of PAH according to protocol-defined guidelines. </comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The study drug will be taken on a daily basis for 36 months on the open label study.  The outcome will be measured by assessing the patient's improvement (Clinical Laboratory Assessments, Adverse Event Assessment, and A 6-Minute Walk Test with Borg Dyspnea Score) over the 36 months</outcome>
      <timepoint>At each visit to the clinic every 3 months over the 36 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The study drug will be taken on a daily basis for 36 months on the open label study.  The outcome will be measured by assessing the tolerance for the study drug over the 36 months</outcome>
      <timepoint>At each visit to the clinic every 3 months over the 36 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the long-term safety of UT-15C SR in these subjects through assessment of adverse events and laboratory parameters. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At the visit 1 (three months after first dose of UT-15C SR; only for subjects randomized to placebo in previous study), visit 2 (six months after first dose of UT-15C SR), visit 3 (12 months after first dose of UT-15C SR), visit 4 (24 months after first dose of UT-15C SR), visit 5 (36 months after first dose of UT-15C SR). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the effect of continued therapy with UT-15C SR on exercise capacity.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After one year of treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participation in study TDE-PH-301 or TDE-PH-302 is required. Subjects must complete all assessments in one of these two studies to be eligible.  Subjects who permanently discontinued study drug during the previous study (TDE-PH-301 or TDE-PH-302) due to treatment related adverse events are not eligible for entry into this study, even if they completed all remaining study visits in the previous study.Subjects who permanently discontinued study drug during the Treatment Phase of Study TDE-PH-301 or TDE-PH-302 due to clinical worsening (as defined in those study protocols) and who did not undergopremature termination assessments prior to discontinuing study drug, and/or who did not complete all remaining study visits through the final scheduled visit, are also not eligible for entry into this study.Subjects who permanently discontinued study drug during the Treatment Phase of the previous study (TDE-PH-301 or TDE-PH-302) due to clinical worsening, who completed premature terminationassessments prior to discontinuing study drug, and who completed all remaining scheduled study visits, are eligible for entry into this study. However, if the subject received active drug during the TreatmentPhase of the previous study (TDE-PH-301 or TDE-PH-302), then the subject may not participate in this study, as the subject previously clinically worsened on active drug. If the subject received placebo duringthe Treatment Phase of the previous study, then the subject is eligible for this study and should start treatment UT-15C SR in the open-label study at 1 mg twice daily.Inclusion Criteria: 1. The subject weighs a minimum of 45 kilograms at Screening. 2. The subject, if female, is physiologically incapable of childbearing or practicing an acceptable method of birth control (i.e., surgical sterilization, approved hormonal contraceptives, barrier methods [such as a condom or diaphragm] used with a spermicide, or an intrauterine device}.For women of childbearing potential, a negative serum pregnancy test will be required at Screening. 3. The subject has a diagnosis of symptomatic Idiopathic or Familial PAH (including PAH associated with appetite suppressant use), PAH associated with repaired congenital systemic-to-pulmonary shunts (repaired = 5 years), PAH associated with Collagen Vascular Disease, or PAH associated with HIV. 4. The subject, if HIV positive, has a CD4 lymphocyte count = 200 within 30 days of Baseline and is receiving current standard of care anti-retroviral or other effective medication for treatment of HIV. 5. The subject must have a Baseline 6-Minute Walk distance of between 100 and 400 meters, inclusive. 6. The subject may benefit from the introduction of additional therapy (e.g. a prostacyclin) as determined by their medical provider. 7. The subject must have been optimally treated with approved oral therapies. Specifically, the subject:a. Has been receiving approved PDE-5 inhibitor or approved ERA therapy alone for at least 90 days and at the current stable dose for 30 days prior to Baseline and is willing to remain on PDE-5 inhibitor or ERA alone and at the same dose for the duration of the 16- week Treatment Phase orb. Has been receiving the combination of approved PDE-5 inhibitor and approved ERA therapy for at least 90 days prior to Baseline with both treatments at the current stable dose at least 30 days prior to Baseline and is willing to remain on the combination of PDE-5 inhibitor and ERA at the same dose for the duration of the 16-week Treatment Phase. 8. The subject must be optimally treated with conventional pulmonary hypertension therapy (anticoagulant, diuretic, oxygen, digoxin, etc) using the same regimen for at least 30 days prior to Baseline. 9. The subject has previously undergone a cardiac catheterization and been documented to have a mean pulmonary artery pressure (PAPm) &gt; 25 mmHg, a pulmonary capillary wedge pressure (PCWP) or a left ventricular end diastolic pressure (LVEDP) &lt; 15 mmHg, and pulmonary vascularresistance (PVR) &gt; 3 Wood units and absence of unrepaired congenital heart disease.10. The subject has previously undergone echocardiography with evidence of normal left systolic and diastolic ventricular function, and absence of any clinically significant left sided heart disease (e.g. mitral valve stenosis).11. The subject has a previous chest radiograph, ventilation perfusion scan, high resolution computerized tomography scan, or pulmonary angiography that are consistent with the diagnosis of PAH (i.e., low probability of pulmonary embolism; absence of major perfusion defects).12. In the opinion of the Principal Investigator, the subject is able to communicate effectively with study personnel, and is considered reliable, willing and likely to be cooperative with protocol requirements.13. The subject voluntarily gives informed consent to participate in the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>12</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. The subject is pregnant or lactating.2. The subject has received epoprostenol, treprostinil, iloprost, beraprost, or any other prostacyclin therapy within 30 days of Baseline (except if used during acute vasoreactivity testing).3. The subject has had a new type of chronic therapy (including but not limited to oxygen, a different category of vasodilator, diuretic, digoxin) for pulmonary hypertension added within 30 days of Baseline.4. The subject has had any PAH medication except for anticoagulants discontinued within 30 days of Baseline.5. The subject has any disease associated with pulmonary arterial hypertension other than collagen vascular disease, HIV, or repaired congenital systemic-to-pulmonary shunts (repaired = 5 years)(e.g. portal hypertension, chronic thromboembolic disease, etc.).6. The subject has a current diagnosis of uncontrolled sleep apnea as defined by their physician.7. The subject has chronic renal insufficiency as defined by either a Screening creatinine value greater than 2.5 mg/dL (221 µmol/L) or the requirement for dialysis.8. The subject has anemia as defined by a Screening hemoglobin value of less than 10 g/dL.9. The subject has a history or current evidence of left-sided heart disease including previous myocardial infarction, or evidence of current left-sided heart disease as defined by PCWPm or LVEDP &gt; 15 mmHg or left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) &lt; 40% as assessed by either multigated angiogram (MUGA), angiography or echocardiography, or left ventricular (LV) shortening fraction &lt; 22% as assessed by echocardiography, or symptomatic coronary artery disease (i.e., demonstratable ischemia either at rest or during exercise).10. The subject has significant parenchymal lung disease as evidenced by pulmonary function tests done within 6 months of Baseline as defined by any one of the following:a. Total Lung Capacity &lt; 60% (predicted), orb. If Total Lung Capacity is between 60% and 70% of predicted, a high resolution CT scan must be performed to document diffuse interstitial fibrosis or alveolitis orc. Forced expiratory volume/forced vital capacity (FEV/FVC) ratio &lt; 50%11. The subject has uncontrolled systemic hypertension as evidenced by systolic blood pressure greater than 160 mmHg or diastolic blood pressure greater than 100 mmHg.12. The subject has a musculoskeletal disorder (e.g. hip replacement, artificial leg, etc.) or any other disease that is likely to limit ambulation, or is connected to a machine that is not portable.13. The subject has an unstable psychiatric condition or is mentally incapable of understanding the objectives, nature, or consequences of the trial, or has any condition which in the Investigator's opinion would constitute an unacceptable risk to the subject's safety.14. The subject is receiving an investigational drug, has an investigational device in place (except a Chronicle® device if in place and without complications for 30 days prior to Screening), or has participated in an investigational drug or device study within 30 days prior to Screening.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/11/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>450</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>United Therapeutics Corporation</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>One Park Drive
P. O. Box 14186
Research Triangle Park NC 27709</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>United Therapeutics Corporation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Icon Clinical Reasearch Organisation will represent the sponsor in Australia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension (PAH) is a medical disorder in which pressure in the blood vessels going from the right side of the heart to the lungs (the pulmonary arteries) is elevated. The symptoms associated with PAH are tiredness, dizziness, and shortness of breath. These symptoms increase over time due to deterioration of the right ventricle of the heart.  Prostacyclin is a naturally occurring hormone like fatty acid which has been found diminished in patients with PAH. Treatment for PAH in Australia include drugs to dilate the blood vessels in the pulmonary artery i.e. Bosentan, Revatio, prostacyclin analogues (a manufactured drug similar in action to naturally occurring prostacyclin), Warfarin is used to thin the blood, oxygen and lung transplantation are all treatment options.
UT-15C is a prostacyclin analogue that has been developed in an oral form. Prostacyclin analogues are currently only available in intravenous and subcutaneous (injected under the skin) forms and have been shown to be a potent vasodilator and an inhibitor of platelet aggregation. These proven forms of treatment for PAH come with additional risks and administration complications. An oral form of the drug would be far more suitable and safer for the patient. 
The purpose of this continuation study is to assess the long-term safety of UT-15C SR and also evaluate the effects of continued therapy with UT-15C SR. Approximately 450 participants at approximately 60 centres will be included in this study.
It is hoped that using a combination treatment of PAH with therapies targeting different mechanisms of action has great promise in addressing the multiple pathophysiologic mechanisms that are implicated in PAH. These combinations may produce an additive effect or enhance and prolong the effect of other therapeutic agents.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Heart/Lung Transplant Unit Xavier 4 St. Vincent’s Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Victoria Street Darlinghurst NSW 2010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Advanced Lung Disease Dept Royal Perth Hospital, South Metropolitan Area Health Service</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Wellington St, WA 6847</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Alfred Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>5th Floor, The Alfred Hospital, Commercial Rd Melbourne VIC 3004</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms. Georgina Spence</name>
      <address>United Therapeutics Europe Ltd, 26 Frederick Sanger Road
Guildford, Surrey
United Kingdom
GU2 7YD</address>
      <phone>+44 1483 207785</phone>
      <fax>+44 1483 207781</fax>
      <email>gspence@unither.com</email>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms. Georgina Spence</name>
      <address>United Therapeutics Europe Ltd, 26 Frederick Sanger Road
Guildford, Surrey
GU2 7YD</address>
      <phone>+44 1483 207785</phone>
      <fax>+44 1483 207781</fax>
      <email>gspence@unither.com</email>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>