<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82734">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/04/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/04/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000188336</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of Mental Health First Aid Educational Materials - a Randomised Controlled Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An evaluation of the effects of mental health first aid training in a community sample of adults by e-learning CD-ROM compared to either a printed manual or no training and the impact on mental health literacy, confidence in providing first aid, stigmatizing attitudes and first aid actions taken to help people with mental health problems.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>mental health literacy</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>confidence in providing mental health first aid</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>stigmatizing attitudes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>number of first aid actions taken to help people with mental health problems</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>first-aider mental health</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Schizophrenia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A 12 hour e-learning CD ROM on Mental Health First Aid (MHFA) or hard-copy MHFA manual or Wait List control. Completion of 3 online surveys (prior to receiving intervention, post intervention and at six-month follow-up).</interventions>
    <comparator>Wait List</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>mental health literacy. This is measured using some of the questions from the National Survey of Mental Health Literacy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Completion of three online surveys (pre-study, post intervention and six month follow-up) to determine changes in knowledge, attitudes and helping behaviour towards people with mental health problems.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Confidence in providing mental health first aid. This was measured by including a questionnaire item which asked participants how confident they would feel in helping a person in a vignette depicting depression (Mary), and another person in a vignette depicting schizophrenia (John). Each were rated on a 5-point scale (1 = Not at all, 2 = A little bit, 3 = Moderately, 4 = Quite a bit and 5 = Extremely).</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline, 1-month post intervention and 6-months follow-up.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of helping behaviours towards people with mental health problems. This was measured including a questionnaire item which asked how often a participant had talked to a person about their mental health problem over the past 6-months. This was rated using a 4-point scale (1 = never, 2 = once, 3 = a few times and 4 = many times). If a participant indicated they had spoken to someone, they were asked to indicate which of the following they had done (multiple responses were allowed): 1) Spent time listening to their problem; 2) Helped to calm them down; 3) Talked to them about suicidal thoughts; 4) Recommended they seek professional help; 5) Recommended self-help strategies; 6) Gave them information about their problem; 7) Gave them information about local services; 8) Made an appointment for them with services; 9) Referred them to books or websites about their problem or 10) other (open-ended response). Scoring was based on 1 point per action taken and totals were converted into percentages.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline and 6-months follow-up.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>stigmatizing attitudes. This is measured using the Social Distance Scale. Also, the Personal and Perceived Stigma Scales will be used.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Completion of three online surveys (pre-study, post intervention and six month follow-up) to determine changes in knowledge, attitudes and helping behaviour towards people with mental health problems.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>first-aider mental health, using the Kessler Psychological Distress Scale (K-10+). This is a 10-item self-report measure of psychological distress in the past month, using a 5-point scale (1 = None of the time , 2 = A little of the time, 3 = Some of the time, 4 = Most of the time, 5 = All of the time). The following questionnaire item was included: ?Over the last 30 days, how often did you feel: a) tired out for no good reason? b) nervous? c) so nervous that nothing could calm you down? d) hopeless? e) restless or fidgety? f) so restless that you could not sit still? g) depressed? h) so depressed that nothing could cheer you up? i) that everything was an effort? j) worthless??  Scores were summed and ranged between 10-50, with scores above 19 indicating higher distress.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline, 1-month post intervention and 6-months follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>computer with a CD drive and internet access</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>no computer or internet access
unable to read English</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The Research Plan is designed to meet the requirements of the CONSORT checklist. Adult members of the general public will be recruited through publicity in newspapers and public noticeboards, primarily from metropolitan Melbourne. Potential participants will contact the Research Assistant via telephone or email and will be emailed a Participant Information Sheet and Consent Form. Once the latter is returned, a unique ID will be generated in Excel and emailed individually to participants, along with a link to the pre-study online questionnaire. On completion of the first questionnaire, the unique ID numbers will be given to Prof A Jorm, who without knowledge of participant details, will use the Random Integers option (Random.org) to generate a randomly assigned variable (values of 1-3) to determine which condition they are allocated to.</concealment>
    <sequence>Prof A Jorm will use the Random Integers option at (Random.org) to generate a value between 1 to 3 (1 = e-learning CD ROM; 2 = printed manual and 3 = added to Wait List). These will be recorded next to the the participants' uinique ID number (with no other information) and returned to the Research Assistant.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/05/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>3040</postcode>
    <postcode>3052</postcode>
    <postcode>3000</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>ORYGEN Research Centre 
35 Poplar Road 
Parkville VIC 3052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Rotary Health Research Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Australian Rotary Health Research Fund
Floor 2
Rotary Down Under House
43 Hunter Street
PARRAMATTA NSW 2150</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Australian Rotary Health Research Fund</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Australian Rotary Health Research Fund
Floor 2
Rotary Down Under House
43 Hunter Street
PARRAMATTA NSW 2150</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The University of Melbourne recruited adult members of the general public in an evaluation of educational materials,  which teach skills in helping someone with a mental health problem. Participants were asked to complete 3 online questionnaires of approximately 20 minutes each (over a seven month period), to gauge their knowledge, attitudes and behaviours towards people with mental health problems. Jorm AF, Kitchener BA, Fischer JA, Cvetkovski S in press, Mental health first aid training by e-learning: a randomized controlled trial, Australian and New Zealand Journal of Psychiatry.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.arhrf.org.au. Upon ethics approval, the online surveys will appear on Survey Monkey, at: http://www.surveymonkey.com.</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Melbourne Human Ethics Advisory Group</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>35 Poplar Road 
Parkville  VIC  3052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>0827110</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>17/04/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Anthony F Jorm</name>
      <address>ORYGEN Research Centre
35 Poplar Road 
PARKVILLE  VIC   3052</address>
      <phone>+ 61 3 9342 3747</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ajorm@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Julie-Anne Fischer</name>
      <address>ORYGEN Research Centre 
35 Poplar Road 
PARKVILLE VIC   3052</address>
      <phone>+ 61 3 9342 3768</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jfischer@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Julie-Anne Fischer</name>
      <address>ORYGEN Research Centre
35 Poplar Road 
PARKVILLE  VIC   3052</address>
      <phone>+ 61 3 9342 3768</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jfischer@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>