<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365150">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/12/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/06/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000601639</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Cultural Influence of Postoperative Pain</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A prospective cohort comparing post-operative opioid requirement and other pain related behaviours and effects after major surgery in two Chinese populations from Hong Kong and Mainland China
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1149-0851 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Post operative pain</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Post operative opioid requirements
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Beliefs and attitudes of patients and carers in relation to post operative analgesia
</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Observational cohort study of pain perception and opioid requirements post major abdominal surgery in chinese adults that are culturally different.
Observations will occur preoperatively and then twice daily for 3 days postoperatively.</interventions>
    <comparator>Comparison of two groups; One group of patient from mainland china which is traditional chinese society, the other from Hong Kong which is heavily westernised.
Both groups having major abdominal surgery with standardised postoperative management.
Standardised postoperative analgesia includes 3 days of morphine IV via patient controlled analgesia. Rescue analgesia includes paracetamol as first line, Non-steroidal anti-inflammatory as second line.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>comparison of opioid requirement after major abdominal surgery between chinese patients living in two distinct cultures</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cumulative opioid requirements measured over first 3 days after surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compare beliefs and attitudes  and anxiety in relation to post operative analgesia among chinese patients in two different cultures.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to surgery patients will be surveyed with a questionaire 'beliefs and attitudes regarding pain management'.
Prior to surgery patients will complete the Hospital Anxiety and depression (HAD) to evaluate pre-existing levels of anxiety and depression
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compare the threshold pain score betweeen that that is associated with request for further analgesai or leading to pain related interference with daily activities.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Using a numerical rating scale pain score will be measured at rest, with coughing, and upon waking from surgery. Patients will be visited at least twice daily for 3 days after surgery. During the visit, patient will be asked if they will consider their current level of pain tolerable, and if they wish to receive further analgesia. Patient satisfaction with analgesia will be ranked as 1 = very satisfied, 2 = somewhat satisfied, 3 = unsatisfied, 4 = unsure. Pain-related interference with: physical activity (walking, movement); coughing and deep breathing, sleep, and mood since last visit using the numeric rating scale of 0-10, where 0 = no interference and 10 = worst interference.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nursing staff will also  be surveyed on their beliefs and attitudes regarding pain management preoperatively.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Preoperatively, the nurse will surveyed and respond by saying whether they strongly disagree, disagree a little, have neutral feelings, agree a little or strongly agree: 
(1)	I prefer to give my patient less opioid because of addiction
(2)	My patient should expect to have severe pain after surgery
(3)	My patient should control their own analgesia therapy.

We will also ask the carers about their expectations regarding analgesic regimen for their patients: 
The analgesia I expect that my patient will need is: no analgesics / weak analgesics / strong analgesics / combinations of weak and strong analgesics, 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Opioid side effects </outcome>
      <timepoint>opioid-related symptom distress scale (ORSDS) recorded daily for 3 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>quantify the biologic equivalence of patients recruited from the two hospitals (same race) we plan to determine the single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) of opioid receptor, mu-1 (OPRM1).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Genomic deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) will be extracted from 5 ml venous blood samples collected before surgery using QIAamp DNA mini kit 250 (Qiagen, Valencia, CA). Genotyping will be performed using Taqman SNP assays </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients are eligible for the study if 
1.18 and 80 years 
2.undergoing major abdominal surgery requiring a wound incision &gt; 10 cm in length. 
3. All patients should have strong Chinese features and lived in their respective cities (Hong Kong or Hangzhou) for most of their lives. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients are excluded if they:
 1. do not agree to receive patient controlled analgesia (PCA) with morphine for at least three days after surgery 
2. do not demonstrate adequate understanding on the principles involving the use of PCA during the preoperative visit. 
3. Allergy to morphine, paracetamol or non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs. 
4. Patients with pre-existing severe renal and liver disease, 5.  chronic pain for &gt; 3 months in the 6 months leading to surgery or who require opioid therapy in the preceding 2 weeks prior to surgery </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Data will be expressed as means (+/- standard deviation), median (interquartile range) or numbers, as appropriate. Continuous data (opioid consumption) will be compared between groups using unpaired t test. Categorical and ordinal data (brief and attitude statements) will be analysed using Fishers exact test and Mann-Whitney test, respectively. The difference in pain scores between patients from mainland hospital (SSRSH) and those in Hong Kong (PWH) will be analysed using a generalized linear model for repeated measures. Covariates will include patient characteristics (anxiety, education level), operative details, SNP, briefs and attitudes, and pain thresholds. Multiple comparisons will be adjusted by Dunn-Sidak procedure. 

We will calculate the threshold significant pain by comparing NRS pain scores in patients that request for further analgesia or patients who reported pain-related interference with daily activities using the largest F-value approach. The threshold pain scores will be compared between groups using unpaired t-test. A p value &lt; 0.05 is considered significant.
Analysis of opioid requirement of Hong Kong patients from a recently published study from the same principal investigator revealed a mean opioid requirement (intravenous morhpine equivalents) in the first 24 hours after surgery to be 46.5 mg with a standard deviation of 23.7. Assuming 55 type 1 error and 20% type two error 70 participants were required in each population to show a significant difference. We have added 50 participants to each group to enable closer analysis of secondary end points</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/10/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>24/10/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/10/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>250</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Zhejiang</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <state>Shatin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Alex Konstantatos</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Alfred Hospital
C/O Department of Anaesthesia and Pain medicine
PO Box 315
Prahran, Victoria 3181</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian and New Zealand College of Anaesthetists</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>630 St Kilda Rd
Melbourne
Victoria 3004</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Matthew Chan
</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Prince of Wales Hospital
Department of Anaesthesia and Intensive Care
Shatin,
New Territories
Hong Kong Special</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Hong Kong</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>We hypothesize that cultural differences within the same race (Chinese) will lead to changes in opioid requirement after major abdominal surgery. This will be reflected by the differences in briefs and attitudes towards postoperative pain between patients living in the two cities.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Prince of Wales Hospital, Shatin, New Territories, Hong Kong Sir Run Run Shaw Hospital, Hangzhou, Zhejiang 
</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sir Run Run Shaw Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/09/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>20130924</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/09/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>China</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alex Konstantatos</name>
      <address>Dept of Anaesthesia and Perioperative Medicine
Alfred Hospital
PO Box 315
Prahran
Victoria 3181</address>
      <phone>+61390763176</phone>
      <fax>+61390762813</fax>
      <email>a.konstantatos@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alex Konstantatos</name>
      <address>Dept of Anaesthesia and Perioperative Medicine
Alfred Hospital
PO Box 315
Prahran
Victoria 3181</address>
      <phone>+61390763176</phone>
      <fax>+61390762813</fax>
      <email>a.konstantatos@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alex Konstantatos</name>
      <address>Dept of Anaesthesia and Perioperative Medicine
Alfred Hospital
PO Box 315
Prahran
Victoria 3181</address>
      <phone>+61390763176</phone>
      <fax>+61390762813</fax>
      <email>a.konstantatos@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Dana Boyd</name>
      <address>Dept of Anaesthesia and Perioperative Medicine
Alfred Hospital
PO Box 315
Prahran
Victoria 3181</address>
      <phone>+61390763176</phone>
      <fax>+61390762813</fax>
      <email>d.boyd@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>