<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367335">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/10/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/11/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001163695</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of a novel glucose sensor in type 1 diabetes</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A comparison of the performance of an orthogonally redundant glucose sensor to an electrochemical glucose sensor with simple redundancy in type 1 diabetes</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1163-5283</utrn>
    <trialacronym>ORS comparison study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 1 diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study evaluates the performance of a novel glucose sensor incorporating simple and orthogonal redundancy in people with type 1 diabetes. Currently available glucose sensors measure interstitial fluid glucose levels via electrochemical sensing. Sensor redundancy involves multiple sensing elements incorporated into a single sensor, thereby providing backup in case one element fails. Simple redundancy involves multiple sensing elements employing the same technology, while orthogonal redundancy involves multiple elements employing different technologies which have distinct failure modes.

Each participant will concurrently wear two glucose sensors for one week: 1) the investigational orthogonally redundant sensor (ORS) incorporating optical plus redundant electrochemical glucose sensing, and 2) an electrochemical comparator sensor (ECS) with simple redundancy.

Each sensor will be inserted subcutaneously into the abdomen using a dedicated sensor inserter in the clinical trials centre (CTC), a procedure which takes less than 5 minutes. Each sensor will be attached to a recorder which captures sensor-related information, and this data will be uploaded at the conclusion of the study. Glucose data from the study devices will not be available to the participants and will not impact upon decisions relating to their care.

Immediately following sensor insertion venous samples will be collected for reference blood glucose measurement at standardised 15-30 minute intervals for 3 hours. After 72 +/- 4 hours of sensor wear, participants will return to the CTC and consume a standardised meal. Venous samples will be collected for reference blood glucose measurement at 15 minute intervals from 1 hour prior to the test meal until 3 hours post-meal.

Between visits to the CTC, participants will be instructed to undertake finger prick capillary blood glucose measurements at least 6-8 times per day (pre-meals and 2 hours post-meals) which will be recorded by the glucose meter. Following 168 +/- 4 hours of sensor wear, both the ORS and ECS will be removed in the CTC.</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator is an electrochemical glucose sensor with simple redundancy, and reference glucose measurements will be venous and capillary blood glucose levels.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Performance of the ORS versus ECS (assessed via accuracy and reliability of sensor data), with blood glucose levels as the reference.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 to 168 hours</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>ORS versus ECS insertion site appearance (skin assessed as normal or abnormal; any skin abnormalities described and photographed).</outcome>
      <timepoint>168 hours post sensor insertion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>ORS versus ECS device comfort and irritability (assessed via non-structured interview).</outcome>
      <timepoint>168 hours post sensor insertion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Clinical diagnosis of type 1 diabetes, insulin treatment for diabetes, experience with glucose sensor use.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>21</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnant, planned pregnancy within study period, inability to tolerate tape adhesive in the area of device placement, adverse skin condition in the area of device placement.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/11/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>10/11/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>2/03/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>21</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne) Ltd - Fitzroy</hospital>
    <postcode>3065 - Fitzroy</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>St Vincent's Hospital Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>41 Victoria Parade
Fitzroy VIC 3065</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Juvenile Diabetes Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>26 Broadway
New York NY 10004</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Medtronic Diabetes</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>18000 Devonshire Street
Northridge CA 91325</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Melbourne</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>29 Regent Street
Fitzroy VIC 3065</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Glucose sensor technology has been evolving with an ultimate goal of achieving a level of accuracy required to replace finger prick glucose testing, together with a level of reliability for use in an artificial pancreas. While there have been recent advances in glucose sensing technology, further improvements relating to sensor accuracy and reliability are required.

A glucose sensor based on a novel technology platform has been developed. Studies in animals and humans during development of this sensor have shown positive results, and this will be the first study in humans to formally compare the novel glucose sensor to a glucose sensor based on the traditional sensing platform.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Feasibility of an Orthogonal Redundant Sensor incorporating Optical plus Redundant Electrochemical Glucose Sensing. Journal of Diabetes Science and Technology 2016. http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/26846821</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital Melbourne</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Governance Unit
Level 5, Mary Aikenhead Building
27 Victoria Parade
Fitzroy VIC 3065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/09/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC-D 093/14</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>David O'Neal</name>
      <address>Department of Endocrinology &amp; Diabetes, St Vincent's Hospital Melbourne, 35 Victoria Parade Fitzroy VIC 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9231 2211</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dno@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sybil McAuley</name>
      <address>Department of Endocrinology &amp; Diabetes, St Vincent's Hospital Melbourne, 35 Victoria Parade Fitzroy VIC 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9231 2211</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sybil.mcauley@svha.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sybil McAuley</name>
      <address>Department of Endocrinology &amp; Diabetes, St Vincent's Hospital Melbourne, 35 Victoria Parade Fitzroy VIC 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9231 2211</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sybil.mcauley@svha.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>