<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367557">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/12/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/12/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001300662</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Examining the Feasibility of an Internet-Delivered Cognitive Behaviour Therapy program for emotional wellbeing among people with epilepsy.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An open trial examining the feasibility of an internet-delivered Cognitive Behaviour Therapy (iCBT) program for adults with epilepsy aimed at improving emotional wellbeing.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Epilepsy</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Epilepsy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be assigned to one group, who will receive an internet-delivered Cognitive Behaviour Therapy program, the Managing Your Wellbeing Epilepsy Course. All participants will have a diagnosis of epilepsy. Participants will complete 5 lessons of Internet based treatment about management of symptoms of anxiety and depression in the context of living with a chronic health condition (epilepsy). One lesson will be completed every 7 to 10 days. Each lesson will take about 15 minutes to complete. Participants will also have access to summaries of each lesson, and will read anonymous stories about other people with chronic health conditions, including epilepsy, taking a further 20 minutes per summary. 

Online monitoring will occur to monitor lessons completed and treatment adherence. When each participant clicks through all the slides of each lesson the computer will log the time spent on the lesson and the time/date when the lesson was completed.

Participants will have the option of weekly telephone calls or emails from a trained and supervised Psychologist at the eCentreClinic to provide support, encouragement and to answer questions about the content of the Course. The duration of the program is 8 weeks. Study questionnaires will be administered at application, pre-treatment, posttreatment, and at 3 month follow-up. Some questionnaires will be administered weekly during the Course. The major sets of questionnaires will take about 10 to 15 minutes to complete. The treatment materials are based on previous internet-based programs, which apply cognitive behavioural techniques. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient Health Questionnaire 9-Item (PHQ9) and Neurological Depressive Disorders Inventory for Epilepsy (NDDI-E), which are two measures of depression.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Application, pre-treatment, weekly during treatment (PHQ-9), post-treatment and 3 month follow-up.
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Generalized Anxiety Disorder 7-Item (GAD7), which is a measure of anxiety.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Application, pre-treatment, weekly during treatment, post-treatment and 3 month follow-up.
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>World Health Organisation Disability Assessment Schedule 2.0 (WHODAS-2), which is a measure of disability associated with living with a chronic health condition. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment, post-treatment and 3 month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Liverpool Seizure Severity (LSSS), which is a measure of patients perception of seizure severity. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Application, pre-treatment, post-treatment and 3 month follow-up.


</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Seizure Frequency Questionnaire (SFQ) and Weekly Seizure Frequency Questionnaire (WSFQ), which are two brief purpose built measures to assess seizure activity. </outcome>
      <timepoint>The SFQ will be administered at application, pre-treatment, post-treatment and 3 month follow-up. The WSFQ will be administered weekly during treatment. 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Satisfaction with Life Questionnaire (SWL), which is a measure of  of satisfaction with life.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment, post-treatment and 3 month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Service Use Questionnaire (SUQ), which is a measure to assess participants use of specific medications and treatment services.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment, post-treatment and 3 month follow-up.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Treatment Satisfaction Questionnaires (TSQ), which measures the acceptability of online treatment Courses and participants satisfaction with treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-treatment, 3 month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceived Difficulties Questionnaire (PDQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-treatment, post-treatment, 3 month follow up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- 18+ years of age.
- Confirmed diagnosis of epilepsy; which is being managed by a GP or specialist. 
- Living in Australia.
- Has had a recent consultation (i.e., in the last 6 months) with a GP or specialist.
- Provide informed consent to participate in the study.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Inability to use a computer. 
- Severe depression (i.e., indicated by a score &gt; 22 on the PHQ-9). 
- Significant suicidal ideation (i.e., indicated by a score &gt; 2 to Question 9 of the PHQ-9). 
- Acutely suicidal or recent history of attempted suicide or self-harm (i.e., last 12 months). 
- Serious cognitive impairment or dementia (&lt;21 on the Telephone Interview of Cognitive Status; TICS).
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants apply online via the clinic's website
(www.ecentreclinic.org.au). Successful applications are followed by a telephone interview to confirm suitability for the trial. Participants who met inclusion criteria will be allocated to one group (i.e., the Managing Your Wellbeing - Epilepsy Course). </concealment>
    <sequence>As open trial, no randomisation sequence required</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>All analyses will be carried out using conservative intention-to-treat principles and using mixed-linear models analyses to handle missing data. Mixed-models are a robust statistical approach for analysing clinical. 

With alpha set at .05, power set at .80 and a sample size of 30, the study is powered to enable the detection of moderate-to-large effect size (i.e., Cohens d &gt; 0.50) differences in symptoms of anxiety, depression and disability from pre-treatment to post-treatment and follow-up. The project is, therefore, well powered. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/04/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>11/06/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>5/10/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>3/07/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>27</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Milena Gandy </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>eCentreClinic, The Centre For Emotional Health (CEH), Department of Psychology, Macquarie University, NSW, 2109, Australia.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Macquarie University </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>eCentreClinic, The Centre For Emotional Health (CEH), Department of Psychology, Macquarie University, NSW, 2109, Australia.
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Blake Dear </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of Psychology
Macquarie University
Balaclava Road, North Ryde, NSW, 2109, Australia.
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Macquarie University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>eCentreClinic, The Centre For Emotional Health (CEH), Department of Psychology, Macquarie University, North Ryde, NSW, 2109, Australia.
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of the proposed project is to examine the acceptability, efficacy and feasibility of a low-intensity Cognitive Behaviour Therapy (CBT)-based self-management program, the Managing Your Wellbeing Epilepsy Course, in reducing symptoms of anxiety, depression and disability among adults with epilepsy. The Course contains a 5-lesson 8 week CBT program, which can be administered via the internet. Participants will have brief weekly contact with a clinical psychologist as they work through the Course. We expect participants will rate the Course as acceptable and will report that it was worth their time. We also expect that overall sample will make improvements in symptoms of disability, anxiety and depression from pre-treatment to post-treatment, which will be maintained at 3-month. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.ecentreclinic.org
</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Gandy, M., Sharpe, L., Nicholson Perry, K., Miller, L, Thayer, Z, Boserio, J., &amp; Mohamed, A. [2014]: Cognitive Behaviour Therapy to Improve Mood in People with Epilepsy: A Randomized Controlled Trial. Cognitive Behaviour Therapy, 43[2], 153-166

Gandy, M., Sharpe, L., &amp; Nicholson Perry, K. [2013]. Cognitive behavior therapy for depression in people with epilepsy: A systematic review. Epilepsia, 54, 1725-1734

Dear, B. F., Titov, N., Nicholson Perry, K., Johnston, L., Wootton, B. M., Terides, M. D. Hudson, J. L. (2013). The Pain Course: A randomised controlled trial of a clinician-guided Internet-delivered cognitive behaviour therapy program for managing chronic pain and emotional well-being. Pain, 154(6), 942-950
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Macquarie University, HUman Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics Committee
Level 3, Research Hub, Building C5C, Macquarie University, North Ryde, NSW, 2109.
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/09/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>5201400820</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Milena Gandy </name>
      <address>Department of Psychology, Macquarie University, NSW 2109, Australia.</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 4152</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>milena.gandy@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Milena Gandy</name>
      <address>Department of Psychology, Macquarie University, NSW 2109, Australia.</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 4152</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>milena.gandy@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Milena Gandy </name>
      <address>Department of Psychology, Macquarie University, NSW 2109, Australia.</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 4152</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>milena.gandy@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Milena Gandy</name>
      <address>Department of Psychology, Macquarie University, NSW 2109, Australia.</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 4152</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>milena.gandy@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>