<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370764">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/05/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000902493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Progressive Pressure Release Versus Dry Needling on Cervical Latent Trigger Points</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Progressive Pressure Release Versus Dry Needling on Cervical Latent Trigger Points</scientifictitle>
    <utrn> U1111-1183-1421</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Latent myofascial trigger points</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study was conducted at the out patient clinic of faculty of Physical Therapy, Cairo University , Egypt. After signing an informed consent form, thirty subjects with latent myofascial trigger points (L-MTrPs) were assigned into two equal groups; (A) 15 subjects received passive stretching and progressive pressure release; 3 times per week for 4 weeks. Group (B) 15 subjects received passive stretching exercise and dry needling using acupuncture needles, 3 times per week for 4 weeks.. 

A certified physical therapist with more that 7 years experience carried out the assessment procedure. Clinical identification of L-MTrPs was based on Travel and Simon (1999) essential criteria, where the upper trapezius was placed in a stretched and relaxed position to easily locate L-MTrPs. Flat or pincer palpation was used to locate L-MTrPs. 
Essential criteria for L-MTrPs included;
1- Palpable taut band: which includes a tender nodule. 
2- Exquisite spot tenderness of a nodule: Palpating through a taut band, there was a tender nodular area.  
3- Limited range of motion at the end of range: it is a common characteristic of myofascial trigger points to restrict the range of motion and produce pain at the end of range (Fernndez et al., 2007 and Mullaney et al., 2010).
He then marked an "X" on the L-MTrPs found, that were;
L-MTrP1: was found in the mid portion of the anterior border of the upper trapezius and involves the most vertical fibers that attach anteriorly to the clavicle.
L-MTrP2: lies caudal and slightly lateral to L-MTrP1 which was located in the middle of the more nearly-horizontal fibers of the upper trapezius 

Measurement outcome included pressure pain threshold using an electronic digital algometer  and active cervical side bending and rotation using an inclinometer. Measurements were taken at the first treatment as baseline measurement and the end of the 4 weeks trial; at the last session as post-test measurement. Each subject had a sheet, where outcome measures were recorded in as well as attendance of sessions was registered in.
 
Another certified physical therapist with 5 years experience carried out the progressive pressure release on the marked "X" L-MTrP and passive stretch treatment procedure. Passive stretch was applied while the patient was in seated position, the head was then taken to flexion, side bending to the opposite side and rotation to the same side, this position was maintained for 30-60 seconds and repeated 3 times. Progressive pressure release technique was applied using the thumbs; steady pressure was applied, moving inward toward the center. Once tissue resistance was felt, we stopped and waited until resistance dissipated, and then when a slow release or a "melting away" sensation of the tissue under treating fingers was felt, further steady pressure moving again inward toward the center was applied for 2-3 minutes. This was repeated 4 times. The muscle was placed in a position to maximize stretch, but in a relaxed one. 

A third certified acupuncture therapist applied the dry needling treatment procedure.  where patients were placed in a comfortable sitting position and encouraged to maintain complete relaxation. The selected L-MTrP (marked by an "X") was prepared by wiping the area with an alcohol pad, and an acupuncture needle with its plastic guide tube in place was placed over the L-MTrP. With pincer palpation,  the needle was applied to a depth of 1-1.5 cm. Needle movement was performed with rotation along its long axis in an effort till eliciting a small muscle twitch around the nodule; a local twitch response, which took from 30 sec to 2 min then the needle was removed. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Comparator treatment was Group (B); that received passive stretching and dry needling using acupuncture needles, 3 times per week for 4 weeks.. 
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>pain pressure threshold by electronic digital algometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>prior to the first treatment session and as baseline measurement and the end of the 4 weeks trial; at the last session as post-test measurement.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Active range of motion including cervical side bending and rotation was taken by a single inclinometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurements were taken at the first treatment as baseline measurement and the end of the 4 weeks trial; at the last session as post-test measurement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Subjects with age ranging from 20 to 30 years old (Edwards, et al., 2003)
2. Subjects havent experienced any neck pain for at least 3 months.
3. Presence of at least one latent MTrPs in the upper trapezius muscle (on the dominant side) and the production of pain by palpation on MTrPs.
4. Limitation in cervical side bending and rotation at the end of range.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>30</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Any inflammatory diseases of musculoskeletal system.
2.	Patients with cervical pain or neurological deficit (radiating pain, loss of sensation, muscle dysfunction, or loss of reflexes), disc prolapse, , previous neck surgery, and other 
3.	Cardiopulmonary diseases which decreases the patients tolerance and activities.
4.	Vascular problems. 
5.	Patient with uncontrolled diabetes.
6.	Neck pain due to unknown cause.
7.	Any dermatological diseases.
8.	Any deformity  of the  spine e.g.: sever scoliosis or kyphosis 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods> Results are expressed as mean +/- standard deviation (SD). Data are normally distributed, so comparison between different variables in the two studied groups was performed using unpaired t test. Pair-wise comparison (pre- versus post-assessment) within the same group for different variables was performed using paired t-test.
Statistical Package for Social Sciences (SPSS) computer program (version 19 windows) was used for data analysis. P value less than 0.05 was considered significant and less than 0.01 was considered highly significant.

Sample size calculation: since our design had paired observations (before-and-after), assuming its just a one-group test where each subject is serving as his/her own control. The study participants were assigned into two homogenous treatment groups. The patients in the first treatment group were given progressive pressure release and those in the second group B were given acupuncture dry needling. The primary endpoint is taken as the mean increase in pressure pain threshold after four weeks. Clinical knowledge suggests that the standard deviation of the increase in pressure pain threshold  with both treatments can be taken as 4.5 kgf.
 A one-tailed t-test for unpaired samples was performed. The level of significance was set at 2.5% for one-tailed test.  The statistical power was set as 80%.

Effect size was computed using Cohen's d and Hedges g that was 2.78 given group a mean &amp; SD (10.48 +/- 1.21) and group b (7.48+/- 0.93) with a sample size of 15 subjects per group

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>3/01/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>4/04/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>30</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>4/05/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <state>cairo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Faculty of Physical therapy, Cairo University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>El-Tahrir street. in front of Ben El- Sarayat Traffic - Dokki - Giza, Giza, 11432</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Egypt</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Mary Takla</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Lecturer at Faculty of Physical therapy, Cairo University. El-Tahrir street. in front of Ben El- Sarayat Traffic - Dokki - Giza, 11432</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Egypt</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Latent myofascial trigger points (L-MTrPs) within the upper trapezius muscle are closely associated with limitation of the cervical range especially at the end of range of motion. Over time, it affects the functional ability &amp; can be converted to active myofascial trigger points (A-MTrPs). Progressive pressure release and dry needling (DN) are two effective techniques used in the treatment of MTrPs.  Objective: to compare between the effect of both progressive pressure release and DN on cervical L-MTrPs. Subjects and methods: Thirty subjects with L-MTrPs were assigned into two equal groups; (A) received passive stretching exercise and progressive pressure release while group (B) received passive stretching exercise and DN. Measurement outcome included pressure pain threshold (PPT) by an electronic digital algometer and active cervical side bending and rotation by an inclinometer. Data was collected at the first treatment as baseline line measurement and the end of the 4 weeks trial; at the last session as post-test measurement.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Board Council ofHigher Education of the School of Physical Therapy</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>El-Tahrir street. - in front of Ben El- Sarayat Traffic - Dokki - Giza,  11432</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/07/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/06/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Egypt</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Institutional Review Board of Higher Education and Research of Cairo University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>1 Cairo University Road, Giza -Cairo- 12613</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/08/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/07/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Egypt</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Supreme Council of Universities at Egypt</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>1 Cairo University Road, Giza -Cairo- 12613</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/09/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/08/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Egypt</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mary Kamal Nassif Takla</name>
      <address>School of Physical therapy, Cairo University; El-Tahrir st. - in front of Ben El- Sarayat Traffic - Dokki - Giza, Giza, 11432</address>
      <phone>+201222817512</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>marytakla@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mary Kamal Nassif Takla</name>
      <address>School of Physical therapy, Cairo University; El-Tahrir st. - in front of Ben El- Sarayat Traffic - Dokki - Giza, Giza, 11432</address>
      <phone>+201222817512</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>marytakla@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mary Kamal Nassif Takla</name>
      <address>School of Physical therapy, Cairo University; El-Tahrir st. - in front of Ben El- Sarayat Traffic - Dokki - Giza, Giza, 11432</address>
      <phone>+201222817512</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>marytakla@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mary Kamal Nassif Takla</name>
      <address>School of Physical therapy, Cairo University; El-Tahrir st. - in front of Ben El- Sarayat Traffic - Dokki - Giza, Giza, 11432</address>
      <phone>+201222817512</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>marytakla@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>