<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370640">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/05/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/05/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000616471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of exercise timing throughout a day of prolonged sitting on blood glucose regulation</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of exercise timing throughout a day of prolonged sitting on blood glucose regulation in overweight/obese young adults</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a randomised, two-condition crossover trial where participants will undergo 2x ~48 h experimental conditions. Each condition will be separated by a minimum 7-day washout period

For both conditions participants will attend the laboratory at ~5 pm on the evening prior to the main experimental trial day (day one) for fitting of a continuous glucose monitoring system and receive a standardised take-home meal for dinner. Participants will also be fitted with an an accelerometer and an inclinometer for measurement of physical activity levels prior and during each experimental condition. Food and activity diaries will also be completed by participants prior to either experimental condition.

On the main experimental trial day (day two) participants will arrive at the laboratory via taxi at ~0730 h. A catheter will be inserted in the antecubital vein of the non-dominant arm at 0800 h and remain in place until 1900 h. Participants will remain seated for the duration of the visit and blood samples will be collected at regular intervals. Identical meals will be provided at 0900 h, 1300 h and 1700 h. . Each meal will contain ~33% total energy intake for the day with a macronutrient profile of 50% from carbohydrates, 30% from fat and 20% from protein. Additionally, participants will perform 30 minutes of aerobic exercise at ~65% VO2max on a cycle ergometer. The timing of the exercise bout will depend on the experimental condition being undertaken. At 1900 h participants will return home via taxi and fast overnight.

Condition A: Exercise will be performed at 0800 h, prior to breakfast.

Condition B: Exercise will be performed at 1600 h, prior to dinner.

Participants will then return to the lab for a follow up (day three) at ~0730 and remain seated for the duration of the visit. A catheter will be inserted in the antecubital vein of the non-dominant arm at 0800 h and remain until 1600 h for serial blood sampling. Participants will be provided identical meals to day two at 0900 h and 1300 h. At 1630 h all monitoring devices will be removed.</interventions>
    <comparator>As this is a randomised, two-condition crossover trial, comparison will be made between the two experimental conditions (morning exercise and evening exercise).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood glucose area under the curve (using continuous glucose monitoring systems)</outcome>
      <timepoint>The duration of the intervention (~48 h monitoring period)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma triglyceride area under the curve</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples from hourly time points (and one time point 30 minutes following each meal) across laboratory visits (Day 2: 0800 h to 1900 h, Day 3: 0800 h to 1600 h)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma insulin area under the curve</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples from hourly time points (and one time point 30 minutes following each meal) across laboratory visits (Day 2: 0800 h to 1900 h, Day 3: 0800 h to 1600 h)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Appetite scores for hunger and satiety measured using a visual analogue scale on a laptop (composite outcome)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every two hours during laboratory visits</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Sedentary overweight or obese [body mass index (BMI) &gt; 25 kg/m2 but &lt; 45 kg/m2] adults with a familial history of type 2 diabetes (diagnosis in a first or second degree relative).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>30</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnancy, use of carbohydrate or lipid-lowering medication, major illness/injury (acute or chronic), current smoker or use of nicotine replacement therapy or physical or major illness/physical problems (acute or chronic) that may limit their ability to participate in the intervention.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed envelopes containing order of conditions.</concealment>
    <sequence>An independent third party will prepare a computer-generated randomised sequence and sealed envelope containing the sequence.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Generalised linear mixed models with random intercepts will be used to compare the impact of each condition on the listed outcomes. We are currently in the process of verifying power calculations, this application will be updated prior to recruitment to include these calculations.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>16/05/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>15/08/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>25</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3065 - Fitzroy</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor John Hawley</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>215 Spring Street-Level 5
Centre for Exercise and Nutrition
Mary MacKillop Institute for Health Research
Melbourne, VIC, 3000
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Novo-Nordisk Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Tuborg Havnevej 19
2900 Hellerup</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Sweden</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor David Dunstan</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Baker IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute
PO Box 6492, Melbourne
Victoria 3004, Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Mr Samuel Pinto</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>215 Spring Street-Level 5
Centre for Exercise and Nutrition
Mary MacKillop Institute for Health Research
Melbourne, VIC, 3000</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Prolonged periods of sitting are prevalent in the modern office workplace and adversely impact on cardiometabolic risk factors including blood glucose and insulin concentrations. Acute aerobic exercise can transiently improve these risk factors. Evidence suggests that the pattern of exercise accumulation throughout a day and the timing of exercise in relation to meals modulates the beneficial effects it has on these markers. However, the role of exercise timing throughout a day on cardiometabolic risk factors has not been evaluated.

The aim of this study is to compare the impact of a morning and evening bout of aerobic exercise on blood glucose and insulin metabolism throughout a day of prolonged sitting. Young overweight or obese men and women with a familial history of type 2 diabetes will be recruited for this study. As this demographic are at an increased risk of developing type 2 diabetes they represent a relevant target population for the prevention of type 2 diabetes.

We hypothesise that aerobic exercise performed in the morning, prior to a prolonged bout of sitting and the ingestion of meals will more effectively improve glycaemic control compared to an identical evening bout.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Australian Catholic University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Manager, Ethics
c/o Office of the Deputy Vice Chancellor (Research)
Australian Catholic University - North Sydney Campus
PO Box 968
NORTH SYDNEY, NSW 2059</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/05/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016-75H</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/03/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>John Hawley</name>
      <address>215 Spring Street-Level 5
Centre for Exercise and Nutrition
Mary MacKillop Institute for Health Research
Melbourne, VIC, 3000</address>
      <phone>+61399533552</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>John.Hawley@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Samuel Pinto</name>
      <address>215 Spring Street-Level 5
Centre for Exercise and Nutrition
Mary MacKillop Institute for Health Research
Melbourne, VIC, 3000</address>
      <phone>+61417315194</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>samuel.pinto@myacu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>John Hawley</name>
      <address>215 Spring Street-Level 5
Centre for Exercise and Nutrition
Mary MacKillop Institute for Health Research
Melbourne, VIC, 3000</address>
      <phone>+61399533552</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>John.Hawley@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Samuel Pinto</name>
      <address>215 Spring Street-Level 5
Centre for Exercise and Nutrition
Mary MacKillop Institute for Health Research
Melbourne, VIC, 3000</address>
      <phone>+61417315194</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>samuel.pinto@myacu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>