<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335964">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/09/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/09/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000788077</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Exercise intervention trial for women with breast cancer related lymphoedema</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy and safety of high versus low intensity resistance exercise for management of lymphoedema in breast cancer survivors</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Lymphoedema secondary to breast cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Progressive supervised resistance exercises (e.g. upper and lower body resistance based exercises using weight machines and free weights) and aerobic exercise (e.g. walking, cycling, rowing etc.) twice weekly (60 minute sessions) for 12 weeks. These supervised sessions will be administered by an exercise physiologist and undertaken in small groups of participants (up to 8). Participants will continue their usual care for breast cancer and lymphoedema management for the duration of the intervention.

Two experimental groups will undertake different types of exercise interventions: (1) high intensity resistance training (HIGH), and (2) low intensity resistance training (LOW). The only difference between these groups will be the intensity of the resistance exercises. For HIGH, the intensity will be manipulated from 6-10 repetition maximum (i.e. the maximal weight that can be lifted 6-10 times) using 1-3 sets per exercise. For LOW, intensity will be manipulated from 15-20 repetition maximum (i.e. the maximal weight that can be lifted 15-20 times) using 1-3 sets per exercise.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants in the usual care delay exercise group will receive usual care for 12 weeks. At the completion of the usual care period participants will then receive the 12 week exercise intervention. Usual care will be determined on a case by case basis by the individuals participants oncologist and lymphoedema therapist.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lymphoedema Status and Associated Symptoms. Lymphoedema status (i.e. the amount of swelling in the upper extremity) will be assessed using standard objective measures including bioimpedance spectroscopy, arm circumference measurements and dual energy x-ray absorptiometry. Lymphoedema associated symptoms will be assessed using a modification of the Brief Pain Inventory.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 12 weeks (post-intervention)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Muscular Strength and Endurance. Maximal strength will be assessed using one-repetition maximum tests. Maximal grip strength will be tested using an isometric dynamometer. Muscle endurance will be assessed using a repetition maximum test (i.e. the maximal number of repetitions possible with 70% of one-repetition maximum)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 12 weeks (post-intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Range of Motion and Functional Ability.  Range of motion around the shoulder and elbow joints will be measured for affected and non-affected limbs using standard goniometric techniques. Functional ability of the upper body will be measured using the Disability of the Arm, Shoulder and Hand (DASH) questionnaire. Functional ability of the lower body will be measured using a repeated chair rise test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 12 weeks (post-intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life.  Quality of life will be assessed using the European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer Core Questionnaire (EORTC QLQ-C30) and breast cancer specific questionnaire (EORTC QLQ-BR23). The Functional Assessment of Chronic Illness Therapy B+4 (FACT-B+4) questionnaire will be utilised to specifically assess health-related quality of life for patients with breast cancer related lymphoedema.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 12 weeks (post-intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Clinical diagnosis of breast cancer related lymphoedema defined as at least a 10% inter-limb discrepancy in volume or circumference at the point of greatest visible difference.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any musculo-skeletal, cardiovascular or neurological disorder that could place the participant at risk of injury or illness resulting from the exercise.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomization by computer</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerized sequence generation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>6027</postcode>
    <postcode>2617</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Edith Cowan University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>270 Joondalup Drive
Joondalup, WA 6027</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Edith Cowan University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>270 Joondalup Drive
Joondalup, WA 6027</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Canberra</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University Drive
Bruce ACT 2617</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Canberra</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University Drive
Bruce ACT 2617</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study looks at the role of exercise in managing lymphoedema status and associated symptoms in women with breast cancer related lymphoedema.

Who is it for? 
You can join this study if you are a women who has a clinical diagnosis of lymphoedema secondary to breast cancer.

Trial details: 
Participants will be divided into three groups. Two groups will take part in progressive supervised resistance exercises performed at relatively higher or lower intensities (i.e. upper and lower body resistance based exercise using weight machines and free weights) twice weekly (60 minute sessions) for 12 weeks. The third group will receive usual care for 12 weeks and then will take part in a 12 week exercise program. 

Lymphoedema status (i.e. the amount of swelling in the upper extremity) will be assessed using standard objective measures including bioimpedance spectroscopy, arm circumference measurements and dual energy x-ray absorptiometry. Lymphoedema associated symptoms will be assessed using a modification of the Brief Pain Inventory. Muscle strength and endurance, shoulder and elbow range of motion, functional ability and quality of life will also be assessed.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Edith Cowan University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Edith Cowan University
Research Ethics
270 Joondalup Drive
Joondalup, WA 6027</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/08/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>5443 CORMIE</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Prue Cormie</name>
      <address>Edith Cowan University Health and Wellness Institute
270 Joondalup Drive
Joondalup WA 6027</address>
      <phone>+61 8 6304 3418</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.cormie@ecu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Prue Cormie</name>
      <address>Edith Cowan University Health and Wellness Institute
270 Joondalup Drive
Joondalup WA 6027</address>
      <phone>+61 8 6304 3418</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.cormie@ecu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Prue Cormie</name>
      <address>Edith Cowan University Health and Wellness Institute
270 Joondalup Drive
Joondalup WA 6027</address>
      <phone>+61 8 6304 3418</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.cormie@ecu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>