<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347901">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/01/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/01/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000021875</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of dairy-based high-protein, variable-carbohydrate diets and exercise on muscle maintenance and movement</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In overweight sedentary adults, is a high protein, dairy based calorie restricted diet combined with exercise, compared with high carbohydrate, adequate protein calorie restricted diet combined with exercise, more effective in maintaining skeletal muscle mass during weight loss</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1126-7965</utrn>
    <trialacronym>DAIRY-FIT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Sarcopenia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Modification of diet into two groups:
G1 = High dairy, high protein moderate carbohydrate (CHO) diet
G2 = High dairy, high protein, high CHO diet
Both groups will have their diet modified for a period of 16 weeks by a qualified dietitian. Group 1's (G1) diet will consist of foods that will make up 40% energy needs from Carbohydrates, 30% energy needs from Protein sources and 30% energy needs from Fat sources and will be individualised for each subject.  Group 2's (G2) diet will consist of foods that will make up 55% of energy needs from Carbohydrates, 30% energy needs from Protein sources and 15% energy needs from Fat sources and will be individualised for each subject.
During the 16 week dietary modification period, participants will complete 3 supervised and 3 unsupervised exercise sessions per week for the entire duration. The supervised exercise sessions will take place at RMIT University Bundoora by CERT3/4 qualified fitness instructors or equivalent.
The diets will not be provided to participants but the dietitian will work with each individual to ensure they achieve the required energy ratios. There are no set number of meals, again this is based on the individual.</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator group (G3) will undertake a healthy diet (high CHO, adequate protein) for 16 weeks and complete the same exercise regime as G1 and G2. The healthy diet will consist of 55% energy needs from Carbohydrates, 30% energy needs from Fat sources and 15% energy needs from Protein sources.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in body composition: lean mass (kg) and fat mass (kg) as measured by Dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry (DXA) and anthropometric measures</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline and at 8 and 16 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Strength and Cardio-respiratory fitness.
Strength will be assessed using four common resistance exercises (seated leg extension, hamstring curls, seated row and chest-press) through 1 repetition maximum (1RM) tests. Cardio-respiratory fitness will be measured through a VO2 max test where a facemask and heart rate monitor are worn throughout an increasing intensity test to fatigue.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline and at 8 and 16 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood profile (lipids; glucose and insulin (HOMA index)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline and at 8 and 16 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Daily energy expenditure will be measured using Sensewear armbands which measures motion, accelerometry, galvanic skin response, skin temperature and heat flux to give a measure of energy expenditure over several days</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline and at 8 and 16 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Body Mass Index (BMI) between 27-40 kg/m2 i.e. classified as overweight, class I Obese or class II Obese; Sedentary</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>35</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>59</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Metabolic risk factors (hypercholesterolemia, hyperinsulinemia, and hyperglycemia, hypertenisive), heart and other organ disease, orthopaedic injury, gastrointestinal disease, clinically diagnosed dairy protein allergy, clinically diagnosed lactose intolerance.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomization will be initially stratified by baseline BMI values (27–29, 30–34, and 35–40 kg/m2) and sex. Subsequently, simple randomisation by roll of dice within the stratified segregation will be used to allocate individuals to each of the 3 groups. This will ensure that an equal number of subjects from each category of BMI will be allocated to a dietary intervention group.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>12/03/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>3/06/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>90</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>115</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3083</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor John Hawley</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Centre for Exercise and Nutrition
Mary MacKillop Institute for Health Research
Australian Catholic University
Level 5, 215 Spring Street
Melbourne VIC 3000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Dairy Health &amp; Nutrition Consortium</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Dairy Innovation Australia
671 Sneydes Road
Werribee, Victoria 3030</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Louise Burke</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of Sports Nutrition
Australian Institute of Sport
PO Box 176
BELCONNEN 
ACT 2616</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Vernon Coffey</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Exercise Metabolism Group
School of Medical Sciences
Building 223.2.51
RMIT University
PO Box 71
Bundoora
Victoria 3083</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Ms Evelyn Parr</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Centre for Exercise and Nutrition
Mary MacKillop Institute for Health Research
Australian Catholic University
Level 5, 215 Spring Street
Melbourne VIC 3000</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Stuart Phillips</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Ivor Wynne Centre, Room E210
Department of Kinesiology
McMaster University
1280 Main Street West
Hamilton, ON L8S 4K1</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Canada</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The willingness of the majority of Australians to adopt a sedentary lifestyle accompanied by an excess energy intake underpins the current epidemic of lifestyle diseases. In an effort to prevent the rise of inactivity-related conditions, medical and health professionals prescribe energy-restricted weight-loss programmes combined with increased physical activity as a means to reduce body mass (weight) and improve health outcomes. However, typical diet-induced weight loss leads to an imbalance in body composition that reduces an individuals functional capacity (i.e., movement and activity patterns) and increases their susceptibility to metabolic disorders. Specifically, the complex interactions between elevated levels of body fat and a reduced muscle size result in a high fat: muscle ratio, leading to a cascade of events that accelerate pre-existing health conditions (i.e., sarcopenia) and simultaneously predispose an individual to further (new) health risks. 
At present, the optimal diet to achieve weight loss and promote favourable body composition changes in overweight adults remains highly controversial. More information is needed to determine the effects of different diets on energy metabolism, energy balance and body composition. Indeed, the biggest concern for the majority of Australian adults is how to lose fat mass while preserving muscle mass and the health benefits that accrue from a nutrient-rich high-quality protein diet and physical activity. Accordingly, the aim of this project is to discover and characterise the best composition of mildly energy restricted high-protein (dairy-based), variable-carbohydrate diets consumed in association with resistance training to improve health.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.rmit.edu.au/browse;ID=6b379xz4gl2a;STATUS=A;SECTION=2;PAGE_AUTHOR=Julia%20Wong</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Parr, E.B., Coffey, V.G., Cato, L.E., Phillips, S.M., Burke, L.M., Hawley, J.A. A randomized trial of high-dairy-protein, variable-carbohydrate diets and exercise on body composition in adults with obesity, Obesity (Silver Spring), 2016, 24(5): 1035-45.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>RMIT Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research &amp; Innovation, 
RMIT University, 
GPO Box 2476V, 
Melbourne, 3001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/01/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>76/11</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/12/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>John Hawley</name>
      <address>Centre for Exercise and Nutrition, Mary MacKillop Institute for Health Research, Australian Catholic University, Level 5, 215 Spring Street, Melbourne VIC 3000</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9953 3552</phone>
      <fax>+61-3-9467 8181</fax>
      <email>john.hawley@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>John Hawley</name>
      <address>Centre for Exercise and Nutrition, Mary MacKillop Institute for Health Research, Australian Catholic University, Level 5, 215 Spring Street, Melbourne VIC 3000</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9953 3552</phone>
      <fax>+61-3-9467 8181</fax>
      <email>john.hawley@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Evelyn Parr</name>
      <address>Centre for Exercise and Nutrition, Mary MacKillop Institute for Health Research, Australian Catholic University, Level 5, 215 Spring Street, Melbourne VIC 3000</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9230 8278</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>evelyn.parr@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>John Hawley</name>
      <address>Centre for Exercise and Nutrition, Mary MacKillop Institute for Health Research, Australian Catholic University, Level 5, 215 Spring Street, Melbourne VIC 3000</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9953 3552</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>john.hawley@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>