<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362276">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/03/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/03/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000340831</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can pre-operative Ivabradine and/or Atorvastatin prevent heart injury following surgery for neck of femur fracture in elderly patients?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial of Ivabradine and Atorvastatin in emergent orthopaedic lower limb surgery for neck of femur fracture in elderly patients: a mechanistic study of peri-operative myocardial injury and its prevention using computed tomography coronary plaque imaging and novel biomarkers of cardiovascular stress and lipid metabolism</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1129-3244</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Coronary artery disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Fractures</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Peri-operative myocardial injury</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fractures</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients will be randomised using a computerised block randomisation method with blocks of variable sizes to ensure true randomisation and equal numbers in each treatment group. Patients will be randomized to one of four groups in a 1:1:1:1 ratio.
1)	No treatment (control group)
2)	Atorvastatin  orally 80 mg daily till discharge from acute hospital care (to home / rehab) 
3)	Ivabradine 5mg orally  twice daily till discharge from acute hospital care (to home / rehab) 
4)	Ivabradine 5 mg orally twice daily  and atorvastatin orally  80 mg daily till discharge from acute hospital care (to home / rehab) 

Treatment would start on randomization prior to surgery which would be as soon as practicable after admission.</interventions>
    <comparator>No treatment</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The frequency (binary outcome) and magnitude (continuous variable) of new myocardial injury following emergent orthopaedic surgery for lower limb fracture as assessed by troponin I, on a per protocol basis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 0
Day 1
Day 2
Day 3</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Myocardial infarction according to the universal definition</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 3</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean HR over 48 hours Holter monitoring postoperatively</outcome>
      <timepoint>48 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence and duration of AF over 48 Holter monitoring postoperatively</outcome>
      <timepoint>48 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum assays of NT-proBNP, MR-proANP, MR-proADM and CT-proET-1. Samples would be stored at negative 80 degrees prior to testing at external laboratory.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 0,1,2,3</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum assays of sPLA2 and Lp-PLA2 mass and activity</outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 0,1</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Platelet activation as measured by VerifyNow P2Y12 assay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Preoperative (day 0)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Death</outcome>
      <timepoint>In hospital
30 days
12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stroke</outcome>
      <timepoint>In hospital
30 days
12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptomatic bradycardia or heart block requiring cessation of ivabradine</outcome>
      <timepoint>In hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Liver enzyme elevation &gt; 3 times the upper limits of normal</outcome>
      <timepoint>In Hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) Age greater than 60 years
2) Neck of femur fracture with planned surgical treatment within 48 hours</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) Current ivabradine use
2) Patients who do not undergo surgical treatment for lower limb fracture for any reason. If such patients were initially enrolled they will be excluded from the analysis, i.e per protocol analysis.
3) Heart rate &lt; 65bpm prior to randomisation
4) Known liver disease or liver enzymes &gt; 3 times the higher limits of normal
5) Pre-operative troponin elevation
6) Artificial pacemakers, sick sinus syndrome or complete heart block
7) Concomittant CYP3A4 inhibitors  ketoconazole, macrolides, cyclosporin, gestodene, antiretrovirals</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients will be randomised using a computerised block randomisation method with blocks of variable sizes to ensure ‘true’ randomisation and equal numbers in each treatment group using sealed opaque envelopes. Patients will be randomized to one of four groups in a 1:1:1:1 ratio
1)	No treatment (control group)
2)	Atorvastatin  80 mg daily
3)	Ivabradine twice daily (as per protocol)
4)	Ivabradine twice daily (as per protocol) and atorvastatin 80 mg daily</concealment>
    <sequence>computerised block randomisation method with blocks of variable sizes to ensure ‘true’ randomisation and equal numbers in each treatment group using sealed opaque envelopes.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Factorial</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/04/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Northern hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Cardiology Department
The Northern hospital
185 Cooper Street
Epping vic 3076</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Northern hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>185 Cooper Street
Epping Vic 3076</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In patients undergoing urgent orthopaedic surgery , Heart muscle damage around the time of surgery(perioperative myocardial Injury-PMI) can occure in 52.9% of patients shown in a study conducted in the northern hospital. The majority of these patients were asymptomatic, with only 9.8% of patients meeting the universal definition criteria for myocardial infarction (heart attack). One year mortality was dramatically increased across the board in those with any troponin(a blood test showing heart muscle damage) elevation (37% versus 2.1%)after the surgery.
The exact mechanisms of PMI  are not well understood, however two broad theories are postulated; myocardial(heart muscle) stress and cholestrol plaque rupture. Prevention of myocardial stress and/or plaque rupture may reduce the incidence of PMI and have been the subject of multiple studies.

 This study is going to assess if Ivabradine(a medication lowers the heart rate without affecting the blood pressure) will reduce the rate and magnitude of PMI following emergent lower limb orthopaedic surgery by reducing heart rate and attenuating catecholamine(stress hormons) induced tachycardia(fast heart rate) after operation and to assess if it will correlate with a reduction in biomarkers of cardiovascular stress(blood tests) as measured by NT-proBNP, MR-proANP, MR-proADM and CT-proET-1 and if it will reduce the incidence and burden of atrial fibrillation after the surgery.

Also this study is going to assess if Atorvastatin(a medication lowers the cholestrol and inflamatiom) will reduce the rate and magnitude of PMI following emergent lower limb orthopaedic surgery and if it will correlate with a reduction in sPLA2 and Lp-PLA2 mass and activity(markers of cholesterol plaque burden and inflammation ).

Also we will assess if that patients with higher measures of platelet function(aggregation and reactivity) before and after surgery will have an increased incidence and magnitude of PMI and if  patients with a higher burden of atherosclerotic(chorestrol plaque) disease as measured by CT coronary calcium scores( a ct scan messuring amount of calcium in arteries supplying blood to the heart) will have a higher incidence and magnitidue of PMI.

And finally to assess if that the benefit from reduction in the incidence and magnitude of PMI by Ivabradine and Atorvastatin is derived primarily in patients with greater atherosclerotic (cholesterol Plaque) burden as measured by higher CT coronary calcium scores.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Northern Health Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>185 Cooper street
Epping Vic 3076</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/03/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Prof William Van Gaal</name>
      <address>Director of Cardiology 
Northern hospital
185 Cooper Street
Epping Vic 3076</address>
      <phone>+61384058154</phone>
      <fax>+61384058405</fax>
      <email>william.vangaal@nh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Prof William Van Gaal</name>
      <address>Director of Cardiology 
Northern hospital
185 Cooper Street
Epping Vic 3076</address>
      <phone>+61384058154</phone>
      <fax>+61384058405</fax>
      <email>william.vangaal@nh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Vivek Mutha</name>
      <address>Cardiology Department
Northern hospital
185 Cooper Street
Epping Vic 3076</address>
      <phone>+61384058154</phone>
      <fax>+61386779769</fax>
      <email>vivek.mutha@nh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>