<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368708">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/06/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/06/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000654550</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Assessment of Citramel in Patients with Cystic Fibrosis </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Double-blind Randomised Placebo-controlled Cross-Over Study of the Effects of  Citramel on the Signs and Symptoms of Cystic Fibrosis </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1171-1611 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>BE10-1001</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cystic Fibrosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human Genetics and Inherited Disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Cystic fibrosis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Citramel - an aqueous solution of sodium citrate (16.18 mg/mL), citric acid (0.046 mg/mL) and ammonium chloride (4.12 mg/mL). Administered by aerosol twice daily (morning and night) for 28 days. This study is a randomised crossover design and there is a washout period of 14 days before the second study treatment is started.

For patients being treated with Tobramycin: this should be administered at least ten minutes after completion of the inhalation of study medication is inhaled. Note that the nebulizing equipment provided for the study medications should NOT be used to administer tobramycin. </interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo: normal saline. Administered by aerosol twice daily (morning and night) for 28 days. Patients will have a 14 day washout period between receiving Citramel and 28 days treatment with placebo in a randomised cross-over design. For patients being treated with Tobramycin: this should be administered at least ten minutes after completion of the inhalation of study medication is inhaled. Note that the nebulizing equipment provided for the study medications should NOT be used to administer tobramycin.
Compliance will be assessed by checking the vials returned by study participants. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety as measured by adverse events, Laboratory tests, vital signs and patient diary </outcome>
      <timepoint>Screening/baseline, Day 3 or 4, weeks 1, 2, 3 and 4 of each of the two treatment periods. Adverse events also assessed at two weeks post last dose of Week 4 of each of the two treatment periods. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Absolute change in FEV1 between Citramel inhalation and placebo inhalation </outcome>
      <timepoint>at the end of each treatment period (Day 28) compared with Baseline for that treatment phase.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Spirometry measures (FVC and FEV1 % of predicted) between Citramel inhalation and placebo inhalation </outcome>
      <timepoint>at the end of each treatment period (Day 28) compared with Baseline for that treatment phase</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incremental AUC of the spirometry measures (FVC and FEV1 % of predicted) between Citramel inhalation and placebo inhalation. </outcome>
      <timepoint>From baseline to day 28 for each treatment phase</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rheology assessments of sputum samples between Citramel inhalation and placebo inhalation Rheology assessments include in vitro ciliary transportability (MCTR), mucus hydration (% solids), and in vitro cough transportability (CTR). Sputum production from CF patients may be very variable. The rheological analysis may only be conducted if a suitable set and number of sputum samples are obtained.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From baseline to end of each treatment phase (day 28)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of the sputum volume between Citramel inhalation and placebo inhalation. Sputum volume will determined using a measuring cylinder.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of each treatment period (Day 28) compared with Baseline for that treatment phase</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of the number and type of organisms cultured (using standard microbiology laboratory procedures) from sputum samples between Citramel inhalation and placebo inhalation</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of each treatment period (day 28) compared with Baseline for that treatment phase</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of the Participant self-assessment of efficacy between Citramel inhalation and placebo inhalation (10cm visual analogue (VAS) scale)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of each treatment period (Day 28) compared with Baseline for that treatment phase</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of CFQ-R questionnaire between Citramel and placebo</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of each treatment period (Day 28) compared with Baseline for that treatment phase</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of CFTSSD questionnaire between Citramel and placebo</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of each treatment period (Day 28) compared with Baseline for that treatment phase</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of Participant self-assessment of satisfaction with the treatment and tolerability of the treatment. Five-point likert rating scales will be used with options from 'very unsatisfied / very poor' to 'very satisfied / very good' </outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of each treatment period (Day 28) compared with Baseline for that treatment phase</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Confirmed diagnosis of cystic fibrosis; aged at least 16 years who provide written informed consent; sexually active females must use contraception; stable medications; FEV1 between 40-100% of normal range. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Clinically significant co-existing disease; current or previous clinically significant smoking history; ECG or blood pressure abnormalities; use of a bronchodilator within 12hrs prior to bronchodilator challenge at screening; renal impairment; elevated liver enzymes; </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>After obtaining consent and confirming eligibility, the participant will be enrolled in the study. Each participant will receive both Citramel and placebo in a cross-over study
design. All study staff will remain blinded; Citramel and matching placebo inhalations will be provided by the Sponsor. Individual randomisation envelopes will be provided in case the identity of study drug administered to a participant for a treatment phase needs to be known.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomization by computer</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A sample size of 20 completed participants will provide &gt;80% power to detect an effect size for the differential change in the absolute FEV1 with Citramel compared with placebo of 0.70 or more as statistically significant (two-tailed a=0.05). Assuming the standard deviation of the differential change is 0.5L the study is adequately powered to detect a difference of approximately 0.35L. Therefore approx. 24 patients will be randomised to allow for 4 patients to drop-out before completing the study.


The primary analysis of study efficacy measures will be performed using the EP population. Additional analyses of all efficacy measures using the ITT will also be performed if the EPP is &lt; 80 % of the ITT population.
Standard descriptive statistics (including means, standard deviations, standard errors, medians, ranges and frequencies), graphs, and participant data listings will be used to summarize the baseline demographic and clinical characteristics, and the efficacy and safety data at relevant time-points. Tabular and graphical summaries will represent
participant groups. Participant data listings will present data by treatment group.

Primary Safety Analyses
Adverse events over the period of the study will be individually listed by treatment groups. The incidences and percentages of individuals experiencing AEs within each treatment group will be summarized by System Organ Class (SOC) with further summaries by severity and relatedness (causality) categories. The more common AEs maybe
compared between treatment groups using Fishers exact tests. The safety analyses will be performed using the Safety population. 

Primary Efficacy Analyses
The primary analyses will compare the changes in the absolute FEV1 between the two randomised treatments. A general linear model will be used for this comparison with treatment sequence included as a between-subjects term in the model. Individual group changes and the difference in the changes will be summarised with 95 % confidence intervals. A two-sided p-value of 0.05 will be used to indicate statistical
significance.

Secondary Efficacy Analyses
The secondary efficacy analyses will compare the changes in the absolute FEV1 between the two randomised treatments. A general linear model will be used for this comparison with treatment sequence included as a between-subjects term in the model. Individual group changes and the difference in the changes will be summarised with 95 % confidence
intervals. A two-sided p-value of 0.05 will be used to indicate statistical significance.
The questionnaire, self-assessment data collected at weeks 4 and 12 will be compared using a general linear model including a between subjects term for treatment sequence. Individual group means and the difference in the means will be summarised with 95 % confidence intervals. A two-sided p-value of 0.05 will be used to indicate statistical significance.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>16/05/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>16/05/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/03/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>10/05/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>24</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>28</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>25/07/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Canterbury</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Otago</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Waikato</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Breathe Easy Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Ground Floor, Shed 20,
139 Quay Street,
Princes Wharf
Auckland 1010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Breathe easy Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Ground Floor, Shed 20,
139 Quay Street,
Princes Wharf
Auckland 1010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NZVIF (New Zealand Venture Investment Fund)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Unit 1B, Ascot Office Park, 93-95 Ascot Ave
Green Lane, Auckland 1051, New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a research study to evaluate Citramel inhalation. It is a double-blind, placebo, cross-over design to assess the safety, tolerability and efficacy of Citramel in approx. 24 cystic fibrosis patients.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Central Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>1 The Terrace
C/- MEDSAFE, Level 6, Deloitte House
10 Brandon Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/07/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>14/CEN/89</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Chris Wynne</name>
      <address>Christchurch Clinical Studies Trust (CCST) 31 Tuam Street Christchurch 8011</address>
      <phone>+64 3 372 9477</phone>
      <fax>+64 3 372 9478</fax>
      <email>Chris@ccst.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Andrea Miller</name>
      <address>Breathe Easy Ltd, Whitecliff College of Arts and Design Building, 24 Balfour Road, Parnell, Auckland 1052, New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 27 770 1699  </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andreajmiller@gmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Andrea Miller</name>
      <address>Breathe Easy Ltd, Whitecliff College of Arts and Design Building, 24 Balfour Road, Parnell, Auckland 1052, New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 27 770 1699  </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andreajmiller@gmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michelle Lockhart</name>
      <address>51 Woodside Road, Mt Eden, Auckland 1024</address>
      <phone>+64 21 665 947</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michellelockhart@xtra.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>