<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371198">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001051437</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised, double-blind, placebo controlled trial to examine the effects of total oestradiol depletion on bone microstructure and the efficacy of denosumab in preventing microstructural bone decay in premenopausal women with early breast cancer 
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy study to evaluate denosumab compared to placebo in preventing microstructural bone decay in premenopausal women receiving total oestradiol depletion therapy for early breast cancer 
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>premenopausal osteoporosis </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>breast cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other endocrine disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoporosis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Denosumab 60mg subcutaneous injection at 6-month intervals for a 12-month study duration administered by trial investigator. </interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo - normal saline subcutaneous injection at 6-month intervals for a 12-month study duration administered by trial investigator. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>bone microstructure measured using high-resolution peripheral quantitative computed tomography</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months from baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>areal bone mineral density (lumbar spine, femoral neck, hip and non-dominant distal radius) as measured by dual energy X-ray absorptiometry (DEXA)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>bone remodeling markers (beta carboxy-terminal type I collagen telopeptide (CTX) and procollagen type 1 amino-terminal propeptide (P1NP) by serum assay</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>lean mass measured by DEXA</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>homeostatic model assessment of insulin resistance derived from measurement of fasting plasma glucose and fasting serum insulin. </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>lipid levels by serum assay</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>quality of life assessed using validated questionnaires (MENQOL and FACT-B/ES)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>visceral fat volume and distribution measured by DEXA</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months from baseline </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>subcutaneous fat volume and distribution measured by DEXA</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-	Premenopausal women with oestrogen-receptor positive, non-metastatic breast cancer (TxNxM0) based on documented pathological and radiological evaluation. Menopausal status will be defined clinically at the diagnosis of breast cancer. 

Premenopausal: a regular cycle in the last 3 months prior to diagnosis of breast cancer
Perimenopausal: absent cycles for 3-12 months 
Postmenopausal: absent cycles for 12 months or more

-	About to commence treatment with ovarian suppression with a view to subsequent aromatase inhibition as determined by the treating oncologist 

-	Endocrine therapy intended for at least 12 months 

-	Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) 0 and 1 

-	Able to personally read and understand the Participant Information and Consent Form and provide written, signed and dated informed consent to participate in the study 

-	Able and willing to meet all protocol-required procedures and visits</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-	Bone mineral density T-score at the lumbar spine/hip/femoral neck &lt;-2.0SD 

-	Pre-existing minimal trauma fractures (excluding fractures of fingers, toes, hands, feet and skull)

Current evidence or prior history of any of the following: 

-	Metabolic bone disorder(s) 

-	Drugs for treatment of bone-related disorders

-	Prolonged glucocorticoid use for 2 or more weeks continuously in the past 6 months 

-	Significant inflammatory or malabsorptive condition(s) 

-	Osteonecrosis or osteomyelitis of the jaw 

-	Atypical femoral fracture(s)

-	Diabetes mellitus 

-	History of any solid organ or bone marrow transplant 

-	Malignancy within the last 5 years (except breast cancer and non-melanoma skin cancers)

Abnormalities of the following per central laboratory reference ranges: 

-	Hypo/hypercalcaemia 

-	Hypo/hyperparathyroidism 

-	Renal impairment (eGFR &lt;45ml/min/1.73m2)

-	25-hydroxy vitamin D deficiency (&lt;12nmol/L). Repletion will be allowed and participants may be re-screened. 

-	Self-reported recreational drug use or alcohol dependence within 12 months prior to screening 

-	Pregnancy 

-	History or evidence of any other clinically significant disorder, condition or disease that in the opinion of the study investigator would pose a risk to participant safety or interfere with the study evaluation, procedures or completion
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomised

Central randomisation by the Austin Health clinical trials pharmacy, supervised by the senior clinical trials pharmacist. Dispensing pharmacists, trial investigators (who will responsible for administration of the drug/placebo) and participants will be blinded to intervention allocation. </concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>1:1 allocation </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>18/08/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>8/09/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>114</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Associate Professor Mathis Grossmann </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Melbourne - Austin Health 
Level 7 Lance Townsend Building, Austin Health, 145 Studley Road, Heidelberg, Victoria, 3084, Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Melbourne</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of Melbourne - Austin Health 
145 Studley Road, Heidelberg, Victoria 3084, Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>NA</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>NA</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of this study is to compare the efficacy of denosumab treatment with placebo in preventing bone decay in premenopausal women being treated with ovarian suppression and aromatase inhibition for breast cancer. 

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to enrol in this trial if you are a premenopausal woman aged 18 to 50 who has been diagnosed with oestrogen-receptor positive, non-metastatic breast cancer (TxNxM0) for which you are scheduled to begin ovarian suppression and aromatase inhibition therapy which is intended to last for at least 12 months.

Study details
All participants enrolled in this trial will be randomly allocated (by chance) to receive either denosumab once every 6 months by subcutaneous injection or to receive placebo once every 6 months for a 12-month study period. 

Participants will be followed-up at 6 and 12 months after starting the trial drug/placebo with scans, blood tests and questionnaires which will be used to measure bone density and structure, body composition, blood markers of bone health and cardiovascular risk and quality of life.

It is hoped that the findings from this trial will provide information on the extent of bone decay which occurs as a result of ovarian suppression and aromatase inhibition therapy, and the efficacy of denosumab in preventing this decay in premenopausal women with oestrogen-receptor positive breast cancer.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Austin Health 
145 Studley Road
Heidelberg 
Victoria 3084</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/08/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC Reference Number: HREC/16/Austin/136</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/04/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Mathis Grossmann </name>
      <address>Level 7 Lance Townsend Building, Austin Health, 145 Studley Road, Heidelberg, Victoria 3084, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61394965000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mathisg@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sabashini Ramchand </name>
      <address>Austin Health, 145 Studley Road, Heidelberg, Victoria 3084, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61478168578</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sabashini.ramchand@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sabashini Ramchand </name>
      <address>Austin Health, 145 Studley Road, Heidelberg, Victoria 3084, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61478168578</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sabashini.ramchand@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>