<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82959">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/07/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/07/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000334303</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Role Of Community Pharmacy in Post Hospital Management of Patients Initiated on Warfarin</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Development of a post hospital discharge pathway for adults taking warfarin which will result in an improved model of care compared to the current process.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>RFT-04</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Medication misadventure reduction in patients discharged from hospital after being commenced on warfarin or whose warfarin treatment was disrupted due to hospitalisation.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haematological diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A proposed best practice discharge pathway for patients either initiated on warfarin in hospital or whose treatment with warfarin was disrupted due to hospitalisation. 
Currently, the usual management of patients taking warfarin who are discharged from hospital into the community involves providing the patient with a medication discharge sheet and notifying the general practitioner (GP) of the patient's condition requiring warfarin, their warfarin dose, their International Normalised Ratio (INR) at discharge and recommended dosage regimen for warfarin for that patient. Patient's routinely have follow-up pathology tests organised by their GP to monitor their INR levels and these are normally more frequent to begin with but taper to a once monthly pathology check once the patient's INR  has stabilised. Unfortunately incomplete or misdirected information together with patient misunderstanding have resulted in inadequate or incorrect patient care. Often community pharmacies are overlooked in the discharge process.
 This study will include, in addition to this usual care, a home follow-up medication review by an accredited pharmacist with an emphasis on patient warfarin education. Additionally a trained accredited pharmacist will take up to three measurements of the INR, two or three days apart, using a portable monitor. This will occur within the first 10 days of the patient's discharge. Feed back to the patient's GP will be provided in each instance. A final visit 90 days after discharge will be used to assess outcomes. Thirty suitable and consenting patients will then be trained to use a point of care monitor to measure their INR in the home. Result obtained will be sent to their GP on a weekly basis over 90 days for his consideration.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will be adult patients initiated on warfarin or whose warfarin treatment was disrupted due to hospital admission and will receive, in addition to the usual care discharge pathway, one visit from a research pharmacist at day 8 post discharge when the INR will be measured. Any issues the pharmacist may discover at this time will be discussed with the patient's GP. This group will also be assessed at 90 days post discharge.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The development of a model supporting the role of the pharmacy profession in improving the transition between hospital and community-based care for patients taking warfarin. The evaluation which will be used to inform the development of this model will include process indicators and clinical outcomes from the study such as INR control and bleeding events in addition to participant satisfaction, determined by a questionnaire and the reconciliation of qualitative interviews and focus group sessions with key stakeholders.</outcome>
      <timepoint>90 days after discharge</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To demonstrate that the proposed Patient Self Monitoring (PSM) model is feasible and that patients, their general practitioners and pharmacists are satisfied with this model of care. Clinical outcomes, such as the time of the INR in therapeutic range (TTR), and participant and stakeholder feedback (GP's and community pharmacists) via questionnaires will inform this part of the study. Issues raised will allow the refinement of the PSM phase of this trial.</outcome>
      <timepoint>180 days after discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Minimum age :18years
Maximum age: no limit
Gender: both males and females
Health: must have had their warfarin treatment disrupted due to hospitalisation or have been initiated on warfarin.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Language; Non English speaking
Other studies: Participation in a concurrent other study.
Demographics; not-home based on discharge or no GP
Dementia.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>400</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>7000</postcode>
    <postcode>5000</postcode>
    <postcode>5042</postcode>
    <postcode>5600</postcode>
    <postcode>2139</postcode>
    <postcode>2065</postcode>
    <postcode>2500</postcode>
    <postcode>7320</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Unit for Medication Outcomes Research and Education, University of Tasmania</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Unit for Medication Outcomes Research and Education,
Tasmanian School of Pharmacy
University of Tasmania
105 Churchill Ave
Sandy Bay  7005</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Health and Ageing via the Fourth Community Pharmacy Agreement  Research and Development Program</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>P.O. Box 9848
Canberra
ACT   2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Faculty of Pharmacy, University of Sydney</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Faculty of Pharmacy,
University of Sydney,
NSW  2006</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of Wollongong</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>University of Wollongong
Wollongong 
NSW  2522</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of South Australia</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Pharmacy and Medical Sciences
University of South Australia
Adelaide   5839</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Warfarin is a difficult drug to manage safely especially when commenced. The Australian population is ageing and the use of warfarin particularly in the elderly as a treatment for stroke prevention is increasing. Furthermore changing treatment trends have resulted in shorter hospital stays which has increased the risk for warfarin patients who are being discharged before achieving a stable and effective warfarin level. This study will compare a control group following the usual care post discharge pathway with an intervention group receiving the proposed best practice discharge pathway. This will include a home medication review from an accredited pharmacist and follow-up checking of the INR of patients using a portable monitor within their home. Result will be referred to the patient's GP for evaluation. Outcomes such as bleeding and clotting events as well as unplanned hospital re-admission will be compared between the two groups. A small group of thirty of the intervention patients will, if consenting and able, be trained to perform self monitoring of the INR in their homes. The results obtained will be forwarded to their GP on a weekly basis for evaluation and possible warfarin dosage adjustment.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.anticoagulation.com.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>EC00337</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/06/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Gregory Peterson</name>
      <address>UMORE
The School of Pharmacy
University of Tasmania
Private Bag 83
Hobart    7001</address>
      <phone>03 62262197</phone>
      <fax>03 62267627</fax>
      <email>G.Peterson@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Geoff Hill</name>
      <address>UMORE
The School of Pharmacy
University of Tasmania
Private Bag 83
Hobart    7001</address>
      <phone>03 62261024</phone>
      <fax>03 62267627</fax>
      <email>geoffh@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Geoff Hill</name>
      <address>UMORE
The School of Pharmacy
University of Tasmania
Private Bag 83
Hobart    7001</address>
      <phone>03 62261024</phone>
      <fax>03 62267627</fax>
      <email>geoffh@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>