<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82587">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/02/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/02/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000074392</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Despatch Trial: DElivering Stroke Prevention for patients with ATrial fibrillation: a Cluster randomised controlled trial in a primary Health care setting.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Does a multifaceted educational intervention targetting general practitioners increase anticoagulant prescribing in patients over the age of 65 with atrial fibrillation compared with evidence-based guidelines? A cluster randomised controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Despatch</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Atrial Fibrillation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Despatch is a multifaceted, tailored educational intervention to redress noted barriers to the translation of best evidence into clinical practice relevant to the management of atrial fibrillation. Despatch will consist of the following components:
a) decisional support through a specifically created Stop Stroke specialist tele-service.  b) Academic detailing: The Stop-Stroke members will include nurses with training in stroke medicine who will be employed as academic detailers.  Academic detailing sessions will be delivered via three telephone sessions. 
c) GP, patient and practice decision tools 

The intervention will be delivered over a 12-month period after GP randomisation. 

Outcomes will be assessed using data collected from patient medical records.</interventions>
    <comparator>GPs randomised to a the Control will receive evidence-based guidelines by mail 

Outcomes will be assessed using data collected from patient medical records.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients over the age of 65 with a diagnosis of atrial fibrillation who have been prescribed warfarin.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1) Note of a prescription at any time during the 12-months after GP randomisation.  
2) Note of a prescription current at 12-months post-randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients prescribed antithrombotic treatment judged as "appropriate" according to stroke risk using a validated evidence-based risk stratification scheme and evidence-based guidelines</outcome>
      <timepoint>1) Note of an "appropriate" prescription at any time from time of GP randomisation up to 12-months after GP randomisation.  
2) Appropriate antithrombotic treatment current at 12-months post-randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of time patients are on warfarin.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From time of GP randomisation up to 12-months post-randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time on warfarin: (survival analysis) Time from "initiation"  of warfarin until ceasation (or end of follow-up period) will be calculated.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured over 12-months from GP randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients over the age of 65 who are receiving appropriate antithrombotic treatment. The appropriateness of warfarin will be judged according to the "quality control" of anticoagulation as assessed using standardised criteria and definitions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12-months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients with a record of having experienced an ischaemic Stroke</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients with a record of having experienced a Haemorrhagic stroke</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients with a record of having experienced a stroke, (type not otherwise specified)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients with a record of having experienced "minor" bleeding. Classification of bleeding using standardised definitions applied in previous clinical trials.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients with a record of having experienced "major bleeding".  
Classification of bleeding using standardised definitions applied in previous clinical trials.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients with a record of having experienced any cerebrovascular event (ischaemic stroke, haemorrhagic stroke, stroke not otherwise specified)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>This is a cluster randomised controlled trial with general practices designated the unit of randomisation.  Outcome measures will be assessed using patient data derived from medical records. 

Inclusion criteria: 
1) GPs with a practice location within Sydney Metropolitan Area. 
2) GPs must utilise an electronic data-base for issuing prescriptions and recording patient information (sex, age, contact details).

Inclusion criteria for patients: 
1) Aged older than 65 years
2) Ability to provide consent for medical record audit.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>N/A</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria for GPs: 

GPs engaged primarily in "special interest practice" with limited contact of elderly patients (&gt; 65 years of age) will be considerd ineligible to participate.

GPs in part-time practice (2 days a week or less) will initially be considered ineligible. However, this ineligibility criterion will be reviewed depending on the rate of recruitment of GPs and feasibility of recruitment.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>In this study, the units of randomisation are general practices.  

The randomisation will be performed by biostaticians from the NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre who are otherwise not involved in the study and therefore have not been involved in participant recruitment.</concealment>
    <sequence>The exact sequence of randomisation will be determined by the biostatistician. At a minimum, permuted block randomisation will be performed using random block sizes.  Randomisation will be stratified by practice size (that is, by the number of GPs per cluster)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/12/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>2000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>2000</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>NHMRC</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>National Health &amp; Medical Research Council, Level 5, 20 Allara Street
Canberra ACT 2601</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health &amp; Medical Research Council, Level 5, 20 Allara Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Non-valvular atrial fibrillation (NVAF) is a common heart condition associated with a major risk of fatal and disabling stroke. Inexpensive anticoagulant medication has been proven to reduce all-cases of death and stroke in people with NVAF.  

Anticoagulant treatment for NVAF is substantially underused resulting in avoidable patient deaths and disabling stroke. This study seeks to optimise the management of NVAF in general practice.  

We are developing an educational program for general practitioners which we hypothesis will increase the number of people with NVAF over the age of 65 who are prescribed anticoagulant medication.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of New South Wales, Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The University of New South Wales
KENSINGTON UNSW NSW 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/05/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC 07068</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Melina Gattellari</name>
      <address>SSWAHS, Division of Population Health
Locked Bag 7008
LIVERPOOL NSW 1871</address>
      <phone>61 2 9828 6914</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Melina.Gattellari@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Melina Gattellari</name>
      <address>SSWAHS, Division of Population Health
Locked Bag 7008
LIVERPOOL NSW 1871</address>
      <phone>61 2 9828 6914</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Melina.Gattellari@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Melina Gattellari</name>
      <address>SSWAHS, Division of Population Health
Locked Bag 7008
LIVERPOOL NSW 1871</address>
      <phone>61 2 9828 6914</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Melina.Gattellari@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>