<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369868">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/01/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/05/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000583448</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of short sprints during exercise on blood glucose management in Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The benefits of sprinting for improving blood glucose management in individuals with Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study will follow a randomised crossover design. On three occasions, the participants will wear a continuous glucose monitoring system (CGMS), and an exercise  watch for 14 days under free-living conditions. On one occasion, the participants will follow their normal diabetes management during periods of physical activity. In the alternate conditions, the participants will incorporate shorts sprints with their normal diabetes management to any period of sustained physical activity.The participants will be instructed that sprints should be performed with maximum effort. However as this is a "real-life" study we will not be measuring the intensity of the sprint.

We will investigate two different sprinting protocols to be performed during sustained (greater than 30 minutes) moderate intensity exercise. Participants will be asked to partake in moderate intensity exercise (running or cycling) at least 3 times a week for at least 30 minutes. This will take place in a real-life, free living setting. 

Intervention 1: Moderate intensity exercise with a 10 seconds sprint at the start, every 20 minutes during, and at the end of the exercise.
Intervention 2: Moderate intensity exercise with a 4 second sprint every 2 minutes, followed by a 10 second sprint at the end of the exercise.
We will monitor adherence to sprinting protocols using a GPS exercise watch (worn during exercise)  and an exercise diary.
All participants will complete intervention 1, intervention 2 and control arms of the study, There will be a 1-2 week washout period between each arm,</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants will be asked to partake in moderate intensity exercise (running or cycling) at least 3 times a week for at least 30 minutes. This will take place in a real-life, free living setting.  Participants will be instructed to follow their normal diabetes management and will NOT be given additional instructions regarding exercise management including insulin and/or carbohydrate adjustment. 

</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The incidence of hypoglycaemia (defined as glucose sensor readings &lt;3.5 mmol/L for greater than or equal to 20 minutes); or treated symptomatic hypoglycaemia.

Treated symptomatic hypoglycaemia will be assessed using self reported episodes in the participant study diary.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Hypoglycaemia will be assessed using continuous glucose monitoring (CGM) throughout the  three (control, intervention 1 and intervention 2), two week study periods- i.e over 6 weeks.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time spent with sensor glucose levels between 3.5 and 8mmol/L, between 8 and 10mmol/L and above 10mmol/L

This will be assessed using continuous glucose monitoring </outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assessed using continuous glucose monitoring (CGM) throughout the  three (control, intervention 1 and intervention 2), two week study periods- i.e over 6 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compliance with the exercise guidelines. This will be assessed using the exercise watch and the participant's exercise diary.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assessed using the exercise watch and the participant's exercise diary throughout the  three (control, intervention 1 and intervention 2), two week study periods- i.e over 6 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The incidence of hypoglycaemia (defined as glucose sensor readings &lt;3.9 mmol/L)

This will be assessed using continuous glucose monitoring. </outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assessed using continuous glucose monitoring (CGM) throughout the three (control, intervention 1 and intervention 2), two week study periods- i.e over 6 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Carbohydrate intake before, during and after exercise.

This will be assessed using the participant's food diary.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assessed using the participant's food diary throughout the three (control, intervention 1 and intervention 2), two week study periods- i.e over 6 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Type 1 Diabetes duration &gt;1y.
 - Male and female participants aged between 14 and 35 years old; 
 - Mean (over last 12 months) glycated haemoglobin levels &lt;9%; 
 - Participate in sustained aerobic exercise at least 3 times per week;
 - Free from any clinical evidence of macrovascular, microvascular or neurological complications associated with Type 1 Diabetes.
 - Hypoglycaemia aware, as assessed by the Modified Clarkes Hypoglycaemia Awareness Questionnaire.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>14</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>35</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Musculoskeletal injuries; 
- Other medical conditions where exercise is contraindicated.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealed through central randomisation using a computer.</concealment>
    <sequence>All participants will complete all three experimental conditions (control, intervention 1 and intervention 2) following a crossover study design and the order of these conditions will be randomised. We will use a counterbalanced design in which participants will be allocated to one of six ‘Sequences’ based on the order in which they receive the conditions. Participants will be evenly distributed across the ‘Sequences’. To allocate participants to a ‘sequence’, adaptive randomization (specifically, minimization) will be used. The following stratifying factors will be used in the minimisation: age group, and gender. This will be done using the computer program  ‘MinimPy’.

 </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Fifty subjects (50 completed studies) will be enrolled in this study. We have previously shown, using a similar experimental design, an average of 1.4 low glucose events (sensor glucose readings &lt;3.5 mmol/L) per day with a standard deviation of 1.0 in free-living individuals with Type 1 Diabates. Since a 30% reduction in this incident rate to 1.0 event per day would represent a statistically significant change with an alpha set at 0.05, we have calculated that a sample size of 45 participants will provide us with enough statistical power (Beta = 0.85) to test our hypothesis. We will recruit 50 participants to account for an approximate 10% loss to follow-up based on previous studies of this nature.
 
Generalized linear mixed models with a Negative Binomial distribution and log link will be used  to determine whether, compared to the control condition sprinting reduces the incidence of hypoglycaemic episodes associated with exercise in individuals with Type 1 Diabetes.

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>29/01/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/07/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Princess Margaret Hospital - Subiaco</hospital>
    <hospital>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital - Nedlands</hospital>
    <hospital>Fiona Stanley Hospital - Murdoch</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Perth Hospital - Perth</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Princess Margaret Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Princess Margaret Hospital
99 Roberts Road
Subiaco, 6008
Perth
Western Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC research grant </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to determine the effectiveness of incorporating short sprints into current clinical practice guidelines for improving blood glucose management during exercise in individuals with Type 1 Diabetes. We hypothesize that incorporating shorts sprints into any sustained period of physical activity will reduce the incidence of exercise-mediated hypoglycaemia in individuals with Type 1 Diabetes in a free-living setting.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Princess Margaret Hospital
99 Roberts Road
Subiaco, 6008
Perth
Western Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/03/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2014109EP</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/10/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Tim Jones</name>
      <address>Department Endocrinology and Diabetes
Princess Margaret Hospital
99 Roberts Road
Subiaco, 6008
Perth 
Western Australia

</address>
      <phone>+618 9340 8090</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Tim.Jones@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tarini Chetty</name>
      <address>Department Endocrinology and Diabetes
Princess Margaret Hospital
99 Roberts Road
Subiaco, 6008
Perth 
Western Australia</address>
      <phone>+618  9340 8090</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Tarini.Chetty@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tarini Chetty</name>
      <address>Department Endocrinology and Diabetes
Princess Margaret Hospital
99 Roberts Road
Subiaco, 6008
Perth 
Western Australia</address>
      <phone>+618 9340 8090</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Tarini.Chetty@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tarini Chetty</name>
      <address>Department Endocrinology and Diabetes
Princess Margaret Hospital
99 Roberts Road
Subiaco, 6008
Perth 
Western Australia</address>
      <phone>+618 9340 8090</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Tarini.Chetty@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>