<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371152">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/07/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000997459p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Assessment of macula function recovery using MAIA microperimetry after Epiretinal membrane peeling surgery.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Assessment of macula function recovery using MAIA microperimetry after Epiretinal membrane peeling surgery.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Epiretinal Membrane</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Vitreoretinal Surgery </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients who are diagnosed with Epiretinal Membrane who will undergo microperimetric testing pre and Pars plana vitrectomy membrane peeling surgery. 

Exposure being studied in this study: Fundus- driven microperimetry 

Microperimetry is a technology that allows concurrent analysis of structural and functional aspects of the retina. It combines fundus imaging, retinal sensitivity mapping and fixation analysis in one exam and has been used over a decade as a powerful tool to detect,
describe and follow-up pathologies affecting the macular area.  Its great advantage is the ability to track patients fixation activity while measuring visual field, hence eliminating errors caused by fixation losses. It is a non-invasive test and can be easily performed by most patients including those with low vision. It works by presenting light stimuli it a unit (one eye is occluded at a time) and the patient is given a button which they press when the stimulus is detected. 

The microperimetry test will be conducted on the patients by a member of the research team (Ophthalmic registrar, clinical research officer) using a standardised protocol at the clinic. The test takes approximately 5 mins per eye. We will try to ensure the same operator will conduct subsequent follow up test for a particular patient. The baseline test will be performed within 4 weeks prior to the patient undergoing surgery and then at 1,3,6 and 12 months post surgery. The data will be collected at these time points. </interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Macular function- this is measured as a change in microperimetric parameters including:
1. Average threshold (dB)
2. Central threshold (dB)
3. Macular Integrity
4. Fixation stability
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change in all parameters mentioned above from baseline will be recorded at 1, 3, 6 and 12 months post operatively. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Best corrected visual acuity: this will be measured using standard Snellen's chart at 6m </outcome>
      <timepoint>Change in best corrected visual acuity  from baseline will be recorded at 1, 3, 6 and 12 months post operatively. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Central macular thickness: This will be measured using SD-OCT (Heidelberg) and measured in micrometers using a drawn vector. 

Central macular thickness (CMT) is defined as the distance between the vitreoretinal interface and the anterior surface of the RPE. A  vector will  be drawn between these two points and distance measured which will provide the CMT. This will be done by same operator per patient. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Change in central macular thickness from baseline will be recorded at 1, 3, 6 and 12 months post operatively. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Ability to provide informed consent and complete study assessments  
2. Age 18 years or older
3. Best corrected baseline visual acuity between 6/60 to 6/9 in the study eye with a documented drop in BCVA
4. Diagnosed with Epiretinal membrane and consented to undergo ERM peeling surgery
5. Persistent metamorphopsia or micropsia for a period of at least 6 months
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Pregnancy or lactation
2. Intraocular surgery in the study eye within 2 months of baseline
3. Macular laser within 2 months or previous laser scar would prevent the improvement of macular function
4. Prior vitrectomy in the study eye
5. Current vitreous haemorrhage in the study eye
6. Active proliferative diabetic retinopathy in study eye
7. Active uveitis in study eye 
8. Uncontrolled glaucoma in the study eye defined as intraocular pressure  greater than 30mmHg on maximal medical therapy
9. Loss of vision due to other causes (e.g. age related macular degeneration, myopic macular degeneration, retinal vein occlusion)
10. An ocular condition that would prevent visual acuity improvement despite resolution of oedema (such as foveal atrophy)
11. Uncontrolled diabetes mellitus, as defined by hemoglobin A1C (HbA1c) &gt; 12%
12. Dense lens media opacity
13. History of stroke, acute myocardial infarction and transient ischemic attack within 3 months of study enrollment
14. Uncontrolled high blood pressure (blood pressure &gt; 180/110 mmHg)
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Study outcomes will be compared between baseline and follow up visits using paired T test as well as Pearsons correlation analysis to assess association between variables. 

There is no formal power calculation performed for this study. Study population recruitment target size chosen for this study has been based on cohort numbers seen in previous similar studies in the literature and this is cohort size will also be make it feasible to complete this project in the prescribed time frame. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Random sample</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>24/04/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/10/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Sydney Retina Clinic &amp; Day Surgery - Sydney</hospital>
    <hospital>Canberra Eye Hospital - Symonston</hospital>
    <postcode>2000 - Sydney</postcode>
    <postcode>2609 - Symonston</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Sydney Retina Clinic and Day Surgery</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>187 Macquarie St
Sydney NSW 2000
Parkhouse Building Level 13</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Sydney Retina Clinic and Day Surgery</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>187 Macquarie St
Sydney NSW 2000
Parkhouse Building Level 13</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Study Design: This is a prospective, non-randomised observational study which will follow post operative progress of patients who have been diagnosed with symptomatic Epiretinal membrane and will undergo epiretinal membrane peeling surgery over a 12 month period. 

Population: 100 eligible subjects will be recruited from Sydney Retina Clinic &amp; Day Surgery, Australia.

Study Duration: The study will be conducted over 18 months (6-month recruitment period and 12 month treatment and follow up period).

Primary Objective: To evaluate the rate and amount of macular functional recovery using visual acuity, MAIA microperimetry and visual functioning questionnaires and to correlate this with anatomical change on SD OCT over 12 months. The aim will also be to determine prognostic indicators of poor visual outcome post surgery. 3. The change of retinal function measured by Macular Integrity Assessment (MAIA) microperimetry  (including central threshold, average threshold, fixation stability and macular integrity) at months 1, 3, 6 and 12 months. 

Secondary Objectives: 
1. Mean change in visual acuity at months 1, 3, 6 and 12 compared to the baseline  using snellens chart at 6m
2. Mean change in central macular thickness  measured by SD-OCT at months 1, 3, 6 and 12 compared to the baseline


</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Research Integrity &amp; Ethics Administration University of Sydney </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The University of Sydney 
Research Integrity and Ethics Administration Department 
 Level 2 , Margaret Telfer Building (K07), The University of Sydney, NSW 
 2006
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/04/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Andrew Chang</name>
      <address>Sydney Retina Clinic and Day Surgery 
Level 13/187 Macquarie St 
Sydney NSW 2000</address>
      <phone>+612 9221 3755</phone>
      <fax>+612 9221 1637</fax>
      <email>achang@sydneyretina.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Thomas Hong</name>
      <address>Sydney Retina Clinic and Day Surgery 
Level 13/187 Macquarie St 
Sydney NSW 2000</address>
      <phone>+612 9221 3755</phone>
      <fax>+612 9221 1637</fax>
      <email>thong@sydneyretina.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rashmi Nair</name>
      <address>Sydney Retina Clinic and Day Surgery 
Level 13/187 Macquarie St 
Sydney NSW 2000</address>
      <phone>+612 9221 3755</phone>
      <fax>+612 9221 1637</fax>
      <email>rnair@sydneyretina.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Thomas Hong</name>
      <address>Sydney Retina Clinic and Day Surgery 
Level 13/187 Macquarie St 
Sydney NSW 2000</address>
      <phone>+612 9221 3755</phone>
      <fax>+612 9221 1637</fax>
      <email>thong@sydneyretina.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>