<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372332">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/02/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/03/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000354381</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A micronutrient intervention for pregnant women experiencing symptoms of depression and anxiety.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An investigation examining the efficacy and safety of a micronutrient intervention on symptoms of depression and anxiety in pregnant women who are symptomatic: A double blind, randomized, placebo controlled trial. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1189-4070</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Depression </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal pregnancy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Micronutrient formula
Participants will be randomly assigned to receive either a micronutrient formula or a placebo for twelve weeks. After twelve weeks, all participants will enter into an open-label phase whereby all mothers can choose to take the micronutrient formula for another 12 weeks or until the birth of their child. Both the micronutrient formula and the placebo are in capsule form and are to be taken orally at a dose of 12 capsules per day; four capsules taken three times per day with food and water. The micronutrient formula and placebo adhere to the New Zealand Ministry of Health recommendation for the daily intake of iodine for pregnant and lactating women. The micronutrient intervention is a blend of vitamins, minerals, antioxidants and amino acids. The formula, Daily Essential Nutrients, is being manufactured and donated by Hardy Nutritionals (Registered Trademark), Canada and consists of the following ingredients. The following doses are for 12 capsules (full dose per day): Vitamin A (as retinyl palmitate), 5,760 IU; Vitamin C (as ascorbic acid), 600 mg; Vitamin D (as cholecalciferol), 3,000 IU; Vitamin E (as d-alpha tocopheryl succinate), 360 IU; Vitamin K (75% as phylloquinone; 25% as menaquinone-7), 120 mcg; Thiamin (as thiamin mononitrate), 60 mg; Riboflavin, 18 mg; Niacin (as niacinamide), 90 mg; Vitamin B6 (as pyridoxine hydrochloride), 69.9 mg; Folate (as L-methylfolate calcium), 801 mcg; Vitamin B12 (as methylcobalamin), 900 mcg; Biotin, 1080 mcg; Pantothenic acid (as d-calcium pantothenate), 30 mg; Calcium (as chelate), 1,320 mg; Iron (as chelate), 13.8 mg; Phosphorus (as chelate), 840 mg; Iodine (as chelate), 204 mcg; Magnesium (as chelate), 600 mg; Zinc (as chelate), 48 mg; Selenium (as chelate), 204 mcg; Copper (as chelate), 7.2 mg; Manganese (as chelate), 9.6 mg; Chromium (as chelate), 624 mcg; Molybdenum (as chelate), 144 mcg; Potassium (as chelate), 240 mg. Proprietary blend: Choline bitartrate, Alpha-lipoic acid, Mineral wax, Inositol, Acetyl-L-carnitine, Grape seed extract, Ginkgo biloba leaf extract, L-methionine, N-acetyl-L-cysteine, Boron, Vanadium, Lithium orotate, Nickel. Other ingredients: Vegetarian capsule (hypromellose), microcrystalline cellulose, magnesium stearate, silicon dioxide, titanium dioxide. 
Adherence to the intervention will be assessed fortnightly throughout the study period. Participants are required to report the number of capsules missed over a two week period and return any unused capsules to the study investigators every fourth week. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo group
The placebo is manufactured and donated by Hardy Nutritionals (Registered Trademark), Canada and consists of the following ingredients taken orally at a dose of 12 capsules per day; four capsules taken three times per day with food and water. The following doses are for 12 capsules: Riboflavin, 1.2g; Potassium iodide, 150 mcg; Silicon dioxide, 30mg; Magnesium stearate,  60mg; Microcrystalline cellulose, 6g.

Riboflavin is known to change the colour of urine and has been added to the placebo so that both the intervention and control group experience the same change in urine colour. Adding riboflavin to the placebo will ensure the blind is maintained. 

Control group
A control group of pregnant women who meet a cut off score of 13 or more on the EPDS but who are not eligible to participate in the main trial or choose not to participate will be recruited in order to further interpret the impact of the intervention. The control group will not receive the intervention. 
</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Edinburgh Postnatal Depression Scale (EPDS; Cox et al, 1987) assesses the presence of depression and anxiety.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Screening, baseline, every two weeks until birth and at 1 month, 3 months and 6 months postpartum.


</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Clinical Global Impressions Improvement (CGI-I) Scale (Guy, 1976) produces a score based on how much the clinician thinks the participant has improved since baseline ranging from 1 (very much improved) to 7 (very much worse).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every four weeks until birth and at 1 month, 3 months and 6 months postpartum.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Montgomery and Asberg Depresion Rating Scale (MADRS; Montgomery &amp; Asberg, 1979) will replace the HAM-D to assess the frequency, severity and duration of depressive symptoms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, every four weeks until birth and at 1 month, 3 months and 6 months postpartum.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression, Anxiety, Stress Scale - 21 - assesses the severity of depression, anxiety and stress. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, every two weeks until birth and at 1 month, 3 months and 6 months postpartum.

</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nutrient levels: vitamin C, vitamin B12, vitamin D, folate, zinc, selenium, iron and homocysteine - assessed in plasma from blood samples taken at baseline and at 12 weeks RCT. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 12 weeks (end of the randomized controlled trial phase) </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Inflammatory biomarkers: interleukin  6 (IL-6), tumor necrosis factor alpha (TNF-a), interleukin-4 (IL-4) and interleukin-10 (IL-10), C-reactive protein (CRP) assessed in plasma from blood samples taken at baseline and at 12 weeks RCT. A complete blood count from the blood samples will also be assessed to assist in the interpretation of the biomarkers.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 12 weeks (end of the randomized controlled trial phase). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Microbiome assessed from stool samples taken at baseline and at week 12 RCT.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 12 weeks (end of the randomized controlled trial phase). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI; Buysse, Reynolds, Monk, Verman &amp; Kupfer, 1989) assesses sleep quality, latency, duration, disturbance, efficiency and daytime dysfunction. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, every four weeks until birth and at 1 month, 3 months, and 6 months postpartum.


</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Short Form Health Survey - 12 (SF-12; Ware, Kosinski &amp; Keller, 1996) assesses quality of life. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, every four weeks until birth and at 1 month, 3 months, and 6 months postpartum.


</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Difficulties in Emotion Regulation Scale -  Short Form (DERS-SF; Kaufman et al, 2015) assesses emotion disregulation. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, every four weeks until birth and at 1 month, 3 months and 6 months postpartum.


</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Electroencephalography (EEG) will be measured at rest and in response to simple audio/visual cues will be used to index anxiety-related endophenotypes, neurophysiological markers of anxiety and related psychophysiological processes. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and end of 12 weeks RCT</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Antidepressant Side-Effect Checklist (ASEC; Uher et al, 2009) and a review of medical records will assess side effects, safety &amp; adverse events of the intervention. The ASEC has been adapted for the purposes of this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>ASEC will be administered every two weeks until birth; medical records reviewed 3 months after birth. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) women aged 19 years and over; 2) 12-18 weeks gestation; 3) singleton pregnancy; 4) free from psychiatric medication for four weeks; 5) score of 13 or more on the Edinburgh Postnatal Depression Scale (EPDS); 6) deemed reliable and compliant with the protocol. 

Control group inclusion criteria:
1) women aged 19 years and over; 2) 12-18 weeks gestation; 3) singleton pregnancy; 4) score of 13 or more on the Edinburgh Postnatal Depression Scale (EPDS)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>19</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) regularly induce self-vomiting; 2) have major foetal abnormalities in the pregnancy; 3) have a serious current or historical medical condition; 4) are known to be allergic to the ingredients of the intervention; 5) have a known metabolic condition such as Wilsons disease, hemochromatosis. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed opaque envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation sequence will be computer-generated by an independent researcher using the website: http://www.randomization.com and will be arranged in a 1:1 ratio using blocks. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>In 2014, there were 57,242 live births in New Zealand, 6,575 of which were in Christchurch (Statistics New Zealand, 2015). Assuming at least 12% meet criteria for PND and accounting for twin births of 1 in every 100 pregnancies, approximately 781 women per year would be eligible for the proposed study in Christchurch alone. 

Based on previous research, to detect a medium effect (Cohens d = 0.6) on the EPDS between groups at a two tailed significance level of 0.05 and power of 0.8 the minimum sample size would be 90 (45 in each group). Assuming a 30% attrition rate (based on the mean attrition rate from previous nutrient RCTs using perinatal women) the adjusted number per treatment condition would be approximately 60. Therefore, the total target sample size for this study is 120 (60 in the micronutrient group and 60 in the placebo group). In order to further interpret the impact of the intervention, we will be following a non-randomized control group of pregnant women who are either not eligible to participate in the intervention trial or choose not to participate. The total sample size of this group is unknown.  

All statistical analyses will be carried out using the Statistical Package for Social Science (SPSS).  Demographic characteristics will be compared across the treatment groups using independent samples t-tests in order to test for potential failures of randomization.  All data will be analyzed on an intention-to-treat basis using the last observation carried forward method.

For the primary outcomes (EPDS and CGI-I scores), the repeated measures of the outcome variables will be modelled using generalized linear mixed effects regression models.  These models will permit the testing of differences between the micronutrient group and the placebo group over the course of the trial. In the case of the EPDS, baseline scores will be used as a covariate factor, as well as measures of demographic characteristics, behaviour and social support, and measures of inflammatory biomarkers.

For secondary outcomes (HDRS. DASS, biomarkers), linear mixed effects models will also be used, and again will be supplemented by as measures of demographic characteristics, behaviour and social support, and measures of inflammatory biomarkers.

The pooled mean scores (and standard deviations) over the course of the trial on each of the primary outcomes will be used to compute estimates of effect size (Cohens d).  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>13/03/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>12/04/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/08/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>28/02/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Canterbury</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Julia Rucklidge</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Psychology
University of Canterbury
Private Bag 4800
Christchurch 8140</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Canterbury, Dept of Psychology Research Funds</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Psychology
University of Canterbury
Private Bag 4800
Christchurch 8140</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Univeristy of Canterbury Foundation - donations given to the principal investigator</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of Canterbury
Private Bag 4800,
Christchurch 8140</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Canterbury Medical Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Canterbury Medical Research Foundation
Level 1/230 Antigua Street
Christchurch 8011</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Hardy Nutritionals (Registered Trademark)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Hardy Nutritionals (Registered Trademark)
69B Broadway Street North
 PO Box 919
 Raymond, Alberta
 Canada T0K 2S0</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Canada</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Roger Mulder</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of Psychological Medicine
University of Otago
PO Box 4345
Christchurch 8140</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Jackeline Henderson </othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Psychology
University of Canterbury
Private Bag 4800
Christchurch 8140</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Martin Kennedy</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Pathology
University of Otago, Christchurch
PO Box 4345
Christchurch 8140</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Kyle Nash</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Psychology
University of Canterbury
Private Bag 4800
Christchurch 8140</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Lesley Dixon</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>New Zealand College of Midwives
376 Manchester Street 
Christchurch 8014</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Hayley Bradley</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Psychology
University of Canterbury
Private Bag 4800
Christchurch 8140</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to compare the effect of a micronutrient (vitamin and mineral) formula to a placebo on symptoms of depression and anxiety in pregnant women who are symptomatic. Given the association between nutritional deficiencies and depression during pregnancy and previous research showing that micronutrients can improve mood and anxiety, this study hypothesizes that a micronutrient formula will reduce symptoms of depression and anxiety during pregnancy more so than a placebo.  </summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.psyc.canterbury.ac.nz/research/Mental_Health_and_Nutrition/studies.shtml</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Hardy Nutritionals (Registered Trademark) are the manufacturer of the study intervention and placebo and have no other involvement in the study other than donating the product free of charge.</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Health and Disabilty Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
133 Molesworth Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/02/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>16/STH/187</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Univeristy of Canterbury Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 5 South, Matariki Building
University of Canterbury
Private Bag 4800
Christchurch 8140</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/02/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/02/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Julia Rucklidge</name>
      <address>Mental Health and Nutrition Research Group
Department of Psychology
University of Canterbury
Private Bag 4800,
Christchurch 8140
</address>
      <phone>+64 3369 4398</phone>
      <fax>+64 33642181</fax>
      <email>julia.rucklidge@canterbury.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Hayley Bradley</name>
      <address>Mental Health and Nutrition Research Group
Department of Psychology
University of Canterbury
Private Bag 4800,
Christchurch 8140</address>
      <phone>+64 3364 2987 ext. 7705</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hayley.bradley@pg.canterbury.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Julia Rucklidge</name>
      <address>Mental Health and Nutrition Research Group
Department of Psychology
University of Canterbury
Private Bag 4800,
Christchurch 8140</address>
      <phone>+64 3369 4398</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>julia.rucklidge@canterbury.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Hayley Bradley </name>
      <address>Mental Health and Nutrition Research Group
Department of Psychology
University of Canterbury
Private Bag 4800,
Christchurch 8140</address>
      <phone>+64 3364 2987 ext. 7705</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hayley.bradley@pg.canterbury.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>