<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82283">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/09/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/09/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000498493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Preventing falls in the acute hospital setting.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of a multifactorial falls prevention program in preventing falls and injurious falls in an acute hospital setting.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute medical and surgical conditions.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A sequential crossover design with a 20 week data collection period has been adopted.  An A/B design is proposed with Phase A being non-intervention and Phase B  intervention.  There are four components: 
1.Research protocol standardisation training (e.g. what is a fall, what is an injurious fall, how do I report etc.)  this will ensure consistent data across both phases
2.Phase A  Pre-intervention data collection (10 weeks)
3.Intervention training
4.Phase B  Intervention data collection (10 weeks)

Education - All staff will attend meetings 1-2 days prior to each phase to be trained in research protocol standardisation and research interventions

The following interventions will be implemented for the duration of persons admission within the 10 weeks of the intervention phase:

Falls Risk Flagging - Every admission will be screened (Have you had a fall in the last 12 months? Observe the patient stand from a chair, walk a short distance and return to sitting) and/or assessed (The Northern Hospital Modified Stratify Falls Risk Assessment Tool) as part of usual care.  In the intervention phase falls risk will be flagged using an orange High Falls Risk Alert Sign on the persons door, above the bed and on their walking aid.  The person will also wear an orange arm band

Mobility and walking aids - Physiotherapy review will be undertaken on the morning of admission for people at high risk of falling.  The physiotherapist will conduct a Timed Up and Go Test, issue an appropriate walking aid where indicated and conduct ongoing mobility and balance training as indicated.

Footwear  people at high risk of falling will be assessed by the admitting nurse for appropriate footwear as outlined in Australian Falls Prevention Guidelines.  Those without appropriate footwear will be offered non-slip socks (GripSox) for walking.

Medications - No new Benzodiazepine will be prescribed by any medical officer without consulting the hospitals Consultant Physician.  

Hydration Programme - Hourly water cues and toileting offers will be made during waking hours for cognitively impaired participants (i.e. defined as persons with an Abbreviated Mental Test Score of &lt;8).  Water fountain with a park bench and reading material will be located on each ward as a place for wandering people to go.  A Happy Hour where non-alcoholic mocktails, soft drinks, cordial and nibbles are served will be held 1-2 times per week and it will be targeted towards cognitively impaired people to improve hydration.

Supervision and surveillance - High Falls Risk Patients will never be left alone in the bathroom

Environment  A 7pm Light round will be conducted where all bathroom lights will be turned on in at night where no sensor light is fitted.

Fracture prevention - Hip protectors will be offered to anyone admitted with a low trauma fracture or anyone who has a diagnosis of osteoporosis

Vision - Patients are offered their own appropriate spectacles for every walk. 

Low beds and appropriate height chairs  A breakfast bed and chair height round will be conducted where beds and chairs are set to popliteal crease height or lowest height, and meal tables will be placed within reach.</interventions>
    <comparator>Ususal Care
Defined as interventions conducted as part of a routine admission for a given condition.  Usual care is guided by clinical pathways or individual clinical decisions by qualified health practitioners.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Falls per 1000 bed days.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 10 week intervention phase.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Injurious falls per 1000 bed days.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 10 week intervention phase.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of multiple fallers.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 10 week intervention phase.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Benzodiazepine prescription volume.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 10 week intervention phase.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adult participants over the age of 18 years. The expected age range 18-100 years Patients being admitted to hospital
Ability to participate voluntarily and provide signed informed consent or access to an appropriate family member/guardian or carer who can provide signed informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>-2147483648</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>The inability to provide signed informed consent or lack of an appropriate family member/guardian or carer who can provide signed informed consent.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/10/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>600</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Health and Ageing Solutions</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Brisbane QLD</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Friendly Society Private Hopsital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Bundaberg QLD</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Medibank Private</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Melbourne VIC</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Trevor Russell</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>University of Queensland</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of this study is to investigate the hypothesis that a multifactorial, multidisciplinary falls prevention programme can prevent falls in an acute hospital setting.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/09/2007</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Michael Bourke</name>
      <address>Health and Ageing Solutions
PO Box 884
Lutwyche
Brisbane QLD</address>
      <phone>+617 33453255</phone>
      <fax>+617 33453255</fax>
      <email>michael.bourke@healthandageingsolutions.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Michael Bourke</name>
      <address>Health and Ageing Solutions
PO Box 884
Lutwyche
Brisbane QLD</address>
      <phone>+617 33453255</phone>
      <fax>+617 33453255</fax>
      <email>michael.bourke@healthandageingsolutions.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Michael Bourke</name>
      <address>Health and Ageing Solutions
PO Box 884
Lutwyche
Brisbane QLD</address>
      <phone>+617 33453255</phone>
      <fax>+617 33453255</fax>
      <email>michael.bourke@healthandageingsolutions.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>