<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343027">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/06/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/06/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000582954</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Myopia control with progressive spectacle lenses trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Investigation of the efficacy of the third generation MC PAL lenses in the retardation of juvenile onset myopic progression in 7 to 12 year old children.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>MCPAL3</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Juvenile onset myopia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Custom designed Progressive Addition Lenses worn binocularly during normal waking hours and for all tasks where spectacles can and normally would be worn. There are two designs, each having 1.00 D addition in the lower viewing zone and different peripheral near power profiles: one with rapid lateral rise in peripheral plus power (narrow near zone design) followed by an early drop off, and the other with a slow rise of peripheral plus power with late drop off (wide near zone design). Subjects are assigned to either of these designs or a single-vision lens control condition according to a pre-defined randomized sequence assigned on an incremental recruitment number. The study will compare the effectiveness of peripheral vision correction during near tasks with two different peripheral power profiles. The addition power will help reduce the accommodative demand of the wearer while doing near vision tasks (&lt; 75 cm). The lens has a progressively increasing addition power starting at the distance viewing reference point and reaching the prescribed addition at approximately 12 mm below the fitting cross. The patient's regular prescription is additionally surfaced on the back surface of these lenses to correct any ocular errors of the eye. This may include sphere and / or cylinder corrections. Patients wear the lenses during normal waking hours and for all tasks where spectacles can be worn for a period of 24 months.</interventions>
    <comparator>Single Vision prescription lens. These lenses are to be worn binocularly during normal waking hours and for all tasks where spectacles can and normally would be worn for a period of 24 months. They correct the wearers ocular errors of focus. This may include sphere and or cylinder corrections. Patients wear the lenses during normal waking hours and for all tasks where spectacles can be worn.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression in sphere equivalent refractive error from cycloplegic autorefraction using the Grand Seiko WR-5100K open field auto-refractor.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6, 12, 18 &amp; 24 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression in axial length of the eyeball. This will be measured using a Sonomed A Scan or Tomey A Scan ultrasound measuring device.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6, 12, 18 &amp; 24 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) Spherical equivalent refractive error (SER) of 1.00 to -4.50 D
2) Astigmatism of not more than -1.50 D.
3) Anisometropia of not more than -1.50 D in spherical or cylindrical error. 
4) Have best corrected visual acuity of at least 6/9 (20/30) in each eye.
5) Normal ocular health other than myopia.
6) No prior use of bifocal or progressive lenses in the last 12 months. 
7) No RPG contact lens experience and must be willing not to wear contact lenses.
8) In satisfactory health.
9) Willing and able to tolerate cycloplegia (no previous adverse reaction to cycloplegics).
10) Informed parental consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>7</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>12</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) Any systemic condition which might affect refractive development or systemic diseases which may affect vision or refractive error.
2) Previous use of contact lens/PALs or other treatment for myopia within the last 12 months.
3) Defective binocular function.
4) Amblyopia and or manifested squint.
5) Vestibular disorders or motor imbalance.
6) Any other conditions precluding adherence to the Protocol.
7) Have best corrected visual acuity worse than 6/9 (20/30) in each eye.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subjects may be recruited through Ministry of Education approved visits to local ethnic Chinese schools accompanied by the screening of students for the eligibility and exclusion criteria. Interested families will be asked to enrol their children that have passed the screening tests into the trial by inviting them to the clinic and performing a range of additional tests covering all inclusion and exclusion criteria, such as ophthalmoscopy, biomicroscopy, tonometry and cover test. If the child meets the ocular selection criteria, the family will be informed and its consent will be obtained. Then the child will be allocated, according to a pre-determined random sequence, to either one of the PAL (treatment) groups or the SV (control) group. Families will not be told the nature of the three lenses being offered and it will be emphasized that allocation to a particular lens would be at random and could not be requested. 
The practitioner examining the child will not know the lens allocated. They will communicate the name of the subject, the allocated subject ID and full prescription to the unmasked investigator (UMI) who will enter the subjects name under the allocated ID and note the randomly pre-assigned lens type for the allocated Subject ID. The UMI will contact the surfacing laboratory with the job order that specifies prescription and lens type assigned.</concealment>
    <sequence>We have generated a randomisation plan for 165 subjects randomised into blocks on the web site http://www.randomization.com.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/06/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>13/06/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>25/06/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>165</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>167</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <state>Kuala Lumpur</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Carl Zeiss Vision</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>26 Cooroora Crescent, Lonsdale 5160, Adelaide, South Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Carl Zeiss Vision</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>26 Cooroora Crescent, Lonsdale 5160, Adelaide, South Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Optometry
Faculty of Allied Health Sciences
Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia
Jalan Raja Muda Abdul Aziz, 50300 Kuala Lumpur</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Malaysia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This double-masked randomised trial hopes to contribute to the overall effort in reducing the prevalence of myopia in general population or, at least, retard the progression of myopia in some children.  It is designed with the following specific aims:
1) To assess the efficacy of the MC PAL 3 spectacle lenses for controlling the progression of myopia in children between the ages of 7 and 12 yrs relative to a SV control lens condition. 
2) To assess the efficacy of two designs with 1.00 D addition and different peripheral near power profiles   a narrow near zone design and wide near zone design.
3) To assess the tolerance of children to wearing MC PAL 3 on a full time basis.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Research Ethics Committee Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Medical Research &amp; Industry Secretariat
Level 1,Clinical Block,
UKM Medical Centre,
Jalan Yaakob Latif, Bandan Tun Razak,
5600 Cheras, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/04/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>UKM 1.5.3.5/244/NN-050-2011</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Malaysia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Saulius Varnas</name>
      <address>Carl Zeiss Vision R&amp;D Australia
26 Cooroora Crescent
Lonsdale, 5160
South Australia</address>
      <phone>+618 8392 8327</phone>
      <fax>+618 8392 8400</fax>
      <email>Saulius.Varnas@vision.zeiss.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Saulius Varnas</name>
      <address>Carl Zeiss Vision R&amp;D Australia
26 Cooroora Crescent
Lonsdale, 5160
South Australia</address>
      <phone>+618 8392 8327</phone>
      <fax>+618 8392 8400</fax>
      <email>Saulius.Varnas@vision.zeiss.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Saulius Varnas</name>
      <address>Carl Zeiss Vision R&amp;D Australia
26 Cooroora Crescent
Lonsdale, 5160
South Australia</address>
      <phone>+618 8392 8327</phone>
      <fax>+618 8392 8400</fax>
      <email>Saulius.Varnas@vision.zeiss.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Saulius Varnas</name>
      <address>Carl Zeiss Vision R&amp;D Australia
26 Cooroora Crescent Lonsdale, 5160 South Australia</address>
      <phone>+618 8392 8327 </phone>
      <fax>+618 8392 8400</fax>
      <email>Saulius.Varnas@vision.zeiss.com </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>