<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82091">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/06/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/06/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000333415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Long term impact of RAS inhibition on cardio-renal outcomes: a comparative trial of angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitors, angiotensin receptor blockers or combined therapy with both agents in patients with one or more cardiovascular risk factors and microalbuminuria, diabetic or not diabetic.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In patients with one or more cardiovascular risk factors and microalbuminuria, diabetic or not diabetic, administration of angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitors, angiotensin receptor blockers or combined therapy with both agents, comparison of three arms to assess the impact on cardiovascular and cerebrovascular outcomes.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>LIRICO</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Patients with one or more cardiovascular risk factors and microalbuminuria, diabetic or not diabetic.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the cardiovascular system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>ACE-inhibitor (ACEi) monotherapy or angiotensin II receptor blocker (ARB) monotherapy or combined treatment with ACEi + ARB. Physicians will able to choose any commercially available  ACEi or ARB of ACEi or ARB commercially available provided a blood pressure target of &lt;130/80 mmHg is addressed.

The dose depends on the drug(s) selected by the investigator; the administration is by mouth (per os).
Duration of intervention/s: daily for the duration of the trial (4 years).
It is not possible to define a standard dose: the randomization decides which drug class will be assigned; the investigators must choose one of the drugs included in the class. The dose will be the standard dose of the selected drug. Therefore as  the investigators can choose among about 85 ACEi and 36 ARB, it is not possible to define a standard dose.</interventions>
    <comparator>The controls are the two monotherapies.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the comparative efficacy for cardiovascular and cerebrovascular outcomes of combined therapy with angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitors (ACEi) and (angiotensin receptor blockers) ARB versus monotherapy with ACEi or ARB in individuals with micro/macroalbuminuria and cardio-renal risk.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every follow up visit (1, 3 and 6 months after randomization and then every six months).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the comparative efficacy for cardiac and cerebrovascular outcomes of ACEi monotherapy versus ARB monotherapy in the same individuals with micro/macroalbuminuria and cardio-renal risk.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every follow up visit (1, 3 and 6 months after randomization and then every six months).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the comparative efficacy for renal outcomes of combined therapy with angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitors (ACEi) and (angiotensin receptor blockers) ARB versus monotherapy with ACEi or ARB in individuals with micro/macroalbuminuria and cardio-renal risk.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every follow up visit (1, 3 and 6 months after randomization and then every six months).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the comparative efficacy for renal outcomes of ACEi monotherapy versus ARB monotherapy in the same individuals with micro/macroalbuminuria and cardio-renal risk.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every follow up visit (1, 3 and 6 months after randomization and then every six months).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Consenting individuals, with microalbuminuria or macroalbuminuria, with one or more cardiovascular risk factors (smoking, diabetes, hypertension, visceral obesity, dyslipidemia, family history of cardiovascular diseases) including those with previous major cardiovascular events provided these have occurred at least 6 months before enrolment.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnancy, no use of birth control measures, neoplasm, clinically significant aortic obstruction, previous evidence of intolerance to study medications, clear contraindications to use of RAS inhibition, major cardiovascular events within 6 months of randomization, any condition which significantly reduces life expectancy and any condition where the patient appears not to be able to guarantee compliance with treatment and follow-up.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>central randomisation by phone</concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted block randomisation, stratified allocation. The centres are used for the stratification.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>22/11/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>2100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Consorzio Mario Negri Sud</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Via Nazionale 8/a 
66030 Santa Maria Imbaro (CH)- Italy</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Italy</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Italian Ministry of Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Via della Sierra nevada, 60 - 00144 Rome- Italy</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Italy</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>no one</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Approved without conditions.
People with high urinary albumin level has a higher risk of cardiovascular diseases than other people.
The aim of the study is to clarify if it is possible to further reduce the renal- and cardiovascular diseases risk using ACE-inhibitors and angiotensin receptor blockers instead of using only ACE-inhibitors or only angiotensin receptor blockers.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Maione A, Nicolucci A, Craig JC, Tognoni G, Moschetta A, Palasciano G, Pugliese G, Procaccini DA, Gesualdo L, Pellegrini F, Strippoli GF; for the LIRICO study group. Protocol of the Long-term Impact of RAS Inhibition on Cardiorenal Outcomes (LIRICO) randomized trial. J Nephrol  2007; 20: 646-655.
Maione A, Nicolucci A, Craig JC, Tognoni G, Moschetta A, Palasciano G, Pugliese G, Procaccini DA, Gesualdo L, Pellegrini F, Strippoli GF. ACE-inibizione, antagonismo recettoriale e terapia combinata in soggetti microalbuminurici con fattori di rischio cardiovascolare. Protocollo dello studio randomizzato multicentrico "Long-term Impact of RAS Inhibition on Cardiorenal Outcomes" LIRICO. G Ital Nefrol 2007; 5: 446-456.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethic Committee of Bari polyclinic-Bari Polyclinic</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/03/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>ITALY</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Giovanni Strippoli</name>
      <address>Dpt. Clinical Pharmacology and Epidemiology
Consorzio Mario Negri Sud
Via Nazionale 8/a
66030 Santa Maria Imbaro (CH)- </address>
      <phone>+39 0872 570356</phone>
      <fax>+39 0872 570263</fax>
      <email>strippoli@negrisud.it</email>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Maria Celeste Pirozzoli</name>
      <address>Dpt. Clinical Pharmacology and Epidemiology
Consorzio Mario Negri Sud
Via Nazionale 8/a
66030 Santa Maria Imbaro (CH)- </address>
      <phone>+39 0872 570311</phone>
      <fax>+39 0872 570263</fax>
      <email>pirozzoli@negrisud.it</email>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>