<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336557">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/02/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/03/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000278932</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>My Road Ahead: An Online Psychological Intervention for Men with Prostate Cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Assessing the efficacy of an online psychological intervention for men with prostate cancer: Impact on quality of life and mood state</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>MHREC 2010.282</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Prostate cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Psychological distress</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants who consent to take part in the study will be required to complete a series of questions online. This developed online assessment will include a measure of anxiety, depression and stress, quality of life, relationship satisfaction and sexual function. Participants will be randomly assigned to one of three groups; group 1 will receive access to the online intervention plus use of a moderated bulletin board. Group 2 will receive access to the online intervention only and group three will receive access to the moderated bulletin board only. Group 3 will be offered the option to complete the online intervention at the conclusion of the study if they would like to. The online intervention is a 6 module self-directed online internet based psychological intervention. Participants will explore emotional responses, thoughts and beliefs, masculinity, sexuality and intimacy, relationship factors and coping with uncertainty. The 6 modules are designed to be complted one module per week; a total of 6 weeks with an estimated time commitment of approximately 1 hour per week.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control participants in group 3 will receive no access to the developed online intervention but will receive access to the moderated bulletin board and will be used as the comparator group.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life:
The prostate cancer-related quality of life scales (PCa-QoL) (Clark et al., 2003) 
The impact of erectile dysfunction on sexual and masculine identity will be measured using the Prostate cancer-related scales, which measure men's perceptions of early prostate cancer treatment outcomes, focussing on behavioural, interpersonal and emotional changes that patients attribute to prostate cancer (Clark et al., 2003).  The prostate cancer-related quality of life questionnaire was developed from focus groups with 130 men (&gt; 50 years old) who had been diagnosed with early stage prostate cancer (T1-T3, N0/X, M0/X) 12-24 months previously (39% treated with prostatectomy; 39% treated with radiotherapy; 8% treated with hormone therapy and 9% chose watchful waiting). The scales contains 84 Likert type items that fall into 11 scales including: 1. Urinary control (behavioural and interpersonal implications of impaired control of one's bladder); 2. Sexual ability - sexual intimacy (ability to perform sexually and feelings of frustration, embarrassment or failure); 3. Sexual confidence (confidence and anxiety about intimate activity and sexual thoughts); 4. Spouse affection (misgivings about demonstrations of affection with one's spouse), 5. Masculine self-esteem; 6. Health worry (uncertainty about one's health); 7. PSA concern; 8. Cancer control; 9. Informed decision; 10. Regret; and, 11. Positive outlook.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks, 12 weeks and 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety
Distress will be measured using the Depression Anxiety and Stress Scales (DASS-21) short version (Lovibond &amp; Lovibond, 1995).  The DASS is a set of three self-report scales designed to measure the negative emotional states of depression, anxiety and stress (Lovibond &amp; Lovibond, 1995).   Each of the three DASS scales contains 7 items.  The depression scale measures dysphoria, hopelessness, devaluation of life, self-deprecation, lack of interest/involvement, anhedonia and inertia.  The anxiety scale measures autonomic arousal, skeletal muscle effects, situational anxiety, and subjective experience of anxious affect.  The stress scale assesses difficulty relaxing, nervous arousal, being irritable and impatient.  Subjects are asked to rate the extent to which they have experienced each state over the past week, using a 4-point severity/frequency scale.  The DASS scales have good concurrent validity with the Beck measures of depression and anxiety (BDI &amp; BAI) and good internal consistency and reliability (Lovibond &amp; Lovibond, 1995).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks, 12 weeks and 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression
Distress will be measured using the Depression Anxiety and Stress Scales (DASS-21) short version (Lovibond &amp; Lovibond, 1995).  The DASS is a set of three self-report scales designed to measure the negative emotional states of depression, anxiety and stress (Lovibond &amp; Lovibond, 1995).   Each of the three DASS scales contains 7 items.  The depression scale measures dysphoria, hopelessness, devaluation of life, self-deprecation, lack of interest/involvement, anhedonia and inertia.  The anxiety scale measures autonomic arousal, skeletal muscle effects, situational anxiety, and subjective experience of anxious affect.  The stress scale assesses difficulty relaxing, nervous arousal, being irritable and impatient.  Subjects are asked to rate the extent to which they have experienced each state over the past week, using a 4-point severity/frequency scale.  The DASS scales have good concurrent validity with the Beck measures of depression and anxiety (BDI &amp; BAI) and good internal consistency and reliability (Lovibond &amp; Lovibond, 1995).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks, 12 weeks and 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>International Index of Erectile Function (IIEF)
The international index of erectile function (IIEF) is a 15-item self-report measure that was developed to assess sexual function among men with Erectile Dysfunction (ED) (Rosen et al., 1997). The IIEF instructs respondents to answer items according to functioning during the past 4 weeks. Responses to items are summed to determine the total IIEF score. Rosen et al. reported high internal consistency, for the total IIEF scale (a=0.91), as well as high test-retest reliability(r=0.82).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks, 12 weeks and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Kansas Marital Satisfaction Scale (KMSS). This is a three item questionnaire that measures overall marital satisfaction.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks, 12 weeks and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Communication Patterns Questionnaire Short Form (CPQ-SF). The CPQ-SF is an 11-item self report questionnaire that assess communication styles within a marital dyad. This scale yields three subscale scores including criticize/defend, discuss/avoid, and positive interaction patterns.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks, 12 weeks and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Men who have received treatment for localised prostate cancer at least 6 months ago.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>100</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Advanced prostate cancer including locally advanced disease and metastatic disease. Any uncontrolled mental health disorder or any signficant cognitive disorder or dementia.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The proposed study aims assess the efficacy of the online intervention utilising a randomised controlled trial and CONSORT requirements for randomised controlled trials will be adhered to throughout the study. This phase will assess the efficacy of the online intervention by comparing the outcome measures of participants in the online intervention group with either a group undertaking the online intervention plus access to the moderated bulletin board or a group that only has access to the moderated bulletin board. 

All participants will be required to complete the online assessment developed in phase 1. Participants will then be randomly assigned to one of three (3) groups.  Randomisation will be concealed and conducted via central randomisation through computer generated allocations. The randomisation process will be fully automated and researchers will be blind to the participant's group allocation. 

Group 1 is the online intervention group whereby participants will be enrolled into the 6 module online program. 

Group 2 is the online intervention plus access to the moderated bulletin board group.

Group 3 is the moderated bulletin board only group where participants allocated to this group will only receive access to the bulletin board across the duration of the study. Participants in this group will act as a wait-list control group and will be offered access to the online program following their completion of the week 18 assessment. 

Participants in all groups will undertake the online assessment at three times; baseline, post-intervention (week 6 for group 3) and 12 weeks post intervention (week 18 for group 3). 

Participants will also be asked to record the number of contacts they have with additional support services including psychiatrists, psychologists and social workers as well as attending a support group or accessing support from the cancer council or other online resources. These factors will be statistically controlled for when analysing the data.</concealment>
    <sequence>computer generated random grouping</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>23/08/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>30/04/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>3050</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Melbourne Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Grattan St
Parkville, VIC 3050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>beyondblue</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 6100
Hawthorn West, 
VIC 3122</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Prostate Cancer Foundation of Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Ground Floor
15-17 Queen St
Melbourne, VIC 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Swinburne University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>National eTherapy Centre
PO BOX 218
Hawthorn VIC, 3122</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Deakin University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Psychology
221 Burwood Highway
Burwood VIC 3125</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Objectives: The overarching objective of this proposal is to develop and assess the efficacy of a unique online psychological intervention that is accessible, user friendly and engaging to men with CaP and that reduces the stigma of psychological distress in the context of prostate cancer. Aims: This project will be conducted over three phases. Phase 1: Development of resources - Develop an online assessment template to assess the psychological status of men with prostate cancer and to highlight specific areas of distress to the patient and the researchers. - Develop a 6 module self-directed online CBT-based psychological intervention for men with CaP. Phase 2: Consumer evaluation of developed resources - Assess the usability and acceptability of the online program with a consumer population Phase 3: Randomised controlled trial examining the efficacy of the online intervention - Assess the efficacy of the online intervention as compared to a usual care group across a number of domains including: Mental Health -Anxiety, Depression, Stress (DASS); Marital Satisfaction; Prostate-Specific Quality of Life (QoL) 1. Urinary control; 2. Sexual intimacy; 3. Sexual confidence; 4. Spouse affection 5. Masculine self-esteem; 6. Health worry; 7. PSA concern; 8. Cancer control; 9. Informed decision; 10. Regret; and, 11. Positive outlook.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Melbourne Health Human ethics committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Royal Melbourne Hospital
Grattan St
Parkville, VIC 3050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/07/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>MHREC: 2008.282</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/11/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Addie Wootten</name>
      <address>Department of Urology
Royal Melbourne Hospital
Grattan St
Parkville VIC 3050</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9342 7458</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>addie.wootten@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Addie Wootten</name>
      <address>Department of Urology
Royal Melbourne Hospital
Grattan St
Parkville VIC 3050</address>
      <phone>+61 3 93427458</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>addie.wootten@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Addie Wootten</name>
      <address>Department of Urology
Royal Melbourne Hospital
Grattan St
Parkville VIC 3050</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9342 7458</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>addie.wootten@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Addie Wootten</name>
      <address>Department of Urology
Level 3 Centre, Royal Melbourne Hospital
Grattan St
Parkville, VIC 3050</address>
      <phone>+61 3 93427458</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>addie.wootten@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>