<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372794">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/05/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000668303p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Testing the efficacy of an Emotion Regulation Group Therapy for adolescent non-suicidal self-injury in Aotearoa New Zealand</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomised Control Trial on the effect of Emotion Regulation Group Therapy on non-suicidal self-injury in adolescent </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1190-5820</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>non-suicidal self-injury (NSSI)</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Emotion Regulation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This randomised control trial (RCT) aims to assess the effectiveness of Emotion Regulation Group therapy (ERGT) in reducing non-suicidal self-injury among adolescents in primary and secondary health services, and secondary school pastoral care, as an adjunct to treatment as usual (TAU). Non-suicidal self-injury (NSSI: direct and deliberate destruction of body tissue) will be the main outcome variable under study. Participants will be randomly allocated either into the TAU condition (control group), or TAU plus ERGT (experimental group). We aim to test the hypothesis that participants in the experimental condition will have significantly greater reductions in their NSSI compared to participants in the control group, over the course of therapy and the follow-up period. Questionnaire data will be collected from participants, their families and clinicians pre-, post- and at follow-up intervals regarding their well being, emotion regulation capacity and self-injury, to assess changes over time. 

ERGT was originally developed by Kim Gratz and Matthew Tull, to reduce self-injury among adults with significant mental health problems. We have adapted ERGT slightly, for adolescents in New Zealand. Gratz and Tull are collaborating on this project, and will assist with maintaining treatment fidelity, but providing supervision, and reviewing our amended ERGT materials. This will ensure that the project team are adhering to the original tenants of ERGT. Where possible, ERGT sessions will be recorded, and these recordings reviewed during supervision. to assess adherence to the concepts of ERGT. ERGT clinicians will have regular meetings to review their practice. 

Materials used in the study include a therapy manual, treatment booklet for participants in the experimental group (with ERGT materials and homework exercise), and questionnaires for the collection of data. 

ERGT involves weekly sessions of group therapy, over a period of 14 weeks. Specifically, there will be 14 weekly sessions; one session per week for 14 weeks. Each session is 90 minutes long. Homework will be assigned each week. The homework will take approximately 20 minutes every week. Intervention will occur at multiple locations, including secondary mental health services (i.e. Child and Adolescent Mental Health Services, CAMHS), primary mental health services (e.g. Evolve in Wellington, a youth health and support agency), and secondary schools, in the Wellington region. 

Two facilitators will conduct each group, with 6 - 8 participants in a group. Facilitators will be trained in providing psychological treatment to mental health clients, and have a background or some experience in either Dialectical Behaviour Therapy or Acceptance and Commitment Therapy. At least one of the two facilitators of each ERGT group will be trained in ERGT, either at an ERGT training provided by Gratz and Tull, or training provided by the lead clinicians on the research team (Garisch and O'Connell). 

ERGT training will be run over 3 days. The training resources will include the treatment manual (which will be reviewed), including the client worksheets, and videos of either recorded sessions (with client consent) or videos of mock-ERGT sessions developed for the purposes of training. The training will be delivered face-to-face, and provided in a group setting (attendees will likely come for a range of service backgrounds, including primary and secondary services, and secondary schools). The three day training will occur over three consecutive days, from 9am - 5pm each day. Training will occur well in advance of the start of the intervention.

ERGT is aimed at developing clients' emotion regulation capacity. ERGT is aimed at helping clients respond to their emotions in more helpful ways, and learning to better understand the functions of emotions and what information may be gleaned from their emotional experience. The treatment includes psychoeducation regarding emotions, and goes through strategies to enable more healthy responses to emotions. Self-injury and its antecedents and consequences are discussed, as a way to determine what emotions may trigger self-injury, and how these emotional experiences and needs can be met in a healthier way. The later part of the group involves values work, and encouraging clients to act and make decisions in accordance with their values and goals, rather than fall into unhelpful responses to manage their emotional distress. 

Treatment as usual will be varied. All participants will need to be engaged in face-to-face work with a case manager or individual clinician. All ERGT participants will be engaged in TAU alongside completing ERGT, The ERGT group is a skills group, not a process group. All issues regarding process, and risk, will be managed by participants ordinary clinician and treatment team. 

Participants in the experimental group will also receive Treatment as Usual (TAU). We are testing whether ERGT improves reductions in NSSI over and above TAU alone. TAU is likely to be varied, and depend on the treatment site, severity of presentation, and the training background of participants' individual clinician or case manager. TAU is likely to include Cognitive Behavioural Therapy (CBT), treatment that includes components of Dialectical Behavioural Therapy (DBT) (i.e. DBT skills taught in individual face-to-face sessions), Acceptance and Commitment Therapy, and psychotherapy. TAU may also include a family therapy component, or psychological support for a primary caregiver (e.g. to assist in their response to their child's mental health concerns). 

TAU will continue for as long as required under treatment sites usual protocol (i.e. ordinarily until a client shows substantial benefit to no longer need service intervention, or until a participant or their family self-selects to discontinue treatment). The research study will follow participants for a minimum of 12 - 18 months, to enable to collection of follow-up data. 

Please note that this trial is in the early stages. Several factors may vary once initial groups have been conducted to 'pilot' ERGT in this population and check feasibility. For example, we may reduce the number of ERGT sessions, as the adult materials will be made shorter and less cognitively taxing, which may lead to less time needed to administer the skills group. </interventions>
    <comparator>The control treatment will be a form of psychological intervention for non-suicidal self-injury and comorbid conditions among adolescent users of primary and secondary mental health services, and secondary school pastoral care. This treatment is likely to be variable, depending on the treatment site, the severity of each participant's mental health presentation (which will likely determine treatment intensity), and the training background of the treating individual clinician or case manager. Treatment is likely to include CBT, DBT- based therapy, ACT, and psychotherapy. Treating clinicians will come from a range of training backgrounds including: clinical psychologists, social workers, psychiatrists, mental health nurses, family therapists, and psychotherapists.

TAU will continue for as long as required under treatment sites usual protocol (i.e. ordinarily until a client shows substantial benefit to no longer need service intervention, or until a participant or their family self-selects to discontinue treatment). The research study will follow participants for a minimum of 12 - 18 months, to enable to collection of follow-up data. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in self-reported non-suicidal self-injury behaviour, as measured by the Deliberate Self-Harm Inventory - 9 item version (DSHI-9; Lundh et al., 2007). 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at start of treatment/engagement in trial; at weekly intervals during ERGT, post-ERGT group (week 15), and at 3-, 6- and 12-month follow-up for all participants</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in self-reported emotion regulation as measured by the Difficulties in Emotion Regulation Scale (DERS; Gratz &amp; Roemer, 2004)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at the start of treatment/engagement in the trial, weekly during ERGT group, post-ERGT group (week 15), and at 3-, 6- and 12- month follow-up for all participants.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Medical intervention needed for NSSI behaviour as measured by participant, family or clinician self-report. This includes going to a doctor, nurse, or medical centre or hospital to address NSSI.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at the beginning of treatment, weekly during the course of ERGT group, and at 3-, 6- and 12 month follow-up. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depressive symptoms (Measured using the Depression, Anxiety and Stress Scales (DASS); Lovibond &amp; Lovibond, 1995).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at the beginning of treatment, weekly during the course of ERGT group, and at 3-, 6- and 12 month follow-up. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxious symptoms (measured using the Depression, Anxiety and Stress Scale (DASS); Lovibond &amp; Lovibond, 1995)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at the beginning of treatment, weekly during the course of ERGT group, and at 3-, 6- and 12 month follow-up. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Alcohol and Substance abuse and risky behaviours associated with misuse (measured using the CRAFFT)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at the beginning of treatment, weekly during the course of ERGT group, and at 3-, 6- and 12 month follow-up. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Intake criteria: Aged 14 - 19 years, current or recent NSSI, willingness to reduce self-injury, 3+ episodes of NSSI in the past year. engaged in treatment with an individual clinician, commitment to staying engaged in treatment. 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>14</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>19</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria: Autistic Spectrum Disorder, intellectual disability, patients unwilling to address their NSSI, engagement in another group therapy, engagement in another research trial, active psychosis, undergoing changes in medication, parents/caregiver unable to support them to attend therapy, actively suicidal requiring inpatient or residential care.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealed (by central randomisation by phone/fax/computer)</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using computer software</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Power analysis indicates that identifying a significant effect of ERGT equivalent to a reduction of one self-injury episode in a given evaluation period requires at least two groups of 32 participants each (total of 64 participants or more)20. We anticipate 40-48 ERGT participants and 40-48 matched controls (totalling 8096 participants) over a 24-month period. The number of participants will depend on funding. Currently we are awaiting outcome(s) of funding applications. If funding is limited, the trial is likely to occur over an extended period as funds and clinician time will be sparse.

Our methods of data analysis will be varied. We will conduct statistical analyses to determine group-level differences between the ERGT and TAU groups, and anticipate conducting multivariate analyses. If sample size allows, we will investigate variation in treatment effects based on treatment site location and/or client demographics (e.g. whether participants are attending primary or secondary services for individual therapy). We will also conduct focsu groups or interviews with participants who complete ERGT, to gain insight into participants' engagement with the ERGT materials, and the experience of participating in this research. We anticipate using content analysis and thematic analysis in regards to our qualitative data.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>2/09/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/12/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Marc Wilson</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Psychology, Victoria University of Wellington, Kelburn Parade, Kelburn, PO Box 600, Wellington, 6140, New Zealand</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Secondary services (e.g. CAMHS)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Child and Adolescent Services in the Wellington region. These are at multiple sites (e.g. Porirua, Wellington Central, and Hutt Valley). 

NB: These services will provide infrastructure support (including staff time, access to therapy rooms).</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Primary Services</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>These are multiple potential sites (e.g. Evolve Youth Service, Eva Street, Wellington; and Vibe Youth Service, Daly Street, Lower Hutt, Wellington).

NB: These services will provide infrastructure support (including staff time, access to therapy rooms).</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Secondary schools in the Wellington region</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>These are at multiple sites. We are unable to confirm were these will be at this stage.

NB: These services will provide infrastructure support (including staff time, access to therapy rooms).</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Jessica Garisch</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Psychology, Victoria University of Wellington, Kelburn Parade, Kelburn, PO Box 600, Wellington, 6140, New Zealand</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Victoria University of Wellington</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Psychology, Victoria University of Wellington, Kelburn Parade, Kelburn, PO Box 600, Wellington, 6140, New Zealand</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Adolescent non-suicidal self-injury (NSSI), damaging ones body without suicidal intent, is common in New Zealand and overseas. Up to half of NZ adolescents engage in NSSI once by age 18, with 20% harming themselves more frequently. Adolescents who engage in NSSI are at increased risk of a range of mental health concerns. Our research aims to assess the efficacy of an adolescent Emotion Regulation Group Therapy (ERGT) protocol developed to reduce NSSI among New Zealand primary and secondary health service clients and secondary school students. We propose running ERGT groups across a range of services, including primary health services in the community (e.g. those that cater to youth with mild to moderate mental health concerns), secondary services that cater to moderate to severe mental health issues (e.g. Child and Adolescent Mental Health Services attached to District Health Boards), and pastoral care departments in schools. 

ERGT was developed in the United States for adults who self-injure and have moderate to severe mental health needs (e.g. major depression, Borderline Personality Disorder, substance use disorders). Research trials have confirmed that ERGT significantly reduces NSSI among adults who self-injure, and that this reduction in NSSI behaviour is sustained over time. But we do not know whether ERGT will be effective with adolescents or whether it can be delivered successfully by a range of providers to young people across NZ. Our project aims to test its treatment potential.

We propose a randomized control trial of Emotion Regulation Group Therapy (ERGT) for adolescents, in collaboration with primary and secondary health services and secondary schools. Randomised control trials are the gold standard assessment of treatment efficacy.We will randomly assign participants to one of two groups, an 'experimental' group, which will receive treatment-as-usual and ERGT, and a treatment-as-usual control group. We will then conduct follow-up surveys to investigate whether outcomes differ across groups. Our hypothesis is that those receiving ERGT will have greater improvements in their wellbeing and greater reductions in their tendency to self-injure following completion of therapy, compared to participants receiving TAU alone.  We will also compare changes in depressive and anxious symptoms, engagement in other unhealthy behaviours (e.g. substance abuse), and capacity for emotion regulation in the two groups.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committee (HDEC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Health and Disability Ethics Committees
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6140</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/05/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Marc Wilson</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
Victoria University of Wellington
Kelburn Parade
PO Box 600
Wellington 6012
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 4 463 5225</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>marc.wilson@vuw.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jessica Garisch</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
Victoria University of Wellington
Kelburn Parade
PO Box 600
Wellington 6012
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+ 64 4 463 9657</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jessica.garisch@vuw.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Marc Wilson</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
Victoria University of Wellington
Kelburn Parade
PO Box 600
Wellington 6012
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+ 64 4 463 5225</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>marc.wilson@vuw.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jessica Garisch</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
Victoria University of Wellington
Kelburn Parade
PO Box 600
Wellington 6012
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+ 64 4 463 9657</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jessica.garisch@vuw.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>