<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336807">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/04/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/04/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000388910</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The utility of mobile phone in the prevention of coronary heart disease, through lifestyle modification  a prospective, randomised, controlled clinical trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>To assess the effectiveness of lifestyle modification messages delivered by SMS to patients following non-fatal cardiac events in reducing the frequency of future hospitalization for cardiovascular illness, and cardiac as well as all-cause mortality, Karachi Pakistan</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Mobile Phone to Prevent Cardiovascular Diseases (MoPCVD)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Coronary Heart Disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cardiac Rehabilitaion</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Epidemiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The mobile phones will be used to deliver Positive Behavioral Change/Positive Life style modification health messages by SMS, MMS, and Voice messages (especially for those who cannot read the text messages). These messages will be tailored to individual intervention group participants, using their name, and incorporating information specific to personal goals, culture, gender, age, and current health status.
Generic cardiovascular health messages are delivered 4 days/week and individually tailored, specific messages 2 days/week. 
The duration of the intervention will vary for the enrolled patients, as patients who will be enrolled at the initial phase of the study will have longer duration of the intervention it can be more than 12 months, but we intend to provide intervention to the last patient that we enroll for at least six months. The minimum intervention period is six months, and maximum period is 18 months.</interventions>
    <comparator>No mobile phone behavioural change message through SMS/MMS/voiceMail, without any interference in the standard of care.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mortality due to cardiovascular and related events as assessed by data linkage to medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>After Every 3 months after randomization (3, 6, 9, 12, 15 and 18 months, time point will varies for the patients according to the time of recruitment in the study), minimum of six months for the last patient recruited in the study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>All cause mortality as assessed by data linkage to medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>After Every 3 months after randomization (3, 6, 9, 12, 15 and 18 months, time point will varies for the patients according to the time of recruitment in the study), minimum of six months for the last patient recruited in the study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rehospitalisation after participating in the study as assessed by data linkage to medical records, and personal or information given by primary care givers</outcome>
      <timepoint>After Every 3 months after randomization (3, 6, 9, 12, 15 and 18 months, time point will varies for the patients according to the time of recruitment in the study), minimum of six months for the last patient recruited in the study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Normal Blood Pressure
Proportion of patients and primary carer who achieve a normal blood pressure (i.e. 90 - 140/60 - 90 mmHg) as assessed by mercury sphygmomanometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>After Every 3 months after randomization (3, 6, 9, 12, 15 and 18 months, time point will varies for the patients according to the time of recruitment in the study), minimum of six months for the last patient recruited in the study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Normal Lipid Levels
Proportion of patients and carer who achieve;
blood cholesterol (to less than 4 mmol/l or 152 mg/dl)
(or reduction of 25% in  total cholesterol, whichever achieves the lower absolute level, may be desirable goal)
Lowering LDL-cholesterol (to less than 2.0 mmol/l or 77 mg/dl)
(or reduction of 30% in LDL-cholesterol, whichever achieves the lower absolute level, may be desirable goal)
Increasing HDL-cholesterol (to more than 1.0 mmol/l or 40 mg/dl)</outcome>
      <timepoint>After Every 3 months after randomization (3, 6, 9, 12, 15 and 18 months, time point will varies for the patients according to the time of recruitment in the study), minimum of six months for the last patient recruited in the study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical Activity
Proportion of the patients and carer engaged in Physical Activity, at least for 30 minutes for most of the days, at least for 5 days, per week.
The physical activity will be assessed by the International Physical activity questionnaire (IPAQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>After Every 3 months after randomization (3, 6, 9, 12, 15 and 18 months, time point will varies for the patients according to the time of recruitment in the study), minimum of six months for the last patient recruited in the study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Healthy Dieatry Habits
Healthy Dietary Habits means reduction in saturated fat, red meat, sweets, and fast foods. Increased consumption of fruits, vegetables and nuts. The dietary habits would be assessed by the structured food frequency questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After Every 3 months after randomization (3, 6, 9, 12, 15 and 18 months, time point will varies for the patients according to the time of recruitment in the study), minimum of six months for the last patient recruited in the study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Normal Blood Glucose levels
Proportion of patients and primary carer who achieve normal blood glucose levels (i.e. 3.6 mmol/L (fasting) - 5.8 mmol/L(random)), as assessed by blood analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After Every 3 months after randomization (3, 6, 9, 12, 15 and 18 months, time point will varies for the patients according to the time of recruitment in the study), minimum of six months for the last patient recruited in the study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quit Tobacco smoking or chewing
Proportion of the patients and carer who remain never smoker, and patients who maintain quitting smoking. 
Tobacco use would be assessed by a validated structured questionnaire. We will use the smoking questionnaire developed by the Minnesota Heart Health survey (EPI/MHHP-Surv 005 6/88 Ver 14)</outcome>
      <timepoint>After Every 3 months after randomization (3, 6, 9, 12, 15 and 18 months, time point will varies for the patients according to the time of recruitment in the study), minimum of six months for the last patient recruited in the study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients who have been hospitalized at one of the participating tertiary care cardiac specific hospitals - (The Karachi Institute of Heart Disease, and the National Institute of the Cardiovascular Diseases in Karachi, Pakistan) with their first event (non-Fatal MI, CABG, PCI, stable and Unstable Angina)
Be of sound state of mind. 
Willing (consent) to participate in the study.
Stable cardiac status on hospital discharge.
Subject must own a personal mobile phone with a SIM/connection registered in their name.
Willing to retain the same SIM/connection for the period of the study, and if had to change the phone number agreed to notify the new number to the study center.
No life threatening significant co-morbidity such as terminal cancer. 
Primary care giver, nominated by the consented patient
Care giver willing (consent) to participate in the study
Primary care giver does not have coronary artery disease</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Do not give consent to participate in the study
Not in a stable state of mind
Pregnant females
Dont have a personal mobile phone and not willing to acquire one.
Life threatening illness, e.g., terminal stage of cancer etc.
Primary care giver have coronary artery disease</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The study subjects will be the diagnosed patients of CAD, admitted in the study participating tertiary care hospitals, and discharged from the hospital in stable condition. Subjects willing to participate, and prepared to give a blood sample for laboratory investigations. We will allocate each participant through randomization, either to intervention group, those who will receive behavioural change/life style modification education through mobile phone, or in the usual standard of care group (non-intervention group, without interfering in their usual treatment).
The research assistants who will recruit the study participants will randomize them by using a sequence of opaque sealed envelopes containing the allocation for each patient. The randomization will be concealed from the research assistants, and created and maintained by the supervisor at Australian School of Advanced Medicine, Macquarie University Sydney, N.S.W. Australia.</concealment>
    <sequence>The patient allocation will be carried out through permuted block randomization to ensure a balance in the patients to each group. Varying block sizes of 4, 6, and 8 will be used and both the allocation within the blocks and the block order will be randomized to create the allocation table. The research assistants who will recruit the study participants will randomize them by using a sequence of opaque sealed envelopes containing the allocation for each patient. The randomization will be concealed from the research assistants, and created and maintained by the supervisor at Australian School of Advanced Medicine, Macquarie University Sydney, N.S.W. Australia.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/06/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>3400</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Pakistan</country>
      <state>Sindh</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Macquarie University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Australian school of Advanced Medicine
Macquarie University
Balaclava road, North Ryde, NSW 2109</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Macquarie University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Australian school of Advanced Medicine
Macquarie University
Balaclava road, North Ryde, NSW 2109</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Karachi Institute of Heart Diseases</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of medical research &amp; CME
ST 15, Block 16
Federal B. Area, Karachi 75950
Sindh</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Pakistan</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>PROBLEM STATEMENT: Cardiovascular disease (CVD) is the leading cause of death globally, responsible for 30% of all cause mortality. According to World Health Organization (No. 317, Jan. 2011) 82% of CVD deaths take place in low- and middle-income countries and occur almost equally in men and women. The largest burden is in South Asia (Pakistan, India, Sri Lanka, Bangladesh, Nepal), where it occurs more frequently in much younger ages as compared to the Western population. Preventive strategies (primary and secondary) have been met with limited success due to the cost and difficulty in healthcare delivery. Mobile phone text messaging (SMS/MMS/Voice messages) demonstrates strong potential as a tool for health care improvement for several reasons; it is available in almost every model of mobile phone, the cost is very low, its use is widespread, it does not require great technological expertise, and it is widely applicable to a variety of health behaviors and conditions
METHODOLOGY: Primary Goal:  To assess the effectiveness of lifestyle modification messages delivered by SMS/MMS/Voice mail to patients following non-fatal cardiac events in reducing future hospitalizations, nonfatal and fatal cardiovascular events, as well as all-cause mortality.
It is a Prospective, Multicenter, Randomized, Controlled health intervention clinical trial. The patients hospitalized with their first cardiac event (nonfatal MI, CABG, PCI, unstable angina) will be recruited from the participating tertiary care cardiac specific hospitals  the Karachi Institute of Heart Disease and the National Institute of Cardiovascular Diseases in Karachi, Pakistan. We will randomize each participant to either the intervention group, i.e. those who will receive behavioural change/life style modification education through mobile phone, or to the usual standard of care group (control or non-intervention group). The patient allocation will be carried out through permuted block randomization to ensure a balance in the patients to each group. The participants will be requested to nominate a carer (close relative or friend) who are the persons responsible for taking day-to-day care of the patients at home. The carer will be allocated the same group as their respective patients. Those carers will be our primary prevention group and will go through the same examinations and follow ups as the patients (secondary prevention) group.

Based on power analysis a total of 1540 patients (770 in the intervention and 770 non-intervention groups) and their respective carers (n: 1540 as well) will be enrolled over 12 to 16 months. All patients will be followed up for a minimum of 6 to 9 months (range 21 to 6 months).   

A regular mobile phone messages (SMS/MMS/Voice mail) regarding lifestyle modification will be delivered to patients of intervention group, and one of their carer. The mobile phone message based rehabilitation program will be structured according to the latest guidelines developed by the WHO for the prevention of cardiovascular disease.

Blood samples will be drawn to investigate lipid profile, HbA1c, blood sugar, and urinary urea creatinine etc at regular designated intervals.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>The study proposal was presented at the faculty meeting by Co-Investigator (Dr. Javed Ismail), as a part requirement of his PhD candidature, at Macquarie University Sydney Australia, on 9th March 2011.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Macquarie University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Macquarie University
Human Research Ethics Commitee
NSW, Sydney</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/04/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>5201100109</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/02/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Hosen Kiat</name>
      <address>Australian School of Advanced Medicine
Cardiac health Institute (CHI)
Suite 202, Level 2
2 technology Place
Macquarie University, NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>(+61 2) 9858 9898</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hosen.kiat@chi.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Javed Ismail</name>
      <address>Australian School of Advanced Medicine
Cardiac health Institute (CHI)
Suite 202, Level 2
2 technology Place
Macquarie University, NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>(+61 2) 9858 9898</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>javed.ismail@students.mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Javed Ismail</name>
      <address>Australian School of Advanced Medicine
Cardiac health Institute (CHI)
Suite 202, Level 2
2 technology Place
Macquarie University, NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>(+61 2) 9858 9898</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>javed.ismail@students.mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>