<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366921">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/10/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/10/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001119684</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of osteopathic manual therapy with breathing re-training on dysfunctional breathing, exercise economy and the autonomic nervous system</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of osteopathic manual therapy with breathing re-training on symptoms of dysfunctional breathing, exercise economy and heart rate variability in active adults</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Dysfunctional Breathing</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of the normal brain and nervous system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Osteopathic Manual Therapy + Breathing Re-training

Osteopathic Manual Therapy is provided by qualified, experienced osteopaths. Therapy will entail a semi-structured 30-minute osteopathy treatment administered weekly for 4 weeks. Treatment will consist of a selection of manual techniques applied mainly to the neck, thorax, lower back and abdomen with postural advice if indicated.

For breathing re-training, participants will be instructed through an individually-paced, progressive programme. Final year osteopathy students will assess the breathing function of participants at study onset and provide instruction for breathing re-training techniques in a 15-minute session. Participants will be asked to practice these techniques as often as possible, incorporated into their normal daily activities, but at least for 10 minutes, 2x per day for 4 weeks. They will also have access to an online video demonstrating these techniques that they can refer to.

Compliance to the breathing retraining will be retrospectively monitored weekly by osteopath practitioners. Practitioners will complete standardised treatment notes for each osteopathy treatment session. Both the structural changes and breathing retraining outcomes will be monitored.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants are randomised to immediate or 4-week delayed start of treatment. The group randomised to delayed start will act as a control group for the period of the delay.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-Evaluation of Breathing Questionnaire (SEBQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Exercise Economy at 3 individually-prescribed workloads

Workload intensity will be determined from a prior VO2max test completed on a cycle ergometer. After completing a 5-minute warm-up, participants will complete 3, 5-minute cycling exercise bouts at individually-prescribed workloads, undertaken consecutively without rest, at a constant pedal cadence of 70 revolutions per minute, and equating to approximately 40%, 55% and 70% of VO2max.

Exercise economy will be assessed by quantifying average oxygen consumption in the final 3 minutes of each exercise bout, measured using a Moxus metabolic cart.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resting heart-rate variability

Heart-rate variability will be recorded for 7 days, for 6 minutes upon waking. Data is measured via Polaris RS800 heart rate monitor using Kubios heart-rate variability analysis software.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nijmegen Questionnaire (for hyperventilation syndrome)</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resting peak expiratory flow rate (PEFR)

Measured via hand-held spirometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resting forced expiratory volume in 1 s (FEV1)

Measured via hand-held spirometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resting forced vital capacity (FVC)

Measured via hand-held spirometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resting upper chest to abdomen breathing distension</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks

Assessed via respiratory inductive plethysmography. This device measures the circumference and change in distension of the upper and lower chest.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Breath-hold time</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks

Timed, using a stopwatch, at the end of a normal tidal volume expiration (at functional residual capacity).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Post-exercise heart rate recovery

Measured, using a Polaris RS800 heart-rate monitor, as change in heart-rate over 3 minutes immediately following the completion of all 3 exercise bouts, whilst sitting stationary on the cycle ergometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resting heart rate

Measured via Polaris RS800 heart-rate monitor as average heart-rate over 7 days, for 6 minutes upon waking.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resting end tidal CO2

Measured using a Moxus metabolic cart and open-circuit spirometry, for 30 s prior to warm-up whilst sitting stationary on a cycle ergometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Borg Ratings of Perceived Exertion (RPE) Scale

Assessed at 3 minutes and 5 minutes of each 5 minute exercise bout at individually-prescribed workloads equating to approximately 40%, 55% and 70% of VO2max, cycling at a constant pedal cadence of 70 revolutions per minute.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>*Participate in aerobic exercise for more than 4 hours per week
*Body mass index no less than 18.5 kg/m2 and not greater than 30 kg/m2
*Perceive that breathing may be limiting their sporting performance
*Understand written and verbal English
*Upon screening, exhibit an SEBQ score of 10 or greater
*In a Functional Movement Screen, exhibit a dysfunction in the neck, thoracic or lumbar region</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>19</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>*Current smoker or smoked in last 6 months
*Respiratory-related hospitalisations in the last 6 months
*Diagnosed emotional disorders
*Diagnosed cardiac condition or dysfunction
*Diagnosed autonomic nervous system pathology or dysfunction</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation involved contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who was not involved in participant recruitment and not in contact with prospective participants.</concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted block randomisation using the website http://www.randomization.org</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Participants were randomly assigned to 4-week delayed start of treatment, thus creating a randomised controlled trial for the first 4 weeks of treatment. All participants eventually received 4 weeks of treatment. Secondary analysis of the whole cohort was also performed.

Participants were not told that some were being deliberately randomised to a delayed start.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Mixed ANOVA model (1 repeated-measures factor and 1 independent measures factor) for RCT analysis.

Paired t-tests for single cohort analysis.

A sample size of 15 for the entire cohort would be required to detect change effect sizes of 0.8, assuming a level of significance of 0.05 and statistical power of 0.8. An effect size of 0.8 equates to a change of approximately 9 points in SEBQ (Mitchell &amp; Technology, 2011) or 0.2 L/min in VO2 (Bacon, Myers, &amp; Karageorghis, 2012) for economy. Because participants are randomised into two groups, requiring an even number, and some people may not be able to complete the study (Immediate- and Delayed-Start), an initial sample size of 18 is proposed. It is acknowledged that the power to detect differences between the two groups in the RCT analysis allowed by the design is more limited with only 8 participants per group. Nonetheless, an effect size of 1.6, equating to a difference in SEBQ of 18.4 and in economy 0.4 L/min could still be detected.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>27/10/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>16/11/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>2/04/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>25/05/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>18</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>19</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland region</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Unitec Institute of Technology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Carrington Rd, Mt Albert
Private Bag 92025
Victoria Street West
Auckland 1142</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Unitec Institute of Technology</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Carrington Rd, Mt Albert
Private Bag 92025
Victoria Street West
Auckland 1142</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aims of this study are to assess the effect of osteopathic treatment and breathing re-training on symptoms associated with dysfunctional breathing, exercise economy, and cardiac variables as indices of autonomic nervous system activity.

Dysfunctional breathing is thought to entail mechanically inefficient ventilation, and often to come about as a result of chronic psychological stress or anxiety. Therefore, we hypothesise improvements in exercise economy and lowered sympathetic drive following osteopathy treatment and breathing re-training.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Unitec Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Office and Postgraduate Centre
Unitec Institute of Technology
Carrington Rd, Mt Albert
Private Bag 92025
Victoria Street West
Auckland 1142</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/05/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2013-1080</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/11/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Catherine Bacon</name>
      <address>Unitec Institute of Technology,
Carrington Rd, Mt Albert,
Private Bag 92025
Victoria Street West,
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 9 849 6794</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cbacon@unitec.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Catherine Bacon</name>
      <address>Unitec Institute of Technology,
Carrington Rd, Mt Albert,
Private Bag 92025
Victoria Street West,
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 9 849 6794</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cbacon@unitec.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Catherine Bacon</name>
      <address>Unitec Institute of Technology,
Carrington Rd, Mt Albert,
Private Bag 92025
Victoria Street West,
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 9 849 6794</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cbacon@unitec.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Catherine Bacon</name>
      <address>Unitec Institute of Technology,
Carrington Rd, Mt Albert,
Private Bag 92025
Victoria Street West,
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 9 815 6794</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cbacon@unitec.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>