<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373350">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/07/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/08/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001139369</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Fibre supplementation and gut health in healthy females</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of fibre supplementation on gut microbiota in healthy females</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1199-6780</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Gut microbiota</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Immune system - Peripheral blood mononuclear cells</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the immune system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal oral and gastrointestinal development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Healthy subjects, 35-65 years, BMI 18-25kg/m2 will be recruited to determine which type of fibre supplement is more efficient at increasing short chain fatty acids (SCFAs) and bacterial diversity in healthy humans.

Each participant will be studied on 3 x 7 day occasions, such that over the experiment they will receive all 3 fibre supplements in random order. The 3 fibre supplements will include Fibremax (New Image), Vitafiber (Myprotein) and Inulin (Myprotein). Each 7 day fibre supplementation period will be separated by a washout period of 2 weeks. 

Participants will be asked to consume daily the 34g of fibreMax, 15g of Vitafiber or 12g of Inulin supplement per day during the treatment period. Participants will be requested to consume a standardised diet where they will be asked to exclude fibre-rich foods (beans, high-fibre cereals and bars), dietary supplements, pre and probiotic foods and supplements, antibiotics and anti-inflammatory drugs throughout the protocol.. 

The intervention will be run by a qualified research dietitian with 5 years research experience and qualified research nutritionist with 10 years experience in running dietary interventions. Participants will be asked to keep a 4 day food diary prior to and in the last 4 days of each 7 day fibre supplementation period in addition to keeping a record of the time each fibre supplement was taken and any symptoms. Participants will also be asked to return their fibre supplements for measurement at the end of each 7 day supplementation period. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>The trial is a randomised crossover-trial, each participant will take each of the 3 supplements.. The 3 fibre supplements will be compared to each other.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gut microbiome will be assessed from bacterial DNA extracted from stool sample. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants will be asked to collect one stool sample in the 2 days before each supplementation period and in the last 2 days of each supplementation period.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasting serum levels of short chain fatty acids.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Fasted serum samples will be collected prior to supplementation on day 1 of each supplementation period and the day following each 7-day supplementation period. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasting plasma immune cell populations.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Fasted plasma samples will be collected prior to supplementation on day 1 of each supplementation period and the day following each 7-day supplementation period. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Habitual diet</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants will be asked to keep a 6 x 4 day food diaries to record their dietary intake 4 days prior to and during the last 4 days of each 7 day fibre supplementation period. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria: Healthy females, 35-65 years, BMI 18-25kg/m2</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>35</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria will include pregnancy or planning pregnancy, breastfeeding, known diabetes, known unstable or untreated blood pressure or cholesterol, cardiovascular disease, chronic inflammatory conditions, medications that may interfere with metabolism, smoking, alcohol consumption above current NHMRC guidelines, allergy or intolerance to foods, irregular eating patterns or eating disorder, following a weight reducing diet, use of antibiotics 4 weeks prior to the start of the study and during the study. Individuals taking anti-inflammatory drugs will also be excluded from the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation will be concealed. Concealment will be performed using sealed opaque numbered envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>Groups will be randomized to each intervention using permuted block randomisation. One random block of 10 will be generated using the R package “blockrand”. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>30 women aged between 35-65 will be recruited. We estimate a drop-out rate of approximately 10%. If we make the assumption of a within-subject correlation of our outcome of 0.5 (SD between supplement group for acetate changes of 42), we will need 30 subjects per group to detect a difference with 80% power and a bilateral alpha risk of 5%.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/06/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/06/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Sydney
NSW, 2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Medical Foundation, The University of Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The University of Sydney
NSW, 2006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Not applicable</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Not applicable</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Gut microbiota is highly influenced by environmental factors particularly the diet and its dietary fibre content. Dietary fibre is non-digestible polysaccharide fermented by gut bacteria, subsequently releasing short chain fatty acids, critical for health. Dietary fibre promotes beneficial gut microbiota. However, the potency of different types of fibre to reshape gut microbial population and to boost the release of short chain fatty acids is unknown. While fibre is found in grains and legumes it can be hard to evaluate which type of fibre is present and how much is consumed. The aim of the current study is to test dietary fibre supplements which are affordable and easily quantifiable to determine which type of fibre supplement might be the most beneficial for gut and overall health.

30 women aged between 35-65 years will be recruited. The study will be a randomised open crossover fibre supplementation trial. Each participant will be studied on 3 occasions, such that over the experiment they will receive all 3 fibre supplements in random order.
The 3 fibre supplements will include Fibremax (New Image), Vitafiber (Myprotein) and Inulin (Myprotein). Participants will be asked to consume daily the 34g of FibreMax, 15g of Vitafiber or 12g of Inulin supplement per day during the treatment period. Participants will be requested to consume a standardised diet that excludes fibre rich foods (beans, high fibre cereals and bars), dietary supplements, pre and probiotic foods and supplements, antibiotics and anti-inflammatory drugs. Participants will attend an RPA blood collection centre where they will complete 6 x blood collections and the RPA clinic at the Charles Perkins Center on 7 occasions where they will be asked to complete 6 x stool collections and 6 x 4 d food diaries. Participants will first attend a screening interview where they will be asked to complete questionnaires on their medical history, medications, and eating behaviours. Two weeks before the start of the first supplementation period, participants will be asked to consume a standardized diet and will then to undergo 3 x 7 d fibre supplementation periods that will each be separated by 2week washout periods. The blood and stool samples will be used to measure short chain fatty acid levels, microbial diversity in response to dietary fibre supplementation. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>Not applicable</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Not applicable</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Local Health District - RPAH</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research and Ethics Governance Office
RPAH Medical Centre
Suite 210A, 100 Carillion Avenue
NEWTOWN, NSW, 2042</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/07/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Protocol No X17-0130 &amp; HREC/17/RPAH/192</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/04/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Laurence Macia</name>
      <address>Charles Perkins Centre
Building D17
The University of Sydney
Camperdown NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8627 1975</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>laurence.macia@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Laurence Macia</name>
      <address>Charles Perkins Centre
Building D17
The University of Sydney
Camperdown NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8627 1975</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>laurence.macia@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Laurence Macia</name>
      <address>Charles Perkins Centre
Building D17
The University of Sydney
Camperdown NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8627 1975</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>laurence.macia@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alison Gosby</name>
      <address>Charles Perkins Centre
Building D17
The University of Sydney
Camperdown NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 86271689</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alison.gosby@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>