<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347532">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/09/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/10/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611001040954</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised, parallel controlled trial on the effect of heated humidification on patient comfort and facial temperature in patients on non-invasive ventilation, using an oro-nasal facemask.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of heated humidification during non-invasive ventilation on patient comfort with acute exacerbations of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD) and Obesity Hypoventilation Syndrome (OHS).</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1124-8817</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD)</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Obesity Hypoventilation Syndrome (OHS)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: Heated humidifier and heated respiratory circuit
A controlled, parallel study.
Patients already prescribed non-invasive ventilation (NIV) are randomised to 2 arms; humidified and non-humidified NIV. Patients are given up to 24 hours to stabilise on NIV, once they are stable on NIV they are asked if they want to take part in the study.
Patients in the humidified arm receive 4 hours of NIV, delivered from a standard hospital NIV ventilator, using the study heated humidifier, heated circuit and mask. The humidifier is turned off and does not contain any water as a washout, to establish a baseline. After 4 hours water is added to the heated humidifier and it is switched on and remains on for the following 8 hour treatment. In this intervention group the  gas is heated and humidified to 31 degrees C, 32mg/L water.


Patients in the non-humidified arm receive 4 hours of NIV, delivered from a standard hospital NIV ventilator, using the study heated humidifier, heated circuit and mask. The humidifier is turned off and does not contain any water as a washout, to establish a baseline. The humidifier remains switched off with no water in it for the 12 hours of the study, 4 hour washout and 8 hours treatment.</interventions>
    <comparator>The placebo is 8 hours of non-invasive ventilation delivered by the same equipment but without adding water to it to provide humidity or turning the heater on.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 1: Change in patient comfort score on a visual analogue scale of 1-10 after the treatment, compared to the baseline reading prior to the treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: At 8 hours of treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 1: Change in patient comfort score on a visual analogue scale of 1-10 during the treatment, compared to the baseline reading prior to the treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: At 4 hours of treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 2: Change in NIV side effects, as determined by a patient questionnaire, compared to the baseline reading prior to the treatment. 

Patients are asked on a 0-4 scale (0= not a problem, 1=slight problem, 2=moderate problem, 3= major problem, 4=NIV use suspended because of it).
The side effects assessed are: 1. pressure from mask or straps, 2. airleaks, 3. air pressure too high, 4. machine noise, 5. claustrophobia, 6. dry mouth or throat, 7. mouth or throat too hot, 8. runny nose, 9. congested nose, 10. nose bleeds, 11. head ache, 12. chest discomfort, 13. mask coming off face, 14. skin irritation under mask, 15. skin too hot under mask, 16. too hot generally.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: At 4 hours and 8 hours of treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 3: Number and timing of breaks from NIV over the 8 hours of treatment, and the reason.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: Throughout the 8 hours of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 4: Change in patient skin facial temperature on the cheek, outside of the mask, compared to the baseline reading prior to the treatment. 
A temperature probe (thermocouple) will be temporarily taped to the patient's face using hypoallergenic tape and a reading taken, using a Fisher and Paykel Healthcare Thermister reader (TM101)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: At 4 hours and 8 hours of treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 5: Change in patient skin facial temperature on the chin, inside of the mask, compared to the baseline reading prior to the treatment.
A temperature probe (thermocouple) will be temporarily taped to the patient's face using hypoallergenic tape and a reading taken, using a Fisher and Paykel Healthcare Thermister reader (TM101)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: At 4 hours and 8 hours of treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 6: Change in patient core temperature, as determined by an ear thermometer, compared to the baseline reading prior to the treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: At 4 hours and 8 hours of treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Acute ventilatory failure in patients with Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD) or Obesity Hypoventilation Syndrome (OHS), or overlap syndrome (COPD and OHS)
2. NIV has been commenced on clinical grounds, in consultation with a Respiratory Physician
3. The patient has shown an initial positive clinical response to NIV
4. Patient has a good understanding of English
5. Patient is capable of giving informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. NIV is medically contraindicated
2. Delirium, dementia or confusion due to any cause   
3. Patients considered as palliative
4. Kyphoscoliosis
5. Neuromuscular disease
6. Motor neuron disease
7. Cardiogenic pulmonary oedema
8. Unstable coronary disease
9. Facial deformity 
10. Pneumothorax
11. NIV failure in the first hour (either intolerance or requirement for intubation)
12. Patient previously enrolled in the study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients who fit the inclusion criteria and are stabilised on NIV within 24 hours of being in the respiratory ward are asked whether they would like to take part in the study. Allocation is according to a table of randomised treatments; Treatment A or Treatment B.
Allocation is not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>22/08/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>22/08/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>20/07/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>42</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Counties Manukau District Health Board</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Middlemore Hospital, 
Hospital Road, 
Otahuhu, 
Auckland,1640</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Fisher and Paykel Healthcare</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>15, Maurice Paykel Place, 
East Tamaki, 
Auckland 2013</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Diana Hart</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Middlemore Hospital, 
Hospital Road, 
Otahuhu, 
Auckland,1640</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Fisher and Paykel Healthcare</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>15, Maurice Paykel Place,
East Tamaki,
Auckland 2013</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Non-invasive ventilation (NIV) provides respiratory support through the patients upper airway using a facemask. NIV is beneficial for some patients, such as those with an exacerbation of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), or obesity hyperventilation syndrome (OHS). Many patients find NIV therapy uncomfortable and difficult to tolerate due to the high pressures and flows of cold gas. Consequently, the success of NIV, and ultimately patient outcome, can be influenced by how much a patient uses it.  

To improve patient tolerance the gas supplied during NIV may be heated and humidified to 31degrees C/ 32mg/L water, although there is little clinical data to support this for this therapy. Patient tolerance is improved because heating and humidifying the gas minimises airway drying and improves secretion clearance from the patients airways, stopping them from becoming dry and sore and making it easier for them to cough up secretions. However, some patients complain of being too hot on NIV and using heated humidification may contribute to this.   
We will test patient comfort, perception of heat, and facial temperature, related to core body temperature, during NIV with and without heated humidification. We will assess the benefits to patients of supplying heated humidification with this therapy.
This study will take place exclusively in the respiratory ward (ward 7) of Middlemore Hospital. Only patients already prescribed NIV by a respiratory physician will be eligible for the study. Patients are given up to 24 hours to stabilise on NIV, once they are stable on NIV they are asked if they want to take part in the study. After the study patients will continue on NIV as prescribed by the respiratory physician. They may stay on the study equipment or use the standard hospital NIV equipment, which they will have been on prior to being recruited on to the study.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication> Hart D, O'Dochartaigh C, Beaumont-Orr S, Lorimer J. The effects of heated humidification on patients on noninvasive ventilation (NIV) for acute ventilatory failure.  European Respiratory Society Meeting, Barcelona. P2483. Sept 2013.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Upper South A Regional Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Montgomery Watson Building,
6 Hazeldean Road,
Christchurch, 8023</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/07/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>URA/11/07/028</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/06/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Diana Hart</name>
      <address>Third Floor, Support Building,
Middlemore Hospital,
Hospital Road,
Otahuhu,
Auckland, 1640</address>
      <phone>+64 9 276 0044 ext 2036</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 276 0249</fax>
      <email>diana.hart@middlemore.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Diana Hart</name>
      <address>Third Floor, Support Building,
Middlemore Hospital,
Hospital Road,
Otahuhu,
Auckland, 1640</address>
      <phone>+64 9 276 0044 ext 2036</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 276 0249</fax>
      <email>diana.hart@middlemore.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Joanne Lorimer</name>
      <address>Fisher and Paykel Healthcare
15, Maurice Paykel Place,
East Tamaki,
Auckland 2013</address>
      <phone>+64 9 574 0123 ext 8329</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 574 0158</fax>
      <email>joanne.lorimer@fphcare.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Mrs Diana Hart</name>
      <address>Third Floor, Support Building, Middlemore Hospital, Hospital Road, Otahuhu, Auckland, 1640</address>
      <phone>+64 9 276 0044 ext 2036</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>diana.hart@middlemore.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>