<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336959">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/08/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/08/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000898954</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Supporting breastfeeding In Local Communities (SILC)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In defined Victorian Local Government Areas (LGAs) with low breastfeeding rates, are home-based breastfeeding support visits by a Maternal and Child Health Nurse (MCHN) with or without access to a community-based breastfeeding drop-in centre effective in increasing the amount of any breastfeeding by 10% at four months of age compared to LGAs which offer standard care?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1122-0768</utrn>
    <trialacronym>SILC</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Breastfeeding</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast feeding</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>There are two intervention groups. One group receives early home-based breastfeeding support by a Maternal and Child Health Nurse (MCHN). The second intervention group receives early home-based breastfeeding support by a MCHN and  access to a community-based breastfeeding drop-in centre. 

Participating MCHNs will have clinical experience in diagnosing and managing common breastfeeding problems: insufficient milk, perceived insufficient milk, nipple pain and damage, breast engorgement and mastitis, nipple/breast thrush, infant tongue-tie. They will assist the mother by giving advice and support, and suggesting appropriate referrals where necessary. It will be up to the allocated MCHN to determine the number and timing of support visits for each woman referred, however, it is anticipated that on average this will be two visits. It is anticipated that up to a third of women in intervention LGAs are likely to receive the home visiting intervention.

The second intervention group will also have access to a community-based breastfeeding drop-in centre. These drop-in centres will operate for the duration of the trial intervention and women can visit them as many times as they wish. The number of days and hours the drop-in centres operate will be affected by number of births in the LGA and availability of a venue.</interventions>
    <comparator>Women in control LGAs will have access to the current breastfeeding support that is available in their communities as well as by telephone outside their communities. This includes usual breastfeeding support provided by MCHNs (encompassing breastfeeding assessment, support and advice as a core component of care); the 24 hour Maternal Child Health line; the 24 hour Australian Breastfeeding Association helpline; and support by general practitioners and other health professionals as usual.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of infants receiving 'any' breast milk at four months of age. Breastfeeding outcomes will be obtained from routinely collected Maternal and Child Health (MCH) centre data. For the period of the study, a new data item will be added to collect information on infant feeding 'in the last 24 hours'. This data item will be collected at the routine MCHN appointment when infants are four months of age.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Four months postpartum</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of infants receiving 'any' breast milk at six months of age. Breastfeeding outcomes will be obtained from routinely collected Maternal and Child Health (MCH) centre data. Information will also be obtained via a postal survey to women who give birth during the intervention time-frame in the participating LGAs when their infants are six months of age.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Six months postpartum</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  LGAs with a low breastfeeding rate for any breastfeeding at discharge from hospital 

- LGAs who agree to participate and be randomised</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- LGAs with substantial initiatives (at the time of LGA selection) to increase breastfeeding duration or other substantial early childhood interventions 

- LGAs where participation is not feasible given the low number of births</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The trial uses a three-arm cluster randomised controlled trial (RCT) design. The unit of randomisation will be the LGA. Eligible LGAs will be randomly allocated to one of three trial arms: standard care; home-based breastfeeding support by a MCHN; or home-based breastfeeding support by a MCHN plus access to a community-based breastfeeding drop-in centre.  

Allocation to trial arms is concealed and will take place at a public forum to which representatives from participating LGAs will be invited. During this forum, allocation to the trial arms will be achieved using sealed opaque envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>Eligible LGAs will be randomly allocated to one of the three trial arms; stratified by metropolitan/rural status. A computer generated randomisation program will be used to conduct the randomisation, administered by an independent statistician. LGAs allocated to the intervention arms will implement the interventions.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1500</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Mother &amp; Child Health Research, La Trobe University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Mother &amp; Child Health Research
La Trobe University
Level 3
215 Franklin St
Melbourne 
VIC 3000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Education and Early Childhood Development</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>2 Treasury Place
East Melbourne
VIC 3002</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Department of Education and Early Childhood Development</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>2 Treasury Place
East Melbourne
VIC 3002</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The Victorian Governments commitment to improving breastfeeding rates includes the development of the Victorian Breastfeeding Action Plan. The Victorian Breastfeeding Research Project (SILC project ) is part of this action plan. 

The SILC project will assess strategies to increase the maintenance of breastfeeding. The research will consist of a three arm cluster randomised control trial. It will determine if home visiting by a Maternal and Child Health Nurse (MCHN) for women with breastfeeding issues increases the maintenance of breastfeeding, and then if a drop-in centre additional to the home-visiting further enhances breastfeeding rates. 

The three arms of the trial will consist of a comparison (control) group receiving standard care, a targeted home-visiting group receiving home-based breastfeeding support visits by a MCHN and the third group receiving the targeted home visits plus access to a facilitated local drop-in centre.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Amir, LH et al. Breastfeeding in Victoria: A Report. http://www.eduweb.vic.gov.au/edulibrary/public/stuman/wellbeing/breastfeeding_vic_report.pdf</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>La Trobe University Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>La Trobe University
Bundoora
VIC 3086</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/11/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/09/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Department of Education and Early Childhood Development</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>2 Treasury Place
East Melbourne
VIC 3002</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/10/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/09/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Helen McLachlan</name>
      <address>Mother &amp; Child Health Research
Level 3
215 Franklin St
La Trobe University
Melbourne
VIC 3000</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9479 8788</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9479 8811</fax>
      <email>h.mclachlan@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Meabh Cullinane</name>
      <address>Mother &amp; Child Health Research
Level 3
215 Franklin St
La Trobe University
Melbourne
VIC 3000</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9479 8778  </phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9479 8811  </fax>
      <email>m.cullinane@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Meabh Cullinane</name>
      <address>Mother &amp; Child Health Research
Level 3
215 Franklin St
La Trobe University
Melbourne
VIC 3000</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9479 8778</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9479 8811</fax>
      <email>m.cullinane@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Helen McLachlan</name>
      <address>Mother &amp; Child Health Research Level 3 215 Franklin St La Trobe University Melbourne VIC 3000  </address>
      <phone>+61 3 9479 8788</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>h.mclachlan@latrobe.edu.au  </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>