<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83513">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/02/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/03/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000140257</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effects of a wild oat extract on cerebral blood flow, cognitive performance and psychological well-being in Australian adults.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of Neuravena 'registered trade mark' (wild oat extract) on cerebral blood flow, blood pressure responses, cognitive performance and psychological well-being in Australian adults with mild cognitive impairment (MCI).</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Mild Cognitive Impairment</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Volunteers will be required to consume two doses of Neuravena 'registered trade mark' (1500 or 2400 mg of Avena sativa extract (Neuravena 'registered trade mark' ). This supplement will be delivered orally in capsule form.
There will be three separate visits to the Nutritional Physiology Research Centre (of 1 - 2 hours duration each) which will occur with a minimum one-week washout between visits. At each visit the participant will consume one dose of Neuravena 'registered trade mark'  (or placebo) per visit.
At 60 min after supplement consumption tests of short-term memory and working memory will be administered. This will be followed by the completion of a time-pressured cognitive test, the Paced Auditory Serial Addition Task (PASAT) and a subsequent carbon dioxide (CO2) challenge whilst assessing cerebral blood flow, heart rate and blood pressure. Participants will then complete the Depression Anxiety Stress Scale (DASS). These measures will be repeated at each visit.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo capsules are identical in appearance to the active capsules but contain an inert filler consisting of Calcium Hydrogen Phosphate, microcrystalline cellulose (MCC) of various particle sizes including Prosolv 50 and talcum powder (hydrated magnesium silicate). 
There are a total of three testing visits for this trial. Two will include the consumption of a single dose of Neuravena® and one will be the placebo and each visit will be one week apart At 60 min after placebo consumption tests of short-term memory and working memory will be administered. This will be followed by the completion of a time-pressured cognitive test, the Paced Auditory Serial Addition Task (PASAT) and a subsequent carbon dioxide (CO2) challenge whilst assessing cerebral blood flow, heart rate and blood pressure. Participants will then complete the Depression Anxiety Stress Scale (DASS).</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Degree of change in cerebral blood flow assessed by Transcranial Doppler (TCD) Sonography in the Middle Cerebral Artery (MCA).</outcome>
      <timepoint>There will be three time points which will occur one week apart. At each visit testing will commence 60 minutes after consumption of either Neuravena or placebo.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Degree of change in performance on cognitive stress tasks assessed by administration of the Paced Auditory Serial Addition Task (PASAT)and the The Stroop test. Degree of changes in short-term memory, spatial memory and working memory tasks assessed by Digits Forwards, Digits Backwards and Letter-Number sequencing from the Wechsler Adults Intelligence Scale (WAIS-III) and the Spatial Span subscale from the Wechsler Memory Scale (WMS-III).</outcome>
      <timepoint>There will be three time points which will occur one week apart. At each visit testing will commence 60 minutes after consumption of either Neuravena or placebo.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Degree of change in psychological well-being assessed by administration of the Depression Anxiety Stress Scale (DASS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>There will be three time points which will occur one week apart. At each visit testing will commence 60 minutes after consumption of either Neuravena or placebo.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Men and Women aged over 50 years who are assessed as having mild cognitive impairment (MCI) but otherwise healthy. The degree of cognitive impairment will be determined at screening by a score in the range of 9-12 points on the Dem tect questionnaire.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>90</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Regular consumption of any form of cognitive enhancers, anticholinergic medication or mood medication during the trial.
History of serious head injury, diagnosed and/or treated mental illness, alcoholism, stroke and/or neurological condition.
Any other medical condition or treatments (including supplements) which, in the opinion of the investigators, may influence the outcome of the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be recruited from the general population by newspaper advertisements, flyers, electronic mail advertisements and radio/television announcements. Volunteers will be requested to attend the Nutritional Physiology Research Centre for a screening to assess their eligibility for the trial. Eligibility will be determined by the study coordinator. Volunteers will be required to consume each dose once, the order will be determined by a random number generator. Doses will be allocated a letter A-D for identification. The identity of the supplement will be held by an individual separate to the study and will not be decoded until all the data has been analysed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using a randomisation table created by computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr. Janet Bryan</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Nutritional Physiology Research Centre University of South Australia, PO Box 2471 Adelaide, South Australia, 5001.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Frutarom Switzerland Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Rutiwisstrasse 7
CH-8820 Wadenswil</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Switzerland</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr. Narelle Berry</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Nutritional Physiology Research Centre University of South Australia, PO Box 2471 Adelaide, South Australia, 5001.</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Avena sativa (oats), in its various forms and extracts, has been traditionally known for its physical and psychological fortifying properties. Proposed beneficial effects include: reduced risk of heart disease,  raised energy levels, increased ability to cope with stress, reduced anxiety and depression, and increased physical and cognitive performance.
The mechanism of effect is currently unknown. However, it has been suggested that green oat extract has a clinically significant inhibitory effect on monoamine oxidase B (MAO-B) and phosphodiesterase 4 (PDE4), effects which may improve cerebral vasodilation. As enhancement of cerebral blood flow by vasoactive nutrients has been hypothesised to improve cognitive function, this may be the mechanism by which oat extract could improve cognitive performance and stress response.
The aim of this study is to examine the short-term dose-response effects of Neuravena® on cognitive performance, on the ability to cope with stressful cognitive tasks and on psychological well-being (depression, anxiety, stress) and whether these effects are mediated by changes in cerebral blood flow.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of South Australia Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>General Purpose Building, Mawson Lakes Campus, Mawson Lakes Boulevard, Mawson Lakes, South Australia, 5095.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/12/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>P238/08</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Janet Bryan</name>
      <address>University of South Australia, Magill Campus, Magill, South Australia, 5072</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 2680</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>janet.bryan@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Janet Bryan</name>
      <address>Nutritional Physiology Research Centre University of South Australia, PO Box 2471 Adelaide, South Australia, 5001.</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 2680</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>janet.bryan@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Narelle Berry</name>
      <address>Nutritional Physiology Research Centre University of South Australia, PO Box 2471 Adelaide, South Australia, 5001.</address>
      <phone>+61 8 830 21817</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 83022178</fax>
      <email>Narelle.Berry@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>