<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362199">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/03/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/05/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000550808</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The use of negative wound therapy to treat surgical incisions after hip arthroplasty: a pilot study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Pilot study of negative pressure wound dressing therapy versus standard care dressing to prevent surgical site infection in patient undergoing hip arthroplasty</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1129-4755</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Using negative therapy wound dressing to prevent surgical site infections in patients undergoing hip arthroplasty</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Wounds complications</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>At the completion of skin closure, participants allocated to Negative pressure wound therapy (NPWT) will have a PICO (Smith* &amp; Nephew) applied under sterile conditions. The dressing is comprised of a four-layer dressing technology to manage fluid, a dressing is connected to a PICO pump which generates a negative pressure of -80mmHg and removes the exudate from the wound bed through absorbency and evaporation onto the dressing. The dressing will remain in place for 4 days, unless it becomes soiled or dislodged. If this occurs, the dressing will be changed using aseptic technique.

All participants (both intervention and control groups). will receive prophylactic antibiotics intraoperatively, Cefazolin 1 gram intravenously will be adminstered. All other aspects of their care will be consistent between the groups.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants in the control arm will have a standard dressing (Primapore Smith* &amp; Nephew) applied per manufacturer's recommendations at the completion of skin closure. Like the NPWT, the dressing will remain in place for 4 days, unless it becomes soiled or dislodged.

All participants (both intervention and control groups). will receive prophylactic antibiotics. All other aspects of their care will be consistent between the groups.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Presence of surgical site infection (SSI)

Presence of SSI will be assessed by visual inspection and /or through an aseptically obtained culture. Superficial SSI will be identified by at least one of the following signs; purulent discharge, organisms idetified through an aseptically obtained culture, pain/tenderness/ localised swelling/ heat, or a diagnosis of SSI by the consulting surgeon. A deep incisional SSI will be identified by one of the following; purulent discharge, wound dehiscence, abscess formation, or diagnosis of SSI by the treating surgeon.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily for the period of hospitalisation and then via telephone interview at 28 days post -surgery follow-up and lastly at 6 weeks appointment at outpatient department.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Wound complications including dehiscence, haematoma and seroma will be assessed by visual inspection.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily for the period of hospitalisation and then via telephone interview at 28 days post -surgery follow-up and lastly at 6 weeks appointment at outpatient department.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>hospital readmission</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily for the period of hospitalisation and then via telephone interview at 28 days post -surgery follow-up and lastly at 6 weeks appointment at outpatient department.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) Signed consent
2) Patients aged 18 years and above
3) Booked for primary hip arthroplasty</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) Existing infection
2) Previous participation in this trial
3) Unable to speak or write English with no interpreter present.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All eligible participants will be approached by for written consent by a research assistant during their final preoperative appointment. When the consenting patient presents for surgery, a staff member will ring a telephone based randomisation service customised for this trial and be advised of group allocation. 


A computer generated allocated randomisation service is provided by an independent randomisation service. Allocation is fully concealed until the patient is randomised.</concealment>
    <sequence>Patients will be randomised to the two study group in a 1:1 ratio, using a simple randomisation stratified by hospital.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>N/A</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>National Health and Medical Research Council Centre of Research Excellence in Nursing Interventions for Hospitalised Patients (NCREN)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Griffith University
Clinical Science Building 2
Parkland Drive,
Southport,
Queensland
4222</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council Centre of Research Excellence in Nursing Interventions for Hospitalised Patients (NCREN)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Griffith University
Clinical Science Building 2
Parkland Drive,
Southport,
Queensland
4222</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>NA</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>NA</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Wounds that fail to heal may cause distress to patients and impact negatively on the physical, social, economic aspects of their life. Wound complications also add to the cost of health care, with clinical comsumables responsible for a large proportion of health care budget. NPWT is based on a therapy on a closed sealed system that produces negative pressure to wound surface. The wound is covered or packed with an open-cell foam or gauze dressings and sealed with an occlusive drape. Intermittent or continuous suction is maintained by connecting suction tubes from the wound dressing to a vacuum pump and liquid waste colelctor. NPWT is growing in use as a prophylactic approach to prevent wound complications especially SSI, yet evidence of its benefits is lacking.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Gold Coast Health service District Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Governance Officer
Gold Coast Health Services District
10 Little High St,
Southport
Qld 4215</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/04/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Brigid Gillespie</name>
      <address>Griffith University
Gold Coast Campus
G16_Rm 2.63 , CLinical Science Building 2
Southport
Qld 4222</address>
      <phone>+61 7 55529718</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>b.gillespie@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Brigid Gillespie</name>
      <address>Griffith University
Gold Coast Campus
G16_Rm 2.63 , CLinical Science Building 2
Southport
Qld 4222</address>
      <phone>+61 7 55529718</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 5552 8526</fax>
      <email>b.gillespie@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>