<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370890">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/06/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000898459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Phase 2, Randomized, Open Label Study to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of Tenofovir Alafenamide (TAF) versus Tenofovir Disoproxil Fumarate (TDF)containing Regimens in
Subjects with Chronic Hepatitis B (HBV) Infection and Stage 2 or Greater Chronic Kidney Disease Who Have Received a Liver Transplant</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 2, Randomized, Open Label Study to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of Tenofovir Alafenamide (TAF) versus Tenofovir Disoproxil Fumarate (TDF)containing Regimens in
Subjects with Chronic HBV Infection and Stage 2 or Greater Chronic Kidney Disease Who Have Received a Liver Transplant</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>GS-US-320-3912</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Hepatitis B</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Kidney Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Approximately 60 subjects with chronic hepatitis B and Stage 2 or greater chronic kidney disease and have received a liver transplant will be assigned to one of the two treatment arms (A:B) for 48 weeks. Randomization will be stratified by baseline renal function. 
- Treatment Arm A: approximately 30 subjects administered Tenofovir Alafenamide (TAF) 25 mg oral daily
- Treatment Arm B: approximately 30 subjects to continue administration of Tenofovir Disoproxil Fumarate (TDF) alone or in combination with other approved antivirals per local practice;
After Week 48, during the optional treatment extension phase, subjects in treatment arms A and B will be eligible to receive TAF 25 mg daily and will be followed for an additional 96 weeks.
An accountability check at each visit, Drug tablet return and lab tests are all part of the protocol to manage and monitor adherence. </interventions>
    <comparator>Tenofovir Disoproxil Furmarate (TDF) alone or in combination with other approved antivirals as per local practice</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in renal function of TAF 25 mg daily versus TDF-containing regimens at Week 24. 
eGFR is calculated by assessing Cystatin C and estimated serum creatinine clearance. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessment timepoints: 
Creatinine Clearance: Baseline, Week 4, Week 8, Week 12, Week 20, and Week 24.
Cystatin C: Baseline, Week 4, Week 12, and Week 24.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of subjects with HBV DNA &lt; 20 IU/mL at Week 24.
The subject's HBV DNA will be assessed using a plasma assay.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessment timepoints: Baseline, Week 4, Week 8, Week 12, Week 20 and Week 24</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percent change from baseline in hip and spine bone mineral density (BMD) of TAF 25 mg daily versus TDF-containing regimens at Weeks 24 and 48. The outcome is assessed using a DEXA scan.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessment timepoints: Screening, Week 24, and Week 48.
For participants who opt in to the treatment extension phase, additional assessments performed at Week 96 and Week 144.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in serum creatinine of TAF 25 mg daily versus TDF-containing regimens at Weeks 24 and 48</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessment timepoints: Baseline, Week 4, Week 8, Week 12, Week 20, Week 24, Week 36, and Week 48.
For participants who opt in to the treatment extension phase, additional assessments performed at Week 60, Week 72, Week 96, Week 120, and Week 144.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in renal function of TAF 25 mg daily versus TDF-containing regimens at Week 48.
eGFR is calculated by assessing Cystatin C and estimated serum creatinine clearance. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessment timepoints: 
Creatinine Clearance: Baseline, Week 4, Week 8, Week 12, Week 20, Week 24, Week 36, and Week 48.
For participants who opt in to the treatment extension phase, additional assessments performed at Week 60, Week 72, Week 96, Week 120, and Week 144.
Cystatin C: Baseline, Week 4, Week 12, Week 24, and Week 48.
For participants who opt in to the treatment extension phase, additional assessments performed at Week 72, Week 96, Week 120, and Week 144.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of subjects with HBV DNA &lt; 20 IU/mL at Week 48.
The subject's HBV DNA will be assessed using a plasma assay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessment timepoints: Baseline, Week 4, Week 8, Week 12, Week 20, Week 24, Week 36, and Week 48.
For participants who opt in to the treatment extension phase, additional assessments performed at Week 60, Week 72, Week 96, Week 120, and Week 144.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) Must have the ability to understand and sign a written informed consent form; consent must be obtained prior to initiation of study procedures
2) Adult male or non-pregnant female subjects, over 18 years of age based on the date of the screening visit
3) Documented evidence of chronic HBV infection prior to transplantation
4) Primary or secondary (re-transplant), liver alone or liver and kidney transplant recipient from deceased or living donor
5) Liver Transplant =&gt;12 weeks prior to screening
6) Maintained on TDF alone or in combination with other approved antivirals for HBV
prophylaxis or treatment
7) Have been on approved HBV OAV treatment for at least 12 weeks post-transplant prior to screening, with HBV DNA &lt; LLOQ at screening
8) Screening renal function &lt; 90 ml/min/1.73m^2
9) Male subjects and female subjects of childbearing potential who engage in heterosexual intercourse must agree to use protocol specified method(s) of contraception
10) Women considered of child bearing potential must have a negative serum
pregnancy test at Screening and a negative urine test at Baseline before dosing
11) Must be willing and able to comply with all study requirements</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) Multi-organ transplant that includes heart or lung recipient (subjects who have their liver transplant as part of a liver-kidney dual transplant are eligible to enroll)
2) Subjects with history of de novo or recurrent hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) post-transplant and at screening
3) Histological evidence of unresolved transplant rejection
4) Current, uncontrolled ascites, variceal hemorrhage, hepatic encephalopathy, hepatorenal syndrome, hepatopulmonary syndrome, or other signs of decompensated cirrhosis
5) Subjects meeting any of the following laboratory parameters at screening:
a) ALT &gt; 10× the upper limit of normal (ULN)
b) INR &gt; 1.5 × ULN unless the subject is stable on anticoagulant regimen affecting INR
c) Albumin &lt; 3.0 g/dL
d) Direct bilirubin =&gt; 4 × ULN
e) Platelet count &lt; 50,000/mL
6) Co-infection with HIV or HCV
7) Recent (within 4 weeks of Screening) episode or infection requiring systemic antibiotics
8) Use or planned use of T-cell depleting/masking antibodies, systemic antineoplastic agents, cyclosporine &gt; 300 mg/day, or use of any prohibited medications within 28 days of the Baseline/Day 1 visit
9) Malignancy within 5 years prior to screening, with the exception of specific cancers that are cured by surgical resection (e.g., basal cell skin cancer, etc) or hepatocellular carcinoma. Subjects under evaluation for possible malignancy are not eligible
10) Significant cardiovascular, pulmonary, or neurological disease
11) Use of investigational agents within 3 months of screening, unless allowed by the Sponsor
12) Use of any prohibited concomitant medications 
13) Current alcohol or substance abuse judged by the investigator to potentially interfere with subject compliance
14) Known hypersensitivity to study drugs, metabolites or formulation excipients
15) Lactating females or those who may wish to become pregnant during the course of the study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence>Computerised sequence generation was employed in the study, The factor used for stratification is the subject's baseline renal function. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The primary analysis set for efficacy analysis is the Full Analysis Set (FAS), defined as all
randomized subjects who receive at least one dose of study drug. Subjects will be analyzed according to the randomized treatment assignment.

The primary analysis set for safety analyses is the Safety Analysis Set (SAS), defined as all randomized subjects who receive at least one dose of study drug. Subjects will be analyzed according to the treatment actually received. All data collected during treatment will be included in the safety summaries.

Please note that this is an exploratory study, so there was no sample size calculation performed. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>15/09/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Gilead Sciences, Inc. </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>333 Lakeside Drive
Foster City, CA 94404</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Gilead Sciences, Inc.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>333 Lakeside Drive
Foster City, CA 94404</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a randomized, open-label, single center Phase 2 study to evaluate the safety and efficacy of TAF 25 mg daily versus TDF in adult chronic hepatitis B infection (CHB) subjects with Stage 2 or greater chronic kidney disease and have received a liver transplant.
Approximately 60 subjects will be randomized in a 1:1 ratio to either continue current treatment regimen with TDF alone or in combination with other approved antivirals or to receive TAF 25 mg oral daily. At least 50 subjects will be enrolled with renal function &lt; 50 ml/min/1.73m^2.
- Treatment Arm A: approximately 30 subjects administered TAF 25 mg oral daily
- Treatment Arm B: approximately 30 subjects to continue administration of TDF alone or in combination with other approved antivirals as per local practice.
After Week 48, all subjects will be eligible to continue in the optional treatment extension phase, wherein they will receive TAF 25 mg daily and will be followed for an additional 96 weeks. 
The primary analysis will occur at Week 24 with the primary efficacy endpoint being the maintenance of viral suppression (HBV DNA &lt; 20 IU/mL).</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committee (HDEC), NZ</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Ethics Department
Freyberg Building
Reception  Ground Floor
20 Aitken Street, Wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/08/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/07/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Edward Gane</name>
      <address>Auckland City Hospital 
Park Road, Grafton 1142 
New Zealand 
</address>
      <phone>+64 9 373 3474</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>edgane@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Ansy Mathews</name>
      <address>Gilead Sciences, Inc.
333 Lakeside Drive
Foster City, CA 94404</address>
      <phone>+1 6505243912</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ansy.mathews@gilead.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Ansy Mathews</name>
      <address>Gilead Sciences, Inc.
333 Lakeside Drive
Foster City, CA 94404</address>
      <phone>+1 6505243912</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ansy.mathews@gilead.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Wayne Paul</name>
      <address>Gilead Sciences Pty Ltd
Level 6, 417 St Kilda Road, 
Melbourne, Victoria 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9272 4451</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>wayne.paul@gilead.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>