<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343269">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/10/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/03/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000330842</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of the Guardian CPV(TM) Laryngeal Mask during Anaesthesia for General Surgery</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of the Guardian CPV(TM) Laryngeal Mask during Anaesthesia for General Surgery</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Assessing suitability of a new laryngeal mask airway for use in general surgical patients under anaesthesia at the Royal Adelaide Hospital</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Use of the Guardian CPV (TM) Laryngeal Mask for airway management under anaesthesia:
The TGA approved Guardian CPV (TM) Laryngeal mask is inserted into the patients upper airway via the mouth, to provide a breathing pathway under anaesthesia for various types of surgery. It is used in place of various competitor products which are also TGA approved and used for many standard anaesthesia procedures. According to the study protocol, the device would be used for surgical procedures which are unlikely to exceed 2 hours duration</interventions>
    <comparator>Not Applicable</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Confirm suitability of device for TGA registered purpose in the study institution:
Assessment occurs during routine anaesthesia practice where an LMA is inserted by an anaesthesia specialist or registrar to facilitate airway management. Assessment is via a questionnaire for the attending anaesthetist which asks whether manufacturers instructions resulted in a clear airway without leaks, and other minor indicators of ease of use.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The assessment occurs during use of the device (over a time period unlikely to exceed 2 hours of use during anaesthesia for a surgical procedure</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The accuracy of the intrinsic cuff pressure indicator is assessed by documenting which colour band the indicator is displaying when inflated according to manufacturers instructions, and measuring the numeric cuff pressure at the same time with a standard analogue cuff pressure gauge. The manufacturer has documented what pressure range is meant to be indicated by each of three colour ranges</outcome>
      <timepoint>This outcome is assessed at a single timepoint during use, as above. Basic statistical analysis will be used at the end of the study to determine agreement between claimed and measured values.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine increase in cuff pressure if there has been use of nitrous oxide for a minimum duration of 30 minutes. 
Assessment occurs by: 
1) Measurement of pressure using the standard cuff pressure gauge, after equilibration with nitrous oxide has occurred (after LMA insertion and at least 30 minutes use of nitrous oxide)
2) Removal of volume from the cuff until pressure returns to the original reading (the volume to achieve this is recorded)</outcome>
      <timepoint>This outcome is assessed at two timepoints during anaesthesia delivery: 
1) when the initial pressure measurement occurs after insertion and inflation.
2) when at least 30 minutes of nitrous oxide anaesthesia has been sustained (cuff pressure changes occur because nitrous oxide diffuses across the cuff membrane and is expected to be in equilibrium after 30 minutes)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine if the device functions satisfactorily for controlled ventilation and at what pressures.
Assessment is via the anaesthetist questionnaire which asks:
1) if mechanical ventilation was used, then was it achievable using the LMA, and what peak airway pressure was used (if not achievable using an LMA, then standard anaesthesia practise is to change to an endotracheal airway)
2) what range was the intrinsic cuff pressure indicator reading when mechanical ventilation was satisfactorily in use, and what pressure did the standard analogue pressure gauge indicate?</outcome>
      <timepoint>This outcome is assessed during anaesthesia delivery once mechanical ventilation has been commenced.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Al patients suitable for laryngeal mask anaesthesia undergoing general surgical procedures under anaesthesia care from the nominated investigators</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Age less than 18 years (LMA use is not age limited in standard anaesthesia practice). 
Body Mass Index (BMI) of  &lt;18  or &gt; 35 kg/m2. 
Inability to communicate well with the study staff or comply with the study requirements and restrictions.
Inability to understand the Study Information Sheet and provide a written consent to take part in the study.
Poor understanding of the procedure.
Poor command of the English Language.
An anaesthesia procedure which is unlikely to extend beyond 2 hours.
Uncontrolled gastro-oesophageal reflux or regurgitation.
High risk for aspiration of gastric contents into lungs.
Previous difficulty with insertion of an LMA.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Given that the trial aims to assess suitability for all patient groups over 18 years old within a specified normal body mass index range who are suitable for a Laryngeal Mask Airway (LMA), the intention is that all eligible patients will be given the opportunity to participate. Patient enrolment will be at the discretion of the anaesthetist but may occur during a standard preoperative assessment interview</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>13/06/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Adelaide Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>North Terrace
Adelaide
South Australia
5000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Anaequip</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Anaequip Medical
U6, 28 Heath Street
LONSDALE  SA  5160</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The main purpose of this study is to determine if claimed improvements in a new version of a common medical device are reasonable and if it is appropriate to use these devices instead of the current devices in use (at the Royal Adelaide Hospital)</summary>
    <trialwebsite>n/a</trialwebsite>
    <publication>n/a</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 3, Hanson Institute
c/o
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace Adelaide
SA
5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/05/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>RAH PROTOCOL No. 110214</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Nicole Dyson</name>
      <address>c/o Department of Anaesthesia, Royal Adelaide Hospital, North Terrace, Adelaide, SA, 5000, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82225421</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 82225887</fax>
      <email>nicole.dyson@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Edward Murphy</name>
      <address>c/o Department of Anaesthesia, Royal Adelaide Hospital, North Terrace, Adelaide, SA, 5000, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82225421</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 82225887</fax>
      <email>edward.murphy@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Nicole Dyson</name>
      <address>c/o Department of Anaesthesia, Royal Adelaide Hospital, North Terrace, Adelaide, SA, 5000, Australia</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>nicole.dyson@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>