<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336389">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/01/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/01/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000058976</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The genomics of taste receptors in the prevention of obesity</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The genomics of taste receptors in the prevention of obesity amongst healthy human subjects via the evaluation of genetic (i.e., allelic variation and taste receptor gene expression) factors which are associated with taste sensitivity</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1118-9421</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>During this study participants will be involved in an exploratory discovery study, during which their dietary intake, weight status and taste sensitivity will be evaluated and compared with 1) allelic variation in taste receptor genes and 2) relative expression of taste receptor genes upon the tongue. A total of five testing sessions will be required for this study, including four x 60 minute taste tests, and one 90 minute session during which tongue tissue will be collected, taste papillae counted, and the questionnaires (food frequency questionnaire and implict attitudes test) will be completed. Taste testing will be done to determine detection thresholds for each tastant, as well as difference thresholds for each tastant. The detection threshold is the lowest concentration of a tastant required for it to be detected within the mouth, wheras the difference threshold is the concentration of a tastant required for it to be perceived as different from an identical tastant, at a different concentration. Testing will take place over a one month period, and all testing will be seperated by at least 24 hours.</interventions>
    <comparator>all participants will take part in this study, there will be no control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome will be taste sensitivity, as measured by detection and difference thresholds for sweet, fatty acid, salty, sour, umami and bitter tastes. Detection thresholds are considered the lowest amount of a tastant required for it to be detected, whereas difference thresholds are the concentration of tastant required for it be tasted as different from another sample at suprathreshold (above detection threshold) concentrations.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Taste thresholds, both detection and difference thresholds for these tastants will be measured  in duplicate. Detection and difference thresholds will be measured on seperated occasions, seperated by 24 hours.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dietary intake, as assessed by a validated food frequency questionnaire (National Health and Nutritional Examination Survey (NHANES)), will be collected.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The food frequency questionnaire will be completed within one month of taste testing.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Allelic variation in taste receptor genes will be measured. This will be done following the collection of blood (30 mls) from each participant. DNA from whole blood will be amplified following Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR) and combined with labelled taste receptor primers (also commercially available), which will be used to evaluate variation (Single Nucleotide Polymorphisms (SNPs)) in taste receptor genes.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood will be collected from all participants within one month of taste testing.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weight, height and waist circumference will be collected. Weight will be collected in Kg using dedicated scales, height in cm using a wall mounted stadiometre and waist circumference using a dedicated measuring tape, which will be passed around the abdomen at belly-button height.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weight, height and waist circumference will be collected in a single testing session, within one month of taste testing.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The number of taste papillae present on the tongue will be counted. For this, a 6 mm piece of filter paper, impregnated with blue food dye, will be placed on the anterior tongue, and used to stain a 6 mm area. Following staining, a picture of the tongue will be captured on a digital camera, blown up, and the papillae within the blue stained area will be counted.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Tongue papillae will be counted within one month of taste testing.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>An Implicit Associations Test (IAT) will be used to capture associations and reactions to food images. This is a validated, time-reaction task used to evaluate subconcious reactions and associations to specific stimuli, in this case, foods.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The IAT will be administered within one month of taste testing.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>For these studies, we are specifically seeking individuals who are:

- 18 years or older
- Living in metropolitan Sydney
- Proficient in both written and spoken English
- Able to attend testing sessions between the hours of 9:00 am - 5:00pm Monday to Friday</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>For these studies we are specifically excluding individuals based upon the following criteria:

- Adults with known medical conditions known to affect weight (hyperthyroidism, Cushing syndrome etc)
- Individuals who are currently on, or have been on a diet, or specific dietary routine within the past 3 months
- Individuals who have experienced fluctuations in their weight by &gt; 3 kg in the past 3 months
- Individuals who do not have adequate taste function
- Individuals who are restrained eaters (as defined by a score of &gt; 12 on factor one of the eating attitudes test
- Individuals who are allergic to, or do not wish to consume dairy products
- Individuals over the age of 55 years
-Smokers</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>NA</concealment>
    <sequence>NA</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Conor Delahunty</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>CSIRO Food and Nutritional Sciences
Riverside Corporate Park
11 Julius Avenue
North Ryde
2113 NSW</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation (CSIRO)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>CSIRO Food and Nutritional Sciences
Riverside Corporate Park
11 Julius Avenue
North Ryde
2113 NSW</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Each year CSIRO Food and Nutritional Sciences perform a number of research projects involving human participants. The present study will be investigating genetic differences in taste perception and how they are associated with genetic factors, susceptibility to chronic disease and dietary intake.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>CSIRO Food and Nutritional Sciences Human Research Ethics Commitee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>CSIRO Food and Nutritional Sciences
Kintore Street
Adelaide, 5000
Adelaide
South Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/01/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Jessica Stewart</name>
      <address>CSIRO Food and Nutritional Sciences
Riverside Corporate park
11 Julius Avenue
North Ryde
2113, NSW</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9490 8363</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jessica.stewart@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Jessica Stewart</name>
      <address>CSIRO Food and Nutritional Sciences
Riverside Corporate park
11 Julius Avenue
North Ryde
2113, NSW</address>
      <phone>+ 61 29490 8363</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jessica.stewart@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Jessica Stewart</name>
      <address>CSIRO Food and Nutritional Sciences
Riverside Corporate park
11 Julius Avenue
North Ryde
2113, NSW</address>
      <phone>+ 61 29490 8363</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jessica.stewart@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>