<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364610">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/07/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/08/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000880741</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A multicentre randomized control study of atrial fibrillation in heart failure (CAMERA-MRI)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Catheter Ablation versus MEdical Rate control in Atrial fibrillation and heart failure  An MRI guided multi-centre randomised controlled trial  the CAMERA-MRI study.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>CAMERA-MRI</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Atrial Fibrillation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Heart Failure</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Arm 1 - Catheter Ablation
Catheter ablation of AF is a minimally invasive procedure (involving the use of specialized instruments through the groin to make a small burn in the area of the heart that is responsible for irregular heart rates) which can eliminate AF in many patients. However in patients with AF and HF, it is currently difficult to identify those in whom the AF is causing or significantly contributing to the HF. Such patients may benefit from catheter ablation. Patients with HF display a unique pattern of scarring in the heart muscle capable of being detected by magnetic resonance imaging (MRI). The amount of scarring in the heart muscle appears proportional to the degree of reversibility of HF. Thus in patients with AF and HF, we propose that MRI may help identify those patients whose HF is most likely to improve, or even completely reverse, following catheter ablation. In this way, catheter ablation may become a useful tool in the treatment of patients with AF and HF.
Catheter ablation will be guided using a 3D mapping system with integration of the left atriogram obtained at the time of MRI. Ablation is performed with an irrigated tip catheter to encircle the left and right sided pulmonary veins (PV) in pairs 1-2 cms from their ostia as defined by PV angiography and the 3D map. At the anterior aspect of the left PVs, ablation is performed along the ridge between the Left Atrial Appendage (LAA) and the PV ostia. The PVs are continuously assessed for electrical disconnection using the circular mapping catheter. If AF continues following PV electrical isolation further substrate modification is at the discretion of the operator and may include (i) linear ablation  a roof line joining the superior aspects of each wide encirclement ablation ring and an inferior LA line to achieve electrical isolation of the posterior LA wall or a mitral isthmus line and/or (ii) complex fractionated electrograms - left and right atria are mapped systematically for fractionated potentials which are then targeted for ablation. The procedure takes approximately 2-4 hours.</interventions>
    <comparator>Arm 2 - Pharmacological rate control
Rate control involves using medications designed to make the heart rate slower by slowing electrical impulses flowing through the Atrio Ventricular node. These include beta blockers (Atenolol, Bisoprolol, Carvedilol, Metropolol, Propranolol, Sotolol) and the cardiacglycoside Digoxin. Individual participant dosage, frequency and duration will be prescribed by the Chief Investigator.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Recovery of Left Ventricular function assesed by improvement in Ejection Fraction determined by cardiac MRI and Echocardiography.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at 6 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Restoration of sinus rhythm assessed by Loop Recorder Interrogation (Catheter Ablation Arm) Holter Monitoring and Electrocardiography (Rate Control Arm).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Loop Recorder assessed at 6 weeks, 3 and 6 months.
Holter Monitoring assessed at 3 and 6 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvement in Heart Failure symptoms as assessed by the 6 Minute Walk Test (6MWT) and Quality of Life as assesed by the individual participant using the SF36v2 Health Survey.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6MWT and SF36 assessed at 3 and 6 months. 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Paroxysmal or persistent AF
LVEF &lt; 45%
Dilated Cadriomyopathy</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Non MRI safe Pacemaker, ICD or BiVentricular Device
Renal Impairment Cr &gt; 200
Left atrial thrombus</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The sample size calculation for the primary endpoint of LVEF assumes the mean EF of both groups (AF ablation and medical therapy) is 40+/-10% based on preliminary data. We will aim to detect minimum absolute difference in EF of 10% then 16 patients will be required in each group to provide a power of 0.8 at an alpha value of 0.05. Successful restoration of sinus rhythm with catheter ablation in this patient population is estimated at 80% requiring 20 patients in each group. Differences in proportions will compared by a chi-squared analysis or Fishers Exact Test. Comparisons between groups will be performed with either an unpaired Students T-Test or where a normal distribution could not be assumed the Mann Whitney U test. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>27/11/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>6/10/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>66</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>8/05/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis>Data analysis is complete</dataanalysis>
    <withdrawnreason>Other reasons/comments</withdrawnreason>
    <withdrawnreasonother>Interim analysis performed on 66 participants and sufficient power achieved for primary outcome</withdrawnreasonother>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - City campus - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Melbourne Private Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Clayton campus - Clayton</hospital>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Baker IDI Heart &amp; Diabetes Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>75 Commercial Road,
Melbourne, VIC 3004</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>N/A</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Heart failure (HF) is a common heart condition whereby the pumping capacity of the heart is significantly reduced. It is the end result of many conditions which weaken the heart muscle. Atrial fibrillation (AF) is a common electrical disturbance of the heart which results in rapid and irregular heart rates which may cause HF or significantly worsen pre-existing HF. Similarly, HF may cause AF which may then worsen the severity of HF. Catheter ablation of AF is a minimally invasive procedure (involving the use of specialized instruments through the groin to make a small burn in the area of the heart that is responsible for irregular heart rates) which can eliminate AF in many patients. However, in patients with AF and HF, it is currently difficult to identify those in whom the AF is causing or significantly contributing to the HF. Such patients may benefit from catheter ablation. Patients with HF display a unique pattern of scarring in the heart muscle capable of being detected by magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) (non-invasive scan of the heart). The amount of scarring in the heart muscle appears proportional to the degree of reversibility of HF. Thus in patients with AF and HF, we propose that MRI may help identify those patients whose HF is most likely to improve, or even completely reverse, following catheter ablation. In this way, catheter ablation may become a useful tool in the treatment of patients with AF and HF. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Alfred Hospital,
Commercial Road,
Prahran,
VIC 3004</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/09/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00315</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>22/07/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Melbourne Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Royal Melbourne Hospital
300 Gratten Street
Parkville, VIC, 3050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/08/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/MH/237</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/03/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash Medical Centre</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Road
Clayton, Victoria, 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/04/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HRECREF:15120X</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/02/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Kistler</name>
      <address>Head, Clinical Electrophysiology Research,
Applied cardiovascular Research,
Baker IDI Heart &amp; Diabetes Institute,
75 Commercial Road,
Melbourne,
VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+613 8532 1427</phone>
      <fax>+613 90762461</fax>
      <email>peter.kistler@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Kistler</name>
      <address>Head, Clinical Electrophysiology Research,
Applied cardiovascular Research,
Baker IDI Heart &amp; Diabetes Institute,
75 Commercial Road,
Melbourne,
VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+613 8532 1427</phone>
      <fax>+613 90762461</fax>
      <email>peter.kistler@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Kistler</name>
      <address>Head, Clinical Electrophysiology Research,
Applied cardiovascular Research,
Baker IDI Heart &amp; Diabetes Institute,
75 Commercial Road,
Melbourne,
VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+613 8532 1427</phone>
      <fax>+613 90762461</fax>
      <email>peter.kistler@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sonia Azzopardi</name>
      <address>Heart Centre At The Alfred,
3rd Floor Philip Block,
Alfred Hospital,
Commercial Road,
Melbourne,
VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+613 9076 3352</phone>
      <fax>+613 8532 1100</fax>
      <email>sonia.azzopardi@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>