<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366098">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/04/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/04/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000433606</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The relationships between obesity, lifestyle behaviours, and cardiovascular health in children. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>PACMAC Study: Analyzing the relationships between obesity, lifestyle behaviours, and cardio-metabolic health in children ages 8-10.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn> U1111-1155-2586</utrn>
    <trialacronym>PACMAC</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cardiovascular Disease </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Obesity Correlates</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the cardiovascular system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Phase one: The study will investigate the relationships between obesity, lifestyle behaviours (nutrition, physical activity/fitness, sleep behaviour, psychosocial influences) and cardiovascular health in a sample of 400 children ages 8-10. Participants are assessed at one timepoint only because this is a cross-sectional study. Phase one of the study will be conducted at primary school locations in the greater Wellington area.

Phase two: In a sub-group of 100 children, additional measurements of cardiovascular health, life style behaviours, and fatness will be obtained to provide objective and detailed data to determine whether the strongest correlate of cardiovascular disease risk is similar for Maori and Caucasian children. Some participants that are involved in phase one of the study will be involved in phase two of the research. Phase two of the study will be done subsequent phase one at a later date.  Phase two of the study will be conducted in the research lab at Massey University. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>This is a cross sectional study</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardio-metabolic health

Phase 1: Biochemical markers will be collected by finger prick procedure and analysed using portable lipid/glucose (CardioChek PA) and HbA1c (Afinion HbA1c) analyzers.</outcome>
      <timepoint>One-off measurement </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardio-Metabolic Health

Phase 2: Flow Mediated Dilation will be used to assess endothelial function.</outcome>
      <timepoint>One-off measurement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fatness

Phase 1: Body composition will be estimated using body mass index (BMI), waist circumference, waist: hip ratio (WHR), and body composition (fat mass, fat-free mass) using bio-impedance analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>One-off measurement 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical Activity 

Phase 1: The Youth Physical Activity Questionnaire (YPAQ) will be used to measure physical activity type, frequency, and duration on a daily basis. The 47 item YPAQ asks students to quantify the frequency and duration of a range of physical and sedentary activities for both week and weekend days over the past 7 days. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>One-off measurement </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical Fitness

Phase 1: A 20-m maximal multistage shuttle run test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>One-off measurement </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sleep

Phase 1: The Childrens Sleep Habits Questionnaire (CSHQ) will be used to measure sleep habits and sleep disturbances.</outcome>
      <timepoint>One-off measurement </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nutritional Behavior

Phase 1: Food choice will be assessed using a specially modified, short version of New Zealand Adolescent Food Frequency Questionnaire (NZAFFQ), the New Zealand Childrens Food Frequency Questionnaire (NZCFFQ), designed for use in this age group. This FFQ is based on the Health Behaviour in School Children (HBSC) FFQ, which is suitable for use in this age group.</outcome>
      <timepoint>One-off measurement </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fatness

Phase 2: Intra-abdominal tissue thickness (IAT) and abdominal wall fat index (AFI) will be measured by an ultrasound device.</outcome>
      <timepoint>One-off measurement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical Activity

Phase 2: Accelerometry will be used to objectively measure moderate to vigorous physical activity levels.</outcome>
      <timepoint>One-off measurement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical Fitness

Phase 2: A continuous, incremental maximal exercise test on a cycle ergometer will be used to measure cardiorespiratory fitness.</outcome>
      <timepoint>One-off measurement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sleep

Phase 2: Accelerometry and a paper-based sleep diary will be used to measure sleep behavior.</outcome>
      <timepoint>One-off measurement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nutritional Behavior

Phase 2: A four day estimated food diary will be used to measure food intake over a four day period.</outcome>
      <timepoint>One-off measurement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Children will be deemed eligible if they are ages 8-10, reside in the greater Wellington area, and do not have any sign of injury or illness. This will be determined by a standardized health screening questionnaire, and a physical activity readiness-questionnaire (PAR-Q) that will be completed by a parent or guardian. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>8</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>10</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Children will be ineligible to participate if they have had an orthopaedic injury or surgery that has prohibited full function within the previous four weeks, have been prescribed any cardiovascular medications, or if the parent or guardian consent form and child assent form are not returned signed.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>For research Question 1: Investigate the associations of physical activity, physical fitness, nutrition, and sleep habits with fatness.
Partial correlations will be used to compare physical activity, physical fitness, nutrition, and sleep habits with fatness.
Two separate multiple regression models will be used to examine the association of the predictor variables with fatness.

For research Question 2:Investigate the strongest correlate of physical activity: physical environment (walkability, playability index) or psychosocial (attraction to physical activity).
Partial correlations will be used to compare physical environment and psychosocial with physical activity.
Two separate multiple regression models will be used to examine the association of the predictor variables with physical activity.

For research Question 3:Investigate the strongest correlate of nutritional behaviour: physical environment (local built food environment), psychosocial (preferences for and attitudes towards healthy foods) or hereditary (genetic variability of taste receptors).
Partial correlations will be used to compare physical environment, psychosocial, and hereditary with independent variables which will include food environment variables, psychosocial variables, and taste response (taste/non-taste) to 6-n-propylthiouracil (PROP).
A two-way (environment index x taste response) analysis of co-variance will be used to examine environment-gene interaction, adjusting for psychosocial variables. 
 
For research Question 4: Investigate the association of fatness, nutrition, physical activity, physical fitness, and sleep with cardio-metabolic health. 
Partial correlations will be used to compare fatness, physical activity, physical fitness, nutrition,and sleep behaviour with cardio-metabolic health.
Two separate multiple regression models will be used to examine the association of the predictor variables with cardio-metabolic health.

Research question 5: Investigate the association of fatness, nutrition, physical activity, physical fitness, and sleep with cardiovascular disease risk, and (b) determine whether the strongest correlate of cardiovascular disease risk is similar for Maori and Caucasian children.
Partial correlations will be used to compare fatness, nutrition, physical activity, physical fitness, and sleep with cardiovascular disease risk score.
Two separate multiple regression models will be used to examine the association of the predictor variables with cardiovascular disease risk score.

Sample Size Calculations

Phase one: Using magnitude-based inferences to estimate the sample size required to detect the smallest beneficial (or detrimental) effect in a cross-sectional study (in this case a correlation of 0.10 which is set lower than the estimated correlation of 0.20 found in previous research between fitness and fatness, with the maximum chances of a Type 1 and 2 error set at 5% (i.e. very unlikely), approximately 272 children are required.  To allow for an approximate 30% non-completion rate across all study measures, 400 children will be recruited to the study. 

Phase two: Using the same method described above, but changing the smallest beneficial effect to match that found previously between flow-mediated dilation and physical activity (i.e. r = 0.40), approximately 20 subjects are required per group (Caucasian or Maori). We will over sample to accommodate for setbacks.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Psychosocial</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Both</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>400</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Wellington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Canterbury</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Otago</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Massey University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Massey University
College of Health
School of Sport and Exercise
Private Bag 756
Wellington 6140</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Massey University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Massey University
College of Health
School of Sport and Exercise
Private Bag 756
Wellington 6140</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr. Lee Stoner</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Massey University
College of Health
School of Sport and Exercise
Private Bag 756
Wellington 6140</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr. James Faulkner</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Massey University
College of Health
School of Sport and Exercise
Private Bag 756
Wellington 6140</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr. Sally Lark</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Massey University
College of Health
School of Sport and Exercise
Private Bag 756
Wellington 6140</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr. Michelle Williams</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Harvard School of Public Health
Department of Epidemiology
Boston, Massachusetts 02115 </othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>United States of America</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This research aims is to investigate the relationships between obesity, lifestyle behaviours (nutrition, physical activity/fitness, sleep behaviour, psychosocial influences) and cardio-metabolic health in pre-pubescent children ages 8-10. 

Furthermore, the research will investigate whether there are differences in the correlates of cardio-metabolic health between Maori and Caucasian children.  </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health &amp; Disability Ethics Committees</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
No 1 The Terrace
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6145</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/05/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Nicholas Castro</name>
      <address>Massey University
College of Health
School of Sport and Exercise
Private Bag 756
Wellington 6140</address>
      <phone>+64.06.356.9099 ext 62284</phone>
      <fax>+64.4.801.4994</fax>
      <email>n.castro@massey.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Nicholas Castro</name>
      <address>Massey University
College of Health
School of Sport and Exercise
Private Bag 756
Wellington 6140</address>
      <phone>+64.06.356.9099 ext 62284</phone>
      <fax>+64.4.801.4994</fax>
      <email>n.castro@massey.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lee Stoner</name>
      <address>Massey University
College of Health
School of Sport and Exercise
Private Bag 756
Wellington 6140</address>
      <phone> +64.4.801.5799 ext 62403 </phone>
      <fax>+64.4.801.4994</fax>
      <email>dr.l.stoner@gmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Nicholas Castro</name>
      <address>Massey University
College of Health
School of Sport and Exercise
Private Bag 756
Wellington 6140</address>
      <phone>+64.06.356.9099 ext 62284</phone>
      <fax>+64.4.801.4994</fax>
      <email>n.castro@massey.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>