<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364586">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/07/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/07/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000828729</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Prescribing physical activity for patients with hip fracture during rehabilitation </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Determining the maximum tolerable dose of prescribed physical activity for patients with hip fracture in inpatient rehabilitation in terms of safety and feasibility</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hip fracture</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fractures</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a phase I dose-response trial to find out how much physical activity, in the form of walking, can be prescribed for people with hip fracture during rehabilitation in terms of safety and feasibility. 
In addition to receiving usual rehabilitation care, groups of 3 participants will be individually supervised to walk at a prescribed level of physical activity for 5 consecutive days. This prescribed level of physical activity will not change for individual participants over the 5 days but may escalate for subsequent groups of participants. 
The dose level of prescribed physical activity will follow a modified Fibonacci scheme starting with an initial dose of 3 minutes of moderate intensity supervised walking per day for the first group of participants. Moderate intensity walking will be defined as a 3 on the modified Borg 0-10 perceived exertion scale, where 3 = I am still comfortable but am breathing a little harder. 
Dose escalation will depend on the presence or absence of adverse incidents among the group of 3 participants. 
Depending on the feasibility and safety of the prescribed dose of walking, the dose may or may not be escalated between subsequent groups of participants.
Dose escalation will start with early larger dose increments between groups which get smaller for higher doses until the guideline stopping value of 30 minutes of walking per day is reached (i.e. 3, 6, 10, 15, 21, 27, 30 mins). 
The trial will stop when/if a group of participants can achieve 30 minutes of prescribed walking as this reflects physical activity guidelines. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>There will be no control group but the trial will involve dose comparison. 
The first group of participants will walk for 3 minutes per day over 5 consecutive days. 
Depending on feasibility and safety, the dose of walking will escalate between groups of participants following a modified Fibonacci scheme of 3, 6, 10, 15, 21, 27 and 30 minutes of walking. </comparator>
    <control>Dose comparison</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximum tolerated dose of physical activity (minutes of walking)</outcome>
      <timepoint>N/A
The maximum tolerated dose of physical activity will be identified when  either:
- groups of participants can no longer feasibly and safely complete the prescribed dose of walking
- a group of participants achieves 30 minutes of prescribed walking (as dose escalation will not continue as this value reflects physical activity guidelines)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity measures from the ActivPAL activity monitor worn continuously over the 5 day period: steps, time spent walking and time spent in moderate-vigorous physical activity</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 5 (average per day over 5 days)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mobility using the De Morten Mobility Index (DEMMI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 and Day 5</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Confidence with mobility using the Ambulatory Self Confidence Questionnaire  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 and Day 5</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients will be eligible if they are: 
- admitted to rehabilitation following surgical management of a hip fracture 
- receive medical approval to participate 
- can walk, either independently or with assistance. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients will not be eligible to participate if they:
- are admitted with diagnoses other than hip fracture
- are not able to walk
- have moderate to severe cognitive impairment. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>This is a nonrandomised trial. The trial will be a phase I dose-response study using the 3+3 design (Gao et al 2008, Lin and Shih 2001).
  
Patients will be recruited consecutively and allocated to a prescribed physical activity dose.

The dose level of prescribed physical activity will follow a modified Fibonacci scheme starting with an initial dose of 3 minutes of supervised walking per day for the first group of participants, with early larger dose increments which get smaller for higher doses until the guideline stopping value of 30 minutes of walking per day is reached. Prescribed walking doses will be 3, 6, 10, 15, 21, 27 and 30 mins. 
Dose escalation will depend on the presence or absence of adverse incidents. 
Thirty minutes is the maximum minutes of prescribed walking per day because if this is achieved without incident it means that participants can safely meet physical activity guidelines for older adults.  </concealment>
    <sequence>This is a nonrandomised trial.
</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This is a Phase I dose-response trial.
Groups will be dose comparison.   </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The primary analysis will be based on decision rules described by Lin and Shih (2001) to determine the maximum tolerated dose (minutes of walking) in relation to incidents.

Feasibility will be described by reporting the proportion of participants unable to complete their prescribed walking dose due to reasons other than safety. 

To determine if the maximum tolerable dose meets current physical activity guidelines, activity monitor data from the participants who completed the maximum dose will be analysed. Activity monitor data from participants who completed other doses of walking will also be analysed to determine if they met current physical activity guidelines for older adults. Physical activity guidelines will be met if the participant spends at least 30 minutes in moderate intensity physical activity (counted in bouts of 10 minutes or more) on one day or a total of 150 minutes over the 5 days. This physical activity may have been completed during the prescribed walking or at other times (independently or during usual therapy). 

Secondary analyses will describe baseline mobility, walking confidence and demographic data. In addition, secondary outcomes will be used for preliminary exploration of any associations between walking dose and change in mobility, confidence or overall activity levels.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/08/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>20/09/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>13/12/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Peter James Centre - Forest Hill</hospital>
    <postcode>3151 - Burwood East</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Nicholas Taylor</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Physiotherapy Department
La Trobe University
Bundoora
VIC
3086</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Physical Activity and Rehabilitation Research Group, Faculty of Health Sciences, La Trobe University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>La Trobe University, Bundoora, Victoria 3086</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nora Shields</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Physiotherapy Department
La Trobe University
Bundoora
Victoria
3086</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Casey Peiris</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Allied Health Clinical Research Office
5 Arnold Street
Box Hill 
VIC
3128</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Genevieve Kennedy</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Peter James Centre
Mahoneys Road
Burwood East
VIC
3151</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>We already know that the amount of walking completed by people in rehabilitation is very low and people find it hard to regain their walking ability in the community after having a hip fracture. This study will find out how much walking can be feasibly and safely completed by people in rehabilitation after having a hip fracture. The results will help guide therapists as to how much walking they could prescribe to optimise patient outcomes. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Nil</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Eastern Health Research and Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 3, 5 Arnold Street
Box Hill
VIC
3128</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/09/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00211</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/06/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>La Trobe University Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Ethics Committee
La Trobe University
Bundoora
VIC
3086</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>EC00226</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Nicholas Taylor</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
La Trobe University
Bundoora
VIC
3086</address>
      <phone>+613 90918874</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>N.Taylor@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Nicholas Taylor</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
La Trobe University
Bundoora
VIC
3086</address>
      <phone>+613 90918874</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>N.Taylor@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Nicholas Taylor</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
La Trobe University
Bundoora
VIC
3086</address>
      <phone>+613 90918874</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>N.Taylor@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Nicholas Taylor</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
La Trobe University
Bundoora
VIC
3086</address>
      <phone>+613 90918874</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>N.Taylor@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>