<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336040">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/09/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/10/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000825055</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Influence of intrinsic and extrinsic constraints on head movements during eye-head coordination in fullterm and preterm infants among 1 to 4 months</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Influence of age and prematurity (instrinsic constraints) and body orientations (supine, semiflexion and reclined postures - extrinsic constraints) on head movements during eye-head coordination in fullterm from 1 to 4 months of age and preterm healthy infants among 1 to 4 months of corrected age measured by kinematical analysis.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1117-2848</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>not applicable</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>head movements in pre-term infants</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>head movements in fullterm infants</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All infants (fullterm and pre-term) will be evaluated in three conditions (supine, semiflexion and reclined) in every assessment (1, 2, 3 and 4 months). 
The infant will be exposed in three conditions:
1) Condition supine, the chair will be positioned parallel to horizontal plane. 
2) Condition semiflexion, the chair will be  positioned parallel to horizontal plane and an infant pillow (25X20 cm), having a small concavity in the center, maintained the infants neck semiflexed to about 15 degrees. The concavity on the pillow did not restricte head movement. 
3) Condition reclined, the chair will be  positioned 20 degrees from the horizontal and infants neck remained semiflexed. 
The sequence order of conditions exposure will be arranged in three predetermined groups: 1) supine-semiflexion-reclined; 2) reclined-semiflexion-supine; and 3) semiflexion-reclined-supine. 
In all conditions, the infant will be presented with a black and white happy face card (10X10 cm), which will be placed in front of his/her face at eyes height and at a distance of 25-40 cm. The card will be moved slowly (manually, always by the same examiner) in a crosswise direction as soon as the infant had gazed it. When visual contact with the card were lost, it will be presented again, as many times as necessary, within the 2-min period determined for each condition. Visual contact during head movement will be monitored through the reflection of the card image in the infants pupil.</interventions>
    <comparator>The treatment will be the same and will be compared the effects of the tratement on pre-term and term infants</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>median angular velocity of head movement measured by kinematical analysis and Matlab software.</outcome>
      <timepoint>monthly, and in each condition, from 1 to 4 months in fulltem infants and from 1 to 4 months of corrected age for pre-term infants</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>range of motion (flexion extension, inclination and rotation) of head movement, measure by kinematica analysis and Matlab software.</outcome>
      <timepoint>monthly, and in each condition, from 1 to 4 months in fulltem infants and from 1 to 4 months of corrected age for pre-term infants</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>frequency of head movement, measured by watching the images recorded during assessment by three video cameras. These images will be watched in Dvideo software for kinematical analysis, after assessment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>monthly, and in each condition, from 1 to 4 months in fulltem infants and from 1 to 4 months of corrected age for pre-term infants, by quantification of frequencies observed when watching the images recorded, afer assessment. On pre-term infants, the assessment will occur in corrected ages of 1, 2, 3 e 4 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Twenty healthy full-term infants free from neurological or musculoeskeletal pathologies, with gestational age between 37 and 40 weeks, birth weight higher than 2.500 g, Apgar in the first minute higher than 7 and in the fifth minute higher than 9.
Twenty healthy pre-term infants free from neurological or musculoeskeletal pathologies, with gestational age between 30 and 36 weeks, birth weight adequated for gestational age, Apgar in the first minute highter than 7 and in the fifth minute higher than 9.
These convenience sample will be selected based on maternity medical records information.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Months</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>6</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Months</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) congenital defects in the central nervous system (anencephaly, spina bifida, micro / macrocephaly, hydrocephalus, among others);
2) signs of neurological damage (hypoxic-ischemic encephalopathy grades: I, II and III, intracranial hemorrhage, neonatal seizures, spasticity, abnormalities in
reflexes and hypotonia), and 3) musculoskeletal (congenital torticollis, arthrogryposis multiplex, achondroplasia), 4) diagnostic of genetic syndromes (Down syndrome or any syndrome deletion chromosome) or symptoms of  withdrawal symptoms associated with maternal report of abuse of alcohol and drugs, 5) congenital infections (toxoplasmosis, rubella, cytomegalovirus, syphilis,
humam imunodeficiency virus (HIV), hepatitis A, B or C) reported by mothers whose serology, as described in the handbook
motherhood, is positive, 6) have sensory deficits (auditory and visual), detected by thorough pediatric examination performed after the birth at the Maternity and signs of retinopathy of prematurity, grade: II and III, 7) cardio-respiratory problems, 8) hyaline membrane syndrome, sepsis or whose mothers have submitted episode
pre-eclampsia or eclampsia. Will be excluded infants who do not attend for the first evaluation on the given date.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The infants will be included alternately in one of three arrangements (1) supine-semiflexion-reclined; 2) reclined-semiflexion-supine; and 3) semiflexion-reclined-supine).</concealment>
    <sequence>The infants will be included in differents groups according to their arrival order on the first assessment day and remained in the same group in all the following assessments.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Sao Carlos</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Carolina Daniel de Lima-Alvarez</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Rod. Washington Luis, Km 235
Sao Carlos/SP CEP: 13 560 000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Brazil</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Foundation for Research Support of Sao Paulo, National Council for Scientific and Technological Development</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>FAPESP: R. Pio XI, 1500 - Alto da Lapa - CEP 05468-901 - Sao Paulo/SP</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Brazil</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Eloisa Tudella</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Rod. Washington Luis, Km 235
Sao Carlos/SP CEP: 13 560 000</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Brazil</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The current study aim to investigate the influence of different body orientations (extrinsic constraint) on continuous (mean velocity; head range of motion: flexion-extention, inclination and rotation) and categorical (head movement frequency; head trajectory  side-to-midline, midline-to-side and side-to-side; initial head position  right, left and midline) variables of head movements in the period when head control is developing (0-4 months of age considered an intrinsic constraint) in both: fullterm and pre-term infants.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee of the Federal  University of Sao Carlos</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Rod. Washington Luis, Km 235
Sao Carlos/SP CEP: 13 560 000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/12/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>289/2006</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/06/2006</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Brazil</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Eloisa Tudella</name>
      <address>Rod. Washington Luis, Km 235
Sao Carlos/SP CEP: 13 560 000</address>
      <phone>00 55 16 3351 8407</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>eloisatudella@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Carolina Daniel de Lima-Alvarez</name>
      <address>Rod. Washington Luis, Km 235
Sao Carlos/SP CEP: 13 560 000</address>
      <phone>00 55 16 3351 8407</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>caroldaniellima@yahoo.com.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Carolina Daniel de Lima-Alvarez</name>
      <address>Rod. Washington Luis, Km 235
Sao Carlos/SP CEP: 13 560 000</address>
      <phone>00 55 16 3351 8407</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>caroldaniellima@yahoo.com.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>