<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82825">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/05/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/07/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000339358</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pilot efficacy bridging study of two human papillomavirus vaccines administered intradermally and intramuscularly</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot non-inferiority immunogenicity single blind randomised study of two human papillomavirus vaccines administered intradermally to females aged 18 to 26 years to bridge previous efficacy findings of intramuscularly administered vaccine</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Human papilloma virus (HPV) infection</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sexually transmitted infections</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A total of 40 female subjects aged 18-26y at the start of the study will be enrolled. After consent, all subjects will have blood taken for serum antibody to HPV16 and HPV18. Those subjects who test negative for both HPV16 and HPV18 will be randomised, using simple randomisation. Subjects will be vaccinated on Day 1, Month 2 (+/- 2 weeks) and Month 6 (+/- 2 weeks). Five subjects for each vaccine type will receive full dose (0.5ml) intramuscularly, five will receive 20% (0.1ml) of the full dose intramuscularly, five will receive a 20% (0.1ml) of full dose intradermally via an intradermal injection device, and five will receive 20% (0.1ml) of full dose intradermally with a tuberculin syringe and needle for all three vaccine doses. An equal number of subjects will receive Gardasil and Cervarix. As this study involves three clearly identifiable routes of administration for the two vaccines, this will not be a double-blind study. Prior to starting the main study a 20%-dose of Cervavix vaccine (0.1-ml) and a 20%-dose of Gardasil vaccine (0.1-ml) will each be given intradermally via syringe and needle to ten adult males with 5 subjects receiving each vaccine to ensure that no unexpectedly severe reactions occur with the Cervavix vaccine which contains a novel adjuvant (ASO4) that has not been administered intradermally before and could be more reactogenic than vaccines such as Gardasil containing traditional alum adjuvants. Subjects in this reactogenicity assessment will complete Diary Cards, undergo two blood tests and photographs of the skin reactions will be taken.</interventions>
    <comparator>Different vaccine (Gardasil and Cervarix), vaccine dose (full dose and 20% of full dose) and vaccine administration route (intramuscular, intradermal with injection device, intradermal with needle and syringe)</comparator>
    <control>Dose comparison</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of subjects receiving a reduced-dose intradermal schedule, that have a type-specific antibody response to the human papilloma virus vaccine 30 days after the third (month 6) vaccination, that is non-inferior to the type-specific antibody response of those subjects receiving a full-dose intramuscular schedule of the vaccine. The antibody response will be defined by geometric mean titres and seroconversion rates.</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 months after 1st vaccination</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety: Proportion of subjects with systemic reactions after the first, second and third vaccination</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month, 3 months and 7 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety: Proportion of subjects with administration site reactions after the first, second and third vaccination</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month, 3 months and 7 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety: Frequency and severity of occurrence of severe adverse events observed during the entire study period.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Information will be sought at least monthly from study subjects about any severe adverse event occuring during the study period from 0 to 7 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Immunogenicity: Proportion of subjects receiving a reduced-dose intradermal schedule, that have a type-specific antibody response to the human papilloma virus vaccine 30 days after the first (day 1) vaccination, that is non-inferior to the type-specific antibody response of those subjects receiving a full-dose intramuscular schedule of the vaccine. The antibody response will be defined by geometric mean titres and seroconversion rates.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Immunogenicity: Proportion of subjects receiving a reduced-dose intradermal schedule, that have a type-specific antibody response to the human papilloma virus vaccine 30 days after the second (month 2) vaccination, that is non-inferior to the type-specific antibody response of those subjects receiving a full-dose intramuscular schedule of the vaccine. The antibody response will be defined by geometric mean titres and seroconversion rates.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Immunogenicity: Compare the levels of type-specific antibody response developed following administration of the two different vaccines after the first, second and third vaccinations.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month, 3 months and 7 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Immunogenicity: Compare the levels of type-specific antibody response developed following administration of the two different vaccines given by the two different intradermal methods (jet injector and 30 gauge needle/syringe) after the first, second and third vaccinations.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month, 3 months and 7 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Female subjects will be eligible to participate in the study if they: 1. Are 18-26 years of age at the start of the study; 2. Participants have an understanding of the study, agree to its requirements, and give written informed consent prior to study entry; 3. Are generally healthy; 4. Agree to keep a record of symptoms for 14 days after each vaccination; 5. Are sexually naive.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Have previously received HPV vaccine 2. Test positive for either HPV 16/18 serum antibody at enrolment; 3. Are not sexually naive at enrollment; 4. Do not agree to use effective contraception if become sexually active; 5. Are allergic to any vaccine component 6. Have received blood products or components during the previous 6-months 7. Have any known immune or coagulation disorder 8. Received any inactivated vaccine product within the 14 days before enrolment 9. Received any live vaccine product within 21 days before enrolment.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A total of 40 female subjects who meet the inclusion and exclusion criteria, and who can provide written informed consent, will be eligible to be included in the study. After obtaining consent, subjects will select an opaque sealed envelope containing a 4 digit random number. For the main study subjects will not be told which vaccine they have received and for those receiving the vaccine intramuscularly they will not be told whether the dose is full dose or 20% of full dose. Subjects will however be aware whether they have received the vaccine intradermally with either a syringe and needle or with an injection device. The initial 10 subjects participating in the reactogenicity assessment will also not be told which vaccine they have received.</concealment>
    <sequence>For the initial reactogenicity study of 10 subjects, simple randomisation using random numbers created by computer software will be used. The subjects will select an envelope containing a 4 digit number. The nurse administering the vaccine will then use a separate list to match this number to a vaccine (either Gardasil or Cervarix). The nurse will not inform the study subject which vaccine was given and the nurse will not be responsible for following-up the subjects. For the main study of 40 subjects, simple randomisation using random numbers created by computer software will also be used. The 40 subjects aged 18-26y will be randomised into one of 8 groups by the subjects selecting an opaque envelope containing a 4 digit random number. The nurse administering the vaccine will use a separate list to match the number to a vaccine (Gardasil or Cervarix), to a dose (full dose or 20% of full dose) and to a route of administration (intramuscular, intradermal by injection device or intradermal by needle and syringe). The nurse administering the vaccine will not inform the subject which vaccine has been given and the nurse will not be responsible for following up the subjects.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>As this study involves three clearly identifiable routes of administration for the two vaccines, this will not be a double-blind study. However subjects will not be informed which vaccine or which intramuscular dose they have received.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>19/07/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Chinese University of Hong Kong</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Paediatrics
The Chinese University of Hong
6F Clinical Science Building
Prince of Wales Hospital
Shatin</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Hong Kong</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Hong Kong</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Pharmajet Inc</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>221 Corporate Circle, Suite D
Golden, Colorado, 80401</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>United States of America</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Human papilloma virus (HPV) vaccines have the potential to significantly reduce the problem of cervical cancer and a number of countries have recommended their routine administration. This single blind randomised study will compare two HPV vaccines administered by two different routes (intra-muscularly and intradermally) in different doses. The study aims to demonstrate that a reduced dose of vaccine given intradermally is not inferior in terms of protective antibody response (immunogenicity) to a full dose of vaccine given intra-muscularly. Following an initial reactogenicity study of 10 male subjects, a total of 40 female subjects aged 18 to 26 years will be recruited. As the intradermal route has the potential for easier and safer administration of vaccines, at significantly reduced cost, there is the potential for this study to have significant global implications in terms of making these newer, and relatively expensive, vaccines more widely available.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Joint The Chinese University of Hong Kong - New Territories East Cluster Clinical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Flat 3C, Block B, Staff Quarters, Prince of Wales Hospital, Shatin</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/01/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CRE-2007.475-T</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/12/2007</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Hong Kong</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Nelson, Edmund Anthony Severn</name>
      <address>Department of Paediatrics
Prince of Wales Hospital
Shatin</address>
      <phone>+852 26322849</phone>
      <fax>+852 26360020</fax>
      <email>tony-nelson@cuhk.edu.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Nelson, Edmund Anthony Severn</name>
      <address>Department of Paediatrics
Prince of Wales Hospital
Shatin</address>
      <phone>+852 26322849</phone>
      <fax>+852 26360020</fax>
      <email>tony-nelson@cuhk.edu.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Nelson, Edmund Anthony Severn</name>
      <address>Department of Paediatrics
Prince of Wales Hospital
Shatin</address>
      <phone>+852 26322849</phone>
      <fax>+852 26360020</fax>
      <email>tony-nelson@cuhk.edu.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>