<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366059">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/03/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/04/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000406606</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Vado 'trademark' Steerable Sheath System; A Safety and Performance Study to evaluate access to the Pulmonary Veins in the Treatment of Paroxysmal and Persistent Atrial Fibrillation </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Steerable Sheath to access Pulmonary Veins in treatment of Paroxysmal Atrial Fibrillation (PAF) and Persistent Atrial Fibrillation at Christchurch Hospital</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1155-0314 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>paroxysmal atrial fibrillation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>atrial fibrillation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Vado is a steerable sheath that will be inserted into the femoral vein and be advanced into the right atrium to the septum. The sheath will be positioned so that an ablation catheter can be inserted and advanced across the septum to ablate the pulmonary veins. Catheter and sheath will be removed after ablation. The procedure is approximately one hour and patient will go home next day. Follow up at discharge only.  </interventions>
    <comparator>Single group study all patients will receive the same treatment</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1.	Safety: Absence of adverse device related events at release from hospital post procedure per institutional standard of care. 
Possible adverse events include hematoma, infection, access site complications. Outcome will be assessed by ability of ablation catheter to be inserted and retrieved through the sheath visualized fluoroscopically.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcome will be assessed during the procedure after sheath insertion and withdrawal as seen fluoroscopically. Discharge is another assessment for serious adverse events.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2.	Performance: Steerability and Positioning to facilitate catheter placement as seen fluoroscopically and by ability to visualize navigation of ablation catheter to the pulmonary veins.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Intra procedurally the ablation will be performed. Sheath will be visualized fluoroscopically during the procedure.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1.	Safety : Hemostasis and ability to visualize the steerable sheath.  Visualize fluoroscopically and cineangiogram to show placement. Withdrawal of the sheath and hemostasis of the femoral venous entry and exit site. </outcome>
      <timepoint>During the conclusion of the procedure an assessment of the access site by visualizing no bleeding or oozing and good hemostasis of the access site.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2.	Safety: Safe event free Insertion of the steerable sheath system in the femoral vein as seen on fluoroscopy and cineangiogram.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the procedure the sheath will be visualized on fluoro.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.Suitable candidate for intra-cardiac mapping for    
              arrhythmias with documented PAF defined by HRS criteria.
        2.	Eighteen (18) to eighty (80) years of age
        3.	Signed Informed Consent
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.  Intracardiac thrombus, tumor or other abnormality that precludes
 catheter introduction and placement
2.    Severe cerebrovascular disease or history of cerebrovascular event
 within one (1) month
3.    Patients with severely impaired kidney function as measured by a
 Cockcroft-Gault Glomerular Filtration Rate (GFR) 3 with a GFR &lt; 29.
4.    Active gastrointestinal bleeding, infection or fever (&gt; 100.5/38C)
5.    Severe co morbidity or Short life expectancy (&lt;1 year) due to other illnesses such as cancer, pulmonary, hepatic or renal disease 
6. Structural heart disease of clinical significance including
      a. Symptoms of congestive heart failure including, but not limited to,  NYHA   Class III or IV CHF and/or documented ejection fraction &lt; 40% measured by acceptable cardiac testing
      b.Stable/unstable angina or ongoing myocardial ischemia
      c.Myocardial infarction (MI) within three months of enrollment
      d.Aortic or mitral valve disease &gt; Grade II
      e. Congenital heart disease (not including ASD or PFO without a right to left shunt) where the underlying abnormality increases the risk of an ablative procedure 
7.   Enrollment in any other ongoing arrhythmia study protocol
8.   Any ventricular tachyarrhythmia currently being treated where the arrhythmia or the management may interfere with this study
9.    Active infection or sepsis
10.  Female patient is pregnant or lactating
11.  Untreatable allergy to contrast media
12.  Any diagnosis of atrial fibrillation secondary to electrolyte imbalance, thyroid disease, or any other reversible or non-cardiovascular causes
13.  History of blood clotting (bleeding or thrombotic) abnormalities
14.  Known sensitivities to heparin or warfarin
15.  Severe COPD (identified by an FEV1 &lt;1) 

</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Individual subjects will be studied during mapping and ablation procedures and followed until release from hospital post procedure per institutional standard of care. 
study involves the sequential enrollment of patients that meet both inclusion/exclusion criteria.   It is intended that the Vado Steerable Sheath will be used as part of standard clinical workflow procedures, with no procedural deviations relative to other procedures requiring steerable sheaths. </concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>
    </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The safety and performance of the device will be assessed relative to the study objectives. Five (5) patients will be treated.All study results will be analyzed using widely accepted statistical or graphical software. Patient data listings and tabular and graphical presentations of baseline and operative characteristics and outcome results will be provided. Additionally, all adverse events will be summarized by type of event, severity, relationship to the device and/or procedure, and timing of event relative to the procedure date. Data will be evaluated to published literature on currently available steerable sheaths. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>18/04/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>21/04/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>5</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Christchurch</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Kalila Medical</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>745 Camden Ave. 
Campbell, California 95008</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Kalila Medical</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>745 Camden Ave. 
Campbell, California 95008</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To confirm the safe insertion of a steerable sheath in the venous system to direct and perform positioning, and removal of the ablation catheter. Ablation is performed when patients have arrhythmias which cause shortness of breath and can be if not treated life threatening. Acute safety evaluation at end of procedure as evidenced by absence of device related adverse events. Our sheath will be used in usual manner as current available steerable sheaths.

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committees</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
 No 1 The Terrace
 PO Box 5013
Wellington  6145
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/03/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ian Crozier</name>
      <address>Christchurch Hospital
Department of Cardiology
Private Bag 4710
Christchurch 8140</address>
      <phone>+6433641096</phone>
      <fax>+6433786378</fax>
      <email>ian.crozier@cdhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Catherine Cruickshank</name>
      <address>Christchurch Hospital
Department of Cardiology
Private Bag 4710
Christchurch 8140</address>
      <phone>+6433641096</phone>
      <fax>+6433786378</fax>
      <email>catherine.cruickshank@cdhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ian Crozier</name>
      <address>Christchurch Hospital
Department of Cardiology
Private Bag 4710
Christchurch 8140</address>
      <phone>+6433641096</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ian.crozier@cdhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Laura Minarsch</name>
      <address>MMC Medical
430 Forest Ave.
Laguna Beach, CALIFORNIA
92651</address>
      <phone>+1 9492805700</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>laura22@mmc-medical.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>