<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373717">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/10/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/10/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001518358p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Los aMiGoS: Is LactOSe tolerance impacted by repeated exposure to A2 beta-casein MIlk, with effects on Gut COmfort Symptoms</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In young lactose intolerant adults, does the prolonged consumption of A1 beta-casein free milk products improve lactose absorption and tolerance by reduced  gastrointestinal inflammation compared to conventional A1 and A2 beta-casein containing milk products</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111­-1201-­8956</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Los aMiGos</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Impaired digestion</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Lactose intolerance</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other inflammatory or immune system disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Subjects randomized to the intervention will be assigned, in a cross-over manner, to 2 weeks daily consumption of either conventional milk products or a2 milk products (500 ml of full fat milk + 80 g hard cheese), each preceded by 2 weeks of dairy avoidance. Participants need to avoid any other dairy products than provided and fill in the food questionnaires (checklist) throughout the intervention period. </interventions>
    <comparator>Conventional milk which contains both a1 and a2 beta-casein protein.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>  Mean change in breath hydrogen between the two intervention arms. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre lactose ingestion (fasting) and every 30 min post lactose ingestion for 5 hours before (baseline) and after the 2 weeks intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Analysis of digestive symptoms scores e.g. bloating, nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, gastric reflux and abdominal pain by 10 cm Visual Analog Scale (VAS) to measure the change in digestive symptoms before and after the 2 weeks of intervention.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre lactose ingestion (fasting) and every 30 min post lactose ingestion for 5 hours before and after the 2 weeks intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of gut inflammation between the two milk products as measured by fecal markers. This includes measuring fecal calprotectin using ELISA and stool cellular indices (protein and gene expression in intestinal cells).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 2 weeks post intervention (fasting).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Non targeted analysis of fecal metabolites between the two intervention arms by using non-targeted GC-MS . </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 2 weeks post intervention (fasting).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in systemic inflammatory response between the two intervention arms. This include circulating protein cytokines (IL-6, CRP, TNF-a) and immunoglobulin (IgG, IgA and IGM) in serum and PBMCs using ELISA.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and two weeks post intervention (fasting).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Differences in plasma glucose level using a Roche Cobas c311 autoanalyser by enzymatic colorimetric assay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre lactose ingestion (fasting) and every 30 minutes post lactose ingestion for first hour then hourly for 5 hours before and after the two weeks intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Differences in plasma amino acid profiles between the two intervention arms using UPLC. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and two weeks post intervention (fasting).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Analysis of the gastrointestinal symptoms assessed during the intervention measured by
Daily Live Gastrointestinal Symptom diary (LGS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily for 3 days at baseline, and start and end of intervention arm.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure the change in serum peptides between the two intervention arms. This will include targeted analyses of beta-casomorphin-7 using LC-MS and non-targeted analyses of peptides using untargeted LCMS approach.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and two weeks post intervention (fasting).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Analyse the changes in fecal microbiome between the two intervention arms.</outcome>
      <timepoint> Baseline and 2 weeks post intervention (fasting)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Analyse the change in miRNA between the two intervention arms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 2 weeks post intervention (fasting).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Analyse the intestinal inflammation using MRI by measuring  the intestinal wall thickness. between the two intervention arms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 2 weeks post intervention (fasting).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Analyse the bowel motions between the two interventions as measured by Bristol Stool Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily for 3 days at baseline, and start and end of intervention arm.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Analyse the digestive symptoms e.g bloating, nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, gastric reflux and abdominal pain before and after the two weeks intervention by using 10 cm Visual Analog Scale (VAS)  during the intervention.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily for 3 days at baseline, and start and end of intervention arm.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Analyse the change in oxidative stress markers between the two intervention groups including  glutathione (GSH), superoxide dismutase  (SOD) using enzyme immunoassays from plasma.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 2 weeks post intervention (fasting).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>20-40 years
BMI 18-28 kg/m2
Self-described lactose intolerant
Lactose intolerant (confirmed by lactose tolerance test: breath hydrogen and symptoms)
No history of gastrointestinal disease or metabolic disease.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Are not lactose intolerant.
Have an allergy to milk.
Are diagnosed with gastrointestinal disease (i.e. celiac, Crohns, colitis, etc.) or pre-existing metabolic disease.
Are currently taking medications expected to interfere with normal digestive or metabolic processes including proton pump inhibitors, laxatives, antibiotics etc.
Have a medical history precluding a healthy state: history of myocardial infarction, angina, stroke, cancer or pre-existing diabetes, self-reported alcohol intake exceeding a moderate intake (&gt;28 units per week).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation to the intervention sequence will be concealed through use of sealed envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>Treatment randomization and allocation is performed by third party who is not involved in the study procedures or analyses by using a randomization table created by a computer software. .</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Factorial ANOVA will be used to determine differences in the primary and secondary continuous endpoints. Secondary outcomes will be analysed by ANOVA, generalised estimating equations and regression models as appropriate.
Using a clinically relevant reduction in breath hydrogen of 50%, and based on data obtained from graded lactose challenges (12.5g versus 25g) to detect a difference of 99ppm/h to 54ppm/h with a standard deviation of 41 would require 18 subjects per group (sex) to achieve a 90% power with alpha set at 0.05. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/10/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/05/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Auckland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Auckland Research Office
Level 10, Building 620
49 Symonds Street
Suburb/Town: Aucklnad
Postcode: 1010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>AgResearch Ltd.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Grasslands Research Centre
Tennet Drive
Palmerston North
Postcode: 4442</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The a2 Milk Company Limited</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Shortland Street
Auckland
1010
New Zealand
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The a2 Milk Company Limited</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Shortland Street
Auckland
1010
New Zealand
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Many people report digestive problems with dairy products. This dairy intolerance may sometimes be caused by lactose intolerance, but not all people reporting intolerance have confirmed lactose intolerance. Rather, some forms of dairy intolerance may be caused or exacerbated by the protein in milk which manifests as inflammation of the small intestine. Conventional milk contains the A1 version of bovine beta-casein protein. A1 beta-casein may cause intolerance type symptoms in some consumers, resulting in small intestinal inflammation that may also contribute to lactose intolerance. It is proposed that these effects are absent or reduced when dairy products free of this variant are consumed. The A2 version of beta-casein is broken down differently, and may not cause intolerance symptoms in consumers who are sensitive to the A1 beta-casein protein. However, the impacts of variation in beta-casein and intestinal inflammation on lactose malabsorption have not yet been investigated in humans. Due to the possible exacerbation of lactose malabsorption by intestinal inflammation, this study aims to understand whether tolerance to lactose is impacted by repeated exposure to variants of beta-casein. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Central Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Ethics Department
133 Molesworth Street
Wellington 6011
New Zealand </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/09/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David Cameron-Smith</name>
      <address>The Liggins Institute
University of Auckland
Building 505
Grafton, Auckland
1023</address>
      <phone> +6499231336</phone>
      <fax>+649 3738763</fax>
      <email>d.cameron-smith@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David Cameron-Smith</name>
      <address>The Liggins Institute
University of Auckland
Building 505
Grafton, Auckland
1023
</address>
      <phone> +6499231336</phone>
      <fax>+649 3738763</fax>
      <email>d.cameron-smith@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David Cameron-Smith</name>
      <address>The Liggins Institute
University of Auckland
Building 505
Grafton, Auckland
1023
</address>
      <phone> +6499231336</phone>
      <fax>+649 3738763</fax>
      <email>d.cameron-smith@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Amber Milan</name>
      <address>The Liggins Institute
University of Auckland
Building 505
Grafton, Auckland, 1023
New Zealand</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>a.milan@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>