<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82027">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/05/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/05/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000271404</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Immunogenicity and safety of orally administered killed whole cell non-typeable Haemophilus influenzae (Study HI-H003)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A single centre, double blind, placebo controlled, prospective study to assess the immunogenicity and safety of orally administered killed whole cell non-typeable Haemophilus influenzae (NTHi) HI-1-164 in smokers at risk of recurrent bronchitis (Study HI-H003)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Hunter Immunology Ltd Protocol HI-H003</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Smokers at risk of recurrent bronchitis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The test product was formalin-inactivated whole cell non-typeable Haemophilus influenzae formulated in enteric-coated tablets to be taken orally. Each tablet contained 45mg of active ingredient plus excipients. Three courses of tablets were taken by each participant at monthly intervals. Each course consisted of 2 tablets per day for three consecutive days. Thus treatment took place over a period of 60 days. Participants attended visits at 2-week intervals for 3 months.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control placebo tablets contained excipients only.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare surrogate markers of mucosal protection (NTHi-specific antibody in saliva and serum, NTHi-specific T cells in blood) and non-specific parameters (INF-gamma, lysozyme, lactoferrin and nitric oxide in saliva) between vaccine and placebo groups.  NTHi-specific antibody, IFNg, lysozyme and lactoferrin were measured by ELISA assays. NTHi-specific lymphocytes were measured by in vitro proliferation of blood lymphocytes in response to antigen stimulation. Nitric oxide was measured by chemical assay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, at weeks 2,4,6 and 8 during intervention and at weeks 10 and 12 post-intervention. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To monitor nasal and pharyngeal colonisation with NTHi, Moraxella catarrhalis and Streptococcus pneumoniae through the study in vaccine and placebo groups. Quantitative bacteriology was performed by plating out serial dilutions of samples on selective media and performing identity tests where required.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Bacterial carriage was monitored at weeks 2,4,6 and 8 during intervention and at weeks 10 and 12 post-intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To demonstrate safety of the product. Blood samples were collected for pathology safety testing. Pathology tests (Haematology and Biochemistry) were performed by the Hunter Area Pathology Service. Advere event information was collected via patient narrative at each visit to demonstrate safety of the product. Examples of adverse events included cough, hayfever, throat infection (these examples were not related to product).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Adverse event information was obtained at weeks 2,4,6,8 during intervention and weeks 10,12 post-intervention.  Blood for safety profiling was obtained at baseline, week 6 during intervention, and week 12 post-intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To identify episodes of acute bronchitis (defined: episode of purulent sputum)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Obtained at weeks 2,4,6,8 during intervention and weeks 10,12 post-intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Smokers who had smoked at least 10 cigarettes per day for the past 2 years (1 pack year), with no medical or social reason for being unable to comply with requirements of the study, and willingness and ability to give signed informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Known current chronic infection (except episodes of acute bronchitis with or without chronic bronchitis); participation in a clinical trial in the past 3 months; pregnant, breast-feeding, or women with child-bearing potential without an effective method of contraception, any patient likely to withdraw or not comply with the study protocol; any other medical reason that the medical advisor feels that a patient should not be included.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Potential subjects were provided with information sheets and invited to attend a first visit at which willing subjects were enrolled by the clinician. Each subject entered into the study was allocated a Randomisation/Subject number. Randomisation numbers were in sequential blocks which ensured balance between those taking the active tablets and those taking the placebo. The randomisation code was generated by the contract CRO (Novotech Pty Ltd) and kept in a sealed envelope off-site.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer-generated randomisation sequence. Randomisation occurred in blocks of eight to ensure balance between treatment groups.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The study was double-blind with all participants blinded to the randomisation code. The code was broken when the data-base was locked and the statistician performed the statistical analysis knowing the code-break. The people involved in the study were: subjects (identified only by initials and study number) and, investigators (2 clinicians who interviewed the subjects and 2 scientists who were involved in the planning and operation of the study), study co-ordinator, study nurse (who collected samples from the subjects), Hunter Immunology Ltd laboratory staff (who performed assays on study samples), study monitor (supplied by Novotech (Aust) Pty Ltd), Hunter Area Pathology Service (HAPS) (performed Biochemistry and Haematology testing). Note that all samples for testing were identified only by subject number, initials and bar code.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Pharmacokinetics / pharmacodynamics</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>25/07/2005</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>64</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Newcastle Research Associates (TUNRA) Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Newcastle, 
University Drive, 
Callaghan NSW 2308</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Hunter Immunology Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Suite 209-210, 
18 Rodborough Road, 
Frenchs Forest, NSW 2086</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Hunter Immunology Ltd</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>18 Rodborough Road, 
Frenchs Forest, NSW 2086</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study monitored safety and measured specific and non-specific immunological parameters in smokers, who are a group at risk of recurrent bronchitis. This group was chosen rather than healthy non-smoking volunteers for this safety/pharmacokinetic study as it was thought possible that the immune parameters may differ in smokers to that in healthy non-smokers. This safety and immunogenicity study has been completed. It was not registered prior to initiation due to our unawareness of the registration system at that time. As it is a Phase I study and is not required to be registered it is being registered for the purpose of public information as we are now aware that post-initiation registration is possible</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Newcastle Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Office, The University of Newcastle, University Drive, Callaghan NSW 2308</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/06/2005</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H-057-0605</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/05/2005</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Prof Margaret Dunkley</name>
      <address>Hunter Immunology Ltd, Level 4 David Maddison Building, University of Newcastle, Callaghan NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4913 8581</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Margaret.Dunkley@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>E/Prof Robert Clancy</name>
      <address>Immunology &amp; Microbiology, Level 4 David Maddison Building, University of Newcastle, Callaghan NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4913 8195</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4913 8998</fax>
      <email>Robert.Clancy@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>