<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347764">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/01/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/01/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000071820</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Aboriginal Cord Delayed Clamping Study: investigating delayed cord clamping versus immediate cord clamping for term newborn Aboriginal infants from remote Aboriginal communities.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of delayed cord clamping on the haemoglobin levels of term newborn Aboriginal infants from remote Aboriginal communities: a pilot randomized controlled trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1126-0867</utrn>
    <trialacronym>ACDC</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>TBA</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Term birth</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>neonatal health</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaemia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Childbirth and postnatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Delayed cord clamping until the cord stops pulsating (at least 1 minute and no more than 3 minutes after delivery) with baby held below level of placenta or vaginal introitus. If there are complications that arise with the delivery or the baby is in distress at birth, immediate cord clamping is done to allow for neonatal resuscitation.</interventions>
    <comparator>Immediate cord clamping soon after birth (within 1 minute after delivery).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neonatal haemoglobin measured using capillary blood sampling and analyzed in hospital laboratory using standard methods.</outcome>
      <timepoint>after birth prior to hospital discharge (~3 days of age)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Morbidity  (incidence of respiratory distress, jaundice, polycythemia, seizures, sepsis, necrotizing enterocolitis, neonatal death) 
Above conditions will be assessed by their presence or absence during the baby's hospital admission and collected from baby's medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>before hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Apgar Scores of less than 7  to indicate low apgar scores and assessed by their presence or absence and collected fom baby's medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 and 5 minutes</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>SCN admission and assessed by admission or none and noted from baby's medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>before hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>types of treatments received with associated conditions and noted for presence or none and collected from the baby's medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>before hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>newborn length of stay assessed by recording total number of hospital days and collected from baby's medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at time of hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>type of feeding assessed by determining if baby was on breastfeeding, bottlefeeding or mixed feeding on discharge and data collected from baby's medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>effect on Indigenous Cord Blood Collection Program by measuring the total placental volume after delayed cord clamping and comparing this volume to the amounts collected after immediate cord clamping to detect any significant difference that will affect the program's usual volume collected primarily after immediate cord clamping. These volumes will be recorded in a data collection sheet.</outcome>
      <timepoint>before hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>mortality to determine incidence and collected from baby's medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>before hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>pregnant Aboriginal women usually resident in a remote Aboriginal community at 36 to 42 weeks gestation who are expected to give birth by uncomplicated normal vaginal delivery or elective Caesarian section.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>pregnancies complicated by maternal hypertension, pre-eclampsia, risk of post-partum haemorrhage, evidence of intra-uterine growth restriction (estimated fetal weight &lt;10th centile) or congenital malformations</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>pregnant Aboriginal women usually resident in a remote Aboriginal community at 36 to 42 weeks gestation who are expected to give birth by uncomplicated normal vaginal delivery or elective Caesarian section will be consented. Randomization will be done by by investigators or midwifery team present during the second stage of labour. Allocation concealment will be achieved by the use of sequentially numbered sealed opaque envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer-generated randomization sequence will be prepared by an independent statistician at NHMRC Clinical TrialsCentre. The randomization code will be stored securely by the NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre.  The allocation sequence will be concealed from all investigators, staff and participants throughout the study.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>19/01/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>72</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Menzies School of Health Research</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Rocklands Drive, Tiwi, NT, 0810</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Darwin Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Rocklands Drive, Tiwi, NT, 0810</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Royal Darwin Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Rocklands Drive, Tiwi, NT, 0810</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Anaemia is prevalent among Aboriginal infants under 12 months old. Delayed cord clamping is a simple way to provide extra blood to the newborn baby. Strong evidence from randomized controlled trials has shown its benefits for neonatal health and reducing anaemia in early infancy. The beneficial effects on Aboriginal infants and beyond the first 6 months of life are still unknown. It is clinically important to determine if this simple intervention at birth will impact greatly the health of remote Aboriginal infants with high risk of anaemia due to poor access to nutrition later in infancy. 
This RCT will enroll 72 Aboriginal pregnant women from remote aboriginal communities who will give birth at 36-42 weeks gestation by uncomplicated NVD or CS. They will be randomly assigned to either receive the interventional delayed cord clamping until the cord stops pulsating or up to 3 minutes with baby held below level of placenta or vaginal introitus or the standard care immediate cord clamping soon after birth under 1 minute. The primary research question is whether haemoglobin  level at discharge is greatest in babies after delayed cord clamping.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee of the Northern Territory Department of Health and Menzies School of Health Research</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/01/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2011-1657</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/11/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Peter Morris</name>
      <address>Menzies School of Health Research
PO Box 41096
CASUARINA NT 0811</address>
      <phone>+61 8 89228296</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 89275187</fax>
      <email>peter.morris@menzies.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Melanie Hanson</name>
      <address>Paediatric Department, Royal Darwin Hospital
Rocklands Drive, TIWI, NT, 0180</address>
      <phone>+61 8 89228888</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 89275187</fax>
      <email>melanie.hanson@menzies.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Melanie Hanson</name>
      <address>Paediatric Department, Royal Darwin Hospital
Rocklands Drive, TIWI, NT, 0180</address>
      <phone>+61 8 89228888</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 89275187</fax>
      <email>melanie.hanson@menzies.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>