<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6001">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02857361</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Crossover Study to Evaluate the PK Effects of Two Different Wafer Administration Protocols.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An Open Label, Two-way Crossover Study to Evaluate the PK Effects of Two Different Wafer Administration Protocols in Healthy Volunteers Under Fasted Conditions.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>KET011</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pain</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Sublingual ketamine wafers

Experimental: Treatment A: Simultaneous Administration - Sublingual ketamine 50mg (2 x 25mg wafers) administered simultaneously at T=0 minute.

Experimental: Treatment B: Sequential Administration - Sublingual ketamine 50mg (2 x 25mg wafers) administered sequentially, one 25 mg wafer at T=0 minute and one 25 mg wafer at T=3 minutes.


Treatment: drugs: Sublingual ketamine wafers
Two sublingual ketamine 25 mg wafers

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bioavailability - Plasma concentrations collected for 10 hours after simultaneous wafer administration and sequential wafer administration</outcome>
      <timepoint>10 hours</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of treatment related adverse events</outcome>
      <timepoint>From time of initial dose until 3 days after final dose.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participant Acceptance - Participant will rate their experience by completing a questionnaire 20 minutes after each dose.</outcome>
      <timepoint>20 minutes</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Administrator Acceptance - The person administering drug will rate their experience by completing a questionnaire 20 minutes after each dose.</outcome>
      <timepoint>20 minutes</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Males or females aged 18-65 years.

          -  Good general health without clinically significant renal, hepatic, cardiac or
             respiratory disease, as determined by the Principal Investigator.

          -  Willing and able to give informed consent and agree to complete all study procedures.

          -  Have suitable venous access for blood sampling.

          -  Female participants are eligible only if all the following apply:

               1. Not pregnant (women of child bearing potential must have a negative serum
                  pregnancy test at screening and negative urine pregnancy test at check-in for
                  each inpatient period);

               2. Not lactating;

               3. Not planning to become pregnant during the study;

               4. Be surgically sterile (irreversible surgical sterilisation by hysterectomy,
                  bilateral oophorectomy, or bilateral salpingectomy), or have undergone bilateral
                  tubal ligation; or be at least two years post-menopausal; or is practicing
                  double-barrier contraception or is using an insertable, injectable, transdermal,
                  or combination oral contraceptive for greater than 2 months prior to screening
                  visits and commits to the use of an acceptable form of highly effective birth
                  control for the duration of the study and for 30 days after the last dose study
                  drug administration.

          -  BMI within the range of 19-30 kg/m2 (inclusive).

          -  Deemed able to read and understand English in order to communicate with research staff
             and complete protocol required questionnaires and forms.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Has a laboratory value at the Screening Visit that is outside the normal range, unless
             it is judged by the Investigator as not clinically significant after appropriate
             evaluation. One repeat of initial laboratory testing is allowed.

          -  AST, ALT and ALP tests in excess of 1.5 times the upper limit of normal.

          -  Any gastrointestinal condition that could affect drug absorption.

          -  History of any clinically significant condition involving the bladder or urinary
             tract, including frequent urinary tract infections (e.g. &gt; 2 per year), or current
             symptoms of bladder irritation such as frequent or urgent need to urinate or burning
             with urination.

          -  History (within the last six months) of or current clinically significant psychiatric
             disorder including anxiety, psychosis or depression.

          -  Current inflammatory or ulcerative disease of the oral cavity that could impair the
             absorption of sublingual medication.

          -  History of severe allergic or anaphylactic drug-related reactions.

          -  History of hypersensitivity to ketamine or any of the excipients of Wafermine.

          -  Intake of any prescribed or Over-The-Counter (OTC)/non-prescribed drugs, vitamins,
             supplements or herbal medicines, within 2 weeks of administration of investigational
             product (or longer if the medication has a half-life long enough to potentially expose
             the healthy participant to any significant systemic exposure). Exception: Hormone
             replacement therapy and oral contraceptives in female participants is allowed.

          -  Use of drugs with enzyme-inducing properties, such as rifampicin and St John's Wort,
             within 3 weeks or 5 half-lives, whichever is greater, prior to treatment period 1 and
             throughout the study, or any drug known to be a strong inhibitor of CYP3A4 within 5
             half-lives of treatment period 1 and throughout the study.

          -  Participation in another clinical trial of an investigational agent within 30 days of
             screening.

          -  Positive serology for hepatitis C virus (HCV), hepatitis B or human immunodeficiency
             virus (HIV).

          -  Clinically significant, as determined by the Investigator, abnormal ECG (12-lead) or
             vital signs at the screening visit or pre-dose on any treatment day.

          -  Known or suspected drug (including analgesic drugs or tranquilizers) or alcohol abuse
             or dependence, as defined by DSM-IV, and not in full remission, as judged by the
             Investigator, or history of alcohol abuse or excessive intake of alcohol, defined as
             regular weekly intake of &gt;15 units for men and &gt;10 units for women. (1 unit = 25 mL
             spirits, 125 mL wine, 250 mL beer or lager.)

          -  Positive results on the urine drug screen or breath alcohol test at screening and/or
             pre-dose. A positive result on the urinary drug screen at screening is allowed at the
             discretion of the Investigator provided the result can be reliably explained by recent
             medication and/or dietary history.

          -  Significant history of illicit drug use (as determined by the Investigator).

          -  Any alcohol use within 24 hours prior to each inpatient treatment period.

          -  Unwillingness or inability to comply with the requirements of this protocol, including
             the presence of any condition (physical, mental, or social) that is likely to affect
             the participant returning for subsequent visits on schedule.

          -  Blood donation (1 unit or more) within 1 month prior to the screening visit and until
             the end of study participation.

          -  Current or previous tobacco user (within 12 months prior to screening).

          -  Participants who routinely consume more than four standard caffeinated beverages per
             24-hour period.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>10</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/08/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Linear Clinical Research - Nedlands</hospital>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>iX Biopharma Ltd.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study will look at whether it is preferable to administer two wafers simultaneously or
      separately.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02857361</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sam Salman, MD</name>
      <address>iX Biopharma</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>