<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3040">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/01/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/01/2011</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01271803</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Study of Vemurafenib and GDC-0973 (Cobimetinib) in Participants With BRAFV600E Mutation-Positive Metastatic Melanoma</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase IB, Open-Label, Dose-Escalation Study Evaluating the Safety, Tolerability and Pharmacokinetics of Vemurafenib in Combination With GDC-0973 (Cobimetinib) When Administered in BRAFV600E Mutation-Positive Patients Previously Treated (But Without Prior Exposure to BRAF or MEK Inhibitor Therapy) or Previously Untreated for Locally Advanced/Unresectable or Metastatic Melanoma or Those Who Have Progressed After Treatment With Vemurafenib</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NO25395</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Malignant Melanoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Malignant melanoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Cobimetinib
Treatment: drugs - vemurafenib

Experimental: DES (Cohort 1): 60 mg Cobimetinib + 720 mg Vemurafenib - Participants will receive oral 60 milligrams (mg) cobimetinib once daily (QD) on Days 1-14, followed by 14 days off on Days 15-28 (14/14 dosing schedule) and oral 720 mg vemurafenib twice daily (BID) on Days 1-28 of every cycle (1 Cycle=28 Days), until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity, or any other discontinuation criteria are met.

Experimental: DES (Cohort 1A): 60 mg Cobimetinib + 720 mg Vemurafenib - Participants will receive oral 60 mg cobimetinib QD on Days 1-21, followed by 7 days off on Days 22-28 (21/7 dosing schedule) and oral 720 mg vemurafenib BID on Days 1-28 of every cycle (1 Cycle=28 Days), until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity, or any other discontinuation criteria are met.

Experimental: DES (Cohort 1B): 60 mg Cobimetinib + 960 mg Vemurafenib - Participants will receive oral 60 mg cobimetinib QD on 21/7 dosing schedule and oral 960 mg vemurafenib BID on Days 1-28 of every cycle (1 Cycle=28 Days), until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity, or any other discontinuation criteria are met.

Experimental: DES (Cohort 1C): 60 mg Cobimetinib + 720 mg Vemurafenib - Participants will receive oral 60 mg cobimetinib QD on Days 1-28 (28/0 dosing schedule) and oral 720 mg vemurafenib BID on Days 1-28 of every cycle (1 Cycle=28 Days), until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity, or any other discontinuation criteria are met.

Experimental: DES (Cohort 1D): 60 mg Cobimetinib + 960 mg Vemurafenib - Participants will receive oral 60 mg cobimetinib QD on 28/0 dosing schedule and oral 960 mg vemurafenib BID on Days 1-28 of every cycle (1 Cycle=28 Days), until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity, or any other discontinuation criteria are met.

Experimental: DES (Cohort 2): 80 mg Cobimetinib + 720 mg Vemurafenib - Participants will receive oral 80 mg cobimetinib QD on 14/14 dosing schedule and oral 720 mg vemurafenib BID on Days 1-28 of every cycle (1 Cycle=28 Days), until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity, or any other discontinuation criteria are met.

Experimental: DES (Cohort 2A): 100 mg Cobimetinib + 720 mg Vemurafenib - Participants will receive oral 100 mg cobimetinib QD on 14/14 dosing schedule and oral 720 mg vemurafenib BID on Days 1-28 of every cycle (1 Cycle=28 Days), until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity, or any other discontinuation criteria are met.

Experimental: DES (Cohort 3): 60 mg Cobimetinib + 960 mg Vemurafenib - Participants will receive oral 60 mg cobimetinib QD on 14/14 dosing schedule and oral 960 mg vemurafenib BID on Days 1-28 of every cycle (1 Cycle=28 Days), until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity, or any other discontinuation criteria are met.

Experimental: DES (Cohort 4): 80 mg Cobimetinib + 960 mg Vemurafenib - Participants will receive oral 80 mg cobimetinib QD on 14/14 dosing schedule and oral 960 mg vemurafenib BID on Days 1-28 of every cycle (1 Cycle=28 Days), until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity, or any other discontinuation criteria are met.

Experimental: Cobimetinib Monotherapy (100 mg or 60 mg) - Participants will receive oral 60 mg cobimetinib QD on 21/7 dosing schedule, or oral 100 mg cobimetinib QD on 14/14 dosing schedule of every cycle (1 Cycle=28 Days), until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity, or any other discontinuation criteria are met.

Experimental: CES (Cohort 1A): 60 mg Cobimetinib + 720 mg Vemurafenib - Participants will receive oral 60 mg cobimetinib QD on 21/7 dosing schedule and oral 720 mg vemurafenib BID on Days 1-28 of every cycle (1 Cycle=28 Days), until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity, or any other discontinuation criteria are met.

Experimental: CES (Cohort 1B): 60 mg Cobimetinib + 960 mg Vemurafenib - Participants will receive oral 60 mg cobimetinib QD on 21/7 dosing schedule and oral 960 mg vemurafenib BID on Days 1-28 of every cycle (1 Cycle=28 Days), until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity, or any other discontinuation criteria are met.


Treatment: drugs: Cobimetinib
Participants will receive cobimetinib 60 to 100 mg at any of the 3 dosing schedules with or without vemurafenib in cycles of 28 days each until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity, or any other discontinuation criteria are met.

Treatment: drugs: vemurafenib
Participants will receive vemurafenib 720 or 960 mg along with cobimetinib in cycles of 28 days each until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity, or any other discontinuation criteria are met.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With Dose-Limiting Toxicities (DLTs) During DES in Combination Cohorts - DLT is defined as 1 of the following toxicities considered by the investigator to be related to study treatment: a) Grade 3 nausea, vomiting or diarrhea that resolved to Grade less than or equal to (=) 1 within 7 days, b) Grade 3 rash or photosensitivity that resolved to Grade =2 within 7 days, c) Grade 3 cutaneous squamous cell carcinoma (cuSCC) that was subsequently resected, d) Grade greater than or equal to (=) 3 fatigue or hyperuricemia that resolved to Grade =2 within 7 days, e) Grade 3 fever, f) Grade 3 or 4 elevation of serum creatine phosphokinase (CPK) levels, which is asymptomatic, deemed by the investigator to be clinically insignificant and that returned to Grade =2 during the 14-day cobimetinib treatment holiday, g) Grade =3 febrile neutropenia, h) Grade =4 neutropenia (absolute neutrophil count [ANC] less than &lt;500/microliter [µL]), i) Grade =4 thrombocytopenia, j) Grade =4 anemia, k) Grade =3 elevation of total bilirubin, hepatic transaminase or alkaline phosphatase.</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 Days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximum Tolerated Doses (MTD) of Vemurafenib and Cobimetinib When Administered in Combination in DES - The highest dose level(s) at which fewer than one-third of participants experienced a DLT was declared the MTD. DLT is defined as 1 of the following toxicities considered by the investigator to be related to study treatment: a) Grade 3 nausea, vomiting or diarrhea that resolved to Grade =1 within 7 days, b) Grade 3 rash/photosensitivity that resolved to Grade =2 within 7 days, c) Grade 3 cuSCC that was subsequently resected, d) Grade =3 fatigue/hyperuricemia that resolved to Grade =2 within 7 days, e) Grade 3 fever, f) Grade 3 or 4 elevation of serum CPK levels, which is asymptomatic, deemed to be clinically insignificant and returns to Grade =2 during the 14-day cobimetinib treatment holiday, g) Grade =3 febrile neutropenia, h) Grade =4 neutropenia (ANC &lt;500/ µL), i) Grade =4 thrombocytopenia, j) Grade =4 anemia, k) Grade =3 elevation of total bilirubin, hepatic transaminase or alkaline phosphatase.</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 Days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximum Plasma Concentration (Cmax) of Cobimetinib on Day 1, Cycle 1</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cycle 1: predose (0 hours [hr]) on Days 1, 2; 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6 hr postdose on Day 1</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cmax of Cobimetinib on Day 1, Cycle 1 in Cohort 3</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cycle 1: predose (0 hr) on Days 1, 2; 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6 hr postdose on Day 1</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time Taken to Reach Maximum Plasma Concentration (Tmax) of Cobimetinib on Day 1, Cycle 1</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cycle 1: predose (0 hr) on Days 1, 2; 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6 hr postdose on Day 1</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Area Under Concentration Versus Time Curve (AUC) Over a Period of 24 Hours (AUC0-24) of Cobimetinib on Day 1, Cycle 1</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cycle 1: predose (0 hr) on Days 1, 2; 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6 hr postdose on Day 1</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>AUC0-24 of Cobimetinib on Day 1, Cycle 1 of Cohort 3</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cycle 1: predose (0 hr) on Days 1, 2; 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6 hr postdose on Day 1</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cmax of Cobimetinib on Day 14 (Steady State), Cycle 1</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cycle 1: predose (0 hr) on Days 8, 14; 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6 hr postdose on Day 14</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tmax of Cobimetinib on Day 14 (Steady State), Cycle 1</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cycle 1: predose (0 hr) on Days 8, 14; 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6 hr postdose on Day 14</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>AUC0-24 of Cobimetinib on Day 14, Cycle 1</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cycle 1: predose (0 hr) on Days 8, 14; 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6 hr postdose on Day 14</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clearance (CL) of Cobimetinib on Day 14 (Steady State), Cycle 1 - Clearance of a drug is a measure of the rate at which a drug is metabolized or eliminated by normal biological processes.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cycle 1: predose (0 hr) on Days 8, 14; 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6 hr postdose on Day 14</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cmax of Vemurafenib on Day -1, Cycle 1 in Participants Previously Treated With Vemurafenib Prior to Enrollment Into This Study</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose (0 hr) on Days -1, 1; 2, 4, 6, 8 hr postdose on Day -1</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cmax of Vemurafenib on Day -1, Cycle 1 of Cohorts 1C and 2A in Participants Previously Treated With Vemurafenib Prior to Enrollment Into This Study</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose (0 hr) on Day -1, 1; 2, 4, 6, 8 hr postdose on Day -1</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tmax of Vemurafenib on Day -1, Cycle 1 in Participants Previously Treated With Vemurafenib Prior to Enrollment Into This Study</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose (0 hr) on Day -1, 1; 2, 4, 6, 8 hr postdose on Day -1</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cmax of Vemurafenib on Day 1, Cycle 1 in BRAFi-naïve Participants</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose (0 hr) on Day 1, 2; 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6 hr postdose on Day 1</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cmax of Vemurafenib on Day 1, Cycle 1 in Cohort 1A in BRAFi-naïve Participants</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose (0 hr) on Day 1, 2; 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6 hr postdose on Day 1</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tmax of Vemurafenib on Day 1, Cycle 1 in BRAFi-naïve Participants</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose (0 hr) on Day 1, 2; 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6 hr postdose on Day 1</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cmax of Vemurafenib on Day 14, Cycle 1</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose (0 hr) on Days 14, 15; 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, 8 hr postdose on Day 14</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tmax of Vemurafenib on Day 14, Cycle 1</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose (0 hr) on Days 14, 15; 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, 8 hr postdose on Day 14</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants With an Objective Response of Complete Response (CR) or Partial Response (PR) According to Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) Version (V) 1.1 - Tumor response of CR or PR is considered as objective response. CR: disappearance of all target lesions, reduction in short axis &lt;10 millimeters in pathological lymph nodes (target and non-target lesions); PR: at least a 30 percent (%) decrease in the sum of the longest diameter of target lesions, taking as reference the baseline sum longest diameter. Responses were confirmed by repeat assessments =4 weeks after initial documentation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Screening to up to data cut-off (01 October 2013) (assessed at screening [within 28 days prior to initiation of Cycle 1], every 6 weeks thereafter until disease progression or death or data cut-off [01 October 2013]) up to 32 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants With Disease Progression According to RECIST V 1.1 - Progressive disease (PD) according to RECIST V 1.1: at least a 20% increase in the sum of the longest diameter of target lesions, taking as reference the smallest sum on study (nadir), including baseline; in addition to the relative increase of 20%, the sum must also demonstrate an absolute increase of at least 5 mm; appearance of 1 or more lesions is also considered as progression.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Screening to up to data cut-off (01 October 2013) (assessed at screening [within 28 days prior to initiation of Cycle 1], every 6 weeks thereafter until disease progression or death or data cut-off [01 October 2013]) up to 32 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Median Duration of Response (DOR) - Duration of response, defined as the time from first occurrence of a documented objective response until the time of disease progression, as determined by investigator review of tumor assessments using RECIST v 1.1, or death from any cause during the study (that is within 30 days after the last dose of study treatment).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Screening to up to data cut-off (01 October 2013) (assessed at screening [within 28 days prior to initiation of Cycle 1], every 6 weeks thereafter until disease progression or death or data cut-off [01 October 2013]) up to 32 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Survival (OS) - OS was defined as the time from the date of randomization to the date of death due to any cause. Participants were censored at the last date of tumor measurement, the last date in the study drug log, or the date of last follow-up. OS analyzed using Kaplan-Meier estimate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Screening to up to data cut-off (01 October 2013) (assessed at screening [within 28 days prior to initiation of Cycle 1], every 6 weeks thereafter until disease progression or death or data cut-off [01 October 2013]) up to 32 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Average Percent Change From Baseline in Fluorodeoxyglucose-positron Emission Tomography (FDG-PET) at Cycle 1 and Cycle 2 - The pharmacodynamic effect of cobimetinib in combination with vemurafenib was assessed by measuring changes in FDG uptake as characterized by the lean body mass corrected (LBM) maximum standardized uptake value (SUV max) measurement using FDG-PET. Post-baseline timepoint Cycle 1 was averaged between Days 10 to 14 and Cycle 2 for Days 14+7.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cycle 1 (Days 10 to 14), Cycle 2 (Days 14+7)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacodynamics: Number of Participants With Mitogen-Activated Protein Kinase (MAPK) Inhibition, as Assessed by Immunohistochemistry (IHC) - Changes in effector molecules of the MAPK pathway that are directly or indirectly affected by BRAF and MEK inhibition (including but not limited to ERK and phosphorylated ERK and MEK) by IHC using biopsies at baseline, between Days 10-14 of Cycle 1, and at disease progression. IHC is a staining process performed on fresh/frozen tumor tissue samples.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline; Cycle 1: Day 14; at disease progression (Up to 32 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Participants with histologically confirmed melanoma (unresectable Stage IIIc and Stage
             IV metastatic melanoma, as defined by American Joint Committee on Cancer [AJCC])

          -  Measurable disease per Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) Version
             (V) 1.1

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status of less than or equal to
             (&lt;/=) 1

          -  Participants must

               1. be previously untreated for locally advanced/unresectable or metastatic melanoma
                  or

               2. previously treated but without prior exposure to any BRAF or MEK inhibitor
                  therapy or

               3. progressed on vemurafenib while participating in a Phase I (including clinical
                  pharmacology studies), II, or III clinical study or expanded access programs
                  (EAP) immediately prior to enrollment in this study or

               4. progressed on vemurafenib administered in a postmarketing setting immediately
                  prior to enrollment in this study.

          -  Life expectancy &gt;/=12 weeks</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  History of prior significant toxicity from another RAF or MEK pathway inhibitor
             requiring discontinuation of treatment

          -  Palliative radiotherapy within 2 weeks prior to first dose of study drug treatment

          -  Experimental therapy within 4 weeks prior to first dose of study drug treatment except
             vemurafenib

          -  Major surgery within 4 weeks of first dose of study drug treatment or planning a major
             surgery during the study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>17/02/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>131</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>29/06/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Peter Maccallum Cancer Institute; Medical Oncology - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3000 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Colorado</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Illinois</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Indiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Michigan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Tennessee</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Hoffmann-La Roche</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This open-label, dose-escalation study of vemurafenib in combination with cobimetinib will
      evaluate the safety, tolerability and pharmacokinetics in participants with BRAFV600
      mutation-positive metastatic melanoma. Participants with previously untreated, BRAFV600E
      mutation-positive, locally advanced/unresectable or metastatic melanoma or those who have
      progressed on vemurafenib monotherapy immediately prior to enrolling in this trial are
      eligible. Participants will be assigned to different cohorts with escalating oral doses of
      vemurafenib and cobimetinib. This study consists of 2 stages, Stage 1 (Dose Escalation Stage
      [DES] and Cohort Expansion Stage [CES]) and the anticipated time on study treatment is until
      disease progression, unacceptable toxicity or any other discontinuation criterion is met.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01271803</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Clinical Trials</name>
      <address>Hoffmann-La Roche</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>