<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="1162">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/05/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/05/2006</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00327171</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Study of AVE0005 (VEGF Trap) in Patients With Chemoresistant Advanced Ovarian Cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Multicenter, Randomized, Double-blind, Parallel-arm, Two-stage Study of the Efficacy and Safety of AVE0005 (VEGF Trap) Administered Intravenously Every 2 Weeks in Patients With Platinum-resistant and topotecan-and/or Liposomal Doxorubicin-resistant Advanced Ovarian Cancer</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>AVE0005</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>ARD6122</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Neoplasms</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cancer of the Ovary</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ovarian and primary peritoneal</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Aflibercept (ziv-aflibercept, AVE0005, VEGF trap, ZALTRAP®)
Treatment: drugs - Aflibercept (ziv-aflibercept, AVE0005, VEGF trap, ZALTRAP®)

Experimental: Aflibercept 2.0 mg/kg - Participants with advanced ovarian epithelial adenocarcinoma administered 2.0 mg/kg Aflibercept.

Experimental: Aflibercept 4.0 mg/kg - Participants with advanced ovarian epithelial adenocarcinoma administered 4.0 mg/kg Aflibercept.


Treatment: drugs: Aflibercept (ziv-aflibercept, AVE0005, VEGF trap, ZALTRAP®)
Aflibercept 4.0 mg/kg administered intravenously (IV) over 1 hour once every 2 weeks.
Aflibercept could be reduced by 1 dose level ( to 2.0 mg/kg) or 2 dose levels (to 1.0 mg/kg) in case of uncontrolled hypertension or urinary protein &gt;3.5 g/24 hours. Intrapatient dose escalation was not to be permitted. Participants requiring more than 2 dose level reductions would be withdrawn from study treatment.

Treatment: drugs: Aflibercept (ziv-aflibercept, AVE0005, VEGF trap, ZALTRAP®)
Aflibercept 2.0 mg/kg administered intravenously (IV) over 1 hour once every 2 weeks.
Aflibercept could be reduced by 1 dose level (to 1.0 mg/kg) or 2 dose levels (to 0.5 mg/kg) in case of uncontrolled hypertension or urinary protein &gt;3.5 g/24 hours. Intrapatient dose escalation was not to be permitted. Participants requiring more than 2 dose level reductions would be withdrawn from study treatment.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With Confirmed Objective Response (OR) as Per Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) Based on the Analysis by an Independent Review Committee (IRC) - Simon's Cohort - OR included Complete Response (CR) and Partial Response (PR). Per RECIST, CR was disappearance of all target or non-target lesions, or normalization of tumor marker levels (for non-target lesions) and PR was at least a 30% decrease in the sum of the longest diameter (LD) of target lesions, with baseline sum LD as reference.
Tumors were assessed by an independent third-party core imaging laboratory evaluating the chest, abdomen, and pelvis by Computerized Tomography (CT) scans or Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) scans; and responses were confirmed by repeat tumor imaging 4-6 weeks later.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From enrollment to efficacy cut-off date, 18 January 2008 (approximately 20 months)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With Confirmed Objective Response (OR) as Per Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) Based on the Analysis by the IRC - Efficacy Evaluable Population - OR included Complete Response (CR) and Partial Response (PR). Per RECIST, CR was disappearance of all target or non-target lesions, or normalization of tumor marker levels (for non-target lesions) and PR was at least a 30% decrease in the sum of the longest diameter (LD) of target lesions, with baseline sum LD as reference.
Tumors were assessed by an independent third-party core imaging laboratory evaluating the chest, abdomen, and pelvis by Computerized Tomography (CT) scans or Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) scans; and responses were confirmed by repeat tumor imaging 4-6 weeks later.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From enrollment to efficacy cut-off date, 18 January 2008 (approximately 20 months)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With a Clinical Benefit Response (CBR) as Per RECIST Based on the Analysis by the IRC - CBR was defined as having a Stable disease (SD) for &gt;= 6 months or a confirmed OR (PR or CR). Based on RECIST:
SD was neither a sufficient shrinkage of the target lesions to qualify for PR nor sufficient increase to qualify for Progressive disease (PD), the persistence of non-target lesions or the maintenance of tumor marker level above the normal limits (for non-target lesions)
CR was the disappearance of all target or non-target lesions; and PR was at least a 30% decrease in the sum of the longest diameter (LD) of target lesions, with reference to the baseline sum LD.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From enrollment to efficacy cut-off date, 18 January 2008 (approximately 20 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of Response (DR) Based on the Analysis by an Independent Review Committee (IRC) - DR was defined as the time interval from the first documentation of CR or PR to the date of tumor progression (or disease progression) as determined by RECIST, or death from any cause, whichever was earlier.
Based on RECIST, progressive disease was at least a 20% increase in the sum of the LD of target lesions, taking as reference the smallest sum LD recorded since the treatment started, the appearance of one or more new target or non-target lesions, or the unequivocal progression of existing non-target lesions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From enrollment to efficacy cut-off date, 18 January 2008 (approximately 20 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tumor Marker Response Rate (TMRR) Based on the Gynecologic Cancer Intergroup (GCIG) Definition - TMRR was the proportion of evaluable participants achieving a cancer antigen -125 (CA-125) response based on GCIG definition. A response to CA-125 occurred if after two elevated levels before therapy there was at least a 50% decrease in a post-treatment serum sample, which was confirmed by an independent sample collected 21 days or later that was =&lt; 110% of the post-treatment serum sample.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From enrollment to efficacy cut-off date, 18 January 2008 (approximately 20 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Tumor Progression (TTP) as Per RECIST Based on the Analysis by the IRC - TTP was defined as the time interval measured from the date of randomization to the date of tumor progression as determined by RECIST. TTP was estimated from Kaplan-Meier curves.
For a participant who did not reach tumor progression during study, the censoring date was the date of the last valid tumor burden assessment or the date of study cut-off, whichever was earlier. If the participant had no valid post-baseline tumor burden assessment due to early termination, the censoring date was the date of randomization.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From enrollment to efficacy cut-off date, 18 January 2008 (approximately 20 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Tumor Marker (CA-125) Progression (TTMP) - TTMP was the time interval from the date of randomization to the date of tumor marker progression as was defined by GCIG for the evaluable participants. TTMP was estimated using Kaplan-Meier curves.
For a participant who did not reach tumor marker progression (TMP) during study, the censoring date was the date of the last valid tumor burden assessment or the date of study cut-off, whichever was earlier. If the participant had no valid post-baseline tumor burden assessment due to early termination, the censoring date was the date of randomization.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From enrollment to efficacy cut-off date, 18 January 2008 (approximately 20 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With Disease Progression Events for Progression-free Survival (PFS) Analysis by the IRC. - PFS was as the time interval measured from the date of randomization to the date of tumor progression as determined by RECIST or death from any cause, whichever was earlier.
The number of participants with tumor/disease progression are reported. Participants who did not reach tumor progression during study, or had no valid post-baseline tumor burden assessment due to early termination, were censored in the PFS analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From enrollment to efficacy cut-off date, 18 January 2008 (approximately 20 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression-free Survival (PFS) Time Based on Analysis by the IRC - PFS was as the time interval measured from the date of randomization to the date of tumor progression as determined by RECIST or death from any cause, whichever was earlier. PFS was estimated using Kaplan-Meier curves.
For a participant who did not reach tumor progression during study, the censoring date was the date of the last valid tumor burden assessment or the date of study cut-off, whichever was earlier. If the participant had no valid post-baseline tumor burden assessment due to early termination, the censoring date was the date of randomization.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From enrollment to efficacy cut-off date, 18 January 2008 (approximately 20 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Survival (OS) Time - OS was the time interval between randomization and the date of death from any cause. OS was estimated using Kaplan-Meier curves
A participant was censored for the OS analysis if the participant were alive during the study. The censoring date was either at the date that the participant was last known to be alive or the date of study cut-off, whichever was earlier.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From enrollment to efficacy cut-off date, 18 January 2008 (approximately 20 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Safety - Number of Participants With Adverse Events (AE) - All AEs regardless of seriousness or relationship to study treatment, spanning from the first administration of study treatment until 30 days after the last administration of study treatment, were recorded, and followed until resolution or stabilization. The number of participants with all treatment emergent adverse events (TEAE), serious adverse events (SAE), TEAE leading to death, and TEAE leading to permanent treatment discontinuation are reported.</outcome>
      <timepoint>up to 30+/-5 days after treatment discontinuation, or up to recovery or stabilization of a followed-up adverse event</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participant's Assessment of Health Related Quality of Life (HRQL) Using a by Using the Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy-Ovarian (FACT-O) Questionnaire - The FACT-O questionnaire consists of 38 scored questions (scored from 0-4) that address physical well-being, social/family well-being, emotional well-being, functional well-being and some additional concerns which relate specifically to ovarian cancer symptoms. For each question, higher scores reflect a better quality of life. The total FACT-O score ranges from 0-152, with 152 indicating the best outcome.</outcome>
      <timepoint>On Day 1 of Cycle 1 (baseline) , and after Day 14 of Cycle 2</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants who met the following criteria were eligible for the study.

        

          -  Histologically-confirmed ovarian epithelial (including fallopian tube and primary
             peritoneal) adenocarcinoma.

          -  Prior treatment with at least 2 treatment regimens in the advanced disease treatment
             setting

          -  Platinum-resistant disease defined by relapse or progression of disease during or
             after treatment, or drug intolerance

          -  Topotecan- and/or liposomal doxorubicin-resistant disease defined by relapse or
             progression of disease during or after treatment, or drug intolerance

          -  Evidence of at least one unidimensional measurable tumor lesion by computed tomography
             (CT) or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan according to Response Evaluation
             Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) that has not been treated with surgery or radiation
             therapy</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Female</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Diagnosis of any second malignancy within the last 5 years, except for adequately
             treated basal cell or squamous cell skin cancer, or for in situ carcinoma of the
             cervix uteri

          -  Prior treatment with a vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) or VEGF receptor
             inhibitor

          -  More than 3 chemotherapy regimens in the advanced disease treatment setting

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension

        The above information is not intended to contain all considerations relevant to potential
        participation in a clinical trial.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/05/2006</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>218</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/03/2010</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>Sanofi-Aventis Administrative Office - Macquarie Park</hospital>
    <postcode> - Macquarie Park</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Jersey</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Laval</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Paris</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Berlin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Milano</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Gouda</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <state>Porto Salvo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Bromma</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state>Geneva</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Sanofi</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Regeneron Pharmaceuticals</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study evaluated outcomes in participants with advanced ovarian epithelial adenocarcinoma
      receiving aflibercept.

      The primary objective was to compare the objective response rate of Aflibercept
      (ziv-aflibercept, AVE0005, VEGF trap, ZALTRAP®) 4.0 mg/kg and 2.0 mg/kg, administered
      intravenously (IV) every 2 weeks with historical control in participants with advanced
      ovarian epithelial (including fallopian tube and primary peritoneal) adenocarcinoma resistant
      to platinum and topotecan and/or liposomal doxorubicin.

      The secondary objectives was to further assess efficacy, safety, pharmacokinetics, potential
      biological and pharmacogenomic markers of study drug activity, and health-related quality of
      life.

      This study employed an Independent Review Committee (IRC) for radiological tumor assessments.
      For all tumor assessment-related efficacy variables, two analyses were performed: the primary
      analysis was based on Independent Review Committee (IRC) reviewed data and the secondary
      analysis was based on Investigator evaluation. If an endpoint was evaluated by the IRC, the
      IRC reviewed data is reported for this study.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00327171</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>ICD CSD</name>
      <address>Sanofi</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>