<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3031">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/12/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/12/2010</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01263275</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Trial of Transcranial Direct Current Stimulation (tDCS) for Depression</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Open Pilot Trial of Transcranial Direct Current Stimulation (tDCS) for Depression.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>10368</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Major Depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - tDCS (Eldith DC-Stimulator (CE certified))

Experimental: Active tDCS - 


Treatment: devices: tDCS (Eldith DC-Stimulator (CE certified))
Each tDCS session lasting continuously for 20 minutes at 2 mA

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Montgomery Asberg Depression Rating Scale for Depression (MADRS). - Baseline (pre-treatment), post 8, post 15 and post 20 tDCS sessions, and follow-up 1 week, 1 month, 3 months and 6 months post treatment</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Subject meets criteria for a DSM-IV Major Depressive Episode.

          2. Total MADRS score =20.

          3. Subject has not responded to tDCS given with a standard montage OR subject is unable
             to receive tDCS with standard montage - for example, due to skin rash etc at site of
             electrode placement for standard montage.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>90</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Diagnosis (as defined by DSM-IV) of: any psychotic disorder (lifetime); eating
             disorder (current or within the past year); obsessive compulsive disorder (lifetime);
             post-traumatic stress disorder (current or within the past year); mental retardation.

          2. History of drug or alcohol abuse or dependence (as per DSM-IV criteria) within the
             last 3 months (except nicotine and caffeine).

          3. Inadequate response to ECT in the current episode of depression.

          4. Subject is on regular benzodiazepine medication which it is not clinically appropriate
             to discontinue.

          5. Subject requires a rapid clinical response due to inanition, psychosis or high suicide
             risk.

          6. Neurological disorder or insult, e.g., recent stroke (CVA), which places subject at
             risk of seizure or neuronal damage with tDCS.

          7. Subject has metal in the cranium, skull defects, or skin lesions on scalp (cuts,
             abrasions, rash) at proposed electrode sites.

          8. Female subject who is pregnant.

          9. Participants who are not fluent in English will not be included in the trial for
             safety reasons: a) It is usually not possible to have an interpreter reliably
             available every weekday for up to 4 weeks and it is not safe to give tDCS to a subject
             who cannot tell us immediately of any side effects; b) As this is a novel treatment,
             the study involves detailed neuropsychological testing for safety reasons. This
             testing cannot be effectively or validly completed by someone who is not fluent in
             English. Note that translation of the proposed tests into English has not been
             validated and that we cannot be confident that neuropsychological impairment would be
             detected using this method.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/12/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>3</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/07/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Black Dog Institute - Randwick, Sydney</hospital>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick, Sydney</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of New South Wales</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Among antidepressant treatments, ECT stands as the most effective in treating acute
      depression. However, patient concerns with the cognitive side effects of ECT have encouraged
      the development of new and more focal forms of brain stimulation such as transcranial Direct
      Current Stimulation (tDCS). However, not all patients may respond to this treatment in the
      way that it is currently administered and this has raised interest in finding alternative,
      possibly more optimal ways of administering tDCS. This study will investigate whether tDCS
      stimulation using an alternative electrode montage has antidepressant effects.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01263275</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Colleen Loo, MBBS, FRANZCP, MD</name>
      <address>School of Psychiatry, University of New South Wales</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>