<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2701">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/03/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/03/2010</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01086930</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>SCIPA (Spinal Cord Injury and Physical Activity) Hands-On: Early Intensive Hand Rehabilitation After Spinal Cord Injury</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>SCIPA (Spinal Cord Injury and Physical Activity) Hands-On: Early Intensive Hand Rehabilitation After Spinal Cord Injury</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>SCIPA Hands-On</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>SCIPA Hands-On</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Spinal Cord Injury</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other skin conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fractures</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - ReJoyce Workstation
Other interventions - Standard Care

Experimental: Intervention Group - In addition to standard care participants in Group A will receive:
 One hour of extra hand training five times per week for 8 weeks
The training will be supervised by a therapist and provided to the target hand. It will consist of FES-assisted hand exercises on an instrumented exercise workstation (ReJoyce). The hand exercises will be incorporated into computer games and will involve the following tasks using different manipulanda:
reaching
grasping
manipulating
pulling
rotating
releasing

Other: Standard Care Group - Participants in the control group will not receive any training on the instrumented workstation or electrical stimulation to the hand or upper limb. They will however continue to receive standard care as well as three 15-minute specific hand activity sessions per week specifically devoted to the practice of hand activities in a one-to-one format with a therapist (as per the treatment received by the experimental group).


Treatment: devices: ReJoyce Workstation
The device has two parts. The first part is a muscle-stimulator garment that incorporates a wireless-triggered stimulator cuff, word on the forearm and triggered when the user clicks his/her teeth. The tooth clicks (vibrations) are detected by an earpiece, similar to a hearing aid, that sends a radio signal to the stimulator cuff. This is turn stimulates the hand to open or close, allowing patients to grasp and release objects. The second part of the device is a specialised workstation known as ReJoyce, which connects to a standard computer via a USB port. This work station will allow the user to play specialised computer games focusing on hand function. The stimulator system and the ReJoyce workstation were developed by Professor Arthur Prochazka, University of Alberta, Canada and has been approved by the Canadian Standards Association. The device is currently being used in a study conducted through the University of Alberta.

Other interventions: Standard Care
All participants will continue to receive the same standard care for the hand and upper limb as typically provided by their rehabilitation units. This will be provided as part of regular physiotherapy, vocational, recreational and occupational therapy and provided by participants' usual treating therapists. These therapists will not be involved in administering the study-specific interventions.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the relative effectiveness of an intensive task-specific motor training program and standard rehabilitation compared with standard rehabilitation alone for improving hand function and clinical outcomes in people with recent tetraplegia.</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients will be included if they:

          1. have sustained a SCI within the preceding 6 months from time of consent

          2. are currently receiving inpatient rehabilitation through one of the study sites

          3. will remain in hospital for 12 weeks after initial screening as part of their standard
             medical/rehabilitation care

          4. are 16 years of age or older and able to provide informed consent

          5. have a motor complete or incomplete spinal cord injury at the neurological level of C2
             to T1 (as per the International Standardised Neurological Assessment for SCI)

          6. can actively flex their shoulder/s to 60 degrees

          7. have reduced ability to grasp using their hands

          8. are able to tolerate sufficient FES to enable one hand to grasp and release

          9. have the potential to benefit from FES and ReJoyce according to the judgment of the
             treating therapist</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients will not be included if they:

          1. have any other type of neurological injury affecting the target hand (e.g. brachial
             plexus or peripheral nerve injuries)

          2. have had recent trauma or surgery to the target hand or upper limb within the last 12
             months

          3. have had amputation of any digits on the target hand

          4. are not able to sit out of bed each day for at least 2 hours over three consecutive
             days

          5. have extensive fixed contractures in the upper limb of the target hand preventing use
             of the ReJoyce

          6. have severe spasticity in the target hand or upper limb preventing use of the ReJoyce

          7. are unable to attend the 6-month and 1-year follow-up assessments at their treating
             spinal unit

          8. are likely to undergo hand surgery in the target hand in the next year

          9. might experience autonomic dysreflexia and/or hypotension in response to electrical
             stimulation

         10. have any contraindications to FES, such as cardiac pacemaker, epilepsy, forearm
             fracture or pregnancy

         11. have intracranial metal implants

         12. have impaired vision and/or are unable to view a computer screen

         13. have any other serious medical condition including malignancies, psychiatric,
             behavioural or drug-dependency problems, which are likely to influence the
             participant's ability to cooperate or in the opinion of the study investigator would
             prevent the participant from adhering to the Protocol.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/09/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>78</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Unknown status</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/12/2013</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,SA,VIC,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Spinal Unit, Prince of Wales Hospital - Randwick</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Rehabilitation Centre Sydney - Sydney</hospital>
    <hospital>Queensland Spinal Cord Injury Service, Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <hospital>South Australian Spinal Cord Injury Service, Hampstead Rehabilitation Centre - Northfield</hospital>
    <hospital>Victorian Spinal Cord Injury Service, Royal Talbot Rehabilitation Centre - Kew</hospital>
    <hospital>Sir George Bebrook Spinal Injuries Centre, Royal Perth Hospital - Shenton Park</hospital>
    <postcode> - Randwick</postcode>
    <postcode> - Sydney</postcode>
    <postcode> - Woolloongabba</postcode>
    <postcode> - Northfield</postcode>
    <postcode>3101 - Kew</postcode>
    <postcode> - Shenton Park</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Christchurch</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Victorian Neurotrauma Initiative</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Lifetime Care and Support Authority (NSW)</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>The University of Western Australia</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Loss of hand function is one of the most devastating consequences of tetraplegia because of
      the severe impact on activities of daily living (ADL) and the resultant dependency on others.
      This multi-centre study in 78 participants will measure whether additional hand therapy
      provided via an electrical stimulator glove and specialised computer workstation improves
      hand function in people with tetraplegia.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01086930</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Lisa Harvey</name>
      <address>University of Sydney</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Lisa Harvey</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+61 2 9809 9099</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lisa.harvey@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>