<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6081">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/09/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/09/2016</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02903771</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Phase I Study of Cantrixil in Patients With Ovarian Cancer, Fallopian Tube Cancer or Primary Peritoneal Cancer.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Phase I Study of Intra-peritoneal Cantrixil in Patients With Persistent or Recurrent Ovarian Cancer, Fallopian Tube Cancer or Primary Peritoneal Cancer.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NVGN-002-101</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Ovarian Neoplasms</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Fallopian Tube Neoplasms</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Peritoneal Neoplasms</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ovarian and primary peritoneal</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Womb (Uterine or endometrial cancer)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Stomach</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Part A: Dose Escalation of Cantrixil
Treatment: drugs - Part B: Expansion Cohort of Cantrixil
Treatment: drugs - Part C: Twice weekly dosing of Cantrixil

Experimental: Part A, Part B and Part C - Part A (Dose Escalation):
Part A is a Dose Escalation study to determine the Maximum Tolerated Dose of Cantrixil as a monotherapy.
The tolerance of Cantrixil in combination with standard chemotherapy agents will also be examined.
Part B (Expansion Cohort):
An expansion cohort of an additional 12 patients will be recruited at the MTD.
Part C (Twice weekly dosing):
Part C will examine the tolerability of twice weekly doses of Cantrixil at the MTD-1 dose level a monotherapy and in combination with chemotherapy agents.


Treatment: drugs: Part A: Dose Escalation of Cantrixil
Cantrixil will be administered via the intraperitoneal route only. The dose of study drug that each participant will receive will depend on how far the study has progressed when the participant enrols. There are 9 potential doses of Cantrixil, they are 0.06, 0.12, 0.24 (starting dose), 0.6, 1.25, 2.5, 5, 10, or 20 mg/kg. The dose each participant receives will remain the same during the study, unless it needs to be reduced for safety reasons. The dose will not be increased.
Each participant will receive the study drug once a week during the first two cycles; each cycle is 21-days (three weeks); the MTD will be determined during Cycle 1 only. If after two cycles of monotherapy, the patient tolerates Cantrixil adequately, they may continue to receive Cantrixil once a week and will also begin combination chemotherapy for another 6 cycles. Participants will receive no more than 8 cycles of study drug.

Treatment: drugs: Part B: Expansion Cohort of Cantrixil
Once the MTD has been established, an expansion cohort will be recruited at the MTD. An additional 12 patients will be recruited in this cohort on top of those recruited in Part A at the MTD. These patients will be subjected to the same intervention described in Part A with 2 cycles of monotherapy followed by up to 6 cycles of combination therapy.

Treatment: drugs: Part C: Twice weekly dosing of Cantrixil
Once Part B is complete, up to 6 patients may be enrolled in Part C. Part C will examine the tolerability of twice weekly doses of Cantrixil at the MTD-1 dose level Twice weekly doses will first be administered as a monotherapy during Cycles 1 and 2 on Days 1 and 4 of each week of the first two 3-week cycles. Patients who have not discontinued from the study at the end of Cycles 1 and 2 will proceed to twice weekly Cantrixil administration together with chemotherapy.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determination of the Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD) - Determination of the MTD of Cantrixil using standard safety monitoring assessments when administered as a monotherapy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During Cycle 1 (21 days)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetic (PK) profile of Cantrixil after intra-peritoneal (IP) administration - Description of the PK of Cantrixil when administered as a monotherapy and in combination with standard chemotherapy agent(s)</outcome>
      <timepoint>0-24 hours after administration</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Progression (TTP) - TTP will be measured as the time from treatment start until objective tumour disease progression as defined by RECIST version 1.1 and/or GCIG criteria, but does not include deaths.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to End of Study (maximum 36 weeks)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Paracentesis - The time to paracentesis will be measured as the time from treatment initiation until the next paracentesis event for ascites.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to End of Study (maximum 36 weeks)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Volume of Malignant Ascites - The volume of abdominal fluid will be measured by estimating the volume of malignant ascites drained at each paracentesis event.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to End of Study (maximum 36 weeks)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disease Response - Disease response will be measured using RECIST version 1.1 criteria; during Follow-up, response may be also assessed using the Gynecological Cancer Intergroup (GCIG) response criteria that incorporates CA-125 measurements</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to End of Study (maximum 36 weeks)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>CA-125 level - Concentration of CA-125 in peripheral blood will be assayed in local laboratories using locally validated assays at baseline and then weekly during treatment, at the End of Therapy and during Follow-up.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to End of Study (maximum 36 weeks)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Patients must have recurrent or persistent epithelial ovarian, fallopian tube, or
             primary peritoneal cancer. The original diagnosis must be verified by a histology
             report. All histological sub-types and all grades of disease are eligible to
             participate; grade, histological sub-type and breast cancer susceptibility gene (BRCA)
             status must be recorded at study entry.

          2. Patients must be female and at least 18 years old.

          3. Patients with malignant ascites are eligible to participate; paracentesis will be
             conducted before the administration of Cantrixil. Drainage of the maximum volume of
             ascites necessary for symptomatic relief should be performed according to local
             standard operating procedures before administration of Cantrixil.

          4. Patients must have completed at least two (2) or more prior therapies (including
             adjuvant therapy) for their ovarian, Fallopian tube or primary peritoneal cancer prior
             to participation in the current study; all prior therapies must be recorded at
             baseline. Patients that have received prior intraperitoneal therapy are eligible for
             this study.

          5. Patients must have platinum-resistant relapsed disease, platinum refractory disease,
             or have documented intolerance to platinum therapy. Patients will not be eligible
             based on rising CA-125 levels alone, patients must have other clinical symptoms (such
             as malignant ascites) or radiological tumour measurements that support disease
             recurrence or progression.

          6. At least 4 weeks must have passed from any previous therapy and any toxicities from
             prior therapies (6 weeks for bevacizumab, nitrosoureas or mitomycin C treatment) must
             have resolved to less than or equal to Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events
             (CTCAE version 4.03) Grade 1 with the exception of alopecia, Grade 2 prior
             platinum-therapy related neuropathy and Grade 2 anaemia.

          7. Patients must have a performance status of Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) 0
             to 2 and, in the Investigator's opinion, be able to complete at least a major part of
             the study.

          8. Patients must be willing and able to undergo insertion of a port or catheter for
             intraperitoneal access; the type of port or catheter used will be recorded.

          9. Patients may have measurable or non-measurable disease; disease response and
             progression will be measured and assessed according to RECIST version 1.1 criteria
             using contrast CT, MRI and CA 125 measurements.

         10. Patients must have acceptable hepatic and marrow function as defined below:

               -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt;1.5 x 109/L

               -  Platelets &gt;100 x 109/L

               -  Total bilirubin; &lt;2.5 times the institutional upper limit of normal (ULN)

               -  Haemoglobin (Hb) of &gt;10 g/dL; patients with Hb &gt;9g/dL will be considered for this
                  study if they have not received a transfusion or other bone marrow support.
                  Patients with Hb &gt;10 g/dL that have received a recent transfusion will only be
                  eligible if there has been a wash-out period of 7 days for rhesus factor and 10
                  days for platelet transfusions, respectively.

               -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) (serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase
                  [SGOT])/ alanine aminotransferase (ALT) (serum glutamic pyruvate transaminase
                  [SGPT]) =2.5 x institutional ULN.

               -  Serum creatinine &lt;1.5 x ULN

               -  Prothrombin time (PT) or international normalised ratio (INR) =1.5 x ULN and
                  activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT) =1.5 x ULN if not on anticoagulation
                  treatments.

         11. Patients must be willing and able to comply with all study requirements, including
             treatment timing and/or nature of required assessments and treatment at designated
             study centre.

         12. Each participant must be adequately informed about the purpose of the study; potential
             benefits and risks; their right to refuse participation or to withdraw consent at any
             time; institutional affiliation and potential competing interests of the researcher;
             and sources of study funding and have signed and dated a written informed consent
             form.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Female</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Patients who have had chemotherapy, biologic therapy, immunotherapy, or radiotherapy
             within 4 weeks (6 weeks for bevacizumab, nitrosoureas or mitomycin C) prior to
             entering the study.

          2. Patients must not have had major surgery within 4 weeks prior to screening.

          3. Patients may not have received any other investigational medicinal products (IMPs) or
             participated in any other interventional clinical research studies within 3 months of
             the first Cantrixil administration.

          4. Patients receiving any medications or substances that are strong inhibitors or
             inducers of cytochrome P450 (CYP)1A2, CYP2B6 and CYP3A4 or those substances with
             narrow therapeutic index are not to be enrolled. These compounds are prohibited from
             screening until completion of end of therapy or first post-treatment follow-up visit.
             For a list of prohibited medications see the University of Indiana Clinical
             Pharmacology Department's P450 Drug Interaction Table
             (http://medicine.iupui.edu/clinpharm/ddis/main-table/). Note: the use of paclitaxel is
             allowed, but only 24 hours after Cantrixil administration.

          5. Patients at high risk of bowel perforation are excluded, including but not limited to
             any one or more of the following;

               -  Patients with a recent history (previous 12 months) of bowel obstruction prior to
                  study entry

               -  Patients with CT scans that suggest invasion of bowel by tumour

               -  Patients with symptoms to suggest impending bowel obstruction

               -  Patients with prior whole abdominal radiotherapy

               -  Patients with chronic inflammatory bowel diseases such as Crohn's disease or
                  ulcerative colitis

          6. Patients may not have uncontrolled or severe systemic diseases or psychiatric
             conditions, which in the treating physician's opinion makes it unsafe for the patient
             to participate in the study or would hinder compliance with the protocol. Screening
             for chronic conditions is not required.

          7. Patients that are pregnant, lactating, or unable to adopt adequate contraception are
             excluded. Women of childbearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test within 7
             days prior to screening.

          8. Patients with a known history of hepatitis B or C.

          9. Patients known to have tested positive for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)

         10. Patients with a known hypersensitivity to or serious reaction to benzopyrans are
             excluded.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/11/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/12/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Westmead Adults Hospital - Westmead</hospital>
    <hospital>ICON Cancer Care - South Brisbane</hospital>
    <hospital>Flinders Medical Centre - Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>2145 - Westmead</postcode>
    <postcode>4101 - South Brisbane</postcode>
    <postcode> - Adelaide</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Oklahoma</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Novogen Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The main purpose of this study is to determine the safety and feasibility of weekly
      intra-peritoneal administration of Cantrixil to women with persistent or recurrent ovarian
      cancer, Fallopian tube cancer or primary peritoneal cancer. The study also aims to determine
      the maximum tolerated dose of Cantrixil in these patients when administered as a monotherapy
      or a combination therapy.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02903771</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Prof Jermaine (Jim) Coward, BSc, MBBS, PhD, MRCP, FRACP</name>
      <address>ICON Cancer Care, Queensland, Australia</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Gordon Hirsch, BSc Hon, MBBCh, FCP(SA), MBA</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+612 94724101</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gordon.hirsch@novogen.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>