<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5758">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/09/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/09/2015</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02574091</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Icotinib Hydrochloride Cream in Healthy Adults and Psoriasis Patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Single-Center, Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-Controlled Study to Evaluate Safety, Tolerability and Pharmacokinetics of Icotinib Hydrochloride Cream in Healthy Adult Participants, Followed by Patients With Mild to Moderate Psoriasis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>BD-ICC-NZ-I01</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Psoriasis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dermatological conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other skin conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - 1% icotinib hydrochloride cream
Treatment: drugs - 2% icotinib hydrochloride cream
Treatment: drugs - Placebo

Experimental: Cohort 1-Experimental - 4 healthy adult participants will be randomized to receive 1% icotinib hydrochloride cream, applied twice daily for 7 consecutive days (final dose on the morning of Day 8).
The drug will be used topically to the back of each participant within an area of 15cm x 25cm.

Placebo Comparator: Cohort 1-Placebo - 2 healthy adult participants will be randomized to receive placebo (blank cream), applied twice daily for 7 consecutive days (final dose on the morning of Day 8).
The drug will be used topically to the back of each participant within an area of 15cm x 25cm.

Experimental: Cohort 2-Experimental - 4 healthy adult participants will be randomized to receive 2% icotinib hydrochloride cream, applied twice daily for 7 consecutive days (final dose on the morning of Day 8).
The drug will be used topically to the back of each participant within an area of 15cm x 25cm.

Placebo Comparator: Cohort 2-Placebo - 2 healthy adult participants will be randomized to receive matching placebo, applied twice daily for 7 consecutive days (final dose on the morning of Day 8).
The drug will be used topically to the back of each participant within an area of 15cm x 25cm.

Experimental: Cohort 3-Experimental - 6 patients with mild to moderate psoriasis will be randomized to receive 1% icotinib hydrochloride cream, applied twice daily for 13 consecutive days (final dose on the morning of Day 14).
The drug will be applied topically to the psoriasis site (excluding face, scalp, genital and groin) on the arms and/or legs and/or trunk only.

Placebo Comparator: Cohort 3-Placebo - 2 patients with mild to moderate psoriasis will be randomized to receive matching placebo, applied twice daily for 13 consecutive days (final dose on the morning of Day 14).
The drug will be applied topically to the psoriasis site (excluding face, scalp, genital and groin) on the arms and/or legs and/or trunk only.

Experimental: Cohort 4-Experimental - 6 patients with mild to moderate psoriasis will be randomized to receive 2% icotinib hydrochloride cream, applied twice daily for 13 consecutive days (final dose on the morning of Day 14).
The drug will be applied topically to the psoriasis site (excluding face, scalp, genital and groin) on the arms and/or legs and/or trunk only.

Placebo Comparator: Cohort 4-Placebo - 2 patients with mild to moderate psoriasis will be randomized to receive matching placebo, applied twice daily for 13 consecutive days (final dose on the morning of Day 14).
The drug will be applied topically to the psoriasis site (excluding face, scalp, genital and groin) on the arms and/or legs and/or trunk only.


Treatment: drugs: 1% icotinib hydrochloride cream
Topical administration for twice daily

Treatment: drugs: 2% icotinib hydrochloride cream
Topical administration for twice daily.

Treatment: drugs: Placebo
Topical administration for twice daily.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse events in healthy subjects - Incidence and severity of Adverse Events (AE) Vital signs (temperature, Heart Rate (HR), BP and respiration); Clinical laboratory assessments (serum chemistry, hematology and urinalysis); ECG; Use of concomitant medications</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse events in patients with mild to moderate psoriasis - Incidence and severity of AEs; Vital signs (temperature, HR, BP and respiration); Clinical laboratory assessments (serum chemistry, hematology and urinalysis); ECG; Use of concomitant medications</outcome>
      <timepoint>14 days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tolerance-related skin reactions in healthy adult participants at the tested sites - Skin irritation and allergy observation (including redness, swelling, itching, pain)</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tolerance-related skin reactions in patients with mild to moderate psoriasis at the tested sites - Skin irritation and allergy observation (including redness, swelling, itching, pain)</outcome>
      <timepoint>14 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate peak plasma concentration (Cmax) of single-dose Icotinib Hydrochloride Cream in healthy adult participants</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate time maximum concentration observed(tmax) of single-dose Icotinib Hydrochloride Cream in healthy adult participants</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate area under the plasma concentration versus time curve(AUC) of single-dose Icotinib Hydrochloride Cream in healthy adult participants - AUClast, AUC0-inf will be assessed</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate half life(t1/2) of single-dose Icotinib Hydrochloride Cream in healthy adult participants</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate stable peak plasma concentration (Cmaxss) of repeat-dose Icotinib Hydrochloride Cream in healthy adult participants</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate time maximum concentration observed(tmax) of repeat-dose Icotinib Hydrochloride Cream in healthy adult participants</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate area under the plasma concentration versus time curve(AUC) of repeat-dose Icotinib Hydrochloride Cream in healthy adult participants - AUC0-12,AUClast, AUC0-inf will be assessed</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate half life(t1/2) of repeat-dose Icotinib Hydrochloride Cream in healthy adult participants</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate peak plasma concentration (Cmax) of single-dose Icotinib Hydrochloride Cream in patients with mild to moderate psoriasis</outcome>
      <timepoint>14 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate time maximum concentration observed(tmax) of single-dose Icotinib Hydrochloride Cream in patients with mild to moderate psoriasis</outcome>
      <timepoint>14 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate area under the plasma concentration versus time curve(AUC) of single-dose Icotinib Hydrochloride Cream in patients with mild to moderate psoriasis - AUClast, AUC0-inf will be assessed</outcome>
      <timepoint>14 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate half life(t1/2) of single-dose Icotinib Hydrochloride Cream in patients with mild to moderate psoriasis</outcome>
      <timepoint>14 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate stable peak plasma concentration (Cmaxss) of repeat-dose Icotinib Hydrochloride Cream in patients with mild to moderate psoriasis</outcome>
      <timepoint>14 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate time maximum concentration observed(tmax) of repeat-dose Icotinib Hydrochloride Cream in patients with mild to moderate psoriasis</outcome>
      <timepoint>14 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate area under the plasma concentration versus time curve(AUC) of repeat-dose Icotinib Hydrochloride Cream in patients with mild to moderate psoriasis - AUC0-12,AUClast, AUC0-inf will be assessed</outcome>
      <timepoint>14 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate half life(t1/2) of repeat-dose Icotinib Hydrochloride Cream in healthy adult participants</outcome>
      <timepoint>14 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psoriasis Area and Severity Index (PASI) Scores in patients with mild to moderate psoriasis</outcome>
      <timepoint>14 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dose-toxicity correlation in single-dose and repeat-dose administration - If observable trends exist between dose applied (in Part 2 of the study) and toxicity and response parameters.</outcome>
      <timepoint>14 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dermatology Life Quality Index (DLQI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>14 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dose-response correlation in single-dose and repeat-dose administration</outcome>
      <timepoint>14 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>For Part 1-Healthy Participants

          -  18-50 years old (inclusive), male or female

          -  Male participants should be = 50 kg, female participants should be = 45 kg; Body Mass
             Index (BMI) should be between 19 and 30 kg/m2 (inclusive)

          -  In good health, with no history of diseases of major organs and no BP, HR, ECG or
             respiratory abnormality on physical examination

          -  Adequate hepatic and renal function, as determined by clinical laboratory assessments
             of blood and urine

          -  Negative serum pregnancy test at Screening and negative urine pregnancy test at Day -1
             for females of child bearing potential

          -  Negative screen for drugs of abuse, alcohol, hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg),
             hepatitis C (HCV) and Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) at screening; and negative
             drugs of abuse, alcohol pre dose on Day -1

          -  Have signed a written informed consent before entering the study

        For Part 2 - Patients with Psoriasis

          -  Clinical diagnosis of psoriasis for at least six months with multiple affected areas
             (excluding the face, scalp, genitals and groin) involving 2%-15% of the total Body
             Surface Area (BSA)

          -  18-65 years old

          -  Male participants should be = 50 kg, female participants should be = 45 kg; BMI should
             be between 19 and 35 kg/m2 (inclusive)

          -  In good health, with no history of diseases of major organs and no BP, HR, ECG or
             respiratory abnormality on physical examination

          -  Adequate hepatic and renal function, as determined by clinical laboratory assessments
             of blood and urine

          -  Negative serum pregnancy test at Screening and negative urine pregnancy test at Day -1
             for females of child bearing potential

          -  Negative screen for drugs of abuse, alcohol, HBsAg, HCV and HIV at screening; and
             negative drugs of abuse, alcohol pre dose on Day1

          -  Women of child-bearing potential must agree to use adequate contraception prior to
             study entry, for the duration of study participation, and for 90 days following
             completion of therapy

          -  Have signed a written informed consent before entering the study</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>For Part 1-Healthy Participants

          -  Any clinically significant central nervous system, cardiac, pulmonary, renal,
             gastrointestinal, respiratory, metabolic conditions (or history), or other
             pathological or physiological conditions that might interfere with the trial result

          -  History of postural hypotension

          -  Use of any topical agents (including non-medicated lotions such as sun screen,
             cosmetics, moisturizing lotion) at the administration site within a week before
             randomization

          -  History of serious skin diseases (as determined by the investigator); no presence of
             skin ulceration at the test area at the time of the Screening visit

          -  Current smoker, or a history of regular (more than weekly) use of tobacco- or
             nicotine-containing products within two months prior to screening

          -  History of excessive alcohol intake (more than four standard drinks daily, on average)
             or use of recreational drugs within the last three months

        For Part 2 - Patients with Psoriasis

          -  Any clinically significant central nervous system, cardiac, pulmonary, renal,
             gastrointestinal, respiratory, metabolic conditions (or history), or other
             pathological or physiological conditions that might interfere with the trial result

          -  History of postural hypotension

          -  Use of any topical agents (including non-medicated lotions such as sun screen,
             cosmetics, moisturizing lotion) at the administration site within a week before
             randomization

          -  History of serious skin diseases (as determined by the investigator); no presence of
             skin ulceration at the test area at the time of the Screening visit

          -  Excessive smoker(=10 cigarettes per day), or a history of regular (more than weekly)
             use of tobacco- or nicotine-containing products within two months prior to screening

          -  History of excessive alcohol intake (more than four standard drinks daily, on average)
             or use of recreational drugs within the last three months</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>26/11/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>28</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>19/02/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Christchurch</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Betta Pharmaceuticals Co.,Ltd.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Quintiles, Inc.</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a phase I study to evaluate the safety, tolerability and pharmacokinetics of Icotinib
      Hydrochloride Cream in healthy adults and patients with mild to moderate psoriasis.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02574091</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Christopher J Wynne</name>
      <address>Christchurch Clinical Studies Trust</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>