<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5735">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/05/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/05/2015</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02442258</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pharmacokinetics and Safety of ABT-493 and ABT-530 in Subjects With Normal and Impaired Renal Function</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of the Pharmacokinetics and Safety of ABT-493 and ABT-530 in Subjects With Normal and Impaired Renal Function</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>M13-600</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Renal Impairment</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - ABT-493
Treatment: drugs - ABT-530

Experimental: Group 1 - Mild Renal Impairment - Subjects with mild renal impairment. eGFR (by MDRD equation) range 60 - 89 mL/min/1.73 m2 as determined at Screening.

Experimental: Group 2 - Moderate Renal Impairment - Subjects with moderate renal impairment. eGFR (by MDRD equation) range 30 - 59 mL/min/1.73 m2 as determined at Screening.

Experimental: Group 3 - Severe Renal Impairment - Subjects with severe renal impairment. eGFR (by MDRD equation) range 15 - 29 mL/min/1.73 m2 as determined at Screening.

Experimental: Group 4 - End Stage Renal Disease, Not Yet on Dialysis - Subjects with end stage renal disease, not yet on dialysis. eGFR (by MDRD equation) range &lt; 15 mL/min/1.73 m2 as determined at Screening.

Experimental: Group 5 - Normal Renal Function - Subjects with normal renal function. eGFR (by MDRD equation) range = 90 mL/min/1.73 m2 as determined at Screening.

Experimental: Group 6 - End Stage Renal Disease, Requiring Dialysis. - Subjects with end stage renal disease, requiring dialysis. eGFR (by MDRD equation) &lt; 15 mL/min/1.73 m2 as determined at Screening.


Treatment: drugs: ABT-493
A single dose of ABT-493 will be given orally in combination with ABT-530.

Treatment: drugs: ABT-530
A single dose of ABT-530 will be given orally in combination with ABT-493.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(SUB-STUDY 1) Area under the plasma concentration-time curve (AUC) from time 0 to infinity for the ABT-493 study drug. - The AUC from time 0 to infinity represents the total drug exposure over time.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to dosing (0-hour), 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 9, 12, 16, 24, 36, 48, 72, 96 hours and 144 hours after dosing on Study Day 1.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall measurement of safety parameters - Measurement of safety parameters include physical examinations, clinical laboratory tests, 12-lead ECGs (electrocardiograms) and vital signs.</outcome>
      <timepoint>SUB-STUDY 1 - Duration of 14 days SUB-STUDY 2 - Duration of 16 Days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of subjects with adverse events - Total number of subjects with adverse events.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 30 days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximum plasma concentration (Cmax) of the ABT-493 study drug. - The peak concentration that a drug achieves in a specified compartment after the drug has been administrated and before administration of a second dose.</outcome>
      <timepoint>(SUB-STUDY 1) Prior to dosing (0-hour), 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 9, 12, 16, 24, 36, 48, 72, 96 hours and 144 hours after dosing on Study Day 1. (SUB-STUDY 2) Prior to dosing (0-hour), and at 1, 2, 3, 9, 12, 16, 24 hours after dosing on Study Day 1 of each Period.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve (AUC) for the ABT-493 study drug. - AUC reflects the actual body exposure to drug after administration of a dose of the drug.</outcome>
      <timepoint>(SUB-STUDY 1) Prior to dosing (0-hour), 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 9, 12, 16, 24, 36, 48, 72, 96 hours and 144 hours after dosing on Study Day 1. (SUB-STUDY 2) Prior to dosing (0-hour), and at 1, 2, 3, 9, 12, 16, 24 hours after dosing on Study Day 1 of each Period.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(SUB-STUDY 1) Area under the plasma concentration-time curve (AUC) from time 0 to infinity for the ABT-530 study drug. - The AUC from time 0 to infinity represents the total drug exposure over time.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to dosing (0-hour), 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 9, 12, 16, 24, 36, 48, 72, 96 hours and 144 hours after dosing on Study Day 1.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximum plasma concentration (Cmax) of the ABT-530 study drug. - The peak concentration that a drug achieves in a specified compartment after the drug has been administrated and before administration of a second dose.</outcome>
      <timepoint>(SUB-STUDY 1) Prior to dosing (0-hour), 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 9, 12, 16, 24, 36, 48, 72, 96 hours and 144 hours after dosing on Study Day 1. (SUB-STUDY 2) Prior to dosing (0-hour), 1, 2, 3, 9, 12, 16, 24 hours after dosing on Study Day 1 of each Period.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve (AUC) for the ABT-530 study drug. - AUC reflects the actual body exposure to drug after administration of a dose of the drug.</outcome>
      <timepoint>(SUB-STUDY 1) Prior to dosing (0-hour), 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 9, 12, 16, 24, 36, 48, 72, 96 hours and 144 hours after dosing on Study Day 1. (SUB-STUDY 2) Prior to dosing (0-hour), and at 1, 2, 3, 9, 12, 16, 24 hours after dosing on Study Day 1 of each Period.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(SUB-STUDY 2) Area under the plasma concentration-time curve (AUC) during hemodialysis for the ABT-493 study drug. - The AUC during hemodialysis represents the total drug exposure over time.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to dosing (0-hour), and at 1, 2, 3, 9, 12, 16, 24 hours after dosing on Study Day 1 of each Period. Additional samples will be collected at 4, 5, and 6 hours after dosing on Study Day 1 of Period 2 only.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(SUB-STUDY 2) Area under the plasma concentration-time curve (AUC) during hemodialysis for the ABT-530 study drug. - The AUC during hemodialysis represents the total drug exposure over time.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to dosing (0-hour), and at 1, 2, 3, 9, 12, 16, 24 hours after dosing on Study Day 1 of each Period. Additional samples will be collected at 4, 5 and 6 hours after dosing on Study Day 1 of Period 2 only.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All Subjects

          -  Females must have negative results for pregnancy tests performed:

               -  At Screening on a urine specimen, and

               -  On a serum sample obtained on Study Day -2 (prior to dosing).

          -  Body Mass Index (BMI) is = 18 to = 38 kg/m2, inclusive.

          -  Body Weight &gt; 50 kg.

        Subjects with Normal Renal Function

        In addition to the main inclusion criteria above for all subjects, the following criteria
        must be met for subjects with normal renal function enrolled in Group 5:

          -  Judged to be in general good health based upon the results of a medical history,
             physical examination, and 12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG).

          -  At screening, estimated GFR (by MDRD equation) should be = 90 mL/min/1.73 m2.

        Subject with Renal Impairment

        In addition to the main inclusion criteria for all subjects, the following criteria must be
        met for all subjects with renal impairment enrolled in Groups 1, 2, 3, 4 and 6:

          -  Judged to be in stable condition and acceptable for study participation based upon the
             results of a medical history, physical examination, laboratory profile and ECG.

          -  Presence of chronic renal impairment as indicated by medical history and a screening
             estimated GFR (by MDRD equation) &lt; 90 mL/min/1.73 m2.

          -  Subjects with ESRD undergoing hemodialysis should have been receiving dialysis for at
             least 1 month.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- History of significant sensitivity to any drug.

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding female.

          -  Recent (6-month) history of drug or alcohol abuse.

          -  Positive test result for hepatitis A virus immunoglobulin M (HAV-IgM), hepatitis B
             surface antigen (HBsAg) or hepatitis C virus antibody (HCV Ab) or HIV antibodies (HIV
             Ab). Negative HIV status will be confirmed at Screening and the results will be
             maintained confidentially by the study site.

          -  Subjects on strict vegetarian diet.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Basic Science</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/03/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>46</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/12/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Grafton, Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>AbbVie</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is an open-label, single dose study designed to assess the pharmacokinetics and safety
      of ABT-493 and ABT-530 in subjects with either normal renal function or impaired renal
      function.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02442258</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>David Pugatch, MD</name>
      <address>AbbVie</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>