<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5723">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/02/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/02/2015</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02369848</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Shockwave Lithoplasty DISRUPT Trial for PAD (DISRUPT PAD 2)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Shockwave Lithoplasty DISRUPT Trial for PAD (DISRUPT PAD 2)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>TD 0232</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Peripheral Arterial Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - Shockwave Lithoplasty System

Experimental: Lithoplasty Treatment - Shockwave Lithoplasty System


Treatment: devices: Shockwave Lithoplasty System


</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Efficacy defined as target lesion patency by duplex ultrasound defined as freedom from =50% restenosis</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months post-procedure</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite of new-onset Major Adverse Events (MAEs) - Need for emergency surgical revascularization of target limb. Unplanned target limb amputation (above the ankle). Symptomatic thrombus or distal emboli, defined as clinical signs or symptoms of thrombus or distal emboli detected in the treated limb in the area of the treated lesion or distal to the treated lesion after the index procedure and results in extended hospitalization or noted angiographically, and requiring mechanical or pharmacologic means to improve flow and results in extended hospitalization.
Perforations and dissections of grade D or greater that require an intervention to resolve, including bail-out stenting.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 30 days following procedure</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety measured by freedom from Major Adverse Events (MAEs)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acute Procedural Success - The ability of the Shockwave Lithoplasty System to achieve a post-Shockwave residual diameter stenosis of &lt;50% (with or without adjunctive PTA therapy) as assessed by quantitative angiography via core lab evaluation.
The ability of the Shockwave Lithoplasty System to achieve a post-Shockwave residual diameter stenosis of &lt;50% (without adjunctive PTA therapy) as assessed by quantitative angiography via core lab evaluation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day of Procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Patency measured by target lesion patency by duplex ultrasound defined as freedom from =50% restenosis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Patency measured by target lesion patency (without adjunctive PTA) by duplex ultrasound defined as freedom from =50% restenosis. - Freedom from Target Lesion Revascularization (TLR).</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical Success - Improvement of Ankle-Brachial Index (ABI) of the target limb. Improvement of Rutherford Clinical Category.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical Success - Improvement of Ankle-Brachial (ABI) of the target limb. Improvement of Rutherford Clinical Category.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Subject is able and willing to comply with all assessments in the study.

          2. Subject or subject's legal representative have been informed of the nature of the
             study, agrees to participate and has signed the approved consent form.

          3. Age of subject is &gt;18.

          4. Rutherford Clinical Category 2, 3, or 4.

          5. Resting ankle-brachial index (ABI) of =0.90, or =0.75 after exercise, of the target
             leg.

          6. Estimated life expectancy &gt;1 year.

        Angiographic 

          1. Subject is a suitable candidate for angiography and endovascular intervention in the
             opinion of the investigator or per hospital guideline.

          2. Target lesion that is located in a native de novo superficial femoral artery (SFA) or
             popliteal artery (popliteal artery extends to and ends proximal to the ostium of the
             anterior tibial artery).

          3. Target lesion reference vessel diameter is between 3.50mm and 7.0mm by visual
             estimate.

          4. Target zone is =150mm in length. Target lesion can be all or part of the 150mm zone.

          5. Target lesion is =70% stenosis by investigator via visual estimate.

          6. Subject has at least one patent tibial vessel on the target leg with runoff to the
             ankle (not supported by collateral circulation.) Tibial vessel patency is defined as
             no stenosis &gt;50%.

          7. Ability to pass the guidewire across the atherosclerotic lesion.

          8. No evidence of aneurysm or acute or chronic thrombus in target vessel.

          9. Calcification is at least moderate. (Presence of fluoroscopic evidence of
             calcification: 1) on parallel sides of the vessel and 2) extending = 50% the length of
             the lesion.)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Rutherford Clinical Category 5 and 6.

          2. Subject has active infection in the target leg.

          3. Planned major amputation of the target leg (transmetatarsal or higher).

          4. The use of chronic total occlusion (CTO) re-entry devices.

          5. CTOs greater than 80 mm in length.

          6. Any in-stent restenosis within the target zone.

          7. Lesions within 10 mm of ostium of the SFA.

          8. Highly tortuous arteries (bends greater than 30 degrees over the arc length of the
             balloon).

          9. Target lesion within native or synthetic vessel grafts.

         10. History of prior endovascular or surgical procedure on the index limb within the past
             30 days.

         11. Subject has significant stenosis (&gt;50% stenosis) or occlusion of inflow tract before
             target treatment zone (e.g. iliac or common femoral) not successfully treated with
             POBA or stent and without complications.

         12. Subject requires treatment of a peripheral lesion on the ipsilateral limb distal and
             beyond the 150mm target zone at the time of the enrollment/index procedure.

         13. Subject has a known coagulopathy or has a bleeding diatheses, thrombocytopenia with
             platelet count less than 100,000/microliter, or INR &gt;1.5.

         14. Subject in whom antiplatelet, anticoagulant, or thrombolytic therapy is
             contraindicated.

         15. Subject has known allergy to contrast agents or medications used to perform
             endovascular intervention that cannot be adequately pre-treated.

         16. Subject has known allergy to urethane, nylon, or silicone.

         17. Myocardial infarction within 60 days prior to enrollment.

         18. History of stroke within 60 days prior to enrollment.

         19. History of unstable coronary artery disease or other uncontrollable comorbidity
             resulting in hospitalization within the last 60 days prior to enrollment.

         20. History of thrombolytic therapy within two weeks of enrollment.

         21. Subject has acute or chronic renal disease (e.g., as measured by a serum creatinine of
             &gt;2.5 mg/dL or &gt;220 umol/L), or on dialysis.

         22. Subject is pregnant or nursing.

         23. Subject is participating in another research study involving an investigational agent
             (pharmaceutical, biologic, or medical device) that has not reached the primary
             endpoint.

         24. Subject has other medical, social or psychological problems that, in the opinion of
             the investigator, preclude them from receiving this treatment, and the procedures and
             evaluations pre- and post-treatment.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/06/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>60</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/12/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Austria</country>
      <state>Graz</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Austria</country>
      <state>Vienna</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Bad Krozingen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Leipzig</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Munster</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Rosenheim</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Shockwave Medical, Inc.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Shockwave Medical, Inc. intends to conduct a prospective, single-arm, multi-center, clinical
      study designed to evaluate the safety and performance of the Shockwave Lithoplasty System in
      subjects with moderate to heavily calcified peripheral arteries with 3.50mm to 7.0mm
      reference vessel diameter at the target site. The Shockwave Lithoplasty System is indicated
      to generate sonic shockwave energy within the target treatment site and disrupt calcium
      within the lesion to allow for subsequent dilation of a peripheral artery stenosis using low
      balloon pressure. Up to sixty (60) subjects will be enrolled and treated with Lithoplasty to
      yield thirty (51) evaluable subjects complete the study assuming a 15% lost to follow-up
      rate.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02369848</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Thomas Zeller, MD</name>
      <address>Universitäts-Herzzentrum Freiburg &amp; Bad Krozingen</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>