<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4311">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/10/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/10/2013</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01970865</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Study Of PF-06463922 An ALK/ROS1 Inhibitor In Patients With Advanced Non Small Cell Lung Cancer With Specific Molecular Alterations</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Phase 1/2 Study Of Pf-06463922 (an Alk/ros1 Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitor) In Patients With Advanced Non-small Cell Lung Cancer Harboring Specific Molecular Alterations</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>2013-002620-17</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>B7461001</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>ALK-positive Non Small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC) and ROS1-positive NSCLC</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lung - Mesothelioma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lung - Non small cell</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lung - Small cell</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - PF-06463922
Treatment: drugs - Crizotinib

Experimental: PF-06463922 - 

Other: Crizotinib - ALK+ NSCLC patients who are treatment na誰ve may be eligible to receive crizotinib following PF-06463922 as a substudy to the main study.


Treatment: drugs: PF-06463922
Oral, starting dose 10mg once a day, dose escalation in Phase 1 until recommended Phase 2 dose determined, continuous daily dosing, cycles lasting 21 days

Treatment: drugs: Crizotinib
Oral, starting dose of 250 mg BID continuous daily dosing every 21 days

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Patients with Overall and Intracranial Objective Response (Phase 2) - Percentage of patients with OR based assessment of intracranial and overall confirmed complete remission (CR) or confirmed partial remission (PR) according to a modified Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST)v 1.1.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 6 weeks from the time of patient enrollment up to 4 years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cycle 1 Dose Limiting Toxicities (DLTs). (Phase 1) - Number of patients reporting DLTs during Cycle 1 of treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>One (1) cycle (21 days)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse Events - Adverse Events as characterized by type, frequency, severity (as graded by NCI CTCAE v.4.03), seriousness and relationship to study therapy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>First dose of study drug through 28 days after the last dose of study drug</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from Baseline in Mini Mental State Examination (MMSE) across treatment cycles (Phase 1) - MMSE measured general cognitive functioning: orientation, memory, attention, calculation, language, visuospatial functions. Total score derived from sub-scores; total ranges from 0 to 30, higher score indicates better cognitive state. Change: across treatment cycles</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to dosing (Day -7 or Cycle 1 Day 1), Every 3 weeks from the time of enrollment up to 4 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Area Under the Curve From Time Zero to Last Quantifiable Concentration (AUClast)(Phase 1 and first 10 patients in Phase 2) - Area under the plasma concentration time-curve from zero to the last measured concentration (AUClast)</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days prior to first dose of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Volume of Distribution at Steady State (Vz/F) (Phase 1 and first 10 patients in Phase 2) - Volume of distribution is defined as the theoretical volume in which the total amount of drug would need to be uniformly distributed to produce the desired blood concentration of a drug. Steady state volume of distribution (Vss) is the apparent volume of distribution at steady-state.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 9 and 24 hours post Cycle 1 Day 15 dose of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Reach Maximum Observed Plasma Concentration (Tmax)(Phase 1 and first 10 patients in Phase 2)</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days prior to the first dose of treatment and pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 9 and 24 hours post Cycle 1 Day 15 dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximum Observed Plasma Concentration (Cmax)(Phase 1 and first 10 patients in Phase 2)</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days prior to the first dose of treatment and pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 9 and 24 hours post Cycle 1 Day 15 dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Area Under the Curve from Time Zero to end of dosing interval (AUCtau)(Phase 1 and first 10 patients in Phase 2)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 9 and 24 hours post Cycle 1 Day 15 dose of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Apparent Volume of Distribution (Vz/F)(Phase 1 and first 10 patients in Phase 2) - Volume of distribution is defined as the theoretical volume in which the total amount of drug would need to be uniformly distributed to produce the desired plasma concentration of a drug. Apparent volume of distribution after oral dose (Vz/F) is influenced by the fraction absorbed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days prior to the first dose of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma Decay Half-Life (t1/2) (Phase 1 and first 10 patients in Phase 2) - Plasma decay half-life is the time measured for the plasma concentration to decrease by one half.</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days prior to the first dose of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Urine clearance of drug (Clr) for subjects in food effect and Midazolam substudy (Phase 1)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2,3, 4, 6, 8, 9 and 24 hours post Cycle 1 Day 15 dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Urine Ae% for subjects in food effect and Midazolam substudy (Phase 1)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre Cycle 1 Day 15 dose of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximum Observed Plasma Concentration (Cmax) for subjects in Midazolam substudy (Phase 1)</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days prior to the first dose of treatment and pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2,3, 4, 6, 8, 9 and 24 hours post Cycle 1 Day 15 dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Reach Maximum Observed Plasma Concentration (Tmax) for subjects in Midazolam substudy (Phase 1)</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days prior to the first dose of treatment and pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2,3, 4, 6, 8, 9 and 24 hours post Cycle 1 Day 15 dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Area Under the Curve From Time Zero to Last Quantifiable Concentration (AUClast) for subjects in Midazolam substudy (Phase 1) - Area under the plasma concentration time-curve from zero to the last measured concentration (AUClast) after administration of MDZ</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days prior to first dose and pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2,3, 4, 6, 8, 9 and 24 hours post Cycle 1 Day 15 dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Area Under the Curve From Time Zero to Extrapolated Infinite Time [AUC (0 - 8)](Phase 1 and first 10 patients in Phase 2) - AUC (0 - 8)= Area under the plasma concentration versus time curve (AUC) from time zero (pre-dose) to extrapolated infinite time (0 - 8). It is obtained from AUC (0 - t) plus AUC (t - 8).</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days prior to the first dose of treatment and pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2,3, 4, 6, 8, 9 and 24 hours post Cycle 1 Day 15 dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma Decay Half-Life (t1/2) for subjects in Midazolam substudy (Phase 1) - Plasma decay half-life is the time measured for the plasma concentration to decrease by one half after administration of MDZ</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days prior to the first dose of treatment and pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2,3, 4, 6, 8, 9 and 24 hours post Cycle 1 Day 15 dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Apparent Oral Clearance (CL/F) for subjects in Midazolam substudy (Phase 1) - Clearance of a drug is a measure of the rate at which a drug is metabolized or eliminated by normal biological processes. Clearance obtained after oral dose (apparent oral clearance) is influenced by the fraction of the dose absorbed. Clearance was estimated from population pharmacokinetic (PK) modeling. Drug clearance is a quantitative measure of the rate at which a drug substance is removed from the blood after administration of MDZ</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days prior to the first dose of treatment and pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2,3, 4, 6, 8, 9 and 24 hours post Cycle 1 Day 15 dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Apparent Oral Clearance (CL/F) (Phase 1) - Clearance of a drug is a measure of the rate at which a drug is metabolized or eliminated by normal biological processes. Clearance obtained after oral dose (apparent oral clearance) is influenced by the fraction of the dose absorbed. Clearance was estimated from population pharmacokinetic (PK) modeling. Drug clearance is a quantitative measure of the rate at which a drug substance is removed from the blood.</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days prior to the first dose of treatment and pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2,3, 4, 6, 8, 9 and 24 hours post Cycle 1 Day 15 dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Area Under the Curve From Time Zero to Last Quantifiable Concentration (AUClast)(Phase 1 and first 10 patients in Phase 2) - Area under the plasma concentration time-curve from zero to the last measured concentration (AUClast)</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days prior to the first dose of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Area Under the Curve From Time Zero to Extrapolated Infinite Time [AUC (0 - 8)](Phase 1 and first 10 patients in Phase 2) - AUC (0 - 8)= Area under the plasma concentration versus time curve (AUC) from time zero (pre-dose) to extrapolated infinite time (0 - 8). It is obtained from AUC (0 - t) plus AUC (t - 8).</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days prior to the first dose of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Selective molecular profiling of circulating nucleic acids (CNA) - Selective molecular profiling of circulating nucleic acids (CNA) at the end of treatment visit defined as 28 days after the last treatment administration.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 28 days of first dose of treatment, at the end of Cycle 2 (Phase 2 only) and at 28 days after the last dose of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Selective molecular profiling of tumor tissue - Blood specimen optimized for plasma preparation for nucleic acid analysis will be collected at screening and at end of treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 28 days prior to first dose of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>QTc interval - ECGs performed to assess QTc (msec) at baseline and on study treatment and at the end of treatment visit defined as 28 days after the last treatment administration.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 28 days prior to first dose of treatment, 7 days prior to the first dose of treatment and Day 1, 8 and 15 of Cycle 1 and Day 1 of Cycles 2-5 and 28 days after the last dose of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient reported Outcomes - To assess impact of disease /treatment related symptoms of lung cancer and quality of life at D1 of every cycle and at the end of treatment visit defined as 28 days after the last treatment administration.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to first dosing (Day -7 or Cycle 1 Day 1), Day 1 of every cycle, pre dose, up to 4 years and at 28 days after the last dose of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of Response - DR is defined as the time from the first documentation of objective tumor response (CR or PR) to the first documentation of disease progression or to death due to any cause, whichever occurs first.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 6 weeks from the time of enrollment up to 4 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression-Free Survival (PFS) - The period from study entry until disease progression, death or date of last contact.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 6 weeks from the time of enrollment to the first documented progression or date of death from any cause, assessed up to 4 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Survival (OS) - Overall survival was the duration from enrollment to death. For participants who are alive, overall survival was censored at the last contact.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From the time of enrollment until the date of death from any causes at 18 months and 1 year.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disease Control Rate (DCR) - DCR is defined as the percent of patients with a confirmed complete response (CR), partial response (PR) or stable disease (SD) according to RECIST 1.1, at 6 weeks.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 12 weeks from the time of enrollment up to 4 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Objective tumor response - Percentage of patients with OR based assessment of intracranial and overall confirmed complete remission (CR) or confirmed partial remission (PR) according to a modified Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST)v 1.1.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 6 weeks from the time of enrollment up to 4 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction (LVEF) - Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction percentage change by echocardiogram or by multigated acquisition gated scan (MUGA)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 28 days prior to the first dose of treatment, pre dose on Day 1 of Cycle 2, pre dose on Day 1 of Cycle 3, pre dose on Day 1 of Cycle 5 and pre dose on Day 1 of every 2 Cycles thereafter; and at 28 days after the last dose of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Apparent Volume of Distribution (Vz/F) for subjects in Midazolam substudy (Phase 1) - Volume of distribution is defined as the theoretical volume in which the total amount of drug would need to be uniformly distributed to produce the desired plasma concentration of a drug. Apparent volume of distribution after oral dose (Vz/F) is influenced by the fraction absorbed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days prior to the first dose of treatment and pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2,3, 4, 6, 8, 9 and 24 hours post Cycle 1 Day 15 dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Tumor Response - TTR is defined as the time from first dose to first documentation of objective tumor response (CR or PR). For patients whose OR proceeds from PR to CR, the onset of PR is taken as the onset of response. TTR will only be calculated for the subgroup of patients with a confirmed objective tumor response.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 6 weeks from the time of enrollment up to 4 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Tumor Progression (Phase 2) - TTP is defined as the time from first dose to first documentation of objective disease progression.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From the time of enrollment up to 4 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Intracranial progression (Phase 2) - Time to Intracranial Progression is defined as the time from first dose to first documentation of objective intracranial disease progression.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From the time of enrollment up to 4 years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Extracranial Progression (Phase 2) - Time to Extracranial defined as the time from first dose to first documentation of objective extracranial disease progression.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From the time of enrollment up to 4 years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Vital signs - heart rate and blood pressure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>First dose of study medication through 28 days after the last dose of study medication.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive Function Assessment (Phase 2) - An assessment of cognitive function via a computerized cognitive test compromised of verbal learning, psychomotor function, attention and memory.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 28 days of first dose of study drug, Baseline (either Day -7 or Cycle 1 Day 1), Day 1 of Cycles 2-6 and then Day 1 of every other Cycle and at the end of treatment visit as defined by 28 days after the last dose of study drug.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse events for patients receiving crizotinib following PF-06463922 (Phase 2) - Adverse Events as characterized by type, frequency, severity (as graded by NCI CTCAE v.4.03), seriousness and relationship to study therapy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 2 Weeks prior to first dose of crizotinib through 28 days of the last dose of crizotinib</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Laboratory abnormalities for patients receiving crizotinib following PF-06463922 (Phase 2) - Laboratory abnormalities as characterized by type, frequency, and severity (as graded by NCI CTCAE v.4.03).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 2 Weeks of first dose of crizotinib through 28 days after the last dose of crizotinib</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Objective tumor response, as assessed by Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumor (RECIST) version 1.1 for patients receiving crizotinib following PF-06463922 (Phase 2) - Percentage of patients with OR based assessment of intracranial and overall confirmed complete remission (CR) or confirmed partial remission (PR) according to a modified Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST)v 1.1.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 6 weeks from the time of enrollment up to 4 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression Free Survival (PFS) for patients receiving crizotinib following PF-06463922 (Phase 2) - The period from study entry to disease progression of death due to any cause or until last contact</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 6 weeks from the time of enrollment to the first documented progression or date of death from any cause, assessed up to 4 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of Response for patients receiving crizotinib following PF-06463922 (Phase 2) - DR is defined as the time from the first documentation of objective tumor response (CR or PR) to the first documentation of disease progression or to death due to any cause, whichever occurs first</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 6 weeks from time of enrollment up to 4 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Tumor Response in patients receiving crizotinib following PF-06463922 (Phase 2) - TTR is defined as the time from first dose to first documentation of objective tumor response (CR or PR). For patients whose OR proceeds from PR to CR, the onset of PR is taken as the onset of response. TTR will only be calculated for the subgroup of patients with a confirmed objective tumor response.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 6 weeks from time of enrollment up to 4 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Survival for patients receiving crizotinib following PF-06463922 (Phase 2) - Overall survival was the duration from enrollment to death. For participants who are alive, overall survival was censored at the last contact</outcome>
      <timepoint>From the time of enrollment until the date of death from any causes</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mood Assessment (Phase 2) - An assessment of mood via the Beck Depression Inventory-II (BDI-II) scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (either Day -7 or Cycle 1 Day 1), Day 1 of Cycles 2-6 and then Day 1 of every other Cycle and at the end of treatment visit as defined by 28 days after the last dose of study drug.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Suicidal Ideation and Behavior Assessment (Phase 2) - An assessment of suicidal ideation and behavior via the Columbia Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (either Day -7 or Cycle 1 Day 1), Day 1 of Cycles 2-6 and then Day 1 of every other Cycle and at the end of treatment visit as defined by 28 days after the last dose of study drug</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Laboratory abnormalities - Laboratory abnormalities as characterized by type, frequency, and severity (as graded by NCI CTCAE v.4.03).</outcome>
      <timepoint>First dose of study drug through 28 days after the last dose of study drug.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion Criteria

          -  Evidence of histologically or cytologically confirmed diagnosis of metastatic NSCLC
             (Stage IV, AJCC v7.0) that carries an ALK rearrangement, as determined by the Food and
             Drug Administration (FDA) approved FISH assay (Abbott Molecular Inc) or by
             Immunohistochemistry (IHC) (Ventana Inc), or a ROS1 rearrangement as determined by
             FISH or RT PCR or Next Generation Sequencing (NGS) via a local diagnostic test (LDT).
             All patients (ALK positive and ROS1 positive) must have archival tissue sample
             available and collected prior to enrollment.

          -  Disease Status Requirements:

        Phase 1: ALK-positive NSCLC and ROS1-positive patients must either be treatment na誰ve in
        the advanced setting or have had disease progression after at least 1 previous ALK/ROS1
        inhibitor therapy(ies).

        Phase 2:

        ALK-positive NSCLC patients must either be or have had:

          -  Treatment na誰ve (ie, no prior chemotherapy in the metastatic disease setting and no
             prior ALK inhibitor therapy allowed).

          -  Disease progression after crizotinib only. No prior chemotherapy is allowed in the
             metastatic disease setting.

          -  Disease progression after crizotinib and 1 or 2 prior regimens of chemotherapy in the
             metastatic disease setting.

          -  Disease progression after 1 prior ALK inhibitor therapy other than crizotinib.
             Patients may have had any number of prior chemotherapy regimens in any disease
             setting.

          -  Disease progression after 2 prior ALK inhibitor therapies. Patients may have had any
             number of prior chemotherapy regimens in any disease setting.

          -  Disease progression after 3 prior ALK inhibitor therapies. Patients may have had any
             number of prior chemotherapy regimens in any disease setting.

        ROS1-positive NSCLC patients may be:

          -  Treatment na誰ve (ie, no prior chemotherapy in the metastatic disease setting and no
             prior ROS inhibitor therapy).

          -  Any number of prior therapies (ie, chemotherapy and/or ROS inhibitor therapies).

               -  Tumor Requirements:

        All Patients must have at least one measurable target extracranial lesion according to
        RECIST v1.1. In addition patients with asymptomatic CNS metastases (including patients
        asymptomatic by means of stable or decreasing doses of steroids within the last 2 weeks
        prior to study entry) will be eligible. Patients who have leptomeningeal disease (LM) or
        carcinomatous meningitis (CM) are eligible.

          -  Adequate Bone Marrow, Pancreatic Function, Renal Function and Liver Function.

          -  Negative Serum pregnancy test for females of childbearing potential</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion Criteria

          -  Radiation therapy (except palliative to relieve bone pain) within 2 weeks of study
             entry. Whole brain radiation must have completed at least 4 weeks prior to study
             entry.

          -  Systemic anti cancer therapy completed within a minimum of 5 half lives of study
             entry.

          -  Prior therapy with an antibody or drug specifically targeting T-cell co-stimulation or
             immune checkpoint pathways, including, but not limited to, anti-PD-1, anti-PD-L1,
             anti-PD-L2, anti-CD137, or anti-cytotoxic T lymphocyte associated antigen 4
             (anti-CTLA-4) antibody.

          -  Active and clinically significant bacterial, fungal, or viral infection including
             hepatitis B (HBV), hepatitis C (HCV), known human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), or
             acquired immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS) related illness.

          -  Clinically significant cardiovascular disease (that is, active or &lt;3 months prior to
             enrollment): cerebral vascular accident/stroke, myocardial infarction, unstable
             angina, congestive heart failure (New York Heart Association Classification Class =
             II), second-degree or third-degree AV block (unless paced) or any AV block with PR
             &gt;220 msec. Ongoing cardiac dysrhythmias of NCI CTCAE Grade =2, uncontrolled atrial
             fibrillation of any grade, bradycardia defined as &lt;50 bpm (unless patient is otherwise
             healthy such as long-distance runners, etc.), machine-read ECG with QTc &gt;470 msec, or
             congenital long QT syndrome.

          -  History of extensive, disseminated, bilateral or presence of Grade 3 or 4 interstitial
             fibrosis or interstitial lung disease including a history of pneumonitis,
             hypersensitivity pneumonitis, interstitial pneumonia, interstitial lung disease,
             obliterative bronchiolitis and pulmonary fibrosis.

          -  Current use or anticipated need for food or drugs that are known strong or moderate
             CYP3A4 inhibitors, inducers and substrates; drugs that are CYP2C9 substrates; drugs
             that are sensitive CYP2B6 substrates; drugs that are strong CYP2C19 inhibitors; drugs
             that are strong CYP2C8 inhibitors; and drugs that are P-gp substrates.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional(has expanded access)</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>8/01/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>361</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>19/02/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Chris O'Brien Lifehouse - Sydney Local Health District [RPA]</hospital>
    <hospital>Chris O'Brien Lifehouse - Sydney</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Sydney</hospital>
    <hospital>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>2050 - Sydney Local Health District [RPA]</postcode>
    <postcode>2050 - Sydney</postcode>
    <postcode>3000 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3050 - Parkville</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Arkansas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Colorado</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Connecticut</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>District of Columbia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Massachusetts</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Michigan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Missouri</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Pennsylvania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Tennessee</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Edegem</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>British Columbia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Grenoble Cedex 9</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Rennes Cedex 9</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Toulouse Cedex 9</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Toulouse</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Villejuif Cedex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>NRW</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <state>Shatin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Aviano (PN)</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Milano</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Perugia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Aichi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Chiba</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Ehime</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Hokkaido</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Hyogo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Osaka</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Shizuoka</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Tokyo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Fukuoka</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Koto-ku, Tokyo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Seoul</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Singapore</country>
      <state>Singapore</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Navarra</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state>Lausanne</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state>Winterthur</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Taipei</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Pfizer</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Phase 1 and 2 trial to study the safety, pharmacokinetics, pharmacodynamics, patient reported
      outcomes and efficacy of PF-06463922 in ALK + advanced non-small cell lung cancer patients
      and ROS1+ advanced non small cell lung cancer patients .</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01970865</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Pfizer CT.gov Call Center</name>
      <address>Pfizer</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>