<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4988">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/05/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/05/2015</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02453581</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effectiveness of OZ439 Against Early Plasmodium Falciparum Blood Stage Infection in Healthy Volunteers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An Experimental Study To Characterize the Effectiveness of OZ439 Against Early Plasmodium Falciparum Blood Stage Infection In Healthy Volunteers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>QP12C10</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Malaria</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - OZ439

Experimental: OZ439 100mg - OZ439 100mg Powder for Oral Suspension

Experimental: OZ439 200mg - OZ439 200mg Powder for Oral Suspension

Experimental: OZ439 500mg - OZ439 500mg Powder for Oral Suspension


Treatment: drugs: OZ439
OZ439 Powder for Oral Suspension

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Individual Parasite Reduction Ratio (PRR) - PRR estimates the efficacy of an anti-malarial treatment and is the ratio of the parasite density between admission and 48 hours post-treatment.
Individual subject PRR and corresponding 95% CI were calculated using the slope and corresponding standard error of mean (SE) of the optimal regression model.</outcome>
      <timepoint>48 hours</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>500mg Cohort Mean Parasite Reduction Ratio (PRR) - OZ439 500mg individual subject PRR and corresponding 95% CI were used to calculate the OZ439 500mg cohort specific PRR and the corresponding 95% CI: the weighted average slope estimate and corresponding SE were calculated by the inverse-variance method.</outcome>
      <timepoint>48 hours</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>OZ439 Cmax - OZ439 Maximum concentration (Cmax)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-dose, and 0.25, 0.5, 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 12, 24, 36, 48, 72, 96, 120 and 144 hours post-dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>OZ439 AUC(0-144) - OZ439 Area under the curve to 144 hours</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-dose, and 0.25, 0.5, 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 12, 24, 36, 48, 72, 96, 120 and 144 hours post-dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Volunteers will be adults (males or non pregnant females), aged between 18 and 45
             years who do not live alone (from Day 1 until at least the end of the antimalarial
             drug treatment).

          -  Volunteers must have a BMI within the range 18-30.

          -  Volunteers must understand the procedures involved and agree to participate in the
             study by giving fully informed, written consent.

          -  Be contactable and available for the duration of the trial (maximum of 4 weeks).

          -  Volunteers must be non-smokers and in good health, as assessed during pre-study
             medical examination and by review of screening results.

          -  Female participants of childbearing potential, should be surgically sterile or using
             an insertable, injectable, transdermal, or combination oral contraceptive approved by
             the US FDA or Therapeutic Goods Administration (TGA) combined with a barrier
             contraceptive through completion of the study and have negative results on a serum or
             urine pregnancy test done before administration of study medication.

          -  Good peripheral venous access.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  History of malaria.

          -  Travelled to or lived (2 weeks or more) in a malaria-endemic country during the past
             12 months or planned travel to a malaria-endemic country during the course of the
             study.

          -  Has evidence of increased cardiovascular disease risk (defined as greater than 10%, 5
             year risk)

          -  History of splenectomy.

          -  History of a severe allergic reaction, anaphylaxis or convulsions following any
             vaccination or infusion.

          -  Presence of current or suspected serious chronic diseases such as cardiac or
             autoimmune disease (HIV or other immunodeficiencies), insulin dependent diabetes,
             progressive neurological disease, severe malnutrition, acute or progressive hepatic
             disease, acute or progressive renal disease, psoriasis, rheumatoid arthritis, asthma,
             epilepsy or obsessive compulsive disorder, skin carcinoma excluding non-spreadable
             skin cancers such as basal cell and squamous cell carcinoma.

          -  Known inherited genetic anomaly (known as cytogenetic disorders) e.g., Down's syndrome

          -  Volunteers unwilling to defer blood donations to the Australian Red Cross Blood
             Service (ARCBS) for 6 months.

          -  The volunteer has a diagnosis of schizophrenia, severe depression, bi-polar disease,
             or other severe (disabling) chronic psychiatric diagnosis. Participants who are
             receiving a single antidepressant drug and are stable for at least 3 months prior to
             enrollment without decompensating may be allowed to enroll in the study at the
             investigator's discretion. 10) Presence of acute infectious disease or fever (e.g.,
             sub-lingual temperature 38.5 degrees C) within the five days prior to study product
             administration.

          -  Evidence of acute illness within the four weeks before trial prior to screening.

          -  Significant intercurrent disease of any type, in particular liver, renal, cardiac,
             pulmonary, neurologic, rheumatologic, or autoimmune disease by history, physical
             examination, and/or laboratory studies including urinalysis.

          -  Have ever received a blood transfusion.

          -  Evidence of any condition that, in the opinion of the clinical investigator, might
             interfere with the evaluation of the study objectives or pose excessive risks to
             participants.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/09/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>24</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/03/2013</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Q-Pharm - Herston</hospital>
    <postcode>QLD 4006 - Herston</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Medicines for Malaria Venture</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Queensland Institute of Medical Research</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A single centre, open, controlled study using Blood Stage Plasmodium falciparum challenge
      inoculum (BSPC) as a model to assess the effectiveness of three dose levels of the
      experimental anti-malarial product, OZ439.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02453581</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>James McCarthy, Pr</name>
      <address>Q-Pharm Pty Limited</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>