<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4080">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/09/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/09/2013</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01939223</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Colorectal Cancer Treated With Adjuvant Regorafenib Versus Placebo After Curative Treatment of Liver Metastases in a Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-Controlled Phase-III STudy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled Phase-III Study of Adjuvant Regorafenib Versus Placebo for Patients With Stage IV Colorectal Cancer After Curative Treatment of Liver Metastases</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>COAST</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>2012-004369-42</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>15983</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Colorectal Neoplasms</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Bowel - Back passage (rectum) or large bowel (colon)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Regorafenib (Stivarga, BAY73-4506)
Treatment: drugs - Placebo

Experimental: Regorafenib - 4 regorafenib tablets taken orally in the morning daily, followed by a low fat meal for 3 weeks on off treatment followed by 1 week off without treatment,Treatment 21 days.

Placebo Comparator: Placebo - 4 placebo tablets taken orally in the morning daily,followed by a low fat meal for 3 weeks on off treatment followed by 1 week off without treatment,Treatment 21 days.


Treatment: drugs: Regorafenib (Stivarga, BAY73-4506)
Four tablets of 40mg taken orally daily in the morning, dose of 160 mg for 21 days of treatment followed by 7 days without treatment

Treatment: drugs: Placebo
Four tablets taken in the morning orally daily for 21 days of treatment followed by 7 days without treatment

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disease Free Survival (DFS) as Assessed by the Investigator - Disease free survival was evaluated by CT / MRI scans as assessed by the investigator, which was defined as the time (in days) from date of randomization to date of first observed radiographic disease recurrence (RECIST 1.1 criteria for measurable and non-measurable disease) or death due to any cause, if death occurred before disease recurrence was documented. For subjects without documented disease recurrence or death at the time of analysis, the DFS time was censored at the date of the last evaluable CT / MRI scan.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From date of randomization to date of first observed radiographic disease recurrence (RECIST 1.1 criteria for measurable and non-measurable disease) or death due to any cause, if death occurred before disease recurrence was documented.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Survival (OS) - Overall survival (OS) is defined as the time (days) from randomization to death due to any cause. The OS time for subjects alive at the time of analysis was censored at their last date known to be alive.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Subjects who experienced disease recurrence (either during treatment or during Active Follow-up), or otherwise withdrew from the study for any reason other than death, were followed for overall survival unless consent was withdrawn.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Have a history of a primary adenocarcinoma of the colon and / or rectum

          -  Have a history of Stage IV Colorectal Cancer (CRC) with metastases to the liver only

          -  Have received at least 3 months ,of neoadjuvant, adjuvant, or perioperative
             chemotherapy, including a fluoropyrimidine and either oxaliplatin or irinotecan or
             both for subjects with initial Stage IV CRC which were treated with surgery with
             curative intent for both primary and metastatic lesions. The total chemotherapy
             administered, including that administered prior to and after liver resection, should
             not exceed 9 months. OR Have received surgery with curative intent for primary CRC and
             at least 3 months ,of neoadjuvant, adjuvant, or perioperative chemotherapy for the
             primary tumor, including a fluoropyrimidine or a fluoropyrimidine and either
             oxaliplatin or irinotecan or both

               -  For subjects with liver metastases developing &gt; 6 months after completing
                  treatment for primary CRC and having undergone surgery with curative intent for
                  liver metastases, a second course of chemotherapy lasting at least 3 months needs
                  to be administered, including a fluoropyrimidine and either oxaliplatin or
                  irinotecan or both. The second course of chemotherapy should not exceed 9 months.

          -  For subjects who developed liver metastases &gt;/=6 months after completing treatment for
             primary CRC and having undergone surgery with curative intent for liver metastases, a
             second course of chemotherapy is not permitted unless initial adjuvant therapy
             consisted of fluoropyrimidine monotherapy. Subjects who received fluoropyrimidine
             alone must have received a second course of chemotherapy with fluoropyrimidine and
             either oxaliplatin or irinotecan or both, which should not exceed 9 months.For
             subjects with initial Stage I or II disease, no chemotherapy is required for a primary
             CRC lesion treated with surgery with curative intent. These subjects must receive
             chemotherapy for the treatment of liver metastases (which were also treated with
             surgery with curative intent), which must last at least 3 months, including a
             fluoropyrimidine and either oxaliplatin or irinotecan or both. The total course of
             chemotherapy should not exceed 9 months.

          -  Prior to randomization, have histological confirmation that CRC lesions were
             adenocarcinoma (subtypes of adenocarcinoma, e.g. mucinous adenocarcinoma are allowed).
             Subjects with CRC lesions of other histological types, including mixed type with
             predominant adenocarcinoma, will not be eligible to be randomized to study treatment.

          -  Have pathology-proven complete removal of all primary and liver metastatic CRC
             lesions. Subjects with positive margins will not be eligible for the study.

          -  Have adequate bone marrow function, liver function, and renal function, as measured by
             the following laboratory assessments conducted within 7 days prior to the initiation
             of study treatment:

               -  Total bilirubin &lt;/=1.5 times the upper limit of normal (ULN)

               -  Alanine aminotransferase and aspartate aminotransferase &lt;/= 3 times the ULN

               -  Lipase&lt;/=1.5 times the ULN

               -  Serum creatinine&lt;/=1.5 times the ULN

               -  Carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA)&lt;/=3 times the ULN

               -  Glomerular filtration rate&gt;/=30 mL/min/1.73 m2 according to the Modified Diet in
                  Renal Disease abbreviated formula

               -  International normalized ratio of prothrombin time and activated partial
                  thromboplastic time &lt;/=1.5 times the ULN. Subjects who are therapeutically
                  treated with an agent such as warfarin or heparin will be allowed to participate
                  if no underlying abnormality in coagulation parameters exists per medical
                  history.

               -  Platelet count &gt;/=100,000 /mm3, hemoglobin &gt;/=9 g/dL, absolute neutrophil count
                  &gt;/= 1500/mm3 without transfusions or granulocyte colony stimulating factor and
                  other hematopoietic growth factors

               -  Alkaline phosphatase = 2.5 times the ULN

          -  Have had a CT or MRI scan (chest, abdomen, pelvis and other suspected sites as
             applicable) to determine eligibility for randomization within 4 weeks prior to
             randomization (hereafter referred to as the "eligibility scan")

          -  Have an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 or 1 within
             14 days prior to the initiation of study treatment

          -  If female and of childbearing potential, or if male, agree to use adequate
             contraception (e.g., abstinence, intrauterine device, oral contraceptive, or double
             barrier method) based on the judgment of the investigator or a designated associate
             from the date on which the ICF is signed until 8 weeks after the last dose of study
             drug.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Are taking strong cytochrome P (CYP) CYP3A4 inhibitors (eg, clarithromycin, indinavir,
             itraconazole, ketoconazole, nefazodone, nelfinavir, posaconazole, ritonavir,
             saquinavir, telithromycin, voriconazole) or strong CYP3A4 inducers (eg, carbamazepine,
             phenobarbital, phenytoin, rifampin, St. John's Wort).

          -  Have used biologic response modifiers, such as granulocyte-colony stimulating factor,
             within 3 weeks prior to signing the ICF.

          -  Have had prior treatment with regorafenib or any other (vascular endothelial growth
             factor receptor) VEGFR-targeting kinase inhibitor.

          -  Have had anti-cancer treatment following liver resection that exceeded a duration of 6
             months.

          -  Have been treated with biologics (eg, antibodies targeting VEGFR or EGFR) after liver
             resection unless the administration of the biologic started prior to liver resection
             and continued after liver resection only to complete a pre-specified number of cycles.

          -  Completed their last dose of chemotherapy or had their last cancer surgery more than
             10 weeks, whichever came later, prior to randomization.

          -  Have extra-hepatic metastatic disease. Suspicious lesions should be rigorously
             evaluated with other imaging techniques and/or biopsy to exclude extra-hepatic
             metastatic disease prior to submitting for central radiology review.

          -  Have had systemic anticancer therapy including cytotoxic therapy, signal transduction
             inhibitors, immunotherapy, and/or hormonal therapy within 4 weeks prior to initiation
             of study treatment.

          -  Are pregnant and or breast feeding.

          -  Have had prior or concurrent cancer distinct in primary site or histology from CRC
             within 5 years prior to randomization EXCEPT for curatively treated cervical cancer in
             situ, nonmelanoma skin cancer, Stage 0 intramucosal gastric cancer after endoscopic
             complete removal, or superficial bladder tumors classified as noninvasive tumor (Ta),
             carcinoma in situ (Tis), or tumor invades lamina propria (T1).

          -  Have congestive heart failure classified as New York Heart Association Class 2 or
             higher.Have had unstable angina (angina symptoms at rest) or new-onset angina = 3
             months prior to screening. Have had a myocardial infarction &lt; 6 months prior to
             initiation of study treatment.

          -  Have cardiac arrhythmias requiring anti-arrhythmic therapy, with the exception of beta
             blockers or digoxin.

          -  Have uncontrolled hypertension (systolic blood pressure [SBP] greater than140 mmHg or
             diastolic blood pressure [DBP] greater than 90 mmHg) despite optimal medical
             management.

          -  Have pheochromocytoma.

          -  Have had arterial or venous thrombotic or embolic events such as cerebrovascular
             accident (including transient ischemic attacks), deep vein thrombosis, or pulmonary
             embolism within 6 months prior to the initiation of study treatment.

          -  Have a known history of human immunodeficiency virus infection.

          -  Have either active or chronic hepatitis B or C requiring treatment with antiviral
             therapy.

          -  Have a seizure disorder requiring medication.

          -  Have evidence or history of any bleeding diathesis (including mild hemophilia),
             irrespective of severity.

          -  Have had a hemorrhage or a bleeding event &gt;/=Grade 3 (NCI-CTCAE v 4.0) within 4 weeks
             prior to the initiation of study treatment.

          -  Have any other serious or unstable illness, or medical, social, or psychological
             condition, that could jeopardize the safety of the subject and/or his/her compliance
             with study procedures, or may interfere with the subject's participation in the study
             or evaluation of the study results.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2>The people administering the treatment/s</masking2>
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>2/12/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>25</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Terminated</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>29/08/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital> - Liverpool</hospital>
    <hospital> - East Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital> - Bentleigh East</hospital>
    <hospital> - Malvern</hospital>
    <postcode>2170 - Liverpool</postcode>
    <postcode>3002 - East Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3165 - Bentleigh East</postcode>
    <postcode>3144 - Malvern</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Connecticut</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Louisiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Maryland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Michigan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Minnesota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Nebraska</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Jersey</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Pennsylvania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Tennessee</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Virginia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Washington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Edegem</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Leuven</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Liege</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Minas Gerais</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Rio Grande do Sul</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Sao Paulo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Alberta</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Quebec</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Montreal</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Fujian</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Guangdong</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Heilongjiang</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Hubei</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Hunan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Shaanxi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Yunnan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Zhejiang</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Beijing</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Shanghai</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Bordeaux</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Brest</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Clermont-Ferrand</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>LYON Cedex 08</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Marseille</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Paris</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Poitiers Cedex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Tours</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Villejuif</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Bayern</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Hessen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Niedersachsen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Rheinland-Pfalz</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Berlin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Haifa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Ramat Gan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Tel Aviv</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Campania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Emilia-Romagna</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Friuli-Venezia Giulia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Lazio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Lombardia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Puglia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Toscana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Chiba</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Hokkaido</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Hyogo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Ibaraki</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Kanagawa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Osaka</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Shizuoka</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Tochigi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Tokyo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Fukuoka</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <state>Almada</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <state>Porto</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <state>Santa Maria da Feira</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Alicante</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Badajoz</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Córdoba</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Valencia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Surrey</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Bristol</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Bayer</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To evaluate and compare the efficacy and safety of regorafenib versus placebo in subjects
      with colorectal cancer (CRC) after curative resection of liver metastasis and completion of
      all planned chemotherapy.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01939223</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Bayer Study Director</name>
      <address>Bayer</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>