<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2310">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/04/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/04/2009</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00874289</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Utility of Neutrophil Gelatinase-associated Lipocalin (NGAL) in Predicting Renal Impairment, Further Decompensation and Rehospitalization in Acutely Decompensated and Chronic Heart Failure Patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Utility of NGAL in Predicting Renal Impairment, Further Decompensation &amp; Rehospitalization in Acutely Decompensated &amp; Chronic Heart Failure Patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ANGLE-HF</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>CP-01/08</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Heart Failure</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - NGAL kit

Acute heart failure patients - 

Chronic heart failure patients - 


Other interventions: NGAL kit
Kit to test NGAL levels in heart failure patients

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the utility of NGAL in predicting death, rehospitalisation or deterioration of renal function (increase in creatinine of &gt;0.3 mmol/L) at 12 months</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the utility of NGAL in predicting subsequent HF rehospitalisation and predicting clinical deterioration, ie worsening symptoms and/or signs (based on NYHA class) at 30, 90 days (ADHF patients), 6 months and 12 months (CHF patients)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Males and Females

          2. Age &gt;18years

          3. Confirmed written informed consent

          4. Acute decompensated heart failure cohort defined as:

               -  Objective evidence of heart failure (of any cause/etiology) demonstrated by
                  typical symptoms/signs combined with an imaging modality (see appendix for
                  criteria)

               -  Requirement for intravenous diuretic whilst either an inpatient or in an
                  emergency room setting with intravenous diuretics, vasodilators or inotropes

               -  No ejection fraction cut-off will be required, ie both systolic and diastolic
                  heart failure patients can be enrolled

          5. Chronic Heart Failure cohort defined as:

               -  Echocardiographic evidence of systolic or diastolic heart failure (see appendix
                  for criteria)

               -  CHF patients in Class III and class IV NYHA symptoms who have had a minimum of
                  one acute decompensated episode in the previous six months

               -  Evidence of impaired renal function (eGFR &lt;60 ml/min)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Patients with a history of a psychological illness or condition such as to interfere
             with the patient's ability to understand the requirements of the study

          2. Not meeting entry criteria for ADAF (as above)

          3. At the discretion of the treating physician</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/12/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>106</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/05/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Alfred Hospital - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Alfred</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Biosite</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Acute decompensated heart failure (ADHF) is the leading cause of admission to hospital in the
      US, and is associated with high mortality, morbidity, and major cost to the health care
      system. Much of this cost relates to prolonged hospitalizations from acute deterioration in
      kidney function (AKI), which in turn is associated with further cardiovascular events such as
      recurrent ADHF. Strategies for early detection minimization and prevention of AKI would
      therefore be of tremendous benefit to both the patient and the health care system.

      A common reason for hospitalization in ADHF is that of altered volume status and renal
      impairment. Also, many patients with ADHF have underlying hypertension and/or a recent acute
      coronary syndrome. Hypertension, diabetes and chronic kidney disease (CKD) are independent
      risk factors for cardiovascular disease, and diabetes is the leading cause of CKD. Therefore,
      patients presenting with ADHF are at high risk for CV events, more so if they develop AKI.
      Therefore, strategies to detect changes in renal status early may allow for more rapid
      intervention with appropriate drug and other therapies to attenuate AKI and subsequent
      complications, which may in turn result in prevention of early readmissions with HF.

      Most ADHF patients have underlying chronic heart failure (CHF). CHF is a major cost to the
      health care system. About two thirds of this cost relates to hospitalization for acute
      deterioration in heart failure (HF). Strategies to minimize or prevent HF hospitalization
      therefore are of tremendous benefit to both the patient and the health care system.

      The most frequent reason for hospitalization in a CHF patient is that of altered volume
      status and renal impairment. Therefore, as with ADHF, strategies for early detection of
      changes in renal status may allow for intervention with appropriate drug and other therapies
      to attenuate, or even prevent, the need for the patient to return to hospital.

      Many approaches have been studied in relation to this concept. Deterioration in renal
      function is a harbinger of a need for hospitalization, and indeed a predictor of medium term
      mortality. However, current measures of renal function are relatively crude with a
      considerable lag between an insult to the kidney and its translation to a measurable
      deterioration in renal function reflected by worsening serum creatinine. Thus, diagnostic
      tests that evaluate renal injury which are modulated early in the time course of this process
      may have considerable utility not only in the ADHF setting but also in predicting
      decompensation in the CHF setting.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00874289</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Henry Krum, MBBS FRACP PhD</name>
      <address>Monash University / Alfred Hospital</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>