<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2826">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/06/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/06/2010</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01150214</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>DECAAF: Delayed-Enhancement MRI (DE-MRI) Determinant of Successful Radiofrequency Catheter Ablation of Atrial Fibrillation</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>DECAAF: DE-MRI Determinant of Successful Radiofrequency Catheter Ablation of Atrial Fibrillation</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>DECAAF</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>IRB_00039522</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Atrial Fibrillation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: surgery - DE-MRI

DE-MRI - All patients will undergo Delayed-Enhancement Magnetic Resonance Imaging (DE-MRI)to quantify the degree of atrial structural remodeling or fibrosis pre-ablation and DE-MRI will be obtained at 3, 6, and 12 months follow-up to detect and quantify ablation-related scar formation.


Treatment: surgery: DE-MRI
Using Delayed-Enhancement Magnetic Resonance Imaging (DE-MRI) to identify fibrotic and scarred cardiac tissue. DE-MRI is a non-invasive method of identifying the extent and the distribution of structural remodeling or fibrosis and scarring associated with atrial fibrillation both pre- and post-ablation.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relationship between extent of pre-ablation fibrosis and recurrence post-ablation - The percentage of pre-ablation fibrosis in atrial fibrillation patients can significantly impact the incidence of recurrences post-ablation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 year</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relationship between extent of Post-ablation scar and incidence of atrial fibrillation recurrences post-catheter ablation for AF - The extent of lesions created by ablation may have an impact on the incidence of recurrence of AF post-ablation</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-ablation scar</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Patients who underwent an AF ablation as per recent Heart Rhythm Society (HRS)
             consensus document, as per the University of Utah AFIB Database (IRB_00020347)

          -  Patients who have had an MRI post-ablation.

          -  Age =18 years.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Contraindication for DE-MRI with a full dose of Gadolinium-based contrast agent.

          -  Previous left atrial ablation or surgical procedure

          -  Renal failure with CrCl &lt;60 ml/min

          -  Women currently pregnant, breastfeeding, or of childbearing age not currently taking
             or not willing to use a reliable form of contraception

          -  Mental or physical inability to take part in the study

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension

          -  Morbid obesity (BMI &gt; 35), or inability to be placed in MRI due to body mass.

          -  Patients who have not had a DE-MRI post-ablation.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>339</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/09/2012</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Adelaide Hospital - Norwood</hospital>
    <postcode>5067 - Norwood</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Illinois</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Pennsylvania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Tennessee</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Ghent</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Bordeaux</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Bad Nauheim</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Coburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Cologne</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Hamburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Leipzig</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Nieuwegein</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Catalonia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Utah</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a multi-center, observational, 1-year prospective cohort study (1 year follow-up, at
      3, 6 and 12 month) with approximately 675 participants. We will conduct a thorough outcomes
      assessment utilizing data from Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) scans, as well as
      pre-procedure and follow-up data. Scans will be blinded to location of participating site.
      MRI scans will be sequenced and analyzed as they arrive from the database.

      Imaging Protocol: All patients will undergo a Delayed-Enhancement MRI (DE-MRI) within 30 days
      prior to the atrial fibrillation (AF) ablation procedure. The purpose of the initial MRI is
      to quantify the degree of atrial structural remodeling or fibrosis pre-ablation. Following
      ablation, DE-MRI will be obtained at 3, 6, and 12 months follow-up to detect and quantify
      ablation-related scar formation.

      Clinical Follow-up: The institution where the ablation was performed will continue
      post-procedural care following standard of care procedures.

      Atrial arrhythmia recurrences will be catalogued up to one year post-ablation and predictors
      of recurrences of AF will be determined by statistical analysis. The specific mechanism and
      electrophysiological characteristics of atrial arrhythmia recurrence will also be analyzed.

      Our hypotheses are (1) DE-MRI will reproducibly stage the progression left atrium fibrosis in
      AF; (2) DE-MRI will reproducibly aid in quantifying and identifying the distribution of
      catheter ablation-related scarring in the left atrium; and (3) the stage of left atrium
      fibrosis pre-ablation and the amount and location of scarring will predict success of
      catheter ablation therapy for AF.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01150214</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Oakes RS, Badger TJ, Kholmovski EG, Akoum N, Burgon NS, Fish EN, Blauer JJ, Rao SN, DiBella EV, Segerson NM, Daccarett M, Windfelder J, McGann CJ, Parker D, MacLeod RS, Marrouche NF. Detection and quantification of left atrial structural remodeling with delayed-enhancement magnetic resonance imaging in patients with atrial fibrillation. Circulation. 2009 Apr 7;119(13):1758-67. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.108.811877. Epub 2009 Mar 23.
McGann CJ, Kholmovski EG, Oakes RS, Blauer JJ, Daccarett M, Segerson N, Airey KJ, Akoum N, Fish E, Badger TJ, DiBella EV, Parker D, MacLeod RS, Marrouche NF. New magnetic resonance imaging-based method for defining the extent of left atrial wall injury after the ablation of atrial fibrillation. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2008 Oct 7;52(15):1263-71. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2008.05.062.
Segerson NM, Daccarett M, Badger TJ, Shabaan A, Akoum N, Fish EN, Rao S, Burgon NS, Adjei-Poku Y, Kholmovski E, Vijayakumar S, DiBella EV, MacLeod RS, Marrouche NF. Magnetic resonance imaging-confirmed ablative debulking of the left atrial posterior wall and septum for treatment of persistent atrial fibrillation: rationale and initial experience. J Cardiovasc Electrophysiol. 2010 Feb;21(2):126-32. doi: 10.1111/j.1540-8167.2009.01611.x. Epub 2009 Oct 5.
Calkins H, Brugada J, Packer DL, Cappato R, Chen SA, Crijns HJ, Damiano RJ Jr, Davies DW, Haines DE, Haissaguerre M, Iesaka Y, Jackman W, Jais P, Kottkamp H, Kuck KH, Lindsay BD, Marchlinski FE, McCarthy PM, Mont JL, Morady F, Nademanee K, Natale A, Pappone C, Prystowsky E, Raviele A, Ruskin JN, Shemin RJ; Heart Rhythm Society; European Heart Rhythm Association; European Cardiac Arrhythmia Society; American College of Cardiology; American Heart Association; Society of Thoracic Surgeons. HRS/EHRA/ECAS expert consensus statement on catheter and surgical ablation of atrial fibrillation: recommendations for personnel, policy, procedures and follow-up. A report of the Heart Rhythm Society (HRS) Task Force on Catheter and Surgical Ablation of Atrial Fibrillation developed in partnership with the European Heart Rhythm Association (EHRA) and the European Cardiac Arrhythmia Society (ECAS); in collaboration with the American College of Cardiology (ACC), American Heart Association (AHA), and the Society of Thoracic Surgeons (STS). Endorsed and approved by the governing bodies of the American College of Cardiology, the American Heart Association, the European Cardiac Arrhythmia Society, the European Heart Rhythm Association, the Society of Thoracic Surgeons, and the Heart Rhythm Society. Europace. 2007 Jun;9(6):335-79. Erratum in: Europace. 2009 Jan;11(1):132.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Nassir F Marrouce, MD, FHRS</name>
      <address>CARMA Center, University of Utah</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>