<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="1077">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/02/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/02/2006</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00294788</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of the Safety and Effectiveness of a Probiotic Bacterium to Boost the Immune Response to Influenza Vaccines</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Phase I/II Placebo-Controlled Study of Consumption of a Probiotic on HAI Titre Following Influenza Vaccination of Healthy Adult Subjects</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>H05/123</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>ProFlu2006</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Influenza</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - Fluvax
Treatment: drugs - PCC® (Lactobacillus fermentum VRI 003)

Other interventions: Fluvax


Treatment: drugs: PCC® (Lactobacillus fermentum VRI 003)


</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The percentage enhancement of the immune response to Fluvax vaccine by PCC® compared to placebo as measured by hemagglutination inhibition (HAI) titre in the serum of subjects 4 weeks after vaccination</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Increase in T cell cytokine expression; Decrease in incidence of respiratory tract illness, an improvement in general intestinal health, and a reduction in the severity of adverse side effects of the injection</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Persons must be adult men and women aged 18-49 years (have not reached 50th birthday).

          -  Persons must be able and willing to provide informed consent.

          -  Persons must be willing to receive the influenza vaccine (Fluvax®) given as an
             intramuscular injection.

          -  Persons must be willing to consume one gelatin capsule per day containing either
             probiotic bacteria or placebo (inactive substance) for the duration (42 days) of the
             study.

          -  Persons must be willing to provide blood specimens, each of 10 ml, collected by
             venepuncture.

          -  Persons must be willing to notify study personnel of a range of health effects by
             questionnaire.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>49</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Any health condition for which the influenza vaccine is not recommended including:
             chronic diseases of the pulmonary or cardiovascular systems (including asthma);
             chronic metabolic diseases (including diabetes); renal dysfunction;
             hemoglobinopathies; immune deficiency diseases (including HIV infection) or on-going
             immunosuppressive therapy.

          -  Currently pregnant; nursing mothers; or planning a pregnancy within one month of
             vaccination.

          -  Allergy to latex, egg, or egg protein, or the antibiotics neomycin or polymyxin.

          -  A prior serious reaction to a vaccine, or have had Guillain-Barre syndrome.

          -  Received an influenza vaccine in the past.

          -  Received any other vaccine within one month prior to enrolment

          -  Are participating in another research study involving any study medication</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/03/2006</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Unknown status</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Good Health Solutions - Sydney</hospital>
    <postcode>2000 - Sydney</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Probiomics Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project aims to test the hypothesis that oral consumption of a specific strain of the
      probiotic bacterium Lactobacillus fermentum (trademarked PCC®) is able to significantly
      enhance the immune response to a vaccine for influenza.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00294788</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Mohamadzadeh M, Olson S, Kalina WV, Ruthel G, Demmin GL, Warfield KL, Bavari S, Klaenhammer TR. Lactobacilli activate human dendritic cells that skew T cells toward T helper 1 polarization. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2005 Feb 22;102(8):2880-5. Epub 2005 Feb 14.
Prescott SL, Dunstan JA, Hale J, Breckler L, Lehmann H, Weston S, Richmond P. Clinical effects of probiotics are associated with increased interferon-gamma responses in very young children with atopic dermatitis. Clin Exp Allergy. 2005 Dec;35(12):1557-64.
Weston S, Halbert A, Richmond P, Prescott SL. Effects of probiotics on atopic dermatitis: a randomised controlled trial. Arch Dis Child. 2005 Sep;90(9):892-7. Epub 2005 Apr 29.
Qi H, Denning TL, Soong L. Differential induction of interleukin-10 and interleukin-12 in dendritic cells by microbial toll-like receptor activators and skewing of T-cell cytokine profiles. Infect Immun. 2003 Jun;71(6):3337-42.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ronald Penny, DSc, MD, FRACP</name>
      <address>Good Health Solutions</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>