<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5287">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/12/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/12/2015</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02629289</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Comparative Study to Evaluate the Effect of HSP-130, US-approved Neulasta and EU-approved Neulasta in Healthy Participants</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 1 Study Assessing The Pharmacodynamic And Pharmacokinetic Equivalence Of HSP-130 With US-approved Neulasta (Registered) And EU-approved Neulasta (Registered) Administered As A Single Subcutaneous Dose To Healthy Volunteers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>C1221001</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>ZIN-130-1505</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Neutropenia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other blood disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - HSP-130
Treatment: drugs - US-approved Neulasta
Treatment: drugs - EU-approved Neulasta

Other: Treatment A - HSP-130, 6 mg, single subcutaneous (SC) injection in the deltoid region

Other: Treatment B - US-approved Neulasta, 6 mg, single SC injection in the deltoid region

Other: Treatment C - EU-approved Neulasta, 6 mg, single SC injection in the deltoid region


Treatment: drugs: HSP-130


Treatment: drugs: US-approved Neulasta


Treatment: drugs: EU-approved Neulasta


</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Area under the effect versus time curve for absolute neutrophil count (ANC) from the time of dose administration to 288 hours after dose administration (AUECANC)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 1 hour prior to dose administration and at 12, 24, 48, 72, 96, 120, 144, 168, 192, 216, 240, 264, and 288 hours post-dose.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximum observed value for ANC (ANC_Cmax)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 1 hour prior to dose administration and at 12, 24, 48, 72, 96, 120, 144, 168, 192, 216, 240, 264, and 288 hours post-dose.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time of maximum value for ANC (ANC_Tmax)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 1 hour prior to dose administration and at 12, 24, 48, 72, 96, 120, 144, 168, 192, 216, 240, 264, and 288 hours post-dose.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Area under the serum pegylated filgrastim versus time curve from the time of dose administration to time infinity (AUC0-8)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 1 hour prior to dose and at 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 16, 24, 48, 72, 96, 120, 144, 168, 192, 216, 240, 264, and 288 hours post-dose.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximum observed serum pegylated filgrastim concentration (Cmax)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 1 hour prior to dose and at 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 16, 24, 48, 72, 96, 120, 144, 168, 192, 216, 240, 264, and 288 hours post-dose.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Area under the serum pegylated filgrastim versus time curve from the time of dose administration to the time of last measurable concentration (AUC0-t)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 1 hour prior to dose and at 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 16, 24, 48, 72, 96, 120, 144, 168, 192, 216, 240, 264, and 288 hours post-dose.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to maximum serum pegylated filgrastim concentration (Tmax)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 1 hour prior to dose and at 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 16, 24, 48, 72, 96, 120, 144, 168, 192, 216, 240, 264, and 288 hours post-dose.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Elimination half-life (t1/2)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 1 hour prior to dose and at 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 16, 24, 48, 72, 96, 120, 144, 168, 192, 216, 240, 264, and 288 hours post-dose.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Elimination rate constant (?z)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 1 hour prior to dose and at 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 16, 24, 48, 72, 96, 120, 144, 168, 192, 216, 240, 264, and 288 hours post-dose.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Provides written informed consent approved by an Independent Ethics Committee (IEC)
             prior to any study related activities

          2. Healthy male or female volunteers between 18 and 65 years of age (both inclusive)

          3. Body mass index (BMI) between 19 and 30 kg/m^2, inclusive, and body weight of not &lt;50
             kg or &gt;100 kg

          4. Non-smoker (defined as a subject who has not smoked and has not used nicotine
             containing products for at least 3 months prior to study drug administration and has a
             negative urine screen for cotinine) at Screening

          5. Female subjects of childbearing potential and male subjects and their partners of
             childbearing potential, agree to pregnancy prevention throughout the duration of the
             study (through the Follow-up Visit). Subjects and their partners must agree to use of
             an effective method of contraception, to avoid impregnation of females throughout the
             course of the study.

        Subjects using oral contraceptives must be on a stable regimen for at least 3 months prior
        to Screening. Adequate forms of contraception to be used include hormonal contraceptives
        (oral, patch, depot), intrauterine devices (IUD), barrier contraceptive methods, such as
        diaphragm, cervical cap/shield, male condoms and female condoms.Sexually active subjects
        must use contraception while on study drug from admission to the Follow-up Visit. Male
        subjects must also refrain from donating sperm from admission to the Follow-up visit 6.
        Willing and able to comply with the requirements of the protocol and available for the
        planned duration of the study</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Any active systemic or immunologic disease or condition, including but not limited to
             the following general categories: cardiovascular/pulmonary, hepatorenal, or systemic
             infection, or lactation

          2. History of, or current, malignancy with the exception of adequately treated squamous
             or basal cell carcinoma of the skin or cervical carcinoma in situ within 5 years

          3. Any disease or condition that might interfere with the absorption, distribution,
             metabolism, or excretion of the study drug or would place the subject at increased
             risk

          4. Hematologic laboratory abnormalities including leukocytosis (defined as total
             leukocytes &gt;11,000/µL), leukopenia (defined as total leukocytes &lt;4000/µL), neutropenia
             (defined as ANC &lt;1500/µL) or thrombocytopenia (defined as platelet count of &lt;150/µL)

          5. Clinically significant, as judged by the investigator, vital sign or 12-lead ECG
             abnormality

          6. History of biological growth factor exposure, including but not limited to filgrastim
             and other granulocyte-colony stimulating factors in the context of treatment,
             prophylaxis, peripheral blood stem cell mobilization, or previous investigational
             study setting. This also includes exclusion for history of interferon, epoetin, and
             intravenous immunoglobulin (IVIG) exposure

          7. Receipt of live vaccination, or exposure to communicable viral diseases such as,
             varicella, mumps, or measles within the 4 weeks prior to Screening

          8. Surgery within the 4 months prior to Screening

          9. Use of any prescription medicine (with the exception of contraceptives) within 7 days
             or at least 5 half-lives, whichever is longer. Use of oral or parenteral anticoagulant
             or antiplatelet agents and corticosteroids should be specifically queried

         10. Administration of a drug by depot injection (with exception of depot contraception)
             within 30 days prior to Randomization or 5 half-lives of that drug, whichever is
             longer

         11. Use of over the counter medications, including aspirin and non-steroidal
             anti-inflammatory drugs, or natural preparations (dietary supplement or herbal
             product) within 7 days or at least 5 half-lives, whichever is longer. Vitamins and
             calcium are allowed (not to exceed 100% Daily Value)

         12. History of drug or alcohol abuse within 2 years prior to Randomization, as determined
             by the investigator or a positive urine screen for drugs of abuse (UDS) at Screening.
             Screening for drugs of abuse will minimally include cannabinoids, opiates,
             barbiturates, amphetamines, cocaine, benzodiazepines, and alcohol

         13. Drug sensitivity, allergic reaction to, or known hypersensitivity/idiosyncratic
             reaction to Escherichia coli-derived proteins, filgrastim, other granulocyte-colony
             stimulating factors, or pegylated agents

         14. History of splenic rupture (or subject who is asplenic), pulmonary infiltrate or
             pneumonia, sickle cell disease, chronic neutropenia, thrombocytopenia, or vasculitis

         15. Any clinically significant, as determined by the investigator, abnormal laboratory
             evaluations, including human immunodeficiency virus antibody (HIVAb), hepatitis B
             virus surface antigen (HBsAg), hepatitis C virus antibody (HCVAb), and liver function
             including alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) &lt; 1.5
             the upper limit of normal taken at Screening. Negative HIVAb status will be confirmed
             at Screening and the results will be maintained confidentially by the study site

         16. Donated or lost 475 mL or more blood volume (including plasmapheresis) or had a
             transfusion of any blood product within 3 months prior to Screening

         17. Participated in another clinical research study with administration of investigational
             drug within 30 days prior to Randomization

         18. Potentially not be able to comply with the requirements of this clinical trial, to
             communicate effectively with study personnel, or is considered by the Investigator,
             for any reason, to be an unsuitable candidate for the study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/08/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>153</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/06/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>CMAX (a Division of IDT Australia Limited) - Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Pfizer</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Hospira, now a wholly owned subsidiary of Pfizer</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is for healthy participants. This study tests single dose of the research drug
      HSP-130 against two existing approved drugs United States - approved Neulasta and European
      Union-approved Neulasta.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02629289</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Pfizer CT.gov Call Center</name>
      <address>Pfizer</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>