<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4925">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/10/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/10/2014</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02283268</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Recombinant Von Willebrand Factor in Subjects With Severe Von Willebrand Disease Undergoing Surgery</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 3, Prospective, Multicenter Study to Evaluate Efficacy and Safety of Recombinant Von Willebrand Factor (rVWF) With or Without ADVATE in Elective Surgical Procedures in Subjects With Severe Von Willebrand Disease</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>2014-003575-38</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>071101</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Von Willebrand Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human Genetics and Inherited Disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other human genetics and inherited disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Clotting disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - Recombinant von Willebrand Factor (rVWF)

Experimental: Recombinant von Willebrand Factor (rVWF) - Surgery participants treated with Recombinant von Willebrand Factor (rVWF)


Other interventions: Recombinant von Willebrand Factor (rVWF)
rVWF will be administered by intravenous bolus infusion. Participants planned for major surgery will undergo a baseline pharmacokinetic assessment prior to surgery. The peri- and postoperative substitution regimen will be individualized according to the PK results, intensity and duration of the hemostatic challenge, and the institution´s standard of care.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Hemostatic Efficacy as Assessed by the Investigator (Hemophilia Physician) - Hemostatic efficacy will be rated on a scale of excellent - good - moderate - none.
Excellent: Intra-, and postoperative hemostasis achieved with rVWF with our without ADVATE was as good or better than that expected for the type of surgical procedure performed in a hemostatically normal subject.
Good: Intra-, and postoperative hemostasis achieved with rVWF with or without ADVATE was probably as good as that expected for the type of surgical procedure performed in a hemostatically normal subject.
Moderate: Intra-, and postoperative hemostasis with rVWF with or without ADVATE was clearly less than optimal for the type of procedure performed but was maintained without the need to change the rVWF concentrate.
None: Participant experienced uncontrolled bleeding that was the result of inadequate therapeutic response despite proper dosing, necessitating a change of rVWF concentrate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours after last peri-operative infusion or at completion of Day 14 (± 2 days) visit, whichever occurs earlier</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intraoperative Actual Versus Predicted Blood Loss as Assessed by the Operating Surgeon - The predicted blood loss will be estimated preoperatively by the operating surgeon based on a hemostatically normal individual of the same sex, age, stature and co-morbidities as the participant.
The actual blood loss will be assessed consisting of the estimated blood loss, including into swabs, towels and suction during the procedure, per the anesthesiologist's record.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 0 (at completion of surgery)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intraoperative Actual Blood Loss Relative to Predicted Blood Loss - Actual blood loss relative to predicted blood loss will be calculated as [Actual Blood loss (mL)] divided by [Predicted Blood Loss (mL) multiplied by 100.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 0 (at completion of surgery)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intraoperative Actual Versus Predicted Blood Loss Score as Assessed by the Operating Surgeon - Hemostatic efficacy will be rated on a scale of excellent - good - moderate - none.
Excellent: Intraoperative blood loss was less than or equal to the maximum blood loss expected for the type of procedure performed in a hemostatically normal subject (= 100%).
Good: Intraoperative blood loss was up to 50% more than the maximum expected blood loss for the type of procedure performed in a hemostatically normal subject (101-150%) Moderate: Intraoperative blood loss was more than 50% of the maximum expected blood loss for the type of procedure performed in a hemostatically normal subject (&gt;150%).
None: Uncontrolled hemorrhage that was the result of inadequate therapeutic response despite proper dosing, necessitating a change of clotting factor replacement regimen.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 0 (at completion of surgery)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intraoperative Hemostatic Efficacy Score as Assessed by the Operating Surgeon - Hemostatic efficacy will be rated on a scale of excellent - good - moderate - none.
Excellent: Intraoperative hemostasis achieved with rVWF with our without ADVATE was as good or better than that expected for the type of surgical procedure performed in a hemostatically normal subject.
Good: Intraoperative hemostasis achieved with rVWF with or without ADVATE was probably as good as that expected for the type of surgical procedure performed in a hemostatically normal subject.
Moderate: Intraoperative hemostasis with rVWF with or without ADVATE was clearly less than optimal for the type of procedure performed but was maintained without the need to change the rVWF concentrate.
None: Participant experienced uncontrolled bleeding that was the result of inadequate therapeutic response despite proper dosing, necessitating a change of rVWF concentrate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 0 (at completion of surgery)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Daily Intra- and Postoperative Weight-adjusted Dose of rVWF With or Without ADVATE</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily, from day of surgery through postoperative Day 14 (± 2 days)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Occurrence of Adverse Events - Treatment emergent adverse events (TEAEs) and treatment emergent serious adverse events (TESAEs) will be evaluated.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From first infusion of investigational product through study completion (ie, 14 (± 2) days post surgery)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Occurrence of Thrombotic Events - Treatment emergent adverse events (TEAEs) and treatment emergent serious adverse events (TESAEs) will be evaluated for thrombotic events.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From first infusion of investigational product through study completion (ie, 14 (± 2) days post surgery)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Occurrence of Severe Allergic Reactions (eg, Anaphylaxis) - Treatment emergent adverse events (TEAEs) and treatment emergent serious adverse events (TESAEs) will be evaluated for severe allergic reactions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From first infusion of investigational product through study completion (ie, 14 (± 2) days post surgery)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants Who Developed Inhibitory and Total Binding Antibodies to Von Willebrand Factor (VWF) and Inhibitory Antibodies to Factor VIII (FVIII) - Participants were treated with recombinant van Willebrand Factor (rVWF) with or without ADVATE.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Testing occurred throughout the study at screening, prior PK infusion, pre-surgery, post surgery in case of excessive bleeding or unexplained bleeding, at postoperative day 7 and at study completion visit (ie. 14 (± 2) days post surgery).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants Who Developed Antibodies to Chinese Hamster Ovary (CHO) Proteins, Mouse Immunoglobulin G (IgG) or Recombinant Furin (rFurin) - Participants were treated with recombinant van Willebrand Factor (rVWF) with or without ADVATE.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Testing occurred throughout the study at screening, prior PK infusion, pre-surgery, post surgery in case of excessive bleeding or unexplained bleeding, at postoperative day 7 and at study completion visit (ie. 14 (± 2) days post surgery).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetics: Area Under the Plasma Concentration Versus Time Curve From 0 to 72 Hours Post-infusion (AUC 0-72 h/Dose) - This assessment is only required for subjects undergoing major surgery. Subjects will receive a PK infusion at a dose of 50±5 IU/kg rVWF:RCo within 42 days prior to surgery. The area under the plasma concentration/time curve from 0 to 72 hours post-infusion will be computed using the linear trapezoidal rule. For the calculation of AUC(0-72h) the levels at 72 hours will be linearly interpolated/extrapolated from the 2 nearest sampling time points.
PK analysis was performed for the following analytes:
VWF Ristocetin Cofactor Activity (VWF:RCo), VWF Antigen Activity (VWF:Ag), VWF Collagen Binding Activity (VWF:CB), VWF Activity Measured INNOVANCE VWF Ac Assay (VWF:Ac), FVIII Coagulation Activity (FVIII:C)</outcome>
      <timepoint>PK measurements were done within 30 minutes pre-infusion, and post infusion at 30 (± 5) minutes, 60 (± 5) minutes, 6 (± 1) hours, 12 (± 1) hours, 24 (± 2) hours, 48 (± 2) hours and 72 (± 2) hours.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetics: Area Under the Plasma Concentration Versus Time Curve From Time 0 to Infinity (AUC 0-8 /Dose) - This assessment is only required for subjects undergoing major surgery. Subjects will receive a PK infusion at a dose of 50±5 IU/kg rVWF:RCo within 42 days prior to surgery. The area under the plasma concentration/time curve from time 0 to infinity and the area under the first moment curve from time 0 to infinity will be calculated as the sum of AUC or AUMC from time 0 to the time of last quantifiable concentration plus a tail area correction calculated as Ct/?z and Ct/?z(t+1/?z), respectively, where Ct is the last quantifiable concentration, t is the time of last quantifiable concentration and ?z is the terminal or disposition rate constant.
PK analysis was performed for the following analytes:
VWF Ristocetin Cofactor Activity (VWF:RCo), VWF Antigen Activity (VWF:Ag), VWF Collagen Binding Activity (VWF:CB), VWF Activity Measured INNOVANCE VWF Ac Assay (VWF:Ac), FVIII Coagulation Activity (FVIII:C)</outcome>
      <timepoint>PK measurements were done within 30 minutes pre-infusion, and post infusion at 30 (± 5) minutes, 60 (± 5) minutes, 6 (± 1) hours, 12 (± 1) hours, 24 (± 2) hours, 48 (± 2) hours and 72 (± 2) hours.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetics: Mean Residence Time (MRT) - This assessment is only required for subjects undergoing major surgery. Subjects will receive a PK infusion at a dose of 50±5 IU/kg rVWF:RCo within 42 days prior to surgery. Mean residence time will be calculated as area under the first moment curve from time 0 to infinity divided by the area under the curve time 0 to infinity minus T/2 where T is the duration of the infusion.
PK analysis was performed for the following analytes:
VWF Ristocetin Cofactor Activity (VWF:RCo), VWF Antigen Activity (VWF:Ag), VWF Collagen Binding Activity (VWF:CB), VWF Activity Measured INNOVANCE VWF Ac Assay (VWF:Ac)</outcome>
      <timepoint>PK measurements were done within 30 minutes pre-infusion, and post infusion at 30 (± 5) minutes, 60 (± 5) minutes, 6 (± 1) hours, 12 (± 1) hours, 24 (± 2) hours, 48 (± 2) hours and 72 (± 2) hours.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetics: Clearance (CL) - This assessment is only required for subjects undergoing major surgery. Subjects will receive a PK infusion at a dose of 50±5 IU/kg rVWF:RCo within 42 days prior to surgery. Clearance will be calculated as dose (IU/kg) divided by the area under the curve time 0 to infinity.
PK analysis was performed for the following analytes:
VWF Ristocetin Cofactor Activity (VWF:RCo), VWF Antigen Activity (VWF:Ag), VWF Collagen Binding Activity (VWF:CB), VWF Activity Measured INNOVANCE VWF Ac Assay (VWF:Ac)</outcome>
      <timepoint>PK measurements were done within 30 minutes pre-infusion, and post infusion at 30 (± 5) minutes, 60 (± 5) minutes, 6 (± 1) hours, 12 (± 1) hours, 24 (± 2) hours, 48 (± 2) hours and 72 (± 2) hours.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetics: Incremental Recovery (IR) - This assessment is only required for subjects undergoing major surgery. Subjects will receive a PK infusion at a dose of 50±5 IU/kg rVWF:RCo within 42 days prior to surgery. Incremental recovery will be calculated as (Cmax minus Cpreinfusion) divided by the dose (IU/kg) where kg refers to the body weight at the time of dosing and Cmax is the observed maximum concentration before correction for pre-infusion values.
PK analysis was performed for the following analytes:
VWF Ristocetin Cofactor Activity (VWF:RCo), VWF Antigen Activity (VWF:Ag), VWF Collagen Binding Activity (VWF:CB), VWF Activity Measured INNOVANCE VWF Ac Assay (VWF:Ac)</outcome>
      <timepoint>PK measurements were done within 30 minutes pre-infusion, and post infusion at 30 (± 5) minutes, 60 (± 5) minutes, 6 (± 1) hours, 12 (± 1) hours, 24 (± 2) hours, 48 (± 2) hours and 72 (± 2) hours.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetics: Elimination Phase Half-life (T1/2) - This assessment is only required for subjects undergoing major surgery. Subjects will receive a PK infusion at a dose of 50±5 IU/kg rVWF:RCo within 42 days prior to surgery. Terminal or disposition half-life (T1/2) will be calculated as ln2/?z where ?z is the terminal elimination rate constant as calculated in WinNonlin NCA using at least three quantifiable concentrations.
PK analysis was performed for the following analytes:
VWF Ristocetin Cofactor Activity (VWF:RCo), VWF Antigen Activity (VWF:Ag), VWF Collagen Binding Activity (VWF:CB), VWF Activity Measured INNOVANCE VWF Ac Assay (VWF:Ac)</outcome>
      <timepoint>PK measurements were done within 30 minutes pre-infusion, and post infusion at 30 (± 5) minutes, 60 (± 5) minutes, 6 (± 1) hours, 12 (± 1) hours, 24 (± 2) hours, 48 (± 2) hours and 72 (± 2) hours.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetics: Volume of Distribution at Steady State (Vss) - This assessment is only required for subjects undergoing major surgery. Subjects will receive a PK infusion at a dose of 50±5 IU/kg rVWF:RCo within 42 days prior to surgery. Vss will be calculated as the clearance multiplied with the mean residence time.
PK analysis was performed for the following analytes:
VWF Ristocetin Cofactor Activity (VWF:RCo), VWF Antigen Activity (VWF:Ag), VWF Collagen Binding Activity (VWF:CB), VWF Activity Measured INNOVANCE VWF Ac Assay (VWF:Ac)</outcome>
      <timepoint>PK measurements were done within 30 minutes pre-infusion, and post infusion at 30 (± 5) minutes, 60 (± 5) minutes, 6 (± 1) hours, 12 (± 1) hours, 24 (± 2) hours, 48 (± 2) hours and 72 (± 2) hours.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Diagnosis of severe von Willebrand disease (VWD) as listed below and elective surgical
             procedure planned

               1. Type 1 (Von Willebrand factor : Ristocetin cofactor activity (VWF:RCo) &lt;20
                  IU/dL), or

               2. Type 2A (as verified by multimer pattern), Type 2B (as diagnosed by genotype),
                  Type 2N (FVIII:C&lt;10% and historically documented genetics), Type 2M, or

               3. Type 3 (Von Willebrand factor antigen (VWF:Ag) = 3 IU/dL)

          -  VWD with a history of requiring substitution therapy with von Willebrand factor (VWF)
             concentrate to control bleeding

          -  If type 3 VWD (VWF Antigen /VWF:Ag = 3 IU/dL), participant has a medical history of at
             least 20 exposure days to VWF/FVIII coagulation factor concentrates (including
             cryoprecipitate or fresh frozen plasma)

          -  If type 1 or type 2 VWD, participant has a medical history of 5 exposure days or a
             past major surgery requiring VWF/FVIII coagulation factor concentrates (including
             cryoprecipitate or fresh frozen plasma)

          -  Participant is at least 18 years of age

          -  If female of childbearing potential, participant presents with a negative pregnancy
             test

          -  If applicable, participant agrees to employ adequate birth control measures for the
             duration of the study

          -  Participant is willing and able to comply with the requirements of the protocol</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Diagnosis of pseudo VWD or another hereditary or acquired coagulation disorder (eg,
             qualitative and quantitative platelet disorders or elevated prothrombin time [PT] /
             international normalized ratio [INR] &gt; 1.4)

          -  History or presence of a VWF inhibitor at screening

          -  History or presence of a factor VIII (FVIII) inhibitor with a titer = 0.4 BU
             (Nijmegen-modified Bethesda assay ) or = 0.6 BU (by Bethesda assay)

          -  Known hypersensitivity to any of the components of the study drugs, such as to mouse
             or hamster proteins

          -  Medical history of immunological disorders, excluding seasonal allergic
             rhinitis/conjunctivitis, mild asthma, food allergies or animal allergies

          -  Medical history of a thromboembolic event

          -  HIV positive with an absolute CD4 count &lt; 200/mm3

          -  Platelet count &lt; 100,000/mL

          -  Diagnosis of significant liver disease, as evidenced by, but not limited to, any of
             the following: serum alanine aminotransferase (ALT) 5 times the upper limit of normal;
             hypoalbuminemia; portal vein hypertension (eg. presence of otherwise unexplained
             splenomegaly, history of esophageal varices) or liver cirrhosis classified as Child B
             or C

          -  Diagnosis of renal disease, with a serum creatinine level = 2 .5mg/dL

          -  Participant has been treated with an immunomodulatory drug, excluding topical
             treatment (eg, ointments, nasal sprays), within 30 days prior to signing the informed
             consent

          -  Participant is pregnant or lactating at the time informed content is obtained

          -  Participant has participated in another clinical study involving an investigational
             product (IP), other than rVWF with or without ADVATE, or investigational device within
             30 days prior to enrollment or is scheduled to participate in another clinical study
             involving an IP or investigational device during the course of this study. However,
             eligible patients participating in the rVWF Prophylaxis Study (071301) may be
             enrolled.

          -  Progressive fatal disease and/or life expectancy of less than 3 months

          -  Participant is identified by the investigator as being unable or unwilling to
             cooperate with study procedures

          -  Participant suffers from a mental condition rendering him/her unable to understand the
             nature, scope and possible consequences of the study and/or evidence of an
             uncooperative attitude

          -  Participant is in prison or compulsory detention by regulatory and/or juridical order

          -  Participant is a member of the study team conducting this study or in a dependent
             relationship with one of the study team members. Dependent relationships include close
             relatives (ie, children, partner/spouse, siblings, parents) as well as employees.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/04/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>24</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>6/07/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>The Perth Blood Institute - Nedlands</hospital>
    <hospital>Fiona Stanley Hospital - Perth</hospital>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
    <postcode>6000 - Perth</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Colorado</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Georgia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Maryland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Massachusetts</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Jersey</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Oklahoma</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>South Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Wisconsin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Austria</country>
      <state>Vienna</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Ostrava</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Rheinland-Pfalz</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Firenze (Florence)</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Milano</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Rome</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Rotterdam</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Barnaul</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Kirov</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>A Coruña</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Valencia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Taichung</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Taipei</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>Izmir</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ukraine</country>
      <state>Lviv</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Devon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Greater London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Oxfordshire</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Baxalta now part of Shire</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of the study is to assess the efficacy and safety of recombinant von Willebrand
      factor (rVWF) with or without ADVATE in major and minor elective surgical procedures in adult
      patients with hereditary severe von Willebrand disease (VWD).</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02283268</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Arthur Sytkowski, MD</name>
      <address>Shire</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>