<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="1395">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/12/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/12/2006</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00408629</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy and Safety of Adalimumab in Subjects With Moderately to Severely Active Ulcerative Colitis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Multicenter, Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled Study of the Human Anti-TNF Monoclonal Antibody Adalimumab for the Induction and Maintenance of Clinical Remission in Subjects With Moderately to Severely Active Ulcerative Colitis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>2006-002782-40</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>M06-827</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Ulcerative Colitis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other inflammatory or immune system disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Inflammatory bowel disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - adalimumab
Other interventions - placebo

Experimental: adalimumab group - 

Experimental: placebo group - 


Other interventions: adalimumab
Prefilled syringe, 40 mg, 160 mg at Week 0, 80 mg at Week 2, and 40 mg every other week between Weeks 4 and 50.

Other interventions: placebo
Matching Placebo for prefilled syringe, 40 mg,

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of Participants Who Achieved Clinical Remission Per Mayo Score at Week 8 - Clinical remission per Mayo score is defined as a total Mayo score of at least 2 and no individual subscore greater than 1. The Mayo Score is a discrete ordinal scale ranging from 0 (normal or inactive disease) to 12 (severe disease) and is a composite of 4 subscores:
Stool Frequency Subscore (SFS), Rectal Bleeding Subscore (RBS), Endoscopy Subscore, and Physician's Global Assessment Subscore (PGA), each of which ranges from 0 (normal) to 3 (severe disease).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 8</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of Participants Who Achieved Clinical Remission Per Mayo Score at Week 52 - Clinical remission per Mayo score is defined as a total Mayo score of at least 2 and no individual subscore greater than 1. The Mayo Score is a discrete ordinal scale ranging from 0 (normal or inactive disease) to 12 (severe disease) and is a composite of 4 subscores:
SFS, RBS, Endoscopy Subscore, and PGA, each of which ranges from 0 (normal) to 3 (severe disease).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 52</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of Participants Who Achieved Sustained Clinical Remission Per Mayo Score at Both Week 8 and Week 52 - Clinical remission per Mayo score is defined as a total Mayo score of at least 2 and no individual subscore greater than 1. The Mayo Score is a discrete ordinal scale ranging from 0 (normal or inactive disease) to 12 (severe disease) and is a composite of 4 subscores:
SFS, RBS, Endoscopy Subscore, and PGA, each of which ranges from 0 (normal) to 3 (severe disease).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 8, Week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of Participants Who Achieved Clinical Response Per Mayo Score at Week 8 - Clinical response per Mayo score is defined as a decrease in Mayo score of at least 3 points and at least 30% from Baseline, plus either a decrease in rectal bleeding subscore (RBS) of at least 1 point from Baseline or an absolute RBS of 0 or 1. The Mayo Score is a discrete ordinal scale ranging from 0 (normal or inactive disease) to 12 (severe disease) and is a composite of 4 subscores:
SFS, RBS, Endoscopy Subscore, and PGA, each of which ranges from 0 (normal) to 3 (severe disease).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 8</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of Participants Who Achieved Clinical Response Per Mayo Score at Week 52 - Clinical response per Mayo score is defined as a decrease in Mayo score of at least 3 points and at least 30% from Baseline, plus either a decrease in RBS of at least 1 point from Baseline or an absolute RBS of 0 or 1. The Mayo Score is a discrete ordinal scale ranging from 0 (normal or inactive disease) to 12 (severe disease) and is a composite of 4 subscores:
SFS, RBS, Endoscopy Subscore, and PGA, each of which ranges from 0 (normal) to 3 (severe disease).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of Participants Who Achieved Sustained Clinical Response Per Mayo Score at Both Week 8 and Week 52 - Clinical response per Mayo score is defined as a decrease in Mayo score of at least 3 points and at least 30% from Baseline, plus either a decrease in RBS of at least 1 point from Baseline or an absolute RBS of 0 or 1. The Mayo Score is a discrete ordinal scale ranging from 0 (normal or inactive disease) to 12 (severe disease) and is a composite of 4 subscores:
SFS, RBS, Endoscopy Subscore, and PGA, each of which ranges from 0 (normal) to 3 (severe disease).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 8, Week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of Participants Who Achieved Mucosal Healing at Week 8 - Mucosal healing is defined as an Endoscopy Subscore of 0 or 1 as assessed by flexible sigmoidoscopy. Possible scores range from 0-3 as follows:
0 = Normal or inactive disease, 1 = Mild disease (erythema, decreased vascular pattern, mild friability), 2 = Moderate disease (marked erythema, absent vascular pattern, friability, erosions), 3 = Severe disease(spontaneous bleeding, ulceration).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 8</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of Participants Who Achieved Mucosal Healing at Week 52 - Mucosal healing is defined as an Endoscopy Subscore of 0 or 1 as assessed by flexible sigmoidoscopy. Possible scores range from 0-3 as follows:
0 = Normal or inactive disease, 1 = Mild disease (erythema, decreased vascular pattern, mild friability), 2 = Moderate disease (marked erythema, absent vascular pattern, friability, erosions), 3 = Severe disease(spontaneous bleeding, ulceration).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of Participants Who Achieved Sustained Mucosal Healing at Both Week 8 and Week 52 - Mucosal healing is defined as an Endoscopy Subscore of 0 or 1 as assessed by flexible sigmoidoscopy. Possible scores range from 0-3 as follows:
0 = Normal or inactive disease, 1 = Mild disease (erythema, decreased vascular pattern, mild friability), 2 = Moderate disease (marked erythema, absent vascular pattern, friability, erosions), 3 = Severe disease(spontaneous bleeding, ulceration).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 8, Week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of Participants Who Discontinued Corticosteroid Use Before Week 52 and Achieved Clinical Remission Per Mayo Score at Week 52 - Clinical remission per Mayo score is defined as a total Mayo score of at least 2 and no individual subscore greater than 1. The Mayo Score is a discrete ordinal scale ranging from 0 (normal or inactive disease) to 12 (severe disease) and is a composite of 4 subscores:
SFS, RBS, Endoscopy Subscore, and PGA, each of which ranges from 0 (normal) to 3 (severe disease).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to Week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of Participants With Physician's Global Assessment Subscore Indicative of Mild Disease (a Score of 0 or 1) at Week 8 - The PGA includes the 3 other subscores (SFS, RBS, and Endoscopy), the participant's daily record of abdominal discomfort and functional assessment, and other observations such as physical findings and the participant's performance status. Possible scores range from 0-3 as follows:
0 = Normal (other subscores are 0), 1 = Mild disease (other subscores are mostly 1), 2 = Moderate disease (other subscores are 1 to 2), 3 = Severe disease (other subscores are 2 to 3).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 8</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of Participants With Stool Frequency Subscore Indicative of Mild Disease (a Score of 0 or 1) at Week 8 - SFS ranges from 0-3 as follows:
0 = Normal number of stools for this participant, 1 = 1-2 stools more than normal, 2 = 3-4 stools more than normal, 3 = 5 or more stools more than normal. The participant served as his/her own control.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 8</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of Participants With Rectal Bleeding Subscore Indicative of Mild Disease (a Score of 0 or 1) at Week 8 - RBS ranges from 0-3 as follows:
0 = no blood seen, 1 = streaks of blood with stool less than half the time, 2 = obvious blood with stool most of the time, 3 = blood alone passed</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 8</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of Participants Who Discontinued Corticosteroid Use for At Least 90 Days and Achieved Clinical Remission Per Mayo Score at Week 52 - Clinical remission per Mayo score is defined as a total Mayo score of at least 2 and no individual subscore greater than 1. The Mayo Score is a discrete ordinal scale ranging from 0 (normal or inactive disease) to 12 (severe disease) and is a composite of 4 subscores:
SFS, RBS, Endoscopy Subscore, and PGA, each of which ranges from 0 (normal) to 3 (severe disease).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to Week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of Participants Who Discontinued Corticosteroid Use and Achieved Clinical Remission Per Mayo Score (Sustained) at Both Weeks 32 and 52 - Clinical remission per Mayo score is defined as a total Mayo score of at least 2 and no individual subscore greater than 1. The Mayo Score is a discrete ordinal scale ranging from 0 (normal or inactive disease) to 12 (severe disease) and is a composite of 4 subscores:
SFS, RBS, Endoscopy Subscore, and PGA, each of which ranges from 0 (normal) to 3 (severe disease).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 32, Week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of Inflammatory Bowel Disease Questionnaire Responders at Week 52 - Response per the Inflammatory Bowel Disease Questionnaire (IBDQ) was defined as at least a 16-point increase from Baseline in total IBDQ score. The IBDQ is a 32-item questionnaire consisting of 4 dimensions: bowel-related symptoms, systemic function, social function, and emotional status. The responses to questions within each domain range from 1 (significant impairment) to 7 (no impairment), with total score ranging from 32 (very poor) to 224 (perfect health-related quality of life).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of Inflammatory Bowel Disease Questionnaire Responders at Week 8 - Response per the Inflammatory Bowel Disease Questionnaire (IBDQ) was defined as at least a 16-point increase from Baseline in total IBDQ score. The IBDQ is a 32-item questionnaire consisting of 4 dimensions: bowel-related symptoms, systemic function, social function, and emotional status. The responses to questions within each domain range from 1 (significant impairment) to 7 (no impairment), with total score ranging from 32 (very poor) to 224 (perfect health-related quality of life).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 8</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Participants &gt;=18 years of age and in good health (Investigator discretion) with a
             recent stable medical history

          2. Diagnosis of UC for greater than 90 days prior to Baseline

          3. Diagnosis of active UC confirmed by colonoscopy with biopsy or flexible sigmoidoscopy
             with biopsy during the Screening Period, with exclusion of infection

          4. Active UC with a Mayo score of 6 to 12 points and endoscopy subscore of 2 to 3 points,
             despite concurrent treatment with at least 1 of the following (oral corticosteroids or
             immunosuppressants or both as defined below):

               -  Stable oral corticosteroid dose (prednisone &gt;= 20 mg/day or equivalent) for at
                  least 14 days prior to Baseline or maintenance, corticosteroid dose (prednisone &lt;
                  20 mg/day or equivalent) for at least 40 days prior to Baseline

             and/or

               -  At least a 90 day course of azathioprine (AZA) or 6-mercaptopurine (6-MP) prior
                  to Baseline, with a dose of AZA &gt;= 1.5 mg/kg/day or 6-MP &gt;= 1 mg/kg/day (rounded
                  to the nearest available tablet formulation), or a dose that is the highest
                  tolerated by the participant (e.g., due to leukopenia, elevated liver enzymes,
                  nausea) during that time. Participant must be on a stable dose for at least 28
                  days prior to Baseline.

             Concurrent therapy was not required for participants who were previously treated with
             corticosteroids or immunosuppressants (AZA or 6-MP) during the past 5 years and in the
             judgment of the Investigator have failed to respond to, or could not tolerate, their
             treatment.

          5. Participants may have been included if they had previously used an anti-tumor necrosis
             factor (TNF) agent (except ADA) and discontinued its use due to a loss of response or
             intolerance to the agent.

          6. Had to be able to self-administer or had caregiver who could reliably administer
             subcutaneous (SC) injections.

          7. Had to be able and willing to give written informed consent and to comply with the
             requirements of the study protocol.

          8. Female had to be either not of childbearing potential, defined as postmenopausal for
             at least 1 year or surgically sterile (bilateral tubal ligation, bilateral
             oophorectomy, or hysterectomy), or of childbearing potential and practicing an
             approved method of birth control throughout the study and for 150 days after the last
             dose of study drug. Examples of approved methods of birth control included the
             following:

               -  Condoms, sponge, foams, jellies, diaphragm, or intrauterine device

               -  Oral, parenteral, intravaginal contraceptives for 90 days prior to study drug
                  administration

               -  A vasectomized partner The results of the serum pregnancy test performed at the
                  Screening Visit and urine pregnancy test performed at the Baseline Visit must
                  have been negative.

          9. Judged to be in generally good health as determined by the Investigator</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. History of subtotal colectomy with ileorectostomy or colectomy with ileoanal pouch,
             Koch pouch, or ileostomy for UC, or planned bowel surgery.

          2. Received previous treatment with ADA or previous participation in an ADA clinical
             study.

          3. Received cyclosporine, tacrolimus, or mycophenolate mofetil within 30 days of
             Baseline.

          4. Received intravenous (IV) corticosteroids within 14 days of Screening or during the
             Screening Period.

          5. Received therapeutic enema or suppository, other than required for endoscopy, within
             14 days of the Screening endoscopy and during the remainder of the Screening Period.

          6. Current diagnosis of fulminant colitis and/or toxic megacolon.

          7. Disease limited to the rectum (ulcerative proctitis).

          8. Current diagnosis of indeterminate colitis.

          9. Current diagnosis and/or history of Crohns disease (CD).

         10. Currently receiving total parenteral nutrition.

         11. Used aminosalicylates for &lt; 90 days before Baseline or not on a stable dose for at
             least 28 days before Baseline or discontinued use within 28 days of Baseline.

         12. Positive Clostridium difficile stool assay.

         13. Previously used infliximab or any anti-TNF agent within 56 days of Baseline.

         14. Previously used infliximab or any anti-TNF agent without clinical response at any time
             ("primary non-responder") unless subject experienced a treatment-limiting reaction.

         15. Infections requiring treatment with IV antibiotics, antivirals, or antifungals within
             30 days of Baseline or oral antibiotics, antivirals, or antifungals within 14 days of
             Baseline.

         16. History of malignancy other than a successfully treated non-metastatic cutaneous
             squamous cell or basal cell carcinoma and/or localized carcinoma in situ of the
             cervix. If the Screening colonoscopy/flexible sigmoidoscopy showed evidence of
             dysplasia or a malignancy, subject was not to be enrolled in the study.

         17. History of listeria, histoplasmosis, chronic or active hepatitis B infection, human
             immunodeficiency virus (HIV), immunodeficiency syndrome, central nervous system
             demyelinating disease, or untreated tuberculosis (TB).

         18. Female subject who was pregnant or breast-feeding or considering becoming pregnant
             during the study (there should be at least 150 days between the last dose of study
             drug and either conception or initiation of breast-feeding in women of childbearing
             potential).

         19. Poorly controlled medical condition(s), such as uncontrolled diabetes, unstable
             ischemic heart disease, moderate to severe congestive heart failure (CHF), recent
             cerebrovascular accident, and any other condition, which in the opinion of the
             investigator, put the subject at risk by participation in the protocol.

         20. Received any investigational agent within 30 days or 5 half lives prior to Baseline
             (whichever was longer).

         21. History of clinically significant drug or alcohol abuse during the past year.

         22. Known hypersensitivity to the excipients of ADA as stated in the label.

         23. Any prior exposure to Tysabri® (natalizumab), or Orencia® (abatacept) or any other
             biological therapy [other than Kineret® (anakinra) and anti-TNF agents].

         24. Currently taking both budesonide and prednisone (or equivalent) simultaneously.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2>The people administering the treatment/s</masking2>
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/11/2006</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>518</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/03/2010</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,QLD,SA,VIC,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Site Ref # / Investigator 13722 - Garran</hospital>
    <hospital>Site Ref # / Investigator 16141 - Bankstown</hospital>
    <hospital>Site Ref # / Investigator 13723 - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>Site Ref # / Investigator 10706 - Bedford Park</hospital>
    <hospital>Site Ref # / Investigator 14882 - Box Hill</hospital>
    <hospital>Site Ref # / Investigator 9002 - Malvern</hospital>
    <hospital>Site Ref # / Investigator 10704 - Fremantle</hospital>
    <postcode>2605 - Garran</postcode>
    <postcode>NSW 2200 - Bankstown</postcode>
    <postcode>4029 - Herston</postcode>
    <postcode>SA 5042 - Bedford Park</postcode>
    <postcode>3128 - Box Hill</postcode>
    <postcode>3144 - Malvern</postcode>
    <postcode>6160 - Fremantle</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Colorado</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Connecticut</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Georgia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Illinois</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Kansas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Maryland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Michigan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Minnesota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Missouri</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Oklahoma</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Pennsylvania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>South Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Tennessee</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Utah</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Washington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Wisconsin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Argentina</country>
      <state>Buenos Aires</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Austria</country>
      <state>Vienna</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Bonheiden</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Brussels</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Ghent</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Leuven</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>British Columbia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Quebec</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czech Republic</country>
      <state>Ceske Budejovice</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czech Republic</country>
      <state>Hradec Kravlove 12</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czech Republic</country>
      <state>Olomouc</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czech Republic</country>
      <state>Prague 4</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czech Republic</country>
      <state>Prague 5</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Denmark</country>
      <state>Hvidovre</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Denmark</country>
      <state>Odense C</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Clichy</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Lille Cedex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Pessac Cedex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Toulouse</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Hamburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Magdeburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Minden</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Muenster</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Munich</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Regensburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Budapest</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Debrecen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Gyula</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Miskoic</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Miskolc</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Kfar Saba</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Petah Tikva</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Tel Aviv</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Christchurch</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Hamilton</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Norway</country>
      <state>Gjovik</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Norway</country>
      <state>Oslo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Norway</country>
      <state>Tromso</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Norway</country>
      <state>Trondheim</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Lodz</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Warsaw</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Wroclaw</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <state>Faro</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <state>Lisbon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state>Basel</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state>Bern</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state>Zurich</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Abbott</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This was a Phase 3, multicenter, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial designed
      to evaluate the efficacy and safety of the human anti-tumor necrosis factor (TNF) monoclonal
      antibody adalimumab (ADA) in patients with moderately to severely active ulcerative colitis
      (UC).</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00408629</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Roopal B Thakkar, M.D.</name>
      <address>Abbott</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>