<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4865">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/06/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/06/2014</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02385214</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>MelmarT Melanoma Margins Trial Investigating 1cm v 2cm Wide Excision Margins for Primary Cutaneous Melanoma</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase III, Multi-centre, Multi-national Randomised Control Trial Investigating 1cm v 2cm Wide Excision Margins for Primary Cutaneous Melanoma</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>MelmarT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>ANZMTG 03.12</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cutaneous Melanoma by AJCC V7 Stage</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Malignant melanoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: surgery - Wide Local Excision = 1cm Margin
Treatment: surgery - Wide Local Excision = 2cm Margin

Experimental: Arm A Wide Local Excision = 1cm Margin - ARM A: Experimental Arm Wide Local Excision = 1cm Margin + Sentinel Lymph Node Biopsy
+/- Reconstruction

Active Comparator: Arm B Wide Local Excision = 2cm Margin - ARM B:Control Arm Wide Local Excision = 2cm Margin + Sentinel Lymph Node Biopsy
+/- Reconstruction


Treatment: surgery: Wide Local Excision = 1cm Margin
A wide local excision involves removing an extra "safety margin" of healthy skin surrounding the original melanoma site to ensure that any remaining scattered melanoma tumour cells are removed that may have been left behind after the first initial biopsy/surgery.

Treatment: surgery: Wide Local Excision = 2cm Margin
A wide local excision involves removing an extra "safety margin" of healthy skin surrounding the original melanoma site to ensure that any remaining scattered melanoma tumour cells are removed that may have been left behind after the first initial biopsy/surgery.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Local Melanoma Recurrence (Melanoma Specific Survival) - Time from randomisation to clinically, histologically or radiologically confirmed local recurrence of melanoma including satellite lesions and in transit metastases to regional draining lymph nodes.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0-120 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Recurrence-Free Survival - Time from randomisation to any clinical, histological or radiologically confirmed melanoma recurrence or death from any cause.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0-120 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>QoL and neuropathic pain assessments Neuropathic Pain (PainDetect) - Quality of Life</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3, 6 12, 24 &amp; 60 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Survival - Time from randomisation to death from any cause.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0-120 Months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse events - An Adverse Event (AE) is any untoward medical occurrence in a participant administered a treatment which does not necessarily have a causal relationship with the treatment. An AE can therefore be any unfavourable or unintended sign (including an abnormal laboratory finding), symptom, or disease temporally associated with the treatment timing, whether or not considered related to the treatment. An AE is any adverse change (developing or worsening) from the participant's pre-treatment condition, including intercurrent illness.
AEs and any pre-existing medical conditions will be recorded at the Baseline assessment and routinely at Follow Up, until the participant completes the study, withdraws or dies.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 1 year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Surgery related adverse events - The following surgical adverse events will be recorded from the time of trial treatment to 30 days following the wide excision (inclusive):
wound separation
seroma/haematoma at wide local excision site
haemorrhage
infection
skin graft failure
necrosis of flap used for reconstruction
deep venous thrombosis
urinary tract infection
pneumonia
cardiac complications</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 30 days from randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health System Resource Use - All hospitalisations and other interventions will be captured in order to measure resource use.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3, 6, 12, 24 and 60 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Patients must have a primary invasive cutaneous melanoma of Breslow thickness greater
             than 1 millimetre as determined by diagnostic biopsy (narrow excision, incision or
             punch biopsy) and subsequent histopathological analysis.

          2. Patients must have had the invasive primary completely excised, including any in situ
             component but excluding melanocytic atypia, with a narrow margin, either in one stage
             or more than one stage in the case where an incision or punch biopsy has previously
             been performed. This information, including measured margins of lateral and deep
             clearance must be documented on the pathology report.

          3. Must have a primary melanoma that is cutaneous (including head, neck, trunk,
             extremity, scalp, palm, sole).

          4. An uninterrupted 2cm margin must be technically feasible around biopsy scar or primary
             melanoma.

          5. Randomisation and the primary study intervention, including staging sentinel node
             biopsy, must be completed by 120 days of original diagnosis.

          6. Patients must be 18 years or older at time of consent.

          7. Patient must be able to give informed consent and comply with the treatment protocol
             and follow-up plan.

          8. Life expectancy of at least 10 years from the time of diagnosis, not considering the
             melanoma in question, as determined by the PI.

          9. Patients must have an ECOG performance score between 0 and 1.

         10. A survivor of prior cancer is eligible provided that ALL of the following criteria are
             met and documented:

               -  The patient has undergone potentially curative therapy for all prior
                  malignancies,

               -  There has been no evidence of recurrence of any prior malignancies for at least
                  FIVE years (except for successfully treated cervical or non-melanoma skin cancer
                  with no evidence of recurrence), and

               -  The patient is deemed by their treating physician to be at low risk of recurrence
                  from previous malignancies.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Uncertain diagnosis of melanoma i.e. so-called 'melanocytic lesion of unknown
             malignant potential'.

          2. Patient has already undergone wide local excision at the site of the primary index
             lesion.

          3. Patient unable or ineligible to undergo staging sentinel lymph node biopsy of the
             primary index lesion.

          4. Desmoplastic or neurotropic melanoma.

          5. Microsatellitosis as per AJCC 2009 definition

          6. Subungual melanoma

          7. Patient has already undergone a local flap reconstruction of the defect after excision
             of the primary and determination of an accurate excision margin is impossible.

          8. History of previous or concurrent (i.e., second primary) invasive melanoma.

          9. Melanoma located distal to the metacarpophalangeal joint, on the tip of the nose, the
             eyelids or on the ear, mucous membranes or internal viscera.

         10. Physical, clinical, radiographic or pathologic evidence of satellite, in-transit,
             regional, or distant metastatic melanoma.

         11. Patient has undergone surgery on a separate occasion to clear the lymph nodes of the
             probable draining lymphatic field, including sentinel lymph node biopsy, of the index
             melanoma.

         12. Any additional solid tumour or hematologic malignancy during the past 5 years except
             T1 skin lesions of squamous cell carcinoma, basal cell carcinoma, or uterine/cervical
             cancer.

         13. Melanoma-related operative procedures not corresponding to criteria described in the
             protocol.

         14. Planned adjuvant radiotherapy to the primary melanoma site after Wide Local Excision
             is not permitted as part of the protocol and any patients given this treatment would
             be excluded from the study.

         15. History of organ transplantation.

         16. Oral or parenteral immunosuppressive agents (not topical or inhaled steroids) at any
             time during study participation or within 6 months prior to enrolment.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/12/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>400</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/12/2029</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Melanoma Institute Australia - Poche Centre - North Sydney</hospital>
    <hospital>Gold Coast Melanom Clinic - Coolangatta</hospital>
    <hospital>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre Division of Cancer Surgery - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Alfred Hospital - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>2060 - North Sydney</postcode>
    <postcode>4225 - Coolangatta</postcode>
    <postcode>3002 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>England</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Mersyside</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Oxford</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Bristol</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Essex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Exeter</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Leeds</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Norwich</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australia and New Zealand Melanoma Trials Group</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre, Australia</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Norfolk and Norwich University Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Patients with a primary invasive melanoma are recommended to undergo excision of the primary
      lesion with a wide margin. There is evidence that less radical margins of excision may be
      just as safe. This is a randomised controlled trial of 1 cm versus 2 cm margin of excision of
      the primary lesion for adult patients with a primary invasive cutaneous melanomas &gt;=1mm thick
      to determine differences in the rate of local recurrence and melanoma specific survival. A
      reduction in margins is expected to improve quality of life in patients</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02385214</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Marc Moncrieff</name>
      <address>Norfolk &amp; Norwich University Hospital</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>ANZMTG Coordinator</name>
      <address />
      <phone>61 2 9911 7200</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>anzmtg0312@melanoma.org.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>