<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5746">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/07/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/07/2015</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02509624</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pharmacokinetics of GS-4997 in Adults With Normal and Impaired Hepatic Function</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 1, Open-Label, Parallel-Group, Single Dose Study to Evaluate the Pharmacokinetics of GS-4997 in Subjects With Normal and Impaired Hepatic Function</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>GS-US-223-1018</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Diabetic Kidney Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - GS-4997

Experimental: Mild hepatic impairment (Class A) - Participants with mild hepatic impairment and matched healthy controls will receive a single dose of GS-4997 on Day 1.

Experimental: Moderate hepatic impairment (Class B) - Participants with moderate hepatic impairment and matched healthy controls will receive a single dose of GS-4997 on Day 1.

Experimental: Severe hepatic impairment (Class C) - Participants with severe hepatic impairment and matched healthy controls will receive a single dose of GS-4997 on Day 1.


Treatment: drugs: GS-4997
GS-4997 6 mg tablet administered orally in a fed state

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Area under the concentration-time curve (AUC) for GS-4997 and its metabolite GS-607509 - AUC is defined as the concentration of drug over time.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose and 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 36, 48, 72, 96, and 120 hours postdose</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximum observed plasma concentration (Cmax) of GS-4997 and its metabolite GS-607509</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose and 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 36, 48, 72, 96, and 120 hours postdose</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of adverse events - The percentage of participants experiencing any adverse event will be summarized.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 31 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of laboratory abnormalities - The percentage of participants experiencing any clinically significant laboratory abnormality will be summarized.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 31 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All individuals:

          -  Body mass index (BMI) from 18 to 40 kg/m^2, inclusive

          -  Creatinine clearance (CrCl) = 60 mL/min (using the Cockcroft-Gault method) based on
             serum creatinine and body weight

        Individuals with impaired hepatic function:

          -  Aside from hepatic insufficiency, must be sufficiently healthy for study participation
             based upon screening evaluations.

          -  Must have diagnosis of chronic (&gt; 6 months), stable hepatic impairment with no
             clinically significant change in hepatic status within the 3 months (90 days) prior to
             study drug administration (Day 1).

          -  Individuals with severe hepatic impairment must have a score on the
             Child-Pugh-Turcotte scale of 10-15 at screening.

          -  Individuals with moderate hepatic impairment must have a score on the
             Child-Pugh-Turcotte scale of 7-9 at screening.

          -  Individuals with mild hepatic impairment must have a score on the Child-Pugh-Turcotte
             scale of 5-6 at screening.

        Healthy individuals (matched control):

          -  Must be in good health based upon screening evaluations.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>All individuals:

          -  Pregnant or lactating females

          -  Have received any investigational compound or device within 30 days prior to study
             dosing

          -  Current alcohol or substance abuse

          -  A positive test result for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV-1/2) antibody

          -  Have poor venous access that limits phlebotomy

          -  Have been treated with systemic steroids, anti-HIV agents, immunosuppressant
             therapies, or chemotherapeutic agents within 3 months prior to screening or expected
             to receive these agents during the study (eg, corticosteroids, immunoglobulins, and
             other immune- or cytokine-based therapies) that would be contraindicated for other
             exclusion criteria.

          -  Significant serious skin disease, such as but not limited to rash, food allergy,
             eczema, psoriasis, or urticaria

          -  Significant drug sensitivity or drug allergy (such as anaphylaxis or hepatoxicity)

          -  Unstable cardiac disease, including history of myocardial infarction within 1 year of
             screening, recurrent episodes of ventricular tachycardia despite appropriate medical
             therapy, decompensated congestive heart failure, or dilated cardiomyopathy with left
             ventricular ejection fraction &lt; 40%), or a family history of Long QT Syndrome, or
             unexplained death in an otherwise healthy individual between the ages of 1 and 30
             years.

          -  Syncope, palpitations, or unexplained dizziness

          -  Implanted defibrillator or pacemaker.

          -  Severe peptic ulcer disease, severe gastroesophageal reflux disease, or other severe
             gastric acid hypersecretory conditions.

          -  Medical or surgical treatment that permanently alters gastric absorption (eg, gastric
             or intestinal surgery). A history of cholecystectomy is not exclusionary.

          -  History of prior allogeneic bone marrow progenitor cell or solid organ
             transplantation.

          -  Currently registered on an organ transplantation list.

          -  History of bleeding from esophageal varices within 90 days prior to Admission (Day
             -1).

          -  Use of strong CYP3A4 inhibitors (eg, indinavir, nelfinavir, ritonavir, clarithromycin,
             itraconazole, ketoconazole, nefazodone, saquinavir, suboxone, telithromycin,
             atazanavir) and strong CYP3A4 inducers (eg, carbamazepine, rifampin, phenytoin and St.
             John's wort), within 28 days prior to study drug administration (Day 1).

          -  Consumption of grapefruit juice, grapefruits, and Seville orange juice within 2 weeks
             prior to study drug administration (Day 1).

          -  Recent significant changes in the use of nicotine or nicotine containing products

        Individuals with impaired hepatic function:

          -  Aside from hepatic insufficiency, serious or active medical or psychiatric illness
             that, in the opinion of the investigator, would interfere with treatment, assessment,
             or compliance with the protocol.

          -  Chronic hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection, defined as a positive test for hepatitis B
             surface antigen (HBsAg), unless the patient has been treated with a nucleos(t)ide
             analog (eg, tenofovir or entecavir) for at least 6 months and the HBV DNA by
             polymerase chain reaction (PCR) assay has been persistently undetectable for at least
             6 months.

          -  Positive test for drugs of abuse, including alcohol at screening or on Day
             -1/check-in, with the exception of opioids and tetrahydrocannabinol (THC, marijuana)
             under prescription and investigator verification for pain management. Individuals who
             screen positive for benzodiazepines may be allowed if prescribed under the care of a
             physician and after review by investigator and Sponsor.

          -  Requires paracentesis &gt; 1 time per month.

          -  Individuals with hepatic impairment with co-morbid diseases not associated with
             hepatic impairment requiring medication(s) must be taking the medication(s) without a
             change in dose for &gt; 3 months prior to screening.

          -  Changes in concomitant medications or dosage used to treat symptoms of hepatic
             impairment or associated co-morbid conditions that could lead to clinically
             significant changes in medical conditions during the course of the study that would
             affect the ability to interpret potential drug-drug interactions within 28 days prior
             to dosing.

        Healthy individuals (matched control):

          -  A positive test result for hepatitis C virus (HCV) antibody, hepatitis B surface
             antigen (HBsAg), or hepatitis B core antibody (anti-HBc)

          -  Positive test for drugs of abuse, including alcohol at screening or on Day
             -1/check-in.

          -  Have any serious or active medical or psychiatric illness (including depression)
             which, in the opinion of the investigator, would interfere with treatment, assessment,
             or compliance with the protocol.

          -  History of liver disease.

          -  Have taken any prescription medications or over-the-counter medications including
             herbal products within 28 days of commencing study drug dosing with the exception of
             vitamins, acetaminophen, ibuprofen, and hormonal contraceptive medications.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/08/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>60</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/12/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Colorado</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Minnesota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Gilead Sciences</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will evaluate the pharmacokinetics (PK), safety, and tolerability of GS-4997 in
      adults with impaired hepatic function relative to matched, healthy controls. Each participant
      in the control group will be matched to a participant with impaired hepatic function by age
      (± 10 years), gender, and body mass index (± 20%).</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02509624</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Thomas O'Riordan, MD</name>
      <address>Gilead Sciences</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>