<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="1112">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/03/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/03/2006</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00308152</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Intravenous Saline Pre-hydration in Patients Undergoing Outpatient Colonoscopy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised, Controlled Trial of Intravenous Saline Pre-hydration in Patients Undergoing Outpatient Colonoscopy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>11/05.851</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Colonic Diseases</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Infusion of 1 litre of normal saline before colonoscopy

No Intervention: Control - Observation only

Active Comparator: Active - Infusion of 1 liter normal saline before sedated colonoscopy


Treatment: drugs: Infusion of 1 litre of normal saline before colonoscopy
Prehydration with normal saline

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The number of subjects with documented hypotension (systolic blood pressure [BP] = 95 mmHg for 1 or more automatic BP measures taken at 3 minute intervals), during colonoscopy or the recovery period</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Colonoscopy completion rates. Raw completion rates, with no allowance for failed bowel preparation or technical difficulties, will be used.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The number of subjects reaching criteria for discharge at 30 minutes after arrival in the recovery area</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comfort and satisfaction scores: discomfort during colonoscopy, discomfort after colonoscopy, satisfaction with sedation, overall satisfaction</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time taken to resume normal activities</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Where relevant, adverse events such as post-procedure nausea, syncope, and prolonged recovery time, will be recorded in both arms of the study for comparison.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Aged 18 or older

          -  Able to provide informed consent

          -  Booked for outpatient colonoscopy, where appointment has been generated by
             Gastroenterology Unit bookings staff.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Booked for anaesthetist-supervised colonoscopy because of previous sedation
             difficulties or significant co-morbidity (American Society of Anesthesiology Class III
             or IV)

          -  Subjects requiring dialysis

          -  Subjects receiving parenteral nutrition

          -  Subjects with current congestive cardiac failure

          -  Subjects with conditions preventing placement and accurate use of the automatic blood
             pressure cuff on the left arm, such as morbid obesity or lymphoedema</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/02/2006</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/05/2008</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Canberra Hospital - Garran</hospital>
    <postcode>2605 - Garran</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Canberra Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Colonoscopy and sedation are frequently accompanied by hypotension, which reduces the amount
      of sedation able to be employed. Blood pressure is restored by the infusion of intravenous
      normal saline. Prophylactic infusion of normal saline may enhance the colonoscopy completion
      rate, and patient comfort during colonoscopy and during the recovery from colonoscopy.

      The investigators propose randomising consenting adult patients attending outpatient
      colonoscopy to one of two treatment arms:

      (i) A control arm

      (ii) A treatment arm, with pre-hydration with an infusion of 1.0 litre of normal saline
      immediately prior to colonoscopy.

      Outcome measures include colonoscopy completion rates, hypotension during or after
      colonoscopy, and patient ratings of comfort and satisfaction.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00308152</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Rex DK, Heuss LT, Walker JA, Qi R. Trained registered nurses/endoscopy teams can administer propofol safely for endoscopy. Gastroenterology. 2005 Nov;129(5):1384-91.
Heuss LT, Schnieper P, Drewe J, Pflimlin E, Beglinger C. Risk stratification and safe administration of propofol by registered nurses supervised by the gastroenterologist: a prospective observational study of more than 2000 cases. Gastrointest Endosc. 2003 May;57(6):664-71.
Schrier RW. Body fluid volume regulation in health and disease: a unifying hypothesis. Ann Intern Med. 1990 Jul 15;113(2):155-9. Review.
Ristikankare M, Julkunen R, Laitinen T, Wang SX, Heikkinen M, Janatuinen E, Hartikainen J. Effect of conscious sedation on cardiac autonomic regulation during colonoscopy. Scand J Gastroenterol. 2000 Sep;35(9):990-6.
Chen SC, Rex DK. Review article: registered nurse-administered propofol sedation for endoscopy. Aliment Pharmacol Ther. 2004 Jan 15;19(2):147-55. Review.
Sipe BW, Rex DK, Latinovich D, Overley C, Kinser K, Bratcher L, Kareken D. Propofol versus midazolam/meperidine for outpatient colonoscopy: administration by nurses supervised by endoscopists. Gastrointest Endosc. 2002 Jun;55(7):815-25. Erratum in: Gastrointest Endosc 2002 Aug;56(2):324.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Douglas R Taupin, MBBS, PhD</name>
      <address>The Canberra Hospital</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>