<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5317">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/10/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/10/2015</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02650674</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Determination of the Glycaemic Index and Insulinaemic Index Values of Five Cereal Products</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Determination of the Glycaemic Index and Insulinaemic Index Values of Five Cereal Products</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>KBE043</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Metabolic Disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - Product A: NP-0148
Other interventions - Glucose solution
Other interventions - Product B: NP-0149
Other interventions - Product C: NP-0150
Other interventions - Product D: NP-0151
Other interventions - Product E: NP-0152

Experimental: Product A: NP-0148 - Cereal product belVita Milk &amp; Cereals - High in SDS

Experimental: Product B: NP-0149 - Cereal product belVita Honey &amp; Nuts - High in SDS

Experimental: Product C: NP-0150 - Cereal product belVita Mixed Berry - High in SDS

Experimental: Product D: NP-0151 - Cereal product Kellogg's Corn Flakes - Low in SDS - Low in fat

Experimental: Product E: NP-0152 - Cereal product Kellogg's Trésor Duo Choco - Low in SDS

Experimental: Glucose reference - Glucose solution performed on three occasions


Other interventions: Product A: NP-0148
Portions of cereal product calculated to provide 50 g of available carbohydrates will be served with 250 mL water.

Other interventions: Glucose solution
Glucose solution providing 50 g of available carbohydrates in 250 ml of water. This will be performed 3 times

Other interventions: Product B: NP-0149
Portions of cereal product calculated to provide 50 g of available carbohydrates will be served with 250 mL water.

Other interventions: Product C: NP-0150
Portions of cereal product calculated to provide 50 g of available carbohydrates will be served with 250 mL water.

Other interventions: Product D: NP-0151
Portions of cereal product calculated to provide 50 g of available carbohydrates will be served with 250 mL water.

Other interventions: Product E: NP-0152
Portions of cereal product calculated to provide 50 g of available carbohydrates will be served with 250 mL water.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Glycaemic index values of five cereal products - Determination of GI in both Caucasian and Asian subjects</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 hours after food consumption</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Glycaemic response assessed by the glycemic index (GI) values of five cereal products - Determination of GI in the global population</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 hours after food consumption</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Glycaemic response assessed by the postprandial changes in glycaemia over 2 hours (iAUC0-120) after consumption of the test products - This parameter will be analyzed first in both Caucasian and Asian populations and second globally</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 hours after food consumption</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Glycaemic response assessed by the kinetic of glycemia over the 120 minutes - This parameter will be analyzed first in both Caucasian and Asian populations and second globally</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 hours after food consumption</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Glycaemic response assessed by the peak value of glycemia - This parameter will be analyzed first in both Caucasian and Asian populations and second globally</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 hours after food consumption</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Glycaemic response assessed by the delta value between baseline and peak values of glycemia - This parameter will be analyzed first in both Caucasian and Asian populations and second globally</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 hours after food consumption</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Insulinaemic response assessed by the insulinemic index (II) values of five cereal products - This parameter will be analyzed first in both Caucasian and Asian populations and second globally</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 hours after food consumption</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Insulinaemic response assessed by the postprandial changes in insulinemia over 2 hours (iAUC0-120) after consumption of the test products - This parameter will be analyzed first in both Caucasian and Asian populations and second globally</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 hours after food consumption</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Insulinaemic response assessed by the kinetic of insulinemia over the 120 minutes - This parameter will be analyzed first in both Caucasian and Asian populations and second globally</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 hours after food consumption</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Insulinaemic response assessed by the peak value of insulinemia - This parameter will be analyzed first in both Caucasian and Asian populations and second globally</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 hours after food consumption</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Insulinaemic response assessed by the delta value between baseline and peak values of insulinemia - This parameter will be analyzed first in both Caucasian and Asian populations and second globally</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 hours after food consumption</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Insulin / glucose ratio (II/GI) evaluation of five cereal products - This parameter will be analyzed first in both Caucasian and Asian populations and second globally</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 hours after food consumption</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postprandial changes in insulin / glucose over 2 hours (iAUC0-120) after consumption of the test products - This parameter will be analyzed first in both Caucasian and Asian populations and second globally</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 hours after food consumption</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Kinetic of insulin / glucose over the 120 minutes - This parameter will be analyzed first in both Caucasian and Asian populations and second globally</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 hours after food consumption</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Peak value of insulin / glucose ratio - This parameter will be analyzed first in both Caucasian and Asian populations and second globally</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 hours after food consumption</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Delta peak value between baseline and peak values of insulin / glucose ratio - This parameter will be analyzed first in both Caucasian and Asian populations and second globally</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 hours after food consumption</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Aged between 18-45 years.

          -  Non-smoker.

          -  BMI values: between 19-25 kg/m2 (bounds included) for Caucasian subjects and between
             19-23 kg/m2 (bounds included) for Asian subjects (WHO expert consultation).

          -  Ethnicity: Caucasian subjects will have both parents from Caucasian ancestry. Asian
             subjects will have both parents from Asian country and will be born in an Asian
             country. Asian countries are: Brunei Darussalam, Cambodia, China, Dem. People's
             Republic of Korea, Hong Kong SAR (China), Indonesia, Japan, Lao People's Democratic
             Republic, Macao SAR (China), Malaysia, Mongolia, Myanmar, Philippines, Republic of
             Korea, Singapore, Taiwan, Thailand, Viet Nam.

          -  Sex ratio: Around half of the subjects should be male and half of the subjects should
             be female within each study group. A plus or minus 1 subject tolerance will be
             accepted.

          -  Healthy subjects with:

        Normal glucose tolerance Normal laboratory values for various measures of metabolic health
        (full blood count, gamma-GT, AST, ALT, glucose, TAGs, total cholesterol, HDL-cholesterol,
        LDL-cholesterol); Normal systolic blood pressure (100-150 mmHg); Normal diastolic blood
        pressure (60-90 mmHg); Normal resting heart rate (50-90 beats per minutes after 3 minutes
        rest).

          -  Stable dietary habits; normal eating patterns; no history of eating disorders or
             strict dieting.

          -  Moderate level of physical activity (from basic daily activity to a high level of
             physical activity (regular physical activity at least 3 times per week))

          -  Able to fast for at least 10 hours the night before each test session.

          -  Able to refrain from eating legumes and drinking alcohol the day before each test
             session.

          -  Subject covered by social security or covered by a similar system

          -  Subject not taking any treatment for anorexia, weight loss, or any form of treatment
             likely to interfere with metabolism or dietary habits

          -  Subject having given written consent to take part in the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Following a restrictive diet.

          -  Family history of Diabetes Mellitus or obesity

          -  Suffering from any clinical, physical or mental illness.

          -  Suffering from any food allergies or hypersensitivities (wheat, milk, egg, nuts, etc).

          -  Taking any regular prescription medication at the time of inclusion (except regular
             oral contraception medication)

          -  Female who is pregnant (positive test results), lactating, planning pregnancy or not
             using acceptable contraceptive.

          -  Females who consistently suffer from premenstrual tension and marked changes in
             appetite during their menstrual cycle.

          -  Subject having taken part in another clinical trial within the last week.

          -  Subject currently taking part in another clinical trial or being in the exclusion
             period of another clinical trial.

          -  Subject undergoing general anaesthesia in the month prior to inclusion.

          -  Subject in a situation which in the investigator's opinion could interfere with
             optimal participation in the present study or could constitute a special risk for the
             subject.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Basic Science</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/10/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>24</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/04/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>University of Sydney - Sydney</hospital>
    <postcode>2006 - Sydney</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Mondelez International, Inc.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of Sydney</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aimed at determining the Glycaemic Index and Insulinaemic Index Values of Five
      Cereal Products in two different ethnic groups.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02650674</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jennie Brand Miller</name>
      <address>University of Sydney</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>