<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5886">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/11/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/11/2013</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02000115</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Portico Re-sheathable Transcatheter Aortic Valve System US IDE Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Portico Re-sheathable Transcatheter Aortic Valve System US IDE Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>PORTICO IDE</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>1203</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Aortic Valve Stenosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - Portico transcatheter aortic valve
Treatment: devices - Commercially available transcatheter aortic valve

Experimental: Portico - Portico transcatheter aortic valve

Active Comparator: Commercially Available Valve - Commercially available transcatheter aortic valve


Treatment: devices: Portico transcatheter aortic valve
St. Jude Medical transcatheter Portico aortic valve

Treatment: devices: Commercially available transcatheter aortic valve
Commercially available transcatheter aortic valve

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Effectiveness Endpoint - A composite of all-cause mortality or disabling stroke at one year.</outcome>
      <timepoint>One year</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Safety Endpoint - Non-hierarchical composite of all-cause mortality, disabling stroke, life threatening bleeding requiring blood transfusion, acute kidney injury requiring dialysis, or major vascular complications at 30 days.</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severe aortic regurgitation - Severe aortic regurgitation (AR) at one year</outcome>
      <timepoint>One year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Kansas City Cardiomyopathy Questionnaire (KCCQ) - Kansas City Cardiomyopathy Questionnaire (KCCQ) at one year</outcome>
      <timepoint>One year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Moderate or severe aortic regurgitation - Moderate or severe aortic regurgitation at one year</outcome>
      <timepoint>One year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Six minute walk - Six minute walk at one year</outcome>
      <timepoint>One year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion:

        High Risk Cohort:

        All candidates for the High Risk Cohort of this study must meet all the following inclusion
        criteria:

          1. Subjects must have co-morbidities such that the surgeon and cardiologist
             Co-Investigators concur that the predicted risk of operative mortality is =15% or a
             minimum STS score of 8%. A candidate who does not meet the STS score criteria of = 8%
             can be included in the study if a peer review by at least two surgeons concludes and
             documents that the patient's predicted risk of operative mortality is =15%. The
             surgeon's assessment of operative comorbidities not captured by the STS score must be
             documented in the study case report form as well as in the patient medical record.

          2. Subject is 21 years of age or older at the time of consent.

          3. Subject has senile degenerative aortic valve stenosis with echocardiographically
             derived criteria: mean gradient &gt;40 mmHg or jet velocity greater than 4.0 m/s or
             Doppler Velocity Index &lt;0.25 and an initial aortic valve area (AVA) of = 1.0 cm2
             (indexed EOA = 0.6 cm2/m2). (Qualifying AVA baseline measurement must be within 60
             days prior to informed consent).

          4. Subject has symptomatic aortic stenosis as demonstrated by NYHA Functional
             Classification of II, III, or IV.

          5. The subject has been informed of the nature of the study, agrees to its provisions and
             has provided written informed consent as approved by the Institutional Review Board
             (IRB) of the respective clinical site.

          6. The subject and the treating physician agree that the subject will return for all
             required post-procedure follow-up visits.

          7. Subject's aortic annulus is 19-27mm diameter as measured by CT conducted within 12
             months prior to informed consent. Note: if CT is contraindicated and/or not possible
             to be obtained for certain subjects, a 3D echo and non-contrast CT of chest and
             abdomen/pelvis may be accepted if approved by the subject selection committee.

        Extreme Risk Cohort:

        All candidates for the Extreme Risk Cohort of this study must meet # 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7 of
        the above criteria, and 1. The subject, after formal consults by a cardiologist and two
        cardiovascular surgeons agree that medical factors preclude operation, based on a
        conclusion that the probability of death or serious, irreversible morbidity exceeds the
        probability of meaningful improvement. Specifically, the probability of death or serious,
        irreversible morbidity should exceed 50%. The surgeons' consult notes shall specify the
        medical or anatomic factors leading to that conclusion and include a printout of the
        calculation of the STS score to additionally identify the risks in these patients.

        All Candidates:

        Additionally, all candidates for the study must meet the following inclusion criteria for
        the TAVR Leaflet Motion Sub-study, until the minimum sub-study sample size has been
        achieved:

        1. Be willing and able to undergo, at both 30-days and 6-months post-implant, a Multi-Slice
        Computed Tomography (MSCT) scan (or TEE, if medically or technically contraindicated for an
        MSCT) of the heart and cardiac structures.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>21</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>High and Extreme Risk Cohort:

        Candidates will be excluded from the study if any of the following conditions are present:

          1. Evidence of an acute myocardial infarction (defined as: ST Segment Elevation as
             evidenced on 12 Lead ECG) within 30 days prior to index procedure.

          2. Aortic valve is a congenital unicuspid or congenital bicuspid valve, or is
             non-calcified as verified by echocardiography.

          3. Mixed aortic valve disease (aortic stenosis and aortic regurgitation with predominant
             aortic regurgitation 3-4+).

          4. Any percutaneous coronary or peripheral interventional procedure performed within 30
             days prior to index procedure.

          5. Pre-existing prosthetic heart valve or other implant in any valve position, prosthetic
             ring, severe circumferential mitral annular calcification (MAC) which is continuous
             with calcium in the LVOT, severe (greater than 3+) mitral insufficiency, or severe
             mitral stenosis with pulmonary compromise. Subjects with pre-existing surgical
             bioprosthetic aortic heart valve should be considered for the Valve-in-Valve registry.

          6. Blood dyscrasias as defined: leukopenia (WBC&lt;3000 mm3), acute anemia (Hb &lt; 9 mg/dL),
             thrombocytopenia (platelet count &lt;50,000 cells/mm³).

          7. History of bleeding diathesis or coagulopathy.

          8. Cardiogenic shock manifested by low cardiac output, vasopressor dependence, or
             mechanical hemodynamic support.

          9. Untreated clinically significant coronary artery disease requiring revascularization.

         10. Hemodynamic instability requiring inotropic support or mechanical heart assistance.

         11. Need for emergency surgery for any reason.

         12. Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy with or without obstruction (HOCM).

         13. Severe ventricular dysfunction with LVEF &lt;20% as measured by resting echocardiogram.

         14. Echocardiographic evidence of intracardiac mass, thrombus or vegetation.

         15. Active peptic ulcer or upper GI bleeding within 3 months prior to index procedure.

         16. A known hypersensitivity or contraindication to aspirin, heparin, ticlopidine
             (Ticlid), or clopidogrel (Plavix), or sensitivity to contrast media which cannot be
             adequately premedicated.

         17. Recent (within 6 months prior to index procedure date) cerebrovascular accident (CVA)
             or a transient ischemic attack (TIA).

         18. Renal insufficiency (creatinine &gt; 3.0 mg/dL) and/or end stage renal disease requiring
             chronic dialysis.

         19. Life expectancy &lt; 12 months from the time of informed consent due to non-cardiac
             co-morbid conditions.

         20. Significant aortic disease, including abdominal aortic or thoracic aneurysm defined as
             maximal luminal diameter 5cm or greater; marked tortuosity (hyperacute bend), aortic
             arch atheroma (especially if thick [&gt; 5 mm], protruding or ulcerated) or narrowing
             (especially with calcification and surface irregularities) of the abdominal or
             thoracic aorta, severe "unfolding" and tortuosity of the thoracic aorta (applicable
             for transfemoral patients only).

         21. Native aortic annulus size &lt; 19 mm or &gt; 27 mm per the baseline diagnostic imaging.

         22. Aortic root angulation &gt; 70° (applicable for transfemoral patients only).

         23. Currently participating in an investigational drug or device study.

         24. Active bacterial endocarditis within 6 months prior to the index procedure.

         25. Bulky calcified aortic valve leaflets in close proximity to coronary ostia.

         26. Non-calcified aortic annulus

         27. Iliofemoral vessel characteristics that would preclude safe placement of the
             introducer sheath such as severe obstructive calcification, or severe tortuosity
             (applicable for transfemoral patients only).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/05/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>758</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/09/2022</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,SA,VIC,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Macquarie University Hospital - Sydney</hospital>
    <hospital>The Prince Charles Hospital - Chermside</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>The Alfred Hospital - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Fiona Stanley Hospital - Murdoch</hospital>
    <postcode>2109 - Sydney</postcode>
    <postcode>4032 - Chermside</postcode>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>6150 - Murdoch</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Alabama</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Arizona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>District of Columbia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Georgia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Illinois</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Indiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Iowa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Kansas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Louisiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Massachusetts</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Michigan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Minnesota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Mississippi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Missouri</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Hampshire</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Jersey</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Oklahoma</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Pennsylvania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>South Dakota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Tennessee</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Utah</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Virginia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>St. Jude Medical</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The PORTICO clinical trial is a prospective, multi-center, randomized, controlled clinical
      study, designed to evaluate the safety and effectiveness of the SJM Portico Transcatheter
      Heart Valve and Delivery Systems (Portico) via transfemoral and alternative delivery methods.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02000115</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Raj Makkar, MD</name>
      <address>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Angie Roach</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>aroach@sjm.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>