<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5288">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/12/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/12/2015</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02629484</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Trial of Focused Cardiac Ultrasound for Fractured Neck of Femur Surgery</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Pilot Study to Assess Feasibility, Compliance, Safety and Group Separation for a Multicentre Randomised Trial of Preoperative Focused Cardiac Ultrasound for Fractured Neck of Femur Surgery</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ECHONOFII</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>2015.231</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hip Fractures</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fractures</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - Focused cardiac ultrasound

Active Comparator: Focused Cardiac Ultrasound - participants randomised to receive focused cardiac ultrasound prior to surgery for hip fracture

No Intervention: Standard care (clinical assessment) - Participants randomised to standard care receive clinical assessment of the patient


Other interventions: Focused cardiac ultrasound
focused cardiac ultrasound is a goal-focused transthoracic echocardiography examination of the heart, aimed to improve the diagnostic accuracy of clinical assessment

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite mortality and morbidity score - The primary outcome is 30 day composite outcome of the incidence of mortality, acute kidney injury, and cardiovascular morbidity (including non-fatal myocardial infarction, stroke, pulmonary embolism or cardiac arrest.</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days after surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The number of days alive, out of hospital, and until return to place of origin - Longitudinal measures include the number of days alive, out of hospital and returning to their place of origin out to 12 months.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in clinician diagnosis and management from a recorded preoperative plan - The treating doctors will complete a diagnosis and management research form prior to revealing the FCU findings or not. The actual management of the patient after allocation will be recorded prospectively for all patients, with the data recording sheets not showing allocation. Data include cardiac monitoring and treatment preoperatively, intraoperatively and postoperatively, including type of anaesthesia, fluid therapy, inotropes, other invasive organ support and intensive care use, surgical technique, and additional cardiovascular management post-hospital discharge.</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total cost of care - Units of health care resources consumed will be combined with Australian unit costs derived from Pharmaceutical benefit schedule, Medicare and Australian Diagnostic group indicators. The dollar value for each component of stay (e.g. days in hospital, drugs used, investigations performed) will be converted into a cost value and aggregated to make a single cost over the 12 month follow up period</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>EuroQol Health status score - The EuroQol health status survey instrument is a a standard, internationally validated instrument with Australian population norms, will be conducted at 12 months follow up</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Patients presenting with isolated, primary, non-metastatic fractured neck of femur,
             where surgery is expected within 48 hours after hospital admission will be recruited.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Patients with prior hip surgery on the affected side, or where the cause is likely to
             be due to metastatic cancer, or where survival is unlikely in the 24 hours from
             admission will not be included.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/02/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>100</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>26/01/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Prince Charles Hospital - Brisbane</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Western and Sunshine General hospitals - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode> - Brisbane</postcode>
    <postcode>3050 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode> - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Melbourne Health</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Austin Health</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Hip fracture surgery is a major world health care burden and concern, as it has a large and
      increasing prevalence and carries very high patient mortality, disability and community
      health care cost. As the commonest cause of mortality is from cardiac complications, and
      cardiac disease is prevalent and frequently missed by standard care, we hypothesise that
      earlier and more accurate diagnosis and treatment of cardiac pathology in this cohort will
      lead to improved outcome. Focused cardiac ultrasound (FCU) is a new increasingly popular
      technique used by doctors that enables earlier and more accurate diagnosis of cardiac
      disorders that can be performed routinely before hip fracture surgery. Our preliminary data
      of 64 patients demonstrated that routine FCU before surgery lead to a change in cardiac
      diagnosis and management in 50% of patients requiring hip fracture surgery, which was
      associated with a 50% reduction in mortality 12 months after surgery compared with controls.
      It is therefore important for a large randomised trial to be performed to confirm or rebuke
      these findings, as if true, would have a very large impact on health care and may also
      improve health care and outcome in other high-risk surgical populations. The proposed pilot
      study is a pilot study which aims to establish feasibility, safety, compliance and group
      separation prior to commencing a definitive multicentre trial.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02629484</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Colin Royse, MD, BS</name>
      <address>University of Melbourne</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>