<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2075">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/08/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/08/2008</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00734084</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Study to Evaluate the DePuy Minimally Invasive Unicompartmental Knee</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Prospective, Non-Comparative Multi-centre Study to Evaluate the Safety and Performance of the DePuy Minimally Invasive (Preservation) Unicompartmental Knee and Instrumentation.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>CT 01/34</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Osteoarthritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - Preservation Unicompartmental Knee

Other: Preservation Unicompartmental Knee - Minimally invasive orthopaedic implant for single compartment knee arthritis


Treatment: devices: Preservation Unicompartmental Knee
Minimally invasive orthopaedic implant for single compartment knee arthritis

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To demonstrate the suitability of the developed instrumentation to safely and accurately implant the Preservation Unicompartmental Knee using radiographic and intra-operative assessment - Intraoperative</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To demonstrate the survivorship and performance of the Preservation Unicompartmental Knee using the American Knee Society clinical and radiographic assessment, Oxford Knee Score and survivorship analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months, 1, 3, 5, 10 and 15 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Male or female subjects, who are 40 to 75 years of age inclusive.

          -  Subjects who are able to give voluntary, written informed consent to participate in
             this investigation and from whom written consent has been obtained.

          -  Subjects who, in the opinion of the Investigator, are able to understand this
             investigation, co-operate with the investigational procedures and are willing to
             return to the hospital for all the required post-operative follow-ups.

          -  Subjects who exhibit loss of articular cartilage which is predominantly confined to a
             single compartment. The remaining compartments must be intact and able to bear normal
             loads.

          -  Subjects who in the opinion of the Clinical Investigator are considered to be suitable
             for treatment with the investigation device, according to the indications specified in
             the package insert leaflet.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Subjects who, in the opinion of the Investigator, have an existing condition that
             would compromise their participation and follow-up in this study.

          -  Subjects with a known history of poor compliance to medical treatment.

          -  Women who are pregnant.

          -  Subjects who are known drug or alcohol abusers or with psychological disorders that
             could effect follow-up care or treatment outcomes.

          -  Subjects who have participated in a clinical study with an investigational product in
             the last month.

          -  Subjects who are currently involved in any injury litigation claims.

          -  Revision of an existing unicompartmental implant.

          -  Subjects who have gross ligament laxity / instability.

          -  Subjects who have an inflammatory joint disease

          -  Subjects in whom there is evidence of previous joint sepsis

          -  Subjects who have a pre-operative flexion contracture of 15° or greater

          -  Subjects who have a pre-operative flexion of less than 90°

          -  Subjects who have a pre-operative limb deformity of greater than 15° varus or valgus

          -  Subjects who have morbid obesity i.e. BMI &gt; 40%</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/06/2001</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>247</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Terminated</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/04/2008</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Sportsmed SA, 32 Payneham, Stepney - Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>5069 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>DePuy International</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of this investigation is to evaluate the surgical performance of the
      DePuy Minimally Invasive (Preservation) Unicompartmental Knee and Instrumentation in a
      Multi-centre setting.

      The secondary objective of this investigation is to evaluate the long-term survivorship of
      the DePuy Minimally Invasive (Preservation) Unicompartmental Knee.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00734084</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kim Dwyer, Ph.D</name>
      <address>DePuy Synthes Joint Reconstruction</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>