<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="1424">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/01/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/01/2007</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00419679</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Use of Hair to Diagnose Breast Cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Prospective Blinded Study to Evaluate and Characterise an Assay for the Diagnosis of Breast Cancer Using Synchrotron-Derived X-Ray Diffraction of Hair Fibres.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>FT3.6k-2006</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Breast Neoplasms</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: surgery - x-ray diffraction of human hair

Treatment: surgery: x-ray diffraction of human hair


</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome is the determination of the accuracy (sensitivity and specificity) of the x-ray diffraction test for breast cancer using hair. Sensitivity is defined as the proportion of all positive Fermiscan tests that are true positives.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The prevalence of a positive x-ray diffraction hair test and a negative mammogram, and of a negative hair test and a positive mammogram</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Adult women (aged &gt;20) who are undergoing mammography at the Mater Hospital, Sydney,
             and

          -  Who are willing and able to provide informed consent; and

          -  Who have usable scalp and/or pubic hair</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Female</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Women who have dyed or permed their scalp hair within the previous 6 weeks and whose
             pubic hair is unavailable;

          -  Women with a history of breast cancer ever or other cancers (excluding non-melanoma
             skin cancer and CIN [cervical intra-epithelial neoplasia]) within 5 years.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/12/2006</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Unknown status</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Mater Hospital - Sydney</hospital>
    <postcode>2065 - Sydney</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Fermiscan Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Study FT3.6k-2006 is a single centre (the Mater Hospital, Sydney), blinded trial of a
      diagnostic test for breast cancer, with outcomes compared to the gold standard of screening
      mammogram followed by biopsy where required. This study aims to perform X-ray diffraction
      analysis of coded hair samples from women with a documented breast health status, to validate
      the findings of James et al (Nature 398: 33-4, 1999; Int J Cancer 114: 969-72, 2005) who
      showed that the presence of breast cancer could be detected using synchrotron-derived x-ray
      diffraction of human hair (scalp or pubic). The aim is also to characterise the sensitivity
      and specificity of the hair test in detecting breast cancer in a screening setting, and to
      determine the significance of a positive hair test and a negative mammogram.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00419679</trialwebsite>
    <publication>James VJ. A place for fiber diffraction in the detection of breast cancer? Cancer Detect Prev. 2006;30(3):233-8. Epub 2006 Jul 28.
James V, Corino G, Robertson T, Dutton N, Halas D, Boyd A, Bentel J, Papadimitriou J. Early diagnosis of breast cancer by hair diffraction. Int J Cancer. 2005 May 10;114(6):969-72.
James V. False-positive results in studies of changes in fiber diffraction of hair from patients with breast cancer may not be false. J Natl Cancer Inst. 2003 Jan 15;95(2):170-1. Erratum in: J Natl Cancer Inst. 2003 Feb 19;95(4):334..
Meyer P, James VJ. Experimental confirmation of a distinctive diffraction pattern in hair from women with breast cancer. J Natl Cancer Inst. 2001 Jun 6;93(11):873-5.
James V, Kearsley J, Irving T, Amemiya Y, Cookson D. Using hair to screen for breast cancer. Nature. 1999 Mar 4;398(6722):33-4.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Phillip Yuile, MBBS (Hons), FRNZCR</name>
      <address>The Mater Hospital, Sydney</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Peter French, BSc, MSc, PhD</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+61292454460</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pfrench@fermiscan.com.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>