<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3101">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/03/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/03/2011</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01311687</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Phase 3, Multicenter, Randomized, Open-Label Study to Compare the Efficacy and Safety of Pomalidomide in Combination With Low-Dose Dexamethasone Versus High-Dose Dexamethasone in Subjects With Refractory Multiple Myeloma or Relapsed and Refractory Multiple Myeloma and Companion Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 3, Muticenter, Randomized, Open-label Study to Compare the Efficacy and Safety of Pomalidomide in Combination With Low-dose Dexamethasone Versus High-dose Dexamethasone in Subjects With Refractory or Relapsed and Refractory Multiple Myeloma</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>NIMBUS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>2010-019820-30</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>CC-4047-MM-003</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Multiple Myeloma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cancer types</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - pomalidomide
Treatment: drugs - dexamethasone

Experimental: Oral Pomalidomide plus Low-Dose Dexamethasone - For Subjects = 75 years of age:
4 mg pomalidomide will be administered by mouth on Days 1-21 of each 28-day treatment cycle until disease progression and 40 mg low-dose dexamethasone will be administered by mouth once per day on Days 1, 8, 15, and 22 of a 28-day cycle until disease progression
For Subjects &gt; 75 years of age:
4 mg pomalidomide will be administered by mouth on Days 1-21 of each 28-day treatment cycle until disease progression and 20 mg low dose dexamethasone will be administered by mouth once per day on Days 1, 8, 15, and 22 of a 28-day cycle until disease progression

Active Comparator: High-Dose Dexamethasone - For Subjects = 75 years of age:
40 mg high-dose dexamethasone will be administered by mouth once per day on Days 1 through 4, 9 through 12, and 17 through 20 of a 28-day cycle until disease progression
For Subjects &gt; 75 years of age:
20 mg high-dose dexamethasone will be administered by mouth once per day on Days 1 through 4, 9 through 7, and 17 through 20 of a 28-day cycle until disease progression


Treatment: drugs: pomalidomide
4 mg pomalidomide will be administered by mouth on Days 1-21 of each 28-day treatment cycle until disease progression

Treatment: drugs: dexamethasone
For Subjects = 75 years of age:
40 mg of low-dose dexamethasone will be administered by mouth once per day on Days 1, 8, 15, and 22 of a 28-day cycle until disease progression
For Subjects &gt; 75 years of age:
20 mg low-dose dexamethasone will be administered by mouth once per day on Days 1, 8, 15, and 22 of a 28-day cycle until disease progression

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression-free Survival (PFS) - Progression-free survival was calculated as the time from randomization to disease progression as determined by the Independent Response Adjudication Committee based on the International Myeloma Working Group Uniform Response criteria (IMWG), or death on study, whichever occurred earlier.
Progressive disease requires 1 of the following:
Increase of = 25% from nadir in:
Serum M-component (absolute increase = 0.5 g/dl);
Urine M-component (absolute increase = 200 mg/24 hours);
Bone marrow plasma cell percentage (absolute % = 10%);
Development of new or increase in the size of existing bone lesions or soft tissue plasmacytomas;
Development of hypercalcemia (corrected serum calcium &gt; 11.5 mg/dl) attributed solely to plasma cell proliferative disease.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From randomization until the data cut-off date of 07 September 2012. Maximum duration of follow-up for PFS assessments was 57 weeks.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression-free Survival (PFS) With a Later Cut-off Date - Progression-free survival was calculated as the time from randomization to disease progression as determined by the Independent Response Adjudication Committee based on the International Myeloma Working Group Uniform Response criteria (IMWG), or death on study, whichever occurred earlier.
Progressive disease requires 1 of the following:
Increase of = 25% from nadir in:
Serum M-component (absolute increase = 0.5 g/dl);
Urine M-component (absolute increase = 200 mg/24 hours);
Bone marrow plasma cell percentage (absolute % = 10%);
Development of new or increase in the size of existing bone lesions or soft tissue plasmacytomas;
Development of hypercalcemia (corrected serum calcium &gt; 11.5 mg/dl) attributed solely to plasma cell proliferative disease.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From randomization until the data cut-off date of 01 March 2013. Maximum duration of follow-up for PFS assessments was 74 weeks.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With Adverse Events (AEs) - An adverse event is any noxious, unintended, or untoward medical occurrence that may appear or worsen in a participant during the course of a study. A serious AE is any AE occurring at any dose that:
Results in death;
Is life-threatening;
Requires or prolongs existing inpatient hospitalization;
Results in persistent or significant disability/incapacity;
Is a congenital anomaly/birth defect;
Constitutes an important medical event.
The Investigator assessed the relationship of each AE to study drug and graded the severity according to the National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE, Version 4.0):
Grade 1 = Mild (no limitation in activity or intervention required); Grade 2 = Moderate (some limitation in activity; no/minimal medical intervention required);-Grade 3 = Severe (marked limitation in activity; medical intervention required, hospitalization possible); Grade 4 = Life-threatening; Grade 5 = Death.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From first dose of study drug through to 30 days after the last dose, until the data cut-off date of 01 March 2013. Maximum time on treatment was 93 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Survival - Overall survival is calculated as the time from randomization to death from any cause. Overall survival was censored at the last date that the participant was known to be alive for participants who were alive at the time of analysis and for participants who were lost to follow-up before death was documented.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From randomization until the data cut-off date of 07 September 2012. Maximum time on follow-up for survival was 70 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Survival With a Later Cut-off Date - Overall survival is calculated as the time from randomization to death from any cause. Overall survival was censored at the last date that the participant was known to be alive for participants who were alive at the time of analysis and for participants who were lost to follow-up before death was documented.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From randomization until the data cut-off date of 01 March 2013. Maximum time on follow-up for survival was 93 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants With an Objective Response According to International Myeloma Working Group (IMWG) Uniform Response Criteria - Objective response is defined as a best overall response of stringent complete response (SCR), complete response (CR), very good partial response (VGPR) or partial response (PR) based on the Independent Response Adjudication Committee:
SCR: CR and normal free light chain (FLC) ratio and no clonal cells in bone marrow; CR: Negative serum and urine on immunofixation, disappearance of any soft tissue plasmacytomas and = 5% plasma cells in bone marrow; VGPR: Serum and urine M-protein detectable by immunofixation but not on electrophoresis or = 90% reduction in serum M-protein and urine M-protein level &lt; 100 mg/24 hours; PR: = 50% reduction of serum M-Protein and reduction in urinary M-protein by = 90% or to &lt; 200 mg/24 hours. In addition to the above, if present at baseline a = 50% reduction in the size of soft tissue plasmacytomas is also required.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From randomization until the data cut-off date of 01 March 2013. Maximum time on follow-up was 93 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants With Objective Response According to European Group for Blood and Marrow Transplantation (EBMT) Criteria - Objective response defined as a best overall response of complete response (CR) or partial response (PR) based on the Independent Response Adjudication Committee:
CR requires all of the following:
Absence of original monoclonal paraprotein in serum and urine by immunofixation maintained at least 42 days.
&lt;5% plasma cell in bone marrow aspirate and on bone marrow biopsy, if performed.
No increase in size or number of lytic bone lesions.
Disappearance of soft tissue plasmacytomas.
PR requires all of the following:
= 50% reduction in level of serum monoclonal paraprotein, maintained at least 42 days.
Reduction in 24-hour urinary light chain extraction by = 90% or to &lt; 200 mg, maintained at least 42 days.
For patients with non-secretory myeloma, = 50% reduction in plasma cells in bone marrow aspirate and on biopsy, if performed, for at least 42 days.
= 50% reduction in the size of soft tissue plasmacytomas.
No increase in size or number of lytic bone lesions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From randomization until the data cut-off date of 01 March 2013. Maximum time on follow-up was 93 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Progression - Time to progression (TTP) is calculated as the time from randomization to the first documented progression confirmed by a blinded, independent Response Adjudication Committee and based on the International Myeloma Working Group Uniform Response criteria (IMWG).
Progressive disease requires 1 of the following:
Increase of = 25% from nadir in:
Serum M-component (absolute increase = 0.5 g/dl);
Urine M-component (absolute increase = 200 mg/24 hours);
Bone marrow plasma cell percentage (absolute % = 10%);
Development of new or increase in the size of existing bone lesions or soft tissue plasmacytomas;
Development of hypercalcemia (corrected serum calcium &gt; 11.5 mg/dl) attributed solely to plasma cell proliferative disease.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From randomization until the data cut-off date of 01 March 2013. Maximum time on follow-up was 93 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Response - Time to response is calculated as the time from randomization to the initial documented response (partial response or better) based on IMWG criteria.
SCR: CR and normal free light chain (FLC) ratio and no clonal cells in bone marrow; CR: Negative serum and urine on immunofixation, disappearance of any soft tissue plasmacytomas and = 5% plasma cells in bone marrow; VGPR: Serum and urine M-protein detectable by immunofixation but not on electrophoresis or = 90% reduction in serum M-protein and urine M-protein level &lt; 100 mg/24 hours; PR: = 50% reduction of serum M-Protein and reduction in urinary M-protein by = 90% or to &lt; 200 mg/24 hours. If present at baseline a = 50% reduction in size of soft tissue plasmacytomas is also required.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From randomization until the data cut-off date of 01 March 2013. Maximum time on follow-up was 93 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of Response - Duration of response (calculated for responders only) is defined as time from the initial documented response (partial response or better) to confirmed disease progression, based on IMWG criteria assessed by the Independent Response Adjudication Committee.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From randomization until the data cut-off date of 01 March 2013. Maximum time on follow-up was 93 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to the First Hemoglobin Improvement - Time to increased hemoglobin, defined as the time from randomization to at least one category improvement from Baseline in common terminology criteria for adverse events (CTCAE) grade for hemoglobin level. Hemoglobin categories are:
Normal;
CTCAE Grade 1: &lt; lower limit of normal (LLN) to 10.0 g/dL;
CTCAE Grade 2: &lt; 10.0 to &lt;8.0 g/dL.
Participants with CTCAE Grade 3 anemia or worse at Baseline were excluded from the study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From randomization until the data cut-off date of 01 March 2013. Maximum time on follow-up was 93 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Improvement in Bone Pain - Time to improvement in bone pain is defined as the time from randomization to at least one category improvement from Baseline in bone pain category.
Bone pain was categorized (from best to worst) according to answers to the European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) Quality of Life Questionnaire for patients with Multiple Myeloma Module (QLQ-MY20), Question 1, "Have you had bone aches or pain?":
Not at all,
A little,
Quite a bit, or
Very much.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From randomization until the data cut-off date of 01 March 2013. Maximum time on follow-up was 93 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Improvement in Renal Function - Time to improvement in renal function is defined as the time from randomization to at least one category improvement from Baseline in renal function.
Renal Function was categorized as (from best to worst):
Normal: creatinine clearance =80 mL/min;
Grade 1: creatinine clearance =60 to &lt;80 mL/min;
Grade 2 : creatinine clearance =45 to &lt; 60 mL/min.
Participants with creatinine clearance &lt; 45 mL/min at baseline were be excluded from the study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From randomization until the data cut-off date of 01 March 2013. Maximum time on follow-up was 93 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Improvement in Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status - Time to improvement in ECOG performance status defined as the time from randomization until at least a one category improvement from Baseline in ECOG performance status score.
The categories of the ECOG Performance Status Scale are as follows:
0: Fully active, able to carry on all pre-disease performance without restriction;
1: Restricted in physically strenuous activity but ambulatory and able to carry our work of a light or sedentary nature, e.g., light housework, office work;
2: Ambulatory and capable of all self-care but unable to carry out any work activities. Up and about more than 50% of waking hours.
Patients with a score of 3, 4 or 5 were excluded from participating in the study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From randomization until the data cut-off date of 01 March 2013. Maximum time on follow-up was 93 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in the European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer Cancer Quality of Life Questionnaire for Patients With Cancer (EORTC QLQ-C30) Global Health Status Domain - The European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) Core Quality of Life (QOL) questionnaire (EORTC QLQ-C30) is a 30-question tool used to assess the overall quality of life in cancer patients. It consists of 15 domains: 1 global health status (GHS) scale, 5 functional scales (Physical, Role, Cognitive, Emotional, Social), and 9 symptom scales/items (Fatigue, Nausea and Vomiting, Pain, Dyspnea, Sleep Disturbance, Appetite Loss, Constipation, Diarrhea, Financial Impact).
The EORTC QLQ-C30 Global Health Status/QOL scale is scored between 0 and 100, with a high score indicating better Global Health Status/QOL. Negative change from Baseline values indicate deterioration in QOL or functioning and positive values indicate improvement.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 of Cycle 1 (Baseline), and Day 1 of Cycles 2, 3, 4, 5 and 6</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in the EORTC QLQ-C30 Physical Functioning Domain - The European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) Core Quality of Life (QOL) questionnaire (EORTC QLQ-C30) is a 30-question tool used in clinical research to assess the overall quality of life in cancer patients. It consists of 15 domains: 1 global health status (GHS) scale, 5 functional scales (Physical, Role, Cognitive, Emotional, Social), and 9 symptom scales/items (Fatigue, Nausea and Vomiting, Pain, Dyspnea, Sleep Disturbance, Appetite Loss, Constipation, Diarrhea, Financial Impact).
The EORTC QLQ-C30 Physical Functioning Scale is scored between 0 and 100, with a high score indicating better functioning/support. Negative change from Baseline values indicate deterioration in functioning and positive values indicate improvement.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 of Cycle 1 (Baseline), and Day 1 of Cycles 2, 3, 4, 5 and 6</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in the EORTC QLQ-C30 Emotional Functioning Domain - The European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) Core Quality of Life (QOL) questionnaire (EORTC QLQ-C30) is a 30-question tool used in clinical research to assess the overall quality of life in cancer patients. It consists of 15 domains: 1 global health status (GHS) scale, 5 functional scales (Physical, Role, Cognitive, Emotional, Social), and 9 symptom scales/items (Fatigue, Nausea and Vomiting, Pain, Dyspnea, Sleep Disturbance, Appetite Loss, Constipation, Diarrhea, Financial Impact).
The EORTC QLQ-C30 Emotional Functioning Scale is scored between 0 and 100, with a high score indicating better functioning/support. Negative change from Baseline values indicate deterioration in functioning and positive values indicate improvement.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 of Cycle 1 (Baseline), and Day 1 of Cycles 2, 3, 4, 5 and 6</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in the EORTC QLQ-C30 Fatigue Domain - The European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) Core Quality of Life (QOL) questionnaire (EORTC QLQ-C30) is a 30-question tool used in clinical research to assess the overall quality of life in cancer patients. It consists of 15 domains: 1 global health status (GHS) scale, 5 functional scales (Physical, Role, Cognitive, Emotional, Social), and 9 symptom scales/items (Fatigue, Nausea and Vomiting, Pain, Dyspnea, Sleep Disturbance, Appetite Loss, Constipation, Diarrhea, Financial Impact).
The EORTC QLQ-C30 Fatigue Scale is scored between 0 and 100, with a high score indicating a higher level of symptoms. Negative change from Baseline values indicate reduction in fatigue (i.e. improvement in symptom) and positive values indicate increases in fatigue (i.e. worsening of symptom).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 of Cycle 1 (Baseline), and Day 1 of Cycles 2, 3, 4, 5 and 6</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in the EORTC QLQ-C30 Pain Domain - The European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) Core Quality of Life (QOL) questionnaire (EORTC QLQ-C30) is a 30-question tool used in clinical research to assess the overall quality of life in cancer patients. It consists of 15 domains: 1 global health status (GHS) scale, 5 functional scales (Physical, Role, Cognitive, Emotional, Social), and 9 symptom scales/items (Fatigue, Nausea and Vomiting, Pain, Dyspnea, Sleep Disturbance, Appetite Loss, Constipation, Diarrhea, Financial Impact).
The EORTC QLQ-C30 Pain Scale is scored between 0 and 100, with a high score indicating a higher level of symptoms. Negative change from Baseline values indicate reductions in pain (i.e. improvement in symptom) and positive values indicate increases in pain (i.e. worsening of symptom).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 of Cycle 1 (Baseline), and Day 1 of Cycles 2, 3, 4, 5 and 6</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in the European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer QoL Questionnaire for Patients With Multiple Myeloma (EORTC QLQ-MY20) Disease Symptoms - The European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer QoL Questionnaire for Patients with Multiple Myeloma (EORTC QLQ-MY20) is a 20-question tool used in clinical research to assess health-related quality of life in multiple myeloma patients. The QLQ-MY20 includes four domains (Disease Symptoms, Side-Effects of Treatment, Body Image and Future Perspective).
The EORTC QLQ-MY20 Disease Symptoms Scale is scored between 0 and 100, with a high score reflecting a higher level of symptoms. Negative change from Baseline values indicate reduction (i.e. improvement) in symptoms and positive values indicate increase (i.e. worsening) of symptoms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 of Cycle 1 (Baseline), and Day 1 of Cycles 2, 3, 4, 5 and 6</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in the EORTC QLQ-MY20 Side Effects Domain - The European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer QoL Questionnaire for Patients with Multiple Myeloma (EORTC QLQ-MY20) is a 20-question tool used in clinical research to assess health-related quality of life in multiple myeloma patients. The QLQ-MY20 includes four domains (Disease Symptoms, Side-Effects of Treatment, Body Image and Future Perspective).
The EORTC QLQ-MY20 Side Effects Scale is scored between 0 and 100, with a high score reflecting a higher level of symptoms. Negative change from Baseline values indicate reduction in side effects (i.e.improvement in symptom) and positive values indicate increase in side effects (i.e. worsening of symptom).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 of Cycle 1 (Baseline), and Day 1 of Cycles 2, 3, 4, 5 and 6</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in the European Quality of Life-5 Dimensions (EQ-5D) Utility Index Score - EQ-5D is a self-administered questionnaire that assesses health-related quality of life (QOL). The EQ-5D descriptive health profile comprises five dimensions of health (mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort, and anxiety/depression). Each dimension has 3 levels of response: No problem (1), some problems (2), and extreme problems (3). A unique EQ-5D health state is defined by combining one level from each of the five dimensions into a single utility index score. EQ-5D index values range from -0.59 to 1.00 where an EQ-5D score of 1.00 equals "perfect health", a score of 0 equals "death" and a score of -0.59 equals worst imaginable health state. A positive change from Baseline score indicates improvement in health status. A negative change from Baseline score indicates worsening in health status. Negative scores represent the possible though unlikely situation that a patient's QOL is worse than death, i.e. they would rather be dead than living with that QOL</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 of Cycle 1 (Baseline), and Day 1 of Cycles 2, 3, 4, 5 and 6</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to First Worsening of Quality of Life (QOL) Domains - Time to worsening in quality of life domains was calculated as the time from Baseline to the first worsened minimally important difference (MID), defined as the smallest change in a QOL score considered important to patients that would lead the patient or clinician to consider a change in therapy. MID thresholds were calculated in Standard Error of Measurement (SEM) units using the Baseline QOL data. Based on the MID, participants were classified as worsened according to the following:
For the EORTC QLQ-C30 global health status and functional scales and the EQ-5D health utility score, participants were classified as worsened if their change from Baseline score was less than -1 SEM.
For the EORTC QLQ-C30 symptom scores (fatigue and pain) and EORTC QLQ-MY20 disease symptoms and side effects scales, participants were classified as worsened if their change from Baseline score was greater than 1 SEM.
See previous outcome measures for definitions of each scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed on Day 1 of the first 6 treatment cycles.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Must be = 18 years of age

          -  Subjects must have documented diagnosis of multiple myeloma and have measurable
             disease

          -  Subjects must have undergone prior treatment with = 2 treatment lines of anti-myeloma
             therapy

          -  Subjects must have either refractory or relapsed and refractory disease defined as
             documented disease progression during or within 60 days of completing their last
             myeloma therapy

          -  All subjects must have received at least 2 consecutive cycles of prior treatment that
             included lenalidomide and bortezomib

          -  All subjects must have failed treatment with both lenalidomide and bortezomib in one
             of the following ways: 1) Documented progressive disease on or within 60 days of
             completing treatment with lenalidomide and/or bortezomib, or 2) In case of prior
             response [= partial response (PR)] to lenalidomide or bortezomib, subjects must have
             relapsed within 6 months after stopping treatment with lenalidomide and/or
             bortezomib-containing regimens, or 3) Subjects who have not had a = minimal response
             (MR) and have developed intolerance/toxicity after a minimum of two cycles of
             lenalidomide- and/or bortezomib-containing regimen

          -  Patients must have received adequate prior alkylator therapy

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status score of 0, 1, or 2

          -  Females of childbearing potential (FCBP) must not become pregnant for 28 days prior to
             initiation of study drug, during the study, and for 28 days after discontinuation

          -  Females must agree to abstain from breastfeeding during study participation and 28
             days after study drug discontinuation

          -  Males must agree to use a latex condom during any sexual during the study and for 28
             days following discontinuation from this study

          -  Males must also agree to refrain from donating semen or sperm while on pomalidomide
             and for 28 days after discontinuation from this study</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Any of the following laboratory abnormalities:

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &lt; 1,000/µL

               -  Platelet count &lt; 75,000/ µL for subjects in whom &lt; 50% of bone marrow nucleated
                  cells are plasma cells

               -  Creatinine Clearance &lt; 45 mL/min

               -  Corrected serum calcium &gt; 14 mg/dL

               -  Hemoglobin = 8 g/dL

               -  Serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase (SGOT)/ aspartate aminotransferase (AST)
                  or Transaminase, serum glutamic pyruvic (SGPT)/ alanine aminotransferase (ALT) &gt;
                  3.0 x upper limit of normal (ULN)

               -  Serum total bilirubin &gt; 2.0 mg/dL

          -  Previous therapy with Pomalidomide

          -  Hypersensitivity to thalidomide, lenalidomide, or dexamethasone

          -  Resistance to high-dose dexamethasone used in the last line of therapy

          -  Peripheral neuropathy = Grade 2

          -  Subjects who received an allogeneic bone marrow or allogeneic peripheral blood stem
             cell transplant

          -  Subjects who are planning for or who are eligible for stem cell transplant

          -  Subjects with any one of the following: 1) Congestive heart failure, 2) Myocardial
             infarction within 12 months prior to starting study treatment, 3) Unstable or poorly
             controlled angina pectoris, including Prinzmetal variant angina pectoris

          -  Subjects who received any of the following within the last 14 days of initiation of
             study treatment: 1) Plasmapheresis, 2) Major surgery, 3) Radiation therapy, 4) Use of
             any anti-myeloma drug therapy

          -  Use of any investigational agents within 28 days or 5 half-lives (whichever is longer)
             of treatment

          -  Subjects with conditions requiring chronic steroid or immunosuppressive treatment

          -  Any condition including the presence of laboratory abnormalities, which places the
             subject at unacceptable risk if he/she were to participate in the study

          -  Incidence of gastrointestinal disease that may significantly alter the absorption of
             pomalidomide

          -  Subjects unable or unwilling to undergo antithrombotic prophylactic treatment

          -  Any serious medical condition, laboratory abnormality, or psychiatric illness that
             would prevent the subjects from signing the informed consent form

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding females

          -  Known Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) positivity or active infectious hepatitis A,
             B or C</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>11/03/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>455</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>29/08/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>Peter MacCallum Cancer Institute - East Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Frankston Hospital - Frankston</hospital>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Brisbane</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>Alfred hospital - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital - Nedlands</hospital>
    <hospital>Calvary Mater Hospital - Waratah</hospital>
    <hospital>Border Medical Oncology - Wodonga</hospital>
    <hospital>Wollongong Hospital - Wollongong</hospital>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>3002 - East Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3199 - Frankston</postcode>
    <postcode>QLD4102 - Brisbane</postcode>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
    <postcode>NSW 2298 - Waratah</postcode>
    <postcode>3690 - Wodonga</postcode>
    <postcode>2500 - Wollongong</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Minnesota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Gent</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Leuven</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Yvoir</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Alberta</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>British Columbia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Nova Scotia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Quebec</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Praha 2</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Denmark</country>
      <state>Aalborg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Denmark</country>
      <state>Arhus C</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Denmark</country>
      <state>Odense C</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Denmark</country>
      <state>Vejle</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Angers Cedex 01</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Bayonne</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>La Roche sur Yon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Lille</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Marseille Cedex 9</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Nantes Cedex 1</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Paris, Cedex 10</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Paris</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Pessac</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Pierre Bénite</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Tours</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Tulouse cedex 9</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Vandoeuvre</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Dresden</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Essen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Hamburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Heidelberg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Jena</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Leipzig</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Tübingen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Ulm</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Wuerzburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Athens</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Bologna</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Genova</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Napoli</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Orbassano</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Padova</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Placenza</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Reggio Emilia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Rome</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Torino</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Amsterdam</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Rotterdam</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Utrecht</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Moscow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Saint Petersburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>St. Petersburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Badalona (Barcelona)</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Salamanca</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>San Sebastián (Guipuzcoa)</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Santander</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Valencia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Göteborg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Lund</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Stockholm</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Uppsala</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state>Berne</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state>Geneva</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state>Zürich</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Bournemouth</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Leeds</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Newcastle Upon Tyne</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Nottingham</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Plymouth</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Sheffield</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Sutton-Surrey</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Wolverhampton</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Celgene</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to compare efficacy and safety of pomalidomide in combination
      with low-dose dexamethasone versus high-dose dexamethasone in subjects with refractory or
      relapsed and refractory multiple myeloma.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01311687</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mohamed Zaki, MD, PhD</name>
      <address>Celgene</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>