<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5991">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/11/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/11/2015</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02626000</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Talimogene Laherparepvec With Pembrolizumab for Recurrent Metastatic Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Head and Neck (MASTERKEY232 / KEYNOTE-137)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 1b/3 Multicenter, Randomized, Trial of Talimogene Laherparepvec in Combination With Pembrolizumab for the Treatment of Subjects With Recurrent or Metastatic Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Head and Neck</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>MASTERKEY232</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>20130232 / KEYNOTE-137</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>20130232</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Carcinoma of the Head and Neck</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Non melanoma skin cancer</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Head and neck</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Talimogene laherparepvec in combination with pembrolizumab

Experimental: Phase 1b - Talimogene laherparepvec in combination with pembrolizumab


Treatment: drugs: Talimogene laherparepvec in combination with pembrolizumab
Talimogene laherparepvec will be administered in combination with pembrolizumab starting on day 1. Talimogene laherparepvec: 10^6 PFU/mL followed 3 weeks (+ 3 days) later by 10^8 PFU/mL every 3 weeks (± 3 days). Pembrolizumab: 200 mg will be administered intravenously every 3 weeks (± 3 days). The second dose of pembrolizumab will be administered 3 weeks (+ 3 days) after the initial dose. Subjects will be followed up for serious adverse events until 90 (+ 7) days after the cessation of all study treatment or 30 (+7) days following cessation of treatment if the subject initiates new anticancer therapy (whichever is earlier)

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of Dose Limiting Toxicity - To evaluate the safety, as assessed by incidence of dose limiting toxicity (DLT), of talimogene laherparepvec in combination with pembrolizumab</outcome>
      <timepoint>At least 6 wks from the initial dosing and 2 doses of treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of treatment-emergent and treatment-related AEs - All adverse events, grade = 3 adverse events, serious adverse events, fatal adverse events, adverse events and serious adverse events leading to discontinuation of treatment, and adverse events defined as events of interest) and clinical laboratory abnormalities.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Start of treatment to 30 (+7) days after end of treatme</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Objective Response Rate - Response evaluation by investigator using irRECIST</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 24 months of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Best Overall Response - Response evaluation by investigator using irRECIST</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 24 months of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of Response - Response evaluation by investigator using irRECIST</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 24 months of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disease Control Rate - Response evaluation by investigator using irRECIST</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 24 months of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression Free Survival - Response evaluation by investigator using irRECIST</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 24 months of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Survival</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 24 months of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion Criteria

          -  Male or female age = 18 years at the time of informed consent

          -  Histologically confirmed diagnosis of metastatic or recurrent SCCHN of the oral
             cavity, oropharynx, hypopharynx, or larynx. Disease must be unsuitable for curative
             surgical resection and must not be amenable to curative radiotherapy.

          -  Disease must have progressed after treatment with a platinum-containing regimen and
             should be defined as one of the following:

             i. disease progression or recurrence between 3 to 6 months of prior curatively
             intended multimodal therapy (which includes platinum therapy) for locoregionally
             advanced SCCHN. ii. disease progression or recurrence after prior platinum therapy in
             the recurrent or metastatic setting Note: This criterion is only applicable for
             subjects who have not had treatment in the recurrent/metastatic setting

          -  Subject must be candidate for intralesional therapy administration defined as one or
             more of the following:

             i. at least 1 injectable cutaneous, subcutaneous, or nodal SCCHN tumor = 10 mm in
             longest diameter ii. multiple injectable cutaneous, subcutaneous, or nodal SCCHN
             tumors that in aggregate have a longest diameter of = 10 mm Note: Mucosal surfaces of
             tumor lesions and visceral metastases should not be injected.

          -  ECOG performance status of 0 or 1

          -  Adequate organ function determined within 14 days prior to enrollment

          -  Female subject of childbearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test within 72
             hours prior to enrollment.

          -  Other Inclusion Criteria May Apply</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion Criteria

          -  Has known active CNS metastases and/or carcinomatous meningitis.

          -  Primary nasopharyngeal carcinoma.

          -  Subject at risk of airway compromise in the event of postinjection tumor
             swelling/inflammation based on investigator judgment.

          -  Phase 3: Previous treatment with 3 or more systemic regimens given for recurrent
             and/or metastatic disease

          -  History of other malignancy within the past 3 years

          -  History of interstitial lung disease (ILD).

          -  Prior therapy with talimogene laherparepvec, pembrolizumab, other anti-PD-1, any other
             antibody or drug specifically targeting T-cell co-stimulation or immune check point
             pathway.

          -  History or evidence of active autoimmune disease that has required systemic treatment
             in the past 2 years (ie, with use of disease modifying agents, corticosteroids or
             immunosuppressive drugs).

          -  Evidence of clinically significant immunosuppression

          -  Active herpetic skin lesions or prior complications of herpetic infection (eg,
             herpetic keratitis or encephalitis).

          -  Requires intermittent or chronic treatment with an antiherpetic drug (eg, acyclovir),
             other than intermittent topical use.

          -  Prior chemotherapy, radiotherapy, biological cancer therapy, targeted therapy, or
             major surgery within 28 days prior to enrollment or has not recovered to CTCAE grade 1
             or better from adverse event due to cancer therapy administered more than 28 days
             prior to enrollment.

          -  Expected to require other cancer therapy while on study with the exception of local
             palliative radiation treatment to the site of bone and other metastasis.

          -  Known human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) disease.

          -  Has acute or chronic active hepatitis B virus or hepatitis C virus infection or
             received treatment with nucleotide analogs such as those used in the treatment of
             hepatitis B virus (eg, lamivudine, adefovir, tenofovir, telbivudine, entecavir),
             ribavirin, or interferon alpha within 12 weeks of initiation of study treatment.

          -  Received live vaccine within 28 days prior to enrollment.

          -  Subject is pregnant or breast-feeding, or expecting to conceive or father children
             within the duration of the trial

          -  Female subject of childbearing potential or male subject of reproductive potential who
             is unwilling to use acceptable method(s) of effective contraception during study
             treatment and through 3 months after the last dose of talimogene laherparepvec/placebo
             or 4 months after the last dose of pembrolizumab, whichever is later.

          -  Sexually active subjects or their partners unwilling to use male or female latex
             condom to avoid potential viral transmission during sexual contact while on treatment
             and within 30 days after treatment with talimogene laherparepvec/placebo.

          -  Subject who is unwilling to minimize exposure with his/her blood or other body fluids
             to individuals who are at higher risks for HSV-1 induced complications (eg,
             immunosuppressed individuals, HIV-positive individuals, pregnant women, or children
             under the age of 1 year) during talimogene laherparepvec treatment and through 30 days
             after the last dose of talimogene laherparepvec

          -  Has history of (non-infectious) pneumonitis that required steriods or current
             pneumonitis

          -  Subjects with tumor that directly contacts or encases a major blood vessel AND there
             is ulceration and/or fungation onto the skin surface

          -  Subject has undergone re-irradiation

          -  Other Exclusion Criteria May Apply</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Other</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>6/04/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>4/12/2022</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Research Site - Geelong</hospital>
    <hospital>Research Site - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3220 - Geelong</postcode>
    <postcode>3000 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Delaware</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Illinois</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Kentucky</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Montana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Austria</country>
      <state>Salzburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Bruxelles</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Wilrijk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Bordeaux</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Pierre-Benite</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Toulouse cedex 9</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Athens</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Ioannina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Milano</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Andalucía</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Cataluña</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state>Bellinzona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state>Geneva 14</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state>Zurich</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Birmingham</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Oxford</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Sutton</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Wirral</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Amgen</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A Phase 1b/3 Multicenter, Randomized, Trial of Talimogene Laherparepvec in Combination With
      Pembrolizumab for the Treatment of Subjects with Recurrent or Metastatic Squamous Cell
      Carcinoma of the Head and Neck</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02626000</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>MD</name>
      <address>Amgen</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Amgen Call Center</name>
      <address />
      <phone>866-572-6436</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>medinfo@amgen.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>