<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6150">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/10/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/10/2015</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02585024</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Cytisine Pharmacokinetics and Dose Response (C-DRAKS 3 and C-DRAKS 4)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Cytisine as a Smoking Cessation Agent: Improving Adherence Through a Better Understanding of Pharmacokinetics and Dose Response</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>AMRF reference 1 1 15 011</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Smoking Cessation</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Cytisine

Experimental: 1.5 mg cytisine - 1.5 mg cytisine given as a single dose

Experimental: 3 mg cytisine - 3 mg cytisine given as a single dose

Experimental: 4.5 mg cytisine - 4.5 mg cytisine given as a single dose

Experimental: 1.5 mg cytisine six times a day - 1.5 mg (1 capsule) is given six times a day (0, 2, 4, 6, 8 and 10 hours) for 5 days

Experimental: 3 mg cytisine three times a day - 3 mg (2 capsules) are given three times a day (0, 4 and 8 hours) for 5 days

Experimental: 4.5 mg cytisine two times a day - 4.5 mg (3 capsules) are given two times a day (0 and 6 hours) for 5 days


Treatment: drugs: Cytisine


</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Exposure (AUC) - Plasma cytisine concentrations will be measured in all groups for 24 hours. For Arms 4-6, we will continue to take blood samples to measure cytisine concentrations throughout the dosing period (Days 1-5). Days 3-5: one blood sample will be taken before the first dose for the day. On Day 5 an extra blood sample will be taken at 7.5 hours post the first dose for that day.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Arms 1-3: 24 hours; Arms 4-6: 24 hours, and up to Day 5</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nicotine and cotinine concentrations - Plasma nicotine and cotinine concentrations will be measured along with cytisine concentrations (from the same plasma samples)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Arms 1-3: 24 hours; Arms 4-6: 24 hours, and up to Day 5</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Craving for cigarettes - The brief Questionnaire on Smoking Urges will be administered</outcome>
      <timepoint>Arms 1-3: 0, 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10 and 24 hours. Arms 4-6: 0, 2, 4 ,6, 8, 10, 24 hours; once on Days 3- 5</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure - Systolic and diastolic blood pressure (mm Hg) will be measured with a blood pressure monitor</outcome>
      <timepoint>Arms: 1-3: 0, 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 24 hours. Arms 4-6: 0, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 24 hours; once on Days 3- 5</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Heart rate - Heart rate (beats per minute) will be simultaneously measured with blood pressure using a blood pressure monitor</outcome>
      <timepoint>Arms: 1-3: 0, 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 24 hours. Arms 4-6: 0, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 24 hours; once on Days 3- 5</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Respiratory rate - Respiratory rate (breaths per minute) will be measured along with blood pressure and heart rate</outcome>
      <timepoint>Arms: 1-3: 0, 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 24 hours. Arms 4-6: 0, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 24 hours; once on Days 3- 5</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  be at least 18 years of age,

          -  be able to provide written consent,

          -  have no significant medical or psychiatric disorder (see below under exclusion
             criteria)

          -  smoke at least 10 cigarettes a day</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  they are pregnant or breastfeeding,

          -  they are current users of NRT products,

          -  they are current users of non-NRT smoking cessation therapies (e.g. bupropion
             [Zyban速], clonidine, nortriptyline, or varenicline [Champix速]),

          -  they are enrolled in another smoking cessation programme (concurrent referral to a
             face-to-face provider from Quitline is acceptable) or other cessation study

          -  they have had a heart attack, stroke, or severe angina within the past three months,

          -  they have uncontrolled high blood pressure (&gt; 150 mmHg systolic, &gt; 100 mmHg
             diastolic),

          -  they have phaeochromocytoma,

          -  they have been diagnosed with epilepsy

          -  they suffer from significant mental health problems

          -  they have severe renal impairment

          -  they are taking medications which are significantly affected by cessation of smoking
             (e.g. warfarin, olanzapine, clozapine, therophylline, etc.)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Other</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/02/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>48</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/03/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Auckland, New Zealand</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A number of pharmacotherapies are available for smoking cessation in New Zealand including
      nicotine replacement therapy, bupropion, an antidepressant medication and varenicline. Of
      these, varenicline is the most effective, but also the most expensive. Varenicline acts like
      nicotine and stimulates nicotine receptors in the brain, but to a lesser extent, and
      simultaneously block nicotine binding to its receptors and thus reduces the rewarding effects
      of cigarette smoking. Cytisine (Tabex速 and Desmoxan速) is a plant alkaloid and also acts in a
      similar way to varenicline but is significantly cheaper. It has been used for more than 50
      years in some parts of eastern and central Europe as an aid to quit smoking, but is not
      approved for use in many countries such as New Zealand, Australia, the UK or the US.
      Randomised, placebo-controlled trials have shown that cytisine is more effective than placebo
      and nicotine replacement therapy (NRT)for smoking cessation. However there is a paucity of
      pre-clinical data on cytisine. In particular, there are limited data on the pharmacokinetic
      and the dose response characteristics of cytisine. Furthermore, the current dosing regimen
      recommended by the manufacturer is complex and has no clear basis in empirical research.

      Complexity of dosing has been shown to be a key factor in determining adherence. Therefore, a
      simpler regimen would likely maximise the effectiveness of treatment through improved
      adherence to the treatment regimen. The investigators therefore propose to undertake two
      studies to investigate the influence of dose, dosing frequency and dosing duration on the
      pharmacokinetics and tolerability of cytisine and cigarette craving in smokers.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02585024</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Soo Hee Jeong, Phd</name>
      <address>University of Auckland, New Zealand</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Soo Hee Jeong, PhD</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>s.jeong@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>