<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="791">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/09/2005</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/09/2005</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00174655</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>BIG 02/98 Docetaxel - Breast Cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An Intergroup Phase III Trial to Evaluate the Activity of Docetaxel, Given Either Sequentially or in Combination With Doxorubicin, Followed by CMF, in Comparison to Doxorubicin Alone or in Combination With Cyclophosphamide, Followed by CMF, in the Adjuvant Treatment of Node-positive Breast Cancer Patients.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>RP56976_PR_315</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Breast Neoplasms</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Doxorubicine + docetaxel sequential
Treatment: drugs - doxorubicine + cyclophosphamide sequential
Treatment: drugs - doxorubicine + cyclophosphamide combined
Treatment: drugs - doxorubicine + docetaxel combined

Active Comparator: A1 - 

Active Comparator: A2 - 

Experimental: B - 

Experimental: C - 


Treatment: drugs: Doxorubicine + docetaxel sequential
doxorubicin 75 mg/m² i.v. day 1, q 21 days for 3 cycles, followed by docetaxel 100 mg/m² i.v., 1 hour infusion, day 1, q 21 days for 3 cycles, followed by CMF for 3 cycles

Treatment: drugs: doxorubicine + cyclophosphamide sequential
doxorubicin 75 mg/m² i.v. day 1 q 21 days for 4 cycles, followed by CMF (C: cyclophosphamide 100 mg/m² orally days 1-14, M: methotrexate: 40 mg/m² i.v. days 1 and 8, FU; 5-fluorouracil: 600 mg/m²) i.v. days 1 and 8, q 28 days for 3 cycles

Treatment: drugs: doxorubicine + cyclophosphamide combined
doxorubicin 60 mg/m² i.v. + cyclophosphamide 600 mg/m² i.v., day 1, q 21 days for 4 cycles, followed by CMF for 3 cycles.

Treatment: drugs: doxorubicine + docetaxel combined
doxorubicin 50 mg/m² i.v. + docetaxel 75 mg/m² i.v. 1 hour infusion (1 hour after doxorubicin), day 1, q 21 days for 4 cycles, followed by CMF for 3 cycles.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>DFS of docetaxel arms versus non toxanes arm (DFS: interval from the date of randomization to the date of local, regional or metastatic relapse or the date of second primary cancer or death for any cause whichever occurs first.</outcome>
      <timepoint>810 events or median 5 year follow-up whichever occurs first</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>DFS sequential/combined arms</outcome>
      <timepoint>810 events or median 5 year follow-up whichever occurs first</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety NCI common toxicity criteria</outcome>
      <timepoint>from baseline to study end</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Histologically proven breast cancer. Interval between definitive surgery that includes
             axillary lymph node dissection and registration must be less than 60 days. A
             representative sample of the primary tumor (either blocks or slides) must be sent to
             the operational office, for central pathology reviews, after patients randomization.

          -  Definitive surgical treatment must be either mastectomy or breast conserving surgery,
             with axillary lymph node dissection (not sampling) for operable breast cancer
             (clinical T1-3, N0-1, M0). Margins of resected specimen from definitive surgery must
             be histologically free of invasive adenocarcinoma and ductal carcinoma in situ (DCIS).
             Lobular carcinoma in-situ does not count as a positive margin. Patients with
             histologically-documented infiltration of the skin (pT4) will not be eligible.
             Patients who have a breast conserving procedure with a positive margin may become
             eligible if they subsequently undergo adequate resection or mastectomy with clear
             margins.

          -  Histologic examination of the tumor: invasive adenocarcinoma with at least one
             axillary lymph node (pN1) showing evidence of tumor among a minimum of eight resected
             lymph nodes. All nodes must be examined by the pathologist. The determination of ER
             (estrogen receptor) and PgR (progesterone receptor) is mandatory and results must be
             known by the end of chemotherapy in order to decide whether hormonal therapy is
             indicated (Biochemical or immunohistochemical methods required ; ER and/or PgR
             positivity should be in accordance with the policy in use at each participating
             center. Each center will specify its own policy).

          -  Age &gt; or = 18 years and age &lt; or = 70 years. The upper age limit is not meant to be
             exclusionary but rather is based on the lack of safety data for women &gt; 70 years of
             age.

          -  Karnofsky Performance status index &gt; or = 70 %.

          -  Normal cardiac function must be confirmed by LVEF (MUGA scan or echocardiography). The
             result must be above the lower limit of normal for the institution.

          -  Laboratory requirements: (within 14 days prior to registration)

               -  Hematology

                    -  Neutrophils &gt; or = 2.0 x 109/L

                    -  Platelets &gt; or =100 x 109/L

                    -  Hemoglobin &gt; or = 10 g/dL

               -  Hepatic function

                    -  Total bilirubin &lt; or = 1 UNL

                    -  ASAT (SGOT) and ALAT (SGPT) &lt; or = 1.5 UNL

                    -  Alkaline phosphatase &lt; or = 2.5 UNL

               -  Renal function

                    -  Creatinine &lt; or = 150 µmol/L (1.5 mg/dL)

                    -  If creatinine is borderline, the calculated creatinine clearance should be &gt;
                       or = 60 mL/min (Cockcroft formula).

          -  Complete staging work-up within 3 months prior to registration. All patients will have
             bilateral mammography, chest X-ray (PA and lateral) and/or CT-scan, abdominal
             ultrasound and/or CT scan, bone scan (in case of positive bone scan suspicious for
             metastases, bone X-ray (or bone CT-scan for spine) on hot spots is mandatory to rule
             out the possibility of metastatic hot spots). Other tests may be performed as
             clinically indicated.

          -  Patients must be accessible for treatment and follow-up. Patients registered on this
             trial must be treated and followed at a participating center which could be a
             Principal or a co-investigator's site. In case patient moves during the follow-up,
             every effort should be done to follow the patient in a participating center.

          -  Negative pregnancy test (urine or serum) within 7 days prior to registration for all
             women of childbearing potential. Patients of childbearing potential must implement
             adequate non-hormonal measures to avoid pregnancy during study treatment(chemotherapy,
             radiotherapy and hormonal therapy).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Female</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Prior systemic anticancer therapy for breast cancer (chemo-immuno-hormonotherapy).

          -  Prior radiation therapy for breast cancer.

          -  Pregnant, or lactating patients.

          -  Any locally advanced (clinical or pathological T4 and/or N2-known N3) or
             metastatic(M1) breast cancer.Patients with inoperable residual axillary nodal disease
             or with supraclavicular nodes.

          -  Pre-existing motor or sensory neurotoxicity of a severity ³ grade 2 by NCI criteria.

          -  Other serious illness or medical condition:

               -  congestive heart failure or unstable angina pectoris, previous history of
                  myocardial infarction within 1 year from study entry, uncontrolled hypertension
                  or high-risk uncontrolled arrhythmias

               -  history of significant neurologic or psychiatric disorders including psychotic
                  disorders, dementia or seizures that would prohibit the understanding and giving
                  of informed consent

               -  active uncontrolled infection

               -  active peptic ulcer, unstable diabetes mellitus

          -  Past or current history of other neoplasms except for:

               -  curatively treated basal cell skin cancer

               -  adequately treated in situ carcinoma of the cervix

          -  In regard to past or current history of other breast carcinoma, criteria of exclusion
             are:

               -  past history of ipsilateral or past or current history of contralateral invasive
                  breast carcinoma

               -  past or current history of contralateral ductal in situ breast carcinoma

        A past or current history of ipsilateral ductal in situ or lobular in situ (ipsilateral or
        contralateral) breast carcinoma is not a criterion of exclusion.

          -  Chronic treatment with corticosteroids unless initiated &gt; 6 months prior to study
             entry and at low dose (&lt; or = 20 mg methylprednisolone or equivalent).

          -  Concurrent treatment with hormonal replacement therapy. Prior treatment should be
             stopped before study entry.

          -  Definite contraindications for the use of corticosteroids.

          -  Concurrent treatment with other experimental drugs. Participation in another clinical
             trial with any investigational not marketed drug within 30 days prior to study entry.

          -  Concurrent treatment with any other anti-cancer therapy.

        The above information is not intended to contain all considerations relevant to a patient's
        potential participation in a clinical trial.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/06/1998</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>2887</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/09/2011</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>Sanofi-Aventis - Macquarie Park</hospital>
    <postcode> - Macquarie Park</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Austria</country>
      <state>Vienna</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Diegem</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Sao Paulo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Chile</country>
      <state>Providencia Santiago</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czech Republic</country>
      <state>Praha</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Denmark</country>
      <state>Horsholm</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Berlin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Budapest</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ireland</country>
      <state>Dublin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Natanya</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Milan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <state>Porto Salvo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Slovakia</country>
      <state>Bratislava</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Slovenia</country>
      <state>Ljubljana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Gauteng</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Bromma</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state>Geneve</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Guildford Surrey</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Sanofi</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Primary objectives:

        -  To compare Disease-Free Survival (DFS) of an adjuvant treatment with docetaxel given
           either sequentially or in combination with doxorubicin and followed by CMF to
           doxorubicin alone or in combination with cyclophosphamide and followed by CMF in
           operable breast cancer patients with positive axillary lymph nodes.

      Secondary objectives:

        -  To compare DFS of an adjuvant treatment with doxorubicin followed by docetaxel followed
           by CMF to doxorubicin followed by CMF in operable breast cancer patients with positive
           axillary lymph nodes

        -  To compare DFS of an adjuvant treatment with docetaxel in combination with doxorubicin
           followed by CMF to doxorubicin in combination with cyclophosphamide followed by CMF in
           operable breast cancer patients with positive axillary lymph nodes

        -  To compare DFS of an adjuvant treatment with doxorubicin followed by docetaxel followed
           by CMF to doxorubicin in combination with docetaxel followed by CMF in operable breast
           cancer patients with positive axillary lymph nodes, (sequential mono-chemotherapy versus
           polychemotherapy).

        -  To compare overall survival of treatment arms.

        -  To compare toxicity of treatment arms.

        -  To evaluate pathologic and molecular markers for predicting efficacy.

        -  Socioeconomic data will be collected in order to be able to perform a socioeconomic
           analysis by country, when needed.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00174655</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jean-Philippe Aussel</name>
      <address>Sanofi</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>