<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3649">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/09/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/09/2012</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01693536</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can Primary Care Change Elderly Physical Activity and Salt Intake? An Australian Pilot Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effective Change of Behaviour of the Elderly in Normal General Practice</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ECOBEING</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>RO783</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Health Behaviour</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Behaviour - Lifestyle counselling

Experimental: Lifestyle counselling - Three dietician visits focussed on education to find food with sodium less than 120mg/100gms.
Two physiotherapist visits focussed on teaching personalised sustainable practical exercise.

No Intervention: Control - Control group was offered free skin cancer check and wait listed for the same lifestyle counselling after the six months of the study.


Behaviour: Lifestyle counselling
as in Arm Description

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>the change in morning urine sodium/potassium ratio - this measure is to reflect sodium intake. A 24hr urinary sodium cannot be readily validated as an accurate collection and even in the Trials of Hypertension Prevention study was changed to 8hrs to assist compliance. A spot morning ratio is a useful marker of sodium intake for group evaluation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>between enrollment and six months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>the increased distance in a six minute walk test - to measure objectively an increase in fitness the increase in the six minute walk test was used</outcome>
      <timepoint>between enrollment and six months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>change in systolic BP - teaching people to reduce sodium intake and increase fitness may reduce systolic blood pressure as a secondary outcome</outcome>
      <timepoint>between enrollment and six months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>change in doses/day of antihypertensive medication - teaching reduction in sodium and increased fitness may mean people need less antihypertensive medication as a secondary outcome</outcome>
      <timepoint>between enrollment and six months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>change in waist measurement - teaching increased fitness would be expected to reduce waist measurement as a secondary outcome</outcome>
      <timepoint>between enrollment and six months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>change in weight &amp; BMI - teaching increased fitness would be expected to reduce weight and therefore calculated Body Mass Index as a secondary outcome</outcome>
      <timepoint>between enrollment and six months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>change in cognition measurement - Cognition measurements using the Standardised Mini-Mental State Examination, and the more comprehensive and sensitive Addenbrooke Cognitive Examination to compare those in the intervention group with the highest and lowest quartiles of reduction in sodium intake + increased fitness (equally weighted), as a secondary outcome of teaching these lifestyle changes.</outcome>
      <timepoint>between enrollment and six months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Living independently

          -  Must be able to walk for six minutes</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>75</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>95</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Dementia as defined by Standardised Mini-Mental State Examination score &lt;25/30

          -  All patients of HealthHQ-Southport General Practice</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/10/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>85</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/12/2010</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Health HQ-Southport General Practice - Southport</hospital>
    <postcode>4215 - Southport</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Health HQ</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A randomised controlled trial to test if offering three visits to a dietician + two visits to
      a physiotherapist over six months + a home sphygmomanometer, will result in a reduction in
      sodium intake and an increase in fitness in people over 75yrs. Volunteers were enrolled from
      Oct 2008 to July 2009.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01693536</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Cook NR, Cutler JA, Obarzanek E, Buring JE, Rexrode KM, Kumanyika SK, Appel LJ, Whelton PK. Long term effects of dietary sodium reduction on cardiovascular disease outcomes: observational follow-up of the trials of hypertension prevention (TOHP). BMJ. 2007 Apr 28;334(7599):885-8. Epub 2007 Apr 20.
Lindström J, Ilanne-Parikka P, Peltonen M, Aunola S, Eriksson JG, Hemiö K, Hämäläinen H, Härkönen P, Keinänen-Kiukaanniemi S, Laakso M, Louheranta A, Mannelin M, Paturi M, Sundvall J, Valle TT, Uusitupa M, Tuomilehto J; Finnish Diabetes Prevention Study Group. Sustained reduction in the incidence of type 2 diabetes by lifestyle intervention: follow-up of the Finnish Diabetes Prevention Study. Lancet. 2006 Nov 11;368(9548):1673-9.
Joint Health Surveys Unit (NatCen and UCL). A survey of 24 hour and spot urinary sodium and potassium excretion in a representative sample of the Scottish population. Food Standards Agency Scotland, 2007
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Norman A Hohl, MBBS, FRACGP</name>
      <address>Medical Director Health HQ, Ass Prof Bond Uni Faculty Health Science</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>