<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2294">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/01/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/01/2009</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00866515</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Drug Interaction Study to Investigate Co-administration of GW642444M With Ketoconazole</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Double-blind, Placebo-controlled, Randomised, 2-way Crossover Drug Interaction Study to Investigate the Pharmacokinetic and Pharmacodynamic Effects Following Co-administration of GW642444M With Ketoconazole</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>112205</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pulmonary Disease, Chronic Obstructive</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Ketoconazole + GW642444M
Treatment: drugs - Placebo + GW642444M

Experimental: Active - Ketoconazole 400mg OD days 1-6

Placebo Comparator: Placebo - Placebo OD for 1 to 6 days


Treatment: drugs: Ketoconazole + GW642444M
Ketoconazole 400mg OD days 1-6, GW642444M 25ug single dose on D5

Treatment: drugs: Placebo + GW642444M
Placebo to match D1-6 + GW642444M 25ug single dose on D5

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Supine heart rate and blood potassium levels</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 5</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma GW642444M concentrations</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 5</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reported Adverse Events</outcome>
      <timepoint>treatment periods</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Healthy as determined by a responsible and experienced physician, based on a medical
             evaluation including medical history, physical examination, laboratory tests and
             cardiac monitoring. A subject with a clinical abnormality or laboratory parameters
             outside the reference range for the population being studied may be included at the
             discretion of the Investigator only if the finding is unlikely to introduce additional
             risk factors and will not interfere with the study procedures.

          -  AST, ALT, alkaline phosphatase and bilirubin = 1.5xULN (isolated bilirubin &gt;1.5xULN is
             acceptable if bilirubin is fractionated and direct bilirubin &lt;35%).

          -  Male or female between 18 and 65 years of age inclusive, at the time of signing the
             informed consent.

          -  A female subject is eligible to participate if she is of:

          -  Non-childbearing potential defined as pre-menopausal females with a documented tubal
             ligation, hysterectomy or bilateral oophorectomy; or postmenopausal defined as 12
             months of spontaneous amenorrhea [in questionable cases a blood sample with
             simultaneous follicle stimulating hormone (FSH) &gt; 40 MlU/ml and estradiol &lt; 40 pg/ml
             (&lt;140 pmol/L) is confirmatory]. Females on hormone replacement therapy (HRT) and whose
             menopausal status is in doubt will be required to use one of the contraception methods
             in Section 8.1 if they wish to continue their HRT during the study. Otherwise, they
             must discontinue HRT to allow confirmation of post-menopausal status prior to study
             enrolment. For most forms of HRT, at least 2-4 weeks will elapse between the cessation
             of therapy and the blood draw; this interval depends on the type and dosage of HRT.
             Following confirmation of their post-menopausal status, they can resume use of HRT
             during the study without use of a contraceptive method.

          -  Child-bearing potential and agrees to use one of the contraception methods listed in
             Section 8.1 for an appropriate period of time (as determined by the product label or
             investigator) prior to the start of dosing to sufficiently minimize the risk of
             pregnancy at that point. Female subjects must agree to use contraception until after
             the final follow-up visit has been completed.

          -  Body weight = 50 kg and BMI within the range 19 - 29.9 kg/m2 (inclusive).

          -  Demonstrated ability to use the inhaler device in a satisfactory and repeatable manner

          -  Subjects who are current non-smokers, who have not used any inhaled tobacco products
             (snuff is permitted) in the 12 month period preceding the screening visit and who have
             a pack history of = 10 pack years.

          -  No significant abnormality on 12-lead ECG at screening, including the following
             requirements:

          -  Ventricular rate = 40 beats per minute

          -  PR interval = 120 and = 210 msec

          -  Q waves &lt; 30 msec (up to 50 msec permitted in lead III only)

          -  QRS interval to be = 60 msec and = 120 msec

          -  QTc interval must be &lt; 450 msec (QTcB or QTcF; machine or manual reading) based on an
             average from three ECGs obtained over a brief recording period

          -  FEV1 = 80% predicted and a FEV1 / FVC ratio = 0.7 at screening

          -  Capable of giving written informed consent, which includes compliance with the
             requirements and restrictions listed in the consent form.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  As a result of medical interview, physical examination or screening investigations,
             the principle investigator or delegate physician deems the subject unsuitable for the
             study.

          -  Systolic blood pressure which is outside the range 90 to 140 mmHg, diastolic blood
             pressure outside the range 50 to 90 mmHg or heart rate outside the range 40 to 90 bpm.

          -  The subject has been treated for or diagnosed with depression within six months of
             screening or has a history of significant psychiatric illness.

          -  The subject has any history of breathing problems in adult life (i.e. history of
             asthmatic symptomatology).

          -  A clinically significant abnormality on standard pulmonary function testing, or any
             other finding that would prevent satisfactory administration of the inhaled study
             medication.

          -  Any contraindication to the administration of ketoconazole, as described in the
             current [NIZORAL Product Information, Janssen-Cilag Pty Limited, 2008].

          -  History of sensitivity to any of the study medications, or components thereof
             (including milk protein) or a history of drug or other allergy that, in the opinion of
             the investigator or GSK Medical Monitor, contraindicates their participation.

          -  Currently taking regular (or a course of) medication whether prescribed or not, with
             the exception of those permitted medications listed in Section 8.1 and Section 9.1.

          -  Use of prescription or non-prescription drugs, including vitamins, herbal and dietary
             supplements (including St John's Wort) within 7 days (or 14 days if the drug is a
             potential enzyme inducer) or 5 half-lives (whichever is longer) prior to the first
             dose of study medication, unless in the opinion of the Investigator and GSK Medical
             Monitor the medication will not interfere with the study procedures or compromise
             subject safety.

          -  History of regular alcohol consumption within 6 months of the study defined as:

          -  An average weekly intake of &gt;21 units for males or &gt;14 units for females. One unit is
             equivalent to 8 g of alcohol: a half-pint (~250 mL) of beer, 1 glass (100 mL) of wine
             or 1 measure (30 mL) of spirits.

          -  The subject has participated in a clinical trial and has received a drug or a new
             chemical entity within 30 days or 5 half-lives, or twice the duration of the
             biological effect of any drug (whichever is longer) prior to the first dose of current
             study medication.

          -  Exposure to more than four new chemical entities within 12 months prior to the first
             dosing day.

          -  The subject has donated a unit of blood within the previous 16 weeks or intends to
             donate within 16 weeks after completing the study.

          -  A positive pre-study Hepatitis B surface antigen or positive Hepatitis C antibody
             result within 3 months of screening.

          -  The subject has tested positive for HIV antibodies.

          -  The subject has a positive pre-study urine drug screen/ alcohol breath test. A minimum
             list of drugs that will be screened for include Amphetamines, Barbiturates, Cocaine,
             Opiates, Cannabinoids and Benzodiazepines.

          -  Where participation in the study would result in donation of blood or blood products
             in excess of 500 mL within a 56 day period.

          -  Unwillingness or inability to follow the procedures outlined in the protocol.

          -  Subjects who have a screening haemoglobin value &lt; 110 mg/L.

          -  Pregnant (as determined by positive (serum or urine) hCG test at screening or prior to
             dosing) or lactating females.

          -  Subject is mentally or legally incapacitated.

          -  CO breath monitoring indicative of smoking or history or regular use of tobacco- or
             nicotine-containing products within 6 months prior to screening.

          -  Consumption of red wine, seville oranges, grapefruit or grapefruit juice and/or
             pummelos, exotic citrus fruits, grapefruit hybrids or fruit juices from 7 days prior
             to the first dose of study medication.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>22/12/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>20</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>27/03/2009</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Randwick</hospital>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>GlaxoSmithKline</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This will be a single-centre, randomised, double blind, placebo controlled, two-way crossover
      study in healthy male and female subjects. There will be two treatment periods each
      consisting of 7 days. During each treatment period subjects will receive single doses of
      ketoconazole or placebo on the morning of days 1-6 with a single dose of GW642444M on the
      morning of Day 5.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00866515</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Kempsford R, Allen A, Bal J, Rubin D, Tombs L. The effect of ketoconazole on the pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of inhaled fluticasone furoate and vilanterol trifenatate in healthy subjects. Br J Clin Pharmacol. 2013 Jun;75(6):1478-87. doi: 10.1111/bcp.12019.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>GSK Clinical Trials</name>
      <address>GlaxoSmithKline</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>