<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5595">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/08/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/08/2011</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01420653</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Maxigesic 325 Acute Dental Pain Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Maxigesic 325 Acute Dental Pain Study: A Double-blind, Placebo-controlled, Randomized, Parallel Group Comparison of the Effects of Maxigesic 325 Versus Acetaminophen, Ibuprofen and Placebo in Participants With Acute Dental Pain</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>AFT-MX-6</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Dental Pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Maxigesic 325
Treatment: drugs - Acetaminophen
Treatment: drugs - Ibuprofen
Treatment: drugs - Placebo

Experimental: Maxigesic 325 - Acetaminophen 325mg + ibuprofen 97.5mg per tablet, two tablets every 6 hours, orally

Active Comparator: Acetaminophen - Acetaminophen 325mg per tablet (standard dose acetaminophen), two tablets every 6 hours, orally

Active Comparator: Ibuprofen - Ibuprofen 97.5mg per tablet (i.e. low dose ibuprofen), two tablets every 6 hours, orally

Placebo Comparator: Placebo - Placebo tablets, every 6 hours, orally


Treatment: drugs: Maxigesic 325
Maxigesic USA (acetaminophen 325 mg + ibuprofen 97.5mg), three tablets four times a day with food for 48 hours

Treatment: drugs: Acetaminophen
Acetaminophen 325 mg, 3 tablets four times a day, with food for 48 hours

Treatment: drugs: Ibuprofen
Ibuprofen 97.5mg, three tablets four times a day, with food for 48 hours.

Treatment: drugs: Placebo
placebo, three tablets four times a day, with food for 48 hours

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>SPID (Summed Pain Intensity Differences) - The time-adjusted SPIDs (Summed Pain Intensity Differences) of the VAS pain intensity scores up to 48 ours after the first dose of study medication.</outcome>
      <timepoint>48 hours afte the first dose</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Provides written informed consent before initiation of any study-related procedures.

          -  Males and females aged at least 10 years and not more than 60 years old on the day of
             consent.

          -  Undergoing dental surgery for the extraction of at least 2 impacted third molar teeth.

          -  A resting VAS pain intensity score at baseline (within 6 hours after the completion of
             surgery) of greater than or equal to 40 mm on a 100 mm VAS scale with 0 = no pain and
             100 = worst pain imaginable.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Has taken any NSAID or acetaminophen within 12 hours prior to the stat of surgery
             other than asprin less than or equal to 150 mg/day

          -  Subjects who have received any anaesthetics within 24 hours prior to surgery

          -  Hypersensitivity to opioids

          -  Known to be pregnant or possibly pregnant

          -  Women of childbearing potential who are unwilling to take adequate contraceptive
             precautions, i.e., hormonal contraceptive, an intrauterine device, double-barrier
             method, or abstinence. A women of childbearing potential is defined as any female who
             is less than 2 years post-menopausal or has not undergone a partial or total
             hysterectomy or surgical sterilization, e.g. bilateral tubal ligation, bilateral
             oophorectomy.

          -  Women of childbearing potential who are unwilling to undergo an urine pregnancy test.

          -  Suffering from a neurological disorder relating to pain perception or any acute or
             chronic condition that, in the opinion of the investigator, makes the subject
             unsuitable from an efficacy or safety perspective.

          -  In the opinion of the investigator, unable to understand the visual analogue pain
             score or comply with the protocol requirements.

          -  Currently, or in the last 30 days, has been in a clinical trial involving another
             study drug.

          -  Currently treated with an ACE inhibitor, warfarin, steroid (other than nasal steroids
             or topical steroids with the approval of the investigator) cyclosporin, tacrolimus or
             methotrexate, or any other medication felt by the investigator to interfere with
             safety or efficacy evaluations.

          -  Participant weight &lt; 50 kg or &gt; 120 kg.

          -  Has a history of drug or alcohol abuse.

          -  Suffering from any other disease or condition which, in the opinion of the
             investigator, means that it would not be in the participants best interests to
             participant in the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/04/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>408</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/01/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Waikato</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Christchurch</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>AFT Pharmaceuticals, Ltd.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to determine whether the analgesic effects of Maxigesic USA are
      greater than acetaminophen, ibuprofen or placebo.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01420653</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>John Currie, Doctor</name>
      <address>Clinical Trial New Zealand</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>