<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="1676">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/08/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/08/2007</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00524576</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Challenge Dose of Hepatitis B Vaccine in Subjects Who Previously Received Engerix-B Vaccine</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Administration of a Challenge Dose of Hepatitis B Vaccine in Subjects Who Previously Received Engerix-B Vaccine.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>108988</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hepatitis B</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - Engerix-B

Experimental: Engerix 2 Doses + Challenge Dose - Subjects received 2 doses of Engerix-B (Month 0 and 6) in the primary study and a single dose of Engerix-B during the booster study.

Experimental: Engerix 3 Doses + Challenge Dose - Subjects received 3 doses of Engerix-B (Month 0, 1 and 6) in the primary study and a single dose of Engerix-B during the booster study.


Other interventions: Engerix-B
One dose (10µg Hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg))

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With Immunological Response to Challenge Dose in Terms of Anti-hepatitis B Surface Antigen (Anti-HBs) Antibody Concentration - Immune response defined as:
For initially seronegative subjects (anti-HBs antibody concentration &lt;3.3 milli-international unit per milliliter [mIU/mL] before vaccination) antibody concentration = 10mIU/mL at post booster.
For initially seropositive subjects: antibody concentration at post booster = 4-fold the pre-vaccination antibody concentration.</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days post-challenge dose</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With Anti-HBs Antibody Concentrations Above the Cut-off Value - Anti-HBs antibody cut-off values assessed include 3.3, 10 and 100 mIU/mL.</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days post-challenge dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Concentration of Anti-HBs Antibodies - Concentrations given as geometric mean concentration (GMC) and expressed in mIU/mL.</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days post-challenge dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants Reporting Solicited Local Symptoms - Solicited local symptoms assessed include pain, redness and swelling.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the 4-day follow-up period (Day 0-3) after the challenge dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants Reporting Solicited General Symptoms - Solicited general symptoms assessed include fatigue, fever, gastrointestinal symptoms, and headache.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the 4-day follow-up period (Day 0-3) after the challenge dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants Reporting Unsolicited Adverse Events (AE) - An AE is any untoward medical occurrence in a clinical investigation subject, temporally associated with the use of a medicinal product, whether or not considered related to the medicinal product.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the 31-day follow-up period (Day 0-30) after the challenge dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants Reporting Serious Adverse Events (SAE) - An SAE is any untoward medical occurrence that: results in death, is life-threatening, requires hospitalization or prolongation of existing hospitalization, results in disability/incapacity, is a congenital anomaly/birth defect in the offspring of a study subject, or may evolve into one of the outcomes listed above.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the 31-day follow-up period (Day 0-30) after the challenge dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Subjects who the investigator believes that they can and will comply with the
             requirements of the protocol.

          -  A male or female who had received complete primary vaccination course of hepatitis B
             vaccine in the primary study

          -  Written informed consent obtained from the subject and/or parent/guardian of the
             subject.

          -  Healthy subjects as established by medical history and clinical examination before
             entering into the study.

          -  If the subject is female, she must be of non-childbearing potential or if she is of
             childbearing potential, she must practice adequate contraception for 30 days prior to
             vaccination, have a negative pregnancy test and continue such precautions for 2 months
             after the hepatitis B challenge dose.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>17</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>22</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Use of any investigational/non-registered drug or vaccine other than the study vaccine
             within 30 days preceding the hepatitis B vaccine challenge dose or planned use during
             the study period.

          -  Chronic administration (more than 14 days) of immunosuppressants other
             immune-modifying drugs within six months prior to the hepatitis B vaccine challenge
             dose.

          -  Planned administration/ administration of a vaccine not foreseen by the study protocol
             during the period starting from 30 days before the hepatitis B vaccine challenge dose
             and ending 30 days after.

          -  Subjects who received an additional dose of hepatitis B vaccine outside the context of
             the study between the primary vaccination course and the hepatitis B challenge
             vaccination visit.

          -  Concurrently participating in another clinical study, at any time during the study
             period, in which the subject has been or will be exposed to an investigational or a
             non-investigational product.

          -  History of allergic disease or reactions likely to be exacerbated by any component of
             the vaccine.

          -  Any confirmed or suspected immunosuppressive or immunodeficient condition, based on
             medical history and physical examination.

          -  Acute disease at the time of enrolment.

          -  Acute or chronic, clinically significant hepatic or renal functional abnormality, as
             determined by physical examination or laboratory screening tests.

          -  Administration of immunoglobulins and/or any blood products within the three months
             preceding the hepatitis B vaccine challenge dose or planned administration during the
             study period (one month).

          -  Pregnant or lactating female.

          -  Female planning to become pregnant or planning to discontinue contraceptive
             precautions.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/11/2007</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>144</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/05/2008</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Westmead</hospital>
    <postcode>2145 - Westmead</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Bruxelles</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Wilrijk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>GlaxoSmithKline</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To evaluate the response to an additional dose (challenge dose) of hepatitis B vaccine, when
      given to subjects who had received primary vaccination of Engerix-B vaccine approximately
      72-78 months ago.

      This protocol posting deals with objectives &amp; outcome measures of the challenge phase. The
      Protocol Posting has been updated in order to comply with the FDA Amendment Act, Sep 2007.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00524576</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Van Damme P, Moiseeva A, Marichev I, Kervyn AD, Booy R, Kuriyakose S, Brockway A, Ng SP, Leyssen M, Jacquet JM. Five years follow-up following two or three doses of a hepatitis B vaccine in adolescents aged 11-15 years: a randomised controlled study. BMC Infect Dis. 2010 Dec 20;10:357. doi: 10.1186/1471-2334-10-357.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>GSK Clinical Trials</name>
      <address>GlaxoSmithKline</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>