<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6104">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/09/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/09/2016</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02914353</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Study to Evaluate Safety, PK and PD of Single and Multiple Ascending Doses of EP-7041 in Healthy Subjects</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Study to Evaluate The Safety Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics, and Pharmacodynamcs of Single and Multiple Ascending Doses of EP-7041 in Hea;Thy Subjects</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>EXI-111</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Arthroplasty, Replacement, Knee</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - EP=7041
Treatment: drugs - Placebo

Experimental: Experimental - EP-7041 - Single Ascending Dose: Single IV dose for each cohort; dose range 0.01 mg/kg to 1.0 mg/kg
Multiple Ascending Dose: 0.01 mg/kg/h - 5 x 24 h continuous infusion up to 0.6 mg/kg/h - 5 x 24 h continuous infusion

Placebo Comparator: Placebo - Sterile Saline - Single Ascending Dose: Single IV dose for each cohort;
Multiple Ascending Dose: 5 x 24 h continuous infusion for each cohort


Treatment: drugs: EP=7041
Factor X!a Inhibitor

Treatment: drugs: Placebo
Normal Saline

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of participants with treatment-related adverse events as assessed by CTCAE v4.0 following a single IV bolus of EP-7041 - Assessment of safety and tolerability to EP-7041, administered as a single IV bolus, will be based on adverse events. Each AE will be graded with respect to its relationship to treatment using five categories: not related, unlikely, possible, probable, and highly probable. Each AE will also be graded on a three-point severity scale: mild, moderate, and severe. Adverse events will be coded by body system and preferred term using the MedDRA (Medical Dictionary for Regulatory Activities) dictionary. Assessments as to the effect of EP-7041 on vital signs, 12-lead ECG, telemetry, clinical laboratory parameters, physical examination, and local response to each injection, and body weight will also be made.
The number and percentage of subjects experiencing adverse events will be tabulated for each treatment group by body system and preferred term. The number and percentage of subjects experiencing AEs will also be tabulated by relationship to drug treatment and by severity. If an AE is</outcome>
      <timepoint>Adverse events will be collected and documented during the course of the study. For a period of 30 days following the last study drug administration, adverse events will also be documented if reported.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of participants with treatment-related adverse events as assessed by CTCAE v4.0 following a continuous IV infusion of EP-7041 administered over 5 days - Assessment of safety and tolerability to EP-7041, administered as a continuous IV infusion over 5 days, will be based on adverse events. Each AE will be graded with respect to its relationship to treatment using five categories: not related, unlikely, possible, probable, and highly probable. Each AE will also be graded on a 3-point severity scale: mild, moderate, and severe. Adverse events will be coded by body system and preferred term using the Medical Dictionary for Regulatory Activities dictionary. Assessments as to the effect of EP-7041 on vital signs, 12-lead ECG, telemetry, clinical laboratory parameters, physical examination, and local response to each injection, and body weight will also be made. The number and percentage of subjects experiencing adverse events will be tabulated for each treatment group by body system and preferred term.
The number and percentage of subjects experiencing AEs will also be tabulated by relationship to drug treatment and by severity.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Adverse events will be collected and documented during the course of the study. For a period of 30 days following the last study drug administration, adverse events will also be documented if reported.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of Maximum Plasma Concentration Achieved Following a Single IV Bolus of EP-7041 - Maximum Plasma Concentration (Cmax)</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of Time of Maximum Plasma Concentration Following a Single IV Bolus of EP-7041 - Time of Maximum Plasma Concentration (Tmax)</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of Plasma Half-Life Following a Single IV Bolus of EP-7041 - Plasma Half-Life (T½)</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of ClearanceFollowing a Single IV Bolus of EP-7041 - Clearance (CL)</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of the Area Under the Plasma Concentration versus Time Curve Following a Single IV Bolus of EP-7041 - Area Under the Curve (AUC)</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of the Elimination Rate Constant Following a Single IV Bolus of EP-7041 - Elimination Rate Constant (Kel)</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of the Apparent Volume of Distribution Following a Single IV Bolus of EP-7041 - Apparent Volume of Distribution (Vd)</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of the Steady-State Concentration with a the Initiation of Continuous IV 5-day Infusion of EP-7041 - Concentration at Steady State (Css)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of the Time to Reach a Steady-State Concentration Following a the Initiation of Continuous IV 5-day Infusion of EP-7041 - Time to Reach Concentration at Steady State (Tss)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of the Clearance During the Course of a Continuous IV 5-day Infusion of EP-7041 - Clearance (CL)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of the Plasma Half-Life Following the Discontinuation of Continuous IV 5-day Infusion of EP-7041 - Plasma Half-Life (T½)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 day</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of Clotting Biomarker Activated Partial Thromboplastin Time Following a Single IV Bolus of EP-7041 - Activated Partial Thromboplastin Time (aPTT)</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 day</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of Clotting Biomarker Activated Partial Thromboplastin Time During the Course of a Continuous IV 5-day Infusion of EP-7041 - Activated Partial Thromboplastin Time (aPTT)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of Clotting Biomarker Prothrombin Following a Single IV Bolus of EP-7041 - Prothrombin Time (PT)</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 day</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of Clotting Biomarker Prothrombin During the Course of a Continuous IV 5-day Infusion of EP-7041 - Prothrombin Time (PT)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 day</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of Clotting Biomarker International Normalized Ratio Following a Single IV Bolus of EP-7041 - International Normalized Ratio (INR)</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 day</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of Clotting Biomarker International Normalized Ratio During the Course of a Continuous IV 5-day Infusion of EP-7041 - International Normalized Ratio (INR)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Male or female, non-smoker (no use of tobacco products within 3 months prior to
             screening), =18 and =60 years of age, with Body Mass Index (BMI) &gt; 18.5 and &lt; 32.0
             kg/m2 and a weight of at least 60 kg but not greater than 100 kg.

          -  Healthy as defined by:

               1. No history of abnormal bleeding episodes, e.g. nosebleeds, or abnormally heavy
                  periods, or extensive bleeding after injury, surgery or dental work.

               2. A normal short physical examination and normal vital signs (heart rate (HR),
                  blood pressure (BP) and tympanic body temperature).

               3. Normal laboratory tests (hematology, biochemistry, urinalysis, coagulation tests
                  (aPTT and PT).

               4. the absence of clinically significant illness and surgery within 4 weeks prior to
                  dosing.

               5. the absence of clinically significant history of neurological, endocrinal,
                  cardiovascular, pulmonary, hematological, immunologic, psychiatric,
                  gastrointestinal, renal, hepatic, and metabolic disease.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Any clinically significant abnormality or abnormal laboratory test results found
             during medical screening which, at the investigator's discretion, warrants exclusion
             or positive test for hepatitis B, hepatitis C, or HIV.

          -  Use of any drugs known to induce or inhibit hepatic drug metabolism within 30 days
             prior to drug administration.

          -  Positive pregnancy test at screening or check-in (Day -1).

          -  Clinically significant ECG abnormalities or vital sign abnormalities (systolic blood
             pressure lower than 90 or over 160 mmHg, diastolic blood pressure lower than 50 or
             over 90 mmHg, or heart rate less than 40 or over 100 bpm) at screening or check-in
             (Day -1).

          -  Participation in a clinical trial involving the administration of an investigational
             or marketed drug within 30 days (90 days for biologics), or five (5) half-lives,
             whichever is longer, prior to the first dosing or concomitant participation in an
             investigational study involving no drug administration.

          -  Hemoglobin or hematocrit clinically significantly less than lower limits of normal at
             screening.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2>The people administering the treatment/s</masking2>
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>80</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/05/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>IDT CMAX - Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode> - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>eXIthera Pharmaceuticals</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>IDT CMAX Clinical Trials</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>INC Research</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>CPR Pharma Services Pty Ltd, Australia</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This First-In-Human study will evaluate the safety and tolerability, pharmacokinetic profile,
      and pharmacodynamic effects of EP-7041, a novel Factor XIa inhibitor, following IV
      administration of single ascending doses in healthy normal volunteers, and following
      continuous IV infusions of multiple ascending doses in healthy normal volunteers.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02914353</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sepehr Shakib, MD</name>
      <address>IDT CMAX</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>