<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4336">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/03/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/03/2014</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02083965</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pharmacokinetics of rFVIIIFc at Two Vial Strengths</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomized, Open-Label, Crossover Study to Evaluate the Pharmacokinetics of 2 Vial Strengths of Recombinant Factor VIII Fc Fusion Protein (rFVIIIFc; BIIB031) in Previously Treated Subjects With Severe Hemophilia A</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>2013-003013-18</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>997HA307</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Severe Hemophilia A</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Clotting disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human Genetics and Inherited Disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other human genetics and inherited disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - rFVIIIFc

Experimental: rFVIIIFc 1000 / 3000 PK Assessment - A single intravenous (IV) injection of rFVIIIFc 50 IU/kg at a strength of 1000 IU/vial followed by a single IV injection of rFVIIIFc 50 IU/kg at a strength of 3000 IU/vial.
Following the PK assessment, participants will receive either an episodic (on-demand) regimen with doses between 20 and 50 IU/kg based on the severity of the bleeding episode, or 1 of 2 prophylactic regimens: 50 IU/kg every 3 to 5 days or 65 IU/kg weekly. Participants will be allowed to switch from one regimen to another if approved by the Investigator.

Experimental: rFVIIIFc 3000 / 1000 PK Assessment - A single IV injection of rFVIIIFc 50 IU/kg at a strength of 3000 IU/vial followed by a single IV injection of rFVIIIFc 50 IU/kg at a strength of 1000 IU/vial.
Following the PK assessment, participants will receive either an episodic (on-demand) regimen with doses between 20 and 50 IU/kg based on the severity of the bleeding episode, or 1 of 2 prophylactic regimens: 50 IU/kg every 3 to 5 days or 65 IU/kg weekly. Participants will be allowed to switch from one regimen to another if approved by the Investigator.


Other interventions: rFVIIIFc
Administered as specified in the treatment arm.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Area Under the Concentration-time Curve From Time Zero to Infinity (AUCinf) as Measured by Activated Partial Thromboplastin Time (aPTT) Clotting Assay - Area under the plasma concentration versus time curve (AUC) from time zero (pre-dose) to extrapolated infinite time (0 - 8).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, 0.5 hour (+-5 minutes); 1 hour and 6 hours (+-10 minutes); and 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours (+-60 minutes) after each injection</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incremental Recovery (IR, K Value) as Estimated From the FVIII Activity Data Measured by aPTT Clotting Assay - The rise in FVIII activity in IU/dL per unit dose administered in IU/kg (IR, K value), as estimated from the FVIII activity data.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, 0.5 hour (+-5 minutes); 1 hour and 6 hours (+-10 minutes); and 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours (+-60 minutes) after each injection</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximum Activity (Cmax) as Measured by the aPTT Clotting Assay - Maximum measured concentration of rFVIIIFc.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, 0.5 hour (+-5 minutes); 1 hour and 6 hours (+-10 minutes); and 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours (+-60 minutes) after each injection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Half-life (t½) as Measured by aPTT Clotting Assay - Time required for the concentration of the drug to reach half of its original value.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, 0.5 hour (+-5 minutes); 1 hour and 6 hours (+-10 minutes); and 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours (+-60 minutes) after each injection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clearance (CL) as Measured by the aPTT Clotting Assay - The measure of the efficiency of the body to remove the drug and the unit is the volume of the plasma or blood cleared of drug per unit time.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, 0.5 hour (+-5 minutes); 1 hour and 6 hours (+-10 minutes); and 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours (+-60 minutes) after each injection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Volume of Distribution at Steady State (Vss) as Measured by the aPTT Clotting Assay - The apparent volume of distribution at steady state. (Volume of distribution is defined as the theoretical volume in which the total amount of drug would need to be uniformly distributed to produce the desired blood concentration of a drug.)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, 0.5 hour (+-5 minutes); 1 hour and 6 hours (+-10 minutes); and 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours (+-60 minutes) after each injection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Residence Time (MRT) as Measured by the aPTT Clotting Assay - The average time at which the number of absorbed molecules reside in the body, after single-dose administration.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, 0.5 hour (+-5 minutes); 1 hour and 6 hours (+-10 minutes); and 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours (+-60 minutes) after each injection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time of Cmax (Tmax) as Measured by aPTT Clotting Assay - Time at which maximum activity (Cmax) is observed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, 0.5 hour (+-5 minutes); 1 hour and 6 hours (+-10 minutes); and 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours (+-60 minutes) after each injection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Area Under the Curve to the Last Measurable Time Point (AUClast) as Measured by aPTT Clotting Assay - Area under the plasma concentration time-curve from zero to the last measured concentration.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, 0.5 hour (+-5 minutes); 1 hour and 6 hours (+-10 minutes); and 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours (+-60 minutes) after each injection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Terminal Exponential Rate Constant (Lambda Z) as Measured by aPTT Clotting Assay - First order rate constant associated with the terminal portion of the curve (lambda z) .</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, 0.5 hour (+-5 minutes); 1 hour and 6 hours (+-10 minutes); and 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours (+-60 minutes) after each injection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of AUCinf From the Last Data Point to Infinity (AUCext) as Measured by aPTT Clotting Assay - Percentage of AUCinf extrapolated from the last data point to infinity.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, 0.5 hour (+-5 minutes); 1 hour and 6 hours (+-10 minutes); and 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours (+-60 minutes) after each injection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dose Normalized Area Under the Curve (DNAUC) as Measured by aPTT Clotting Assay - Dose normalized area under the FVIII activity-time curve.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, 0.5 hour (+-5 minutes); 1 hour and 6 hours (+-10 minutes); and 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours (+-60 minutes) after each injection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Terminal Exponential Volume of Distribution (Vz) as Measured by aPTT - The theoretical volume in which the total amount of drug would need to be uniformly distributed to produce the desired plasma concentration of a drug.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, 0.5 hour (+-5 minutes); 1 hour and 6 hours (+-10 minutes); and 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours (+-60 minutes) after each injection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>AUCinf as Estimated From the FVIII Activity Data as Measured by Two-Stage Chromogenic Clotting Assay - Area under the plasma concentration versus time curve (AUC) from time zero (pre-dose) to extrapolated infinite time (0 - 8).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, 0.5 hour (+-5 minutes); 1 hour and 6 hours (+-10 minutes); and 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours (+-60 minutes) after each injection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>IR, K Value as Measured by Two-Stage Chromogenic Clotting Assay - The rise in FVIII activity in IU/dL per unit dose administered in IU/kg (IR, K value), as estimated from the FVIII activity data.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, 0.5 hour (+-5 minutes); 1 hour and 6 hours (+-10 minutes); and 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours (+-60 minutes) after each injection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cmax as Measured by Two-Stage Chromogenic Clotting Assay - Maximum measured concentration of rFVIIIFc.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, 0.5 hour (+-5 minutes); 1 hour and 6 hours (+-10 minutes); and 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours (+-60 minutes) after each injection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>t½ as Measured by Two-Stage Chromogenic Clotting Assay - Time required for the concentration of the drug to reach half of its original value.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, 0.5 hour (+-5 minutes); 1 hour and 6 hours (+-10 minutes); and 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours (+-60 minutes) after each injection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>CL as Measured by Two-Stage Chromogenic Clotting Assay - The measure of the efficiency of the body to remove the drug and the unit is the volume of the plasma or blood cleared of drug per unit time.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, 0.5 hour (+-5 minutes); 1 hour and 6 hours (+-10 minutes); and 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours (+-60 minutes) after each injection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Vss as Measured by Two-Stage Chromogenic Clotting Assay - The apparent volume of distribution at steady state. (Volume of distribution is defined as the theoretical volume in which the total amount of drug would need to be uniformly distributed to produce the desired blood concentration of a drug.)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, 0.5 hour (+-5 minutes); 1 hour and 6 hours (+-10 minutes); and 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours (+-60 minutes) after each injection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>MRT as Measured by Two-Stage Chromogenic Clotting Assay - The average time at which the number of absorbed molecules reside in the body, after single-dose administration.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, 0.5 hour (+-5 minutes); 1 hour and 6 hours (+-10 minutes); and 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours (+-60 minutes) after each injection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tmax as Measured by Two-Stage Chromogenic Clotting Assay - Time at which maximum activity (Cmax) is observed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, 0.5 hour (+-5 minutes); 1 hour and 6 hours (+-10 minutes); and 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours (+-60 minutes) after each injection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>AUClast as Measured by Two-Stage Chromogenic Clotting Assay - Area under the plasma concentration time-curve from zero to the last measured concentration.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, 0.5 hour (+-5 minutes); 1 hour and 6 hours (+-10 minutes); and 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours (+-60 minutes) after each injection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lambda Z as Measured by Two-Stage Chromogenic Clotting Assay - First order rate constant associated with the terminal portion of the curve (lambda z).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, 0.5 hour (+-5 minutes); 1 hour and 6 hours (+-10 minutes); and 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours (+-60 minutes) after each injection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>AUCext as Measured by Two-Stage Chromogenic Clotting Assay - Percentage of AUCinf extrapolated from the last data point to infinity.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, 0.5 hour (+-5 minutes); 1 hour and 6 hours (+-10 minutes); and 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours (+-60 minutes) after each injection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>DNAUC as Measured by Two-Stage Chromogenic Clotting Assay - Dose normalized area under the FVIII activity-time curve.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, 0.5 hour (+-5 minutes); 1 hour and 6 hours (+-10 minutes); and 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours (+-60 minutes) after each injection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Vz as Measured by Two-Stage Chromogenic Clotting Assay - The theoretical volume in which the total amount of drug would need to be uniformly distributed to produce the desired plasma concentration of a drug.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, 0.5 hour (+-5 minutes); 1 hour and 6 hours (+-10 minutes); and 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours (+-60 minutes) after each injection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Development of Inhibitor as Measured by the Nijmegen-Modified Bethesda Assay - An inhibitor test result =0.6 Bethesda units (BU)/mL, confirmed on 2 separate samples drawn 2 to 4 weeks apart, was considered positive. Both tests were to be performed by the central laboratory using the Nijmegen-modified Bethesda Assay. An exact 95% confidence interval (CI) for the proportion of subjects with a confirmed inhibitor was calculated using the Clopper-Pearson method for a binomial proportion. Percentage of participants with confirmed inhibitor development was summarized overall.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, Month 3, Month 6/early withdrawal. Additionally: If inhibitor suspected; at 10-15 EDs; 2-4 weeks prior to scheduled surgery; preoperatively on day of surgery; 1-2 weeks post-surgery; at last postoperative visit (last 2 for major surgery only)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Key 

          -  Have severe hemophilia A

          -  Previously treated subject, defined as having at least 150 documented prior exposure
             days to any recombinant and/or plasma-derived FVIII and/or cryoprecipitate products
             (other than any use of rFVIIIFc- study drug or commercial product) at Day 1. Fresh
             frozen plasma treatment must not be considered in the count for documented exposure
             days.

          -  No history of a positive inhibitor test or clinical signs of decreased response to
             FVIII administrations. Family history of inhibitors will not exclude subjects.

          -  No measurable inhibitor activity using the Nijmegen-modified Bethesda assay at
             Screening.

          -  Platelet count =100,000 platelets/µL at screening

          -  CD4 lymphocytes &gt;200 mm3 if known as HIV antibody positive at screening.

          -  Viral load of &lt;400 copies/mL if known HIV antibody positive at screening.

        Key</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>12</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Male</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Subject is at high risk of bleeding during the 5-day period between the first and
             second injections for PK analyses, as per Investigator discretion.

          -  Previous treatment with rFVIIIFc as study drug or commercial product.

          -  Other coagulation disorder(s) in addition to hemophilia A.

          -  History of hypersensitivity or anaphylaxis associated with any FVIII or IV
             immunoglobulin administration.

          -  Currently taking (or likely to require during the study) acetylsalicylic acid (ASA),
             except for low-dose ASA as prophylaxis (other nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs are
             permitted).

          -  Concurrent systemic treatment with immunosuppressive drugs within 12 weeks prior to
             Day 1. Exceptions to this include: ribavirin for treatment of hepatitis C virus (HCV),
             and/or systemic steroids (a total of 2 courses of pulse treatments lasting no more
             than 7 days at a dose of =1 mg/kg within 12 weeks prior to Day 1) and/or inhaled
             steroids.

        NOTE: Other protocol-defined inclusion/exclusion Criteria May Apply</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/03/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>19</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/05/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>Research Site - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>Research Site - Perth</hospital>
    <postcode> - Herston</postcode>
    <postcode> - Perth</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Utah</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Washington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Basingstoke</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Cambridge</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Bioverativ Therapeutics Inc.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary objective of the study is to characterize the pharmacokinetics (PK) of rFVIIIFc
      administered at vial strengths of 1000 and 3000 IU in subjects with severe hemophilia A. The
      secondary objective of the study is to evaluate the safety of rFVIIIFc beyond the PK
      assessment for up to 6 months for a continued treatment period.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02083965</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Medical Director</name>
      <address>Bioverativ Therapeutics Inc.</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>