<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2160">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/10/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/10/2008</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00782262</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Weight Loss Effects on Heart and Blood Vessel Function in Obesity</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of Obesity and Diet Induced Weight Loss on Cardiovascular Risk Factors, Vascular and Ventricular Structure and Function in Obese Men</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>050226</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - KicStart

Other: Group 1 (n=20) - BP &lt; 140/90, no diabetes mellitus and fasting glucose &lt; 5.5

Other: Group 2 (n=20) - BP &gt; 140/100, no diabetes mellitus and fasting glucose &lt; 5.5

Other: Group 3 (n=20) - BP &lt;140/100, no diabetes mellitus, fasting glucose 5.5 - 6.9


Other interventions: KicStart
KicStart is a nutritionally complete, but lower energy formulated liquid meal. Two sachets of KicStart (one for breakfast and one for lunch) provides 450 cal of energy per day, 0.8 grams per kilogram ideal body weight of high quality protein, and the recommended daily allowances (RDI) of minerals, vitamins, trace elements, omega 3 and 6 essential fatty acids. The Kicstart is supplemented with some salads, carbohydrate free vegetables and a small piece of meat fish or chicken each day in order to achieve a total energy intake of approximately 850 kcals/day.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>This will be the first analysis of the impact of rapid aggressive weight loss in obese individuals on both short and long-term cardiovascular indices.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Obese Caucasian men age 18-65 years, who are non smokers, and consuming 2 or fewer
             standard alcoholic drinks per day (on average over the past 5 years) will be
             recruited.

          -  Obesity, for the purposes of this study, is defined by a BMI &gt; 30 and a waist
             circumference &gt; 102 cm.

          -  Caucasian men only are enrolled because the cut-off points for the definition of
             obesity vary significantly by race.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Male</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Men are excluded if they have any previously diagnoses or symptomatic atherosclerotic
             disease, or are taking any cardiovascular medication.

          -  Men with known gallstones, history of gout, or any contraindication to MRI are also
             excluded.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/04/2005</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Unknown status</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>University of Adelaide, Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Adelaide</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Royal Adelaide Hospital</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Obesity is a growing epidemic and is associated with an increased risk of heart attack and
      stroke. The investigators know that obesity leads to abnormalities in how the blood vessels
      and the heart function and that these abnormalities are an important cause of this increased
      risk in obese individuals. While improvements in these abnormalities have been reported with
      marked weight reduction (eg surgery) and lifestyle changes including exercise training, it is
      not clear that these abnormalities can be substantially reversed with standard dietary
      interventions. Additional information is needed regarding the degree of weight loss required,
      the time course of these improvements, nor the mechanisms. All of these have major
      implications for the potential role of weight loss in the management of these patients.

      The investigators will assess the effects of dietary induced weight loss in both the short
      and long term on the function of blood vessels and the heart, and the relationship of any
      changes with markers of inflammation that are present in obesity.

      By understanding the factors that are important in reversing these abnormalities in obesity
      the investigators will be better to identify and reduce heart attack and stroke in obese
      individuals in the future.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00782262</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Cynthia Piantadosi, PhD</name>
      <address />
      <phone>61 8 82222473</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cynthia.piantadosi@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>