<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4943">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/04/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/04/2015</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02432703</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Safety and Efficacy Study of JNJ-42165279 in Participants With Social Anxiety Disorder</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 2a Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-Controlled, Parallel-Group, Multi-center Study Investigating the Efficacy, Safety, and Tolerability of JNJ-42165279 in Subjects With Social Anxiety Disorder.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>42165279SAX2001</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>CR106641</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Phobic Disorders</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - JNJ-42165279
Treatment: drugs - Placebo

Experimental: JNJ-42165279 - Participants will receive 25 milligram (mg) JNJ-42165279 orally once-daily from Day 1 up to 12 weeks.

Placebo Comparator: Placebo - Participants will receive a matching placebo orally once-daily from Day 1 up to 12 weeks.


Treatment: drugs: JNJ-42165279
Participants will receive 25 milligram (mg) JNJ-42165279 orally once-daily from Day 1 up to 12 weeks.

Treatment: drugs: Placebo
Participants will receive a matching placebo orally once-daily from Day 1 up to 12 weeks.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in the Liebowitz Social Anxiety Scale (LSAS) Total Score at Week 12 - The Liebowitz Social Anxiety Scale (LSAS) is a 24-item measure designed to assess both fear and avoidance of social and performance situations. The total score ranges from 0 to 144; where higher score indicates worsening.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Week 12</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Liebowitz Social Anxiety Scale (LSAS) Fear/Anxiety and Avoidance Subscales at Week 12 - The 24-items on LSAS scale assess both fear and avoidance of social and performance situations. Each item is rated from 0-3 for both fear and avoidance with the total subscale score ranging from 0 to 72 each; where higher score indicates worsening.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants who are Responders and Remitters on Liebowitz Social Anxiety Scale (LSAS) Total Score at Week 12 - Responders are participants with greater than or equal (&gt;=) 50 percent (%) improvement from baseline and remitters are participants with &gt;= 30% improvement from baseline on LSAS total score.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants who are Responders and Remitters on Liebowitz Social Anxiety Scale (LSAS) Total Score at Week 12 - Percentage of Participants who would be responders and remitters on Liebowitz Social Anxiety Scale (LSAS) Total Score will be observed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from Baseline in Structured Interview Guide for the Hamilton Anxiety Rating Scale (SIGH-A) Total Score at Week 12 - Structured Interview Guide for the Hamilton Anxiety Rating Scale (SIGH-A) is a 14-item scale designed to measure anxiety in individuals. Each question reflects a symptom of anxiety and physical as well as mental symptoms are represented. The answers range from 0 which signifies a complete lack of that symptom to 4, which indicates a very severe show of anxiety with that symptom. The total score ranges from 0 to 56, where higher score indicates worsening.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from Baseline in Hamilton Anxiety Rating scale (HAM-A6) Score at Week 12 - Hamilton Anxiety Rating scale (HAM-A6) is a 6-item subscale derived from the original Hamilton Anxiety scale (HAM-A). It comprises five psychic anxiety symptoms: anxious mood, psychic tension, fears, intellectual disturbances, and anxious behavior observed at the interview, as well as one somatic item, muscular tension, with a total score range of 0 to 24. The rating scale measures the severity of anxiety symptomatology. Higher scores represent more severe anxiety symptoms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from Baseline in Hamilton Depression Rating Scale (HDRS17) Total Score at Week 12 - Hamilton Depression Rating Scale (HDRS17) is a clinician-administered rating scale designed to assess the severity of symptoms in patients diagnosed with depression with a total score range of 0 to 52. Questions are related to symptoms such as depressed mood, guilt feelings, suicide, sleep disturbances, anxiety levels and weight loss. The higher the score, the more severe the depression.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in HDRS17 Anxiety/Somatization Factor Total Score at Week 12 - Hamilton Depression Rating Scale (HDRS17) used to assess the anxiety/somatization factor. The total score ranges from 0 to 18. The higher the score, the more severe the depression.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in 6-Item Hamilton Depression Scale (HAM-D6) Score at Week 12 - The 6-Item Hamilton Depression Scale (HAMD-6), derived by the sum of HAMD-17 items 1, 2, 7, 8, 10 and 13, evaluates "core" symptoms of Major Depressive Disorder (MDD). Total subscale scores range from 0 (normal) to 22 (severe). The higher the score, the more severe the depression.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical Global Impression - Improvement (CGI-I) Score From Baseline at Week 12 - The CGI-I is a 7-point scale that requires the clinician to assess how much the participant's illness has improved or worsened relative to a baseline state at the beginning of the intervention and rated as: 1=very much improved; 2=much improved; 3=minimally improved; 4=no change; 5=minimally worse; 6=much worse; 7=very much worse.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants who are Responders on SIGH-A Total Score at Week 12 - Responders are participants with &gt;= 50% improvement from baseline on SIGH-A total score as assessed at the 12-week endpoint.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants who are Responders on SIGH-A Total Score at Week 12 - Percentage of participants who are responders will be reported.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Must have a primary DSM-5 diagnosis of Social anxiety disorder (SAD) except those with
             performance only as a specifier. Participants with a diagnosis of comorbid Generalized
             Anxiety Disorder (GAD) or Major Depressive Disorder (MDD) may be included if the
             Investigator considers SAD to be the predominant diagnosis. Participants with current
             or lifetime history of Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) and specific
             phobia may be included as well

          -  Must have a Liebowitz Social Anxiety Scale score greater than or equal (&gt;=) 70 at
             Screening and Baseline

          -  Participants with a current episode of MDD must have a HDRS17 total score less than or
             equal to (&lt;=) 18

          -  Must have a body mass index (BMI) between 18 and 35 kilogram per meter square
             (kg/m^2), inclusive, at screening

          -  Female participants must be either postmenopausal or surgically sterile</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>64</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Participants who have performance only SAD are excluded. Participants with other
             current significant psychiatric condition(s) (Axis 1 under DSM-IV), including, but not
             limited to, MDD with psychotic features (lifetime), bipolar disorder (including
             lifetime diagnosis), obsessive-compulsive disorder, borderline personality disorder,
             eating disorder (e.g., bulimia, anorexia nervosa), autism spectrum disorders,
             post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) or schizophrenia are excluded. Participants with
             a diagnosis of comorbid GAD or MDD may be included

          -  Participants is currently receiving specific psychotherapy for SAD

          -  Has a history of more than two unsuccessful adequate pharmacological treatment trials
             for SAD, defined as lack of response to at least 10 weeks of treatment at adequate
             doses (e.g., paroxetine &gt;= 40 milligram per day (mg/day) or its equivalent; or
             clonazepam &gt;= 2.5 mg/day or its equivalent)

          -  Concurrent use of psychotropic medications

          -  has a history of or current thyroid disease, thyroid dysfunction and is currently
             untreated for it</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>15/06/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>122</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>7/09/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>The Lyell McEwin Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>Brain &amp; Mind Research Institute - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>Peninsula Therapeutic &amp; Research Group - Frankston</hospital>
    <hospital>Monash Alfred Psychiatry Research Centre - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>The Melbourne Clinic - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital - Perth</hospital>
    <postcode>5112 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>3199 - Frankston</postcode>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3121 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Perth</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Connecticut</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Illinois</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Massachusetts</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Pennsylvania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Utah</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Alberta</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to investigate the efficacy of JNJ-42165279 during 12 weeks of
      treatment in participants with Social Anxiety Disorder (SAD).</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02432703</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC Clinical Trial</name>
      <address>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Use link at the bottom of the page to see if you qualify for an enrolling site (see list). If you still have questions:</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>JNJ.CT@sylogent.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>