<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6475">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/05/2017</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT03151265</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Prospective Pilot Study Investigating the Impact of ThermaCare on Flexibility, Muscle Relaxation &amp; Low Back Pain</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Prospective Open Label Pilot Study Investigating the Impact of ThermaCare on Flexibility, Muscle Relaxation &amp; Low Back Pain in Two Different Populations</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>2017THERMA</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Low Back Pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - ThermaCare Low Back Heat Wrap

Experimental: Low Back Pain Group - Low Back Pain (LBP) group will be assessed on two consecutive days. The first day will have no ThermaCare intervention applied, and is for a Baseline assessment of flexibility, muscle relaxation and low back pain.
The second day will have the ThermaCare Low Back Heat Wrap intervention applied, and will have the same assessments as the Baseline day.

Experimental: Active in Sport Group - Sport group will be assessed on two consecutive days. The first day will have no ThermaCare intervention applied, and is for a baseline assessment of flexibility, muscle relaxation and low back pain.
The second day will have the ThermaCare Low Back Heat Wrap intervention applied, and will have the same assessments as the Baseline day.


Treatment: devices: ThermaCare Low Back Heat Wrap
The ThermaCare Low Back Heat Wrap, is a continuous, low-level, direct heat therapy. It comes in the form of a heat-pack that is strapped to the low back. Heat is provided for approximately 8-hours.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Movement data over time - Collection of movement data from all participants.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change from Baseline movement data after 1 consecutive day.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Erector spinae muscle activity over time - Collection of erector spinae muscle activity data from all participants</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change from Baseline Erector spinae muscle activity data after 1 consecutive day.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A change over time in range of motion in any one plane of movement compared to pre-intervention range of motion. - Maximal range of low back movement in sagittal,axial and coronal planes</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change from Baseline after 1 consecutive day.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In Group 1 (LBP patients), a change in maximum pain during movement score, for any one plane of movement. - Pain Score out of 10 as rated on the ViMove scale during movement assessment</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change from Baseline after 1 consecutive day.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A change in Muscle Activity from baseline in subjects where abnormal EMG activity during baseline is detected. - Surface EMG measurement of erector spinae muscle activity at L3 vertebra level</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change from Baseline after 1 consecutive day.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Pain from baseline - Pain Score out of 10 as measured on a Numeric Rating scale (NRS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change from Baseline after 1 consecutive day.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Observation of self-reported changes in functional status pre- and post- ThermaCare application as measured by the Oswestry Disability Index (ODI) if subjects scored &gt;3 on the NRS - Measurement of disability related to low back pain</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change from Baseline after 1 consecutive day.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Impression of change from subjects post intervention and/or assessment period using the Patient Global Impression of Change Scale (PGIC). - Measurement of perceived change in Low back pain.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change from Baseline after 1 consecutive day.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Observation of self-reported changes in functional status pre- and post- ThermaCare application as measured by the Roland Morris Disability Questionnaire (RMDQ) if subjects scored &gt;3 on the NRS - Measurement of disability related to low back pain</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change from Baseline after 1 consecutive day.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria for recent low back pain patients (Group 1):

          1. Adults between the age of 21-54 inclusive, male and female.

          2. Low back pain is the primary source of pain over the last 3 weeks.

          3. Have experienced and received treatment for muscle related low back pain with an
             average score of at least 3/10 on a 10-point Numeric Rating scale over the past 3
             weeks.

          4. Must be able to communicate fluently in English.

          5. Must provide written informed consent.

          6. Must agree to confidentiality.

        Inclusion criteria for people who are active in sports (Group 2):

          1. Adults between the age of 21-54 inclusive, male and female.

          2. Participate in 30 min of moderate to high intensity exercise 3 times per week. As
             defined by Borg Rating of Perceived Exertion scale.

          3. Must be able to communicate fluently in English.

          4. Must provide written informed consent.

          5. Must agree to confidentiality.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>21</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>54</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion Criteria (applies to both Groups):

          1. The subject is pregnant.

          2. The subject has a severe hearing impairment.

          3. The subject is cognitively impaired.

          4. Known allergic skin reaction to tapes and plasters.

          5. Co-morbidities of neoplasm, infection, fracture, inflammatory or metabolic disorder
             that has potential to affect the lumbo-pelvic region.

          6. Person who is currently enrolled in another investigational drug or device study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>3/07/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/05/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Clifton Hill Physiotherapy - Clifton Hill</hospital>
    <hospital>Peak MSK Physiotherapy - Hampton</hospital>
    <hospital>Hoppers Physio - Hoppers Crossing</hospital>
    <postcode>3068 - Clifton Hill</postcode>
    <postcode>3188 - Hampton</postcode>
    <postcode>3168 - Hoppers Crossing</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>dorsaVi Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Monash University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The objective of this Investigator Initiated study is to evaluate the effectiveness of
      ThermaCare HeatWraps in improving flexibility and low back muscle relaxation, and in
      participants experiencing pain, reducing pain during movement. This study is an intervention
      trial on two discrete subject samples; (1) people with recent back pain, and (2) people who
      regularly play sport. ViMove wearable sensors provide precise objective measurements of low
      back muscle activity and movement in real time and can capture a patient's reporting of pain
      during movement. Outcomes will be assessed through standard ViMove protocols in conjunction
      with multiple validated measures of pain, perception of change, and function.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03151265</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Andrew Ronchi, PhD</name>
      <address>dorsaVi Ltd</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sangeeth Wanasinghage, BSc(Hons)</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+61 422 106 668</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>swanasinghage@dorsavi.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>