<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3218">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/04/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/04/2011</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01387217</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>GSK2018682 FTIH in Healthy Volunteers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Single-blind, Placebo-controlled, Two Part Study to Assess the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics of Single Ascending Doses of GSK2018682 in Healthy Volunteers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>P1A114070</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>114070</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Multiple Sclerosis</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - GSK2018682
Treatment: drugs - Placebo

Experimental: Part A - Part A will be used to confirm the prediction of GSK2018682 PK, assess its effects on lymphocytes, and monitor its safety profile in a single cohort (Cohort 1). Cohort 1 will consist of 4 subjects and explore 4 doses of GSK2018682 in 4 study sessions. In each session, three subjects will receive GSK2018682 and one subject will receive placebo. Thus, when the cohort completes, each subject will receive placebo and 3 doses of GSK2018682.

Experimental: Part B - Part B will explore doses to refine the dose-response curve of GSK2018682 on lymphocyte suppression, as allowed by stopping criteria, in 1 or 2 cohorts of up to 15 subjects (Cohort 2 and Cohort 3). In Part B, up to six single ascending doses of GSK2018682 and one dose of placebo will be investigated in up to 8 sessions.


Treatment: drugs: GSK2018682
GSK2018682

Treatment: drugs: Placebo
Matched Placebo

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate the safety and tolerability of single escalating oral doses of GSK2018682 - Adverse event and safety lab monitoring</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants will be followed and monitored for the duration of their hospital stay. The longest duration of participation in the study will be approximately 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate effects of GSK2018682 on heart rate and blood pressure - 12 lead ECG and telemetry monitoring plus vital signs (systolic and diastolic blood blood pressures), heart rate, respiratory rate and temperature</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants will be followed and monitored for the duration of their hospital stay. The longest duration of participation in the study will be approximately 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate the pharmacokinetics of single doses of GSK2018682 - Peak blood concentration, time of peak blood concentration, oral clearance, half life and AUC</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants will be followed and monitored for the duration of their hospital stay. The longest duration of participation in the study will be approximately 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluate the effect of single escalating oral doses of GSK2018682 on lymphocytes (totals plus subsets) - Reduction from baseline in lymphocyte counts obtained at different time points after dosing and at different dose levels</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants will be followed and monitored for the duration of their hospital stay. The longest duration of participation in the study will be approximately 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Healthy as determined by a responsible and experienced physician, based on a medical
             evaluation including medical history, physical examination, laboratory tests and
             cardiac monitoring. A subject with a clinical abnormality or laboratory parameters
             significantly outside the reference range for the population being studied may be
             included only if the Investigator and the GSK Medical Monitor agree that the finding
             is unlikely to introduce additional risk factors and will not interfere with the study
             procedures. Subjects with lymphocyte counts outside the normal range should always be
             excluded from enrollment

          -  BMI within the range 19 - 28 kg/m2 (inclusive).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  A positive pre-study Hepatitis B surface antigen or positive Hepatitis C antibody
             result within 3 months of screening

          -  Current or chronic history of liver disease, or known hepatic or biliary abnormalities
             (with the exception of Gilbert's syndrome or asymptomatic gallstones).

          -  A positive pre-study drug/alcohol screen.

          -  A positive test for HIV antibody.

          -  History of regular alcohol consumption

          -  Subjects with a history of, or examination suspicious for, skin cancer(s) including
             melanoma, basal cell or squamous cell carcinoma.

          -  Systolic blood pressure less than 95 mmHg or greater than 140 mmHg, or diastolic blood
             pressure less than or equal to 50 mmHg or greater than or equal to 95 mmHg.

          -  Symptomatic reduction in blood pressure after orthostatic challenge.

          -  Subjects with resting heart rate less than 45 beats per minute or greater than 90
             beats per minute

        Other criteria may apply as defined by the clinical protocol.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>21/05/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>27</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>20/12/2010</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Randwick</hospital>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>GlaxoSmithKline</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This protocol describes the first administration of GSK2018682 to humans. The study will
      evaluate the safety, tolerability, pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of single ascending
      doses of GSK2018682. The study will also provide preliminary evidence of the potential
      therapeutic dose-range by measuring the inhibitory effect of GSK2018682 on total lymphocyte
      counts.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01387217</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>GSK Clinical Trials</name>
      <address>GlaxoSmithKline</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>