<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="1576">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/05/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/05/2007</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00481026</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Double Blind Sham Controlled Trial of tDCS in Treating Schizophrenia and Depression</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Double Blind Sham Controlled Trial of tDCS in Treating Schizophrenia and Depression</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>11707</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Schizophrenia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Major Depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Schizophrenia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - transcranial direct current stimulation (tDCS)
Treatment: devices - active tDCS

Sham Comparator: Placebo - Placebo tDCS

Active Comparator: active tDCS - active tDCS


Treatment: devices: transcranial direct current stimulation (tDCS)
tDCS

Treatment: devices: active tDCS
Active tDCS

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical Scales</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Schizophrenia

          -  Participants will be included if they:

               1. Are voluntary and competent to consent;

               2. Have a diagnosis of Schizophrenia or Schizoaffective Disorder as confirmed by the
                  Structure Clinical Interview for the DSM-IV (SCID-IV)

               3. Have persistent positive and negative symptoms despite having trialled, or being
                  currently medicated, with antipsychotic medication; and

               4. are between the ages of 18 and 65.

          -  Concomitant medications including:

               1. Benzodiazepines,

               2. Mood stabilizers (lithium, valproic acid)

               3. Antidepressants (including serotonin reuptake inhibitors and tricyclic
                  antidepressants) and anticholinergics will be allowed. Since carbamazepine has
                  been shown to interfere with the effects of anodal tDCS, potential participants
                  taking it will not be suitable for inclusion in the trial.

          -  Depression

          -  Participants will be included if they:

               1. Are competent to consent;

               2. Have a diagnosis of Major Depression and are currently experiencing a Major
                  Depressive Episode as confirmed by the Structure Clinical Interview for the
                  DSM-IV (SCID-IV);

               3. Are treatment resistant, defined as a failure to achieve a clinical response, or
                  an inability to tolerate, an antidepressant trial of sufficient dose for at least
                  6 weeks; and

               4. Are between the ages of 18 and 75.

          -  Concomitant medications including:

               1. Benzodiazepines,

               2. Mood stabilizers (lithium, valproic acid)

               3. Antidepressants (including serotonin reuptake inhibitors and tricyclic
                  antidepressants) and anticholinergics will be allowed. Since carbamazepine has
                  been shown to interfere with the effects of anodal tDCS, potential participants
                  taking it will not be suitable for inclusion in the trial.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Patients will be excluded if they:

               1. Have a DSM-IV history of substance abuse or dependence in the last 6 months;

               2. Have a concomitant major and unstable medical or neurologic illness;

               3. Are currently taking carbamazepine; or,

               4. Are pregnant.

          -  Patients will be withdrawn from the study if they:

               1. Withdraw consent;

               2. Experience significant clinical deterioration;

               3. Fail to tolerate the procedure; or,

               4. Develop a serious adverse event. In the event that a patient is withdrawn or
                  drops out of the study, efforts will be made to obtain a final set of clinical,
                  cognitive and neurophysiological measures at the time of withdrawal for a last
                  observation carried forward analysis.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2007</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Unknown status</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/12/2010</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Alfred Psychiatry Research Centre - Prahran</hospital>
    <postcode>3181 - Prahran</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Bayside Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The project will investigate the use of a novel technique, transcranial direct current
      stimulation (tDCS) in the treatment of patients with schizophrenia and patients with
      depression. tDCS involves the application of an extremely weak continuous electrical current
      to the brain through the placement of anode and a cathode on the scalp. The electrical
      current is generally completely imperceptible after initial period of tingling which takes
      about 30 seconds. Stimulation under the anode appears to increase brain activity where as
      stimulation under the cathode has the opposite effect. This research plan involves two
      clinical trials:

        1. A study using tDCS to treat both the positive and negative symptoms of schizophrenia.
           The negative symptoms of schizophrenia such as lack of motivation and energy appear to
           arise due to a lack of activity in frontal brain areas. Positive symptoms such as
           hallucinations and confused thoughts may arise through over activity of brain areas more
           on the side and towards the back of the brain called the temporal cortex. We plan to
           apply tDCS such that it can simultaneously increased activity in these frontal brain
           areas and reduce activity over temporal cortex. We will compare active stimulation to a
           placebo condition which involves turning the stimulator off after 30 seconds. The
           capacity to target multiple symptom clusters is unique with this type of brain
           stimulation.

        2. The study using tDCS in treatment resistant depression builds on a work with
           transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS). TMS techniques in depression seem to work which
           increased left frontal brain activity or decrease right frontal brain activity. tDCS
           will be used to do the same thing with the anode used to increase left-sided brain
           activity and the cathode used to simultaneously decreased right-sided brain activity.

      tDCS is potentially a better tolerated procedure than TMS and does not appear to have the
      same risk of seizure induction. Importantly, the equipment is quite inexpensive and this may
      prove to be an extremely safe and effective low-cost treatment for psychiatric disorders in
      Third World countries.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00481026</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Paul B Fitzgerald, MBBS, MPM, PhD, FRANZCP</name>
      <address>Alfred Psychiatry Research Centre</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Paul B Fitzgerald, MBBS, MPM, PhD, FRANZCP</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+61 3 9076 6552</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.fitzgerald@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>