<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5920">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/05/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/05/2016</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02795793</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Non-operative Management for Appendicitis in Children</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Prospective Randomised Controlled Non-inferiority Study to Evaluate the Effectiveness and Safety (APRES) of Non-operative Management in Children With Acute Uncomplicated Appendicitis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>APRES</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>HERC/15/SCHN/266</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute Focal Appendicitis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Appendicitis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Non-operative management group (NOM)
Treatment: surgery - Appendectomy group (Operative management, OM)

Experimental: Non-operative management group (NOM) - Children in the NOM group will receive intravenous Piperacillin with Tazobactam (Tazocin) 100mg/kg/dose every 8 hours for at least 24 hours, and they will be observed and reassessed within 24 hours after randomisation. A further 24 hours of intravenous Piperacillin with Tazobactam therapy will be offered to children in invariable condition. A clinical decision will be made by the attending surgeon to offer OM if a patient's condition deteriorates at any time, or if a patient has failed to improve after 48 hours of intravenous antibiotic therapy. Once the patient is clinically improving and tolerating oral intake, the antibiotic regimen will be changed to oral Amoxicillin plus Clavulanic acid (Augmentin) 22.5mg/kg/dose twice per day to complete a total seven day course of antibiotics. Oral Ciprofloxacin 15mg/kg/dose twice daily and oral Metronidazole 10mg/kg/dose twice daily will be offered to children who are known to have an intolerance or allergy to Amoxicillin or Clavulanic acid.

Active Comparator: Appendectomy group (Operative management, OM) - Children allocated to OM may receive preoperative antibiotic prophylaxis as clinically indicated. Appendicectomy will be performed laparoscopically, or via open surgery according to the surgeon's standard practice. Postoperative antibiotic treatment will be determined on the basis of intraoperative findings in accordance with the institutional practice. The appendix specimen will be examined by a paediatric pathologist, and the formal histopathology report will be recorded.


Treatment: drugs: Non-operative management group (NOM)
With intravenous Piperacillin with Tazobactam (Tazocin)

Treatment: surgery: Appendectomy group (Operative management, OM)


</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Unplanned or unnecessary operation(s) and complications</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Unplanned or unnecessary operation, or complications</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of primary hospital stay - Time of randomisation to discharge</outcome>
      <timepoint>72 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Treatment-related complications</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Redamission and Emergency Department presentation</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost of treatment in Australian Dollars (AUD)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Return to school from time of randomisation</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Return to normal activities from time of randomisation</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Age between 5 and 15 years;

          2. Clinical diagnosis by at least one paediatric surgeon (or duty surgical registrar) of
             acute uncomplicated appendicitis based on with a combination of clinical, laboratory
             and/or imaging findings; that before the study would have led to the decision to
             recommend been subjected to an appendicectomy.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>5</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>16</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>if one or more of the following is assessed to be present

          1. Suspicion of perforated appendicitis on the basis of generalised peritonitis and/or
             imaging studyA diagnosis of perforated or complicated appendicitis (e.g. peritonitis,
             appendiceal mass) is made on the basis of clinical, laboratory and/or imaging
             findings;

          2. Previous non-operative treatment of acute appendicitis;

          3. Age younger than 5 years or older than 16 years;

          4. Known intolerance or allergy to Piperacillin with Tazobactam;

          5. Known history of inflammatory bowel disease, or other chronic abdominal pain syndrome;

          6. Known concurrent significant illness;

          7. Unable to obtain informed consent from parents or guardian;

          8. Known to have a cognitive impairment, an intellectual disability or a mental illness
             that would impair participation.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/05/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>226</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/12/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Sydney Children's Hospital - Randwick</hospital>
    <hospital>The Children's Hospital at Westmead - Westmead</hospital>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
    <postcode>2145 - Westmead</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Sydney Children's Hospitals Network</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is designed to determine the safety and efficacy of non-operative antibiotic
      management of clinically diagnosed acute uncomplicated appendicitis in children. Enrolled
      patients will be randomised and an allocation ratio of 1:1 will be made via weighted
      minimisation, where half of the patients will receive non-operative management with
      intravenous Piperacillin with Tazobactam, while the other half will have an appendicectomy.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02795793</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Susan Adams, MBBS</name>
      <address />
      <phone>61 02 9382 1776</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>susan.adams@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>