<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3774">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/01/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/01/2013</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01771042</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Effects of Weight Loss on Neuroadrenergic Function</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Neuroadrenergic Dysfunction Along the Diabetes Continuum: Benefits of Weight Loss Within Different Strata of Metabolic Risk</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>1/13</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>1/13</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Metabolic Syndrome</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Hypertension</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - Dietary weight loss at 25% energy deficit

Experimental: Normal glucose tolerant - Weight loss attained by 25% caloric restriction.
This arm will be both a glycemic and time control. Initially they will undergo a 4-month weight maintenance phase (acting as time control), followed by 4 month weight loss.

Experimental: Impaired glucose tolerant - Weight loss using 25% caloric restriction.
Impaired glucose tolerant subjects will undergo 4 months weight loss (25% caloric deficit) followed by 3 months weight loss maintenance

Experimental: Type 2 diabetic hyperinsulinemic - Weight loss using 25% caloric restriction.
This group will undergo 4 months weight loss (25% caloric deficit) followed by 3 months weight loss maintenance

Experimental: Type 2 diabetic hypoinsulinemic - Weight loss via 25% caloric restriction.
This group will undergo 4 months weight loss (25% caloric deficit) followed by 3 months weight loss maintenance


Other interventions: Dietary weight loss at 25% energy deficit
Dietary weight loss at 25% energy deficit. Dietary macronutrient content will comprise 25% protein, 30% fat and 45% carbohydrate.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in whole-body norepinephrine kinetics - The study will examine the dynamic processes of norepinephrine spillover into and removal from the central plasma compartment using the isotope dilution technique.Measurements will be made at baseline, after 4 months active weight loss, and again after 3 months weight loss maintenance. The weight loss maintenance phase will permit differentiation of the effects of active weight loss (incorporating both negative energy balance and weight loss per se) and stable lower body weight on sympathetic neural parameters.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 months and 7 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in muscle sympathetic nerve activity - Muscle sympathetic nerve firing will be quantified by the technique of mirconeurography at baseline and after 4 months active weight loss and 3 months weight loss maintenance. The weight loss maintenance phase will permit differentiation of the effects of active weight loss (incorporating both negative energy balance and weight loss per se) and stable lower body weight on sympathetic nerve firing and pattern.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 months and 7 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Men and postmenopausal women (n=120), untreated, weight-stable, non-smoking, aged 45-65
        years, BMI 27-45 kg/m2, will be recruited. Glucose tolerance status will be determined by a
        75-g oral glucose tolerance test (OGTT), using WHO criteria (53): normal glucose tolerance,
        fasting plasma glucose &lt; 7.0 mmol/L and 2-h plasma glucose &lt; 7.8 mmol/L; IGT, fasting
        plasma glucose &lt; 7.0 mmol/L and 2-h plasma glucose &gt; 7.8 and &lt; 11.1 mmol/L; T2D, fasting
        plasma glucose &gt; 7.0 mmol/L or 2-h plasma glucose &gt; 11.1 mmol/L. Hyper-insulinemia will be
        defined as an insulin area under the curve during OGTT &gt; 8000 mU/L · min-1 and
        hypo-insulinemia as &lt; 8000 mU/L · min-1.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>45</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Prior history of cardiovascular disease (previous myocardial infarction, angina, stroke,
        heart failure, secondary hypertension), renal (serum creatinine &gt;0.12 mmol/L or estimated
        GFR &lt;60 ml/min/1.73 m2) or hepatic disease or diseases which may affect measured parameters
        (e.g. thyroid disease); severe hypertension; a history of surgical weight loss; CPAP
        therapy; and &gt;4 alcoholic drinks/day. T2D individuals with moderate hyperglycemia (HbA1c
        &gt;9%) will be excluded so that hypoglycaemic pharmacotherapy may be instituted (54).
        Participants will be sought through newspaper advertising and poster displays in primary
        health care centres (General Practices). Newly diagnosed T2D subjects</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/04/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Unknown status</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/04/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Baker IDI Heart &amp; Diabetes Institute - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>8008 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Baker Heart Research Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Elevated subconscious nervous system activity is a characteristic of the obese state and
      contributes importantly to the risk of heart disease and diabetes. This project will compare
      sympathetic nervous system activity and function in a group of obese persons with differing
      levels of sugar tolerance (normal, impaired and type 2 diabetic). Inter-relationships with
      insulin action, blood pressure, heart and kidney function will be determined before and after
      a 4-month weight loss and 3-month weight loss maintenance program.

      It is hypothesized that the transition from normal sugar tolerance to impaired sugar
      tolerance to type 2 diabetes will be accompanied by escalating sympathetic nervous system
      dysfunction. Furthermore, that weight loss will favorably improve sympathetic function, with
      greatest benefits occurring in those subjects who are insulin resistant with high blood
      insulin concentration.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01771042</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Nora E Straznicky, PhD MPH</name>
      <address>Baker IDI Heart &amp; Diabetes Institute</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Nora E Straznicky, PhD MPH</name>
      <address />
      <phone>61 3 8532 1371</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nora.straznicky@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>