<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3739">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/08/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/08/2012</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01659658</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Study of Dexamethasone Plus IXAZOMIB (MLN9708) or Physicians Choice of Treatment in Relapsed or Refractory Systemic Light Chain (AL) Amyloidosis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 3, Randomized, Controlled, Open-label, Multicenter, Safety and Efficacy Study of Dexamethasone Plus MLN9708 or Physicians Choice of Treatment Administered to Patients With Relapsed or Refractory Systemic Light Chain (AL) Amyloidosis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>2011-005468-10</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>C16011</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Relapsed or Refractory Systemic Light Chain Amyloidosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human Genetics and Inherited Disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other human genetics and inherited disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - IXAZOMIB
Treatment: drugs - Dexamethasone
Treatment: drugs - Melphalan
Treatment: drugs - Cyclophosphamide
Treatment: drugs - Thalidomide
Treatment: drugs - Lenalidomide

Experimental: IXAZOMIB 4 mg + Dexamethasone 20 mg/day - IXAZOMIB 4 mg, capsules, orally, once on Days 1, 8, and 15; plus dexamethasone 20 mg/day, orally, weekly on Days 1, 8, 15, and 22 of each 28-day cycle; dexamethasone may be increased up to 40 mg/day after 4 weeks, if tolerated. Participants may continue to receive treatment until Progressive Disease (PD) or unacceptable toxicity, whichever comes first.

Active Comparator: Physician's Choice - Participants will receive one of the following treatment options as selected by the physician:
Dexamethasone 20 mg/day: dexamethasone 20 mg/day, orally, on Days 1-4, 9-12 and 17- 20 of each 28-day cycle.
Dexamethasone 20 mg/day + Melphalan 0.22 mg/kg: dexamethasone 20 mg/day, orally, on Days 1-4 of each 28-day cycle; plus melphalan 0.22 mg/kg, orally, on Days 1-4 every 28 days.
Dexamethasone 20 mg/day + Cyclophosphamide 500 mg: dexamethasone 20 mg/day, orally, weekly on Days 1, 8, 15 and 22 of each 28-day cycle; plus cyclophosphamide 500 mg, orally, on Days 1, 8 and 15 every 28 days.
Dexamethasone 20 mg/day + Thalidomide 200 mg/day: dexamethasone 20 mg/day, orally, weekly Days 1, 8, 15 and 22 of each 28-day cycle; plus thalidomide total dose up to 200 mg/day, orally.
Dexamethasone 20 mg/day+ Lenalidomide 15 mg/day: dexamethasone 20 mg/day, orally, weekly on Days 1, 8, 15 and 22 of each 28-day cycle; plus lenalidomide 15 mg/day, orally, for 21 days every 28 days.


Treatment: drugs: IXAZOMIB
IXAZOMIB capsules

Treatment: drugs: Dexamethasone
Dexamethasone tablets

Treatment: drugs: Melphalan
Melphalan tablets

Treatment: drugs: Cyclophosphamide
Cyclophosphamide tablets

Treatment: drugs: Thalidomide
Thalidomide capsules

Treatment: drugs: Lenalidomide
Lenalidomide capsules

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage Of Participants With Overall Hematologic Response - Overall Hematologic Response was defined as the percentage of participants with Complete Response (CR), Very Good Partial Response (VGPR) and Partial Response (PR) based on central laboratory results and the 2010 International Society of Amyloidosis (ISA) Consensus Criteria as assessed by an Adjudication Committee. CR: Complete disappearance of M-protein from serum and urine on immunofixation, and normalization of Free Light Chain (FLC) ratio. VGPR: Differential Free Light Chain (difference between involved and uninvolved FLC levels; dFLC) &lt; 40 mg/L. PR: =50% reduction in dFLC.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From first dose of study drug until discontinuation of study drug due to disease progression or unacceptable toxicity, or death which occurs first (approximately 9.3 years)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2-Year Vital Organ (Heart Or Kidney) Deterioration And Mortality Rate - Cardiac (Heart) deterioration is defined as the need for hospitalization for heart failure. Kidney deterioration is defined as progression to end-stage renal disease (ESRD) with the need for maintenance dialysis or renal transplantation. Vital organ deterioration will be evaluated by an Adjudication Committee.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monthly or until death (Up to 2 years)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage Of Participants With Complete Hematologic Response - Complete Hematologic Response was defined as the percentage of participants with CR based on central laboratory results and the 2010 ISA Consensus Criteria as assessed by an Adjudication Committee. CR: Complete disappearance of M-protein from serum and urine on immunofixation, and normalization of FLC ratio.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From first dose of study drug until discontinuation of study drug due to disease progression or unacceptable toxicity, or death whichever occurs first (approximately 9.3 years)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Survival - Overall survival is defined as the time from the date of randomization to the date of death.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From the date of randomization until death (approximately 9.3 years)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression Free Survival (PFS) - PFS is defined as the time from the date of randomization to the date of first documentation of hematologic disease progression, or organ (cardiac or renal) progression, or death due to any cause, whichever occurs first according to central laboratory results and ISA criteria as evaluated by an Adjudication Committee.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From date of randomization until discontinuation of study drug due to disease progression or unacceptable toxicity, or death which occurs first (approximately 9.3 years)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hematologic Disease Progression Free Survival - Hematologic disease PFS is defined as the time from the date of randomization to the date of first documentation of hematologic PD according to central laboratory results and ISA criteria as evaluated by an Adjudication Committee, or death due to any cause, whichever occurs first.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From date of randomization until discontinuation of study drug due to disease progression or unacceptable toxicity, or death which occurs first (approximately 9.3 years)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time To Vital Organ (Heart Or Kidney) Deterioration And Mortality Rate - Time to vital organ deterioration or death defined as the time from randomization to vital organ (heart or kidney) deterioration or death, whichever occurs first. Cardiac deterioration is defined as the need for hospitalization for heart failure. Kidney deterioration is defined as progression to ESRD with the need for maintenance dialysis or renal transplantation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From randomization to time of vital organ deterioration or death (approximately 9.3 years)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage Of Participants With Best Vital Organ (Cardiac And/Or Kidney) Response - Vital organ (heart and kidney) response rate is defined as the percentage of participants who achieved vital organ response according to central laboratory results and ISA criteria as evaluated by an Adjudication Committee. A vital organ response is defined as response of 1 or 2 of the involved vital organs with no change from Baseline in the rest of involved vital organs.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From randomization until discontinuation of study drug due to disease progression or unacceptable toxicity, or death which occurs first (approximately 9.3 years)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Vital Organ Progression Free Survival - Vital organ PFS is defined as the time from the date of randomization to the date of first documentation of progression of vital organ (heart or kidney) according to central laboratory results and ISA criteria as evaluated by an Adjudication Committee, or death due to any cause, whichever occurs first.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From randomization until discontinuation of study drug due to disease progression or unacceptable toxicity, or death which occurs first (approximately 9.3 years)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of Hematologic Response - Duration of hematologic response (DOR) is defined as the time from the date of first documentation of a hematologic response to the date of first documented hematologic disease progression according to central laboratory results and ISA criteria as determined by an Adjudication Committee.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From time of first documented response to disease progression (up to 9.3 years)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With Adverse Events (AEs) and Serious Adverse Events (SAEs) - An Adverse Event (AE) is defined as any untoward medical occurrence in a clinical investigation participant administered a drug; it does not necessarily have to have a causal relationship with this treatment. An AE can therefore be any unfavorable and unintended sign (example, a clinically significant abnormal laboratory finding), symptom, or disease temporally associated with the use of a drug, whether or not it is considered related to the drug. A serious adverse event (SAE) is an AE resulting in any of the following outcomes or deemed significant for any other reason: death; initial or prolonged inpatient hospitalization; life-threatening experience (immediate risk of dying); persistent or significant disability/incapacity; or congenital anomaly; or a medically important event.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From first dose of study drug through 30 days after administration of the last dose of study drug (approximately 9.3 years)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time To Treatment Failure (TTF) - TTF is defined as the time from randomization to the date of first documented treatment failure. Treatment failure is defined as: 1) death due to any cause; 2) hematologic progression or major organ progression according to central laboratory results and ISA criteria as evaluated by an Adjudication Committee; 3) clinically morbid organ disease requiring additional therapy; or 4) withdrawn for any reason.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From first dose of study drug until discontinuation of study drug due to disease progression or unacceptable toxicity, or death whichever occurs first (approximately 9.3 years)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time To Subsequent Anticancer Treatment - Time to subsequent anticancer therapy is defined as the time from randomization to the first date of subsequent anticancer therapy. Participants without subsequent anticancer therapy will be censored at the date of death or last known to be alive.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From first dose of study drug until subsequent anticancer treatment (up to 9.3 years)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline In SF-36 General Health Survey Score - SF-36 v2 is a multipurpose, participant completed, short-form health survey with 36 questions that consists of an 8- scale profile of functional health and well-being scores as well as psychometrically-based physical and mental health summary measures. Physical component summary (PCS) is mostly contributed by physical function (PF), role physical (RP), bodily pain (BP), and general health (GH). Mental component summary (MCS) is mostly contributed by mental health (MH), role emotional (RE), social function (SF), and vitality (VT). The sub-score scale ranges from 0 (best) to 100 (worst). A negative change from Baseline indicates improvement.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At screening (Baseline); Cycle 1, Day 1; Cycle 3, Day 1; Day 1 of every 3 cycles until disease progression (approximately 9.3 years)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline In Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy/Gynecologic Oncology Group-Neurotoxicity (FACT/GOG-Ntx) Score - The FACT/GOG-Ntx is a participant completed questionnaire that comprises 11 individual items evaluating symptoms of neurotoxicity on a 5-point scale where: 0 =not at all (best) to 4=very much for a total possible score of 0 to 44. A negative change from Baseline indicates improvement.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At screening (Baseline); Cycle 1, Day 1; Cycle 2, Day 1;Cycle 3, Day 1; Day 1 of every 3 cycles until disease progression (approximately 9.3 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline In Amyloidosis Symptom Scale Score - The Amyloidosis symptom scale questionnaire is a participant completed questionnaire that evaluates symptom severity of 3 symptoms: Swelling, Shortness of Breath and Dizziness, each rated on an 11-point scale where: 0 =No symptoms to 10=very severe symptoms. A negative change from Baseline indicates improvement.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At screening (Baseline); Cycle 1, Day 1; Cycle 2, Day 1;Cycle 3, Day 1; Day 1 of every 3 cycles until disease progression (approximately 9.3 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>EuroQol 5-Dimensional (EQ-5D) Questionnaire Score - The European Quality of Life (EuroQOL) 5-Dimensional (EQ-5D) is a patient completed questionnaire consisting of 2 pages: the EQ-5D descriptive system and the EQ visual Analogue scale (EQ VAS). The descriptive system comprises 5 dimensions (mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort, anxiety/depression). Each dimension has 3 possible choices: no problems to extreme problems. The EQ visual analogue scale (VAS) records the participant's self-rated health on a 20 centimeter vertical VAS that ranges from 0 (worst imaginable health state) to 100 (best imaginable health state).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At screening; Cycle 1, Day 1; Cycle 2, Day 1; Cycle 3, Day 1; Day 1 of every 3 cycles until disease progression(approximately 9.3 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tmax: Time to Reach the Maximum Plasma Concentration (Cmax) for IXAZOMIB and its metabolite MLN2238 - Tmax: Time to reach the maximum plasma concentration (Cmax), equal to time (hours) to Cmax.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cycle 1, Day 1 at multiple time points (up to 4 hours) postdose and Day 14 at any time; Cycle 2, Day 1 predose and Day 14 at any time; Cycles 3-10 predose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Medical Encounters Participant Experiences - Medical encounters will be recorded as the number of admissions to an inpatient and outpatient setting for any reason (including length of stay, inpatient, outpatient and reason), number of missing days from work or other activities by participant or care-giver.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At screening; Cycle 1, Day 1; Cycle 2, Day 1; Cycle 3, Day 1; Day 1 of every 3 cycles until disease progression (approximately 9.3 years)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Male or female participants 18 years or older.

          2. Biopsy-proven diagnosis of primary systemic light chain amyloidosis (AL amyloidosis)
             according to the following standard criteria:

               1. Histochemical diagnosis of amyloidosis, as based on tissue specimens with Congo
                  red staining with exhibition of an apple-green birefringence

               2. If clinical and laboratory parameters insufficient to establish AL amyloidosis or
                  in cases of doubt, amyloid typing may be necessary.

          3. Measurable disease as defined by serum differential free light chain concentration
             (dFLC, difference between amyloid forming [involved] and nonamyloid forming
             [uninvolved] free light chain [FLC]) = 50 mg/L.

          4. Objective, measurable major (cardiac or renal) organ amyloid involvement as defined as
             follows (amyloid involvement of at least 1 required):

               1. Cardiac involvement is defined as the presence of a mean left ventricular wall
                  thickness on echocardiogram greater than 12 mm in the absence of other potential
                  causes of left ventricular hypertrophy (controlled hypertension is allowed) with
                  a noncardiac biopsy showing amyloid, or a positive cardiac biopsy in the presence
                  of clinical or laboratory evidence of involvement. If there is isolated cardiac
                  involvement, then typing of amyloid deposits is recommended.

               2. Renal involvement is defined as proteinuria (predominantly albumin) &gt;0.5 g/day in
                  a 24-hour urine collection.

             Note: Amyloid involvement of other organ systems is allowed, but not required.

          5. Must be relapsed or refractory after 1 or 2 prior therapies. For this protocol,
             relapsed is defined as progressive disease (PD) documented more than 60 days after
             last dose; refractory is defined as documented absence of hematologic response or
             hematologic progression on or within 60 days after last dose of prior therapy.

               1. Participant must not have been previously treated with proteasome inhibitors.
                  (The sponsor reserves the right to open the study to proteasome inhibitor-exposed
                  participants in the future, at some time point after the first interim analysis
                  (IA). In that case, the participant may not be refractory to proteasome inhibitor
                  therapy.)

               2. Given that the physician may select from an offered list of regimens to treat a
                  specific participant, the participant may be refractory to an agent/s listed
                  within the list of offered treatment choices

               3. Must have recovered (ie, = Grade 1 toxicity or participant's baseline status)
                  from the reversible effects of prior therapy

               4. If a participant has received a transplant as his/her first-line therapy, he/she
                  must be at least 3 months post transplantation and recovered from the side
                  effects of the stem cell transplant.

          6. Must meet criteria for 1 of the following AL Amyloidosis Risk Stages (as defined by
             N-terminal proBNP [NT-proBNP] cut-off of &lt; 332 pg/mL and troponin T cut-off of 0.035
             ng/mL as thresholds):

               1. Stage 1: both NT-proBNP and troponin T under threshold

               2. Stage 2: either NT-proBNP or troponin T (but not both) over threshold;

               3. Stage 3: both NT-proBNP and troponin T over threshold (but NT-proBNP &lt; 8000
                  pg/mL)

          7. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status = 2.

          8. Clinical laboratory values:

               1. Absolute neutrophil count = 1000/µL

               2. Platelet count = 75,000/µL

               3. Total bilirubin = 1.5 upper limit of normal (ULN), except for participants with
                  Gilbert's syndrome as defined by &gt; 80% unconjugated bilirubin and total bilirubin
                  = 6 mg/dL

               4. Alkaline phosphatase = 5 x ULN

               5. Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) or aspartate aminotransferase (AST) =3 x ULN

               6. Calculated creatinine clearance = 30 mL/min

          9. Female participants who:

               1. If they are of childbearing potential, agree to practice 2 effective methods of
                  contraception, at the same time, from the time of signing the informed consent
                  through 90 days after the last dose of study treatment, AND

               2. Must also adhere to the guidelines of any treatment-specific pregnancy prevention
                  program, if applicable, OR

               3. Agree to practice true abstinence when this is line with the preferred and usual
                  lifestyle of the participant. (Periodic abstinence [eg, calendar, ovulation,
                  symptothermal, post-ovulation methods] and withdrawal are not acceptable methods
                  of contraception.).

             Male participants, even if surgically sterilized (ie, status post vasectomy), who:

               1. Agree to practice effective barrier contraception during the entire study
                  treatment period and through 90 days after the last dose of study drug, AND

               2. Must also adhere to the guidelines of any treatment-specific pregnancy prevention
                  program, if applicable, OR

               3. Agree to practice true abstinence when this is line with the preferred and usual
                  lifestyle of the participant. (Periodic abstinence [eg, calendar, ovulation,
                  symptothermal, post-ovulation methods] and withdrawal are not acceptable methods
                  of contraception.)

         10. Voluntary written consent must be given before performance of any study-related
             procedure not part of standard medical care with the understanding that consent may be
             withdrawn by the participant at any time without prejudice to future medical care.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Amyloidosis due to mutations of the transthyretin gene or presence of other non-AL
             amyloidosis.

          2. Female participants who are lactating, breast feeding, or pregnant.

          3. Medically documented cardiac syncope, uncompensated New York Heart Association (NYHA)
             Class 3 or 4 congestive heart failure, myocardial infarction within the previous 6
             months, unstable angina pectoris, clinically significant repetitive ventricular
             arrhythmias despite antiarrhythmic treatment, or severe orthostatic hypotension or
             clinically important autonomic disease.

          4. Clinically overt multiple myeloma, according to the International Myeloma Working
             Group (IMWG) criteria with at least 1 of the following:

               1. Bone lesions

               2. Hypercalcemia, defined as a calcium of &gt; 11 mg/dL

          5. Inability to swallow oral medication, inability or unwillingness to comply with the
             drug administration requirements, or gastrointestinal (GI) procedure that could
             interfere with the oral absorption or tolerance of treatment.

          6. Requirement for other concomitant chemotherapy, immunotherapy, radiotherapy, or any
             ancillary therapy considered to be investigational or which would be considered as a
             treatment of AL amyloidosis. However, participants may be on chronic steroids (maximum
             dose 20 mg/day prednisone or equivalent) if they are being given for disorders other
             than amyloidosis (eg, adrenal insufficiency, rheumatoid arthritis, etc.).

          7. Comorbid systemic illnesses or other severe concurrent disease which, in the judgment
             of the investigator, would make the participant inappropriate for entry into this
             study or interfere significantly with the proper assessment of safety and toxicity of
             the prescribed regimens.

          8. Ongoing or active infection, known human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) positive, active
             hepatitis B or C infection.

          9. Psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with study
             requirements.

         10. Known allergy to boron, MLN9708, any of the study treatments, their analogues, or
             excipients.

         11. Systemic treatment with strong CYP3A inducers (rifampin, rifapentine, rifabutin,
             carbamazepine, phenytoin, phenobarbital), or use of Ginkgo biloba or St. John's wort
             within 14 days before the first dose of study treatment.

         12. Diagnosed or treated for another malignancy within 3 years (5 years for sites in
             France) before study enrollment or previously diagnosed with another malignancy and
             have any evidence of residual disease. Participants with nonmelanoma skin cancer or
             carcinoma in situ of any type are not excluded if they have undergone complete
             resection.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>26/12/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>248</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/09/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,VIC,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Westmead Hospital - Westmead</hospital>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <hospital>Box Hill Hospital - Box Hill</hospital>
    <hospital>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital - Nedlands</hospital>
    <postcode>214 - Westmead</postcode>
    <postcode>4102 - Woolloongabba</postcode>
    <postcode>3128 - Box Hill</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Illinois</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Indiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Massachusetts</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Michigan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Minnesota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Missouri</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Tennessee</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Wisconsin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Santa Catarina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Rio de Janeiro</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Sao Paulo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Alberta</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>British Columbia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Moravskoslezsk kraj</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Praha, hlavni mesto</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Denmark</country>
      <state>Aahus</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Denmark</country>
      <state>Copenhagen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Loire-Atlantique</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Lille</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Limoges</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Paris</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Toulouse</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Berlin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Hamburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Heidelberg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Achaia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Athens</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Haifa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Jerusalem</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Kfar Saba</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Petach Tikva</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Ramat-Gan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Bologna</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Pavia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Incheon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Seoul</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Noord-Holland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>AZ Maastricht</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Utrecht</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Navarra</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Majadahonda</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Salamanca</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Birmingham</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Manchester</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Oxford</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Millennium Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to determine whether dexamethasone plus IXAZOMIB improves
      hematologic response, 2-year vital organ (that is, heart or kidney) deterioration and
      mortality rate versus a physician's choice of a chemotherapy regimen in participants
      diagnosed with relapsed or refractory systemic light chain (AL) amyloidosis.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01659658</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Medical Monitor</name>
      <address>Millennium Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Takeda Study Registration Call Center</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+1-844-662-8532</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>globaloncologymedinfo@takeda.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>