<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2931">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/09/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/09/2010</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01212107</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Study of LY2874455 in Patients With Advanced Cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 1 Study of LY2874455 to Assess Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics, Pharmacodynamics, and Efficacy in Patients With Advanced Cancer.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>I4R-MC-FGAA</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>13843</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Advanced Cancer</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - LY2874455

Experimental: 2 mg LY2874455 - 2 mg LY287445 administered orally once daily for a minimum of (1) 28 day cycle

Experimental: 4 mg LY2874455 - 4 mg LY2874455 administered orally once daily for a minimum of (1) 28 day cycle

Experimental: 10 mg LY287445 - 10 mg LY2874455 administered orally once daily for a minimum of (1) 28 day cycle

Experimental: 16 mg LY2874455 - 8 mg LY2874455 administered orally twice daily for a minimum of (1) 28 day cycle

Experimental: 20 to 24 mg LY2874455 - 10 to 12 mg of LY2874455 administered orally twice daily for a minimum of (1) 28 day cycle

Experimental: 24 to 36 mg LY2874455 - 12 to 18 mg LY2874455 administered orally twice daily for a minimum of (1) 28 day cycle

Experimental: 28 to 56 mg LY2874455 - 14 to 28 mg LY2874455 administered orally twice daily for a minimum of (1) 28 day cycle

Experimental: 36 to 94 mg LY2874455 - 18 to 42 mg LY2874455 administered orally twice daily for a minimum of (1) 28 day cycle

Experimental: 44 to 128 mg LY2874455 - 22 to 64 mg LY2874455 administered orally twice daily for a minimum of (1) 28 day cycle

Experimental: 56 to 192 mg LY2874455 - 28 to 96 mg LY2874455 administered orally, twice daily for a minimum of (1) 28 day cycle

Experimental: 72 to 200 mg LY2874455 - 36 to 100 mg LY2874455 administered orally twice daily for a minimum of (1) 28 day cycle


Treatment: drugs: LY2874455
LY2874455 will be taken orally (capsules) once or twice daily for a minimum of (1) 28 day cycle.
Part A: dose escalation
2-200 mg, administered orally, once or twice daily for a minimum of one (1) 28 day cycle
Part B: dose confirmation
dose determined by Part A dose escalation, administered orally, once or twice daily for a minimum of one (1) 28 day cycle
Both parts: If patients are determined to be receiving benefit, study treatment may be continued for up to one (1) year (12 cycles of 28 days)

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Recommended dose for Phase 2 studies</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to study completion</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of participants with clinically significant effects</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to study completion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tumor measurement (palpable or visible)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Cycle 1 Day-1, then each cycle until study completion Day 28, Follow-up Visit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Radiological tumor measurement</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, completed prior to every other Cycle beginning with Cycle 3, Follow-up Visit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetic (PK) of LY2874455, maximum concentration (Cmax)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Part A: Cycle 1 Day -1, Cycle 1 Day-28, Part B: Cycle 1 Day-1, Cycle 1 Day-28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetic (PK) of LY2874455, area under the concentration-time curve (AUC)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Part A: Cycle 1 Day 1, Cycle 1 Day-28, Part B: Cycle 1 Day-1, Cycle 1 Day-28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Have histological or cytological evidence of a diagnosis of cancer (solid tumors,
             lymphoma, or chronic lymphocytic leukemia) that is advanced and/or metastatic and for
             which all standard therapies have failed

          -  Have the presence of measurable or nonmeasurable disease

          -  Have given written informed consent prior to any study-specific procedures

          -  Have adequate organ function including:

               -  Hematologic: Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) equal to or greater than 1.5 x
                  10(9)/L platelets equal to or greater than 100 x 10(9)/L, and hemoglobin equal to
                  or greater than 8 g/dL. Patients may receive erythrocyte transfusions to achieve
                  this hemoglobin level at the discretion of the investigator. Initial treatment
                  must not begin until 14 days after the erythrocyte transfusion

               -  Hepatic: Bilirubin equal to or less than 1.5 times upper limits of normal (ULN),
                  alanine transaminase (ALT), and aspartate transaminase (AST) equal to or less
                  than 2.5 times ULN. If the liver has tumor involvement, AST and ALT equaling
                  equal to or less than 5 times ULN are acceptable

               -  Renal: Serum creatinine less than or equal to 1.2 times ULN or calculated
                  creatinine clearance greater than or equal to 60 milliliters per minute using the
                  Standard Cockcroft and Gault Creatinine Clearance Calculation

               -  Calcium and phosphate less than or equal to 1.1 times ULN

          -  Have a performance status of 0, 1, or 2 on the Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group
             (ECOG) scale

          -  Have discontinued chemotherapy and cancer-related hormonal therapy with commercially
             available agents for at least 21 days (6 weeks for mitomycin-C or nitrosoureas) and
             radiotherapy for at least 14 days prior to study enrollment and recovered from the
             acute effects of therapy. Hormone refractory prostate cancer patients receiving
             gonadotropin releasing hormone (GnRH) agonist therapy or breast cancer patients on
             antiestrogen therapy (for example, an aromatase inhibitor) prior to entrance on the
             study may have that treatment continued while they are enrolled in the study

          -  Females with childbearing potential must have had a negative serum pregnancy test less
             than or equal to 7 days prior to the first dose of study drug. Males and females with
             reproductive potential must agree to use 2 medically approved contraceptive methods
             during the trial and for 3 months following the last dose of study drug. Female
             patients must agree to use 2 medically acceptable methods of contraception, 1 being an
             oral contraceptive, dermal patch, or progestin (implantation or injection), and the
             other being a medically acceptable barrier method; alternatively, 2 medically
             acceptable barrier methods may be used. Medically acceptable barrier methods of
             contraception that may be used by the participant and/or his/her partner include:
             abstinence; diaphragm with spermicide; intrauterine device (IUD); condom together with
             foam, spermicide, or vaginal spermicidal suppository. Prohibited methods include the
             rhythm method, withdrawal, condoms alone, or diaphragm alone

          -  Have an estimated life expectancy of greater than or equal to 12 weeks</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Have received treatment with an investigational drug, which has not received
             regulatory approval for any indication, within 28 days of study treatment with
             LY2874455

          -  Currently taking agents to control serum phosphate or calcium levels. This includes
             dietary restrictions

          -  Have medical conditions that, in the opinion of the investigator, would preclude
             participation in this study

          -  Have symptomatic central nervous system (CNS) malignancy or metastasis. Patients with
             treated CNS metastases are eligible provided their disease is radiographically stable,
             asymptomatic, and they are not currently receiving corticosteroids and/or
             anticonvulsants. Screening of asymptomatic patients without history of CNS metastases
             is not required

          -  Have a history of major organ transplant (for example: heart, lungs, liver, and
             kidney)

          -  Have current acute leukemia

          -  Females who are pregnant or nursing

          -  An untreated or uncontrolled acute infection, including urinary tract infection,
             within 7 days of study entry

          -  Have Bazett's corrected QT (QTcB) greater than 470 msec (female) or greater than 450
             msec (male), history of unexplained recurrent syncope, history of congenital long QT
             syndrome, family history of sudden death, or the presence in the screening
             electrocardiogram (ECG) of a conduction abnormality that in the opinion of the
             investigator would preclude safe participation in this study

          -  Have had an autologous or allogenic bone marrow transplant

          -  Previously treated with LY2874455</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/12/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>94</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/02/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>For additional information regarding investigative sites for this trial, contact 1-877-CTLILLY (1-877-285-4559, 1-317-615-4559) Mon - Fri from 9 AM to 5 PM Eastern Time (UTC/GMT - 5 hours, EST), or speak with your personal physician. - East Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>For additional information regarding investigative sites for this trial, contact 1-877-CTLILLY (1-877-285-4559, 1-317-615-4559) Mon - Fri from 9 AM to 5 PM Eastern Time (UTC/GMT - 5 hours, EST), or speak with your personal physician. - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>3002 - East Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3050 - Parkville</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Seoul</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Eli Lilly and Company</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study is to determine the recommended Phase 2 regimen of study drug that may be safely
      administered to patients with advanced and or metastatic cancer. The study consists of two
      parts: a dose escalation and a dose confirmation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01212107</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Call 1-877-CTLILLY (1-877-285-4559) or 1-317-615-4559 Mon - Fri 9 AM - 5 PM Eastern time (UTC/GMT - 5 hours, EST)</name>
      <address>Eli Lilly and Company</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>