<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2652">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/01/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/01/2010</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01058980</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>ADenosine Following Pulmonary Vein Isolation to Target Dormant Conduction Elimination: the ADVICE Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>ADenosine Following Pulmonary Vein Isolation to Target Dormant Conduction Elimination: the ADVICE Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ADVICE</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>ICM 08-1067</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Paroxysmal Atrial Fibrillation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Pulmonary Vein Isolation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Dormant Pulmonary Vein Conduction</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: surgery - Additional ablation until elimination of dormant conduction
Treatment: surgery - No additional ablation
Treatment: surgery - Registry group
Treatment: surgery - Usual medical care

Active Comparator: Dormant PV conduction - After PVI, dormant conduction will be evaluated using intravenous adenosine. If dormant conduction is present, the patients will be randomized to two parallel groups:
Group 1: No additional ablation
Group 2: Additional ablation until elimination of dormant conduction.

Active Comparator: No dormant PV conduction - If no dormant conduction is documented, patients will be selected in a random fashion to be included in a registry (follow-up as planned for group 1 and 2 above). The registry group will allow for further assessment of the role of dormant conduction as a predictor of AF recurrence by comparing the success rate after ablation in patients without dormant conduction with those of Group 1 and 2.


Treatment: surgery: Additional ablation until elimination of dormant conduction
Additional RF energy will be delivered at sites of re-conduction on the circular mapping catheter in each PV. Abolition of the dormant conduction will then be assessed by repeated injections of adenosine using the same doses previously used to reveal dormant conduction. Additional ablation as described will be performed until re-injection of adenosine shows no re-conduction in any of the PV.

Treatment: surgery: No additional ablation
Presence of dormant PV conduction, no additional ablation.

Treatment: surgery: Registry group
Among those who will be found not to have the presence of dormant conduction, and within each site, three-quarters of the patients will be randomly selected to be included in the registry group.

Treatment: surgery: Usual medical care
Clinical follow-up will be performed according to the regular follow-up after AF ablation procedures in each of the participating centers. No data will be collected after discharge.One-fourth of the patients will be randomly selected to be included in the usual medical care group.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to first recurrence of electrocardiographically documented, symptomatic AF or atrial flutter/tachycardia between 3 and 12 months post ablation in the absence of antiarrhythmic drug therapy. - The primary outcome is time to first recurrence of symptomatic ECG-documented AF or atrial flutter/tachycardia between days 91 &amp; 365 after ablation, or repeat ablation procedure during the first 90 days. AF or atrial flutter/tachycardia will qualify as an arrhythmia recurrence after ablation if it lasts 30 seconds or longer and is documented by 12-lead ECG, surface ECG rhythm strips, or TTM recordings. Documented episodes will be adjudicated by a blinded committee. Time 0 is defined as day 91 post ablation with FUp's extending 365 days post ablation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Between 3 and 12 months post ablation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to first recurrence of any electrocardiographically documented AF or atrial flutter/tachycardia (symptomatic or asymptomatic) between days 91 and 365 after ablation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>between 3 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Repeat ablation procedure for documented recurrence of symptomatic AF or atrial flutter/tachycardia.</outcome>
      <timepoint>between 3 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Emergency visits or hospitalizations</outcome>
      <timepoint>between 0 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Antiarrhythmic drug use because of documented recurrence of symptomatic AF or atrial flutter/tachycardia</outcome>
      <timepoint>between 0 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients with AF or left atrial flutter/tachycardia occurring during the first 90 days post ablation</outcome>
      <timepoint>between 0 and 3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Major peri-procedural complications including stroke, PV stenosis, cardiac perforation, atrio-esophageal fistulae, and death</outcome>
      <timepoint>between 0 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Generic and disease specific quality of life (assessed by the Cardiovascular Society Severity in AF (CCS-SAF) scale and SF-36 questionnaire at baseline, and at 3, 6 and 12 months post randomization).</outcome>
      <timepoint>between 0 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Age more than 18 years

          -  Paroxysmal AF for at least 6 months with at least 3 symptomatic episodes (using
             patient history) during the previous 6 months

          -  Patients must be felt to be candidates for AF ablation based on AF that is symptomatic
             and refractory or intolerant to at least one class 1 or 3 antiarrhythmic agent.

          -  Documentation of at least one episode of AF on 12 lead ECG, TTM or Holter monitor
             within 12 months of randomization in the trial

          -  Patients must be on continuous anticoagulation with warfarin (INR 2-3) or fractionated
             subcutaneous heparin for &gt;4 weeks prior to the ablation or they have undergone a
             recent (less than 48 hours before planned ablation) transoesophageal echocardiogram to
             exclude left atrial thrombus.

          -  Patients must provide written informed consent to participate in the clinical trial.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Contraindications to oral anticoagulants

          -  History of any previous ablation or surgical maze for AF

          -  Intracardiac thrombus

          -  AF due to reversible cause

          -  Patients with left atrial size &gt; 55mm or significant mitral valve disease (moderate or
             severe mitral stenosis or regurgitation)

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Asthma, history of bronchospasm or known adverse reaction to adenosine</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/12/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>550</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/12/2013</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Perth Hospital - Perth</hospital>
    <postcode> - Perth</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Austria</country>
      <state>Linz</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Bruxelles</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Alberta</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>British Columbia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Nova Scotia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Quebec</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Bordeaux</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Eppendorf</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Muenchen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Bad Krozingen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Montreal Heart Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR)</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>St. Jude Medical</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Johnson &amp; Johnson</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Atrial fibrillation (AF) is the most common heart rhythm disorder, impairs quality of life
      and increases stroke risk and mortality. Despite advances in medical treatment, AF remains
      uncontrolled in many patients. In many patients, AF is initiated by abnormal electrical
      impulses from the pulmonary veins. A catheter ablation procedure called pulmonary vein
      isolation (PVI) has therefore been developed, using heat to isolate the PV foci from the
      heart. PVI is very effective, but must be repeated in up to 50% of cases because the foci
      isolation is not permanent after initial PVI. The intravenous administration of a drug called
      adenosine during the PVI procedure can unmask residual conduction that would otherwise remain
      unnoticed, so-called "dormant conduction". In our experience, additional ablation guided by
      adenosine reduces AF recurrence and the need for a repeat PVI procedure. However, the
      adenosine-guided approach has not yet been proven as standard therapy. The present study, to
      be conducted at 15 clinical centres in Canada, Europe and Australia is therefore intended to
      evaluate the efficacy of adenosine-guided ablation to prevent AF recurrence. Five hundred
      twenty-six patients will be included in the study, which should be completed within 2 years.
      In all patients, the presence of dormant conduction will be tested with adenosine during PVI.
      If dormant conduction is observed, additional ablation will be performed in half of these
      patients selected randomly. If there is no dormant conduction, randomly selected patients
      will be followed in a registry. If the adenosine-guided approach is demonstrated to improve
      the success rate of PVI procedures, it should become the standard approach for a "permanent
      cure" of AF, and therefore benefit patients by reducing arrhythmia recurrence,
      hospitalizations and the need for repeat interventions.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01058980</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Laurent Macle, MD</name>
      <address>Montreal Heart Institute</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>