<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3488">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/03/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/03/2012</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01554592</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Polypharmacy in the Heart Failure Patient: Are All Prescribed Drug Classes Required? Statin Withdrawal Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Polypharmacy in the Heart Failure Patient: Are All Prescribed Drug Classes Required? Statin Withdrawal Study.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>CP-02/12</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Heart Failure</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Withdrawal of statin therapy
Treatment: drugs - Statin therapy

Experimental: Statin withdrawal - Participants will received a placebo for 12 weeks.

Active Comparator: Stable statin therapy - Participants need to have been receiving statin therapy for at least 3 months and be on a stable dose.


Treatment: drugs: Withdrawal of statin therapy
Participants currently received statin therapy will have their statin stopped for 12 weeks.

Treatment: drugs: Statin therapy
Participants will continue on stable statin therapy.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>NYHA (New York Heart Association) Heart Failure class</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and after 12 weeks of treatemnt</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>6 minutes walk test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and after 12 weeks of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and after 12 weeks of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in BNP (Brain natriuretic peptide)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and after 12 weeks of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Over the age of 18 years

          2. Documented heart failure of ischaemic, idiopathic or hypertensive cause

          3. New York Heart Association (NYHA) class II, III or IV symptoms

          4. LVEF &lt; 0.40, or no more than 0.35 if NYHA class II and ischaemic aetiology.

          5. Receiving ACE inhibitor or ARB (Angiotensin II Receptor Blockers), ß-blocker and
             diuretic therapy at the optimal doses.

          6. Has been receiving statin therapy for at least 3 months

          7. Willing and able to provide informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Treatment with statins primarily for treatment of hypercholesterolaemia

          2. Obstructive or restrictive cardiomyopathy

          3. Uncorrected primary valvular disease

          4. Active myocarditis

          5. Decompensated heart failure or a need for inotropic therapy

          6. Myocardial infarction within the past 6 months

          7. Unstable angina or stroke within the past 3 months

          8. PCI (Percutaneous coronary intervention), CABG (coronary artery bypass graft)or
             implantation of cardioverter-defibrillator or biventricular pacemaker within the past
             3 months or a planned implantation of such a device

          9. Previous or planned cardiac transplantation

         10. Pericardial disease or systemic disease (eg amyloidosis)

         11. Acute or chronic liver disease

         12. Alanine and aspartate transminase concentrations more than 1.5 times the upper limit
             of normal

         13. Chronic muscle disease or an unexplained creatinine kinase level of more than 2.5
             times the upper limit of normal

         14. Serum creatinine level greater than 221 micromol/L

         15. Previous treatment with cyclosporine

         16. Exercise capacity limited by factors other than cardiac dyspnoea

         17. Hospitalisation within one month of randomisation

         18. Pregnant or lactating women or women of childbearing potential who were not adequately
             protected against becoming pregnant

         19. Any other concurrent condition that, in the opinion of the investigator, would prevent
             completion of the clinical trial</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/03/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>13</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/12/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Clinical Pharmacology, Alfred Hospital - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Alfred</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Heart failure (cardiomyopathy) is a chronic condition in which the heart fails to function as
      a pump to move blood around the body. This sets up a complex physiologic response to
      compensate, which include activation of many hormonal mechanisms which result in fluid
      accumulation.

      In recent years, medications to block the hormonal response to heart failure are given as
      standard drugs, and these include ACE inhibitors and beta blockers. Mortality is reduced with
      these medications, as well as symptoms improved. Other medications are also used in heart
      failure, for which a clear-cut benefit has not been demonstrated. Statins, also called HMG
      CoA reductase inhibitors, are used to reduce cholesterol levels and can help to prevent heart
      failure by preventing heart attacks. They have been used in heart failure that is not caused
      by heart attacks in the belief that they had "pleiotropic" effects, meaning that they had
      beneficial effects in heart failure separate from the reduction in cholesterol.

      However large trials in heart failure have demonstrated that statins do not increase survival
      compared with placebo. There is no evidence to recommend their routine use in established
      heart failure caused by either heart attacks or genetics.

      The investigators propose that the use of statins in heart failure is unnecessary and could
      be stopped. The importance of finding evidence to cease unproven medications in heart failure
      cannot be understated. Patients with heart failure take an average of six prescription
      medications each day. Each medication has side effects and the interactions of all the drugs
      together are unknown. Statins are the commonest reason for side effects in patients with
      heart failure, causing muscle pains and gastrointestinal upset.

      In this study, the investigators plan to withdraw statins from patients with stable heart
      failure in a closely monitored environment and watch for the effect of this on heart failure
      and on how they feel generally.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01554592</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Henry Krum, MBBS FRACP PhD</name>
      <address>Alfred Hospital/Monash University</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>