<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2961">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/10/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/10/2010</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01227889</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Study Comparing GSK2118436 to Dacarbazine (DTIC) in Previously Untreated Subjects With BRAF Mutation Positive Advanced (Stage III) or Metastatic (Stage IV) Melanoma</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase III Randomized, Open-label Study Comparing GSK2118436 to Dacarbazine (DTIC) in Previously Untreated Subjects With BRAF Mutation Positive Advanced (Stage III) or Metastatic (Stage IV) Melanoma</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>113683</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Malignant melanoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - GSK2118436
Treatment: drugs - Dacarbazine (DTIC)

Experimental: GSK2118436 - Subjects in this arm will receive GSK2118436 150 mg twice daily.

Active Comparator: Dacarbazine (DTIC) - Subjects will receive intravenous dacarbazine (DTIC) 1000 mg/m2 every 3 weeks

Experimental: Crossover - Subjects who initially receive DTIC will be allowed to receive GSK2118436 after initial progression.


Treatment: drugs: GSK2118436
150 mg twice daily

Treatment: drugs: Dacarbazine (DTIC)
Intravenous (IV), 1000 mg/m2 every 3 weeks until initial progression

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression-free Survival (PFS) as Assessed by the Investigator - PFS is defined as the interval of time between the date of randomization and the earlier of the date of disease progression or the date of death due to any cause. Disease progression was based on radiographic or photographic evidence, and assessments were made by the investigator according to Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) version 1.1. PD is defined as at least a 20% increase in the sum of the diameters of target lesions, taking as a reference, the smallest sum of diameters recorded since the treatment started (e.g., percent change from nadir, where nadir is defined as the smallest sum of diameters recorded since treatment start). In addition, the sum must have an absolute increase from nadir of 5 millimeters (mm). For participants who did not progress or die, PFS was censored at the date of last contact. Data are presented as median and 96% confidence interval.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time interval between the date of randomization and the earlier of the date of disease progression or the date of death due to any cause (up to 9.9 months)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression-free Survival (PFS) as Assessed by an Independent Radiologist: Randomized Phase - PFS is defined as the interval of time between the date of randomization and the earlier of the date of disease progression or the date of death due to any cause. Disease progression was based on radiographic or photographic evidence, and assessments were made by an independent radiologist according to RECIST version 1.1. PD is defined as at least a 20% increase in the sum of the diameters of target lesions, taking as a reference, the smallest sum of diameters recorded since the treatment started (e.g., percent change from nadir, where nadir is defined as the smallest sum of diameters recorded since treatment start). In addition, the sum must have an absolute increase from nadir of 5 mm. For participants who did not progress or die, PFS was censored at the date of last contact.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time interval between the date of randomization and the earlier of the date of disease progression or the date of death due to any cause (up to 9.9 months)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Survival - Overall survival is defined as the interval of time between the date of randomization and the date of death due to any cause. For participants who did not die, overall survival was censored at the date of last contact.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time interval between the date of randomization and the date of death due to any cause (up to 22.1 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With a Best Overall Response of Confirmed Complete Response (CR) or Confirmed Partial Response (PR) as Assessed by the Investigator: Randomized Phase - A participant was defined as a responder if he/she achieved either a CR (the disappearance of all target lesions. Any pathological lymph nodes must be &lt;10 mm in the short axis.) or PR (at least a 30% decrease in the sum of the diameters of target lesions, taking as a reference, the Baseline sum of the diameters [e.g., percent change from Baseline]). Response was evaluated by an investigator per RECIST, version 1.1. A participant without a post-Baseline assessment of response was considered a non-responder. Confirmation, per RECIST version 1.1, requires a confimatory disease assessment of CR or PR at least 28 days after the initial disease assessment of CR or PR.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From randomization until the first documented evidence of a confirmed complete response or partial response (median of 6.6 weeks)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With a Best Overall Response of Confirmed CR or PR as Assessed by an Independent Radiologist: Randomized Phase - A participant was defined as a responder if he/she achieved either a CR (the disappearance of all target lesions. Any pathological lymph nodes must be &lt;10 mm in the short axis.) or PR (at least a 30% decrease in the sum of the diameters of target lesions, taking as a reference, the Baseline sum of the diameters [e.g., percent change from Baseline]). Response was evaluated by an independent radiologist per RECIST, version 1.1. A participant without a post-Baseline assessment of response was considered a non-responder. Confirmation, per RECIST version 1.1, requires a confimatory disease assessment of CR or PR at least 28 days after the initial disease assessment of CR or PR.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From randomization until the first documented evidence of a confirmed complete response or partial response (median of 12.0 weeks)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of Response as Assessed by the Investigator: Randomized Phase - Duration of response for participants with either a CR (the disappearance of all target lesions. Any pathological lymph nodes must be &lt;10 mm in the short axis.) or PR (at least a 30% decrease in the sum of the diameters of target lesions, taking as a reference, the Baseline sum of the diameters [e.g., percent change from Baseline]) was defined as the time from the first documented evidence of a PR or CR until the first documented sign of PD or death due to any cause. PD is defined as at least a 20% increase in the sum of the diameters of target lesions, taking as a reference, the smallest sum of diameters recorded since the treatment started (e.g., percent change from nadir, where nadir is defined as the smallest sum of diameters recorded since treatment start). In addition, the sum must have an absolute increase from nadir of 5 mm.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time from the first documented evidence of PR or CR until the first documented sign of disease progression or death due to any cause (up to 65.6 weeks)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of Response as Assessed by an Independent Radiologist: Randomized Phase - Duration of response for participants with either a CR (the disappearance of all target lesions. Any pathological lymph nodes must be &lt;10 mm in the short axis.) or PR (at least a 30% decrease in the sum of the diameters of target lesions, taking as a reference, the Baseline sum of the diameters [e.g., percent change from Baseline]) was defined as the time from the first documented evidence of a PR or CR until the first documented sign of PD or death due to any cause. PD is defined as at least a 20% increase in the sum of the diameters of target lesions, taking as a reference, the smallest sum of diameters recorded since the treatment started (e.g., percent change from nadir, where nadir is defined as the smallest sum of diameters recorded since treatment start). In addition, the sum must have an absolute increase from nadir of 5 mm. NA indicates that data is not available.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time from the first documented evidence of PR or CR until the first documented sign of disease progression or death due to any cause (up to 7.4 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression-free Survival (PFS2) as Assessed by the Investigator: Crossover Phase - PFS2 is defined as the time from the first dose of GSK2118436, in participants randomized to DTIC who crossed over to GSK2118436 after initial progression, to the earliest date of radiographic or photographic disease progression or death due to any cause. Disease progression was based on radiographic or photographic evidence, and assessments were made by the investigator according to RECIST version 1.1. PD is defined as at least a 20% increase in the sum of the diameters of target lesions, taking as a reference, the smallest sum of diameters recorded since the treatment started (e.g., percent change from nadir, where nadir is defined as the smallest sum of diameters recorded since treatment start). In addition, the sum must have an absolute increase from nadir of 5 mm. For participants who did not progress or die, PFS was censored at the date of last contact.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time from first dose of GSK2118436 in participants who crossover after initial progression to the earliest date of radiographical or photographical PD or death due to any cause (up to 6.4 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With a Best Overall Response of Confirmed Complete Response (CR) or Confirmed Partial Response (PR) as Assessed by the Investigator: Crossover Phase - A participant was defined as a responder if he/she achieved either a CR (the disappearance of all target lesions. Any pathological lymph nodes must be &lt;10 mm in the short axis.) or PR (at least a 30% decrease in the sum of the diameters of target lesions, taking as a reference, the Baseline sum of the diameters [e.g., percent change from Baseline]). Response was evaluated by an investigator per RECIST, version 1.1. A participant without a post-Baseline assessment of response was considered a non-responder. Confirmation, per RECIST version 1.1, requires a confimatory disease assessment of CR or PR at least 28 days after the initial disease assessment of CR or PR.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From randomization until the first documented evidence of a confirmed complete response or partial response (up to 6.4 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of Response as Assessed by the Investigator: Crossover Phase - Duration of response for participants with either a CR (the disappearance of all target lesions. Any pathological lymph nodes must be &lt;10 mm in the short axis.) or PR (at least a 30% decrease in the sum of the diameters of target lesions, taking as a reference, the Baseline sum of the diameters [e.g., percent change from Baseline]) was defined as the time from the first documented evidence of a PR or CR until the first documented sign of PD or death due to any cause. PD is defined as at least a 20% increase in the sum of the diameters of target lesions, taking as a reference, the smallest sum of diameters recorded since the treatment started (e.g., percent change from nadir, where nadir is defined as the smallest sum of diameters recorded since treatment start). In addition, the sum must have an absolute increase from nadir of 5 mm.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time from the first documented evidence of PR or CR until the first documented sign of disease progression or death due to any cause (up to 6.4 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With Non-melanoma Skin Lesions: Randomized Phase - Dermatological examinations were performed by the investigator, or at the discretion of the investigator, referred to a dermatologist. The number of participants with non-melanoma skin lessions was assessed from the time of Screening until study completion or discontinuation from the study for any reason.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Screening until study completion or discontinuation from the study (up to 9.9 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Agreement Rate for V600E Mutation Validation of the BRAF Mutation Assay - Analytical and clinical validation of the companion diagnostic (cDx) assay was performed to determine the extent of agreement between the bioMerieux cDx assay (THxID BRAF Assay) and the Clinical Trial Assay (CTA) to detect BRAF mutations to determine participant eligibility into the study. Skin tissue samples collected at the Screening visit were used for this analysis. Multiple specimen per participant were analyzed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Screening</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Adults at least 18 years of age

          -  Has advanced (unresectable Stage III) or metastatic (Stage IV) melanoma that is BRAF
             mutation positive (V600E)

          -  Is treatment naive for advanced (unresectable) or metastatic melanoma, with the
             exception of Interleukin 2 (IL-2) which is allowed.

          -  Has measurable disease according to RECIST 1.1 criteria.

          -  Women of child-bearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test within 14 days
             prior to the first dose of study treatment.

          -  Women with reproductive potential must be willing to practice acceptable methods of
             birth control during the study and for up to 4 weeks after the last dose of study
             medication.

          -  Men with reproductive potential must be willing to practice acceptable methods of
             birth control during the study and for up to 16 weeks after the last dose of study
             medication.

          -  Must have adequate organ function.

          -  Must have Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status of 0-1.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Currently receiving cancer therapy (chemotherapy, radiation therapy, immunotherapy,
             biologic therapy or surgery).

          -  Evidence of active central nervous system (CNS) disease.

          -  Previous treatment for metastatic melanoma, including treatment with BRAF or MEK
             inhibitor.

          -  A history of other malignancy. Subjects who have been disease-free for 5 years or
             subjects with a history of complete resected non-melanoma skin cancer or successfully
             treated in situ carcinoma are eligible.

          -  History of Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) infection.

          -  Certain cardiac abnormalities</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>23/12/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>251</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>16/09/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,SA,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Westmead</hospital>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Southport</hospital>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Nedlands</hospital>
    <postcode>2145 - Westmead</postcode>
    <postcode>4215 - Southport</postcode>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Alabama</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Indiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Michigan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Hampshire</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Alberta</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>British Columbia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Quebec</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Bordeaux</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Lille</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Marseille Cedex 5</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Nice</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Paris cedex 18</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Paris</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Reims</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Villejuif</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Baden-Wuerttemberg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Bayern</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Hessen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Niedersachsen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Nordrhein-Westfalen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Rheinland-Pfalz</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Saarland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Sachsen-Anhalt</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Schleswig-Holstein</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Thueringen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Budapest</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Debrecen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Gyor</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Miskolc</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Pecs</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ireland</country>
      <state>Cork</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ireland</country>
      <state>Dublin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ireland</country>
      <state>Galway</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Emilia-Romagna</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Friuli-Venezia-Giulia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Lazio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Liguria</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Lombardia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Toscana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Umbria</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Veneto</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Amsterdam</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Brzozow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Konin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Krakow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Slupsk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Warszawa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Kazan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Moscow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Ryazan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>St. Petersburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Stavropol</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Badalona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Hospitalet de Llobregat, Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Pamplona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Sevilla</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>GlaxoSmithKline</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>BRF113683 is a Phase III, randomized, open-label study comparing the efficacy, safety, and
      tolerability of GSK2118436 to dacarbazine (DTIC), in subjects with BRAF mutant advanced
      (Stage III) or metastatic (Stage IV) melanoma. Subjects will be randomized to receive 150 mg
      of GSK2118436 twice daily or 1000 mg/m2 DTIC every 3 weeks and continue on treatment until
      disease progression, death, or unacceptable adverse event. Subjects who progress on DTIC will
      be allowed to crossover to an optional extension arm of the study to receive GSK2118436.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01227889</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Hauschild A, Grob JJ, Demidov LV, Jouary T, Gutzmer R, Millward M, Rutkowski P, Blank CU, Miller WH Jr, Kaempgen E, Martín-Algarra S, Karaszewska B, Mauch C, Chiarion-Sileni V, Martin AM, Swann S, Haney P, Mirakhur B, Guckert ME, Goodman V, Chapman PB. Dabrafenib in BRAF-mutated metastatic melanoma: a multicentre, open-label, phase 3 randomised controlled trial. Lancet. 2012 Jul 28;380(9839):358-65. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(12)60868-X. Epub 2012 Jun 25.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>GSK Clinical Trials</name>
      <address>GlaxoSmithKline</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>