<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="1072">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/02/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/02/2006</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00294047</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Study to Evaluate the Efficacy of the Human Papillomavirus Vaccine in Healthy Adult Women of 26 Years of Age and Older</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Study to Evaluate Safety, Immunogenicity and Efficacy of GSK Biologicals HPV-16/18 L1/AS04 Vaccine Administered Intramuscularly According to a Three-dose Schedule (0, 1, 6 Month) in Healthy Adult Female Subjects Aged 26 Years and Above</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>104820</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Infections, Papillomavirus</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - Cervarix
Other interventions - Placebo control

Experimental: Cervarix Group - Subjects received 3 doses of Cervarix vaccine. Cervarix vaccine was administered intramuscularly into the deltoid region of the non-dominant arm according to a 0, 1, 6 months schedule.

Placebo Comparator: Aluminium Hydroxide Group - Subjects received 3 doses of Aluminium Hydroxide [Al(OH)3]. Aluminium Hydroxide was administered intramuscularly into the deltoid region of the non-dominant arm according to a 0, 1, 6 months schedule.


Other interventions: Cervarix
Subjects were planned to receive three doses of the study vaccine administered intramuscularly according to a 0, 1, 6 month vaccination schedule.

Other interventions: Placebo control
Subjects were planned to receive three doses of the control vaccine administered intramuscularly according to a 0, 1, 6 month vaccination schedule.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Persistent Infection (6-month Definition) With Human Papillomavirus (HPV)-16 or HPV-18 and/or With Histopathologically-confirmed Cervical Intraepithelial Neoplasia (CIN)1+ Associated With HPV-16 and/or -18 Cervical Infection. - CIN1+ = CIN grades 1, 2 and 3, adenocarcinoma in situ (AIS) and invasive cervical cancer.
Persistent HPV infection = detection of the same HPV type(s) by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) in cervical samples at 2 consecutive evaluations over approximately a 6-month interval.
DNA- and sero-/+: subjects HPV deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) negative (DNA-) at Month 0 and 6 and seronegative/positive (sero-/+) at Month 0 for the corresponding HPV-type by Enzyme-linked Immunosorbent Assay (ELISA)
Overall: subjects DNA- at Month 0 and 6 for the corresponding HPV-type, regardless of initial serostatus</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 48</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Persistent Infection (6-month Definition) With HPV-16 or HPV-18 and/or With Histopathologically-CIN1+ Associated With HPV-16 and/or -18 Cervical Infection Detected Using the HPV Type Assignment Algorithm (TAA). - CIN1+ = CIN grades 1, 2 and 3, AIS and invasive cervical cancer. Persistent cervical HPV infection (6-month definition) = detection of the same HPV type(s) by PCR in cervical samples at 2 consecutive evaluations over approximately a 6-month interval.
DNA- and sero-/+: subjects HPV DNA negative (DNA-) at Month 0 and Month 6 for the corresponding HPV-type and seronegative/positive (sero-/+) for HPV-16 and/or HPV-18 by ELISA at baseline (Month 0).
Overall: subjects DNA- at Month 0 and Month 6 for the corresponding HPV-type and regardless of initial serostatus at baseline.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 48</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Persistent Infection (6-month Definition) With Human Papillomavirus (HPV)-16 or HPV-18 and/or With Histopathologically-confirmed Cervical Intraepithelial Neoplasia (CIN)1+ Associated With HPV-16 and/or -18 Cervical Infection. - CIN1+ = CIN grades 1, 2 and 3, adenocarcinoma in situ (AIS) and invasive cervical cancer. Persistent HPV infection = detection of the same HPV type(s) by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) in cervical samples at 2 consecutive evaluations over approximately a 6-month interval. - DNA- and sero-/+: subjects HPV deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) negative (DNA-) at Month 0 and 6 and seronegative/positive (sero-/+) at Month 0 for the corresponding HPV-type by Enzyme-linked Immunosorbent Assay (ELISA) - Overall: subjects DNA- at Month 0 and 6 for the corresponding HPV-type, regardless of initial serostatus</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 84</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Persistent Infection (6-month Definition) With HPV-16 or HPV-18 and/or With Histopathologically-CIN1+ Associated With HPV-16 and/or -18 Cervical Infection Detected Using the HPV Type Assignment Algorithm (TAA). - CIN1+ = CIN grades 1, 2 and 3, AIS and invasive cervical cancer. Persistent cervical HPV infection (6-month definition) = detection of the same HPV type(s) by PCR in cervical samples at 2 consecutive evaluations over approximately a 6-month interval. - DNA- and sero-/+: subjects HPV DNA negative (DNA-) at Month 0 and Month 6 for the corresponding HPV-type and seronegative/positive (sero-/+) for HPV-16 and/or HPV-18 by ELISA at baseline (Month 0). - Overall: subjects DNA- at Month 0 and Month 6 for the corresponding HPV-type and regardless of initial serostatus at baseline.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 84</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Persistent Infection (6-month Definition) With Human Papillomavirus (HPV)-16 or HPV-18 - Persistent cervical HPV infection (6-month definition) was defined as the detection of the same HPV type(s) by PCR in cervical samples at 2 consecutive evaluations over approximately a 6-month interval.
Detection was done in:
DNA- and sero-/+: subjects HPV DNA negative (DNA-) at Month 0 and Month 6 for the corresponding HPV-type and seronegative/positive (sero-/+) for HPV-16 and/or HPV-18 by ELISA at baseline (Month 0).
Overall: subjects DNA- at Month 0 and Month 6 for the corresponding HPV-type and regardless of initial serostatus at baseline.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Persistent Infection (12-month Definition) With Human Papillomavirus (HPV)-16 or HPV-18 - Persistent cervical HPV infection (12-month definition) was defined as the detection of the same HPV type(s) PCR in cervical samples at all available time points over approximately a 12-month interval (evaluations are planned at approximately 6-month intervals).
DNA- and sero-/+: subjects HPV DNA negative (DNA-) at Month 0 and Month 6 for the corresponding HPV-type and seronegative/positive (sero-/+) for HPV-16 and/or HPV-18 by ELISA at baseline (Month 0).
Overall: subjects DNA- at Month 0 and Month 6 for the corresponding HPV-type and regardless of initial serostatus at baseline.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Persistent Infection (6-month Definition) With Oncogenic HPV Types Individually or in Combinations. - Persistent cervical HPV infection (6-month definition) = detection of the same HPV type(s) by PCR in cervical samples at 2 consecutive evaluations over approximately a 6-month interval.
Oncogenic HPV types included HPV-16, 18, 31, 33, 35, 39, 45, 51, 52, 56, 58, 59, 66 and 68.
Detection was done in subjects HPV DNA- for the corresponding HPV type at baseline (at month 0 and Month 6) regardless of initial serostatus.
HPV-HRW=All high-risk (oncogenic) HPV types excluding HPV-16 and HPV-18. HPV-HR=High-risk (oncogenic) HPV types: HPV-16, 18, 31, 33, 35, 39, 45, 51, 52, 56, 58, 59, 66 and 68.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Persistent Infection (12-month Definition) With Oncogenic HPV Types Individually or in Combinations. - Persistent HPV infection (12-month definition) = detection of the same HPV type(s) by PCR in cervical samples at available time points over approximately a 12-month interval (evaluations are planned at approximately 6-month intervals).
Oncogenic HPV types included HPV-16, 18, 31, 33, 35, 39, 45, 51, 52, 56, 58, 59, 66 and 68.
subjects HPV DNA- for the corresponding HPV type at Month 0 6, regardless of initial serostatus.
HPV-HRW=All high-risk (oncogenic) HPV types excluding HPV-16 and HPV-18 HPV-HR=High-risk (oncogenic) HPV types: HPV-16, 18, 31, 33, 35, 39, 45, 51, 52, 56, 58, 59, 66 , 68</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Histopathologically-confirmed Cervical Intraepithelial Neoplasia (CIN)2+ Associated With HPV-16 and/or -18 Cervical Infection Detected Within the Lesional Component of the Cervical Tissue Specimen - CIN2+ was defined as CIN grades 2 and 3, adenocarcinoma in situ (AIS) and invasive cervical cancer.
Detection was done in:
DNA- and sero-: subjects HPV deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) negative (DNA-) at Month 0 and Month 6 for the corresponding HPV-type and seronegative (sero-) for HPV-16 and/or HPV-18 by Enzyme-linked Immunosorbent Assay (ELISA) at baseline (Month 0).
Overall: subjects DNA- at Month 0 and Month 6 for the corresponding HPV-type and regardless of initial serostatus at baseline.
Note: Results for seropositive status were not analysed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Histopathologically-confirmed Cervical Intraepithelial Neoplasia (CIN)1+ Associated With HPV-16 and/or -18 Cervical Infection Detected Within the Lesional Component of the Cervical Tissue Specimen - CIN1+ was defined as CIN grades 1, 2 and 3, adenocarcinoma in situ (AIS) and invasive cervical cancer.
Detection was done in:
DNA- and sero-/+: subjects HPV deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) negative (DNA-) at Month 0 and Month 6 for the corresponding HPV-type and seronegative/positive (sero-/+) for HPV-16 and/or HPV-18 by Enzyme-linked Immunosorbent Assay (ELISA) at baseline (Month 0).
Overall: subjects DNA- at Month 0 and Month 6 for the corresponding HPV-type and regardless of initial serostatus at baseline.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Histopathologically-confirmed Cervical Intraepithelial Neoplasia (CIN)1+ Associated With HPV-16 and/or -18 Cervical Infection Detected Within the Lesional Component of the Cervical Tissue Specimen - CIN1+ was defined as CIN grades 1, 2 and 3, adenocarcinoma in situ (AIS) and invasive cervical cancer.
Detection was done on all subjects irrespective of their baseline HPV DNA and serostatus.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Histopathologically-confirmed Cervical Intraepithelial Neoplasia (CIN)1+ Irrespective of HPV Cervical Infection and Irrespective of Baseline HPV DNA Status - CIN1+ was defined as CIN grades 1, 2 and 3, adenocarcinoma in situ (AIS) and invasive cervical cancer.
Detection was done on all subjects irrespective of their baseline HPV DNA status.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Any Cytological Abnormalities Associated With HPV-16 or HPV-18 Cervical Infection - Cytological abnormalities = atypical squamous cells of undetermined significance (ASC-US).
Detection was done in:
DNA- and sero-: subjects HPV deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) negative (DNA-) at Month 0 and Month 6 for the corresponding HPV-type and seronegative (sero-) for HPV-16 and/or HPV-18 by Enzyme-linked Immunosorbent Assay (ELISA) at baseline (Month 0).
Overall: subjects DNA- at Month 0 and Month 6 for the corresponding HPV-type and regardless of initial serostatus at baseline.
Results for seropositive status were not analysed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Cytological Abnormalities Associated With Oncogenic HPV Types Individually or in Combinations - Oncogenic HPV types included HPV-16, 18, 31, 33, 35, 39, 45, 51, 52, 56, 58, 59, 66 and 68.
Detection was done in subjects who were HPV DNA negative for the corresponding HPV type at baseline (at month 0 and Month 6) regardless of initial serostatus.
HRW-HPV= All high-risk (oncogenic) HPV types excluding HPV-16 and HPV-18 HPV-HR= High-risk (oncogenic) HPV types: HPV-16, 18, 31, 33, 35, 39, 45, 51, 52, 56, 58, 59, 66 and 68</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Histopathologically Confirmed Reduction of Local Cervical Therapy - Detection was done on all subjects irrespective of their baseline HPV DNA status.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With First Colposcopy - Detection was done on all subjects irrespective of their baseline HPV DNA status.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Persistent Infection (6-month Definition) With Human Papillomavirus (HPV)-16 or HPV-18 and/or With Histopathologically-confirmed Cervical Intraepithelial Neoplasia (CIN)1+ Associated With HPV-16 and/or -18 Cervical Infection - Persistent cervical HPV infection (6-month definition) was defined as the detection of the same HPV type(s) by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) in cervical samples at 2 consecutive evaluations over approximately a 6-month interval.
CIN1+ was defined as CIN grades 1, 2 and 3, adenocarcinoma in situ (AIS) and invasive cervical cancer.
Detection was done on all subjects irrespective of their baseline HPV DNA and serostatus.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Persistent Infection (6-month Definition) With HPV-16 or HPV-18 and/or With Histopathologically-confirmed CIN1+ Associated With HPV-16 and/or -18 Cervical Infection Detected Using the HPV Type Assignment Algorithm (TAA). - Persistent cervical HPV infection (6-month definition) was defined as the detection of the same HPV type(s) by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) in cervical samples at 2 consecutive evaluations over approximately a 6-month interval.
Detection was done on all subjects irrespective of their baseline HPV DNA and serostatus.
The lesion was assigned to an HPV type found in the lesion if (1) the same HPV type was found in at least 1 of the 2 (closest) preceding cytology samples, or (2) none of the HPV types found in the lesion were found in any of the 2 preceding cytology samples (isolate HPV types)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Seroconverted Subjects Against HPV-16 in the Immunogenicity Subset. - Seroconversion was defined as the appearance of antibodies (i.e.; titre greater than or equal to the cut-off value) in the serum of subjects seronegative before vaccination.
HPV-16 assay cut-off value was defined as greater than or equal to 8 ELISA units per millilitre (EL.U/mL). Seronegative (Sero-) subjects are subjects who had an antibody concentration below 8 EL.U/mL prior to vaccination. Seropositive (Sero+) subjects are subjects who had an antibody concentration equal to or above 8 EL.U/mL prior to vaccination.
Immuno subset=subjects from selected sites N=1000, at least 250 per region</outcome>
      <timepoint>At pre-vaccination and at Month 7, 12, 18, 24, 36, 48, 60, 72 and 84</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Seroconverted Subjects Against HPV-18 in the Immunogenicity Subset. - Seroconversion was defined as the appearance of antibodies (i.e.; titre greater than or equal to the cut-off value) in the serum of subjects seronegative before vaccination.
HPV-18 assay cut-off value was defined as greater than or equal to 7 ELISA units per millilitre (EL.U/mL). Seronegative (Sero-) subjects are subjects who had an antibody concentration below 7 EL.U/mL prior to vaccination. Seropositive (Sero+) subjects are subjects who had an antibody concentration equal to or above 7 EL.U/mL prior to vaccination.
Immuno subset=subjects from selected sites N=1000, at least 250 per region</outcome>
      <timepoint>At pre-vaccination and at Month 7, 12, 18, 24, 36, 48, 60, 72 and 84</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Geometric Mean Concentrations (GMCs) Against HPV-16 Antibody in the Immunogenicity Subset. - GMCs were expressed in ELISA units per milliliter (EL.U/mL).
Seronegative (Sero-) subjects are subjects who had an antibody concentration below 8 EL.U/mL prior to vaccination. Seropositive (Sero+) subjects are subjects who had an antibody concentration equal to or above 8 EL.U/mL prior to vaccination.
Immuno subset=subjects from selected sites (N=1000, at least 250 per region)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At pre-vaccination and at Month 7, 12, 18, 24, 36, 48, 60, 72 and 84</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Geometric Mean Concentrations (GMCs) Against HPV-18 Antibody in the Immunogenicity Subset. - GMCs were expressed in ELISA units per milliliter (EL.U/mL).
Seronegative (Sero-) subjects are subjects who had an antibody concentration below 7 EL.U/mL prior to vaccination. Seropositive (Sero+) subjects are subjects who had an antibody concentration equal to or above 7 EL.U/mL prior to vaccination.
Immuno subset=subjects from selected sites (N=1000, at least 250 per region)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At pre-vaccination and at Month 7, 12, 18, 24, 36, 48, 60, 72 and 84</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Seroconverted Subjects Against HPV-16 and HPV-18 Viral Neutralization in a Selected Subset of Subjects. - Seroconversion was defined as the appearance of antibodies (i.e.; titre greater than or equal to the cut-off value) in the serum of subjects seronegative before vaccination. HPV-16/18 assay cut-off value was defined as greater than or equal to 40 Estimated dose 50% (ED50). Sero- subjects are subjects who had an antibody concentration below 40 ED50 prior to vaccination. Sero+ subjects are subjects who had an antibody concentration equal to or above 50 ED50 prior to vaccination. ED50 = the estimated serum dilution reducing the signal generated by viral infection by 50%</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to vaccination and at Months 7, 12, 18, 24, 48 and 84.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Geometric Mean Titers (GMTs) Against HPV-16 and HPV-18 Viral Neutralization Antibodies in a Selected Subset of Subjects. - Titers are expressed as geometric mean antibody titers (GMTs).
Seronegative (Sero-) subjects are subjects who had an antibody titer below 40 ED50 prior to vaccination. Seropositive (Sero+) subjects are subjects who had an antibody titer equal to or above 40 ED50 prior to vaccination.
ED50 = Estimated dose 50%, the estimated serum dilution reducing the signal generated by viral infection by 50%</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to vaccination and at Months 7, 12, 18, 24, 48 and 84.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects Reporting Any and Grade 3 Solicited Local Symptoms. - Solicited local symptoms assessed were pain, redness and swelling. Any was defined as any solicited local symptom reported irrespective of intensity. Grade 3 pain was defined as pain that prevented normal activity. Grade 3 redness and swelling was defined as redness/swelling above 50 millimeter (mm).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 7 days (Days 0-6) after vaccination</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects Reporting Any, Grade 3 and Related Solicited General Symptoms. - Solicited general symptoms assessed were arthralgia, fatigue, gastrointestinal, headache, myalgia, rash, urticaria and fever (Fever = axillary temperature above 37.5 degrees Celsius (°C)). Any = any solicited general symptom reported irrespective of intensity and relationship to vaccination. Related = symptoms considered by the investigator to have a causal relationship to vaccination. Grade 3 symptoms = symptoms that prevented normal activity. Grade 3 urticaria = urticaria distributed on at least 4 body areas. Grade 3 fever = axillary temperature above 39.0°C.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 7 days (Days 0-6) after vaccination</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects Reporting Any, Grade 3 and Related Unsolicited Adverse Events (AEs). - An unsolicited adverse event is any adverse event (i.e. any untoward medical occurrence in a patient or clinical investigation subject, temporally associated with use of a medicinal product, whether or not considered related to the medicinal product) reported in addition to those solicited during the clinical study and any solicited symptom with onset outside the specified period of follow-up for solicited symptoms. Grade 3 unsolicited AE = an event that prevented normal activity.
A related AE = event assessed by the investigator as causally related to the study vaccination.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 30 days (Days 0 - 29) post-vaccination period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects Reporting Any and Related Serious Adverse Events (SAEs). - SAEs assessed include medical occurrences that results in death, are life threatening, require hospitalization or prolongation of hospitalization, results in disability/incapacity or are a congenital anomaly/birth defect in the offspring of a study subjects. A related SAE was defined as an event assessed by the investigator as causally related to the study vaccination.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 48 and up to Month 84</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects Reporting Related or Fatal Serious Adverse Event. - Serious adverse events (SAEs) assessed include medical occurrences that result in death, are life threatening, require hospitalization or prolongation of hospitalization or result in disability/incapacity.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 84</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects Reporting Any AE/SAE Leading to Premature Discontinuation of the Study. - An unsolicited AE covers any untoward medical occurrence in a clinical investigation subject temporally associated with the use of a medicinal product, whether or not considered related to the medicinal product and reported in addition to those solicited during the clinical study and any solicited symptom with onset outside the specified period of follow-up for solicited symptoms.
Serious adverse events (SAEs) assessed include medical occurrences that result in death, are life threatening, require hospitalization or prolongation of hospitalization or result in disability/incapacity.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 84</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects Reporting New Onset of Chronic Disease (NOCDs). - NOCDs include autoimmune disorders, asthma and type I diabetes.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects Reporting New Onset of Autoimmune Disease (NOADs).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects Reporting Medically Significant Conditions (MAEs). - Medically significant conditions were defined as: AEs prompting emergency room or physician visits that were not (1) related to common diseases or (2) routine visits for physical examination or vaccination, or SAEs that were not related to common diseases. Common diseases included: upper respiratory infections, sinusitis, pharyngitis, gastroenteritis, urinary tract infections, cervicovaginal yeast infections, menstrual cycle abnormalities and injury.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Pregnancies and Their Outcomes. - Pregnancy outcomes are live infant, premature live infant, elective termination, ectopic pregnancy, spontaneous abortion, lost to follow-up and pregnancy ongoing. For each category it was specified if the infant presents congenital anomaly (CA) or no apparent congenital anomaly (No ACA).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Histopathologically-confirmed Cervical Intraepithelial Neoplasia (CIN)1+ Associated With HPV-16 and/or -18 Cervical Infection Detected Using the Type Assignment Algorithm (TAA) - CIN1+ was defined as CIN grades 1, 2 and 3, adenocarcinoma in situ (AIS) and invasive cervical cancer.
Detection was done on subjects DNA- at Month 0 and Month 6 for the corresponding HPV-type and regardless of initial serostatus at baseline.
TAA: Type assignment algorithm. The lesion was assigned to an HPV type found in the lesion if
the same HPV type was found in at least one of the two (closest) preceding cytology samples, or
none of the HPV types found in the lesion were found in any of the two preceding cytology samples (isolate HPV types)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Persistent Infection (6-month Definition) With Human Papillomavirus (HPV)-16 or HPV-18 - Persistent cervical HPV infection (6-month definition) was defined as the detection of the same HPV type(s) by PCR in cervical samples at 2 consecutive evaluations over approximately a 6-month interval. Detection was done in: - DNA- and sero-/+: subjects HPV DNA negative (DNA-) at Month 0 and Month 6 for the corresponding HPV-type and seronegative/positive (sero-/+) for HPV-16 and/or HPV-18 by ELISA at baseline (Month 0). - Overall: subjects DNA- at Month 0 and Month 6 for the corresponding HPV-type and regardless of initial serostatus at baseline.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 84</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Persistent Infection (12-month Definition) With Human Papillomavirus (HPV)-16 or HPV-18 - Persistent cervical HPV infection (12-month definition) was defined as the detection of the same HPV type(s) PCR in cervical samples at all available time points over approximately a 12-month interval (evaluations are planned at approximately 6-month intervals). - DNA- and sero-/+: subjects HPV DNA negative (DNA-) at Month 0 and Month 6 for the corresponding HPV-type and seronegative/positive (sero-/+) for HPV-16 and/or HPV-18 by ELISA at baseline (Month 0). - Overall: subjects DNA- at Month 0 and Month 6 for the corresponding HPV-type and regardless of initial serostatus at baseline.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 84</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Persistent Infection (6-month Definition) With Oncogenic HPV Types Individually or in Combinations. - Persistent cervical HPV infection (6-month definition) = detection of the same HPV type(s) by PCR in cervical samples at 2 consecutive evaluations over approximately a 6-month interval. Oncogenic HPV types included HPV-16, 18, 31, 33, 35, 39, 45, 51, 52, 56, 58, 59, 66 and 68. Detection was done in subjects HPV DNA- for the corresponding HPV type at baseline (at month 0 and Month 6) regardless of initial serostatus. HPV-HRW=All high-risk (oncogenic) HPV types excluding HPV-16 and HPV-18. HPV-HR=High-risk (oncogenic) HPV types: HPV-16, 18, 31, 33, 35, 39, 45, 51, 52, 56, 58, 59, 66 and 68.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 84</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Persistent Infection (12-month Definition) With Oncogenic HPV Types Individually or in Combinations. - Oncogenic HPV types included HPV-16, 18, 31, 33, 35, 39, 45, 51, 52, 56, 58, 59, 66 and 68. subjects HPV DNA- for the corresponding HPV type at Month 0 6, regardless of initial serostatus. HPV-HRW=All high-risk (oncogenic) HPV types excluding HPV-16 and HPV-18 HPV-HR=High-risk (oncogenic) HPV types: HPV-16, 18, 31, 33, 35, 39, 45, 51, 52, 56, 58, 59, 66 , 68</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 84</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Histopathologically-confirmed Cervical Intraepithelial Neoplasia (CIN)2+ Associated With HPV-16 and/or -18 Cervical Infection Detected Within the Lesional Component of the Cervical Tissue Specimen - CIN2+ was defined as CIN grades 2 and 3, adenocarcinoma in situ (AIS) and invasive cervical cancer. Detection was done in: - DNA- and sero-: subjects HPV deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) negative (DNA-) at Month 0 and Month 6 for the corresponding HPV-type and seronegative (sero-) for HPV-16 and/or HPV-18 by Enzyme-linked Immunosorbent Assay (ELISA) at baseline (Month 0). - Overall: subjects DNA- at Month 0 and Month 6 for the corresponding HPV-type and regardless of initial serostatus at baseline. Note: Results for seropositive status were not analysed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 84</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Histopathologically-confirmed Cervical Intraepithelial Neoplasia (CIN)1+ Associated With HPV-16 and/or -18 Cervical Infection Detected Within the Lesional Component of the Cervical Tissue Specimen - CIN1+ was defined as CIN grades 1, 2 and 3, adenocarcinoma in situ (AIS) and invasive cervical cancer. Detection was done in: - DNA- and sero-/+: subjects HPV deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) negative (DNA-) at Month 0 and Month 6 for the corresponding HPV-type and seronegative/positive (sero-/+) for HPV-16 and/or HPV-18 by Enzyme-linked Immunosorbent Assay (ELISA) at baseline (Month 0). - Overall: subjects DNA- at Month 0 and Month 6 for the corresponding HPV-type and regardless of initial serostatus at baseline.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 84</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Histopathologically-confirmed Cervical Intraepithelial Neoplasia (CIN)1+ Associated With HPV-16 and/or -18 Cervical Infection Detected Within the Lesional Component of the Cervical Tissue Specimen</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 84</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Histopathologically-confirmed Cervical Intraepithelial Neoplasia (CIN)1+ Irrespective of HPV Cervical Infection and Irrespective of Baseline HPV DNA Status - CIN1+ was defined as CIN grades 1, 2 and 3, adenocarcinoma in situ (AIS) and invasive cervical cancer. Detection was done on all subjects irrespective of their baseline HPV DNA status.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 84</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Any Cytological Abnormalities Associated With HPV-16 or HPV-18 Cervical Infection - Cytological abnormalities = atypical squamous cells of undetermined significance (ASC-US). Detection was done in: - DNA- and sero-: subjects HPV deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) negative (DNA-) at Month 0 and Month 6 for the corresponding HPV-type and seronegative (sero-) for HPV-16 and/or HPV-18 by Enzyme-linked Immunosorbent Assay (ELISA) at baseline (Month 0). - Overall: subjects DNA- at Month 0 and Month 6 for the corresponding HPV-type and regardless of initial serostatus at baseline. Results for seropositive status were not analysed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 84</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Cytological Abnormalities Associated With Oncogenic HPV Types Individually or in Combinations - Oncogenic HPV types included HPV-16, 18, 31, 33, 35, 39, 45, 51, 52, 56, 58, 59, 66 and 68. Detection was done in subjects who were HPV DNA negative for the corresponding HPV type at baseline (at month 0 and Month 6) regardless of initial serostatus. HRW-HPV= All high-risk (oncogenic) HPV types excluding HPV-16 and HPV-18 HPV-HR= High-risk (oncogenic) HPV types: HPV-16, 18, 31, 33, 35, 39, 45, 51, 52, 56, 58, 59, 66 and 68</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Histopathologically Confirmed Reduction of Local Cervical Therapy - Detection was done on all subjects irrespective of their baseline HPV DNA status.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 84</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With First Colposcopy - Detection was done on all subjects irrespective of their baseline HPV DNA status.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 84</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Persistent Infection (6-month Definition) With Human Papillomavirus (HPV)-16 or HPV-18 and/or With Histopathologically-confirmed Cervical Intraepithelial Neoplasia (CIN)1+ Associated With HPV-16 and/or -18 Cervical Infection - Persistent cervical HPV infection (6-month definition) was defined as the detection of the same HPV type(s) by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) in cervical samples at 2 consecutive evaluations over approximately a 6-month interval. CIN1+ was defined as CIN grades 1, 2 and 3, adenocarcinoma in situ (AIS) and invasive cervical cancer. Detection was done on all subjects irrespective of their baseline HPV DNA and serostatus.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 84</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Persistent Infection (6-month Definition) With HPV-16 or HPV-18 and/or With Histopathologically-confirmed CIN1+ Associated With HPV-16 and/or -18 Cervical Infection Detected Using the HPV Type Assignment Algorithm (TAA). - Persistent cervical HPV infection (6-month definition) was defined as the detection of the same HPV type(s) by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) in cervical samples at 2 consecutive evaluations over approximately a 6-month interval. Detection was done on all subjects irrespective of their baseline HPV DNA and serostatus. The lesion was assigned to an HPV type found in the lesion if (1) the same HPV type was found in at least 1 of the 2 (closest) preceding cytology samples, or (2) none of the HPV types found in the lesion were found in any of the 2 preceding cytology samples (isolate HPV types)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 84</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria:

          -  A woman who the investigator believes that she can and will comply with the
             requirements of the protocol.

          -  A women of at least 26 years of age at the time of the first vaccination.

          -  Written informed consent obtained from the subject prior to enrolment.

          -  Free of obvious health problems as established by medical history and clinical
             examination before entering into the study.

          -  Subject must have intact cervix.

          -  Subject must have a negative urine pregnancy test. This test is not applicable to
             women of non-childbearing potential.

          -  Subject must be of non-childbearing potential or, if of childbearing potential, she
             must be abstinent or must be using an effective method of birth control for 30 days
             prior to the first vaccination and must agree to continue such precautions for two
             months after completion of the vaccination series.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>26</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Female</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria:

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding (women must be at least three months post-pregnancy and not
             breastfeeding to enter the study).

          -  A women planning to become pregnant, likely to become pregnant (as determined by the
             investigator) or planning to discontinue contraceptive precautions during the
             vaccination phase of the study, i.e. up to two months after the last vaccine dose
             (Month 0 - 8).

          -  Use of any investigational or non-registered product (drug or vaccine) other than the
             study vaccine within 30 days preceding the first dose of study vaccine, or planned use
             during the study period (up to Month 84).

          -  Chronic administration of immunosuppressants or other immune-modifying drugs within
             six months prior to the first vaccine dose.

          -  Planned administration/administration of a vaccine not foreseen by the study protocol
             within 30 days before and 30 days after (i.e. days 0 - 29) the first dose of study
             vaccine. Planned administration/administration of routine vaccines up to 8 days before
             the first dose of study vaccine is allowed. Enrolment will be deferred until the
             subject is outside of specified window.

          -  Previous administration of components of the investigational vaccine

          -  Previous vaccination against HPV or planned administration of any HPV vaccine other
             than that foreseen by the study protocol during the study period.

          -  History of HPV infection/treatment or planned treatment to evaluate an abnormal
             cervical cytology (Pap smear) test, e.g. colposcopy.

          -  Any medically diagnosed or suspected immunodeficient condition based on medical
             history and physical examination.

          -  History of allergic disease, suspected allergy or reactions likely to be exacerbated
             by any component of the study vaccine.

          -  Hypersensitivity to latex.

          -  Known acute or chronic, clinically significant neurologic, hepatic or renal functional
             abnormality, as determined by previous physical examination or laboratory tests.

          -  History of chronic condition(s) requiring treatment.

          -  Administration of immunoglobulins and/or any blood product within three months
             preceding the first dose of study vaccine, or planned administration during the study
             period. Enrolment will be deferred until the subject is outside of specified window.

          -  Acute disease at the time of enrolment.

          -  Heavy bleeding (menstruation or other) or heavy vaginal discharge in which a pelvic
             exam cannot be performed (and no cervical sample can be taken). Enrolment will be
             deferred until condition is resolved according to investigators medical judgement.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2>The people administering the treatment/s</masking2>
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/02/2006</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>5752</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/01/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>TAS,VIC,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Hobart</hospital>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Perth</hospital>
    <postcode> - Hobart</postcode>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
    <postcode> - Perth</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Colorado</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Georgia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Iowa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Kansas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Kentucky</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Minnesota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Nebraska</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Hampshire</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Mexico</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Oklahoma</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Oregon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Pennsylvania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Utah</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Washington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Wisconsin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Alberta</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>British Columbia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Nova Scotia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Quebec</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mexico</country>
      <state>Morelos</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mexico</country>
      <state>Jojutla / Morelos</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Amsterdam</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Delft</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Rotterdam</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Peru</country>
      <state>Lima</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Philippines</country>
      <state>Laguna</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Philippines</country>
      <state>San Pablo City</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Philippines</country>
      <state>Taft Avenue, Manila</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <state>Almada</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <state>Coimbra</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <state>Lisboa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <state>Porto</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <state>Setúbal</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Ekaterinburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Moscow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Sankt-Petersburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Singapore</country>
      <state>Singapore</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Thailand</country>
      <state>Bangkok</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Middlesex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Aberdeen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Cardiff</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Gateshead</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Manchester</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>GlaxoSmithKline</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a multicentre study in which women were planned to receive either the Human
      Papillomavirus Vaccine (HPV) vaccine or control. Under Protocol Amendment 3, study
      participation will last approximately 48 months and involves a total of eleven scheduled
      visits. Under Protocol Amendment 4, study participation will last up to 84 months and
      involves a maximum of seventeen scheduled visits.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00294047</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>GSK Clinical Trials</name>
      <address>GlaxoSmithKline</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>