<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2209">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/12/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/12/2008</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00808782</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Use of rTMS to Improve Theory of Mind Among Adults With Autism and Asperger's Disorder</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Use of rTMS to Improve Theory of Mind Among Adults With Autism and Asperger's Disorder</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>277/07</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Autistic Disorder</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Asperger's Disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Autistic spectrum disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - Deep rTMS
Treatment: devices - Sham rTMS

Sham Comparator: Sham rTMS - Sham 5Hz rTMS.

Experimental: rTMS - Active 5Hz deep TMS.


Treatment: devices: Deep rTMS
Repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation targeting the medial prefrontal cortices. 30 10s 5Hz rTMS trains per day, with a 20 gap between each (15 minutes total), each consecutive weekday for two weeks.

Treatment: devices: Sham rTMS
Sham (non-active) repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation over the medial prefrontal cortices. 30 10s 5Hz rTMS trains per day, with a 20 gap between each (15 minutes total), each consecutive weekday for two weeks

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Theory of Mind Neurobehavioural Battery</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre, Post, One-month Post</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Autism Spectrum Quotient</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre, Post, One-month Post</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  18 years or above. DSM-IV-TR diagnosis of either autistic disorder (autism) or
             Asperger's disorder.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Hearing or visual impairment. Neurological illness (e.g., epilepsy).

          -  Unstable medical condition.

          -  History of seizures or convulsions.

          -  History of serious head injury. Metal implants or medical devices (e.g., pacemaker,
             cochlear implant, medication pump) in the head or body. Professional drivers.

          -  Machine operators.

          -  Women who are pregnant or lactating.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/12/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>30</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/10/2012</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Alfred Psychiatry Research Centre - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Bayside Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Theory of mind (ToM) refers to the ability to infer others mental states. It includes a
      recognition that other individuals experience thoughts, feelings, intentions, and desires
      that may be different to our own. ToM is often impaired among individuals with an autism
      spectrum disorder (such as autism and Asperger's disorder), and may underlie aspects of
      social dysfunction in this population. Indeed, it has been suggested that impaired ToM is the
      core deficit of autism and Asperger's disorder.

      Imaging studies suggest that the bilateral medial prefrontal cortex, the most important brain
      region in ToM processing, is underactive in autism. The current study examines whether
      repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS) to the bilateral medial prefrontal cortex
      can modulate ToM ability among healthy adults, and improve ToM ability among adults with
      autism or Asperger's disorder. With the prevalence of autism increasing, there is a clear
      need to develop appropriate therapeutic interventions to improve social functioning.

      This study involves a double-blind study using high-frequency rTMS in an attempt to improve
      ToM among adults with either autism or Asperger's disorder. Theory of mind will be measured
      using behavioural tasks that require the participant to infer what someone is thinking or
      feeling by observing their behaviour. These tasks will administered both before and after
      rTMS to determine whether any change in theory of mind has occurred.

      Thirty adults with either autism (n = 15) or Asperger's disorder (n = 15) will initially
      undergo functional and structural MRI to determine the site on the scalp that lies over the
      medial prefrontal cortex (to which rTMS will be administered). They will then attend our lab
      each consecutive weekday for a two-week period, during which they will 15 minutes
      high-frequency (5 Hz) rTMS (either active or sham) to the medial prefrontal cortex. ToM and
      clinical measures will be collected before the first session, soon after the last session,
      and one month after the last session.

      Based on prior imaging data, it is expected that high-frequency rTMS (compared with sham
      rTMS) to the medial prefrontal cortex will improve ToM ability and reduce social dysfunction
      among adults with autism or Asperger's disorder. Should these hypotheses be supported, it
      will indicate the suitability of rTMS as a neurobiological intervention designed to improve
      ToM and social function among individuals with autism and related disorders.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00808782</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Paul B Fitzgerald, MBBS, PhD</name>
      <address>The Alfred, Monash University</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>