<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4626">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/09/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/09/2014</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02247362</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Study of Safety and Immunogenicity of a Quadrivalent Influenza Vaccine in Healthy Adults Age 65-75 Years</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Phase 1b/2 Double Blind, Randomized, Placebo Controlled Study of Safety and Immunogenicity of VAX2012Q: A Quadrivalent Influenza Vaccine in Healthy Adults Age 65-75 Years</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>VAX2012Q-02</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Influenza</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - VAX2012Q
Other interventions - Placebo

Experimental: Vaccine Dose Group 12 mcg - VAX2012Q, 12 mcg dose

Experimental: Vaccine Dose Group 20 mcg - VAX2012Q, 20 mcg dose

Experimental: Vaccine Dose Group 16 mcg - VAX2012Q; 16 mcg dose

Placebo Comparator: Vaccine Diluent - Vaccine Diluent, F147, as placebo control


Other interventions: VAX2012Q
Recombinant influenza HA vaccine consisting of two Influenza A subtypes and two Influenza B lineages and delivered IM

Other interventions: Placebo
Vaccine Diluent

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Injection site and systemic symptoms will be collected for 21 days after vaccination. Other AEs assessed as related to vaccination will be collected at a 6 month and 1 year phone call.</outcome>
      <timepoint>21 days post-immunization; follow up at 6 months and one year</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Immune response to vaccine will be measured by serum HAI levels</outcome>
      <timepoint>21 days post-immunization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Males and females aged 65-75 years of age at the time of vaccination in good health.
             Individuals that are stably treated for hypertension may be eligible.

          -  Able to provide informed consent

          -  Willing to receive the unlicensed vaccine

          -  Willing to provide multiple blood specimens

          -  Live in the community, independently or in an assisted living environment

          -  Based on the results of the Short Portable Mental Status Questionnaire be rated as
             normal or have no greater than mild severity dementia

          -  As defined by the Canadian Study of Health and Aging Clinical Frailty Scale be a Class
             1 to 5</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Preceding the administration of study vaccine, has received or will receive 1) any
             licensed or investigational influenza vaccine product within 6 months, 2) any
             investigational drug or any investigational vaccine product other than influenza
             vaccine within the 30 days, 3) any licensed live vaccine other than influenza vaccine
             within 4 weeks, 4) any licensed inactivated vaccine other than influenza vaccine
             within 2 weeks

          -  Planned receipt before the Day 21 blood draw of 1) any licensed or investigational
             influenza vaccine product, 2) any investigational drug or any investigational vaccine
             product other than influenza vaccine, 3) any licensed live vaccine other than
             influenza vaccine, 4) any licensed inactivated vaccine other than influenza vaccine

          -  History of excessive alcohol use, drug abuse or significant psychiatric illness

          -  Has a chronic illness that is not medically stable, is receiving a concomitant therapy
             in which the medication dose has not been stable for at least 3 weeks prior to
             immunization or has any other condition that could interfere with the subject's
             participation in the study or interpretation of the study results

          -  Clinically significant abnormal liver function tests at screening

          -  Subjects with Grade 2 or higher abnormalities in total bilirubin at screening

          -  Subjects with any of the following laboratory abnormalities at screening: Creatinine
             &gt;1.7mg/dL, Hemoglobin &lt; 11g/dL for females; &lt;12.5 g/dL for males, WBC &lt;2500cell/mm3 or
             &gt; 15,000cell/mm3 and Platelet Count &lt;125,000cell/mm3

          -  Positive serology of HBSAg, HCV or HIV antibodies

          -  Having cancer or have received treatment for cancer within three years, excluding
             minor skin cancers, which are allowed unless located at the vaccination site. Persons
             with a history of cancer who are disease-free without treatment for three years or
             more are eligible.

          -  Persons with impaired immune responsiveness (of any cause), including Type 1 diabetes
             mellitus and auto immune disorders or any known or suspected autoimmune disease

          -  Persons with congenital immunodeficiency or history of acquired immunodeficiency, or
             immunosuppressive therapy such as anti-cancer chemotherapy or radiation therapy within
             the preceding six months.

          -  Persons with a history of severe allergic reaction after previous vaccinations or
             hypersensitivity to any seasonal influenza vaccine component

          -  Persons with a history of Guillain-Barré Syndrome

          -  Receipt or donation of blood or blood products 8 weeks prior to vaccination or during
             the three week study period following vaccination

          -  Acute disease within 72 hours prior to vaccination.

          -  An oral temperature &gt;100.4°F (38°C)

          -  Systolic blood pressure &lt; 85 mm Hg and subjects whose hypertension is untreated or
             unstable with antihypertensive therapy or that have systolic BP = 160 mm Hg or
             diastolic BP = 100 mm Hg requiring medical intervention with more than one drug or
             more intensive therapy than previously used or indicated.

          -  Body Mass Index &gt;40

          -  Disorders of coagulation

          -  Women less than 1 year post menopausal

          -  A clinical diagnosis of influenza within the previous 6 months

          -  Any other condition or circumstance which, in the opinion of the Principal
             Investigator, poses an unacceptable risk for participation in the study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/11/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Unknown status</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/03/2016</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD,SA,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Q-Pharm Pty Limited - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>CMAX, a division of IDT Australia Limited - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>Linear Clinical Research Limited - Nedlands</hospital>
    <postcode>4006 - Herston</postcode>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>VaxInnate Corporation</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>One dose of escalating strengths of an investigational influenza vaccine, VAX2012Q
      (Quadrivalent Recombinant Hemagglutinin Seasonal Influenza Vaccine), will be evaluated for
      safety and immunogenicity in healthy adults 65 to 75 years of age in this placebo-controlled
      study.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02247362</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Lynda Tussey, PHD</name>
      <address>VaxInnate Corporation</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>