<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4431">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/05/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/05/2014</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02131649</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>PET/MRI for Men Being Considered for Radiotherapy for Suspected Prostate Cancer Recurrence Post-Prostatectomy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>PROPS (PET/MRI Pre-Radiotherapy for Post-Prostatectomy Salvage)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>PROPS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>GAP02-01.1</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Prostate Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Prostate</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - 18F-FCH PET/MRI Scan

Experimental: 18F-FCH PET/MRI Scan - Patients will undergo an injection of 18F-fluoromethyl-choline at 3.6 MBq/kg followed by whole body PET/CT imaging. Patients will also undergo a whole body MRI including T2 weighted, Diffusion weighted and Gadolinium Contrast Enhanced sequences. Patients with suspicion for recurrence may undergo biopsy if lesions identified on PET/CT or MRI are accessible for biopsy


Treatment: devices: 18F-FCH PET/MRI Scan
Patients will first undergo screening to ensure eligibility. If eligible, they will undergo a PET/MRI scan using 18F-FCH as the radiolabeled tracer. If prostate cancer is detected outside the prostate, patients may undergo a biopsy or follow-up 18F-FCH PET/MRI to confirm the results.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of men with negative or equivocal conventional restaging imaging (bone scan + CT scan of abdomen and pelvis) with uptake identified outside of the prostate bed on 18F-FCH PET</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 2 weeks of 18F-FCH PET scan</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Biochemical disease free survival at 3 years post-treatment - Whether biochemical (PSA) control rates 3 years post-treatment are improved for participants with 18F-FCH PET imaging that was negative or demonstrated uptake confined to the prostate bed and received salvage pelvic radiotherapy compared to published results for men with adverse features.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 years post-treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Male, aged 18 years or older.

          -  Confirmation of prostate cancer on prostatectomy pathology report.

          -  No lymph node involvement (N0 or Nx) reported on prostatectomy pathology report.

          -  Documented PSA rise measured on 3 occasions.

          -  PSA = 0.2 ng/ml at enrolment.

          -  At least one adverse feature: Current PSA &gt; or equal to 1.0, Initial Gleason Grade &gt;
             or equal to 8, Positive surgical margin, pT3b (seminal vesicle involvement), or PSA
             doubling time &lt; 10 months.

          -  Bone scan and CT scan within 12 weeks of enrolment negative or equivocal for
             metastatic disease.

          -  Suitable candidate for radiotherapy and not yet had any salvage treatment
             post-prostatectomy.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Male</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Prostate cancer with significant sarcomatoid or spindle cell or neuroendocrine small
             cell components.

          -  Proven metastatic disease.

          -  Patients who refuse salvage prostate bed radiotherapy.

          -  Patients who refuse to join the trial or are unable to consent.

          -  Patients not being considered for further therapy.

          -  Patients who cannot lie still for at least 30 minutes or comply with imaging.

          -  Unequivocal evidence of disease outside the prostate bed on conventional imaging

          -  Allergy to MRI contrast agent (exclusion for MRI component only) or PET tracer to be
             used as part of the imaging

          -  Sickle cell disease or other anemias

          -  Insufficient renal function (eGFR &lt; 30 mL/min/1.73 m2)

          -  Residual bladder volume &gt; 150 cc (determined by post-void ultrasound)

          -  Hip prosthesis, vascular grafting or other conditions affecting imaging or delivery of
             therapeutic radiation

          -  Contraindication to MRI, including but not restricted to: pacemaker or other
             electronic implants, known metal in the orbit, MR incompatible surgical or cerebral
             aneurysm clips, Shrapnel, tattoos, non-removable body piercings (relative
             contraindications)

          -  Hormone Androgen deprivation therapy of any type within 6 months prior to enrollment</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/02/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>140</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Unknown status</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/03/2016</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St. Vincent's Hospital - Sydney</hospital>
    <hospital>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Austin Hospital - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Eastern Health - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>2010 - Sydney</postcode>
    <postcode>3002 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3084 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3128 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Quebec</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>South Glamorgan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Lawson Health Research Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The PROPS trial is for men being considered for radiotherapy due to the suspicion that their
      prostate cancer has recurred following the surgical removal of their prostate
      (prostatectomy). This suspicion is based on rises seen on Prostate Specific Antigen (PSA)
      blood tests. Only men who demonstrate the absence of disease on standard imaging scans
      (Computed Tomography (CT) and bone scans) will be invited to participate.

      This study will be assessing if the imaging probe 18-F Fluorocholine (18F-FCH) used during
      Positron Emission Tomography (PET) and Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) scans, can better
      predict who will benefit from radiotherapy by identifying the source of cancer recurrence.
      This will be determined by measuring the number of men who have disease identified outside of
      the prostate bed (the small pocket or depression where the prostate used to be) on their
      18F-FCH PET scan. Since F-18-FCH has been shown to be more sensitive in detecting prostate
      cancer that may have spread into lymph nodes or bone, it may potentially identify areas of
      prostate cancer spread not seen with standard imaging.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02131649</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Glenn Bauman, MD</name>
      <address>London Regional Cancer Program</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ashley Lozanski</name>
      <address />
      <phone>519-685-8500</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ashley.lozanski@lhsc.on.ca</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>