<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2798">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/06/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/06/2010</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01135953</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Methods to Enhance Transcranial Direct Stimulation (tDCS)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Investigating Methods to Enhance the Excitatory Effects of Transcranial Direct Stimulation (tDCS)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>HREC09344</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Healthy Volunteers</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Brain Excitation</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - Transcranial Direct Current Stimulation (tDCS)
Treatment: devices - Transcranial Direct Current Stimulation (tDCS)
Other interventions - Transcranial direct Stimulation (tDCS) and D-cycloserine

Experimental: ARM 1 - CONTROL - Subject given tDCS every day of the week (5 sessions) at 2 mA.

Experimental: Arm 2 - INCREASING - Subjects given increasing intensity during tDCS across the week (Monday 1mA, Tuesday 1.5mA, Wednesday 1.5 mA, Thursday 2 mA, Friday 2mA).

Experimental: ARM 3 - CYCLOSERINE - D-cycloserine (100 mg) given on the Monday and Thursday sessions, administering tDCS at 2 mA.


Treatment: devices: Transcranial Direct Current Stimulation (tDCS)
tDCS applied to to motor cortex every weekday (5 sessions), at 2mA ,during 20 minutes.Conductive rubber electrodes (7 x 5 cm = 35 cm2) covered by sponges soaked in saline will be used, held in place by a band. The current will be gradually increased to the level of 2 mA over 30 seconds (to avoid the sensation of a flash).

Treatment: devices: Transcranial Direct Current Stimulation (tDCS)
tDCS applied to the motor cortex every day of the week during 20 minutes, at 1mA first session, 1.5 mA second and third sessions, and 2mA fourth and fifth sessions, during 20 minutes. Conductive rubber electrodes (7 x 5 cm = 35 cm2) covered by sponges soaked in saline will be used, held in place by a band. The current will be gradually increased over 30 seconds (to avoid the sensation of a flash).

Other interventions: Transcranial direct Stimulation (tDCS) and D-cycloserine
Transcranial Direct Stimulation applied to the motor cortex every day of the week (5 sessions) at 2mA, during 20 minutes. Conductive rubber electrodes (7 x 5 cm = 35 cm2) covered by sponges soaked in saline will be used, held in place by a band. The current will be gradually increased to the level of 2 mA over 30 seconds (to avoid the sensation of a flash).
D-cycloserine, administered orally (capsules), 100 mg, twice a week (Monday and Thursday), prior to the tDCS session.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in brain excitability measured through motor evoked potentials (MEP) 0 to 120 minutes after tDCS session.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment, post treatment at minute 0, minute 5, minute 10, minute 15, minute 20, minute 25, minute 30, minute 60, minute 90, minute 120.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Male

          -  Right handed (&gt; 18/20 on the Edinburgh Handedness)

          -  Aged 18-40</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Male</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Mental illness

          -  General medical illness

          -  Neurological illness, epilepsy

          -  Alcohol use above National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC) guidelines

          -  Smokers

          -  Excessive caffeine intake

          -  Illicit drug use

          -  Herbal medication use

          -  Electronic implant, e.g, cochlear implant, pacemaker

          -  Musculoskeletal problem in the arm</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/01/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>24</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/07/2010</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Black Dog Institute, University of New South Wales - Sydney</hospital>
    <postcode>2031 - Sydney</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of New South Wales</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>tDCS has been shown to be an effective treatment for depression. However, tDCS is a
      relatively new clinical tool and more needs to be understood about its use. This study hopes
      to further the field of knowledge by examining how tDCS should be optimally used. Application
      of tDCS in clinical trials of depression is typically to the prefrontal cortex, but in this
      project, tDCS application will be to the motor cortex as it provides a more ready measure of
      excitability. Excitability will be measured using Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (TMS) to
      the motor cortex and electromyography (EMG) recordings from peripheral muscles stimulated.
      Using a cross-over three-arm design this study aims to investigate whether daily tDCS
      administered in increasing intensity across sessions leads to greater and lasting effects on
      brain excitability than keeping the intensity at a same dose across the days and whether the
      excitatory effect could be enhanced with D-cycloserine, a medication known to prolong the
      excitatory effects of a single session of tDCS. This in turn will inform on how to optimize
      tDCS for therapeutic applications, e.g treatment of depression. The study hypothesis is that
      5 sessions of tDCS with a dose of D-cycloserine given on the Monday and Thursday sessions
      will result in more sustained effect on motor cortex excitability than 5 sessions of tDCS
      alone. The second hypothesis is that the gradational increases in tDCS intensity over 5
      sessions will result in greater motor cortex excitability than 5 sessions of tDCS where
      intensity is kept constant across sessions.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01135953</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>