<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5310">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/10/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/10/2015</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02580058</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Study Of Avelumab Alone Or In Combination With Pegylated Liposomal Doxorubicin Versus Pegylated Liposomal Doxorubicin Alone In Patients With Platinum Resistant/Refractory Ovarian Cancer (JAVELIN Ovarian 200)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 3, Multicenter, Randomized, Open-label Study Of Avelumab (msb0010718c) Alone Or In Combination With Pegylated Liposomal Doxorubicin Versus Pegylated Liposomal Doxorubicin Alone In Patients With Platinum-resistant/Refractory Ovarian Cancer</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>2015-003091-77</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>B9991009</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Ovarian Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ovarian and primary peritoneal</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - avelumab
Treatment: drugs - PLD

Experimental: avelumab - Arm A: avelumab alone

Experimental: avelumab plus pegylated liposomal doxorubicin (PLD) - Arm B: avelumab plus PLD

Active Comparator: PLD - Arm C: PLD alone


Other interventions: avelumab
10 mg/kg will be given as a 1 hour intravenous infusion (IV) every 2 weeks (Q2W) in 4 week cycles

Treatment: drugs: PLD
PLD (Arm B, Arm C) 40 mg/m2 will be given as a 1 hour IV infusion every 4 weeks (Q4W) in 4 week cycles

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Survival (OS) - Overall survival was the duration from enrollment to death. For participants who are alive, overall survival was censored at the last contact.</outcome>
      <timepoint>randomization up to approximately 20 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression Free Survival (PFS) - To demonstrate that avelumab given alone or in combination with PLD is superior to PLD alone in prolonging Progression Free Survival (PFS) in patients with platinum resistant/platinum refractory ovarian cancer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>randomization up to approximately 20 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>OR (Objective Response) - Number of participants with objective response based on assessment of confirmed complete response (CR) or confirmed partial response (PR) according to RECIST. Confirmed responses are those that persist on repeat imaging study =4 weeks after initial documentation of response.
Per RECIST v1.0: CR defined as disappearance of all target lesions and non-target lesions. PR defined as =30% decrease in sum of the longest diameters dimensions (LD) of the target lesions taking as a reference the baseline sum LD according to RECIST associated to non-progressive disease response for non target lesions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline up to approximately 20 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PFS (Progression Free Survival) - The period from study entry until disease progression, death or date of last contact.</outcome>
      <timepoint>randomization up to approximately 20 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>DR (Duration of Response) - Duration of response (DR) is defined, for patients with an objective response per RECIST v1.1, as the time from the first documentation of objective tumor response (CR or PR) to the first documentation of objective tumor progression or death due to any cause, whichever occurs first.</outcome>
      <timepoint>first documentation of objective tumor response up to approximately 20 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>DC (Disease Control) - Defined as complete response (CR), partial response (PR), or stable disease (SD) 24 weeks according to the RECIST version 1.1 recorded from randomization until disease progression or death due to any cause. The DC rate (DCR) on each randomized treatment arm will be estimated by dividing the number of patients with CR, PR, or SD 24 weeks by the number of patients randomized to the treatment arm. The corresponding exact 2 sided 95% CI for the DC rates will be provided by treatment arm</outcome>
      <timepoint>Randomization up to approximately 20 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ctrough for avelumab - Ctrough is defined as the trough plasma concentrate at the end of an avelumab interval</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre dose and at the end of infusion (immediately before the end of avelumab infusion) on Days 1 and 15.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cmax for avelumab - Cmax defined as the maximum plasma concentration of avelumab</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre dose and at the end of infusion (immediately before the end of avelumab infusion) on Days 1 and 15.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cmax for PLD - Cmax defined as the maximum plasma concentration of PLD</outcome>
      <timepoint>in the first 12 patients pre dose, immediately prior to end of infusion, and at 2, 6, 24, and 336 hours (Day 15) post start infusion of PLD on Day 1 of next dose.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Vd (volume of distribution) for PLD - Volume of distribution is defined as the theoretical volume in which the total amount of drug would need to be uniformly distributed to produce the desired blood concentration of a drug</outcome>
      <timepoint>in the first 12 patients pre dose, immediately prior to end of infusion, and at 2, 6, 24, and 336 hours (Day 15) post start infusion of PLD on Day 1 of next dose.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>CL (clearance) for PLD - CL is a quantitative measure of the rate at which PLD is removed from the body</outcome>
      <timepoint>in the first 12 patients pre dose, immediately prior to end of infusion, and at 2, 6, 24, and 336 hours (Day 15) post start infusion of PLD on Day 1 of next dose.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>AUC (area under the concentration time curve) for PLD - AUC is a measure of the serum concentration of the drug over time. It is used to characterize drug absorption</outcome>
      <timepoint>in the first 12 patients pre dose, immediately prior to end of infusion, and at 2, 6, 24, and 336 hours (Day 15) post start infusion of PLD on Day 1 of next dose.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of Anti-Drug Antibody (ADA) - immunogenicity assessment for avelumab</outcome>
      <timepoint>prior to start of avelumab infusion on Day 1 and at end of treatment for up to 24 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>EORTC QLQ C30 - European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer Quality of Life Questionnaire: 30 question survey and includes 5 functional domain subscales, including a physical functioning sub scale, a role functioning subscale, an emotional functioning sub scale, a cognitive functioning sub scale and a social functioning subscale. Higher scores on the functioning domains are indicative of higher levels of functioning</outcome>
      <timepoint>once a month before dosing, up to 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>EORTC QLQ OV28 - European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer Quality of Life Questionnaire: 28 item instrument with seven (7) functional domain subscales. The 7 subscales include: (i) an abdominal/gastrointestinal symptom subscale (7 items); (ii) a peripheral neuropathy subscale (3 items); (iii) an other chemotherapy side effects subscale (7 items); (iv) a hormonal/menopausal symptoms subscale (2 items); (v) a body image subscale (2 items); (vi) an attitude to disease and treatment subscale (3 items) and (vii) a sexual function subscale (4 items)</outcome>
      <timepoint>once a month before dosing, up to 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>FOSI - a very brief ovarian cancer symptom index derived from the FACT O (ie, Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy Ovarian) to measure symptom response to treatment for ovarian cancer. The 8 item FOSI includes items assessing worry about future deterioration, contentment with QoL, and lack of energy in addition to 5 questions to assess GI related symptoms</outcome>
      <timepoint>once a month before dosing, up to 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>EuroQoL EQ 5D - Euro Quality of Life: 6 item patient completed questionnaire designed to assess health status in terms of a single index value or utility score. There are 2 components to the EuroQol EQ 5D: a Health State Profile which has individuals rate their level of problems (no, some or moderate, extreme) in 5 areas (mobility, self care, usual activities, pain/discomfort, and anxiety/depression) and a Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) in which patients rate their overall health status from 0 (worst imaginable) to 100 (best imaginable). Published weights are available that allow for the creation of a single summary score. Overall scores range from 0 to 1, with low scores representing a higher level of dysfunction</outcome>
      <timepoint>once a month before dosing, up to 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tumor Tissue Biomarkers - May include but not limited to PD L1 expression and tumor infiltrating CD8+ T lymphocytes by IHC, and/or tissue expression of FoxP3, PD 1, PD L2</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, optional sample at disease progression</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nab (neutralizing antibodies) against avelumab - immunogenicity assessment for avelumab</outcome>
      <timepoint>performed if ADA is positive: prior to start of avelumab infusion on Day 1 and at end of treatment for up to 24 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Histologically confirmed epithelial ovarian, fallopian tube, or peritoneal cancer,
             including malignant mixed Müllerian tumors with high grade serous component.

          -  Platinum resistant/refractory disease, defined as disease progression within 180 days
             following the last administered dose of platinum therapy (resistant), or lack of
             response or disease progression while receiving the most recent platinum based therapy
             (refractory), respectively.

          -  Received up to 3 lines of systemic anticancer therapy for platinum sensitive disease,
             most recently platinum containing, and no prior systemic therapy for platinum
             resistant disease

          -  Measurable disease by investigator assessment with at least 1 unidimensional
             measurable lesion by RECIST v.1.1 that has not previously been irradiated

          -  Active autoimmune disease that might deteriorate when receiving an immunostimulatory
             agents. Patients with diabetes type I, vitiligo, psoriasis, hypo or hyperthyroid
             disease not requiring immunosuppressive treatment are eligible.

        Mandatory tumor biopsy must be performed prior to enrollment for all patients (unless there
        is a documented clinical contraindication). In addition, availability of archived FFPE
        tumor tissue should be confirmed. If a patient underwent tumor tissue collection within 3
        months prior to enrollment with no intervening treatment, and the sample is provided, then
        a new de novo tumor biopsy is not required.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Female</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Non epithelial tumor or ovarian tumors with low malignant potential (ie, borderline
             tumors).

          -  Prior therapy with an anti PD 1, anti PD L1, anti PD L2, anti CD137, or anti cytotoxic
             T lymphocyte associated antigen 4 (CTLA 4) antibody (including ipilimumab,
             tremelimumab or any other antibody or drug specifically targeting T cell co
             stimulation or immune checkpoint pathways).

          -  Known symptomatic brain metastases requiring steroids. Patients with previously
             diagnosed brain metastases are eligible if they have completed their treatment and
             have recovered from the acute effects of radiation therapy or surgery prior to study
             entry, have discontinued corticosteroid treatment for these metastases for at least 4
             weeks prior to study entry and are neurologically stable.

          -  Diagnosis of any other malignancy within 5 years prior to registration, except for
             adequately treated basal cell or squamous cell skin cancer, or carcinoma in situ of
             the breast or of the cervix.

          -  Severe gastrointestinal conditions such as clinical or radiological evidence of bowel
             obstruction within 4 weeks prior to study entry, uncontrolled diarrhea in the last 4
             weeks prior to enrollment, or history of inflammatory bowel disease.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>23/12/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>546</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>12/03/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Epic Pharmacy,Newcastle Private Hospital - New Lambton Heights</hospital>
    <hospital>Newcastle Private Hospital Pty Limited - Newcastle</hospital>
    <hospital>Icon Cancer Care Wesley - Auchenflower</hospital>
    <hospital>Rivercity Pharmacy - Auchenflower</hospital>
    <hospital>Mater Pharmacy Services - Brisbane</hospital>
    <hospital>Icon Cancer Care Chermside - Chermside</hospital>
    <hospital>Clinical Research Unit - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>Metro North Hospital and Health Service - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>Oncology Pharmacy - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>Icon Cancer Care - South Brisbane</hospital>
    <hospital>Icon Cancer Foundation - South Brisbane</hospital>
    <hospital>Mater Cancer Care Centre - South Brisbane</hospital>
    <hospital>Icon Cancer Care Southport - Southport</hospital>
    <hospital>Cabrini Health Limited - Brighton</hospital>
    <hospital>Cabrini Health Limited - Malvern</hospital>
    <hospital>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Pharmacy Department - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>The Royal Women's Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>2305 - New Lambton Heights</postcode>
    <postcode>2305 - Newcastle</postcode>
    <postcode>4066 - Auchenflower</postcode>
    <postcode>4101 - Brisbane</postcode>
    <postcode>4032 - Chermside</postcode>
    <postcode>4029 - Herston</postcode>
    <postcode>4101 - South Brisbane</postcode>
    <postcode>4215 - Southport</postcode>
    <postcode>3186 - Brighton</postcode>
    <postcode>3144 - Malvern</postcode>
    <postcode>3000 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3050 - Parkville</postcode>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Arizona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Arkansas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Colorado</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Georgia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Kansas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Kentucky</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Maryland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Massachusetts</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Missouri</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Nevada</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Mexico</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Oregon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Pennsylvania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Tennessee</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Utah</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Virginia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Wisconsin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Austria</country>
      <state>Graz</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Austria</country>
      <state>Innsbruck</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>East Flanders</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Brussels</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Kortrijk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Leuven</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Liege</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Namur</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Alberta</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>British Columbia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Manitoba</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Nova Scotia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Quebec</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Czech Republic</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Olomouc</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Ostrava-Poruba</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Praha 2</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Praha 5</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Usti nad Labem</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Denmark</country>
      <state>Aalborg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Denmark</country>
      <state>Copenhagen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Caen Cedex 5</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Lyon cedex 08</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Nice cedex 2</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Paris cedex 15</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Paris</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Pierre Benite cedex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Vandoeuvre-lès-Nancy cedex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Villejuif cedex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Athens/New Kifissia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Athens</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <state>Hong Kong</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Budapest</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Debrecen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Szolnok</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ireland</country>
      <state>Dublin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ireland</country>
      <state>Dublin 4</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ireland</country>
      <state>Dublin 8</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ireland</country>
      <state>Waterford</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Jerusalem</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Ehime</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Hokkaido</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Hyogo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Ibaraki</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Kanagawa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Miyagi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Saitama</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Shizuoka</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Tochigi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Tokyo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Kagoshima</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Niigata</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Gyeonggi-do</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Daegu</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Seoul</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Groningen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Leiden</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Maastricht</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Norway</country>
      <state>Bergen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Norway</country>
      <state>Oslo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Krakow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Olsztyn</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Poznan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Rybnik</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Krasnodar Region</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Stavropol Krai</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Stavropol Region</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Chelyabinsk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Krasnodar</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Moscow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Nizhniy Novgorod</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Orenburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Velikiy Novgorod</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Singapore</country>
      <state>Singapore</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Cordoba</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Girona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Sevilla</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state>Basel-stadt</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state>Luzern</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state>Ticino</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state>Zurich</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Tainan city</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Tainan City</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Taipei city</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Taipei City</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Taipei</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Taoyuan City</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Taoyuan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>City of Glasgow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Merseyside</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Middlesex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Northamptonshire</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Oxford</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Surrey</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Cambridge</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Glasgow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Manchester</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Nottingham</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Stockport</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Pfizer</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A Phase 3 global study comparing avelumab alone to avelumab plus PLD and to PLD alone to
      demonstrate that avelumab given alone or in combination with PLD is superior to PLD alone in
      prolonging Overall Survival in patients with platinum resistant/platinum refractory ovarian
      cancer.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02580058</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Pfizer CT.gov Call Center</name>
      <address>Pfizer</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>