<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5276">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/11/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/11/2015</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02624414</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Capsule Colonoscopy in Crohn's Disease and Its Correlation With Conventional Colonoscopy and Faecal Calprotectin</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Prospective Study of the Feasibility of Capsule Colonoscopy in Crohn's Disease and Its Correlation With Conventional Colonoscopy and Faecal Calprotectin</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>2014.214</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Crohn's Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Inflammatory bowel disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other inflammatory or immune system disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Crohn's disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - PillCam® COLON 2 Capsule Endoscopy

Other: Anti TNF induction therapy 6-12 months - All subjects will be identified through The Royal Melbourne Hospital's IBD clinic, associated specialty clinics and the colonoscopy waiting list of The Royal Melbourne Hospital. The potential participants who have been commenced on Anti TNF induction therapy 6-12 months prior to commencement of the study will be identified. The potential participants identified in this way will be informed of the project at the time of contact and assessment; in some instances the potential participant will be informed of the project via telephone where subjects are remote. The potential participants will be provided an Ethically-approved information sheet at this time. Consent will be gained at the time of assessment.


Treatment: devices: PillCam® COLON 2 Capsule Endoscopy


</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess bowel cleanness based on the % of mucosal surface visualized by the Capsule colonoscopy - The quality of bowel preparation will be assessed using a new grading system proposed by Segal, et al, University of Melbourne Honours thesis in preparation, 2014. The investigator will assess five colonic segments (cecum, ascending, transverse and descending colon and the rectum). The investigator will assess bowel cleanness based on the % of mucosal surface visualized by the capsule for the presence of: Faecal residue, Turbid Fluid, Bubbles , Faecal residue on Dome, Rapid movement , Poor lighting, Light reflection.
Each segment will be given a number out of 4: 0 =not present and 4=significantly prevented mucosal visualization.
SES-CD= sum of the above 4 variables for 5 bowel segments (rectum, sigmoid and ascending colon, transverse colon, descending colon and ileum.
The images taken during this procedure will be recorded and analysed at a later date.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Simple Endoscopic Score for Crohn's Disease from Conventional colonoscopy</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Levels of Faecal calprotectin</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Adults with established diagnosis of CD with ileal, colonic or ileo-colonic disease
             aged 18-75 years. Gender: both male and female

          -  Patients of RMH IBD clinic and other specialty clinics where assessment of mucosal
             healing is clinically indicated this includes: Patients who have had Anti TNF
             induction therapy 6-12 months prior to commencement of this study AND/OR Patients
             referred for colonoscopy to assess mucosal disease status with a view to treatment
             escalation based on the findings.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients must not:

          -  Have known/suspected gastrointestinal obstruction

          -  Have swallowing disorder

          -  Have a known oesophageal stricture

          -  Have severe gastroparesis

          -  Have dementia

          -  Have a cardiac pacemaker or other implanted medical device

          -  Have sever cardiac or renal insufficiency

          -  Have a previous allergy or contraindication to bowel preparation

          -  Be pregnant

          -  Prior major abdominal surgery

          -  Colonoscopy is contraindicated</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Supportive Care</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>6/02/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>34</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>3050 - Parkville</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Melbourne Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Medtronic</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Aims:

        -  To study the feasibility of capsule colonoscopy in patients with Crohn's Disease (CD).

        -  To compare the results of capsule colonoscopy with conventional colonoscopy in assessing
           mucosal healing.

        -  To correlate the level of faecal calprotectin with the results of capsule colonoscopy
           and conventional colonoscopy.

        -  To document changes in clinical practice attributable to the capsule colonoscopy
           findings a) concordant with and b) in addition to the parallel findings at colonoscopy
           and ileoscopy.

      Project design: Cross sectional, prospective, comparative study

      Methodology: Patients of the Royal Melbourne Hospital (RMH) and other associated speciality
      clinics with an established diagnosis of CD who need assessment of mucosal healing and have
      consented to be part of the study will undergo capsule colonoscopy and conventional
      colonoscopy on the same day after undergoing bowel preparation. The images of both the
      conventional and capsule colonoscopies will be recorded. In addition calprotectin (an
      inflammatory marker in faeces) will be measured in a sample of faeces collected by the
      patients prior to the colonoscopy day.

      Professor Macrae and the scholarly selective student researcher will assess the recorded
      images obtained from capsule colonoscopies once the images have been deidentified.

      To assess the level of mucosal disease they will use the Simple Endoscopic Score for CD
      (SESCD).

      The results of the assessment of mucosal healing obtained from conventional colonoscopy will
      be compared with those of capsule colonoscopy and levels of faecal calprotectin will then be
      correlated.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02624414</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Finlay Macrae</name>
      <address>Melbourne Health</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Finlay Macrae</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+61393427580</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>finlay.macrae@mh.org.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>