<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="1202">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/06/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/06/2006</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00337103</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>E7389 Versus Capecitabine in Patients With Locally Advanced or Metastatic Breast Cancer Previously Treated With Anthracyclines and Taxanes</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase III Open Label, Randomized Two-Parallel-Arm Multicenter Study of E7389 Versus Capecitabine in Patients With Locally Advanced or Metastatic Breast Cancer Previously Treated With Anthracyclines and Taxanes</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>E7389-G000-301</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Metastatic Breast Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Eribulin Mesylate
Treatment: drugs - Capecitabine

Experimental: 1 - 

Active Comparator: 2 - 


Treatment: drugs: Eribulin Mesylate
1.4 mg/m^2 intravenous (IV) infusion given over 2-5 minutes on Days 1 and 8 every 21 days

Treatment: drugs: Capecitabine
Capecitabine 2.5 g/m^2/day administered orally twice daily in two equal doses on Days 1 to 14 every 21 days

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Survival (OS) - OS was measured from the date of randomization until the date of death from any cause, or the last date the participant was known to be alive. Participants who were lost to follow-up or who were alive at the date of data cutoff were censored. The censoring rules for OS were as follows: 1) if the participant died during the study, the date of death was considered the end date, 2) if the participant was still alive at data cutoff, the date of data cutoff was considered the end date, and 3) if the participant was lost to follow-up before data cutoff, the date they were last known to be alive was considered the end date. Participants who survived past the end of the study were counted as in the full study period. If death occurred after data cutoff, the end date was to be censored at the time of data cutoff.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From date of randomization until date of death from any cause, assessed up to data cutoff date of 12 Mar 2012, or up to approximately 6 years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression Free Survival (PFS) - PFS was defined as the time (in days) from the date of randomization to the date of the first sign of disease progression based on Response Evaluation Criteria In Solid Tumors (RECIST) version 1.1 (v 1.1) or date of death, regardless of cause. Disease progression was measured by computed tomography (CT) and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) performed on lesions targeted at baseline for tumor assessment. Disease progression (as assessed by independent review of the imaging scans) per RECIST v 1.1 was defined as at least a 20% increase in the sum of the diameters of the target lesions (taking as reference the smallest sum on study, including the baseline sum if that is the smallest), and an absolute increase of at least 5 mm. Note that the appearance of one or more new lesions was also considered as PD.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From date of randomization to the date of disease progression or death (whichever occurred first), assessed up to data cutoff date 12 Mar 2012 or up to approximately 6 years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Female patients with histologically or cytologically confirmed carcinoma of the
             breast. Every effort should be made to ensure that paraffin embedded tissue or slides
             from the diagnostic biopsy or surgical specimen are available for confirmation of
             diagnosis.

          2. Patients with locally advanced or metastatic disease who have received up to three
             prior chemotherapy regimens, and no more than two prior regimens for advanced and/or
             metastatic disease.

               -  Regimens must have included an anthracycline (e.g., doxorubicin, epirubicin) and
                  a taxane (e.g., paclitaxel, docetaxel), either in combination or in separate
                  regimens.

               -  Patients with known human epidermal growth factor 2 (HER2/neu) over-expressing
                  tumors may additionally have been treated with trastuzumab in centers where this
                  treatment is available.

               -  Patients with known estrogen and/or progesterone receptor-expressing tumors may
                  have additionally been treated with hormonal therapy.

          3. Resolution of all chemotherapy or radiation-related toxicities to Grade 1 severity or
             lower, except for stable sensory neuropathy &lt;= Grade 2 and alopecia.

          4. Age &gt;= 18 years.

          5. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0, 1 or 2.

          6. Life expectancy of &gt;= 3 months.

          7. Adequate renal function as evidenced by serum creatinine &lt;1.5 mg/dL or calculated
             creatinine clearance &gt; 50 mL/minute (min) per the Cockcroft and Gault formula.

          8. Adequate bone marrow function as evidenced by absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 1.5 x
             10^9/L, hemoglobin &gt;= 10.0 g/dL (a hemoglobin &lt; 10.0 g/dL acceptable if it is
             corrected by growth factor or transfusion), and platelet count &gt;= 100 x 10^9/L.

          9. Adequate liver function as evidenced by bilirubin &lt;= 1.5 times the upper limits of
             normal (ULN) and alkaline phosphatase, alanine transaminase (ALT), and aspartate
             transaminase (AST) &lt;= 3 x ULN (in the case of liver metastases &lt;= 5 x ULN), or in case
             of bone metastases, liver specific alkaline phosphatase &lt;= 3 x ULN.

         10. Patients willing and able to complete the EORTC (European Organization for Research on
             the Treatment of Cancer) quality of life questionnaire (QLQ-C30 with breast cancer
             module QLQ-BR23) and to record their pain level on the Visual Analog Scale (VAS).

         11. Patients willing and able to comply with the study protocol for the duration of the
             study.

         12. Written informed consent prior to any study-specific screening procedures with the
             understanding that the patient may withdraw consent at any time without prejudice.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Female</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Patients who have received more than three prior chemotherapy regimens for their
             disease, including adjuvant therapies, or patients who have received more than two
             prior chemotherapy regimens for advanced disease (other therapies are allowed e.g.,
             anti-estrogens, trastuzumab and radiotherapy).

          2. Patients who have received capecitabine as a prior therapy for their disease.

          3. Patients who have received chemotherapy, radiation, or biological therapy within two
             weeks, or hormonal therapy, within one week before study treatment start, or any
             investigational drug within four weeks before study treatment start.

          4. Radiation therapy encompassing &gt; 30% of marrow.

          5. Prior treatment with mitomycin C or nitrosourea.

          6. Pulmonary lymphangitic involvement that results in pulmonary dysfunction requiring
             active treatment, including the use of oxygen.

          7. Patients with brain or subdural metastases are not eligible, unless they have
             completed local therapy and have discontinued the use of corticosteroids for this
             indication for at least 4 weeks before starting treatment with study treatment. Any
             symptoms attributed to brain metastases must be stable for at least 4 weeks before
             starting study treatment; radiographic stability should be determined by comparing a
             contrast-enhanced Computed Tomography Scan (CT) or Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI)
             brain scan performed during screening to a prior scan performed at least 4 weeks
             earlier.

          8. Patients with meningeal carcinomatosis.

          9. Patients who are receiving anti-coagulant therapy with warfarin or related compounds,
             other than for line patency, and cannot be changed to heparin-based therapy, are not
             eligible. If a patient is to continue on mini-dose warfarin, then the prothrombin time
             (PT)/international normalized ratio (INR) must be closely monitored.

         10. Women who are pregnant or breast-feeding; women of childbearing potential with either
             a positive pregnancy test at screening or no pregnancy test; women of childbearing
             potential unless (1) surgically sterile or (2) using adequate measures of
             contraception (considered to be two methods of contraception, one of which must be a
             barrier method, e.g. condom, diaphragm or cervical cap). Perimenopausal women must be
             amenorrheic for at least 12 months to be considered of non-childbearing potential.

         11. Severe/uncontrolled intercurrent illness/infection.

         12. Significant cardiovascular impairment (history of congestive heart failure &gt; New York
             Heart Association [NYHA] Grade II, unstable angina or myocardial infarction within the
             past six months, or serious cardiac arrhythmia).

         13. Patients with organ allografts requiring immunosuppression.

         14. Patients with known positive human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) status.

         15. Patients who have had a prior malignancy, other than carcinoma in situ of the cervix,
             or non-melanoma skin cancer, unless the prior malignancy was diagnosed and
             definitively treated &gt;= 5 years previously with no subsequent evidence of recurrence.

         16. Patients with pre-existing neuropathy &gt; Grade 2.

         17. Patients with a hypersensitivity to halichondrin B and/or halichondrin B chemical
             derivative.

         18. Patients who participated in a prior E7389 clinical trial.

         19. Patients with other significant disease or disorders that, in the Investigator's
             opinion, would exclude the patient from the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>15/06/2006</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>1102</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/12/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,SA,TAS,VIC,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Bankstown Hospital, Oncology Trials Unit - Bankstown</hospital>
    <hospital> - Hornsby</hospital>
    <hospital>Liverpool Hospital, Cancer Therapy Centre - Liverpool</hospital>
    <hospital>Ashford Cancer Centre - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Hobart Hospital - Hobart</hospital>
    <hospital>Saint Vincent's Hospital - Fitzroy</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Perth Hospital - Perth</hospital>
    <hospital>Epworth Freemasons Hospital - East Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital, Dept. of Medical Oncology - Nedlands</hospital>
    <hospital>Mater Adult Hospital - South Brisbane</hospital>
    <postcode> - Bankstown</postcode>
    <postcode>2077 - Hornsby</postcode>
    <postcode> - Liverpool</postcode>
    <postcode>5035 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>7000 - Hobart</postcode>
    <postcode>3065 - Fitzroy</postcode>
    <postcode>6000 - Perth</postcode>
    <postcode> - East Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode> - Nedlands</postcode>
    <postcode> - South Brisbane</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Illinois</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Maine</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Massachusetts</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Missouri</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Hampshire</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Pennsylvania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Tennessee</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Washington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Argentina</country>
      <state>Buenos Aires</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Argentina</country>
      <state>Santa Fe</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Argentina</country>
      <state>Tucuman</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Argentina</country>
      <state>Bahia Blanca</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Argentina</country>
      <state>Ciudad Autonoma de Buenos Aires</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Argentina</country>
      <state>Ciudad Autonoma</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Argentina</country>
      <state>Mendoza</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Aalst</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Brussels</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Ghent</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Liege</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Florianopolis</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Ijui</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Jundiai</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Londrina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Porto Alegre</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Recife</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Ribeirao Preto</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Salvador</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Santo Andre</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Sao Paulo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Bulgaria</country>
      <state>Burgas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Bulgaria</country>
      <state>Gabrovo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Bulgaria</country>
      <state>Pieven</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Bulgaria</country>
      <state>Plovdiv</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Bulgaria</country>
      <state>Ruse</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Bulgaria</country>
      <state>Shumen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Bulgaria</country>
      <state>Sofia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Bulgaria</country>
      <state>Stara Zagora</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Bulgaria</country>
      <state>Varna</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Quebec</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Montreal</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Thunder Bay</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Ceske Budejovice</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Olomouc</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Prague 8</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Zlin Poiters</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>La Roche sur Yon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Poitiers Cedex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Saint Priest en Jarez</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Bochum</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Hamburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Homburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Magdeburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Rostock</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Patra</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Budapest</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Debrecen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Gyula</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Pecs</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Szeged</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Veszprem</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Ashkelon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Beer Sheva</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Jerusalem</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Kfar Saba</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Petach Tikva</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Rechovot</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Tel Hashomer</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Ancona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Lugo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Meldola</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Modena</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Pesaro</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Ravenna</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Rimini</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Sassari</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mexico</country>
      <state>Chihuahua</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mexico</country>
      <state>Monterrey</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mexico</country>
      <state>Morelia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Bialystok</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Bytom</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Elblag</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Gdansk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Krakow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Olsztyn</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Rybnik</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Torun</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Wroclaw</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Romania</country>
      <state>Cluj</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Romania</country>
      <state>Bucharest</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Romania</country>
      <state>Bucuresti</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Romania</country>
      <state>Cluj-Napoca</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Romania</country>
      <state>Iasi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Romania</country>
      <state>Sibiu</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Romania</country>
      <state>Timisoara</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Yaroslavlr</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Barnaul</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Kazan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Kirov</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Krasnodar</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Moscow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Nizhny Novgorod</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Obninsk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Rostov-on-Don</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Saint Petersburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Saratov</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Sochi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Tomsk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Vladimir</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Singapore</country>
      <state>Singapore</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Durban</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Gaunteng</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Pretoria</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Cape Town</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Johannesburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Sandton</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Vizcaya</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Guadalajara</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>La Coruna</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Sevilla</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Valencia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Changhua</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Taichung</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Tainan County</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Taipei</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Yung-Kang City</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ukraine</country>
      <state>Chernigov</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ukraine</country>
      <state>Dnepropetrovsk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ukraine</country>
      <state>Donetsk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ukraine</country>
      <state>Kharkov</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ukraine</country>
      <state>Khmelnitsky</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ukraine</country>
      <state>Kiev</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ukraine</country>
      <state>Krivoy Rog</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ukraine</country>
      <state>Kyiv</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ukraine</country>
      <state>Lvov</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ukraine</country>
      <state>Odessa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Eisai Inc.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to compare E7389 versus capecitabine in patients with locally
      advanced or metastatic breast cancer who are refractory to the most recent chemotherapy. This
      is an open-label, randomized, two-parallel arm study. Patients will be randomized to receive
      either E7389 or capecitabine on a one-to-one ratio.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00337103</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>