<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6721">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/11/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/11/2016</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02964507</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Dose Escalation and Expansion Study of GSK525762 in Combination With Fulvestrant in Subjects With Estrogen Receptor Positive (ER+) Breast Cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase I/II Dose Escalation and Expansion Study to Investigate the Safety, Pharmacokinetics, Pharmacodynamics and Clinical Activity of GSK525762 in Combination With Fulvestrant in Subjects With ER+ Breast Cancer</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>201973</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - GSK525762
Treatment: drugs - Placebo
Treatment: drugs - Fulvestrant

Experimental: GSK525762 + Fulvestrant (Phase I) - In Phase I, all subjects will receive treatment with GSK525762 in combination with fulvestrant. Dosing will be continued until unacceptable toxicity, progression of disease, death, or withdrawal of consent.

Experimental: GSK525762 + Fulvestrant (Phase II) - Subjects will receive treatment with GSK525762 in combination with fulvestrant, at a GSK525762-dose level selected from Phase I. Dosing will be continued until unacceptable toxicity, progression of disease, death, or withdrawal of consent.

Placebo Comparator: Placebo + Fulvestrant (Phase II) - In Phase II, subjects will receive treatment with placebo in combination with fulvestrant. Dosing will be continued until unacceptable toxicity, progression of disease, death, or withdrawal of consent.


Treatment: drugs: GSK525762
For Phase I, GSK525762 will be available as 5 mg and 25 mg oral tablets. Subjects will be initially dosed at 60 mg daily (Dose Level 1). Further subjects will be dosed based on the dose limiting toxicity rate, at a higher 'Dose Level 2' (or still higher, based on PK data), same 'Dose Level 1', or lower 'Dose Level 1'.

Treatment: drugs: Placebo
Placebo will match GSK525762 tablets, and will be provided in Phase II only. Dosing will be done until unacceptable toxicity, progression of disease, death, or withdrawal of consent.

Treatment: drugs: Fulvestrant
Fulvestrant will be supplied as a solution for injection in a prefilled syringe, at a strength of 250 milligrams (mg) per 5 milliliters (mL), for slow intramuscular (IM) injection into the buttocks. Two 5 mL injections (total 500 mg of fulvestrant) will be administered, one in each buttock, on Day 1, Day 15, Day 29, and once monthly thereafter.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase I: Number of subjects with adverse events (AE) and serious adverse events (SAE), for the determination of recommended Phase II dose of GSK525762 - An AE is any untoward medical occurrence in a clinical investigation subject, temporally associated with the use of a medicinal product, whether or not considered related to the medicinal product. Any untoward event resulting in death, life threatening, requires hospitalization or prolongation of existing hospitalization, results in disability/incapacity, congenital anomaly/birth defect or any other situation according to medical or scientific judgment will be categorized as SAE.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 1 until end of treatment (approximately 15 months)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase I: Number of subjects with dose limiting toxicities (DLT) - An event will be considered a DLT if it occurs within the first 28 days of treatment and meets at least one of the DLT criteria.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 1 until end of treatment (approximately 15 months)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase I: Number of subjects with dose reductions or delays, for the determination of recommended Phase II dose of GSK525762 - Subjects who experience toxicity may require dose delay and/or reduction of dose based on which phase II dose will be determined.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 1 until end of treatment (approximately 15 months)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase I: Overall response rate (ORR) - ORR is defined as complete response (CR) rate plus partial response (PR) rate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 1 until end of treatment (approximately 15 months)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase I: Plasma concentration of GSK525762, for the determination of recommended Phase II dose of GSK525762 - Subjects will be instructed to withhold their dose of orally administered study drugs, including GSK525762 and fulvestrant, until after the pre-dose pharmacokinetic blood sample is collected.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 of Weeks 1, 3, 5, 9, 16, and 24</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase I: Plasma concentration of fulvestrant, for the determination of recommended Phase II dose of GSK525762 - Blood samples for PK analysis will be collected at the indicated timepoints.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 of Weeks 1, 3, 5, 9, 16, and 24</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase II: Progression free survival (PFS) - PFS will be defined as the time from study treatment start until the first date of either disease progression or death due to any cause.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 1 until disease progression or death (approximately 16 months)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase I: Number of subjects with AEs or SAEs, as a measure of safety and tolerability - An AE is any untoward medical occurrence in a clinical investigation subject, temporally associated with the use of a medicinal product, whether or not considered related to the medicinal product. Any untoward event resulting in death, life threatening, requires hospitalization or prolongation of existing hospitalization, results in disability/incapacity, congenital anomaly/birth defect or any other situation according to medical or scientific judgment will be categorized as SAE.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 1 until end of treatment (approximately 15 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase I: Number of subjects with dose reductions or delays, as a measure of safety and tolerability - Subjects who experience toxicity may require dose delay and/or reduction of dose which will be determined as a measure of safety and tolerability.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 1 until end of treatment (approximately 15 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase I: Number of subjects withdrawn due to toxicity - To determine the safety, tolerability, and maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of GSK525762, when given in combination with fulvestrant in women with advanced or metastatic ER+BC</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 1 until end of treatment (approximately 15 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase I: Number of subjects with abnormality in hematology parameters - hematology parameters included white blood cells (WBCs), hemoglobin, platelet count, neutrophils, lymphocytes, monocytes, eosinophils and basophils.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 1 until end of treatment (approximately 15 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase I: Number of subjects with abnormality in clinical chemistry parameters - Clinical chemistry parameters included sodium, potassium, chloride, total carbondioxide, blood urea nitrogen, creatinine, fasting glucose, magnesium, calcium, total protein, albumin, bilirubin, aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and alkaline phosphatase.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 1 until end of treatment (approximately 15 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase I: Number of subjects with abnormality in urinalysis parameters - Urianalysis parameters included Specific gravity, pH, glucose, protein, blood, and ketones by dipstick Microscopic examination (if urinalysis is abnormal, if available at participating site) Urine hCG pregnancy test (only for women of child bearing potential.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 1 until end of treatment (approximately 15 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase I: Number of subjects with abnormality in systolic and diastolic blood pressure - Systolic and diastolic blood pressure should be measured in semi-supine position after 5 minutes rest</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 1 until end of treatment (approximately 15 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase I: Number of subjects with abnormality in pulse rate - Pulse rate should be measured in semi-supine position after 5 minutes rest</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 1 until end of treatment (approximately 15 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase I: Number of subjects with abnormality in respiratory rate - Respiratory rate should be measured in semi-supine position after 5 minutes rest</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 1 until end of treatment (approximately 15 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase I: Number of subjects with abnormality in electrocardiogram (ECG) - Triplicate 12-lead ECGs will be obtained using an ECG machine that automatically calculates the heart rate and measures PR, QRS, QT, and QTcF intervals.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 1 until end of treatment (approximately 15 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase I: Number of subjects with abnormality in any cardiotoxicity parameters - Cardiotoicity parameters included troponin (I or T at local laboratory), NT-proBNP, Total Cholesterol, low density lipoprotein (LDL), high density lipoprotien (HDL) and triglycerides.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 1 until end of treatment (approximately 15 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase I: Number of subjects with abnormality in gastrointestinal parameters - During clinical studies, medical history, physical examination (including weight) and clinical laboratory assessments will be used to identify and assess toxicity in the GI tract.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 1 until end of treatment (approximately 15 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase I: Disease control rate (DCR) - DCR is defined as CR plus PR plus stable disease [SD] rate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 1 until end of treatment (approximately 15 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase I: Duration of response - Duration of response is the subset of subjects who show a confirmed CR or PR, the time from first documented evidence of CR or PR until the first documented sign of disease progression or death.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 1 until disease progression or death (approximately 15 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase I: PFS - Progression-free survival (PFS) will be defined as the time from study treatment start until the first date of either disease progression or death due to any cause.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 1 until disease progression or death (approximately 15 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase I: Time to progression (TTP) - Duration of time from the Day1 until the first disease progression.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 1 until disease progression or death (approximately 15 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase I: Plasma concentration of GSK525762 and its metabolites, as a measure of drug exposure - Blood samples for PK analysis will be collected at the indicated timepoints.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 of Weeks 1, 3, 5, 9, 16, and 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase I: Plasma concentration of fulvestrant, as a measure of drug exposure - Blood samples for PK analysis will be collected at the indicated timepoints.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 of Weeks 1, 3, 5, 9, 16, and 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase I: Correlation between ESR1 mutations and clinical response, determined by targeted sequencing of tumor tissue - To evaluate ESR1 mutational status as a potential indicator of sensitivity and/or response to GSK525762 and fulvestrant, when given in combination in women with advanced or metastatic ER+BC</outcome>
      <timepoint>Over a period of approximately 15 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase II: Overall Survival (OS) - For the analysis of OS, the last date of known contact will be used for those subjects who have not died at the time of analysis; such subjects will be considered censored.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 1 until death (approximately 16 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase II: TTP - Duration of time from the Day1 until the first disease progression.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 1 until disease progression or death (approximately 16 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase II: ORR - ORR is defined as the percentage of subjects with a confirmed CR or a PR at any time.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 1 until end of treatment (approximately 16 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase II: DCR - DCR is defined as CR plus PR plus stable disease [SD] rate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 1 until end of treatment (approximately 16 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase II: Plasma concentration of GSK525762 and its metabolites, as a measure of drug exposure - Blood samples for PK analysis will be collected at the indicated timepoints.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 of Weeks 1, 5, 9, 16, and 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase II: Plasma concentration of fulvestrant, as a measure of drug exposure - Blood samples for PK analysis will be collected at the indicated timepoints.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 of Weeks 1, 5, 9, 16, and 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase II: Correlation between ESR1 mutations and clinical response, determined by targeted sequencing of tumor tissue - To evaluate ESR1 mutational status as a potential indicator of sensitivity and/or response to GSK525762 and fulvestrant, when given in combination in women with advanced or metastatic ER+BC</outcome>
      <timepoint>Screening, and (optionally) at end of treatment (approximately 16 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Females 18 years old and greater with histologically or cytologically confirmed
             diagnosis of advanced or metastatic adenocarcinoma of the breast.

          -  History of prior therapy that satisfies one of the following criteria:

               1. Disease that progressed during treatment or within 12 months of completion of
                  adjuvant therapy with tamoxifen and/or an aromatase inhibitor (AI).

               2. Disease that progressed during treatment or within 1 month after the end of
                  treatment with prior tamoxifen, AI, or cyclin-dependent kinase (CDK) 4/6
                  inhibitor plus letrozole, for advanced/metastatic disease.

          -  Documentation of ER-positive and/or progesterone receptor (PR)-positive tumor.

          -  Documentation of human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER2)-negative tumor.

          -  Measurable disease as per Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST)

          -  Adequate organ function as per pre-defined hematologic, hepatic, renal, and cardiac
             criteria.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Female</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Prior therapy with more than one line of cytotoxic chemotherapy following diagnosis of
             advanced/metastatic disease, or disease which has progressed despite prior fulvestrant
             therapy.

          -  Concomitant active malignancy other than ER+ breast cancer.

          -  Therapeutic-dose anticoagulation must be discontinued and coagulation parameters must
             be normalized prior to the first dose of GSK525762 and fulvestrant.

          -  Evidence of severe or uncontrolled systemic diseases (example, unstable or
             uncompensated respiratory, hepatic, renal, cardiac disease, or clinically significant
             bleeding episodes).

          -  Subjects with advanced/metastatic, symptomatic, visceral spread, that are at risk of
             life-threatening complications in the short term including subjects with massive
             uncontrolled effusions, pulmonary lymphangitis, and over 50% of liver involvement in
             metastases.

          -  Symptomatic or untreated leptomeningeal or brain metastases or spinal cord
             compression.

          -  Cardiac abnormalities</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>2/02/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>294</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/06/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Port Macquarie</hospital>
    <postcode>2444 - Port Macquarie</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Georgia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Massachusetts</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Missouri</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Virginia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Washington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Quebec</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Gyeonggi-do</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Seoul</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>A Coruna</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Lerida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Middlesex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Nottinghamshire</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Glasgow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>GlaxoSmithKline</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a combination Phase I and Phase II study, with an aim to evaluate the combination of
      GSK525762 and fulvestrant in women with advanced or metastatic ER+ breast cancer, who have
      disease that has progressed after prior treatment with at least one line of endocrine
      therapy.

      The objectives of the study are to first identify, in open-label single-arm Phase I, a
      recommended Phase II dose of GSK525762 that may be combined safely with fulvestrant. Phase I
      will follow a modified toxicity probability interval (mTPI) design, and a sentinel group will
      be evaluated first for dose-limiting toxicity and further expanded to collect additional
      safety data. This will be followed by a double-blind, randomized controlled Phase II, to
      identify the clinical activity of the two study treatments when given in combination. The
      composition of Phase II will be selected at the end of Phase I.

      Approximately, up to 140 subjects and 154 subjects will receive study treatment in Phase I
      and Phase II respectively. A completed subject will be one who is followed until death.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02964507</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>GSK Clinical Trials</name>
      <address>GlaxoSmithKline</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</name>
      <address />
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>