<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="1802">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/12/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/12/2007</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00603746</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Randomized Study To Evaluate The Efficacy And Safety Of An Investigational Drug In Adolescent And Adult Subjects With Asthma Uncontrolled on Moderate-Dose ICS Therapy.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomized Double-Blind, Double Dummy, Placebo-Controlled, Parallel-Group, Multicenter Dose Ranging Study to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of GW685698X Inhalation Powder Once Daily and Fluticasone Propionate Inhalation Powder 500mcg Twice Daily Compared With Placebo for 8 Weeks in Adolescent an</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>FFA109684</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Asthma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Asthma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - GW685698X

Experimental: GW685698X - GW685698X


Treatment: drugs: GW685698X
GW685698X

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Change From Baseline in Trough (Evening Pre-dose and Pre- Rescue Bronchodilator) FEV1 at Week 8 - Pulmonary function was measured by forced expiratory volume in one second (FEV1), defined as the maximal amount of air that can be forcibly exhaled from the lungs in one second. Pre-dose and pre-rescue bronchodilator (albuterol/salbutamol) trough FEV1 (the measurement of FEV1 performed at the end of the dosing interval) was measured electronically by spirometry in the evening at the Baseline (BL) through Week 8 clinic visits. The highest of 3 technically acceptable measurements was recorded. The Visit 3 FEV1 assessment was used as the Baseline value. Change from Baseline in trough FEV1 was calculated as the value at Week 8 minus the value at Baseline. The analysis was performed using an Analysis of Covariance (ANCOVA) model with covariates of Baseline trough FEV1, country, sex, age, and treatment group.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Week 8</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Change From Baseline in Daily Trough (Pre-dose and Pre-rescue Bronchodilator) Evening Peak Expiratory Flow (PEF) Averaged Over the 8-week Treatment Period - PEF is defined as the maximum airflow during a forced expiration beginning with the lungs fully inflated. Trough PEF is defined as the maximal rate (speed) that a person can exhale during a short maximal expiratory effort after a full inspiration. PEF was measured by the participants using a hand-held electronic peak flow meter each evening prior to the dose of study medication and any rescue albuterol/salbutamol inhalation aerosol use. The best of three attempts was recorded by the participants in a daily diary. The Baseline value was derived from the last 7 days of the daily diary prior to the randomization of the participant. Change from Baseline was calculated as the value of the averaged daily evening PEF over the 8-week treatment period minus the value at Baseline. The analysis was performed using an ANCOVA model with covariates of Baseline trough evening PEF, country, sex, age, and treatment group.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Baseline up to Week 8</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Change From Baseline in Daily Morning PEF Averaged Over the 8-week Treatment Period - PEF is defined as the maximum airflow during a forced expiration beginning with the lungs fully inflated. Trough PEF is defined as the maximal rate (speed) that a person can exhale during a short maximal expiratory effort after a full inspiration. PEF was measured by the participants using a hand-held electronic peak flow meter each morning prior to the dose of study medication and any rescue albuterol/salbutamol inhalation aerosol use. The best of three attempts was recorded by the participants in a daily diary. The Baseline value was derived from the last 7 days of the daily diary prior to the randomization of the participant. Change from Baseline was calculated as the value of the averaged daily morning PEF over the 8-week treatment period minus the value at Baseline. The analysis was performed using an ANCOVA model with covariates of Baseline trough morning PEF, country, sex, age, and treatment group.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Baseline up to Week 8</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Change From Baseline in the Percentage of Symptom-free 24-hour (hr) Periods During the 8-week Treatment Period - Asthma symptoms were recorded in a daily dairy by the participants every day in the morning and evening before taking any rescue or study medication and before PEF measurement. A 24-hour period in which a participant's responses to both the morning and evening assessments indicated no symptoms was considered as symptom-free. The Baseline value was derived from the last 7 days of the daily diary prior to the randomization of the participant. Change from Baseline was calculated as the averaged value during the 8-week Treatment Period minus the value at Baseline. The analysis was performed using an ANCOVA model with covariates of Baseline, country, sex, age, and treatment group.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Baseline up to Week 8</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Change From Baseline in the Percentage of Rescue-free 24-hour (hr) Periods During the 8-week Treatment Period - The number of inhalations of rescue albuterol/salbutamol inhalation aerosol used during the day and night was recorded by the participants in a daily diary. A 24-hour period in which a participant's responses to both the morning and evening assessments indicated no use of rescue medication was considered as rescue-free. The Baseline value was derived from the last 7 days of the daily diary prior to the randomization of the participant. Change from Baseline was calculated as the averaged value during the 8-week Treatment Period minus the value at Baseline. The analysis was performed using an ANCOVA model with covariates of Baseline, country, sex, age, and treatment group.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Baseline up to Week 8</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number Participants Who Withdrew Due to Lack of Efficacy During the 8-week Treatment Period - The number of participants whose primary reason for withdrawal was lack of efficacy was analyzed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From the first dose of the study medication up to Week 8/Early Withdrawal</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With Any On-treatment Adverse Event or Serious Adverse Event Throughout the 8-week Treatment Period - An adverse event (AE) is defined as any untoward medical occurrence in a participant, temporally associated with the use of a medicinal product, whether or not considered related to the medicinal product. A serious adverse event (SAE) is defined as any untoward medical occurrence that, at any dose: results in death; is life-threatening; requires hospitalization or prolongation of existing hospitalization; results in disability/incapacity; or is a congenital anomaly/birth defect. Medical or scientific judgment should have been exercised in other situations. Refer to the general AE/SAE module for a list of AEs (occurring at a frequency threshold &gt;=3%) and SAEs.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From the first dose of the study medication up to Week 8/Early Withdrawal</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With Clinical/Visual Evidence of Oropharyngeal Candidiasis - A detailed oropharyngeal examination for visual evidence of oral candidiasis was performed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Baseline up to Week 8/Early Withdrawal</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Basophils, Eosinophils, Lymphocytes, Monocytes, and Total Neutrophils in the Blood at Baseline and Week 8 - Blood samples were collected for the measurement of the percentage of basophils, eosinophils, lymphocytes, monocytes, and total neutrophils in the blood at Baseline (BL) and Week 8 (W8). The Baseline value was the measurement taken at screening (Visit 1).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Week 8</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hematocrit at Baseline and Week 8 - Blood samples were collected for the measurement of hematocrit at Baseline and Week 8. The Baseline value was the measurement taken at screening (Visit 1).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Week 8</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hemoglobin at Baseline and Week 8 - Blood samples were collected for the measurement of hemoglobin at Baseline and Week 8. The Baseline value was the measurement taken at screening (Visit 1).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Week 8</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Platelet Count and White Blood Cell Count at Baseline and Week 8 - Blood samples were collected for determining the platelet count and white blood cell (WBC) count at Baseline and Week 8. The Baseline value was the measurement taken at screening (Visit 1).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Week 8</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Red Blood Cell Count at Baseline and Week 8 - Blood samples were collected for determining the red blood cell count at Baseline and Week 8. The Baseline value was the measurement taken at screening (Visit1).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Week 8</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical Chemistry Parameters of Alanine Amino Transferase (ALT), Alkaline Phosphatase (ALP), Aspartate Amino Transferase (AST), Gamma Glutamyl Transferase (GGT), and Lactate Dehydrogenase (LDH) at Baseline and Week 8 - Blood samples were collected for the measurement of ALT, ALP, AST, GGT, and LDH at Baseline and Week 8. The Baseline value was the measurement taken at screening (Visit 1).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Week 8</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical Chemistry Parameters of Albumin and Total Protein at Baseline and Week 8 - Blood samples were collected for the measurement of albumin and total protein at Baseline and Week 8. The Baseline value was the measurement taken at screening (Visit 1).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Week 8</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical Chemistry Parameters of Calcium, Carbon Dioxide Content/Bicarbonate, Chloride, Cholesterol, Glucose, Phosphorus Inorganic, Potassium, Sodium, and Urea at Baseline and Week 8 - Blood samples were collected for the measurement of calcium, carbon dioxide content/bicarbonate (CO2/BI), chloride, cholesterol, glucose, phosphorus inorganic (PI), potassium, sodium, and urea at Baseline and Week 8. The Baseline value was the measurement taken at screening (Visit 1).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Week 8</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical Chemistry Parameters of Creatinine, Direct Bilirubin, Total Bilirubin, and Uric Acid at Baseline and Week 8 - Blood samples were collected for the measurement of creatinine, direct bilirubin (DBIL), total bilirubin (TBIL), and uric acid at Baseline and Week 8. The Baseline value was the measurement taken at screening (Visit 1).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Week 8</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With the Indicated Result for the Indicated Urinalysis Parameters Tested by Dipstick at Baseline and Week 8/Withdrawal - Urinalysis parameters included: Urine Occult Blood (UOB), Urine Glucose (UG), Urine Ketones (UK), Urine Protein (UP), and Urine Leukocyte Esterase test for detecting White Blood Cells (UWBC). The dipstick was a strip used to detect the presence or absence of these parameters in the urine sample. The dipstick test gives results in a semi-quantitative manner; results for urinalysis parameters can be read as 1+, 2+, 3+, Large, Moderate, Negative (Neg), Small, and Trace. For UG, the result can be read as Neg, Trace, Trace or 1/10 grams per deciliter (G/dL), 1+ or 1/4 G/dL, 2+ or 1/2 G/dL, 3+ or 1 G/dL, 4+ or 2 or more G/dL, indicating proportional concentrations in the urine sample. Data are reported as the number of participants who had 1+, 2+, 3+, Large, Moderate, Neg, Small, or Trace levels at Baseline (BL) and Week 8 (W8)/Early Withdrawal (EW). The Baseline value was the measurement taken at screening (Visit 1).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Week 8/Early Withdrawal</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Urine Specific Gravity at Baseline and Week 8/Early Withdrawal - Urine samples were collected for the measurement of urine specific gravity by dipstick method at Baseline and at Week 8/Early Withdrawal. The Baseline value was the measurement taken at screening (Visit 1). Specific gravity is a measure of the amount of material dissolved in the urine. Specific gravity is the ratio of the density (mass of a unit volume) of a substance to the density (mass of the same unit volume) of a reference substance. Normal urine has a specific gravity between 1.010 and 1.020.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Week 8/Early Withdrawal</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Urine pH at Baseline and Week 8/Early Withdrawal - Urine samples were collected for the measurement of urine pH by dipstick method at Baseline and at Week 8/Early Withdrawal. The Baseline value was the measurement taken at screening (Visit 1). Urine pH is an acid-base measurement. pH is measured on a numeric scale ranging from 0 to 14; values on the scale refer to the degree of alkalinity or acidity. A pH of 7 is neutral. A pH less than 7 is acidic, and a pH greater than 7 is basic. Normal urine has a slightly acid pH (5.0 - 6.0).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Week 8/Early Withdrawal</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>24-hour Urinary Cortisol Excretion at Baseline and Week 8 - A 24-hour urine sample was collected for the measurement of 24-hour urinary cortisol excretion at the following scheduled time points: within 7 days prior to Study Visit 3 (Baseline; Week 0) and Study Visit 8 (Week 8). The Baseline value for 24-hour urinary cortisol was taken from Visit 3.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Week 8</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Systolic Blood Pressure (SBP) and Diastolic Blood Pressure (DBP) at Week 8 - Change from Baseline was calculated as the Week 8 value minus the Baseline value.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Week 8</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Heart Rate at Week 8 - Change from Baseline was calculated as the Week 8 value minus the Baseline value.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Week 8</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Subjects eligible for enrolment in the study must meet all of the following criteria:

          -  Type of Subject: Outpatient

          -  Age: 12 years of age or older at Visit 1. For sites in the following countries,
             subjects recruited will be =18 years of age: Bulgaria, Czech Republic, Germany,
             Greece, Lithuania, New Zealand, Russian Federation, Turkey and any other countries
             where local regulations or the regulatory status of study medication permit enrolment
             of adults only.

          -  3. Gender: Male or Eligible Female

          -  To be eligible for entry into the study, females of childbearing potential must commit
             to consistent and correct use of an acceptable method of birth control, as defined by
             the following:

          -  Male partner who is sterile prior to the female subject's entry into the study and is
             the sole sexual partner for that female subject

          -  Implants of levonorgestrel

          -  Injectable progestogen

          -  Oral contraceptive (either combined estrogen/progestin or progestin only)

          -  Any intrauterine device (IUD) with a documented failure rate of less than 1% per year.

          -  Females of childbearing potential who are not sexually active must commit to complete
             abstinence from intercourse throughout the clinical trial and for a period after the
             trial to account for elimination of the drug (minimum of six days).

          -  Double barrier method - spermicide plus a mechanical barrier (e.g., spermicide plus a
             male condom or a spermicide and female diaphragm).

          -  NB: For German sites, female subjects must use a method of birth control other than
             the double barrier method.

          -  The contraceptive transdermal patch, Ortho Evra (if the subject is less than 198
             pounds)

          -  Female subjects should not be enrolled if they are pregnant, lactating or plan to
             become pregnant during the time of study participation. A serum pregnancy test is
             required of all females. This test will be performed at the initial screening visit
             (Visit 1) and Visit 8. In addition, a urine pregnancy test will be performed on the
             evening of the double-blind treatment visit, prior to randomization (Visit 3) and at
             Visits 4 through 7.

          -  Asthma Diagnosis: Asthma as defined by the National Institutes of Health [National
             Institutes of Health, 2007].

          -  Severity of Disease: A best FEV1 of 40%-85% of the predicted normal value during the
             morning Visit 1 screening period or a best FEV1 of 40%-90% of the predicted normal
             value during the evening Visit 1 screening period.

          -  Reversibility of Disease: Demonstrated a = 12% and =200mL reversibility of FEV1 within
             approximately 30-minutes following 4 inhalations of albuterol/salbutamol inhalation
             aerosol (if required, spacers are permitted for reversibility testing only) or one
             nebulized albuterol/salbutamol solution during the screening period.

        Re-screening of subjects during the Visit 1 screening period: If a subject does not meet
        the inclusion criteria based upon FEV1 percent predicted and/or reversibility, the subject
        may return to the site once within 4 days and repeat the lung function tests.

          -  Current Anti-Asthma Therapy: Subjects must have been using a inhaled corticosteroid
             for at least 8 weeks prior to Visit 1 and maintained on a stable dose of inhaled
             corticosteroids for four weeks prior to Visit 1 at one of the following doses:
             [fluticasone propionate MDI CFC/HFA &gt;176 = 440mcg exactuator or &gt; 200 =500mcg ex
             valve]; [fluticasone propionate DPI &gt; 200=500mcg]; [beclomethasone dipropionate DPI &gt;
             420 = 840mcg exactuator or &gt; 500 = 1000mcg ex-valve]; [beclomethasone dipropionate HFA
             Qvar &gt; 160 = 480mcg exactuator or &gt; 200 = 500mcg ex-valve]; [budesonide DPI MDI &gt;400
             =1200mcg]; [flunisolide &gt; 1000 = 2000mcg]; [triamcinolone acetonide &gt;1000 =1600mcg];
             [mometasone furoate DPI &gt;200 = 440mcg]; [ciclesonide MDI HFA &gt;160 mcg = 320mcg
             ex-actuator dose / &gt;200mcg = 400mcg ex-valve dose}

          -  Short- Acting Beta2-Agonists: All subjects must be able to replace their current
             short-acting beta2-agonists with albuterol/salbutamol inhalation aerosol at Visit 1
             for use as needed for the duration of the study. The use of spacer devices with
             metered dose inhaler (MDI) or nebulized albuterol/salbutamol will not be allowed
             during the study with the exception of their use during reversibility testing at Visit
             1. Subjects must be able to withhold all inhaled short-acting beta sympathomimetic
             bronchodilators for at least 6 hours prior to all study visits.

          -  Informed Consent: All subjects must be able and willing to give written informed
             consent to take part in the study.

          -  Compliance: Subjects must be able to comply with completion of the Daily Diary
             (includes paper medical conditions diary).

          -  French subjects: In France, a subject will be eligible for inclusion in this study
             only if either affiliated to or a beneficiary of a social security category.

        Inclusion Criteria for Randomization

        At the end of the run-in period, a subject will be eligible to enter the treatment period
        of the study if he/she meets the following criteria at Visit 3:

          1. Evening pre-dose percent predicted FEV1 of between 40% and 90% of their predicted
             normal.

          2. Any combination of the daily asthma symptom scores (day-time plus night-time) of =1 or
             albuterol/salbutamol use on at least 4 of the last 7 consecutive days of the run-in
             period (immediately preceding Visit 3).

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  History of Life-threatening asthma: Defined for this protocol as an asthma episode
             that required intubation and/or was associated with hypercapnia, respiratory arrest or
             hypoxic seizures.

          -  Respiratory Infection: Culture-documented or suspected bacterial or viral infection of
             the upper or lower respiratory tract, sinus or middle ear that is not resolved within
             4 weeks of Visit 1 and led to a change in asthma management, or in the opinion of the
             Investigator is expected to affect the subject's asthma status or the subject's
             ability to participate in the study.

          -  Asthma Exacerbation: Any asthma exacerbation requiring oral corticosteroids within 3
             months of Visit 1. A subject must not have had any hospitalization for asthma within 6
             months prior to Visit 1.

          -  Concurrent Diseases/Abnormalities: Historical or current evidence of clinically
             significant uncontrolled disease including, but not limited to: cardiovascular
             disease, hepatic disease, renal disease, hematological disease, neurological disease,
             or pulmonary disease (including, but not confined to chronic bronchitis, emphysema,
             bronchiectasis with the need of treatment, cystic fibrosis, bronchopulmonary
             dysplasia, and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease). Significant is defined as any
             disease that, in the opinion of the investigator, would put the safety of the subject
             at risk through participation, or which would affect the efficacy or safety analysis
             if the disease/condition exacerbated during the study. The list of additional excluded
             conditions/diseases includes, but is not limited to the following: congestive heart
             failure, clinically significant coronary artery disease, stroke within 3 months of
             Visit 1, poorly controlled peptic ulcer, immunologic compromise, tuberculosis (current
             or untreated), Addison's disease, uncontrolled thyroid disorder, known aortic
             aneurysm, clinically significant cardiac arrhythmia, uncontrolled hypertension,
             hematological, hepatic, or renal disease, current malignancy, cushings disease,
             uncontrolled diabetes mellitus, recent history of drug or alcohol abuse.

          -  Oropharyngeal Examination: A subject will not be eligible for the run-in if he/she has
             clinical visual evidence of oral candidiasis at Visit 1.

          -  Investigational Medications: A subject must not have participated in a study or used
             any investigational drug within 30 days prior to Visit 1.

          -  Drug Allergy: Any adverse reaction including immediate or delayed hypersensitivity to
             any beta2-agonist, sympathomimetic drug, or any intranasal, inhaled, or systemic
             corticosteroid therapy. Known or suspected sensitivity to the constituents of the
             novel dry powder inhaler or DISKUS/ACCUHALER (i.e., lactose or magnesium stearate).

          -  Milk Protein Allergy: History of severe milk protein allergy.

          -  Immunosuppressive Medications: A subject must not be using, or require use, of
             immunosuppressive medications during the study. NOTE: Immunotherapy for the treatment
             of allergies is allowed during the study provided that the treatment was initiated
             prior to Visit 1 and the subject is maintained on a stable regimen throughout the
             study period.

          -  Attendance: A subject will not be eligible if he/she or his/her parent or legal
             guardian has any infirmity, disability, or geographical location which seems likely
             (in the opinion of the Investigator) to impair compliance with any aspect of this
             study protocol or scheduled visits to the study center and non-compliant with study
             medication or procedures (e.g. completion of daily diary). Neurological or psychiatric
             disease or history of drug or alcohol abuse which in the opinion of the investigator
             could interfere with the subject's proper completion of the protocol requirements
             excludes study participation.

          -  Tobacco Use : Current smoker or a smoking history of 10 pack years or more (e.g. 20
             cigarettes/day for 10 years). A subject may not have used tobacco products within the
             past one year (i.e., cigarettes, cigars, or pipe tobacco).

          -  Affiliation with Investigator's Site: A subject will not be eligible for this study if
             he/she is an immediate family member of the participating Investigator,
             sub-Investigator, study coordinator, or employee of the participating Investigator.

          -  Corticosteroid Use: Administration of systemic, oral or depot corticosteroids within
             12 weeks of Visit 1.

          -  Potent Cytochrome P450 3A4 (CYP3A4) inhibitors: Patients who are receiving potent
             CYP3A4 inhibitors within 4 weeks of Visit 1 (e.g., ritonavir, ketoconazole,
             itraconazole).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>12</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion Criteria for Randomization At the end of the run-in period, a subject will not be
        eligible to enter the treatment period of the study if they meet any of the following
        criteria.

          1. Clinical Laboratory Abnormalities: Clinically significant abnormal laboratory tests
             during Visit 1 which are still abnormal upon repeat analysis and are not believed to
             be due to disease(s) present. Each Investigator will use his/her own discretion in
             determining the clinical significance of the abnormality. When in doubt,
             GlaxoSmithKline, or designee, should be notified so that a joint decision can be made.

          2. Changes in asthma medication (excluding albuterol/salbutamol inhalation aerosol
             provided at Visit 1).

          3. Occurrence of a culture-documented or suspected bacterial or viral infection of the
             upper or lower respiratory tract, sinus or middle ear during the run-in period that
             led to a change in asthma management, or in the opinion of the Investigator is
             expected to affect the subject's asthma status or the subject's ability to participate
             in the study.

          4. Asthma exacerbation, defined as any worsening of asthma requiring any treatment other
             than rescue albuterol/salbutamol or regular inhaled corticosteroid use. This includes
             requiring the use of systemic corticosteroids and / or emergency room visit or
             hospitalization or a change in subject's regular inhaled corticosteroid dose.

          5. A subject will not be eligible for randomization if he/she has an abnormal visual
             oropharyngeal exam at the randomization Visit 3 (visual clinical evidence of oral
             candidiasis).

          6. Non-compliance with completion of the Daily Diary, defined as: -Completion of AM and
             PM symptom scores on less than 4 days out of the last 7 days immediately preceding
             Visit 3.

               -  Completion of AM and PM rescue use on less than 4 days out of the last 7 days
                  immediately preceding Visit 3.

               -  Completion of AM and PM PEF measurements on less than 4 days out of the last 7
                  days immediately preceding Visit 3.

               -  Recording run-in asthma medication use on less than 4 days out of the last 7 days
                  immediately preceding Visit 3.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/12/2007</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>627</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>20/09/2008</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA,VIC,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Clayton</hospital>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Nedlands</hospital>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Arizona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Arkansas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Colorado</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Connecticut</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Georgia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Illinois</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Indiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Iowa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Kansas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Kentucky</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Louisiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Maine</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Massachusetts</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Michigan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Minnesota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Mississippi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Missouri</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Montana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Nevada</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Jersey</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Oklahoma</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Oregon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Pennsylvania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>South Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Tennessee</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Vermont</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Virginia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Washington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Bulgaria</country>
      <state>Pleven</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Bulgaria</country>
      <state>Ruse</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Bulgaria</country>
      <state>Sofia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Newfoundland and Labrador</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Quebec</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Chile</country>
      <state>Región Metro De Santiago</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Chile</country>
      <state>Valparaíso</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Chile</country>
      <state>Santiago</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Beroun</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Brno</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Kutna Hora</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Tabor</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Estonia</country>
      <state>Tallinn</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Estonia</country>
      <state>Tartu</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Grenoble</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Marseille</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Montpellier</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Nantes</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Hessen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Niedersachsen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Berlin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mexico</country>
      <state>Jalisco</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mexico</country>
      <state>Distrito Federal</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mexico</country>
      <state>Mexico</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Amsterdam</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Eindhoven</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Hengelo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Schiedam</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Utrecht</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Peru</country>
      <state>Lima</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Bialystok</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Warszawa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Wroclaw</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Irkutsk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Kazan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Moscow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Tomsk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Amanzimtoti</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Bellville</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Durban</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Mowbray</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Thailand</country>
      <state>Bangkok</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>GlaxoSmithKline</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is designed to determine if the investigational drug is effective and safe in
      individuals with asthma.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00603746</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Busse WW, Bleecker ER, Bateman ED, Lötvall J, Forth R, Davis AM, Jacques L, Haumann B, Woodcock A. Fluticasone furoate demonstrates efficacy in patients with asthma symptomatic on medium doses of inhaled corticosteroid therapy: an 8-week, randomised, placebo-controlled trial. Thorax. 2012 Jan;67(1):35-41. doi: 10.1136/thoraxjnl-2011-200308. Epub 2011 Aug 9.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>GSK Clinical Trials</name>
      <address>GlaxoSmithKline</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>