<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5696">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/07/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/07/2014</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02202980</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy and Safety of Oral Regimens for the Treatment of Chronic HCV Infection</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 2, Multicenter, Open-Label Study to Assess the Efficacy and Safety of Oral Regimens for the Treatment of Chronic HCV Infection</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>GS-US-337-1468</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Hepatitis C</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - LDV/SOF
Treatment: drugs - RBV
Treatment: drugs - GS-9857
Treatment: drugs - SOF/GS-5816

Experimental: LDV/SOF+RBV 24 wk - Participants who previously received ledipasvir/sofosbuvir (LDV/SOF) fixed-dose combination (FDC) plus ribavirin (RBV) for = 12 weeks without achieving SVR12 will receive LDV/SOF+RBV for 24 weeks.

Experimental: LDV/SOF+RBV 12 wk - Participants who previously received a sofosbuvir-based regimen without achieving SVR12 will receive LDV/SOF+RBV for 12 weeks (excluding participants who previously received LDV/SOF+RBV for = 12 weeks).

Experimental: LDV/SOF GT2 12 wk - Participants with genotype 2 (GT2) HCV infection will receive LDV/SOF FDC for 12 weeks.

Experimental: LDV/SOF GT2 8 wk - Participants with genotype 2 HCV infection will receive LDV/SOF FDC for 8 weeks.

Experimental: LDV/SOF GT1 or GT2 12 wk - Participants with genotype 1 (GT1) or genotype 2 (GT2) HCV infection and extrahepatic manifestations of chronic HCV infection will receive LDV/SOF FDC for 12 weeks.

Experimental: LDV/SOF+RBV GT3 12 wk - Participants with genotype 3 (GT3) HCV infection and extrahepatic manifestations of chronic HCV infection will receive LDV/SOF FDC plus RBV for 12 weeks.

Experimental: GS-9857 100 mg + SOF/GS-5816 TN GT1 - Treatment-naive (TN) participants with genotype 1 HCV infection without cirrhosis will receive GS-9857 100 mg on Day 1 followed by GS-9857 100 mg plus SOF/GS-5816 for 6 weeks.

Experimental: GS-9857+SOF/GS-5816 TN GT1 4 wk - Treatment-naive participants with genotype 1 HCV infection without cirrhosis will receive up to 300 mg of GS-9857 plus SOF/GS-5816 for 4 weeks.

Experimental: GS-9857+SOF/GS-5816 TN GT1 6 wk - Treatment-naive participants with genotype 1 HCV infection with cirrhosis will receive up to 300 mg of GS-9857 plus SOF/GS-5816 for 6 weeks.

Experimental: GS-9857+SOF/GS-5816 TN GT3 6 wk - Treatment-naive participants with genotype 3 (GT3) HCV infection with cirrhosis will receive up to 300 mg of GS-9857 plus SOF/GS-5816 for 6 weeks.

Experimental: GS-9857+SOF/GS-5816 GT1 TE 6 wk - Treatment-experienced (TE) participants with genotype 1 HCV infection with cirrhosis will receive up to 300 mg of GS-9857 plus SOF/GS-5816 for 6 weeks.

Experimental: GS-9857+SOF/GS-5816 TE GT3 6 wk - Treatment-experienced participants with genotype 3 HCV infection with cirrhosis will receive up to 300 mg of GS-9857 plus SOF/GS-5816 for 6 weeks.

Experimental: GS-9857+SOF/GS-5816 TE PI GT1 6 wk - Treatment-experienced participants with genotype 1 HCV infection with or without cirrhosis who were previously treated with non-structural protein (NS)3/4A protease inhibitor (PI) will receive up to 300 mg of GS-9857 plus SOF/GS-5816 for 6 weeks.

Experimental: GS-9857+SOF/GS-5816 TE DAA GT1 6 wk - Treatment-experienced participants with genotype 1 HCV infection with or without cirrhosis who were previously treated with direct acting antivirals (DAA) will receive up to 300 mg of GS-9857 plus SOF/GS-5816 for 6 weeks.

Experimental: GS-9857+SOF/GS-5816 TE DAA GT3 6 wk - Treatment-experienced participants with genotype 3 HCV infection with or without cirrhosis who were previously treated with direct acting antivirals (DAA) will receive up to 300 mg of GS-9857 plus SOF/GS-5816 for 6 weeks.


Treatment: drugs: LDV/SOF
Ledipasvir 90 mg/sofosbuvir 400 mg (LDV/SOF) FDC tablet administered orally once daily

Treatment: drugs: RBV
Ribavirin (RBV) tablets administered orally in a divided daily dose according to package insert weight-based dosing recommendations (&lt; 75 kg = 1000 mg and = 75 kg = 1200 mg)

Treatment: drugs: GS-9857
GS-9857 tablets administered orally once daily with food

Treatment: drugs: SOF/GS-5816
Sofosbuvir (SOF) 400 mg/GS-5816 100 mg fixed-dose combination (FDC) tablets administered orally once daily

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of participants with sustained virologic response 12 weeks after discontinuation of therapy (SVR12) - SVR12 is defined as HCV RNA &lt; the lower limit of quantitation (LLOQ) 12 weeks following the last dose of study drug.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Posttreatment Week 12</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of any adverse events leading to permanent discontinuation of study drug(s)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of participants with sustained virologic response 4 and 24 weeks after discontinuation of therapy (SVR4 and SVR24) - SVR4 and SVR24 are defined as HCV RNA &lt; LLOQ at 4 and 24 weeks following the last dose of study drug, respectively.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Posttreatment Weeks 4 and 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of participants with on treatment virologic failure and relapse - On treatment virologic failure is defined as:
HCV RNA = LLOQ after having previously had HCV RNA &lt; LLOQ, while on treatment,
&gt; 1 log10 IU/mL increase in HCV RNA from nadir while on treatment,
HCV RNA persistently = LLOQ through 8 weeks of treatment (ie nonresponse)
Relapse is defined as:
HCV RNA = LLOQ during the posttreatment period having achieved HCV RNA &lt; LLOQ at end of treatment, confirmed with 2 consecutive values or last available posttreatment measurement</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Posttreatment Week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of participants with sustained virologic response (ie, HCV RNA &lt; LLOQ) while on treatment</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Willing and able to provide written informed consent

          -  Chronic HCV infection

          -  Cirrhosis determination (liver biopsy may be required)

          -  Screening laboratory values within specified limits

          -  Males and females of childbearing potential who engage in heterosexual intercourse
             must agree to use protocol specified method(s) of contraception

          -  Specific genotype, prior medical history, or concurrent disease as required by the
             specific study group</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  History of clinically significant illness or any other medical disorder that may
             interfere with subject treatment, assessment or compliance with the protocol

          -  Pregnant or nursing female, or male with pregnant female partner

          -  Clinical hepatic decompensation (ie, ascites, encephalopathy or variceal hemorrhage)

          -  Use of any prohibited concomitant medications</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/08/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>269</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/05/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Christchurch</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Gilead Sciences</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will evaluate the antiviral efficacy, safety, and tolerability of combination
      therapy with oral regimens for the treatment of chronic hepatitis C virus (HCV) infection.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02202980</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Robert H Hyland, PhD</name>
      <address>Gilead Sciences</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>