<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4171">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/11/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/11/2013</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01989208</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Assessing the Safety and Ability of SG1002 to Overcome Deficits in Hydrogen Sulfide in Heart Failure Patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Dose Escalation Study to Assess the Safety and Ability of SG1002 to Overcome Circulating Deficits in Hydrogen Sulfide Found in Heart Failure Patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>SG1002-001</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Heart Failure</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - SG1002

Placebo Comparator: Sugar capsule - One normal healthy subject and two heart failure subjects will be randomized and given placebo throughout the trial period.

Experimental: SG1002 - 200 mg capsule of SG1002 (alpha sulfur/sodium sulfate)


Other interventions: SG1002
200 mg capsules will be administered BID for 7 days, then doubled to 2 capsules BID for 7 days and doubled again to 4 capsules BID for the final 7 days.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety of multiple doses of SG1002 - Concomitant medication use, clinical laboratory tests, physical examination, vital signs, ECG, and adverse events will be used to assess safety of each dose.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Following 7 days of treatment at each of three doses</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessing changes in hydrogen sulfide levels with each dose. - At the start of each dose, blood samples will be obtained and circulating hydrogen sulfide levels will be assessed over a 24 hour period to determine whether SG1002 can overcome the deficits reported in heart failure patients.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion Criteria (healthy volunteers):

          -  Healthy male volunteers aged between 18 and 45 years (inclusive);

          -  Body mass index between 19 and 30 kg/m2 (inclusive);

          -  No clinically significant findings in the medical history and physical examination;

          -  No clinically significant laboratory values and urinalysis, unless the investigator
             considers any abnormality to be clinically irrelevant;

          -  Normal ECG, blood pressure and heart rate, unless the Investigator considers any
             abnormality to be not clinically significant (NCS);

          -  Willing to use contraception (single barrier methods); and

          -  Willing and able to provide written informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>35</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion Criteria (healthy volunteers):

          -  Have received blood products within 1 month prior to Screening;

          -  Have received any investigational research agent within 30 days or 5 half-lives
             (whichever is longer) prior to the first dose of trial medical food;

          -  Have received an investigational vaccine within 6 months, a live attenuated vaccine
             within 60 days or a registered vaccine within 30 days prior to the first dose of the
             trial medical food;

          -  Have a history of thyroidectomy or thyroid disease that required medication within the
             past 12 months;

          -  Have had serious angioedema episodes within the previous 3 years or requiring
             medication in the previous two years;

          -  Have a bleeding disorder diagnosed by a doctor (for example factor deficiency,
             coagulopathy, or platelet disorder requiring special precautions) or significant
             bruising or bleeding difficulties during blood draws;

          -  Have a psychiatric condition that precludes compliance with the protocol, past or
             present psychoses, past or present bipolar disorder, or a disorder requiring lithium,
             within five years prior to enrolment;

          -  Has a history of suicide plan;

          -  Any clinically significant abnormality at Screening determined by medical history,
             physical examination, blood chemistry, haematology, urinalysis and a 12-lead ECG, or
             positive urine screen for drugs of abuse;

          -  Any other condition which in the view of the Investigator is likely to interfere with
             the study or put the subject at risk;

          -  HIV, or hepatitis B or C positive;

          -  Have a history of or current clinically significant gastrointestinal, hepatic, renal,
             cardiovascular, respiratory, endocrine, oncological, immunodeficiency, neurological,
             metabolic, haematological or autoimmune disorder;

          -  Have a history of or current tuberculosis, epilepsy, diabetes or glaucoma;

          -  Have clinical signs of active infection or a temperature more than 38.0°C at the time
             of screening. Study entry may be deferred at the discretion of the Principal
             Investigator;

          -  Have evidence of drug or alcohol abuse;

          -  Be unable to provide repeated blood samples without undue trauma or distress;

          -  Anticipate surgery within the trial period; or

          -  Inability to speak English (due to need to administer standardized English-language
             questionnaire).

        Inclusion Criteria (heart failure subjects):

          -  Aged between 35 and 85 years (inclusive);

          -  Has symptomatic heart failure, with New York Heart Association (NYHA)classification of
             II or III;

          -  Ambulatory;

          -  Left ventricular ejection fraction less than 40%;

          -  Congestive heart failure has been stable for the previous 3 months (defined by no
             change in baseline therapy or symptoms of heart failure for the previous 3 months);
             and

          -  Willing and able to provide written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria (heart failure subjects):

          -  Subject is pregnant or breastfeeding;

          -  If female, the subject is either post-menopausal or surgically sterilised or willing
             to use an acceptable method of birth control (i.e., a hormonal contraceptive,
             intrauterine device, diaphragm with spermicide, condom with spermicide, or abstinence)
             from signing of the informed consent form though to the Final Visit/Early Termination
             Visit;

          -  Myocardial infarction, unstable angina, stroke, cerebrovascular accident, percutaneous
             coronary intervention, open heart surgery or transient ischemic attack (TIA) within 3
             months prior to Screening;

          -  Current symptomatic hypotension (defined as systolic blood pressure (SBP) = 90 mmHg or
             diastolic blood pressure (DBP) = 40 mmHg);

          -  Poorly controlled hypertension (defined as SBP = 160 mmHg or DBP = 100 mmHg) despite
             therapy

          -  Subjects with NYHA grade IV heart failure;

          -  Subjects awaiting percutaneous coronary intervention or open heart surgery;

          -  Subjects with serious liver disease;

          -  Subjects with liver function test results three times the upper limit of normal.

          -  Any change in cardiovascular drug therapy within three months prior to randomization

          -  History of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (diagnosed using GOLD criteria) or
             evidence of restrictive lung disease (defined as forced expiratory volume (FEV1) to
             forced vital capacity (FCV) ratio of &gt; 80%);

          -  Poorly controlled diabetes (defined as HbA1c &gt; 10.0 %);

          -  Has undergone Cardiac Resynchronisation Therapy (CRT) in the last 6 months and no
             planned CRT;

          -  Implantable cardioverter defibrillator (ICD) implant planned during the study;

          -  Hypersensitivity to sulfur or related compounds;

          -  Renal insufficiency defined as estimated Glomerular Filtration Rate (eGFR) &lt; 30
             mL/minute/1.73 m2 (Modification of Diet in Renal Disease Study MDRD) [2];

          -  Life expectancy less than 6 months;

          -  Active malignancy requiring active anti-neoplastic therapy that will, in the opinion
             of the investigator, interfere with study treatment or participation. (Stable basal
             cell skin cancer and cancers being treated solely with hormonal therapy are allowed.)

          -  Inability to speak English (due to need to administer standardized English-language
             questionnaire); or

          -  Any other chronic illness that may, in the opinion of the Investigator, increase the
             risks associated with this trial.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2>The people administering the treatment/s</masking2>
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/01/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>14</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Unknown status</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/12/2014</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Alfred Health - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Nucleus Network - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Sulfagenix Australia Pty Ltd.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Patients with heart failure are reported to have lower levels of hydrogen sulfide in their
      blood, even though sulfur is available naturally in the diet. Hydrogen sulfide is a molecule
      that has been shown to have a number of beneficial effects and thus the low levels may
      contribute to the disease. This trial is testing whether a medical food product of synthetic
      sulfur molecules, SG1002, can overcome this deficit in blood levels of hydrogen sulfide.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01989208</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jason Lickliter, MD, PhD</name>
      <address>Nucleus Network</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>