<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3606">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/08/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/08/2012</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01657526</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Safety, Reactogenicity and Immunogenicity of GlaxoSmithKline (GSK) Biologicals' Non-typeable Haemophilus Influenzae (NTHI) Vaccine</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An Observer-blind Study to Evaluate the Safety, Reactogenicity and Immunogenicity of GSK Biologicals' Non-typeable Haemophilus Influenzae (NTHi) Investigational Vaccine (GSK2838497A) in Healthy Adults</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>116018</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Respiratory Disorders</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - GSK Biologicals' Non-Typeable H. influenzae (GSK2838500A)
Other interventions - GSK Biologicals' Non-Typeable H. influenzae (GSK2838501A)
Other interventions - Saline placebo

Experimental: Group A - Subjects in this group will receive GSK Biologicals' NTHi candidate vaccine in Step 1 of the study

Placebo Comparator: Group B - Subjects in this group will receive placebo in Step 1 of the study

Experimental: Group C - Subjects in this group will receive GSK Biologicals' NTHi candidate vaccine in Step 2 of the study

Placebo Comparator: Group D - Subjects in this group will receive placebo in Step 2 of the study


Other interventions: GSK Biologicals' Non-Typeable H. influenzae (GSK2838500A)
Administered intramuscularly (IM) in the deltoid region of non-dominant arm

Other interventions: GSK Biologicals' Non-Typeable H. influenzae (GSK2838501A)
2 doses administered IM in the deltoid region of non-dominant arm

Other interventions: Saline placebo
2 doses administered IM in the deltoid region of non-dominant arm

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Occurrence of solicited local and general adverse event (AE), in all subjects, in all vaccine groups</outcome>
      <timepoint>During a 7-day follow-up period (i.e. day of vaccination and 6 subsequent days) after each vaccination.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Occurrence of any unsolicited AE, in all subjects, in all vaccine groups</outcome>
      <timepoint>During a 30-day follow-up period (i.e. day of vaccination and 29 subsequent days) after each vaccination.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Occurrence of haematological and biochemical laboratory abnormalities, in all subjects, in all vaccine groups</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline (Screening visit) and after each vaccination.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Occurrence of any serious adverse event (SAE), in all subjects, in all vaccine groups</outcome>
      <timepoint>From first vaccination to study conclusion (Day 420).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Occurrence of any potential Immune-Mediated Disease (pIMDs) in all subjects, in all vaccine groups</outcome>
      <timepoint>From first vaccination to study conclusion (Day 420).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Humoral immune response to components of the NTHi vaccine formulations, in all subjects, in all vaccine groups</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to each vaccination and 30 days post each vaccination.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Subjects who, in the opinion of the investigator, can and will comply with the
             requirements of the protocol.

          -  Written informed consent obtained from the subject.

          -  A male or female between, and including, 18 and 40 years of age at the time of the
             first vaccination.

          -  Healthy subjects as established by medical history, physical examination and
             laboratory assessment before entering into the study.

          -  Female subjects of non-childbearing potential may be enrolled in the study.

          -  Female subjects of childbearing potential may be enrolled in the study, if the
             subject:

               -  has practiced adequate contraception for 30 days prior to vaccination, and

               -  has a negative pregnancy test on the day of vaccination, and

               -  has agreed to continue adequate contraception during the entire treatment period
                  and for 2 months after completion of the vaccination series.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Use of any investigational or non-registered product other than the study vaccines
             within 30 days preceding the first dose of study vaccines, or planned use during the
             study period.

          -  Concurrently participating in another clinical study, at any time during the study
             period, in which the subject has been or will be exposed to an investigational or a
             non-investigational vaccine/product.

          -  Planned administration/administration of a vaccine/product not foreseen by the study
             protocol in the period starting 30 days before the first vaccine dose and ending 30
             days after the last dose of vaccines.

          -  Previous vaccination with a vaccine containing NTHi antigens.

          -  Chronic administration of immunosuppressants or other immune-modifying drugs within
             six months prior to the first vaccine dose, or equivalent. Topical steroids are
             allowed.

          -  Administration of immunoglobulins and/or any blood products within the 3 months
             preceding the first dose of study vaccines or planned administration during the study
             period.

          -  Any confirmed or suspected immunosuppressive or immunodeficient condition, based on
             medical history and physical examination.

          -  Laboratory evidence of clinically significant haematological (complete blood cell
             count [Red Blood Cells (RBC), White Blood Cells (WBC)], WBC differential count,
             platelets count and haemoglobin level) and biochemical (Alanine Aminotransferase
             [ALT], Aspartate Aminotransferase [AST], creatinine and lactate dehydrogenase [LDH])
             abnormalities as per the opinion of the investigator based on the local laboratory
             normative data.

          -  Acute disease and/or fever at the time of enrolment.

          -  Acute or chronic, clinically significant pulmonary, cardiovascular, hepatic or renal
             functional abnormality, as determined by physical examination or laboratory screening
             tests.

          -  History of or current condition preventing intramuscular injection as bleeding or
             coagulation disorder.

          -  Malignancies within previous 5 years (excluding non-melanic skin cancer) and
             lymphoproliferative disorders.

          -  Pregnant or lactating female.

          -  Female planning to become pregnant or planning to discontinue contraceptive
             precautions.

          -  History of chronic alcohol consumption and/or drug abuse.

          -  Any other condition that the investigator judges may interfere with study findings.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>8/08/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>48</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>25/11/2013</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>GlaxoSmithKline</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to evaluate the safety, reactogenicity and immunogenicity of GSK
      Biologicals' NTHi candidate vaccine in adults, administered for the first time in humans.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01657526</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>GSK Clinical Trials</name>
      <address>GlaxoSmithKline</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>