<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3064">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/01/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/01/2011</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01289782</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An Efficacy, Safety, and Tolerability Study of TMC435 in Treatment-naive, Genotype 1 Hepatitis C-infected Patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 3, Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled Study to Investigate the Efficacy, Safety and Tolerability of TMC435 vs Placebo as Part of a Treatment Regimen Including Peginterferon a-2a and Ribavirin in Treatment-naïve, Genotype 1 Hepatitis Cinfected Subjects</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>QUEST-1</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>TMC435-TiDP16-C208</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>CR017386</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hepatitis C</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Placebo
Treatment: drugs - TMC435
Treatment: drugs - Peginterferon alpha-2a (PegIFN alpha-2a)
Treatment: drugs - Ribavirin (RBV)

Experimental: TMC435 - TMC435 150 mg capsule once daily for 12 weeks in addition to peginterferon alpha-2a (PegIFN alpha-2a) and ribavirin (RBV) for 24 or 48 weeks

Placebo Comparator: Placebo - Placebo 150 mg capsule once daily for 12 weeks in addition to PegIFNa-2a and RBV for 48 weeks


Treatment: drugs: Placebo
150 mg capsule once daily for 12 weeks in addition to PegIFN alpha-2a and RBV for 48 weeks

Treatment: drugs: TMC435
150 mg capsule once daily for 12 weeks in addition to PegIFN alpha-2a and RBV for 24 or 48 weeks

Treatment: drugs: Peginterferon alpha-2a (PegIFN alpha-2a)
One subcutaneous (under the skin) injection containing 0.5 mL solution with 180 mcg PegIFN alpha-2a once weekly for up to 48 weeks.

Treatment: drugs: Ribavirin (RBV)
200-mg tablets of RBV (body-weight adjusted dose) taken orally (by mouth) twice daily for up to 48 weeks.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Percentage of Participants Achieving a Sustained Virologic Response 12 Weeks After the Planned End of Treatment (SVR12) - The table below shows the percentage of participants in each treatment group who achieved a SVR12, defined as the percentage of participants with undetectable plasma Hepatitis C virus ribonucleic acid 12 weeks after planned end of treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 36 or Week 60</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Percentage of Participants Achieving a Sustained Virologic Response at Week 72 (SVRW72) - The table below shows the percentage of participants in each treatment group who achieved a SVRW72, defined as the percentage of participants with undetectable plasma Hepatitis C virus ribonucleic acid levels at end of treatment (EOT) and at Week 72.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 72</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Percentage of Participants Who Achieved a Sustained Virologic Response 24 Weeks After the Planned End of Treatment (SVR24) - The table below shows the percentage of participants in each treatment group who achieved a SVR24, defined as the percentage of participants with undetectable plasma Hepatitis C virus ribonucleic acid levels 24 weeks after planned end of treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 48 or Week 72</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Percentage of Participants Who Achieved a Sustained Virologic Response 4 Weeks After the Planned End of Treatment (SVR4) - The table below shows the percentage of participants in each treatment group who achieved a SVR4, defined as the percentage of participants with undetectable plasma Hepatitis C virus ribonucleic acid levels 4 weeks after planned end of treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 28 or Week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in log10 Hepatitis C Virus (HCV) Ribonucleic Acid (RNA) - The table below shows the change from baseline in log10 HCV RNA levels.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 3, Week 1, Week 4, Week 12, Week 24, and Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Actual Values of log10 Hepatitis C Virus (HCV) Ribonucleic Acid (RNA) - The table below shows actual values of log10 HCV RNA levels.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 3, Week 1, Week 4, Week 12, Week 24, and Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants With On-treatment Virologic Response at All Time Points - The table below shows the percentage of participants with Hepatitis C virus (HCV) ribonucleic acid (RNA) plasma levels below the limit of detection (ie, &lt;25 IU/mL undetectable), the percentage of participants with a HCV RNA plasma level below the limit of quantification (ie, &lt; 25 IU/mL detectable or undetectable), the percentage of participants with plasma levels of HCV RNA &lt;100 IU/mL, the percentage of participants with virologic responses of a greater than or equal to 2 log10 change from baseline in plasma levels of HCV RNA.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 3, Week 1, Week 2, Week 8, Week 16, Week 20, Week 28, Week 36, and Week 42</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Percentage of Participants Achieving a Rapid Virologic Response (RVR) - The table below shows the percentage of participants in each treatment group who achieved a RVR, defined as having undetectable plasma Hepatitis C virus ribonucleic acid levels after receiving 4 weeks of treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 4</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Percentage of Participants Achieving a Early Virologic Response (EVR) - The table below shows the percentage of participants who achieved an EVR, defined as having a change from baseline in plasma Hepatitis C virus ribonucleic acid of greater than or equal to 2 log10 at Week 12.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Percentage of Participants Achieving a Complete Early Virologic Response (cEVR) - The table below shows the percentage of participants in each treatment group who had a cEVR, defined as having undetectable plasma Hepatitis C Virus ribonucleic acid levels at Week 12.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Percentage of Participants Achieving a Extended Rapid Virologic Response (eRVR) - The table below shows the percentage of participants in each treatment group who had a eRVR, defined as having undetectable plasma Hepatitis C Virus ribonucleic acid levels at Week 4 and 12.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 4 and 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Percentage of Participants With &lt;1 log10 Decrease in Hepatitis C Virus (HCV) Ribonucleic Acid (RNA) From Baseline at Week 4 - The table below shows the percentage of participants in each treatment group with &lt;1 log10 HCV RNA decrease at Week 4.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 4</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants With in Hepatitis C Virus (HCV) Ribonucleic Acid (RNA) Levels &gt;1000 IU/mL at Week 4 - The table below shows the percentage of participants in each treatment group with HCV RNA levels &gt;1000 IU/mL at Week 4.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 4</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants With Null Response - The table below shows the percentage of participants with null response, defined as &lt;2 log10 reduction in Hepatitis C virus ribonucleic acid at Week 12 compared to baseline.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants With Partial Response - The table below shows the percentage of participants with partial response, defined as greater than or equal to 2 log10 reduction in Hepatitis C virus ribonucleic acid at Week 12 compared to baseline, but not achieving undetectable HCV RNA while on treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants With Viral Breakthrough - The table below shows the percentage of participants with viral breakthrough, defined as a confirmed increase of greater than 1 log10 IU/mL in plasma Hepatitis C virus (HCV) ribonucleic acid (RNA) level from the lowest level reached (ie, lowest value measured in between baseline and current value), or a confirmed plasma HCV RNA level of greater than 100 IU/mL in participants whose plasma HCV RNA had previously been below the limit of quantification (25 IU/mL detectable) or undetectable (&lt;25 IU/mL undetectable).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants With Viral Relapse - The table below shows the percentage of participants with viral relapse, defined as having confirmed detectable plasma level of Hepatitis C virus (HCV) ribonucleic acid (RNA) during the follow-up period in participants with undetectable plasma HCV RNA (less than 25 IU/mL undetectable) at the end of treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Week 72</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants Who Completed All Study Treatment at Week 24 Because of the Treatment Duration Rule - The table below shows the percentage of participants in the TMC435 treatment group who met the treatment duration rule (ie, having hepatitis C virus [HCV] ribonucleic acid [RNA] levels &lt;25 IU/mL detectable or undetectable at Week 4 and undetectable HCV RNA levels at Week 12) and completed treatment with PegIFNa-2a and RBV for 24 weeks. Participants in the TMC435 treatment group not meeting RGT criteria and participants in the placebo group were treated with PegIFNa-2a and RBV treatment for 48 weeks.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants With On-treatment Failure - The table below shows percentage of participants with on-treatment failure defined as confirmed detectable Hepatitis C virus ribonucleic acid levels at actual end of treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Reach Hepatitis C Virus (HCV) Ribonucleic Acid (RNA) &lt;25 IU/mL Undetectable or Detectable - The table below shows median time in days to reach HCV RNA levels &lt;25 IU/mL undetectable or detectable.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Reach Hepatitis C Virus (HCV) Ribonucleic Acid (RNA) &lt;25 IU/mL Undetectable - The table below shows median time in days to reach HCV RNA levels &lt;25 IU/mL undetectable.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Reach Hepatitis C Virus (HCV) Ribonucleic Acid (RNA) &lt;100 IU/mL - The table below shows median time in days to reach HCV RNA levels &lt;100 IU/mL.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Reach Hepatitis C Virus (HCV) Ribonucleic Acid (RNA) &lt;1000 IU/mL - The table below shows median time in days to reach HCV RNA levels &lt;1000 IU/mL.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Percentage of Participants With Viral Breakthrough at Different Time Points - The table below shows the percentage of participants at different time points with viral breakthrough, defined as a confirmed increase of greater than 1 log10 IU/mL in plasma HCV ribonucleic acid (RNA) level from the lowest level reached (ie, lowest value measured in between baseline and current value), or a confirmed plasma HCV RNA level of greater than 100 IU/mL in participants whose plasma HCV RNA had previously been below the limit of quantification (25 IU/mL detectable) or undetectable (&lt;25 IU/mL undetectable).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time From End-of-treatment to Viral Relapse - The table below shows the mean number of days to viral relapse, defined as participants having confirmed detectable plasma level of Hepatitis C Virus (HCV) ribonucleic acid (RNA) during the follow-up period in participants with undetectable plasma HCV RNA (&lt;25 IU/mL undetectable) at the end of treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Week 72</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Percentage of Participants With Normalization of Alanine Aminotransferase (ALT) - The percentage of participants analyzed were those with baseline ALT values out of the normal range (ie, 158 of 264 participants in the TMC435 treatment group and 89 of 130 participants in the Placebo group had ALT values at baseline that were out of the normal range.). Normalization of ALT values means that ALT values out of the normal range returned to within the normal range.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Median Time to Normalization of Alanine Aminotransferase (ALT) Levels - The table below shows the median time in weeks to normalization of ALT levels.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma Concentration of TMC435: Area Under the Plasma Concentration-time Curve From the Time of Administration to 24 Hours After Dosing (AUC24h) - The table below shows mean (standard deviation) values of the area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time of administration to 24 hours after dosing for TMC435 for all participants. To calculate the mean AUC 24 for the study, AUC 24 hr values were derived for each participant at each visit and then a median AUC value calcuated across all visits for each participant. The median AUC value across all visits for each participant was used to calculate the mean AUC 24 hr all participants in the study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Fom the time of administration up to 24 hours after dosing at Weeks 2, 4, 8, and 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma Concentration of TMC435: Predose Plasma Concentration (C0h) - The table below shows the mean (standard deviation) values for the C0h of TMC435.To calculate the mean C0h for the study, C0h values were derived for each participant at each visit and then a median C0H value calculated across visits for each participant. The median COh value for each participant across all visits was used to calculate the mean C0h for the study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before administration of TMC435 at Weeks 2, 4, 8, and 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma Concentration of TMC435: Systemic Clearance (CL) - The table below shows the mean (standard deviation) values for the CL of TMC435.To calculate the mean CL for all participants in the study, CL values were first derived for each participant at each visit and then a median CL value calculated across visits for each participant. The median CL value for each participant was used to calculate the mean CL for all participants in the study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Across Weeks 2, 4, 8, and 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Area Under the Curve From Baseline to Week 60 (AUC60) and Week 72 (AUC72) for the Fatigue Severity Scale (FSS) Total Scores - Study participants completed FSS questionnaires during study visits before treatment began and throughout treatment and follow-up to rate the severity and impact of fatigue they experienced in the preceding 2 weeks on their daily lives. FSS total scores are the average of nine questions with a range from 1 [no fatigue] to 7 [worst possible fatigue]. An area under the curve (AUC) analysis compared the overall severity of fatigue in each treatment group from baseline to Week 72. The null hypothesis was that there would be no difference between the treatment arms in the amount of fatigue participants experienced throughout the study resulting in equal AUC from baseline to Week 72 (AUC72) for FSS total scores. The Table below shows the lease squares (LS) mean estimates of AUC at Week 72 (as well as at Week 60) and the statistical comparison between treatment groups.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to Week 60 and Week 72</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Area Under the Curve From Baseline to Week 60 (AUC60) and Week 72 (AUC72) for Impairment in Overall Work Productivity Scores Due to Hepatitis C Virus (HCV) Infection and Its Treatment - Impairment in overall work productivity was measured using the Work Productivity and Activity Impairment (WPAI): Hepatitis C questionnaire completed by participants during study visits throughout the study. WPAI Overall Productivity Scores ranged from 0% to 100% (higher WPAI scores indicated greater impairment in productivity). An area under the curve (AUC) analysis compared the overall WPAI Overall Work Productivity Scores in each treatment group from Baseline to Week 72. The null hypothesis was that there would be no difference between the treatment arms in the WPAI Overall Work Productivity Scores from Baseline to Week 72. The Table below shows the lease squares (LS) mean estimates of AUC at Week 72 (as well as at Week 60) in WPAI Work Productivity Scores and the statistical comparison between treatment groups.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to Week 60 and Week 72</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Area Under the Curve From Baseline to Week 60 (AUC60) and Week 72 (AUC72) for Impairment in Daily Activity Scores Due to Hepatitis C Virus (HCV) Infection and Its Treatment - Impairment in daily activity was measured using the Work Productivity and Activity Impairment (WPAI): Hepatitis C questionnaire, Question 6. Scores ranged from 0 (no effect on activities) to 10 (completely prevented me from doing my daily activities). An area under the curve (AUC) analysis compared the impairment in daily activity scores in each treatment group from Baseline to Week 72. The null hypothesis was that there would be no difference between the treatment arms in impairment in daily activity scores from Baseline to Week 72. The Table below shows the lease squares (LS) mean estimates of AUC at Week 72 (as well as at Week 60) in the impairment in daily activity scores and the statistical comparison between treatment groups.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to Week 60 and Week 72</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Area Under the Curve From Baseline to Week 60 (AUC60) and Week 72 (AUC72) in Work Productivity and Activity (WPAI) Absenteeism Scores Due to Hepatitis C Virus (HCV) Infection and Its Treatment - Time missed from work in hours because of HCV infection or its treatment was assessed by measuring the change from baseline in the Work Productivity and Activity Impairment (WPAI): Hepatitis C questionnaire Absenteeism score (time missed from work, question #2). The number of hours missed from work because of HCV was divided by the total number of hours supposed to work, and expressed as a percentage. An area under the curve (AUC) analysis compared the WPAI absenteeism scores in each treatment group from Baseline to Week 72. The null hypothesis was that there would be no difference between the treatment arms WPAI absenteeism scores from Baseline to Week 72. The Table below shows the lease squares (LS) mean estimates of AUC at Week 72 (as well as at Week 60) in WPAI absenteeism scores and the statistical comparison between treatment groups.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to Week 60 and Week 72</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Genotype 1 hepatitis C infection (confirmed at screening)

          -  Patient has not received any prior treatment for hepatitis C

          -  Patient must have had a liver biopsy within 3 years before screening (or between the
             screening and baseline visit) showing chronic hepatitis C infection

          -  Must agree to use 2 forms of effective contraception throughout study (both males and
             females)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Infection with HIV or non genotype 1 hepatitis C

          -  Liver disease not related to hepatitic C infection

          -  Hepatic decompensation

          -  Significant laboratory abnormalities or other active diseases

          -  Pregnant or planning to become pregnant</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2>The people administering the treatment/s</masking2>
    <masking3 />
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/02/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>395</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/01/2013</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital> - Darlinghurst</hospital>
    <hospital> - Fitzroy</hospital>
    <hospital> - Kingswood</hospital>
    <hospital> - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital> - Sydney</hospital>
    <hospital> - Wolloongabba</hospital>
    <postcode> - Darlinghurst</postcode>
    <postcode> - Fitzroy</postcode>
    <postcode> - Kingswood</postcode>
    <postcode> - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode> - Sydney</postcode>
    <postcode> - Wolloongabba</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Alabama</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Arizona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Colorado</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Illinois</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Mississippi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Missouri</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Pennsylvania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Tennessee</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Alberta</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Quebec</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Berlin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Heidelberg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Kiel</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Tübingen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mexico</country>
      <state>Guadalajara</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mexico</country>
      <state>Mex Ctity</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mexico</country>
      <state>Monterrey</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Christchurch</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Hamilton</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Puerto Rico</country>
      <state>San Juan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Romania</country>
      <state>Bucuresti</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Moscow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Nizhny Novgorod</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Saint-Petersburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Samara</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Smolensk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>St Petersburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Sevilla N/A</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Valencia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ukraine</country>
      <state>Donetsk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ukraine</country>
      <state>Kiev</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ukraine</country>
      <state>Kyiv</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ukraine</country>
      <state>Vinnytsia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Derby</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Liverpool</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Nottingham</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Plymouth</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Janssen R&amp;D Ireland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to investigate the effectiveness and safety of TMC435 compared
      with placebo in participants who are infected with genotype 1 hepatitis C virus who have
      never received treatment before. Participants will also receive peginterferon alpha-2a and
      ribavirin as part of their treatment.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01289782</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Janssen R&amp;D Ireland Clinical Trial</name>
      <address>Janssen R&amp;D Ireland</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>