<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5219">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/07/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/07/2015</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02588846</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Multi-target Tracking in Prostate Radiotherapy Using MLC and KIM</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Phase I Feasibility Study of Accounting for Relative Motion of Multiple Targets in Prostate Cancer Radiotherapy Using Realtime Multi-leaf Collimator Adaptation and Kilovoltage (kV) Intrafraction Monitoring</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Multi-target tracking</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Prostate Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Prostate</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - Combined real-time use of 'Multi-Leaf Collimator Adaptation' and 'kV Intrafraction Monitoring'

Experimental: Stage 1: Optimise nodal treatment margin - During Stage 1: Optimise nodal treatment margin, Combined real-time use of 'Multi-Leaf Collimator Adaptation' and 'kV Intrafraction Monitoring' will be used to reshape the radiation beam in real-time. The nodal target position stability will be evaluated by the cone beam computed tomography (CBCT) imaging before and after each treatment session for the first 10 patients.

Experimental: Stage 2: Use treatment margin - During Stage 2: Use treatment margin, Combined real-time use of 'Multi-Leaf Collimator Adaptation' and 'kV Intrafraction Monitoring' will be used to reshape the radiation beam in real-time. At the same time, multi-leaf collimator (MLC) tracking will be used to reshape the radiation beam in real-time using the margin size determined in Stage 1.


Treatment: devices: Combined real-time use of 'Multi-Leaf Collimator Adaptation' and 'kV Intrafraction Monitoring'
This intervention uses the simultaneous combined use of two technologies: 'Multi-Leaf Collimator Adaptation' and 'kV Intrafraction Monitoring'. kV Intrafraction Monitoring (KIM) measures the motion of tissues targeted for radiotherapy in real time using kV imaging.The multi-leaf collimator (MLC) reshapes the radiation beam to maximise dose to the target tissue and minimise dose to the surrounding healthy tissue. Combining KIM and MLC allows the shaped radiation beam to follow the moving target (the prostate) while remaining fixed on a stationary target (lymph nodes) that are also being treated at the same time.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Software or mechanical failure - The percentage of fractions delivered without software or mechanical failure</outcome>
      <timepoint>The treatment period (2-9 weeks)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Geometric accuracy - The geometric accuracy of the beam shape, determined by comparing the ideal beam shape with the actual beam shape.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The treatment period (2-9 weeks)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prostate motion trajectory - Prostate motion trajectory measured by KIM.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Treatment period (2-9 weeks)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dosimetric accuracy - The estimated dose distributions will be compared to the original plan using the dose reconstruction method18 based on the prostate motion trajectory and the logged MLC positions (beam shapes).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Treatment period (2-9 weeks)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acute toxicity - Toxicity during treatment</outcome>
      <timepoint>Treatment period (2-9 weeks) plus 3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Patients undergoing definitive external beam radiotherapy at Northern Sydney Cancer
             Centre

          -  Patients histologically proven prostate adenocarcinoma

          -  PSA obtained within 3 months prior to enrolment

          -  Pelvic lymph nodes are included for treatment for patients at stage T1c-T3b with
             Gleason 8-10 or prostate-specific antigen (PSA) &gt; 20 ng/ml or pelvic lymph node
             positivity on conventional imaging or prostate-specific membrane antigen (PSMA) scans.

          -  Patient must be able to have gold fiducial markers placed in the prostate

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0-2

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document.

          -  Prostate dimension that allows leaf span with tracking margin of ±8mm</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Male</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Patients with artificial Hip(s), lumbar spinal surgical rods or other large metallic
             pelvic implants

          -  Patient's dimensions &gt;40cm as measured at the level of the prostate

          -  Patients with overlapping implanted gold fiducials in x-ray imaging</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2018</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/12/2023</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal North Shore Hospital - St Leonards</hospital>
    <postcode>2065 - St Leonards</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal North Shore Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Assessing the feasibility of implementing real-time multi-leaf collimator (MLC) tracking to
      account for the relative motion of the moving prostate tumour target and the static pelvic
      nodal target for high-risk prostate cancer patients. The capability of tracking for the
      relative motion of multiple targets will ensure that all the treatment targets receive
      correct dose as prescribed by the doctor and minimise side effects to the critical organs.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02588846</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Thomas Eade, MBBS, RANZCR</name>
      <address>Director of Research, Senior Staff Specialist</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Clare Banks, BASc MPH</name>
      <address />
      <phone>1 2 9463 1345</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Clare.Banks@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>