<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="1668">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/08/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/08/2007</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00521079</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>EMPOWER Clinical Trial: Vagal Blocking for Obesity Control</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>EMPOWER Clinical Trial: Vagal Blocking for Obesity Control</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>EMPOWER</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>D00343-000</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - Therapy ON
Treatment: devices - Therapy OFF

Experimental: vBloc - Subjects implanted with a functional Maestro System device that delivers therapy (Therapy ON).

Sham Comparator: Placebo - Subjects implanted with a functional Maestro System device that does NOT deliver therapy (Therapy OFF).


Treatment: devices: Therapy ON
Intermittent, programmable, intra-abdominal vagal blocking device that delivers therapy (Therapy ON)

Treatment: devices: Therapy OFF
Active intra-abdominal placebo device that delivers no therapy (Therapy OFF)

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Excess Weight Loss (EWL) With the Maestro System - Observe at least a 10% greater percentage excess weight loss (%EWL) with vBloc therapy delivered by the Maestro System compared to sham 12 months following randomization using MetLife Method (ideal body weight is calculated based on Metropolitan Height and Weight Tables)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 1 Year</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of System and Procedure-related Serious Adverse Events (SAEs). - To estimate the rate of serious, system- and procedure-related adverse events associated with the Maestro System.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 Year</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants Achieving 25% Excess Weight Loss (%EWL) - To evaluate the percentage of participants achieving 25% excess weight loss from baseline (implant) to 12 months between treatment groups.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 1 Year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria

          1. Informed consent.

          2. Body mass index (BMI) = 40 kg/m2 to 45 kg/m2 or BMI = 35 kg/m2 to 39.9 kg/m2 with one
             or more obesity related co-morbid condition. Co-morbid conditions may include one or
             more of the following:

               -  Type 2 diabetes mellitus (note: type 2 diabetics are allowed at selected centers
                  only, see Inclusion criterion #5)

               -  Hypertension as defined by systolic pressure =140 mmHg and/or diastolic pressure
                  =90 mmHg a) treated or untreated with systolic =140 mmHg or diastolic =90 mmHg or
                  b) treated with systolic &lt;140 mmHg and diastolic &lt;90 mmHg

               -  Dyslipidemia as defined by total cholesterol =200 or LDL =130 a) treated or
                  untreated with total cholesterol =200 or LDL =130 or b) treated with total
                  cholesterol &lt;200 or LDL &lt;130

               -  Sleep apnea syndrome (confirmed by overnight p02 studies)

               -  Obesity related cardiomyopathy

          3. Females or males Note: females of child-bearing potential must have a negative urine
             pregnancy test at Screen and also within 14 days of implant procedure followed by
             physician-approved contraceptive regimen for the duration of the study period.

          4. 18-65 years of age inclusive.

          5. Type 2 diabetes mellitus subjects (at selected centers, limited to approximately 34
             subjects) with:

               -  Glycosylated hemoglobin (Hb A1c) 6.5 - 9 % inclusive at screening visit.

               -  Onset: 10 years or less since initial diagnosis.

               -  Stable treatment regimen: no change in oral hypoglycemic treatment regimen within
                  past 3 months.

               -  Currently not using insulin therapy, GLP-1 receptor agonists (e.g., exenatide),
                  or DPP-4 inhibitors (e.g., sitagliptin) for diabetes treatment and have not been
                  on these treatments in the past 6 months.

               -  Creatinine within normal reference range.

               -  No history of proliferative retinopathy.

               -  No history of peripheral neuropathy.

               -  No history of autonomic neuropathy.

               -  No history of coronary artery disease, with or without angina pectoris.

               -  No history of peripheral vascular disease.

          6. Failure to respond to supervised diet/exercise program(s) in which the subject was
             engaged for at least 6 months within the last five years.

          7. Ability to complete all study visits and procedures.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria

          1. Concurrent chronic pancreatic disease.

          2. History of Crohn's disease and/or ulcerative colitis.

          3. History of bariatric surgery, fundoplication, gastric resection or major
             upper-abdominal surgery (acceptable surgeries include cholecystectomy, hysterectomy).

          4. History of pulmonary embolism or blood coagulation disorders.

          5. Clinically significant hiatal hernias known from subject's medical record as or
             determined by upper endoscopy prior to implant if they have not had one done during
             the previous 6 months that specifically reported on the presence or absence of hiatal
             hernia making reference to the Z-line and/or diaphragmatic notch, in order to rule out
             subjects with hiatal hernia that may require surgical repair (to support exclusion
             criterion #7).

          6. Current portal hypertension and/or esophageal varices.

          7. Intra-operative exclusion: hiatal hernia requiring surgical repair or extensive
             dissection at esophagogastric junction at time of surgery.

          8. Treatment with weight-loss prescription drug therapy within the prior three months and
             the use of prescription drug therapy or the use over-the-counter weight loss
             preparations for the duration of the trial.

          9. Smoking cessation within the prior six months.

         10. Known genetic cause of obesity (e.g., Prader-Willi Syndrome).

         11. Overall sustained reduction of more than 10% of body weight in the previous 12 months.

         12. Physician-prescribed pre-operative diet with intent to lose weight prior to surgery
             (note: a) study subject may continue any personal diet they were on prior to study
             enrollment [see exclusion criterion #24] b) standardized EMPOWER weight management
             program to be initiated in all subjects at time of activation, approximately two weeks
             after implant)

         13. Current type 1 diabetes mellitus (DM).

         14. Current or recent history (within 12 months) of ongoing bulimia.

         15. Current alterations in treatment for thyroid disorders (stable treatment regimen for
             prior three months acceptable).

         16. Current alterations in treatment for epilepsy (stable treatment regimen for prior six
             months acceptable).

         17. Current treatment for peptic ulcer disease (previous history acceptable).

         18. Chronic (more than 4 weeks of daily use) treatment with narcotic analgesic drug
             regimens (treatment with non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs acceptable).

         19. Current alterations in treatment regimens of anti-cholinergic drugs, including
             tricyclic antidepressants (stable treatment regimen for prior six months acceptable).

         20. Current medical condition that, in the opinion of the investigator, would make subject
             unfit for surgery under general anesthesia or that would be exacerbated by intentional
             weight loss. Some examples include diagnosis of cancer, recent heart attack, recent
             stroke or recent serious trauma.

         21. Presence of permanently implanted electrical powered medical device or implanted
             gastrointestinal device or prosthesis (e.g., pacemakers, implanted defibrillators,
             neurostimulators etc.).

         22. Planned or contemplated use of Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) or oncological
             radiation during the course of the trial.

         23. Significant psychiatric disorders that, in the opinion of the investigator, may
             interfere with subject's ability to follow study procedures and/or instructions.

         24. Current, active member of an organized weight loss program (e.g., Weight Watchers,
             TOPS).

         25. Current participant in another weight loss study or other clinical trials.

         26. Have a friend or family member who is currently participating or is planning to
             participate in this clinical trial.

         27. Patient reported:

               -  inability to walk for about 10 minutes without stopping,

               -  feeling of pain in chest when doing physical activity,

               -  feeling of pain in chest when not doing physical activity. Note: unless pain in
                  chest in known to be related to upper gastrointestinal disorders such as
                  gastroesophageal reflux disease or heartburn.

         28. Clinically significant cardiac rhythm disorder that requires either medical and/or
             surgical intervention (e.g., paroxysmal or chronic atrial fibrillation).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2>The people administering the treatment/s</masking2>
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/08/2007</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>294</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/12/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Institute of Weight Control - Sydney</hospital>
    <hospital>Adelaide Bariatric Center - Flinders Private Hospital - Bedford Park</hospital>
    <postcode>2153 - Sydney</postcode>
    <postcode>5042 - Bedford Park</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Arizona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Maryland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Massachusetts</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Minnesota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Missouri</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Oregon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Virginia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>EnteroMedics</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a randomized multi-center study being done to measure the ability of a new medical
      device, Maestro System, to safely reduce body weight over five years in people who are
      considered obese.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00521079</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Charles J Billington, MD</name>
      <address>VA Medical Center, Minneapolis, MN / University of Minnesota</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>