<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6679">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/02/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/02/2017</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT03069352</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Study of Venetoclax in Combination With Low Dose Cytarabine Versus Low Dose Cytarabine Alone in Treatment Naïve Patients With Acute Myeloid Leukemia Who Are Ineligible for Intensive Chemotherapy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo Controlled Study of Venetoclax Co-Administered With Low Dose Cytarabine Versus Low Dose Cytarabine in Treatment Naïve Patients With Acute Myeloid Leukemia Who Are Ineligible for Intensive Chemotherapy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>2016-003900-30</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>M16-043</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute Myeloid Leukemia (AML)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Leukaemia - Acute leukaemia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Leukaemia - Chronic leukaemia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Children's - Leukaemia &amp; Lymphoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Venetoclax
Treatment: drugs - Placebo
Treatment: drugs - Cytarabine

Experimental: Venetoclax + Low Dose Cytarabine (LDAC) - Venetoclax 600 mg orally every day (QD) QD on Days 1 - 28 plus LDAC 20 mg/m^2 subcutaneously QD on Days 1 - 10 (28 day cycle)

Placebo Comparator: Placebo + LDAC - Matching Placebo for Venetoclax 600 mg orally QD on Days 1 - 28 plus LDAC 20 mg/m^2 subcutaneous QD on Days 1 - 10 (28 day cycle)


Treatment: drugs: Venetoclax
tablet

Treatment: drugs: Placebo
tablet

Treatment: drugs: Cytarabine
Subcutaneous

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall survival (OS) - OS is defined as the number of days from the date of randomization to the date of death.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured up to 2 years after the last participant is enrolled</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of participants with complete remission (CR) or complete remission with incomplete marrow recovery (CRi) - This will be calculated based on current International Working Group (IWG) criteria. CR is defined as absolute neutrophil count greater than 10^3/ microliter (mcL), platelets greater than or equal to 10^5/mcL, red cell transfusion independence, and bone marrow with less than 5% blasts. CRi is defined as bone marrow with less than 5% blasts, and absolute neutrophils of less than 10^3/mcL or thrombocytopenia less than or equal to 10^5/mcL (100,000/mcL)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 2 years after the last participant is randomized</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Event-free survival (EFS) - EFS will be defined as the number of days from randomization to the date of progressive disease, relapse from CR to CRi, treatment failure, or death from any cause.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 2 years after the last participant is enrolled</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of participants with CR or CRi recovery (CR + CRi) by the initiation of Cycle 2 - This will be calculated based on current International Working Group (IWG) criteria. CR is defined as absolute neutrophil count greater than 10^3/ microliter (mcL), platelets greater than or equal to 10^5/mcL, red cell transfusion independence, and bone marrow with less than 5% blasts. CRi is defined as bone marrow with less than 5% blasts, and absolute neutrophils of less than 10^3/mcL or thrombocytopenia less than or equal to 10^5/mcL (100,000/mcL)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 6 months after the last participant is randomized</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System (PROMIS) Cancer Fatigue Short Form [SF] 7a - Fatigue will be assessed using the Patient Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System (PROMIS) Cancer Fatigue Short Form (SF) 7a global fatigue score. PROMIS Cancer Fatigue SF 7a is a seven item questionnaire that assesses the impact and experience of fatigue over the past 7 days.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 2 years after the last participant is enrolled</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Global Health Status/Quality of Life (GHS/QoL) - Global health status/quality of life will be assessed using the GHS/QoL scale from the European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer Quality of Life Questionnaire Core (EORTC QLQC30).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 2 years after the last participant is enrolled</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Participant must have histological confirmation of Acute Myeloid
        Leukemia (AML) by World Health Organization criteria, is ineligible for intensive induction
        chemotherapy and either is:

          1. = 75 years of age OR

          2. = 18 to 74 years of age and fulfill at least one criteria associated with lack of
             fitness for intensive induction chemotherapy:

        i. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance status of 2 - 3; ii. Cardiac
        history of Congestive Heart Failure (CHF) requiring treatment or Ejection Fraction = 50% or
        chronic stable angina; iii. Diffusing Capacity of the Lung for Carbon Monoxide (DLCO) = 65%
        or Forced Expiratory Volume in 1 second(FEV1) = 65%; iv. Creatinine clearance = 30 mL/min
        to &lt; 45 ml/min; v. Moderate hepatic impairment with total bilirubin &gt; 1.5 to = 3.0 × Upper
        Limit of Normal (ULN); vi. Other comorbidity that the physician judges to be incompatible
        with conventional intensive chemotherapy which must be reviewed and approved by the study
        medical monitor before study enrollment.

          -  Participant must have an ECOG Performance status:

               1. of 0 to 2 for participants = 75 years of age or

               2. of 0 to 3 for participants between 18 to 74 years of age.

          -  Participant must have a projected life expectancy of at least 12 weeks.

          -  Participant must have adequate renal function as demonstrated by a creatinine
             clearance = 30 mL/min; calculated by the Cockcroft Gault formula or measured by
             24-hours urine collection.

          -  Participant must have adequate liver function as demonstrated by:

             a. aspartate aminotransferase (AST) = 3.0 × ULN* b. alanine aminotransferase (ALT) =
             3.0 × ULN* c. bilirubin = 1.5 × ULN* i. Subjects who are &lt; 75 years of age may have
             bilirubin of = 3.0 × ULN

             * Unless considered to be due to leukemic organ involvement.

          -  Female participants must be either postmenopausal defined as:

               1. Age &gt; 55 years with no menses for 12 or more months without an alternative
                  medical cause.

               2. Age = 55 years with no menses for 12 or more months without an alternative
                  medical cause AND an FSH level &gt; 40 IU/L; or

               3. Permanently surgical sterile (bilateral oophorectomy, bilateral salpingectomy or
                  hysterectomy); or

               4. A Woman of Childbearing Potential (WOCBP) practicing at least one protocol
                  specified method of birth control starting at Study Day 1 through at least 180
                  days after the last dose of study drug.

          -  Male participants who are sexually active, must agree, from Study Day 1 through at
             least 180 days after the last dose of study drug, to practice the protocol specified
             contraception. Male subjects must agree to refrain from sperm donation from initial
             study drug administration through at least 180 days after the last dose of study drug.

          -  Females of childbearing potential must have negative results for pregnancy test
             performed:

               1. At Screening with a serum sample obtained within 14 days prior to the first study
                  drug administration, and

               2. Prior to dosing with urine sample obtained on Week 1 Day 1, if it has been &gt; 7
                  days since obtaining the serum pregnancy test results.

               3. Participants with borderline pregnancy tests at Screening must have a serum
                  pregnancy test = 3 days later to document continued lack of a positive result.

          -  Participant must voluntarily sign and date an informed, approved by an Independent
             Ethics Committee (IEC)/Institutional Review Board (IRB), prior to the initiation of
             any screening or study-specific procedures.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>99</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Participant has received any prior treatment for AML with the
        exception of hydroxyurea, allowed through the first cycle of study treatment. Note: Prior
        treatment for Myelodysplastic Syndrome is allowed except for use of cytarabine.

          -  Participant had an antecedent myeloproliferative neoplasm (MPN) including
             myelofibrosis, essential thrombocytosis, polycythemia vera, or chronic myelogenous
             leukemia (CML) with or without BCR-ABL mutation.

          -  Participants that have acute promyelocytic leukemia (APL).

          -  Participant has known Central Nervous System (CNS) involvement with AML.

          -  Participant has known Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) infection (due to potential
             drug-drug interactions between antiretroviral medications and venetoclax).

          -  Participant is known to be positive for hepatitis B virus (HBV), or hepatitis C virus
             (HCV) infection. Inactive hepatitis carrier status or low viral hepatitis titer on
             antivirals (non-exclusionary medications) are not excluded.

          -  Participant has received strong or moderate CYP3A inducers 7 days prior to the
             initiation of study treatment.

          -  Participant has consumed grapefruit, grapefruit products, Seville oranges (including
             marmalade containing Seville oranges) or Star fruit within 3 days prior to the
             initiation of study treatment.

          -  Participant has cardiovascular disability status of New York Heart Association Class &gt;
             2.

        Class 2 is defined as cardiac disease which subjects are comfortable at rest but ordinary
        physical activity results in fatigue, palpitations, dyspnea, or angina pain.

        Class 3 is defined as cardiac disease which subjects are comfortable at rest but less than
        ordinary activity causes fatigue, palpitation, or dyspnea.

        Class 4 is defined as cardiac disease which subjects have an inability to carry on any
        physical activity without discomfort, symptoms of heart failure at rest, and if any
        physical activity is undertaken then discomfort increases.

          -  Participant has chronic respiratory disease that requires continuous oxygen, or
             significant history of renal, neurologic, psychiatric, endocrinologic, metabolic,
             immunologic, hepatic, cardiovascular disease, or any other medical condition that in
             the opinion of the investigator would adversely affect his/her participating in this
             study.

          -  Participant has a malabsorption syndrome or other condition that precludes enteral
             route of administration.

          -  Participant exhibits evidence of other clinically significant uncontrolled systemic
             infection requiring therapy (viral, bacterial or fungal).

          -  Participant has a history of other malignancies prior to study entry, with the
             exception of:

               1. Adequately treated in situ carcinoma of the cervix uteri or carcinoma in situ of
                  breast;

               2. Basal cell carcinoma of the skin or localized squamous cell carcinoma of the
                  skin;

               3. Previous malignancy confined and surgically resected (or treated with other
                  modalities) with curative intent.

          -  Participant has a white blood cell count &gt; 25 × 109/L. (Note: Hydroxyurea
             administration or leukapheresis is permitted to meet this criterion).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional(has expanded access)</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2>The people administering the treatment/s</masking2>
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>24/05/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>175</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>4/04/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>The Alfred Hospital /ID# 160125 - Prahran</hospital>
    <postcode>3181 - Prahran</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Kentucky</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Wisconsin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Woluwe-Saint-Lambert</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Barretos</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Florianopolis</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Porto Alegre/RS</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Sao Paulo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Montreal</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Praha</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Le Mans Cedex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Alexandroupolis</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Athens</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Exohi , Thessaloniki</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Patras</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Budapest</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Derbrecen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Gyor</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Kaposvar</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Miskolc</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Pecs</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Ancona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Bologna</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Lecce</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Milano</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Milan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Naples</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Pesaro</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Fukuoka</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Hidaka-shi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Ibaraki</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Kamigyo-Ku, Kyoto</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Komae, Tokyo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Maebashi-shi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Nagasaki-shi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Nagoya</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Osaka sayama-shi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Osaka-shi, Osaka</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Sendai-shi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Shinagawa-ku, Tokyo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Tokyo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Yamagata-shi,Yamagata</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Yoshida-gun,Fukui</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Busan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Daejeon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Seoul</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Puerto Rico</country>
      <state>San Juan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Kemerovo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Moscow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Nizhniy Novgorod</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Ryazan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Saratov</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Pretoria</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Kaohsiung</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Birmingham</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Harrow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>AbbVie</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Acute Myeloid Leukaemia (AML) is an aggressive and rare cancer of myeloid cells (a white
      blood cell responsible for fighting infections). Successful treatment of AML is dependent on
      what subtype of AML the patient has, and the age of the patient when diagnosed.

      Venetoclax is an experimental drug that kills cancer cells by blocking a protein (part of a
      cell) that allows cancer cells to stay alive. This study is designed to see if adding
      venetoclax to cytarabine works better than cytarabine on its own.

      This is a Phase 3, randomized, double-blind (treatment unknown to patients and doctors),
      placebo-controlled, multicenter study in patients with AML who are 18 or more years old and
      have not been treated before. Patients who take part in this study should not be suitable for
      intensive induction chemotherapy (usual starting treatment). Abbvie is funding this study
      which will take place at approximately 125 hospitals globally and enrol approximately 175
      patients. In this study, 2/3 of patients will receive venetoclax every day with cytarabine
      and the remaining 1/3 will receive placebo (dummy) tablets with azacitidine.

      Patients will continue to have study visits and receive treatment for as long as they are
      having a clinical benefit. The effect of the treatment on AML will be checked by taking
      blood, bone marrow, scans, measuring side effects and by completing health questionnaires.
      Blood and bone marrow tests will be completed to see why some people respond better than
      others. Additional blood tests will be completed for genetic factors and to see how long the
      drug remains in the body.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03069352</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>AbbVie Inc</name>
      <address>AbbVie</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>AbbVie_Call Center</name>
      <address />
      <phone>847.283.8955</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>abbvieclinicaltrials@abbvie.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>