<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5439">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/12/2005</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/12/2005</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00266786</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Safety and Efficacy of Multiple Doses of Intranasal Ketorolac in Postoperative Pain Following Major Abdominal Surgery</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 3, Double-Blind, Randomized Study of the Safety, Tolerability, and Analgesic Efficacy of Multiple Doses of Ketorolac Tromethamine Administered Intranasally for Postoperative Pain Following Major Abdominal Surgery</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>ROX 2005-01</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Postoperative Pain</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Intranasal Ketorolac Tromethamine
Treatment: drugs - Intranasal Placebo

Experimental: Intranasal Ketorolac Tromethamine - 

Placebo Comparator: Intranasal Placebo - 


Treatment: drugs: Intranasal Ketorolac Tromethamine
Intranasal at 30mg

Treatment: drugs: Intranasal Placebo
Intranasal Placebo

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Summed Pain Intensity Difference (SPID) on Day 1 - Ratings of Pain Intensity (PI) were made using a 100-mm Visual Analog Scale (VAS) on which 0 = no pain and 100 = worst pain possible. The PI values were obtained every hour following the first dose of study medication on Day 1. Pain intensity difference (PID) was calculated by subtracting the posttreatment score from the baseline score, where the baseline score was the PI rating made prior to the first dose of study medication. A summed PID (SPID) on the first postoperative day was calculated at 6 hours.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 hours after drug administration</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain intensity difference scores - Ratings of Pain Intensity (PI) were made using a 100-mm Visual Analog Scale (VAS) on which 0 = no pain and 100 = worst pain possible. PID was calculated by subtracting the posttreatment score from the baseline score, where the baseline score was the PI rating made prior to the first dose of study medication.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to receiving study drug and at 20, 40, and 60 minutes, and 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 12, 18, 24, 30, 36, 42, and 48 hours after the first dose, then prior to each dose up to 72 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of analgesia - Quality of analgesia was assessed on a 5-point categorical scale with 0 = poor, 1 = fair, 2 = good, 3 = very good, and 4 = excellent.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to receiving study drug and at 20, 40, and 60 minutes, and 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 12, 18, 24, 30, 36, 42, and 48 hours after the first dose, then prior to each dose up to 72 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Global assessment of pain control - A global evaluation of pain control was conducted once daily at bedtime using a 5-point categorical scale on which 0 = poor, 1 = fair, 2 = good, 3 = very good, and 4 = excellent.</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 hours following first dose of study medication</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Morphine sulfate consumption at 24, 48, and 72 hours</outcome>
      <timepoint>24, 48, and 72 hours after drug administration</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Men or women age 18 through 64 years

          -  Major abdominal surgery

          -  Body weight = 100 and = 300 pounds

          -  Negative serum pregnancy test

          -  Pain intensity score at least 40 (moderate pain) on 100 mm visual analog scale

          -  Minimum 48 hour hospital stay and 5 day maximum stay

          -  Able to provide written informed consent

          -  Willing and able to comply with all testing requirements of the protocol</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>64</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Allergy or sensitivity to ketorolac or ethylene diamine tetraacetic acid (EDTA)

          -  Allergy or significant reaction to opioids

          -  Allergic reaction to aspirin or other nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drug (NSAIDs)

          -  Current upper respiratory tract infection or other respiratory tract condition that
             could interfere with absorption of the nasal spray or adverse event assessment

          -  Use of any intranasal product in past 24 hours

          -  Clinically significant abnormality on screening lab tests

          -  History of cocaine use

          -  Active peptic ulcer disease or significant history of peptic ulcer disease or
             gastrointestinal bleeding

          -  Advanced renal impairment or risk for renal failure

          -  History of other medical problems that could interfere with the study participation

          -  Pregnancy or breastfeeding

          -  Participation in another investigational study within past 30 days</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/12/2005</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>321</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Hamilton</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Egalet Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Ketorolac has been marketed for several years in other forms (tablet and injectable) for the
      short-term relief of pain. This study will test whether a new dosage form (nasal spray)
      containing ketorolac is effective at relieving the pain of major abdominal surgery, and will
      also assess product safety. Previous studies with the nasal spray have suggested that it is
      similar to the previously approved injectable form in effectiveness for pain relief and in
      its safety profile.

      Patients will be randomized in a 2:1 ratio to receive intranasal ketorolac or placebo when
      the pain reaches a moderate level (40 on a scale of 100) following surgery. After the first
      dose, subjects will receive study drug every 6 hours for 48 hours, and then as needed (up to
      4 times a day) for a total of 5 days. If pain is not adequately relieved by the study drug,
      subjects will be given morphine sulfate or other standard analgesics. Follow-up safety
      evaluations will occur about 1 and 2 weeks after the start of dosing.

      Subjects will be asked to answer questions about their pain relief and any possible side
      effects of the drug during the study, and will be given physical examinations, including
      nasal evaluations, before and during the clinical trial. A small amount of blood will be
      drawn for routine clinical laboratory testing.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00266786</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Lincoln Bynum, MD</name>
      <address>ICON Clinical Research</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>