<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2817">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/06/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/06/2010</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01145157</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Comparison Between Signature Total Knee Arthroplasty (TKA) to Conventional TKA and Computer Assisted TKA</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Comparison Between 'Signature Personalised Patient Care' to Conventional Total Knee Arthroplasty and Computer Assisted Navigation and a Cost Benefit Analysis for the Australian Market</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>BMET AU03 (INT.CR.LAU3)</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Joint Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - Signature Knee Guide
Treatment: devices - Conventional Instrumentation
Treatment: devices - Computer Assisted Navigation

Experimental: Signature Knee Guide - Total Knee Arthroplasty using the Signature Knee Guide with the Vanguard Knee System

Active Comparator: Conventional Instrumentation - Total Knee Arthroplasty will be performed using Conventional Instrumentation with the Vanguard Knee System

Active Comparator: Computer Assisted Navigation - Total Knee Arthroplasty will be performed using Computer Assisted Navigation with the Vanguard Knee System


Treatment: devices: Signature Knee Guide
Total Knee Arthroplasty performed using Signature Knee Guide

Treatment: devices: Conventional Instrumentation
Total Knee Arthroplasty performed using Conventional Instrumentation

Treatment: devices: Computer Assisted Navigation
Total Knee Arthroplasty performed using Computer Assisted Navigation

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mechanical Axial Alignment - The primary radiological outcome will be tibial rotation</outcome>
      <timepoint>Six months post-operative</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional outcomes - Knee Society Score - The Knee Score consists of points given for pain, range of motion, and stability in both the coronal and sagittal planes, with deductions for fixed deformity, and extensor lag. The Function Score consists of points given for the ability to walk on level surfaces, and the ability to ascend and descend stairs, with deductions for the use of external supporting devices.</outcome>
      <timepoint>One year post-operative</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Patient is of legal age and skeletally mature

          -  Patient requires primary total knee arthroplasty due to non- inflammatory degenerative
             joint disease (e.g. osteoarthritis, traumatic arthritis, a vascular necrosis,
             dysplasia/DDH) or inflammatory joint disease (e.g., Rheumatoid arthritis).

          -  Patient has met an acceptable preoperative medical clearance and is free from or
             treated for cardiac, pulmonary, haematological, etc., conditions that would pose
             excessive operative risk

          -  The patient will be available for follow up throughout the duration of the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Patient is unable to have an MRI scan due to the following conditions:

               -  Cardiac pacemaker

               -  Surgical clips in head (aneurysm clips)

               -  Some artificial heart valves

               -  Electronic inner ear implants

               -  Metal fragments in eyes

               -  Electronic stimulators

               -  Implanted pumps

          -  Patient has active infection or sepsis (treated or untreated)

          -  Patient has any vascular insufficiency, muscular atrophy, or neuromuscular disease
             severe enough to compromise implant stability or postoperative recovery.

          -  Patient is female of child-bearing age and not taking contraceptive precautions.

          -  Patient has inadequate bone stock to support the device (e.g. severe osteopenia,
             family history of severe osteoporosis or osteopenia).

          -  Patient has known moderate to severe renal insufficiency.

          -  Patient has a known or suspected metal sensitivity.

          -  Patient is immunosuppressed or receiving high doses of corticosteroids.

          -  Patient has an emotional or neurological condition that would pre-empt their ability
             or willingness to participate in the study including mental illness, mental
             retardation, or drug, alcohol abuse.

          -  Patient has BMI &gt;40.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>150</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/02/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Repatriation General Hospital (RGH) - Daw Park</hospital>
    <postcode>5041 - Daw Park</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Zimmer Biomet</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a prospective, randomised clinical outcomes study comparing the Signature
      Personalised Patient Care, Conventional Total Knee Arthroplasty and Computer Assisted
      Navigation, using Vanguard Knee System. The aim of the study is to evaluate the safety and
      efficacy of TKA using Signature Personalised Patient Care compared to Conventional TKA and
      Computer Assisted Navigation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01145157</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jegan Krishnan</name>
      <address>Flinders Medical Centre</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>