<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6004">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/07/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/07/2015</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02517398</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>MSB0011359C (M7824) in Metastatic or Locally Advanced Solid Tumors</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase I, Open-label, Multiple-ascending Dose Trial to Investigate the Safety, Tolerability,Pharmacokinetics, Biological and Clinical Activity of MSB0011359C in Subjects With Metastatic or Locally Advanced Solid Tumors and Expansion to Selected Indications</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>2015-004366-28</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>EMR 200647-001</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Solid Tumors</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - MSB0011359C

Experimental: MSB0011359C (M7824) - 


Treatment: drugs: MSB0011359C
Subjects will receive intravenous infusion of MSB0011359C once every 2 weeks in a dose escalation fashion until confirmed progression, unacceptable toxicity, or any criterion for withdrawal from the trial or investigational medicinal product (IMP) occurs.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dose-escalation Part: Number of Subjects With Treatment Emergent Adverse Events (TEAEs) - An Adverse Event (AE) is defined as any new untoward medical occurrences/worsening of pre-existing medical condition without regard to possibility of causal relationship. A Serious Adverse Event (SAE) is an AE that resulted in any of the following outcomes: death; life threatening; persistent/significant disability/incapacity; initial or prolonged inpatient hospitalization; congenital anomaly/birth defect. AEs (SAEs and non-SAEs) will be considered TEAEs when emerging on treatment period defined as the time from the first trial drug administration up to 10 weeks after the last drug administration date.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 10 weeks after last treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dose-escalation Part: Number of Subjects With Treatment-Related AEs - Treatment related AEs are any untoward medical occurrence in a subject who received study drug with causal relationship with the investigational product as assessed by the investigator. AEs will be assessed according to severity; mild (not causing any significant problem, dose adjustment not required), moderate (caused problem that does not interfere significantly with usual activities or the clinical status, dose adjustment needed due to adverse event) and severe (caused problem that interferes significantly with usual activities or the clinical status, study drug stopped due to adverse event).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 10 weeks after last treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dose-escalation Part: Number of Treatment Emergent Adverse Events (TEAEs) and Related TEAEs by Severity</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 10 weeks after last treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dose-escalation Part: Duration of Treatment Emergent Adverse Events (TEAEs) and Related TEAEs</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 10 weeks after last treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dose-escalation Part: Number of Subjects With Dose Limiting Toxicities (DLT) - A DLT is defined as any grade greater than or equal to (&gt;=) 3 AE suspected to be related to investigational medicinal product (IMP) by the Investigator and / or Sponsor occurring in the DLT evaluation period confirmed by the Safety Monitoring Committee (SMC) to be relevant for the IMP treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Week 3</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dose-expansion Part: Best Overall Response (BOR) as Assessed by Independent Endpoint Review Committee (IRC) - BOR according to Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) Version 1.1 and as adjudicated by the Independent Endpoint Review Committee (IRC).The BOR per IRC adjudication will be determined according to RECIST 1.1 and modified immune related response criteria (irRC), respectively. BOR is defined as sum of complete response and partial response (CR+PR). For target lesions (TLs), CR was defined as the disappearance of all TLs; PR was defined as at least a 30% decrease in the sum of largest diameter (SLD) of the TLs, taking as a reference the baseline SLD. Overall immune-related complete response: Complete disappearance of all lesions (whether measurable or not) and no new lesions. All measurable lymph nodes also must have a reduction in short axis to 10 mm or less. Overall immune-related partial response (irPR): Sum of the longest diameters of target and new measurable lesions decreases &gt;= 30 percent (%).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Date of randomization up to Week 52</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dose-expansion Part: Disease Control Rate According to Response Assessment in Neuro-Oncology (RANO) as Adjudicated by the IRC for Subjects With Glioblastoma - The primary efficacy endpoint for the dose expansion part of the trial is the confirmed BOR according to RECIST 1.1 as adjudicated by the Independent Endpoint Review Committee (IRC) and will be evaluated by confirmed objective response rate (ORR). For glioblastoma, the primary endpoint will be disease control according to RANO as adjudicated by the IRC.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Week 52</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dose Escalation and Expansion Part: Maximum Concentration (Cmax) of MSB0011359C in Plasma</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, 0, 4, and 30 hours post dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dose Escalation and Expansion Part: Minimum Concentration (Cmin) of MSB0011359C in Plasma</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, 0, 4, and 30 hours post dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dose Escalation and Expansion Part: Area Under the Plasma Concentration Time Curve From Zero to Last Sampling Time (AUC0-t) of MSB0011359C</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, 0, 4, and 30 hours post dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dose Escalation and Expansion Part: Area Under the Plasma Concentration Time Curve From Time Zero to Infinity (AUC0-inf) of MSB0011359C</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, 0, 4, and 30 hours post dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dose Escalation and Expansion Part: Terminal Half Life (t1/2) of MSB0011359C</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, 0, 4, and 30 hours post dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dose Escalation and Expansion Part: Serum Titers of Anti-MSB0011359C Antibodies</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, Day 15, Day 43, Day 85 and every 6-weekly until progression or end of the treatment whichever occur first, assessed up to Week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dose Escalation and Expansion Part: Best Overall Response (BOR) as Assessed by Investigator - BOR according to Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) Version 1.1 and as adjudicated by the Investigator.The BOR per investigator adjudication will be determined according to RECIST 1.1 and modified immune related response criteria (irRC), respectively. BOR is defined as sum of complete response and partial response (CR+PR). For target lesions (TLs), CR was defined as the disappearance of all TLs; PR was defined as at least a 30% decrease in the sum of largest diameter (SLD) of the TLs, taking as a reference the baseline SLD. Overall immune-related complete response: Complete disappearance of all lesions (whether measurable or not) and no new lesions. All measurable lymph nodes also must have a reduction in short axis to 10 mm or less. Overall immune-related partial response (irPR): Sum of the longest diameters of target and new measurable lesions decreases &gt;= 30%.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Date of randomization up to Week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dose Expansion Part: Number of Subjects With Treatment Emergent Adverse Events (TEAEs) - An Adverse Event (AE) is defined as any new untoward medical occurrences/worsening of pre-existing medical condition without regard to possibility of causal relationship. A Serious Adverse Event (SAE) is an AE that resulted in any of the following outcomes: death; life threatening; persistent/significant disability/incapacity; initial or prolonged inpatient hospitalization; congenital anomaly/birth defect. AEs (SAEs and non-SAEs) will be considered TEAEs when emerging on treatment period defined as the time from the first trial drug administration up to 29 days after the last drug administration date or the earliest date of subsequent anticancer drug therapy minus 1 day, whichever occurs first, unless otherwise stated.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time from the first trial drug administration up to 10 weeks last drug administration date</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dose Expansion Part: Number of Subjects With Treatment-Related AEs - Treatment related AEs are any untoward medical occurrence in a subject who received study drug with causal relationship with the investigational product as assessed by the investigator. AEs will be assessed according to severity; mild (not causing any significant problem, dose adjustment not required), moderate (caused problem that does not interfere significantly with usual activities or the clinical status, dose adjustment needed due to adverse event) and severe (caused problem that interferes significantly with usual activities or the clinical status, study drug stopped due to adverse event).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time from the first trial drug administration up to 10 weeks after the last drug administration date</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dose Expansion Part: Number of Treatment Emergent Adverse Events (TEAEs) and Related TEAEs by Severity</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time from the first trial drug administration up to 10 weeks after the last drug administration date</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dose Expansion Part: Duration of Treatment Emergent Adverse Events (TEAEs) and Related TEAEs</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time from the first trial drug administration up to 10 weeks after the last drug administration date</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Ability to understand the purpose of the study, provide signed and dated informed
             consent, and able to comply with all procedures

          -  Male or female subjects aged greater than or equal to (&gt;=) 18 years

          -  Life expectancy &gt;= 12 weeks as judged by the Investigator

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 to 1 at trial entry

          -  Disease must be measurable with at least 1 uni dimensional measurable lesion by
             Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) version 1.1.

          -  Adequate hematological, hepatic and renal function as defined in the protocol

          -  Effective contraception for both male and female subjects if the risk of conception
             exists

        Other protocol-defined inclusion criteria could apply.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Concurrent treatment with non-permitted drugs and other interventions

          -  Anticancer treatment within 28 days before the start of trial treatment, for example
             cyto reductive therapy, radiotherapy (with the exception of palliative radiotherapy
             delivered in a normal organ-spearing technique), immune therapy, or cytokine therapy

          -  Major surgery within 28 days before the start of trial treatment (prior diagnostic
             biopsy is permitted)

          -  Systemic therapy with immunosuppressive agents within 7 days before the start of trial
             treatment; or use of any investigational drug within 28 days before the start of trial
             treatment

          -  Previous malignant disease (other than the target malignancy to be investigated in
             this trial) within the last 3 years. Subjects with history of cervical carcinoma in
             situ, superficial or non invasive bladder cancer or basal cell or squamous cell cancer
             in situ previously treated with curative intent are NOT excluded. Subjects with other
             localized malignancies treated with curative intent need to be discussed with the
             Medical Monitor.

          -  Rapidly progressive disease which, in the opinion of the Investigator, may predispose
             to inability to tolerate treatment or trial procedures

          -  Subjects with active central nervous system (CNS) metastases causing clinical symptoms
             or metastases that require therapeutic intervention are excluded

          -  Receipt of any organ transplantation, including allogeneic stem-cell transplantation,
             but with the exception of transplants that do not require immunosuppression (eg,
             corneal transplant, hair transplant)

        Other protocol-defined exclusion criteria could apply</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>31/08/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>702</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>12/12/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,SA,VIC,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Blacktown Hospital - Blacktown</hospital>
    <hospital>Chris O'Brien Lifehouse - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>St George Hospital - Kogarah</hospital>
    <hospital>Liverpool Hospital - Liverpool</hospital>
    <hospital>Port Macquarie Base Hospital - Port Macquarie</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal North Shore Hospital - St Leonards</hospital>
    <hospital>Calvary Mater Newcastle - Waratah</hospital>
    <hospital>Greenslopes Private Hospital - Greenslopes</hospital>
    <hospital>Tasman Oncology Research Ltd - Southport</hospital>
    <hospital>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital - Woodville South</hospital>
    <hospital>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre-East Melbourne - East Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Cabrini Hospital Malvern - Malvern</hospital>
    <hospital>Border Medical Oncology Research Unit - Wodonga</hospital>
    <hospital>Fiona Stanley Hospital - Murdoch</hospital>
    <hospital>Linear Clinical Research Limited - Nedlands</hospital>
    <postcode>2148 - Blacktown</postcode>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>2217 - Kogarah</postcode>
    <postcode>2170 - Liverpool</postcode>
    <postcode>2444 - Port Macquarie</postcode>
    <postcode>2065 - St Leonards</postcode>
    <postcode>2298 - Waratah</postcode>
    <postcode>4120 - Greenslopes</postcode>
    <postcode>4216 - Southport</postcode>
    <postcode>5011 - Woodville South</postcode>
    <postcode>3002 - East Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3144 - Malvern</postcode>
    <postcode>3690 - Wodonga</postcode>
    <postcode>6150 - Murdoch</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Arizona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Colorado</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Connecticut</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Georgia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Illinois</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Kansas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Louisiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Maryland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Massachusetts</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Michigan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Missouri</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Nevada</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Hampshire</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Pennsylvania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Rhode Island</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>South Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Tennessee</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Virginia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Washington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Bruxelles</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Charleroi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Edegem</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Gent</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Libramont</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Liège</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Wilrijk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Alberta</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Alpes Maritimes</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Bas Rhin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Bouches-du-Rhône</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Côte-d'Or</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Gironde</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Haute Garonne</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Isere</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Loire Atlantique</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Nord</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Paris</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Rhone</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Val de Marne</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Montpellier</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Baden Wuerttemberg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Hessen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Niedersachsen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Nordrhein Westfalen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Saarland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Sachsen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Berlin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Milano</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Torino</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Benevento</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Bologna</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Napoli</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Pavia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Pisa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Roma</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Siena</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Chiba-Ken</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Osaka-Fu</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Chungcheongbuk-do</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Gyeonggi-do</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Busan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Seoul</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Badajoz</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Sevilla</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Valencia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Kaohsiung</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Taipei</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Greater London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Greater Manchester</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Hampshire</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Strathclyde</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Tyne &amp; Wear</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>West Midlands</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>EMD Serono Research &amp; Development Institute, Inc.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Merck KGaA</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The main purpose of this Phase I study is to test MSB0011359C (M7824) at different dose
      levels to see if it is safe and well tolerated when given once every 2 weeks. Phase I means
      the study drug has not previously been given to humans or has only been given to a limited
      number of people, although it has been extensively studied in animals. Based on this
      information, it is hoped to find out which dose could be best for the treatment of patients.
      There are two parts of this research study: a dose-escalation part and an expansion part.
      Dose escalation means that the first people taking part in the study will receive low doses
      of the study drug, and as more people take part, the additional participants will receive a
      higher dose. This is done to find the safest dose for the study drug. Expansion means that
      after the dose-escalation part of the study has looked at the safety and effectiveness of
      different doses, many more people will be invited to take part in the study and will receive
      the study drug at the safest dose. Additional purposes of the study are to find out whether
      the study drug has anti-cancer effects and how the study drug is processed by the body.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02517398</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Medical Responsible</name>
      <address>EMD Serono Research &amp; Development Institute, Inc, an affiliate of MerckKGaA, Darmstadt, Germany</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>US Medical Information</name>
      <address />
      <phone>888-275-7376</phone>
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>