<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6396">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/12/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/12/2016</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT03001700</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>PRospective Study for the TrEatment of Atherosclerotic Lesions in the Superficial Femoral and/or Popliteal Arteries Using the Serranator DevicE</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>PRospective Study for the TrEatment of Atherosclerotic Lesions in the Superficial Femoral and/or Popliteal Arteries Using the Serranator DevicE: PRELUDE Study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>PRELUDE</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>CSP-0109</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Peripheral Arterial Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - Serranator Alto PTA Serration Balloon Catheter

Experimental: Treatment - Subjects will be treated with the Serranator Alto PTA Serration Balloon Catheter device


Treatment: devices: Serranator Alto PTA Serration Balloon Catheter
The Serranator is an over-the-wire (OTW) balloon dilatation catheter designed to perform percutaneous transluminal angioplasty (PTA) for peripheral indications.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the technical feasibility of using the Serranator Alto PTA Serration Balloon Catheter during the endovascular treatment of critical SFA or popliteal artery lesions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Through Study Completion, approximately 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>OCT and/or IVUS imaging post use of the Serranator to document evidence of vessel wall serrations in a sub-set of up to 10 subjects.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Through Study Completion, approximately 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Male or female of &gt;18 years old.

          2. Women of child bearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test within 7 days of
             index procedure.

          3. Subject or subject's legal representative has been informed of the nature of the
             study, agrees to participate and comply with all follow-up visits and has signed the
             consent form.

          4. Resting ABI -&lt; 0.9.

          5. Subject is eligible for standard surgical repair in target limb if necessary.

          6. Subject has Rutherford Clinical Category 2,3, or 4

          7. Estimated life expectancy &gt; 1 year.

        Angiographic 

          1. Lesion(s) located within the SFA and or popliteal arteries.

          2. Target lesion(s) has stenosis &gt;70% by visual assessment.

          3. Reference vessel diameter is between 4.0mm and 6.0mm, inclusive.

          4. One long or multiple serial lesions that are up to 10 cms, (total occlusions up to
             6cm) in length that can be covered by a single balloon.

          5. De-novo, or non-stented re-stenotic lesions

          6. At least one below the knee artery patent to the ankle.

          7. Successful treatment of iliac inflow stenosis to the target limb. Stenosis can be
             treated during the same procedure using standard angioplasty and or stenting but use
             of atherectomy is excluded. The inflow lesion(s) must be treated first, prior to
             consideration of treatment of the target lesion. Subject can be enrolled if the inflow
             lesion(s) are treated and results in &lt;30% residual stenosis and no evidence of
             embolization or significant complications.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Rutherford Clinical Category 1, 5 or 6.

          2. Previously implanted ipsilateral femoral or popliteal stent.

          3. Evidence of aneurysm or acute thrombus in the target vessel.

          4. Subjects with previous bypass surgery in lower target extremity.

          5. Planned major amputation (above the ankle) of either limb.

          6. Subject has significant stenosis or occlusion of inflow tract not successfully treated
             (&gt;30% residual stenosis and/or significant complication of the procedure).

          7. History of any open surgical procedure within the past 30 days.

          8. Planned endovascular or vascular surgery procedure within 14 days prior to the ATK
             procedure, except to treat the inflow vessels on the day of the procedure, or within
             the next 30 days after the ATK procedure on the target limb.

          9. Subject has an allergy to contrast medium that cannot be pretreated.

         10. Episode of acute limb ischemia within past 30 days.

         11. Subject has systemic infection with positive blood cultures/ bacteremia within one
             week.

         12. Subject has a hypercoagulable disorder

         13. Subject in whom antiplatelet, anticoagulant, or thrombolytic therapy is
             contraindicated.

         14. Myocardial infarction within 30 days prior to enrollment.

         15. History of stroke or TIA within 90 days prior to enrollment.

         16. Subject has acute or chronic renal disease (e.g., as measured by a serum creatinine of
             &gt;2.5 mg/dL or &gt;220 umol/L).

         17. Subject is pregnant or breastfeeding.

         18. Subject is participating in another research study of a device, medication, which
             could, in the opinion of the investigator, affect the results of this study.

         19. Subject has other medical, social or psychological problems that in the opinion of the
             investigator would preclude them from receiving this treatment and the procedures and
             or participating in evaluations pre- and post-treatment.

         20. Thrombolysis of the target vessel within 72 hours prior to the index procedure, where
             complete resolution of the thrombus was not achieved.

         21. Known allergies to both antiplatelet agents, aspirin, or heparin.

         22. History of neutropenia, coagulopathy, or thrombocytopenia that was unexplained or is
             considered to be at risk for reoccurrence.

         23. Platelet count less than 80,000/µL,

         24. Subject requires general anesthesia for the procedure.

         25. Subject requires dialysis.

        Angiographic 

          1. Chronic Total Occlusions (CTO) &gt; 6cm in length

          2. Acute Total Occlusions; evidence of acute thrombus formation by angiography

          3. Severe calcification of target lesion described as circumferential calcium and &gt;50% of
             lesion length.

          4. Sub-intimal access required

          5. Inability to cross the lesion with a guidewire

          6. Atherectomy in the target lesion, target artery or for inflow treatment</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/02/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>25</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/12/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Austria</country>
      <state>Graz</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Grafton</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Chrzanow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Krakow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Cagent Vascular LLC</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To assess preliminary safety and efficacy of the Serranator Alto PTA Serration Balloon
      Catheter in subjects with atherosclerotic peripheral artery disease of the superficial
      femoral and popliteal arteries.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03001700</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>