<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6076">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/04/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/04/2016</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02747342</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Phase 1 Trial of SHR3680 in Prostate Cancer as Monotherapy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 1 Trial of SHR3680 in Subjects With Metastatic Castration-Resistant Prostate Cancer as Monotherapy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>SHR3680-002</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Neoplasm</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Prostate Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Prostate</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - SHR3680

Experimental: SHR3680 - SHR3680 will be administered orally at the starting dose of 40 mg/day.


Treatment: drugs: SHR3680
SHR3680 will be administered orally at the starting dose of 40 mg/day.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximum tolerated dose (MTD) - MTD is defined as the maximum dose level at which no more than 1 out of 3 participants experience a DLT within the first 4 weeks of multiple dosing</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of participants with treatment-emergent adverse events</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Peak plasma concentration (Cmax)</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve (AUC)</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>T1/2 (half-life)</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of participants reaching at least a 50% reduction in prostate specific antigen (PSA) at Week 12 as compared to baseline</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to PSA progression</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Objective response rate (ORR)</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Radiological progression-free survival (PFS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Male 18 years or older.

          2. Ability to understand the purposes and risks of the trial and his signed informed
             consent form approved (ICF) by the Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC) of the trial
             site and obtained before entering the trial

          3. Histologically or cytologically confirmed adenocarcinoma of the prostate without
             neuroendocrine differentiation or small cell features.

          4. For patients who have not had an orchiectomy, there must be a plan to maintain
             effective GnRH-analogue therapy for the duration of the trial.

          5. Serum testosterone level &lt;1.7 nmol/L (50 ng/dL) at the screening visit.

          6. Ongoing androgen deprivation therapy with a gonadotropin releasing hormone (GnRH)
             analogue or orchiectomy (i.e., surgical or medical castration).

          7. Progressive disease by PSA or imaging after docetaxel-based chemotherapy in the
             setting of medical or surgical castration. Prior enzalutamide is allowed as long as
             patients had a PSA response &gt;50% or were treated for at least 6 months. Disease
             progression for study entry is defined as one or more of the following 3 criteria:

               -  PSA progression defined by a minimum of three rising PSA levels with an interval
                  of =1 week between each determination. The PSA value at the Screening visit
                  should be =2 ng/mL.

               -  Soft tissue disease progression defined by RECIST.

               -  Bone disease progression defined by two or more new lesions on bone scan

          8. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 or 1.

          9. Life expectancy of at least 6 months.

         10. Able to swallow the study drug and comply with the study requirements.

         11. Acceptable liver function defined below:

               -  Total bilirubin =1.5 times upper limit of normal (ULN)

               -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) =2 times ULN;
                  however, =5 times ULN in a participant who has liver metastases or treated with
                  biliary drainage.

         12. Acceptable renal function: serum creatinine =1.5 times ULN.

         13. Acceptable hematologic status (without hematologic support including hematopoietic
             factor, blood transfusion) defined below:

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) =1500/µL

               -  Platelet count =100,000/µL

               -  Hemoglobin =9.0 dL</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Male</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Treatment with androgen receptor antagonists (enzalutamide, bicalutamide, flutamide,
             nilutamide), 5-alpha reductase inhibitors (finasteride, dutasteride), estrogens, or
             chemotherapy within 4 weeks of enrollment (Day 1 visit) or plans to initiate treatment
             with any of these drugs during the study. Ongoing therapy with biphosphonates or Rank
             Ligand inhibitors are acceptable.

          2. Treatment with therapeutic immunizations for prostate cancer (e.g.,PROVENGE®) or plans
             to initiate treatment with any of these treatments during the study.

          3. Metastases in the brain or active epidural disease (Note: patients with treated
             epidural disease are allowed).

          4. Use of herbal products that may PSA levels (e.g., saw palmetto) or systemic
             corticosteroids greater than the equivalent of 10 mg of prednisone/prednisolone per
             day within 4 weeks of enrollment (day 1 visit) or plans to initiate treatment with any
             of these therapies during the study.

          5. History of another malignancy within the previous 5 years other than curatively
             treated non-melanomatous skin cancer.

          6. Radiation therapy within 3 weeks (if single fraction of radiotherapy within 2 weeks)
             and radionuclide therapy within 8 weeks of enrollment (Day 1 visit).

          7. Have used or plan to use from 30 days prior to enrollment (day 1 visit) through to the
             end of the study medications known to lower the seizure threshold or prolong the QT
             interval.

          8. Cardiac disease with New York Heart Association (NYHA) Class III or IV, including
             congestive heart failure, myocardial infarction within 6 months prior to the trial
             entry, unstable arrhythmia, or symptomatic peripheral arterial vascular disease.

          9. Severe concurrent disease, infection, or co-morbidity that, in the judgment of the
             investigator, would make the patient inappropriate for enrollment.

         10. History of seizure, including any febrile seizure, loss of consciousness, or transient
             ischemic attack within 12 months of enrollment (Day 1 visit), or any condition that
             may pre-dispose to seizure.

         11. Use of an investigational agent within 4 weeks of enrollment or plans to initiate
             treatment with an investigational agent during the study.

         12. Major surgery, other than diagnostic surgery, within 4 weeks prior to trial entry,
             without complete recovery.

         13. Gastrointestinal disorder affecting absorption.

         14. Structurally unstable bone lesions suggesting impending fracture.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/09/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>42</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/09/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Chris O'Brien Lifehouse - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>St George Hospital - Kogarah</hospital>
    <hospital>Liverpool Hospital - Liverpool</hospital>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>2217 - Kogarah</postcode>
    <postcode>2170 - Liverpool</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Atridia Pty Ltd.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a multicenter, dose-escalation phase 1 trial to evaluate the safety and tolerability
      of SHR3680 given orally to subjects with metastatic castration-resistant prostate cancer
      (mCRPC) as monotherapy.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02747342</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kathy You, MD, PhD</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+61 02 9299 0433</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kathyyou@atridia.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>