<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6691">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/09/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/09/2016</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02931539</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy and Safety of Maribavir in Transplant Recipients With Cytomegalovirus (CMV) Infections That Are Refractory or Resistant to Treatment</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 3, Multicenter, Randomized, Open-label, Active-controlled Study to Assess the Efficacy and Safety of Maribavir Treatment Compared to Investigator-assigned Treatment in Transplant Recipients With Cytomegalovirus (CMV) Infections That Are Refractory or Resistant to Treatment With Ganciclovir, Valganciclovir, Foscarnet, or Cidofovir</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>2015-004725-13</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>SHP620-303</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cytomegalovirus (CMV)</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Maribavir
Treatment: drugs - Investigator-Assigned Treatment

Experimental: Maribavir Treatment - Two 200mg tablets taken by mouth twice daily

Active Comparator: Investigator-Assigned Treatment - anti-CMV agent best suited to treat the respective subject. agents of choice include: ganciclovir, valganciclovir, foscarnet, or cidofovir


Treatment: drugs: Maribavir
Maribavir 2X200 mg two times per day

Treatment: drugs: Investigator-Assigned Treatment
Active Comparator: anti-CMV agent

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To Compare the Efficacy of Maribavir to Investigator-assigned Anti-CMV Therapy in CMV Viremia Clearance at the End of Study Week 8, in Transplant Recipients Who are Refractory or Resistant to Prior Anti-CMV Treatment - Viremia clearance will be defined as plasma CMV DNA concentration below the lower limit of quantification less than (&lt;) LLOQ; that is (i.e), &lt;137 International Units per millilitre (IU/mL) when assessed by COBAS® AmpliPrep/COBAS® TaqMan® CMV Test at a central specialty laboratory, in 2 consecutive postbaseline samples, separated by at least 5 days, regardless of whether either study-assigned treatment was discontinued before the end of the stipulated 8 weeks of therapy. The difference in proportion of subjects with confirmed CMV viremia clearance, at the end of Study Week 8, between treatment groups (maribavir and investigator's choice of anti CMV treatment) will be obtained using Cochran-Mantel-Haenszel (CMH) weighted average across all strata, and analyzed using CMH test with transplant type and baseline plasma CMV DNA concentration as 2 stratification factors.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 8</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To Compare the Efficacy of Two Study Treatment Arms on CMV Viremia Clearance and Tissue-invasive CMV Disease Improvement or Resolution at the End of Week 8, and Week 16 - Viremia clearance will be defined as plasma CMV DNA concentration below the lower limit of quantification (&lt;LLOQ; i.e &lt;137 IU/mL when assessed by COBAS® AmpliPrep/COBAS® TaqMan® CMV Test at a central specialty laboratory, in 2 consecutive postbaseline samples, separated by at least 5 days. Tissue invasive CMV disease will be defined as described by Ljungman et al. (2002 and 2016) The gold standard for diagnosing CMV tissue invasive disease is the identification of CMV inclusions in the infected cells of the tissues or identification of CMV in biopsy tissue samples. Achievement of CMV viremia clearance and resolution or improvement of tissue-invasive CMV disease for subjects symptomatic at baseline or achievement of clearance of viremia and no symptoms of tissue invasive CMV disease for subjects asymptomatic at baseline at the end of Study Week 8, followed by maintenance of this treatment effect (Follow-up Week 16).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 8, Week 16</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To Compare the Efficacy of Maribavir to Investigator-assigned Anti-CMV Therapy on CMV Viremia Clearance After Completion of 8 Weeks of Study Treatment in Transplant Recipients Who are Refractory or Resistant to Prior Anti-CMV Treatment - Viremia clearance will be defined as plasma CMV DNA concentration below the lower limit of quantification (&lt;LLOQ; i.e &lt;137 IU/mL when assessed by COBAS® AmpliPrep/COBAS® TaqMan® CMV Test at a central specialty laboratory, in 2 consecutive postbaseline samples, separated by at least 5 days.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 8</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To Compare the Efficacy of Two Study Treatment Arms on CMV Viremia Clearance and Tissue-Invasive CMV Disease Improvement or Resolution after Completion of 8 Weeks Through Weeks 12, 16 and 20 - Viremia clearance will be defined as plasma CMV DNA concentration below the lower limit of quantification (&lt;LLOQ; i.e &lt;137 IU/mL when assessed by COBAS® AmpliPrep/COBAS® TaqMan® CMV Test at a central specialty laboratory, in 2 consecutive postbaseline samples, separated by at least 5 days. Tissue invasive CMV disease will be defined as described by Ljungman et al. (2002 and 2016) The gold standard for diagnosing CMV tissue invasive disease is the identification of CMV inclusions in the infected cells of the tissues OR identification of CMV in biopsy tissue samples. The achievement of the confirmed CMV viremia clearance and resolution or improvement of tissue invasive CMV disease for subjects symptomatic at baseline or achievement of clearance of viremia and no symptoms of tissue invasive CMV disease for subjects asymptomatic at baseline after receiving 8 weeks of study-assigned treatment, followed by maintenance of this treatment effect through study weeks 12, week 16 and week 20.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 8, Week 12, Week 16, Week 20</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of Two Study Treatment for Maintenance of CMV Viremia Clearance and Resolution or Improvement of Tissue Invasive CMV Disease - Viremia clearance will be defined as plasma CMV DNA concentration below the lower limit of quantification (&lt;LLOQ; i.e &lt;137 IU/mL when assessed by COBAS® AmpliPrep/COBAS® TaqMan® CMV Test at a central specialty laboratory, in 2 consecutive postbaseline samples, separated by at least 5 days. Tissue invasive CMV disease will be defined as described by Ljungman et al. (2002 and 2016) The gold standard for diagnosing CMV tissue invasive disease is the identification of CMV inclusions in the infected cells of the tissues OR identification of CMV in biopsy tissue samples. Maintenance of CMV viremia clearance and resolution or improvement of tissue invasive CMV disease will be analyzed at 12, 16 and 20 weeks post-treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 8, Week 12, Week 20</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Subjects With Incidence of Recurrence of CMV Viremia in Two Study Treatment Arms During the Study - Recurrence of CMV viremia is defined as the presence of signs or symptoms of the tissue invasive CMV disease (same or new symptomatology) confirmed as per Ljungman et al. (2016), after the period of resolution of the disease in subjects symptomatic at baseline.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout 8 Weeks to 12 Weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Subjects With incidence of Recurrence of CMV Viremia in Two Study Treatment Arms When Subjects are On Treatment and Off Treatment - Recurrence of CMV viremia is defined as the presence of signs or symptoms of the tissue invasive CMV disease (same or new symptomatology) confirmed as per Ljungman et al. (2016), after the period of resolution of the disease in subjects symptomatic at baseline. Incidence of recurrence of CMV viremia is evaluated in the two study treatment arms when subjects are on and off treatment</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 8 to Week 20</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Profile of Mutations in the CMV Genes Conferring Resistance to Maribavir - Specific mutations in the UL97 and/or UL54 human cytomegalovirus (HCMV) genes are associated with resistance to certain anti-CMV drugs.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0 to week 20</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With All-cause Mortality - Mortality was assessed by the number of subjects who died between week 0 to week 20. A summary of death details was given which included whether the participant died between week 0 to week 20, whether the death was related sepsis, cause of death, the source of the information, and whether the cause of death was verified by a death record. Number of subjects who died at the end of the study and the corresponding 95% confidence intervals (CIs) will be calculated.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0 to week 20</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess the Efficacy of Maribavir Administered as the Rescue Treatment on CMV Viremia Clearance as Measured by Plasma CMV DNA Concentration, at the End of the Study Treatment Period - Viremia clearance will be defined as plasma CMV DNA concentration below the lower limit of quantification (&lt;LLOQ; i.e &lt;137 IU/mL when assessed by COBAS® AmpliPrep/COBAS® TaqMan® CMV Test at a central specialty laboratory, in 2 consecutive postbaseline samples, separated by at least 5 days.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout 8 weeks from the entry into maribavir rescue arm</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>CMV Viremia Clearance, Resolution/Improvement of Tissue Invasive CMV Disease if Present at Baseline and no New Onset of Disease in Patients Asymptomatic at Baseline, at the End of the Study Treatment and the Follow up in Maribavir Rescue Arm - Viremia clearance will be defined as plasma CMV DNA concentration below the lower limit of quantification (&lt;LLOQ; i.e &lt;137 IU/mL when assessed by COBAS® AmpliPrep/COBAS® TaqMan® CMV Test at a central specialty laboratory, in 2 consecutive postbaseline samples, separated by at least 5 days. Tissue invasive CMV disease will be defined as described by Ljungman et al. (2002 and 2016) The gold standard for diagnosing CMV tissue invasive disease is the identification of CMV inclusions in the infected cells of the tissues OR identification of CMV in biopsy tissue samples.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout 8 weeks from the entry into maribavir rescue arm to 8 weeks of follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects with Overall Study Adverse Events (AEs), Overall Study Serious Adverse Events (SAEs), and Treatment-emergent Adverse Events (TEAEs) and Treatment-emergent Serious Adverse Events (TESAEs) - An AE was any untoward medical occurrence in a participant who received study drug without regard to possibility of causal relationship. An SAE was an AE resulting in any of the following outcomes or deemed significant for any other reason: death; initial or prolonged inpatient hospitalization; life-threatening experience (immediate risk of dying); persistent or significant disability/incapacity; congenital anomaly. TEAEs were defined as AEs/SAEs observed during the on treatment observation period occurring within 7 days after the end of the study treatment will be considered treatment-emergent.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0 to within 7 days After the End of Study Treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetics (PK) of Maribavir Based on Sparse Sampling as Measured by Area Under The Curve (AUC) - Maribavir PK will be analyzed for all subjects with maribavir plasma concentration results. The AUC reflects the actual body exposure to drug after administration of a dose of the drug.This area under the curve is dependant on the rate of elimination of the drug from the body and the dose administered.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 1 to week 8</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from Baseline in Vital Signs - Vital signs include body temperature, arterial blood pressure, and pulse.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0 to week 20</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from Baseline in Clinical Laboratory Tests - Clinical laboratory tests include hematology, chemistry, urinalysis, HBV, HCV, pregnancy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0 to week 20</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Abnormal Findings for Physical Examination - Physical examinations include body weight and height.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0 to week 20</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from Baseline in Electrocardiogram (ECG) Assessment - Twelve -lead ECGs will be performed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0 to week 20</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects That Require Treatment With Hemopoietic Growth Factors - Change from baseline in the number of subjects that require treatment with hemopoietic growth factors are analyzed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0 to week 20</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects That Require Treatment With Blood or Blood Products - Change in the number of subjects from baseline that require treatment with blood or blood products are analyzed</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0 to week 20</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects That Require Treatment With Invasive Bacterial And Fungal Infections - Incidence of invasive bacterial and fungal infections for each treatment group for on treatment period and overall-study period will be provided.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0 to week 20</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. The subject must be able to provide written, personally signed, and dated informed
             consent to participate in the study before completing any study-related procedures. As
             applicable, a parent/both parents or legally authorized representative (LAR) must
             provide signature of informed consent and there must be documentation of assent by the
             subject before completing any study-related procedures.

          2. The subject must be a recipient of hematopoietic stem cell or solid organ transplant.

          3. The subject must have a documented CMV infection greater than or equal to = 910 IU/ml
             in blood or plasma samples, from two consecutive assessments separated by at least one
             day, taken within 14 days prior to randomization with second sample obtained within 5
             days prior to randomization.

          4. The subject must have a current CMV infection refractory or resistant to treatment.
             Refractory is defined as failure to have greater than (&gt;)1 log10 decrease in CMV viral
             load within minimum of 2 weeks of treatment with ganciclovir, valganciclovir,
             foscarnet or cidofovir .

          5. The Investigator must be willing to treat the subject with at least one of the
             available anti-CMV drugs (ganciclovir, valganciclovir, foscarnet, or cidofovir). Note:
             Combination therapy with foscarnet and cidofovir is not permitted in the
             investigator-assigned anti-CMV treatment (IAT) arm due to the potential for serious
             nephrotoxicity.

          6. The subject must be =12 years of age at the time of consent

          7. The subject must weigh =35 kilogram (kg).

          8. The subject must have all of the following results as part of screening laboratory
             assessments (results from either the central laboratory or a local laboratory can be
             used for qualification):

               1. Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) = 1000/ millimeter cube (mm^3) [1.0 x 109^9/L]

               2. Platelet count = 25,000/mm^3 [25 x 10^9/L],

               3. Hemoglobin = 8 gram per deciliter (g/dL).

               4. Estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) &gt;30 (milliliter per minute (mL/min)
                  /1.73 meter square (m^2) as assessed by Modification of Diet in Renal Disease
                  (MDRD) formula for subjects =18 years of age or Schwartz formula for subjects
                  less than (&lt;)18 years of age.

          9. The subject must have a negative pregnancy test at screening, if a female of child
             bearing potential. Additional urine pregnancy tests may be done per institutional
             requirements. Sexually active females of child bearing potential must agree to comply
             with any applicable contraceptive requirements of the protocol. If male, must agree to
             use an acceptable method of birth control, as defined in the protocol, during the
             study treatment administration period and for 90 days afterward if treated with
             maribavir, ganciclovir, valganciclovir, or cidofovir and for 180 days afterward if
             treated with foscarnet.

         10. The subject must be able to swallow tablets, or receive tablets crushed and/or
             dispensed in water via nasogastric or orogastric tube.

         11. The subject must be willing and have an understanding and ability to fully comply with
             study procedures and restrictions defined in the protocol.

         12. The subject must be willing to provide necessary samples (example [e.g,] biopsy) for
             the diagnosis of tissue invasive CMV disease at baseline as determined by the
             Investigator.

         13. The subject must have a life expectancy of = 8 weeks.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>12</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Have a current CMV infection that is considered refractory or resistant due to
             inadequate adherence to prior anti-CMV treatment, to the best knowledge of the
             Investigator.

          2. Require ganciclovir, valganciclovir, foscarnet, or cidofovir administration for
             conditions other than CMV when study treatment is initiated NOTE: A subject who is not
             continuing with the same anti-CMV drug(s) (ganciclovir, valganciclovir or foscarnet)
             for the study must discontinue their use before the first dose of study drug. If
             subject is currently receiving cidofovir and is assigned another anti-CMV agent by the
             investigator the subject must discontinue its use at least 14 days prior to
             randomization at Visit 2/Day 0 and the first dose of study treatment.

          3. Be receiving leflunomide, or artesunate when study treatment is initiated. NOTE:
             Subjects who may be receiving leflunomide must discontinue the use at least 14 days
             prior to randomization at Visit 2/Day 0 and the first dose of study treatment.
             Subjects receiving artesunate must discontinue the use prior to the first dose of
             study treatment.

          4. Have severe vomiting, diarrhea, or other severe gastrointestinal illness within 24
             hours prior to the first dose of study treatment that would preclude administration of
             oral/enteral medication.

          5. Have known hypersensitivity to the active substance or to an excipient for a study
             treatment.

          6. Have tissue invasive CMV disease with central nervous system involvement.

          7. Have serum aspartate aminotransferase (AST) &gt;5 times upper limit of normal (ULN) at
             screening, or serum alanine aminotransferase (ALT) &gt;5 times ULN at screening, or total
             bilirubin =3.0 x ULN at screening (except for documented Gilbert's syndrome), by local
             or central lab. Subjects with CMV hepatitis will not be excluded despite having &gt;5
             times ULN at screening.

          8. Have known (previously documented) positive results for human immunodeficiency virus
             (HIV).

          9. Require mechanical ventilation or vasopressors for hemodynamic support at the time of
             enrollment.

         10. Be female and pregnant or breast feeding

         11. Have previously received maribavir.

         12. Have received any investigational agent with known anti-CMV activity within 30 days
             before initiation of study treatment or investigational CMV vaccine at any time.

         13. Have received any unapproved agent or device within 30 days before initiation of study
             treatment.

         14. Have active malignancy with the exception of nonmelanoma skin cancer. Subjects who
             have had a hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HSCT) and who experience relapse or
             progression of the malignancy as per investigator's opinion are not to be enrolled.

         15. Be undergoing treatment for acute or chronic hepatitis C.

         16. Have any clinically significant medical or surgical condition that, in the
             Investigator's opinion, could interfere with the interpretation of study results,
             contraindicate the administration of the assigned study treatment, or compromise the
             safety or well-being of the subject.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/12/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>351</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/05/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Westmead Hospital - Westmead</hospital>
    <hospital>The Alfred Hospital - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Brisbane</hospital>
    <postcode>2145 - Westmead</postcode>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3050 - Parkville</postcode>
    <postcode>4102 - Brisbane</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Alabama</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Illinois</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Louisiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Maryland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Massachusetts</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Michigan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Minnesota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Nebraska</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Pennsylvania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>South Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Utah</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Washington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Antwerpen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Vlaams Brabant</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>West-Vlaanderen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Brussels</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Bruxelles</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Ghent</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Haute-Garonne</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Hauts-de-Seine</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Ille-et-Vilaine</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Indre-et-Loire</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Loire-Atlantique</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Rhône</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Somme</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Val-de-Marne</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Amiens Cedex 1</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Clermont-Ferrand</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Lille Cedex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Limoges</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Paris</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Poitiers</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>STRASBOURG Cedex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Strasbourg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Lombardia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Roma</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Singapore</country>
      <state>Singapore</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barakaldo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Salamanca</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Valencia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Birmingham</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Glasgow City</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Manchester</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Yorkshire</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Liverpool</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Oxford</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Shire</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to determine if an investigational treatment (Maribavir) is safe
      and effective in treating transplant recipient patients with cytomegalovirus (CMV) infections
      that are refractory or resistant to treatment.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02931539</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Shire Physician</name>
      <address>Shire</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Shire Contact, 866-842-5335</name>
      <address />
      <phone>ClinicalTransparency@shire.com</phone>
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>