<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5142">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/07/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/07/2015</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02543086</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effectiveness of KAE609 in Reducing Asexual &amp; Sexual Blood-stage P.Falciparum Infection &amp; Infectivity to Mosquitos</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase1 Interventional Sequential Single Site Study to Characterize the Effectiveness of Oral KAE609 in Reducing Asexual &amp; Sexual Blood-stage P. Falciparum Following Inoculation in Healthy-volunteers &amp; Subsequent Infectivity to Mosquitoes</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>CKAE609A2109</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Plasmodium Falciparum Malaria</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - KAE609
Treatment: drugs - Piperaquine Phosphate

Experimental: Multiple Sequential Cohort - This study is divided in 2 parts (Part A and part B). Each participant in each of the cohorts will be inoculated with viable parasites of Plasmodium falciparum-infected human erythrocytes administered intravenously. For Part A &amp; Part B, commencement of treatment will be determined by Quantitative-Polymerase Chain Reaction results.
The First cohort of Part A (A1) will be dosed with a single dose of KAE609. During Part A, an additional second single-dose of KAE609 may be tested (~15 days after first dose of KAE609 but may vary) if sexual parasitemia is identified. Subsequent cohorts of part A (An) will be dosed based on the results of first cohort (A1).
Subjects enrolled in Cohort B will receive a pre-treatment with Piperaquine followed by KAE609 (~15 days).


Treatment: drugs: KAE609
Study drug

Treatment: drugs: Piperaquine Phosphate
Pre-administration of Piperaquine Phosphate will be done to eliminate the asexual form of the parasite and induce gametocytaemia before characterizing the activity of KAE609 in clearing sexual blood stage parasites from the blood of healthy subjects in the Induced Blood Stage Malaria Challenge model in Part B of study

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parasitic count in blood by Polymerase Chain Reaction - Clearance of Plasmodium falciparum asexual and sexual blood stage parasites from the blood of healthy subjects in the Induced Blood Stage Malaria Challenge model</outcome>
      <timepoint>36 days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma Pharmacokinetics (PK) of KAE609: Area Under the Plasma Concentration-time Curve (AUC) - It will be measured by Area Under the Concentration-Time Curve (AUC) from the time of dosing to the last quantifiable concentration</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1: 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 8, 12, 16 hours, then 24, 36, 48, 72, 96 and 120 hours post dose Days 2 to 6, Day 15 0, 12 hours post dose then 24, 48, 72, 96 and 120 hours post dose Day 16 to Day 20</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and Tolerability as measured by adverse events (including serious) for incidence, KAE609 (and inoculum) relatedness and severity - Adverse events (including serious) will be recorded during the study and will be rated according to incidence, relation to study drug (inoculum) and severity</outcome>
      <timepoint>From day of screening until end of study (day 36)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Written informed consent must be obtained before any assessment is performed.

          2. Male and females participants between 18 and 55 years of age. Female participants
             between 18 and 55 years of age have to be of non-child bearing potential.

          3. Body weight, minimum 50.0 kg, body mass index (BMI) between 18.0 and 32.0 kg/m2,
             inclusive.

          4. Certified as healthy by a comprehensive clinical assessment.

          5. Normal standard 12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG).

          6. Laboratory parameters within the normal range.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Any history of malaria or participation to a previous malaria challenge study

          2. Spent more than four weeks in a malaria-endemic country during the past 12 months or
             planned travel to a malaria endemic area during the course of the study

          3. Has evidence of increased cardiovascular disease risk

          4. History of splenectomy

          5. Presence or history of drug hypersensitivity, or allergic disease diagnosed

          6. Presence of current or suspected serious chronic diseases

          7. History of malignancy of any organ system

          8. Presence of acute infectious disease or fever (e.g., sub-lingual temperature

               -  38.5°C) within the five days prior to inoculation with malaria parasites.

          9. Participation in any investigational product study within the 12 weeks preceding the
             study.

         10. Participant who has ever received a blood transfusion.

         11. History or presence of alcohol abuse

         12. Any vaccination within the last 28 days.

         13. Any corticosteroids, anti-inflammatory drugs, immunomodulators or anticoagulants.

         14. Any recent (&lt; 1 month) or current systemic therapy with an antibiotic or drug with
             potential antimalarial activity (including chloroquine, piperaquine, tetracycline,
             azithromycin, clindamycin, hydroxychloroquine,).

         15. Medicinal products that are known to prolong the QTc interval.

         16. Positive result on any of the following tests: hepatitis B surface (HBs Ag) antigen,
             antihepatitis B core antibodies (anti-HBc Ab), anti-hepatitis C virus (anti-HCV)
             antibodies, anti-human immunodeficiency virus 1 and 2 antibodies (anti-HIV1 and anti
             HIV2 Ab).

         17. Known severe reaction to mosquito bites other than local itching and redness</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>8</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Terminated</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/09/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Novartis Investigative Site - Brisbane</hospital>
    <postcode>4006 - Brisbane</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Medicine for Malaria Venture</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a single-center open label study conducted in multiple sequential cohorts using
      Induced Blood Stage Malaria infection in healthy volunteers to characterize the effectiveness
      of KAE609 against sexual and asexual blood stage forms of Plasmodium falciparum. This study
      is divided in 2 parts (Part A and part B). A total of 8 healthy volunteers per cohort will be
      enrolled. Based on the results of Part A, Part B will be undertaken to evaluate the effect of
      KAE609 following pretreatment with Piperaquine on sexual stage/gametocytemia and its activity
      as an inhibitor of onward transmission to mosquito vectors using experimental mosquito
      feeding assays.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02543086</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>James McCarthy, MD FRACP</name>
      <address>Q-Pharm Pty Limited</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>