<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5896">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/07/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/07/2015</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02503774</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>MEDI9447 Alone and in Combination With MEDI4736 in Adult Subjects With Select Advanced Solid Tumors</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 1 Multicenter, Open-label, Dose-escalation and Dose-expansion Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics, Immunogenicity, and Antitumor Activity of MEDI9447 Alone and in Combination With MEDI4736 in Adult Subjects With Select Advanced Solid Tumors</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>D6070C00001</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Solid Tumours</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - MEDI9447
Other interventions - MEDI4736 and MEDI9447

Experimental: Monotherapy - MEDI9447 only

Experimental: Combination - MEDI9447 and MEDI4736


Other interventions: MEDI9447
Subjects will receive MEDI9447 until disease progression

Other interventions: MEDI4736 and MEDI9447
Subjects will receive MEDI9447 and MEDI4736 until disease progression

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants with Adverse Events as a Measure of Safety - The primary endpoint is safety as assessed by the presence of AEs, serious adverse events (SAEs).</outcome>
      <timepoint>From time of informed consent through 12 weeks after last dose of investigational product</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite measure of Preliminary antitumor activity - Assessment of antitumor activity include OR, disease control (DC), duration of response (DoR), progression-free survival (PFS), and overall survival (OS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>From the time of informed consent through an average of 1 year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite measure of Pharmacokinetics of MEDI9447 or MEDI9447/MEDI4736 - Including Cmax and AUC of MEDI9447 administered as a single agent and the Cmax and AUC of both MEDI9447 and MEDI4736 when administered in combination.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From time of informed consent through 12 weeks after last dose of investigational product</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite measure of Immunogenicity - Immunogenicity of MEDI9447 and MEDI4736 include the number and percentage of subjects who develop detectable anti-drug antibodies (ADAs).</outcome>
      <timepoint>From time of informed consent through 12 weeks after last dose of investigational product</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Biomarker activity - Assessment of target expression in subject samples.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From time of informed consent through 12 weeks after last dose of investigational product</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Adult subjects; age = 18

          2. Written and signed informed consent must be obtained

          3. Have histologic or cytologic documentation of solid tumor

             ? Must have received and have progressed, are refractory, or are intolerant to
             standard therapy appropriate for the specific tumor type. Depending on tumor type,
             subjects should not have received more than 5 prior lines of therapy for recurrent or
             metastatic disease including both standards of care and investigational therapies

          4. Subjects must have at least 1 lesion that is measureable using RECIST guidelines

          5. Subjects must consent to provide archived tumor specimens or tumor biopsies for
             correlative biomarker studies.

          6. All subjects are encouraged to consent to and provide paired pretreatment and
             on-treatment tumor biopsies.

          7. In the dose-expansion phase, all subjects are encouraged to consent and provide paired
             on-treatment tumor biopsies

          8. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance score of 0 or 1

          9. In the opinion of the investigator, likely to complete = 56 days of treatment

         10. Adequate organ function as determined by: I.Absolute neutrophil count = 1.5 × 109/L
             (1,500/mm3) II.Platelet count = 75 × 109/L (75,000/mm3) III.Hemoglobin = 9.0 g/dL
             IV.Prothrombin time-international normalized ratio and partial thromboplastin time =
             1.5 × ULN V.Calculated creatinine clearance* (CrCl) or 24 hour urine CrCl &gt; 50
             mL/minute VI.Total bilirubin = 1.5 × ULN; for subjects with documented/suspected
             Gilbert's disease, bilirubin = 3 × UL VII.AST and ALT = 2.5 × ULN VIII.Serum
             electrolytes within normal limits

         11. Female subjects of childbearing potential who are sexually active with a
             non-sterilized male partner must use at least one highly effective method of
             contraception from the time of screening, and must agree to continue using such
             precautions for 90 days (or 180 days) after the final dose of investigational product.

         12. Nonsterilized males who are sexually active with a female partner of childbearing
             potential must use condom plus spermicide from Day 1 through 90 days (or 180 days)
             after receipt of the last dose of investigational product.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>101</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Prior treatment with tumor necrosis factor receptor superfamily agonists including
             OX40, CD27, CD137 (4-1BB), CD357 (GITR). One cohort also excludes anti CTLA-4, anti
             PDL-1 and anti PDL-1.

          2. Subjects who have received prior therapy with regimens containing CTLA-4, PD-L1, or
             PD-1 antagonists are NOT permitted to enroll unless all of the following apply:

               -  Dose of immunotherapy must have been administered at least 28 days or 5 half
                  lives, whichever is shorter, prior to planned first dose of MEDI9447/MEDI4736

               -  Must not have experienced a toxicity that led to permanent discontinuation of
                  prior immunotherapy

               -  All AEs while receiving prior immunotherapy must have resolved to = Grade 1 or
                  baseline prior to screening for this study

          3. Must not have required the use of additional immunosuppression other than
             corticosteroids for the management of an AE, not have experienced recurrence of an AE
             if re-challenged, and not currently require maintenance doses of &gt; 10 mg prednisone or
             equivalent per day

          4. Known allergy or hypersensitivity to investigational product formulations

          5. History of more than one event of IRR requiring permanent discontinuation of IV drug
             treatment

          6. History of severe drug allergies or anaphylaxis to 2 or more food products or medicine
             (including known sensitivity to acetaminophen/paracetamol, diphenhydramine or
             equivalent antihistamine, and methylprednisolone or equivalent glucocorticoid)

          7. Cardiac or peripheral vascular disease meeting any of the following criteria:

               -  Past history of myocardial infarction in the prior 12 months

               -  Past history of stroke or transient ischemic attack requiring medical therapy

               -  Congestive heart failure = Class 3 based on New York Heart Association Functional
                  Classification

          8. Grade 3 or greater edema (eg, peripheral, pulmonary)

          9. History of Grade 3 or greater thromboembolic events or thromboembolic event of any
             grade with on going symptoms

         10. Subjects with active tuberculosis are ineligible. In settings where there is clinical
             or radiographic evidence of tuberculosis, active disease must be ruled out

         11. Active or prior documented autoimmune or inflammatory disorders (including
             inflammatory bowel disease [eg, colitis, Crohn's disease], celiac disease, or other
             serious gastrointestinal chronic conditions associated with diarrhea, etc) within the
             past 3 years prior to the start of treatment. The following are exceptions to this
             criterion are subjects s with vitiligo or alopecia or hypothyroidism.

         12. Untreated central nervous system (CNS) metastatic disease

         13. Concurrent enrollment in another clinical study, unless it is an observational (non
             interventional) clinical study or the follow-up period of an interventional study

         14. Receipt of any conventional or investigational anticancer therapy not otherwise
             specified above within 28 days prior to the first dose of Investigational product

         15. Any concurrent chemotherapy, immunotherapy, or biologic or hormonal therapy for cancer
             treatment.

         16. Unresolved toxicities from prior anticancer therapy

         17. Current or prior use of immunosuppressive medication within 14 days prior to the first
             dose of Investigational product

         18. History of primary immunodeficiency, solid organ transplantation

         19. Known positive for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), chronic or active hepatitis B
             or active hepatitis A or C

         20. Receipt of live, attenuated vaccine within 28 days prior to the first dose of
             investigational products

         21. Females who are pregnant, lactating, or intend to become pregnant during their
             participation in the study

         22. Major surgery within 28 days prior to first dose of Investigational Product or still
             recovering from prior surgery.

         23. Other invasive malignancy within 2 years except for noninvasive malignancies such as
             cervical carcinoma in situ, in situ prostate cancer, non-melanomatous carcinoma of the
             skin, ductal carcinoma in situ of the breast that has been surgically cured

         24. Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, active peptic ulcer disease or gastritis, uncontrolled hypertension,
             uncontrolled diabetes, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit
             compliance with study requirement</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>24/07/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>188</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>15/02/2021</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>Research Site - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>Research Site - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Research Site - St Leonards</hospital>
    <hospital>Research Site - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>3050 - Parkville</postcode>
    <postcode>2065 - St Leonards</postcode>
    <postcode>4068 - Woolloongabba</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Connecticut</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Georgia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Missouri</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Tennessee</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>MedImmune LLC</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics,
      Immunogenicity, and Antitumor Activity of MEDI9447 Alone and in Combination with MEDI4736 in
      Adult Subjects with Select Advanced Solid Tumors</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02503774</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>MedImmune LLC</name>
      <address>MedImmune LLC</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>AstraZeneca Clinical Study Information Center</name>
      <address />
      <phone>1-877-240-9479</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>information.center@astrazeneca.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>