<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="1222">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/06/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/06/2006</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00348140</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Rosiglitazone (Extended Release Tablets) As Adjunctive Therapy In Subjects With Mild To Moderate Alzheimer's Disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A 54 Week, Double-blind, Randomised, Placebo-controlled, Parallel Group Study to Investigate the Effects of Rosiglitazone (Extended Release Tablets) as Adjunctive Therapy to Acetylcholinesterase Inhibitors on Cognition and Overall Clinical Response in APOE4-stratified Subjects With Mild to Moderate Alzheimer's Disease</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>REFLECT-3</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>AVA102670</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Alzheimer's Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Alzheimer's disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dementias</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Rosiglitazone Extended Release 2mg
Treatment: drugs - Rosiglitazone Extended Release 8mg
Other interventions - Placebo

Experimental: Arm 1 - Rosiglitazone Extended Release 2mg OD

Experimental: Arm 2 - Rosiglitazone Extended Release 8mg OD

Placebo Comparator: Arm 3 - Placebo


Treatment: drugs: Rosiglitazone Extended Release 2mg
Rosiglitazone Extended Release 2mg OD

Treatment: drugs: Rosiglitazone Extended Release 8mg
Rosiglitazone Extended Release 8mg OD

Other interventions: Placebo
Placebo

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Alzheimer's Disease Assessment Scale - Cognitive Subscale (ADAS-Cog) Total Score at Week 48, as a Function of APOE e4 Status in APOE4 Negatives Cohort - The 11-item ADAS-Cog assessed a range of cognitive abilities including memory, comprehension, orientation in time and place and spontaneous speech. Most items were evaluated by tests, but some were dependent on clinician ratings on a five point scale. Scores range from 0 to 70 with higher scores indicating greater dysfunction. Change from Baseline was calculated as value at scheduled time point minus Baseline value. Baseline was defined as value at Week 0. Estimated value was calculated by Active treatment minus Placebo. The adjusted means were presented. A hierarchical testing procedure was used to control for statistical tests in the two RSG dose groups and the genetic subgroups.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Week 0) and Week 48</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in ADAS-Cog Total Score at Week 48, as a Function of APOE e4 Status in All Except E4/E4s Cohort - The 11-item ADAS-Cog assessed a range of cognitive abilities including memory, comprehension, orientation in time and place and spontaneous speech. Most items were evaluated by tests, but some were dependent on clinician ratings on a five point scale. Scores range from 0 to 70 with higher scores indicating greater dysfunction. Change from Baseline was calculated as value at scheduled time point minus Baseline value. Baseline was defined as value a t Week 0. Estimated value was calculated by Active treatment minus Placebo. The adjusted means were presented. A hierarchical testing procedure was used to control for statistical tests in the two RSG dose groups and the genetic subgroups.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Week 0) and Week 48</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in ADAS-Cog Total Score at Week 48, as a Function of APOE e4 Status in Full Population Cohort - The 11-item ADAS-Cog assessed a range of cognitive abilities including memory, comprehension, orientation in time and place and spontaneous speech. Most items were evaluated by tests, but some were dependent on clinician ratings on a five point scale. Scores range from 0 to 70 with higher scores indicating greater dysfunction. Change from Baseline was calculated as value at scheduled time point minus Baseline value. Baseline was defined as value a t Week 0. Estimated value was calculated by Active treatment minus Placebo. The adjusted means were presented. A hierarchical testing procedure was used to control for statistical tests in the two RSG dose groups and the genetic subgroups.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Week 0) and Week 48</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Clinical Dementia Rating Scale - Sum of Boxes (CDR-SB) Score at Week 48, as a Function of APOE e4 Status in APOE4 Negatives Cohort - The CDR-SB was a validated clinical assessment of global function in patients with AD. Impairment was scored in each of 6 cognitive categories on a scale in which none = 0, questionable = 0.5, mild = 1, moderate = 2, and severe = 3. The 6 individual category ratings, or "box scores", can be added together to give the CDR-Sum of Boxes which ranges from 0 to 18 (severe impairment). Change from Baseline was calculated as value at scheduled time point minus Baseline value. Baseline was defined as value a t Week 0. Estimated value was calculated by Active treatment minus Placebo. The adjusted means were presented. Primary inference will be based on the week 48 treatment differences obtained from the MMRM model. A hierarchical testing procedure was used to control for statistical tests in the two RSG dose groups and the genetic subgroups.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Week 0) and Week 48</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in CDR-SB Score at Week 48, as a Function of APOE e4 Status in All Except E4/E4s Cohort - The CDR-SB was a validated clinical assessment of global function in patients with AD. Impairment was scored in each of 6 cognitive categories on a scale in which none = 0, questionable = 0.5, mild = 1, moderate = 2, and severe = 3. The 6 individual category ratings, or "box scores", can be added together to give the CDR-Sum of Boxes which ranges from 0 to 18 (severe impairment). Change from Baseline was calculated as value at scheduled time point minus Baseline value. Baseline was defined as value a t Week 0. Estimated value was calculated by Active treatment minus Placebo. The adjusted means were presented. Primary inference will be based on the week 48 treatment differences obtained from the MMRM model. A hierarchical testing procedure was used to control for statistical tests in the two RSG dose groups and the genetic subgroups.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Week 0) and Week 48</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in CDR-SB Score at Week 48, as a Function of APOE e4 Status in Full Population Cohort - The CDR-SB was a validated clinical assessment of global function in patients with AD. Impairment was scored in each of 6 cognitive categories on a scale in which none = 0, questionable = 0.5, mild = 1, moderate = 2, and severe = 3. The 6 individual category ratings, or "box scores", can be added together to give the CDR-Sum of Boxes which ranges from 0 to 18 (severe impairment). Change from Baseline was calculated as value at scheduled time point minus Baseline value. Baseline was defined as value a t Week 0. Estimated value was calculated by Active treatment minus Placebo. The adjusted means were presented. Primary inference will be based on the week 48 treatment differences obtained from the MMRM model. A hierarchical testing procedure was used to control for statistical tests in the two RSG dose groups and the genetic subgroups.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Week 0) and Week 48</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in ADAS-Cog Total Score at Weeks 8, 16, 24 and 36 - The 11-item ADAS-Cog assessed a range of cognitive abilities including memory, comprehension, orientation in time and place and spontaneous speech. Most items were evaluated by tests, but some were dependent on clinician ratings on a five point scale. Scores range from 0 to 70 with higher scores indicating greater dysfunction. Change from Baseline was calculated as value at scheduled time point minus Baseline value. Baseline was defined as value a t Week 0. It was calculated at Weeks 8, 16, 24 and 36. Full population data was presented.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Week 0) and Week 8, 16, 24, 36</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in CDR-SB Score at Weeks 12, 24 and 36 - The CDR-SB was a validated clinical assessment of global function in patients with AD. Impairment was scored in each of 6 cognitive categories on a scale in which none = 0, questionable = 0.5, mild = 1, moderate = 2, and severe = 3. The 6 individual category ratings, or "box scores", can be added together to give the CDR-Sum of Boxes which ranges from 0 to 18 (severe impairment). Change from Baseline was calculated as value at scheduled time point minus Baseline value. Baseline was defined as value a t Week 0. Estimated value was calculated by Active treatment minus Placebo. The adjusted means were presented. It was calculated at Weeks 12, 24 and 36. Full population data was presented.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Week 0) and Week 12, 24, 36</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Screening in Mini Mental State Examination (MMSE) Total Score - The MMSE consists of 11 tests of orientation, memory (recent and immediate), concentration, language and praxis. Scores range from 0 to 30, with lower scores indicating greater cognitive impairment. The scale is completed by the investigator, based on the performance of the participant. Change from screening was calculated as value at scheduled time point minus screening value. Baseline was defined as value a t Week 0. Estimated value was calculated by Active treatment minus Placebo. The adjusted means were presented. Full population data was presented.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Screening (Week -4) and Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Disability Assessment for Dementia (DAD) Total Score - The DAD assessed the ability of a participant to execute basic and instrumental activities of daily living (ADL) and leisure activities. The scale consists of 40 questions assessing basic and instrumental ADLs. This scale assessed a participants' ability to initiate, plan, and perform activities related to hygiene, dressing, continence, eating, meal preparation, telephoning, going on an outing, finance and correspondence, medications, leisure, and housework. Each item was scored as yes: 1, no: 0 and N/A: not applicable. Higher scores indicate less disability with a score of 100 indicating no disability and 0 indicating no functional ability. The percentage score was calculated as (DAD Total score /Total number of applicable items) multiplied by 100. Change from Baseline was calculated as value at scheduled time point minus Baseline value. Baseline was defined as value at Week 0. Full population data was presented.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Week 0) and Week 8, 16, 24, 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Neuropsychiatric Inventory (NPI) Total Score - NPI is an assessment of frequency and severity of behavioral disturbances in dementia that comprised of 10 dimensions: delusions, hallucinations, dysphoria, apathy, euphoria, disinhibition, aggressiveness and agitation, irritability, anxiety, aberrant motor activity. Participant's caregiver asked about behavior in participant. If "Yes", informant then rated both severity on a 3-point scale, 1-mild to 3-severe (total range: 0-36) and frequency using a 4-point scale, 1-occasionally to 4-very frequently. Total score was frequency × severity. Distress was scored on 5-point scale, 0-no distress to 5-very severe or extreme. Total NPI score was calculated by adding all domain scores; NPI total score: 0-144 and NPI distress score: 0-60, higher scores indicated more severe behavioral disturbance. Change from Baseline was calculated as value at scheduled time point minus Baseline value. Baseline was defined as value at Week 0. Adjusted means were presented. Full population data was presented.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Week 0) and Week 8, 16, 24, 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Domains of the Resource Utilization in Dementia Scale (RUD)- Q1 and Q2 Caregiver Hours - The RUD instrument was developed as a comprehensive tool to assess the amount of resource use among demented patients. RUD assessd both formal and informal resource use of the patient and the primary caregiver, making it possible to calculate costs from a societal perspective. Q1 corresponds to the number of hours during the last month the caregiver spent assisting the patient with toilet visits, eating, dressing, grooming, walking and bathing and Q2 corresponds to the number of hours during the last month the caregiver spent assisting the patient with shopping, food preparation, housekeeping, laundry, transportation, taking medication and managing financial matters. Change from Baseline was calculated as value at scheduled time point minus Baseline value. Baseline was defined as value at Week 0. Estimated value was calculated by Active treatment minus Placebo. The adjusted means were presented. Full population data was presented.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Week 0) and Week 12, 24, 36, 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in European Quality of Life -5 Dimensions (EQ-5D) Scale Total Score- Thermometer Score - The EQ-5D Proxy is an assessment of quality of life and utility benefit. The EQ-5D Proxy is composed of two parts: part two is the visual analogue scale 'Thermometer'. Caregivers are asked to respond as they feel the participant would on dimensions of mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort and anxiety/depression. The 'Thermometer' has endpoints of 100 (best imaginable health state) and 0 (worst imaginable health state). Change from Baseline was calculated as value at scheduled time point minus Baseline value. Baseline was defined as value a t Week 0. Estimated value was calculated by Active treatment minus Placebo. The adjusted means were presented. Full population data was presented.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Week 0) and Week 12, 36, 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in EQ-5D Scale Total Score- Utility Score - The EQ-5D Proxy is an assessment of quality of life and utility benefit. The EQ-5D Proxy is composed of two parts: part one is the five dimensional Health State Classification. The Utility score is a caregiver rating of health status on dimensions of mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort, and anxiety/depression. Answers to each question were responded to on a 3-point scale which indicates the level of impairment (level 1= no problem; level 2=some or moderate problem(s) and level 3=unable, or extreme problem with higher scores indicating greater dysfunction. Change from Baseline was calculated as value at scheduled time point minus Baseline value. Baseline was defined as value a t Week 0. Estimated value was calculated by Active treatment minus Placebo. The adjusted means were presented. Full population data was presented.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Week 0) and Week 12, 36, 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Alzheimer's Carer's Quality of Life Instrument (ACQLI) Score - The ACQLI is an assessment of caregiver quality of life. This instrument consisted of 30 questions exploring various aspects of carer's quality of life. Each of the questions had two point response, and the 30 questions were summed to provide a total score. Items were assumed to be unidimensional (i.e., represent a single variable) and were scored 0/1 (false/true) before summation into a total score with a 0-30 range. To ease comparisons between scales, ACQLI scores were transformed to range between 0-100 (100: worse). Change from Baseline was calculated as value at scheduled time point minus Baseline value. Baseline was defined as value a t Week 0. Estimated value was calculated by Active treatment minus Placebo. The adjusted means were presented. Full population data was presented.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Week 0) and Week 12, 36, 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in ADAS-Cog Total Score for Observed Cases at Week 54 Compared to Week 48 - The 11-item ADAS-Cog assessed a range of cognitive abilities including memory, comprehension, orientation in time and place and spontaneous speech. Most items were evaluated by tests, but some were dependent on clinician ratings on a five point scale. Scores range from 0 to 70 with higher scores indicating greater dysfunction. It was of interest to compare the single blind phase data between the treatment groups defined based on the double blind treatment group. This analysis only included participants who received at least one dose of single-blind medication. Change from Baseline was calculated as value at scheduled time point minus Baseline value. Baseline was defined as value at Week 0. Full population data was presented.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 48 and Week 54</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in CDR-SB Total Score for Observed Cases at Week 54 Compared to Week 48 - The CDR-SB was a validated clinical assessment of global function in participants with AD. Impairment was scored in each of 6 cognitive categories on a scale in which none = 0, questionable = 0.5, mild = 1, moderate = 2, and severe = 3. The 6 individual category ratings, or "box scores", can be added together to give the CDR-Sum of Boxes which ranges from 0 to 18 (severe impairment). It was of interest to compare the single blind phase data between the treatment groups defined based on the double blind treatment group. This analysis only included participants who received at least one dose of single-blind medication. Change from Baseline was calculated as value at scheduled time point minus Baseline value. Baseline was defined as value at Week 0. Full population data was presented.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 48 and Week 54</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Glycosylated Hemoglobin (HbA1c) at Week 48 - Blood samples were collected for assessments of HbA1c levels at Baseline and up to Week 48. Change from Baseline was calculated as value at scheduled time point minus Baseline value . Baseline was defined as value at Week 0. Endpoint treatment differences which were adjusted to take account of missing data are derived. Full population data was presented.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Week 0) and Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With On-treatment Adverse Events (AEs), Serious Adverse Events (SAEs) and Severity of AEs - AE was defined as any untoward medical occurrence in a participant temporarily associated with the use of a medicinal product, whether or not considered related to the medicinal product. SAE was any untoward medical occurrence that, at any dose results in death, was life threatening, required hospitalization or prolongation of existing hospitalization, resulted in disability/incapacity, was a congenital anomaly/birth defect or was considered as medically significant.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Upto Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With Change From Baseline in Vital Signs of Clinical Concern at Any Time on Treatment- Weight - Body weight was measured at all visits, without shoes and wearing light clothing. The assessment was performed a t Baseline and up to Week 54. Change from Baseline was calculated as value at scheduled time point minus Baseline value. Baseline was defined as value at Week 0. Full population data was presented.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Upto Week 54</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With Change From Baseline in Vital Signs of Clinical Concern at Any Time on Treatment- Systolic Blood Pressure (SBP) and Diastolic Blood Pressure (DBP) - SBP and DBP of participants were recorded in sitting posture as vital sign at each visit. The blood pressure (BP) values were identified as of potential clinical concern if the values were out of the reference range (for SBP, 90 to 140 mmHg and DBP, 50 to 90 mmHg) or meet a change from baseline criterion. The change from baseline criterion for SBP, was increase from Baseline (high) if increased by more than or equal to (&gt;=) 40 mm Hg from Baseline; decrease from Baseline (low) if decreased by &gt;= 30 mmHg from Baseline. For DBP, increase from baseline (high) if increased by &gt;=30 mmHg from baseline; decrease from Baseline (low) if decreased by &gt;= 20 mmHg from Baseline. Baseline was defined as value at Week 0.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Upto Week 54</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With Change From Baseline in Vital Signs of Clinical Concern at Any Time on Treatment- Heart Rate (HR) - HR of participants were recorded in sitting posture as vital sign at each visit. The HR values were identified as of potential clinical concern if the values were out of the reference range (50 to 100 beats per minute) or meet a change from baseline criterion. The change from baseline criterion for HR, was increase from Baseline (high) if increased by more than or equal to (&gt;=) 30 from Baseline; decrease from Baseline (low) if decreased by &gt;= 30 from Baseline. Baseline was defined as value at Week 0. Full population data was presented.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Upto Week 54</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Weight - Body weight was measured at all visits, without shoes and wearing light clothing. The assessment was performed at Baseline, Weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 24, 36, 48, 54. Change from Baseline was calculated as value at scheduled time point minus Baseline value. Baseline was defined as value at Week 0. Full population data was presented.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Week 0) and Weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 24, 36, 48, 54</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Hemoglobin - Hematology parameters were assessed at Baseline, Weeks 4, 16, 36, 48. Change from Baseline was calculated as value at scheduled time point minus Baseline value. Baseline was defined as value at Week 0. Full population data was presented.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Week 0) and Weeks 4, 16, 36, 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Hematocrit - Hematology parameters were assessed at Baseline and up to Week 48. Change from Baseline was calculated as value at scheduled time point minus Baseline value. Baseline was defined as value at Week 0.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Week 0) and Weeks 4, 16, 36, 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Any Time on Treatment Differences in Frequencies of Hematology Data Outside the Reference Range - Haematology parameters were identified as of PCC (high [H], low [L]), if the values were out of the reference range (RR). The range for parameters was: platelet (100AV-500AV), red blood cell (RBC , 0.8-1.2), hemoglobin (L: female [F]:10, male [M]:11; H: F:16.5-AV, M:18), hematocrit (0.8-1.2), white blood cell (WBC, 3-15), Total neutrophils (ANC- absolute Neutrophil count) (0.75-1.5), lymphocytes (0.75-1.5), monocyte s (0.75-2), eosinophils (none -2), basophils (none -2), mean corpuscle volume (MCV, 0.8-1.2), mean corpuscular hemoglobin (MCH, 0.8-1.2), mean corpuscular hemoglobin concentration (MCHC , 0.8-1.2), red cell distribution width (RDW, 0.8-1.2), Neutrophil bands (none-1) and segmented neutrophils (0.75-1.3). Full population data was presented.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Any Time on Treatment Differences in Frequencies of Clinical Chemistry Data Outside the Reference Range - Clinical chemistry parameters were identified as of PCC (High, Low), if values were out of RR: Alanine amino transferase (ALT,none-120 [250percent upper limit of RR, ULRR ]),Album in (0.75-2),Aldolase(1.1-1.1),Aspartate amino transferase (AST,none-105 (3-64y),137.5(65+y),&gt;250 percent ULRR), Alkaline phosphatase(ALP,none-312.5 (20+y),&gt;250percent ULRR),blood urea nitrogen(BUN)/Creatinine ratio(none-1.25),BUN(none-11),Chloride(80-115),Calcium (0.75-1.25),Carbon dioxide(CO2,15-40) content,Creatinine (22,&lt;50percent lower limit of RR [LLRR ]-155, &gt;125percent ULRR),Creatine phosphokinase(CPK,none-1.25),Gamma glutamyl transferase(GGT,none-2.5),Glucose (3.6-7.8),HbA1C, High density lipoprotein (HDL,0.65-none),Lactate dehydrogenase (LDH,none -2), Low density lipoprotein(LDL,none-1.25),Magnesium (0.5-2),Potassium (3-5.5),Phosphorus inorganic(0.5-1.5), Sodium (130-150), Total protein (0.8-1.5),Total cholesterol(none -1.5),Direct Billirubin.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Upto Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes From Baseline in Electrocardiogram (ECG) Parameters- HR - Triplicate 12-lead ECG measures was obtained digitally, approximately one minute apart after the participant had rested in the supine position in a quiet room (no TV, minimal talking) for atleast 10 minutes. The ECG parameters includes HR. The assessments were performed at Baseline and up to Week 54. Change from Baseline was calculated as value at scheduled time point minus Baseline value . Baseline was defined as value at Week 0. Full population data was presented.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Week 0) and Weeks 4, 8, 16, 24, 36, 48, 54</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes From Baseline in ECG Parameters- RR Interval, QT Interval, QTcB, QTcF, PR Interval and QRS Duration - Triplicate 12-lead ECG measures was obtained digitally, approximately one minute apart after the participant had rested in the supine position in a quiet room (no TV, minimal talking) for atleast 10 minutes. The ECG parameters includes PR interval, QRS duration, QT - uncorrected interval, QTc Bazett (QTcB), QTc Fridericia (QTcF) and RR interval. The assessments were performed at Baseline and up to Week 54. Change from Baseline was calculated as value at scheduled time point minus Baseline value. Baseline was defined as value at Week 0. Full population data was presented.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Week 0) and Weeks 4, 8, 16, 24, 36, 48, 54</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in HbA1c up to Week 54 - Blood samples were collected for assessments of HbA1c levels at Baseline, Weeks 12, 24, 36, 48, 54. Change from Baseline was calculated as value at scheduled time point minus Baseline value. Baseline was defined as value at Week 0.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Week 0) and Weeks 12, 24, 36, 48, 54</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Short Term Memory Assessment - The 11-item ADAS-Cog assessed a range of cognitive abilities including memory, comprehension, orientation in time and place and spontaneous speech. Most items were evaluated by tests, but some were dependent on clinician ratings on a five point scale. Scores range from 0 to 70 with higher scores indicating greater dysfunction. Questions 1 (word recall) and 7 (word recognition) of ADAS-Cog questionnaire was summed to get a short term memory assessment. The score for Question 1 was calculated as the mean number of words not recalled over the trials for which data was available. If data for all three trials was missing, or if the score for Question 7 was missing then the short term memory score will also be set to missing. Change from Baseline was calculated as value at scheduled time point minus Baseline value. Baseline was defined as value a t Week 0. Estimated value was calculated by Active treatment minus Placebo. The adjusted means were presented.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Week 0) and upto Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>A subject will be eligible for inclusion in this study only if all of the following
        criteria apply:

          -  Male or female subject with a clinical diagnosis of probable Alzheimer's disease in
             accordance with NINCDS-ADRDA criteria (Appendix 2).

        (Note: National Institute of Neurological and Communicative Disorders and Stroke (NINCDS)
        and Alzheimer's Disease and Related Disorders Association (ADRDA).)

          -  Subject has mild to moderate Alzheimer's disease as defined by a MMSE score 10 to 26
             inclusive at Screening.

          -  Hachinski Ischemia Score = 4 at Screening (See Appendix 3).

          -  Age =50 and =90 years.

          -  At least 6 months of ongoing acetylcholinesterase inhibitor therapy for Alzheimer's
             disease, with stable dosing for at least the last 2 months (and with no intent to
             change for the duration of the study).

          -  Current use of medication is in accordance with the criteria listed in Table 2
             (Permitted Medications, Section 8.1).

          -  Female subjects must be post-menopausal (i.e. &gt;1 year without menstrual period),
             surgically sterile, or agree to use adequate method of contraception (Appendix 4) for
             the duration of the study. Female subjects who are pre-menopausal or who have been
             post-menopausal for &lt;1 year must undertake pregnancy testing (urine test) at Visit 1,
             which must be negative.

          -  Brain CT or MRI scan performed within the past 12 months or at Screening, showing no
             evidence of any other potential cause of dementia other than Alzheimer's disease.

        (Note: Questionable CT or MRI scans should be discussed with the medical monitor, using
        central imaging guidelines.)

          -  Neurological exam without focal changes (excluding changes attributable to AD or
             peripheral trauma).

          -  Subject has the ability to comply with procedures for cognitive and other testing.

          -  Subject lives with (or has substantial periods of contact with) a regular caregiver
             who is willing to attend all visits, oversee the subject's compliance with
             protocol-specified procedures and study medication, and report on subject's status.

        (Note: A non-cohabiting caregiver must spend sufficient time with the subject so that, in
        the opinion of the Investigator, the caregiver can reliably assess cognitive function,
        activities and behavior, and report on the subject's compliance and health. As caregiver
        time spent with a potential subject is anticipated to be highly variable across countries
        and cultures, GSK will consider a variety of different measures by which this stipulation
        may be met, and GSK should be consulted if adequacy of a caregiver situation is in doubt.
        However, as guidance, the ability for a caregiver to meet his/her expected responsibilities
        for this study would normally be possible when the caregiver spends no less than 10 hours
        per week with the subject, divided over multiple days.)

          -  Subject has provided full written informed consent prior to the performance of any
             protocol-specified procedure; or if unable to provide informed consent due to
             cognitive status, full written informed consent on behalf of the subject has been
             provided by a legally acceptable representative.

        (Note: Consent by legally acceptable representative is allowed where this is in accordance
        with local laws, regulations and ethics committee policy.)

          -  Caregiver has provided full written informed consent on his/her own behalf prior to
             the performance of any protocol-specified procedure.

          -  Subjects considered for enrolment must have a QTc (either QTc B (Bazett's correction)
             or QTc F (Fridericia's correction)) &lt;450msec at Visit 1, with the exception of
             subjects with bundle branch block (for whom either QTc B or QTc F must be &lt;480msec).

        (Note: For the purposes of these criteria, QTc B is defined as (QT interval [msec]) /
        (square root of RR interval [seconds]); and QTc F is defined as (QT interval [msec]) /
        (cube root of RR interval [seconds]).)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>90</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>A subject will not be eligible for inclusion in this study if any of the following criteria
        apply:

          -  Diagnosis of possible, probable, or definite vascular dementia in accordance with
             NINDS-AIREN criteria (Appendix 5).

        (Note: National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS) and Association
        Internationale pour la Recherche et l'Enseignement en Neurosciences (AIREN).)

          -  History or evidence of any other CNS disorder that could be interpreted as a cause of
             dementia: e.g. cerebrovascular disease (stroke, hemorrhage), structural abnormality,
             epilepsy, infectious or inflammatory/demyelinating CNS conditions, Parkinson's
             disease.

          -  Evidence of the following disorders: current vitamin B12 deficiency, positive syphilis
             serology, or active thyroid dysfunction (particularly that suggestive of
             hypothyroidism), including abnormally high or low serum levels of thyroid stimulating
             hormone (TSH), that are clinically significant in the opinion of the investigator.

        (Note: Testing is required for each parameter only when no result is available from
        previous 12 months.)

          -  History of Type 1 diabetes mellitus or secondary diabetes mellitus.

          -  Type 2 diabetes mellitus where the subject is being treated with insulin, a PPAR?
             agonist, or an insulin secretagogue (e.g. a sulfonylurea or glitinide).

          -  Any patient with an HbA1c =8.5%. (See Section 6.3.8.4 for Safety Measures for Enrolled
             Subjects with Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus.)

          -  History or clinical/investigational evidence of congestive heart failure defined by
             the New York Heart Association criteria (Class I to IV cardiac status; Appendix 6).

          -  History of cardiovascular event within the last 6 months (i.e. intervention,
             percutaneous coronary intervention, vascular surgery, acute coronary syndrome [non
             Q-wave myocardial infarction, Q-wave myocardial infarction, unstable angina] or
             significant arrhythmia; or major intervention (e.g. cardiac surgery or angiography
             plus stenting) scheduled).

          -  History of significant psychiatric illness such as schizophrenia or bipolar affective
             disorder that in the opinion of the Investigator would interfere with participation in
             the study, major depressive disorder (according to DSM-IV) in the past year, or
             current active depression requiring initiation of treatment.

        (Note: If not currently treated, but active depression is suspected, the Cornell Scale for
        Depression in Dementia (CSDD, Appendix 7) can be used by the Investigator as a guide for
        deciding whether a prospective subject requires treatment. If the subject has a CSDD score
        &gt;7, the Investigator should decide if the subject has depression in need of prescribed
        medication, and a CSDD &gt;12 is considered a strong indicator that treatment is needed.
        Subjects will be allowed to re-screen after their depression has been adequately managed
        for &gt;3 months.)

          -  History or presence of gastro-intestinal, hepatic, or renal disease or other condition
             known to interfere with the absorption, distribution, metabolism, or excretion of
             drugs, or any other clinically relevant abnormality, medical or psychiatric condition,
             which, in the opinion of the Investigator, makes the subject unsuitable for inclusion
             in the study.

          -  Clinically significant peripheral edema at the time of screening.

          -  Current or recent drug or alcohol abuse or dependence (defined by DSM-IV criteria for
             substance-related disorders), or recent or remote history of the same if that could be
             a contributing factor to the dementia.

          -  Systolic blood pressure &gt;165 or &lt;90 mmHg or diastolic blood pressure &gt;95 or &lt;60 mmHg
             at the time of screening.

          -  Clinically significant anemia (i.e. hemoglobin &lt;11 g/dL for males or &lt;10 g/dL for
             females) or presence of hemoglobinopathies which would prevent accurate assessment of
             HbA1c.

          -  Abnormal kidney function tests (&gt;1.5 times the upper limit of normal (ULN)).

          -  ALT, AST, or alkaline phosphatase values &gt;2.5 times the ULN, total bilirubin values
             &gt;1.5 times the ULN, or history of severe hepatobiliary disease (e.g. hepatitis B or C,
             or cirrhosis, Child-Pugh Class B/C).

        (Note: For subjects with a diagnosis of Gilberts Syndrome and an isolated increase in total
        bilirubin &gt;1.5 ULN, fractionation should be performed. If all of the following conditions
        are met, the patient may enter or remain in the study, even if total bilirubin &gt;1.5 ULN:

          -  an elevated unconjugated (indirect) bilirubin;

          -  the percentage of direct bilirubin &lt;35%;

          -  ALT, AST, and alkaline phosphatase &lt;2.5 ULN if subject is in screening (&lt;2.0 ULN for
             Canadian subjects only), or =3 ULN if subject is already randomized into the study)

          -  History of a bone marrow transplant.

          -  Subject is unable (with assistance, if appropriate) to take study medication as
             prescribed throughout the study or is at risk of non-compliance with study medication
             or procedures.

          -  Subject is an immediate family member or employee of the participating Investigator,
             of any of the participating site staff, or of GSK.

          -  In France, a subject is neither affiliated with nor a beneficiary of a social security
             category.

          -  The French subject has participated in any study using an investigational drug during
             the previous 30 days or 5 half-lives (whichever is longer).

          -  Cognitive tasks prescribed for cognitive rehabilitation and performed under medical
             supervision are prohibited for 6 months prior to Screening, as well as for the
             duration of the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2>The people administering the treatment/s</masking2>
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>12/07/2006</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>1468</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>20/03/2009</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,SA,VIC,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Hornsby</hospital>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Randwick</hospital>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Auchenflower</hospital>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Chermside</hospital>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Kippa Ring</hospital>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Woodville</hospital>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Cheltenham</hospital>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Heidelberg West</hospital>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Kew</hospital>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Nedlands</hospital>
    <postcode>2077 - Hornsby</postcode>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
    <postcode>4066 - Auchenflower</postcode>
    <postcode>4032 - Chermside</postcode>
    <postcode>4021 - Kippa Ring</postcode>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>5011 - Woodville</postcode>
    <postcode>3192 - Cheltenham</postcode>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg West</postcode>
    <postcode>3101 - Kew</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Arizona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Arkansas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Connecticut</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Georgia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Illinois</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Massachusetts</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Jersey</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Oklahoma</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Pennsylvania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Rhode Island</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>South Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Utah</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Virginia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Washington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Wisconsin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Bruxelles</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Kortrijk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Leuven</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Woluwe-Saint-Lambert</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Bulgaria</country>
      <state>Sofia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Bulgaria</country>
      <state>Varna</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>British Columbia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>New Brunswick</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Nova Scotia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Quebec</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Québec</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Olomouc</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Praha 10</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Praha 8</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Trutnov</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Finland</country>
      <state>Helsinki</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Finland</country>
      <state>Joensuu</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Finland</country>
      <state>Kuopio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Bordeaux</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>La Chapelle sur Erdre</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>La Seyne sur Mer</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Lille</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Limoges</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Metz</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Nantes</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Paris</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Sautron</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Toulon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Toulouse</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Valence</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Baden-Wuerttemberg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Bayern</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Brandenburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Hessen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Sachsen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Thueringen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Berlin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <state>Hong Kong</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <state>Shatin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Seongnam-si,</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Seoul</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <state>Bandar Tun Razak, Cheras</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <state>Ipoh</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <state>Kelantan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Alkmaar</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Blaricum</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Den Bosch</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Den Haag</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Hengelo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Hilversum</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Philippines</country>
      <state>Manila</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Philippines</country>
      <state>Pasig City</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Bydgoszcz</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Krakow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Torun</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Warsaw</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Singapore</country>
      <state>Singapore</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Slovakia</country>
      <state>Bratislava</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Slovakia</country>
      <state>Kosice</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Slovenia</country>
      <state>Ljubljana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Slovenia</country>
      <state>Šempeter</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Loeventstein</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Oakdale</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Richards Bay</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Rosebank</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Somerset West</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Waverley, Bloemfontein</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Willows, X14, Pretoria</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Baracaldo/Vizcaya</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Palma de Mallorca</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Tarrasa, Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Falköping</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Jönköping</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Kalix</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Mölndal</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Sundsvall</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Umeå</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Lancashire</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Bradford</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Liverpool</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Stirling</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>West End, Southampton</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>West of Scotland Science Park, Glasgow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>GlaxoSmithKline</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Rosiglitazone (RSG) has been tested in clinical studies and is approved by the FDA as a
      treatment for type II diabetes mellitus, a disease that occurs when the body is unable to
      effectively use glucose. RSG XR, the investigational drug used in this study, is an
      extended-release form of RSG.

      This study tests whether RSG XR safely provides clinical benefit to people with mild to
      moderate Alzheimer's disease (AD) when combined with one of the currently approved AD
      medications, Aricept®, Razadyne® or Exelon®. RSG XR is a new approach to AD therapy and this
      study tests a new way to treat AD by testing whether one's genetic makeup affects the
      response to the study drug. Clinical data suggesting that RSG may benefit AD patients was
      first seen in a small study performed at the University of Washington and then from a larger
      GSK study conducted in Europe and New Zealand. In the first study, subjects receiving RSG
      once daily for 6 months scored significantly better on 3 tests of memory and thought than
      those who did not receive RSG. In the GSK study, those that appeared to benefit most from
      treatment with RSG XR had a specific genetic pattern. They did not have the gene that caused
      them to produce the protein apolipoprotein E e4 (APOE e4). Subjects who have the APOE e4 gene
      may have two copies, one from each parent, or they may have only one APOE e4 gene meaning
      that they inherited either the APOE e2 or APOE e3 version of the gene, instead of APOE e4,
      from one of their parents. Subjects with one copy of the APOE e4 gene remained at their same
      level of thinking ability while those with two copies of the APOE e4 gene, continued to
      worsen during the 6-month treatment. The current study will more directly test the
      effectiveness or RSG XR on people who either have or lack the APOE e4 gene.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00348140</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Harrington C, Sawchak S, Chiang C, Davies J, Donovan C, Saunders AM, Irizarry M, Jeter B, Zvartau-Hind M, van Dyck CH, Gold M. Rosiglitazone does not improve cognition or global function when used as adjunctive therapy to AChE inhibitors in mild-to-moderate Alzheimer's disease: two phase 3 studies. Curr Alzheimer Res. 2011 Aug;8(5):592-606.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>GSK Clinical Trials</name>
      <address>GlaxoSmithKline</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>