<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="1426">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/01/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/01/2007</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00419900</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Use of Hair to Diagnose the Presence of Breast Cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle />
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>FER2k</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Breast Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: surgery - diagnosis of breast cancer by x-ray diffraction of hair

Treatment: surgery: diagnosis of breast cancer by x-ray diffraction of hair


</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Accuracy (sensitivity and specificity) of the breast cancer test based on detection of an abnormal pattern of hair x-ray diffraction compared to the gold standard of mammography plus biopsy where indicated</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The prevalence of a positive hair x-ray diffraction pattern and a negative mammogram; and the prevalence of a negative hair x-ray diffraction pattern and a positive mammogram;</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Adult women (aged &gt;20) who are undergoing mammography, and

          -  Who are willing and able to provide informed consent; and

          -  Who have usable scalp and/or pubic hair</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Female</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Women who have dyed or permed their scalp hair within the previous 6 weeks and whose
             pubic hair is unavailable;

          -  Women with a history of breast cancer ever or other cancers (excluding non-melanoma
             skin cancer and CIN [cervical intra-epithelial neoplasia]) within 5 years.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Screening</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/12/2006</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Unknown status</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Bankstown Diagnostic Imaging Centre - Sydney</hospital>
    <hospital>Campbelltown Ultrascan Radiology - Sydney</hospital>
    <hospital>Diagnostic Imaging Centre, St George Private Hospital - Sydney</hospital>
    <hospital>Liverpool Ultrascan Radiology - Sydney</hospital>
    <hospital>Penrith Imaging - Sydney</hospital>
    <postcode>2200 - Sydney</postcode>
    <postcode> - Sydney</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Fermiscan Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Using synchrotron X-ray diffraction, it has been reported that a hair from an individual with
      breast cancer exhibits a difference in its molecular structure compared to that of an
      individual without breast cancer. This difference is visible in the X-ray diffraction pattern
      as a ring superimposed on the pattern for normal hair.

      The hypothesis of this study is that synchrotron x-ray diffraction can be used to
      differentiate hairs from women with medically diagnosed breast cancer from women not known to
      have the disease.

      To test this hypothesis, hair from 2000 women attending radiology clinics for mammography
      will be collected, analysed by x-ray diffraction and then analysed using Fermiscan
      proprietary image analysis software. The mammogram status of the subjects will be blinded
      from the diffraction analysts. Results will then be compared with mammography results to
      allow a direct comparison between the Fermiscan test and mammography in terms of specificity
      and sensitivity.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00419900</trialwebsite>
    <publication>James VJ. A place for fiber diffraction in the detection of breast cancer? Cancer Detect Prev. 2006;30(3):233-8. Epub 2006 Jul 28.
James V, Corino G, Robertson T, Dutton N, Halas D, Boyd A, Bentel J, Papadimitriou J. Early diagnosis of breast cancer by hair diffraction. Int J Cancer. 2005 May 10;114(6):969-72.
James V. False-positive results in studies of changes in fiber diffraction of hair from patients with breast cancer may not be false. J Natl Cancer Inst. 2003 Jan 15;95(2):170-1. Erratum in: J Natl Cancer Inst. 2003 Feb 19;95(4):334..
Meyer P, James VJ. Experimental confirmation of a distinctive diffraction pattern in hair from women with breast cancer. J Natl Cancer Inst. 2001 Jun 6;93(11):873-5.
James V, Kearsley J, Irving T, Amemiya Y, Cookson D. Using hair to screen for breast cancer. Nature. 1999 Mar 4;398(6722):33-4.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Phillip Yuile, MBBS, FRACR</name>
      <address>Radiation Oncology Associates, Sydney, Australia</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Peter W French, BSc, MSc, PhD</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+61292454460</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pfrench@fermiscan.com.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>