<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3866">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/12/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/12/2012</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01794507</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Study Evaluating ABT-199 in Multiple Myeloma Subjects Who Are Receiving Bortezomib and Dexamethasone as Standard Therapy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 1b Study Evaluating the Safety and Pharmacokinetics of ABT-199 in Relapsed or Refractory Multiple Myeloma Subjects Who Are Receiving Bortezomib and Dexamethasone as Their Standard Therapy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>2011-004626-10</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>M12-901</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Relapsed/Refractory Multiple Myeloma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cancer types</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - ABT-199
Treatment: drugs - bortezomib
Treatment: drugs - dexamethasone

Experimental: ABT-199 + BTZ/Dex Dose Escalation Cohorts - Evaluate the safety and pharmacokinetics profile of ABT-199 administered with standard therapy bortezomib and dexamethasone in a dose escalation scheme in approximately 18 subjects.

Experimental: ABT-199 + BTZ/Dex Safety Expansion Cohort - Safety expansion cohort to further evaluate recommended phase two dose (RPTD) of ABT-199 administered with standard therapy bortezomib and dexamethasone in approximately 12 subjects.


Treatment: drugs: ABT-199
ABT-199 at cohort-defined dosing schedules and dose levels. ABT-199 at defined dose and schedule for Safety Expansion cohort

Treatment: drugs: bortezomib
Bortezomib at cohort-defined dosing schedules and dose levels. Bortezomib at defined dose and schedule for Safety Expansion cohort

Treatment: drugs: dexamethasone
Dexamethasone at cohort-defined dosing schedules and dose levels. Dexamethasone at defined dose and schedule for Safety Expansion cohort.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number and percentage of subjects with adverse events - Collect all adverse events at each visit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From subject's first dose of ABT-199 until 30 days after subject's last dose of ABT-199; up to 2 years following last subject first dose.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in physical exam findings, including vital signs - Blood pressure, heart rate and body temperature</outcome>
      <timepoint>From subject's baseline (prior to subject's first dose) assessed up to 2 years following the last subject first dose.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine dosing schedule, maximum tolerated dose (MTD), and recommended phase two dose (RPTD) of ABT-199 - ABT-199 will be dose-escalated until the largest dose is reached that is determined to be safe based on adverse event reporting and dose-limiting toxicities information from all subjects.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Minimum first cycle of dosing (21 days) plus any lead-in period dosing (if used)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in clinical laboratory test results - Hematology, chemistry, urinalysis, electrophoresis, immunofixation, viral serologies, free light chains</outcome>
      <timepoint>From subject's baseline (prior to subject's first dose) assessed up to 2 years following the last subject first dose.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in cardiac assessment findings - Electrocardiogram and Multiple Gated Acquisition Scan and/or Echocardiogram</outcome>
      <timepoint>From subject's baseline (prior to subject's first dose) assessed up to 2 years following the last subject first dose.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determination of peak concentration (Cmax), trough concentration (Ctrough) and area under the concentration versus time curve (AUC) of ABT-199 - Blood samples for pharmacokinetic analysis of ABT-199 will be collected at designated timepoints</outcome>
      <timepoint>Dose Escalation: Once on Lead-in D1; 5 times on Lead-in D7; twice on Cycle 1 D1; 5 times C1 D11; once on C1 D12 &amp; on Day 1 of Cycles 2, 4, 6 &amp; 8. Safety Exp: Once on Lead-in Day1; 5 times Cycle 1 D1; once on Cycle 1 D2 &amp; on Day 1 of Cycles 2, 4, 6 &amp; 8.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Exploratory pharmacodynamic studies: Change in bone marrow aspirate and core biopsy samples for Cytogenetics/FISH, Bcl-2 Family Member mRNA Analysis, Bcl-2 Family Member Protein Analysis - Bone marrow aspirate and core biopsy samples may be evaluated with the goal of defining the relationship between drug concentration and disease status.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From subject's baseline (prior to subject's first dose) assessed up to 2 years following the last subject first dose.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Calculation of Objective Response Rate - The proportion of subjects with response using International Myeloma Working Group (IMWG) response criteria will be computed for all subjects with active disease at baseline (in the opinion of the investigator)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at Day 0, Cycle 3 Day 1, Cycle 5 Day 1, Cycle 9 Day 1 and Day 1 every other Cycle thereafter (e.g., 11, 13, 15, etc.) up to 48 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Calculation of Time to Disease Progression - Number of days from the date of the first dose of ABT-199 to the date of the subject's disease progression.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at Day 0, Cycle 3 Day 1, Cycle 5 Day 1, Cycle 9 Day 1 and Day 1 every other Cycle thereafter (e.g., 11, 13, 15, etc.) up to 48 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Calculation of Duration of Response - Number of days from the day of initial response is objectively documented to the day that disease progression is objectively documented</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at Day 0, Cycle 3 Day 1, Cycle 5 Day 1, Cycle 9 Day 1 and Day 1 every other Cycle thereafter (e.g., 11, 13, 15, etc.) up to 48 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Exploratory pharmacodynamic studies: Change in Serum Markers and Plasma Markers Blood Samples - Blood samples may be evaluated with the goal of defining the relationship between drug concentration and disease status</outcome>
      <timepoint>From subject's baseline (prior to subject's first dose) assessed up to 2 years following the last subject first dose.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Exploratory pharmacogenetic study: Evaluate blood samples to define relationship between drug concentration and disease status - Blood sample may be evaluated with goal of defining relationship between drug concentration and disease status</outcome>
      <timepoint>Screening (prior to subject's first dose)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance score less than or equal to 1

          -  Diagnosis of multiple myeloma previously treated with at least 1 prior line of therapy
             (dose escalation only) or (safety expansion only) received treatment with a proteasome
             inhibitor or an IMiD(r) or immunomodulatory agent (e.g., thalidomide, lenalidomide).
             Induction therapy and following stem cell transplant are considered a single line of
             therapy.

          -  Measurable disease at Screening: Serum monoclonal protein greater than or equal to 1
             g/dL by protein electrophoresis, or greater than or equal to 200 mg monoclonal protein
             in the urine on 24-hr electrophoresis, or serum immunoglobulin free light chain
             greater than or equal to 10 mg/dL and abnormal serum immunoglobulin kappa to lambda
             free light chain ratio.

          -  Subject has a history of autologous or allogenic stem cell transplant, have adequate
             bone marrow independent of any growth factor support, and have recovered from any
             transplant related toxicity(s); and either greater than 100 days post-autologous
             transplant (prior to first dose of study drug) or greater than or equal to 6 months
             post-allogenic transplant (prior to first dose of study drug) and not have active
             graft-versus-host disease (i.e., requiring treatment).

          -  Subject must have adequate coagulation, renal, and hepatic function, per laboratory
             reference range at Screening.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>99</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Exhibits evidence of other clinically significant uncontrolled condition(s),
             including, but not limited to: uncontrolled systemic infection (viral, bacterial, or
             fungal), diagnosis of fever and neutropenia within 1 week prior to first dose of study
             drug

          -  Cardiovascular disability status of New York Heart Association Class greater than 2.
             Class 2 is defined as cardiac disease in which patients are comfortable at rest but
             ordinary physical activity results in fatigue, palpitations, dyspnea or anginal pain.

          -  Significant history of renal, neurologic, psychiatric, endocrinologic, metabolic,
             immunologic, cardiovascular, pulmonary or hepatic disease, that in the opinion of the
             investigator, would adversely affect his/her participation in the study.

          -  History of other active malignancies other than multiple myeloma within the past 3
             years prior to study entry, with the following exceptions: adequately treated in situ
             carcinoma of the cervix uteri, basal cell carcinoma of the skin or localized squamous
             cell carcinoma of the skin, previous malignancy confined and surgically resected (or
             treated with other modalities) with curative intent.

          -  Tested positive for HIV or hepatitis.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>26/11/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>66</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>15/05/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital /ID# 79533 - Parkville, Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre /ID# 79553 - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>3050 - Parkville, Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3000 - Parkville</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Arizona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Michigan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Minnesota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Lille</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Nantes, Cedex 1</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>AbbVie (prior sponsor, Abbott)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Genentech, Inc.</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary objectives of this study are to assess the safety profile, characterize
      pharmacokinetics (PK) and determine the dosing schedule, maximum tolerated dose (MTD), and
      the recommended phase two dose (RPTD) of ABT-199 when administered in subjects with relapsed
      /refactory multiple myeloma who are receiving bortezomib and dexamethasone as their standard
      therapy.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01794507</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Paulo Maciag, MD</name>
      <address>AbbVie</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>