<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4936">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/10/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/10/2014</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02264574</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Multi-Center Study of Ibrutinib in Combination With Obinutuzumab Versus Chlorambucil in Combination With Obinutuzumab in Patients With Treatment naïve CLL or SLL</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomized, Multi-center, Open-label, Phase 3 Study of the Bruton's Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitor Ibrutinib in Combination With Obinutuzumab Versus Chlorambucil in Combination With Obinutuzumab in Subjects With Treatment-naïve Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia or Small Lymphocytic Lymphoma</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>PCYC-1130-CA</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Small-Cell Lymphoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lymphoma (non Hodgkin's lymphoma) - High grade lymphoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lymphoma (non Hodgkin's lymphoma) - Low grade lymphoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Leukaemia - Acute leukaemia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Leukaemia - Chronic leukaemia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Children's - Leukaemia &amp; Lymphoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Ibrutinib
Treatment: drugs - Obinutuzumab
Treatment: drugs - Chlorambucil

Experimental: A - Oral ibrutinib 420 mg daily (3 capsules) continuously (until evidence of progressive disease or no longer tolerated by the patient) in combination with obinutuzumab 1000 mg intravenously over 6 cycles: Days 1+2 (100 mg on Day 1 and 900 mg on Day 2), 8 and 15 of Cycle 1 followed by Day 1 only on Cycles 2-6..

Experimental: B - Treatment will be 6 cycles. Chlorambucil will be administered orally at a dose of 0.5 mg/kg body weight, on Days 1 and 15 of each cycle. Obinutuzumab will be administered intravenously at a dose of 1000 mg, over 6 cycles: given on Days 1+2 (100 mg on Day 1 and 900 mg on Day 2), 8 and 15 of Cycle 1 and on Day 1 only on Cycles 2-6. Treatment will be administered up to a maximum of 6 cycles or until disease progression or unacceptable toxicity, whichever occurs first.


Treatment: drugs: Ibrutinib
Ibrutinib will be supplied as 140 mg hard gelatin capsules for oral (PO) administration.

Treatment: drugs: Obinutuzumab
Obinutuzumab will be supplied as 1000 mg/40 mL solution in a single-use vial for intravenous (IV) administration

Treatment: drugs: Chlorambucil
Chlorambucil will be supplied as 2 mg film-coated tablets for oral (PO) administration

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary endpoint of this study is Progressive Free Survival - The efficacy of ibrutinib in combination with obinutuzumab versus chlorambucil in combination with obinutuzumab based on the IRC assessment compared to chlorambucil in combination with obinutuzumab based on the Independent Review Committee (IRC) assessment of progression-free survival (PFS) in subjects with treatment-naive chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL) or small lymphocytic lymphoma (SLL)by independent central radiologists, findings from physical examinations and hematology results</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 years after last subject is randomized</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Response Rate - Overall response rate (ORR) is defined as the proportion of subjects who achieve a CR, CRi, nPR, or PR, over the course of the study as evaluated by the IRC using IWCLL 2008 criteria, with modification for treatment-related lymphocytosis. Subjects who do not have any postbaseline response assessment will be considered as nonresponders. A chi-square test will be used to compare the two treatment arms</outcome>
      <timepoint>At disease progression, 5 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of minimal residual disease (MRD)-negative responses - A chi-square test will be used to compare the rate of MRD-negative responses between the two treatment arms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At disease progression, 5 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Disease Related:

          1. Diagnosis of CLL/SLL that meets IWCLL diagnostic criteria.

          2. Age 65 yrs and older OR if less than 65 years, must have at least one of the following
             criteria:

               -  Cumulative Illness Rating Score (CIRS) &gt;6

               -  Creatinine clearance estimated &lt;70 mL/min using Cockcroft-Gault equation.

               -  Del 17p by FISH or TP53 mutation by PCR or Next Generation Sequencing

          3. Active disease meeting at least 1 of the following IWCLL criteria for requiring
             treatment:

               -  Evidence of progressive marrow failure as manifested by the development of, or
                  worsening of, anemia and thrombocytopenia

               -  Massive, progressive, or symptomatic splenomegaly

               -  Massive nodes (at least 10 cm longest diameter), or progressive or symptomatic
                  lymphadenopathy.

               -  Progressive lymphocytosis with an increase of more than 50 percent over a 2-month
                  period or a lymphocyte doubling time (LDT) of &lt;6 months. LDT may be obtained by
                  linear regression extrapolation of absolute lymphocyte counts obtained at
                  intervals of 2 weeks over an observation period of 2 to 3 months. In patients
                  with initial blood lymphocyte counts of &lt;3,000/µL, LDT should not be used as a
                  single parameter to define indication for treatment. In addition, factors
                  contributing to lymphocytosis or lymphadenopathy other than CLL (eg, infections)
                  should be excluded.

               -  Autoimmune hemolytic anemia and/or immune thrombocytopenia that is poorly
                  responsive to corticosteroids or other standard therapy.

               -  Autoimmune hemolytic anemia is defined by at least one marker of hemolysis
                  (indirect bilirubin above the upper limit of normal (ULN) not due to liver
                  disease, increased lactate dehydrogenase (above ULN) without alternative
                  etiology, or increased absolute reticulocytosis (above ULN) or bone marrow
                  erythropoiesis in the absence of bleeding AND at least one marker direct or
                  indirect autoimmune mechanism (positive direct antiglobulin for IgG or C3d, cold
                  agglutinins).

               -  Immune thrombocytopenia is defined by platelets =100,000/µL and increased
                  megakaryocytes on the bone marrow exam.

               -  Constitutional symptoms, defined as one or more of the following disease-related
                  symptoms or signs, documented in the patient's record prior to randomization:

               -  unintentional weight loss &gt;10 percent within 6 months prior to screening.

               -  significant fatigue (inability to work or perform usual activities).

               -  fevers &gt;100.5°F or 38.0°C for 2 or more weeks prior to screening without evidence
                  of infection.

               -  night sweats for more than 1 month prior to screening without evidence of
                  infection.

          4. Measurable nodal disease by computed tomography (CT), defined as at least 1 lymph node
             &gt;1.5 cm in the longest diameter in a site that has not been previously irradiated. An
             irradiated lesion may be assessed for measurable disease only if there has been
             documented progression in that lesion since radiotherapy has ended.

             Laboratory

          5. Adequate hematologic function independent of transfusion and growth factor support for
             at least 7 days prior to screening and randomization.

          6. Adequate hepatic and renal function

          7. Men and women = 18 years of age.

          8. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 to 2.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Any prior treatment of CLL or SLL

          2. Evidence of central nervous system (CNS) involvement with primary disease of CLL/SLL

          3. History of other malignancies, except:

               -  Malignancy treated with curative intent and with no known active disease present
                  for =3 years before the first dose of study drug and felt to be at low risk for
                  recurrence by treating physician.

          4. Uncontrolled autoimmune hemolytic anemia or idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura

          5. Known or suspected history of Richter's transformation.

          6. Concurrent administration of &gt;20mg/day of prednisone within 7 days of randomization
             unless indicated for prophylaxis or management of allergic reactions (eg, contrast)

          7. Known hypersensitivity to one or more study drugs

          8. Vaccinated with live, attenuated vaccines within 4 weeks of first dose of study drug.

          9. Any uncontrolled active systemic infection or an infection requiring systemic
             treatment that was completed = 7 days before randomization.

         10. Known bleeding disorders or hemophilia.

         11. History of stroke or intracranial hemorrhage within 6 months prior to enrollment.

         12. Known history of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or active with hepatitis B virus
             (HBV) or hepatitis C virus (HCV).

         13. Major surgery within 4 weeks of randomization.

         14. Any life-threatening illness, medical condition, or organ system dysfunction that, in
             the investigator's opinion, could compromise the subject's safety or put the study
             outcomes at undue risk.

         15. Currently active, clinically significant cardiovascular disease, such as uncontrolled
             arrhythmia or Class 3 or 4 congestive heart failure or a history of myocardial
             infarction, unstable angina, or acute coronary syndrome within 6 months prior to
             randomization.

         16. Unable to swallow capsules or malabsorption syndrome, disease significantly affecting
             gastrointestinal function, or resection of the stomach or small bowel, symptomatic
             inflammatory bowel disease or ulcerative colitis, or partial or complete bowel
             obstruction.

         17. Concomitant use of warfarin or other vitamin K antagonists.

         18. Requires treatment with a strong cytochrome P450 (CYP) 3A inhibitor.

         19. Lactating or pregnant

         20. Unwilling or unable to participate in all required study evaluations and procedures.

         21. Unable to understand the purpose and risks of the study and to provide a signed and
             dated informed consent form (ICF) and authorization to use protected health
             information (in accordance with national and local subject privacy regulations).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/10/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>212</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/01/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD,SA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Site Reference ID/Investigator #0503 - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <hospital>Site Reference ID/Investigator# 0650 - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>Site Reference ID/Investigator# 0888 - Ballarat</hospital>
    <hospital>Site Reference ID/Investigator# 0193 - Box Hill</hospital>
    <hospital>Site Reference ID/Investigator# 0633 - Fitzroy</hospital>
    <hospital>Site Reference ID/Investigator# 0170 - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <postcode> - Woolloongabba</postcode>
    <postcode> - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode> - Ballarat</postcode>
    <postcode> - Box Hill</postcode>
    <postcode> - Fitzroy</postcode>
    <postcode> - Heidelberg</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Kentucky</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Nevada</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Tennessee</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Austria</country>
      <state>Linz</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Austria</country>
      <state>Salzburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Leuven</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Turnhout</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Alberta</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czech Republic</country>
      <state>Hradec Kralove</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czech Republic</country>
      <state>Praha 10</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Gironde</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Loire Atlantique</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Meurthe et Moselle</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Pyrenees Atlantiques</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Haifa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Jerusalem</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Petach Tikva</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Tel Aviv</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Zerifin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Firenze</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Milano</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Modena</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Novara</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Roma</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Siena</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Hamilton</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Brzozow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Lodz</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Nizhniy Novgorod</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Ryazan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Saint-Petersburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>St. Petersburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Yaroslavl</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Salamanca</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Borås</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Luleå</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Lund</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Stockholm</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>Nisantasi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>Ankara</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>Denizli</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>Izmir</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>Samsun</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Essex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Pharmacyclics LLC.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>An open-label, multi-center randomized, phase 3 study of ibrutinib combined with obinutuzumab
      versus Chlorambucil in combination with obinutuzumab in subjects with treatment-naïve Chronic
      Lymphocytic Leukemia or Small Lymphocytic Lymphoma.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02264574</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>