<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3700">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/12/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/12/2012</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01742260</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Cranial Reconstruction Using Mesenchymal Stromal Cells and Resorbable Biomaterials</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Pilot Study to Demonstrate Safety and Feasibility of Cranial Reconstruction Using Mesenchymal Stromal Cells and Resorbable Biomaterials</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>2012/022238</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>2012/047</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Surgically-Created Resection Cavity</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: surgery - Repair of cranial defects by tissue engineering

Experimental: Repair of cranial defect - Repair of cranial defects by tissue engineering


Treatment: surgery: Repair of cranial defects by tissue engineering
Repair of defect using mesenchymal stromal cells seeded between moulded bioceramic plates

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Failure of cranioplasty implant - The primary outcome measures will be failure of the tissue engineered construct such that it requires removal (due to infection, resorption, dislodgement or cosmetic failure), as well as any significant adverse events attributable to treatment allocation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quantitative bone density of the tissue engineered construct and adjacent bone from CT scan at 12 months.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of cosmesis by photography</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  All adult patients (age &gt; 18 years) who have had a decompressive craniectomy, with a
             defect size of less than 80 mm in diameter.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Patients who have had a previous cranial infection

          -  Patients with a penetrating bone injury

          -  Positive bone marrow aspirate on testing for microcontamination

          -  Positive testing for infectious disease

          -  Cranial void size of larger than 80mm

          -  Patients who have neurocognitive difficulties and are as such unable to provide
             informed consent

          -  Failure to sign informed consent

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding females</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>10</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/12/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Perth Hospital - Perth</hospital>
    <postcode>6000 - Perth</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>R.P.Herrmann</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Formal study hypothesis:

      Cranial reconstruction using mesenchymal stromal cells and resorbable biomaterials, will
      result in the patient producing their own bone to fill the void which will reduce the risk of
      infection and resorption, lead to a better cosmetic result and obviate any long term
      consequence of having a synthetic material in vivo.

      Introduction:

      There are several reasons that parts of the skull may need to be removed:

        -  After trauma to relieve brain swelling

        -  During brain surgery (for brain cancer)

        -  After trauma where the bone is so badly fractured/fragmented it needs to be removed.

      In all but the last case the bone flap is temporarily stored in a freezer and once the brain
      swelling has subsided it is reinserted. This procedure is called "autologous cranioplasty";
      autologous, because it originally came from the patient and cranioplasty, referring to the
      repair. Although this is a straightforward procedure, there are a number of complications
      including infection and bone resorption that can occur.

      This study:

      Stromal cells have a proven ability to aid in bony healing. Furthermore stromal cells on a
      ceramic framework encased in a plastic scaffold have been shown in a small clinical trial to
      lead to healing of skull defects. In the present study, it is proposed to add stromal cells
      from a suitable donor to medical grade ceramic granules, place them in between specially
      moulded plastic scaffolds and insert the sandwich into the skull. Both the ceramic and
      plastic materials are medical grade and commonly used in reconstructive surgery, the ceramic
      for packing into bony defects due to trauma or removal of cancer and the polymer in bony
      reconstruction. Both materials are approved by the TGA. They are designed to dissolve away
      over time as the body's own blood vessels and cells populate the sandwich and create the
      patient's new bone. It has been proven that without the encouragement of the cells and
      temporary scaffold materials, a hole in the skull will not heal. Given the incidence of bone
      resorption/infection and metal plate infection using traditional methods, it would seem
      prudent to provide a construct that will allow controlled replacement with the patient's own
      bone, thus negating any adverse long-term complications with synthetic materials that remain
      for life.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01742260</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Stephen Honeybul, MD</name>
      <address>Royal Perth Hospital</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Stephen Honeybul, MD</name>
      <address />
      <phone>61893463333</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>stephen.honeybul@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>