<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3800">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/02/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/02/2013</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01790802</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Laser Intervention in Early Age-Related Macular Degeneration Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Multi-centre, Randomized Trial Into the Safety and Efficacy of Nanosecond Microsurgical Laser Intervention in Early Age-related Macular Degeneration</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>LEAD</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>ACTRN12612000704897</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>CERA201201</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Age-related Macular Degeneration</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - 2RT nanosecond laser

Experimental: Active laser - Twelve 2RT nanosecond laser shots in two arcs of 6 shots superiorly and 6 shots inferiorly, inside the retinal vascular arcades at an approximate distance from the fovea of 3000 microns, with approximately one laser spot diameter between them.

Sham Comparator: Sham laser procedure - The maximum illumination button on hte 2RT laser will be briefly pressed by the operating physician at each of the 12 locations where and when the laser would normally be applied. The laser remains in standby mode preventing accidental laser firing.


Treatment: devices: 2RT nanosecond laser
active laser therapy

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>progression to advanced Age-related Macular Degeneration (AMD) in the treated eye - rate of progression to advanced AMD, either Choroidal Neovascularization (CNV), Geographic Atrophy (GA) or preclinical atrophy, in the study eye of treatment group compared to the sham procedure group</outcome>
      <timepoint>36 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>progression to advanced AMD in the untreated eye - rate of progression to advanced AMD, CNV, GA or preclinical atrophy in the fellow (untreated) eye</outcome>
      <timepoint>36 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Males or females from 50 to 95 years of age at the time of consent

          -  Best corrected visual acuity (BCVA) of 6/12 (20/40) or better in each eye.

          -  Bilateral high-risk early AMD: At least one druse =125um within an inner macular zone
             (a circle with a radius of 1500 microns centred on the fovea) with or without pigment.

          -  A MAIA static threshold sensitivity less than 25 dB at any point, within a customized
             grid, as measured using a Macular Integrity Assessment (MAIA) device), at the same
             location of the one eye on two separate occasions.

          -  Pupil dilation of a least 5 mm in each eye

          -  Fundus photographs, OCT and FAF images of adequate quality as assessed by the LEAD
             Image Reading Centre.

          -  Ability and willingness to consent, and be randomized, to the 2RT active or sham laser
             treatment, and all qualification and follow-up phases of the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>95</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Any evidence of definite geographic atrophy within the macula (a circle with a radius
             of 3000 microns centred on the fovea).

          -  Any black (hypofluorescent) area of FAF consistent with GA (roughly round or oval
             shape, sharp margins), and corroborated on colour photography as a patch of
             hypopigmentation.

          -  Any evidence of 'preclinical atrophy' as determined on OCT: loss of the outer retina
             (RPE and photoreceptors on the cube scan (Spectralis OCT) (49 horizontal B scans, 120
             µm apart over a 20 x 20 degree scan). This covers approximately 6 x 6 mm in an
             emmetropic eye (N.B., peri-papillary atrophy (PPA) further than 1500 microns from the
             fovea is allowed).

          -  Current CNV, or past evidence of CNV in either eye.

          -  Any other experimental treatment for AMD, excluding dietary supplements, received in
             the past 12 months or thought likely to chronically change the course of the
             participant's retinal disease.

          -  Any OCT showing evidence of intraretinal fluid, or subretinal fluid for which CNV
             cannot be excluded as a cause.

          -  A subfoveal pigment epithelial detachment/drusenoid detachment greater than 1000
             microns in diameter.

          -  Other macular disease with subretinal deposits not typical of AMD, e.g., Malattia
             Leventinese, Sorsby fundus dystrophy, Alports syndrome

          -  Ocular disease in either eye, other than AMD, which significantly compromises the
             ability to treat or visualize the fundus or would compromise the ability to assess any
             effect following laser application including;

          -  Known allergic hypersensitivity to fluorescein.

          -  Previous retinal or other ocular surgical procedures, the effects of which may now or
             in the future complicate assessment of the progression of AMD.

          -  Requirement for any systemic or ocular medication known to be toxic to the retina,
             such as: Deferoxamine, Chloroquine/Hydroxychloroquine (Plaquenil), Chlorpromazine,
             Phenothiazines, Ethambutol

          -  Any serious systemic disease that will preclude a 3 year survival and regular
             attendance for follow up.

          -  Sensitivity to contact lens application.

          -  Any condition that would make adherence to the examination schedule for 3 years
             difficult or unlikely.

          -  Any history of prior laser surgery to the retina.

          -  Intraocular pressures of 26mm Hg or higher or if there is some reason to believe the
             participant may have glaucoma

          -  Significant cataract: Nuclear cataract grade 2 or 3, cortical cataract Grade 2 or 3 or
             posterior subcapsular cataract Grade 2 or 3, by Simplified Cataract Grading System
             (WHO Cataract Grading Group).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/11/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>292</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/06/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Centre for Eye Research Australia - Royal Victorian Eye &amp; Ear Hospital - East Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3002 - East Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Center for Eye Research Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to determine whether 2RT nanosecond laser therapy slows the
      progression to advanced age-related macular degeneration.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01790802</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Robyn H Guymer, PhD, FRANZCO</name>
      <address>Deputy Director CERA</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>