<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3562">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/03/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/03/2012</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01610375</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Telephone Follow-up After Treatment for Endometrial Cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Telephone Follow-up After Treatment for Endometrial Cancer.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>TEACUP</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>TEACUP</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Endometrial Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Womb (Uterine or endometrial cancer)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - Telephone Follow-up

Other: Telephone Follow-up - Women previously treated for endometrial cancer will be recruited into one study group and continue to be followed per the current routine clinic follow-up. However, an additional program (telephone follow-up) will be offered in parallel to the current clinic follow-up. Outcomes obtained from the telephone follow-up will be compared with the current clinical assessment.


Other interventions: Telephone Follow-up
This is a non-randomised observational study to assess the value of a symptom checklist to detect recurrence in women with endometrial cancer. Women will be telephoned using an evidence-based symptom checklist in parallel to the standard clinic-based follow-up. The researcher will call the participants 2 to 5 days prior to their scheduled clinic review dates to enquire about the presence of symptoms which may be indicative of disease recurrence. In addition, the researcher will also enquire about the participants' wellbeing and provide standard lifestyle resource on physical activity, diet and other lifestyle behaviours and supportive care when needed.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sensitivity, specificity and overall accuracy of the telephone follow-up compared to clinic-based follow-up and patients' satisfaction. - The proposed project will involve generation of an evidence-based checklist of signs and symptoms of recurrence from a thorough literature review. The generated symptom checklist will be pilot tested and used in a one year prospective cohort study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in lifestyle behaviours and quality of life overtime. - The researcher will conduct a telephone interview and will enquire about the participant's wellbeing and provide resources on physical activity, quality of life, diet, anxiety and depression and supportive care when needed prior to each clinic visit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>To be eligible for this pilot study, the patient must;

          -  Have completed primary treatment for endometrial cancer

          -  Be recurrence-free

          -  In the first to third year after treatment

          -  Be able to read and understand English

          -  Must have access to a telephone and adequate hearing

          -  Participants must be willing to complete questionnaire on satisfaction with nurse and
             clinic follow-up</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Female</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Patients with disease recurrent or relapse

          -  Patients with metastatic disease presentation</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Health Services Research</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/06/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>280</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/12/2016</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <postcode>4029 - Herston</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Queensland Centre for Gynaecological Cancer</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to investigate the feasibility, safety and accuracy of a telephone
      follow-up for women previously treatment for endometrial cancer.

      To achieve this aim, potentially eligible women attending the Queensland Centre for
      Gynaecological Cancer (QCGC) outpatient clinic for review following previous treatment for
      endometrial cancer will be recruited by this study. The study aims to recruit all new
      patients as well as all patients who return to QCGC for their follow-up and who had treatment
      within the previous 2 years.

      The proposed project will involve generation of an evidence-based checklist of signs and
      symptoms of disease recurrence from a thorough literature review. The generated symptom
      checklist will be pilot tested and the refined symptom checklist will be used to follow study
      participants over a period of 12 months.

      During the follow-up period, the basic standard of follow-up after primary treatment for
      endometrial cancer at the QCGC, Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital (RBWH)will not be
      altered; however, the study participants will be interview via telephone 2 to 5 days prior to
      their scheduled review dates.

      The main outcome measure will be the estimated recurrence rate as derived from the telephone
      assessment and this will be compared to the clinically detected recurrences as recorded in
      patients' medical files.

      It is hypothesized, that the telephone follow-up will identify 90% of all recurrences
      correctly that are later confirmed during the clinical follow-up.

      In addition to the main outcome, we will also assess patients' satisfaction with each of the
      follow-up programs, whether or not lifestyle behaviours were queried and support offered to
      improve wellbeing.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01610375</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Andreas Obermair, MD FRANZCOG CGO</name>
      <address>Queensland Center for Gynecological Cancer</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>