<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5340">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/01/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/01/2016</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02657850</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Head and Neck Cancer Treatment Related Dysphagia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Multi-Institution Longitudinal Evaluation of Head and Neck Cancer Treatment - Related Dysphagia</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>IRB00074509</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Head and Neck Cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Dysphagia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Head and neck</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - non- head and neck self reporting
Other interventions - head neck self reporting
Other interventions - provider reporting

control cohort - study subject self-reporting - Participants who have another cancer (not head and neck cancer) and undergoing treatment will self-report their dysphagia symptoms.

study cohort - study subject self-reporting - Participants who have head and neck cancer and undergoing treatment will self-report their dysphagia symptoms.

study cohort - provider reporting - Participants who have head and neck cancer and undergoing treatment will have their dysphagia symptoms reported by the provider.


Other interventions: non- head and neck self reporting
non- head and neck patient self reports dysphagia symptoms

Other interventions: head neck self reporting
head and neck patient self reports dysphagia symptoms

Other interventions: provider reporting
provider reports on head and neck cancer patients' dysphagia symptoms

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in rate of dysphagia symptoms - To estimate the 24-month rate of dysphagia (SSQ &gt;234 rate) as defined by the proportion of patients with total SSQ score greater than 234 at the end of 24 months follow up. This threshold value has previously been validated (1).</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in rate of dysphagia between non head and neck and head and neck patients - To compare the 24-month rates of dysphagia (SSQ &gt;234 rate) between head and neck cancer patients and non-head and neck patients.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>change in dysphagia across different patient treatments - To estimate the treatment specific rate of dysphagia (SSQ &gt;234 rate). Treatment modality by surgery.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>change in dysphagia across different patient treatments - To estimate the treatment specific rate of surgery with postoperative radiotherapy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>change in dysphagia across different patient treatments - To estimate the treatment specific rate of surgery with surgery with postoperative concurrent chemoradiation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>change in dysphagia across different patient treatments - To estimate the treatment specific rate of surgery with radiotherapy alone.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>change in dysphagia across different patient treatments - To estimate the treatment specific rate of surgery with concurrent chemoradiation and induction chemotherapy followed by concurrent chemoradiation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>change in rate of secondary treatment side effect - To explore treatment effects on other secondary endpoint: pain visual analog scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>change in rate of secondary treatment side effect - To explore treatment effects on other secondary endpoint: speech-language pathology (SLP) recommended swallow exercise adherence status.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>change in rate of secondary treatment side effect - To explore treatment effects on other secondary endpoint: Functional Oral Intake Scale (FOIS) Diet Level and disease status / pattern of relapse.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion Criteria - Head and Neck Cancer Study Subjects:

          1. Previously untreated head and neck cancer of any histology receiving treatment with
             curative oncologic intent regardless of the treatment modality.

          2. Capable of providing informed consent.

        Inclusion Criteria - Non-Head and Neck Cancer Study Subjects

          1. Previously untreated cancer of any histology with no prior history of swallowing
             disorder and receiving radiation or concurrent chemoradiation or chemotherapy followed
             by radiation or concurrent chemoradiation.

          2. Screening SSQ &lt;234 prior to any cancer treatment.

          3. Capable of providing informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>100</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion Criteria -

          1. Potential study subjects who are unwilling or unable to be adherent to longitudinal
             assessment and follow-up. This will include potential study subjects who have poor
             performance status at the time of study enrollment evaluation.

          2. Potential study subjects who have cognitive limitations / impairments that prevent a
             potential study subject's ability to provide self-reporting with the SSQ instrument
             and/or other data elements required as described in the study calendar.

          3. Potential study subjects who have motor skill limitations that prevent a potential
             study subject's ability to provide self-reporting with the SSQ instrument and/or other
             data elements required as described in the study calendar.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2018</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>250</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>University of New South Wales - St. George Hospital - Sydney</hospital>
    <postcode> - Sydney</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Arizona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Colorado</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Minnesota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Missouri</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Washington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Hong Kong</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Cancers located in the upper aerodigestive tract of the head and neck region present unique
      management challenges due to the crucial functions in this anatomic region along with its
      anatomic density. As such, cancers themselves and the actual treatment can affect these
      functions. Of these, the ability to effectively and safely transport a swallow bolus from the
      oral cavity to the esophagus is particularly important. This consideration has in fact been a
      major source of debate regarding the optimal management for head and neck cancers as both
      oncologic-effective and function-preserving therapies are desired. Accomplishing this
      therapeutic goal has been elusive and can be attributed to a lack of tools that effectively
      and longitudinally evaluate swallow function over the course of a treatment and in follow-up.
      As such, investigators surprisingly lack a clear understanding of the natural history of
      treatment -related swallow dysfunction (dysphagia) regardless of the treatment modality. As
      such, understanding the prevalence of this significant complication is in fact not well
      established. Understanding the true prevalence of treatment-related dysphagia is in fact
      critical to establish as it will help guide decisions as to whether or not treatment
      strategies require modification including de-intensification of treatment that is receiving
      considerable attention for favourable prognosis patients associated with the human
      papillomavirus (HPV).

      To address this problem, winvestigators hypothesize that the quantitative and validated
      patient-reported outcome (PRO) instrument, the Sydney Swallow Questionnaire (SSQ), can be an
      effective tool to longitudinally measure swallow function to determine the natural history of
      head and neck cancer treatment-related swallow dysphagia. The SSQ is particularly well suited
      for longitudinal evaluation of swallow function as it quantifies various aspect of
      patient-perceived swallow function in contrast to other swallow PROs that measure the impact
      of swallow function on quality of life domains. To determine the two-year prevalence of
      dysphagia, investigators will employ a multi-institution prospective study design using our
      Oncospace® web-portal to facilitate secure prospective data curation and analysis that will
      include evaluations before, during and following standard of care definitive cancer treatment
      for a total of 36 months in the follow-up period.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02657850</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Harry Quon, M.D.</name>
      <address>The SKCCC at Johns Hopkins</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Harry Quon, M.D.</name>
      <address />
      <phone>410-502-3877</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hquon2@jhmi.edu</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>