<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6131">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/09/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/09/2016</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02934412</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Study of SHR-1314 in Healthy Subjects</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase I, Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled, Single Dose Escalation Study to Investigate Safety and Pharmacokinetics of SHR-1314 in Healthy Subjects</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>SHR-1314-A101</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Psoriasis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dermatological conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other skin conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - SHR-1314
Treatment: drugs - placebo

Experimental: SHR-1314 20mg - 20mg SHR-1314 or placebo is administered subcutaneously to healthy subjects

Experimental: SHR-1314 40mg - 40mg SHR-1314 or placebo is administered subcutaneously to healthy subjects

Experimental: SHR-1314 80mg - 80mg SHR-1314 or placebo is administered subcutaneously to healthy subjects

Experimental: SHR-1314 160mg - 160mg SHR-1314 or placebo is administered subcutaneously to healthy subjects

Experimental: SHR-1314 240mg - 240mg SHR-1314 or placebo is administered subcutaneously to healthy subjects


Treatment: drugs: SHR-1314
Single subcutaneous injection of SHR-1314 at 5 dose levels (20mg, 40mg, 80mg, 160mg, and 240mg) in healthy subjects.

Treatment: drugs: placebo
Single subcutaneous injection of placebo at 5 dose levels (20mg, 40mg, 80mg, 160mg, and 240mg) in healthy subjects.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence and severity of adverse events</outcome>
      <timepoint>70 days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum concentrations of SHR01314</outcome>
      <timepoint>70 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum anti-drug antibodies</outcome>
      <timepoint>70 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Provide written informed consent before any study assessment is performed.

          2. Male or female between the ages of 18 and 55 years (inclusive) at screening,

          3. Good general health as defined as no clinically relevant abnormalities identified by a
             detailed medical history, full physical examination including measurement of vital
             signs, 12-lead ECG, and clinical laboratory tests. (Evaluations must be considered
             "not clinically significant (NCS)" if outside of the reference range).

          4. Body Mass Index (BMI) of 18 to 30 kg/m2 (inclusive), and a total body weight =50 kg at
             screening.

          5. Willing and able to comply with scheduled visits, treatment plan, laboratory tests,
             and other study procedures as specified in the protocol.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Subjects who are investigational site staff members or subjects who are Sponsor
             employees directly involved in the conduct of the study.

          2. Use of other investigational drugs within 5 half-lives of screening, or within 30 days
             of screening (for small molecules), or until the expected pharmacodynamic effect has
             returned to baseline (for biologics), whichever is longer.

          3. Pregnant or nursing (lactating) women, where pregnancy is defined as the state of a
             female after conception and until the termination of gestation, confirmed by a
             positive human chorionic gonadotropin laboratory test at screening or Day -1.

          4. Females of child-bearing potential (defined as all females physiologically capable of
             becoming pregnant) and males who are unwilling or unable to use effective
             contraception during the study and until 2 months after drug administration
             (approximately 5 half-lives). Effective contraception is defined use of two of the
             following methods of contraception:

               -  Barrier method: Condom or Occlusive cap (diaphragm or cervical/vault caps).

               -  Female sterilization: have had surgical bilateral oophorectomy (with or without
                  hysterectomy) or tubal ligation at least six weeks before taking study treatment.
                  In case of oophorectomy alone, only when the reproductive status of the woman has
                  been confirmed by follow up hormone level assessment.

               -  Male sterilization

               -  Use of established oral, injected or implanted hormonal methods of contraception,

               -  Use of an intrauterine device or intrauterine system.

          5. Blood donation of approximately 500 mL within 56 days prior to dosing on Day 1 and for
             the duration of the study.

          6. A positive urine drug screen at screening and Day -1.

          7. History of regular alcohol consumption exceeding 14 drinks/week for females or 21
             drinks/week for males (1 drink = 100 mL of wine or 360 mL of beer or 45 mL of hard
             liquor) within 6 months of screening.

          8. Use of tobacco or nicotine containing products (including e-cigarettes) at any time
             within six months before screening and for the duration of the study.

          9. History of hypersensitivity to any of the study biologics, drugs or to drugs of
             similar chemical classes.

         10. History of malignancy of any organ system, treated or untreated, within the past 5
             years, regardless of whether there is evidence of local recurrence or metastases.

         11. History or complication of tuberculosis.

         12. Has a clinically significant abnormality on the screening chest x-ray that, in the
             opinion of the investigator, could affect the subject's safety or ability to
             participate in the study; including, but not limited to, evidence of previous exposure
             to tuberculosis.

         13. History of immunodeficiency diseases, including a positive human immunodeficiency
             virus (HIV) test result at screening.

         14. Positive hepatitis B or hepatitis C test result at Screening

         15. Recent (within the last 3 years) and/or recurrent history of acute or chronic
             bronchospastic pulmonary disease (including asthma and chronic obstructive pulmonary
             disease, treated or not treated).

         16. Use of live vaccines (attenuated) within 3 months before study Day 1 or at any time
             during the study.

         17. Evidence of latent tuberculosis by QuantiFERON screening.

         18. Use of any of the following, unless agreed as non-clinically relevant by the
             Investigator and the Sponsor:

               1. Prescription medication within four weeks prior to dosing on Day 1

               2. Over-the-counter medication (excluding paracetamol) within seven days prior to
                  the treatment day. Paracetamol use must be limited to 2 g per day and no more
                  than three days usage in the four weeks prior to dosing on Day 1

               3. Vitamin therapy or dietary supplements within seven days prior to dosing on Day 1
                  and for the duration of the study

               4. Herbal supplements within 28 days prior to the dosing on Day 1 and for the
                  duration of the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2>The people administering the treatment/s</masking2>
    <masking3 />
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/08/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/09/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Atridia Pty Limited - Sydney</hospital>
    <postcode>2000 - Sydney</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Atridia Pty Ltd.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, single dose escalating, study in 5
      sequential cohorts to investigate the effect of a single s.c. injection of SHR-1314 at 5 dose
      levels (20mg, 40mg, 80mg, 160mg, and 240mg) in healthy subjects. Each cohort will consist of
      6 subjects receiving active drug and 2 subjects receiving placebo, for a total of
      approximately 40 subjects dosed at one study site.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02934412</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Nicholas Farinola, B.Sc,BMBS</name>
      <address>Royal Adelaide Hospital</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kathy You</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>kathyyou@atridia.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>