<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5399">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/10/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/10/2014</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02281084</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Safety and Efficacy Study of CC-486 and Durvalumab in Subjects With Myelodysplastic Syndromes</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 2, International, Multicenter, Randomized, Open-label, Parallel Group to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of Cc-486 (Oral Azacitidine) Alone in Combination With Durvalumab (MEDI4736) in Subjects With Myelodysplastic Syndromes Who Fail to Achieve an Objective Response to Treatment With Azacitidine for Injection or Decitabine</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>CC-486-MDS-006</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haematological diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other blood disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - CC-486 (ORAL AZACITIDINE)
Treatment: drugs - Durvalumab

Experimental: Monotherapy - Dispense CC-486 (Oral azacitidine) alone to subjects divided in 2 Cohorts of Stable versus Progressive disease

Experimental: Combination Therapy - Dispense CC-486 (Oral azacitidine) and Durvalumab in combination to subjects divided in 2 Cohorts of Stable versus Progressive disease


Treatment: drugs: CC-486 (ORAL AZACITIDINE)
200 mg CC-486 (Oral Azacitidine) will be given for the first 21 days of each 28-day treatment cycle

Treatment: drugs: Durvalumab


</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Response Rate - Subjects achieving an objective response according to the modified IWG -international working group- 2006 criteria</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 3 years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall survival - Subjects surviving until the end of follow-up period</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 3 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to onset of responses - Number of days from starting treatment to the occurrence of response by the end of follow-up as per modified IWG -international working group- 2006 criteria</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 3 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of responses - Number of days from beginning of response (modified IWG -international working group- criteria) to relapse during the treatment and follow-up period</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 3 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression free survival - Number of days from starting treatment to disease progression or death from any cause</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 3 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stabilization of progression disease - Subjects with progressive disease at baseline achieving stable disease status</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 3 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to achieving stable disease - Number of days from starting treatment to first documented Stable Disease</outcome>
      <timepoint>Approximately 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of stable disease - Time from first documented Stable Disease to Disease Progression</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 3 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression to AML - subjects with disease progression to FAB-defined (French American British) AML (Acute Myeloid Leukemia)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 3 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to AML progression - Time from starting treatment to onset of AML (Acute Myeloid Leukemia)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 3 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse Events - Type, frequency, severity of AEs (adverse events) and relationship of AEs (adverse events) to CC-486</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 3 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetic - Cmax - Maximum observed plasma concentration</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetic - AUCt - Area under the plasma concentration-time</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetic - AUCinf - Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from Time 0 extrapolated to infinity</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetic - Tmax - Time to Cmax, obtained directly from the observed concentration versus time data.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetic - t1/2 - Terminal phase half-life in plasma</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetic - CL/F - Apparent total clearance</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetic - Vz/F - volume of distribution (Vz/F)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Male or female, = 18 years of age at the time of signing the informed consent document

          2. Documented diagnosis of MDS (MYELODYSPLASTIC SYNDROMES), classified according to FAB
             (FRENCH-AMERICAN BRITISH) classification criteria

          3. Adequate course of treatment with an injectable hypomethylating agent (azacitidine for
             injection or decitabine) as the last therapeutic intervention for MDS (MYELODYSPLASTIC
             SYNDROMES) prior to beginning screening for this study. Adequate is defined as:

               -  having received at least 6 consecutive 4-week treatment cycles with azacitidine
                  for injection, or

               -  having received at least 4 consecutive 6-week treatment cycles with decitabine
                  (3-day regimen) or at least 6 consecutive 4-week treatment cycles with decitabine
                  (5-day regimen), or

               -  having demonstrated inability to tolerate treatment with an injectable
                  hypomethylating agent because of unacceptable drug-related toxicity after at
                  least 3 months of attempted treatment: Three 28-day cycles of azacitidine for
                  injection or decitabine 5-day regimen; two 42-day cycles of decitabine 3-day
                  regimen.

          4. Documented disease progression or stable disease as best response to treatment (or
             attempted treatment) with azacitidine for injection or decitabine. Those achieving an
             objective response to treatment regimen with an injectable Hypomethylating agent (HMA)
             are excluded from participation in this study.

             Definitions of disease progression are modified from IWG (INTERNATIONAL WORKING GROUP)
             2006 criteria and include:

               -  Pre-injectable HMA (HYPOMETHYLATING AGENT) baseline bone marrow myeloblasts:

                    1. Less than 5%: = 100% increase to = 8% blasts

                    2. = 5%: = 50% increase to = 10% blasts Note: = 30% blasts is considered AML
                       (ACUTE MYELOID LEUKEMIAT) per FAB (FRENCH-AMERICAN BRITISH)classification.
                       Subjects known to have = 30% blasts are not eligible for inclusion in this
                       study. RECOG (Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group) nizing limitations of
                       blast cell quantification, this protocol will allow subjects with
                       pre-enrollment bone marrow blast counts up to 33% on the screening bone
                       marrow examination to be considered for inclusion. Assessment may be made
                       according to local bone marrow examination to facilitate enrollment of
                       eligible subjects into the treatment phase of the study.

               -  Any clinical worsening from pre-injectable HMA (HYPOMETHYLATING AGENT) baseline
                  condition, including:

                  a. sustained clinically-significant worsening (investigator's assessment) from
                  baseline granulocyte, platelet, or hemoglobin values (= 2 values, separated by =
                  2 weeks)

               -  worsening granulocytes should be = 50% decrease from pre-injectable HMA
                  (HYPOMETHYLATING AGENT) baseline value

               -  worsening platelets should be = 50% decrease from pre-injectable HMA
                  (HYPOMETHYLATING AGENT) baseline value (untransfused)

               -  worsening hemoglobin should be = 1.5 g/dL decrease from preinjectable HMA
                  (HYPOMETHYLATING AGENT) baseline value in subjects not receiving RBC (RED BLOOD
                  CELL) transfusions b. meaningful worsening in RBC (RED BLOOD CELL) or platelet
                  transfusion requirement

             Definition of stable disease is based on modified IWG (INTERNATIONAL WORKING GROUP)
             2006 criteria:

             - Failure to achieve any objective response (CR - complete remission, PR - partial
             remissino, mCR - marrow complete remission, or HI - hematologic improvement), but no
             evidence of disease progression within the 8 weeks leading to the subject's first dose
             of IP (INVESTIGATIONAL PRODUCT) in this study (Cycle 1, Day 1)

          5. Have the last dose of the prior treatment regimen (injectable HMA (HYPOMETHYLATING
             AGENT) - azacitidine for injection or decitabine) not more than 16 weeks prior to
             screening for this study (date of informed consent signature).

          6. No less than 3 weeks between the last dose of the prior treatment regimen (injectable
             HMA (HYPOMETHYLATING AGENT) - azacitidine for injection or decitabine) and the planned
             date of first dose of IP (IINVESTIGATIONAL PRODUCT).

          7. Have an ECOG (EASTERN COOPERATIVE ONCOLOGY GROUP) performance status of 0, 1, or 2

          8. Females subjects of childbearing potential (FCBP)1 may participate, providing they
             meet the following conditions:

               1. Have two negative pregnancy tests as verified by the investigator prior to
                  starting any IP therapy: serum pregnancy test at screening and negative serum or
                  urine pregnancy test (investigator's discretion) within 72 hours prior to
                  starting treatment with IP (Cycle 1, Day 1). They must agree to ongoing pregnancy
                  testing during the course of the study (before beginning each subsequent cycle of
                  treatment), and after the last dose of any IP. This applies even if the subject
                  practices complete abstinence2 from heterosexual contact.

               2. Agree to practice true abstinence2 (which must be reviewed on a monthly basis and
                  source documented) or agree to the use of highly effective methods of
                  contraception from 28 days prior to starting durvalumab or azacitidine, and must
                  agree to continue using such precautions while taking durvalumab or azacitidine
                  (including dose interruptions) and for up to 90 days after the last dose of
                  durvalumab or azacitidine. Cessation of contraception after this point should be
                  discussed with a responsible physician.

               3. Agree to abstain from breastfeeding during study participation and for at least
                  90 days after the last dose of IP.

               4. Refrain from egg cell donation while taking durvalumab and for at least 90 days
                  after the last dose of durvalumab.

             Note that the screening serum pregnancy test can also be used as the test prior to
             starting IP (Investigational Product) if it is performed within the 72-hour timeframe.

          9. Male subjects must:

               1. Either practice true abstinence2 from heterosexual contact (which must be
                  reviewed on a monthly basis) or agree to avoid fathering a child, to use highly
                  effective methods of contraception, male condom plus spermicide during sexual
                  contact with a pregnant female or a female of child bearing potential (even if he
                  has undergone a successful vasectomy) from starting dose of IP (Cycle 1 Day 1),
                  including dose interruptions through 90 days after receipt of the last dose of
                  durvalumab or azacitidine.

               2. Refrain from semen or sperm donation while taking IP and for at least 90 days
                  after the last dose of IP.

         10. Understand and voluntarily sign an informed consent document prior to any
             study-related assessments or procedures conducted.

         11. Be able to adhere to the study visit schedule and other protocol requirements.

         12. Understand and voluntarily sign a biomarker-specific component of the informed consent
             document prior to any study-related procedures conducted.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Rapidly-progressing MDS (MYELODYSPLASTIC SYNDROMES), defined as:

               1. Known clinically-significant doubling in marrow or perIP (INVESTIGATIONAL
                  PRODUCT) heral blood blast percentage (to = 20%) in the 8-week period leading to
                  the first dose of IP (INVESTIGATIONAL PRODUCT) (Cycle 1, Day 1)

               2. =100% increase in WBC count (myeloid cell line and monocyte series) within the
                  8-week period leading to Cycle 1, Day 1

          2. Acute myelogenous leukemia (AML (ACUTE MYELOID LEUKEMIA) - FAB
             (FRENCH-AMERICAN-BRITISH) classification: = 30% blasts in bone marrow). Subjects known
             to have = 30% blasts are not eligible for inclusion in this study. Recognizing
             limitations of blast cell quantification, this protocol will allow subjects with
             pre-enrollment (screening/baseline) bone marrow blast counts up to 33% to be
             considered for inclusion.

          3. Prior allogeneic stem cell transplant

          4. Prior exposure to the investigational oral formulation of decitabine, or other oral
             azacitidine derivative at any time in the subject's prior history

          5. Prior or ongoing response (IWG 2006: HI, PR, CR, or marrow CR) to treatment with
             azacitidine for injection or decitabine, at any time in the subject's prior history,
             which includes relapsed disease

          6. Ongoing medically significant adverse events from previous treatment, regardless of
             the time period

          7. Use of any of the following within 28 days prior to the first dose of IP
             (INVESTIGATIONAL PRODUCT):

               1. thrombopoiesis-stimulating agents ([TSAs]; eg, Romiplostim, Eltrombopag,
                  Interleukin-11)

               2. ESAs (Erythropoiesis stimulating agent) and other RBC (Red blood cell)
                  hematopoietic growth factors (eg, interleukin-3)

               3. hydroxyurea

          8. Concurrent use of corticosteroids unless the subject is on a stable or decreasing dose
             for = 1 week prior to enrollment for medical conditions other than MDS
             (MYELODYSPLASTIC SYNDROMES)

          9. History of inflammatory bowel disease (eg, Crohn's disease, ulcerative colitis),
             celiac disease (ie, sprue), prior gastrectomy or upper bowel removal, or any other
             gastrointestinal disorder or defect that would interfere with the absorption,
             distribution, metabolism or excretion of the IP (INVESTIGATIONAL PRODUCT) and/or
             predispose the subject to an increased risk of gastrointestinal toxicity

         10. Prior history of malignancies, other than MDS (MYELODYSPLASTIC SYNDROMES), unless the
             subject has been free of the disease for = 3 years. However, subjects with the
             following history/concurrent conditions are allowed:

               1. Basal or squamous cell carcinoma of the skin

               2. Carcinoma in situ of the cervix

               3. Carcinoma in situ of the breast

               4. Incidental histologic finding of prostate cancer (T1a or T1b using the tumor,
                  nodes, metastasis [TNM] clinical staging system)

         11. Significant active cardiac disease within the previous 6 months, including:

               1. New York Heart Association (NYHA) class IV congestive heart failure;

               2. Unstable angina or angina requiring surgical or medical intervention; and/or

               3. Myocardial infarction

         12. Uncontrolled systemic fungal, bacterial, or viral infection (defined as ongoing
             signs/symptoms related to the infection without improvement despite appropriate
             antibiotics, antiviral therapy, and/or other treatment)

         13. Known Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) or Hepatitis C (HCV) infection, or evidence
             of active Hepatitis B Virus (HBV) infection

         14. Any of the following laboratory abnormalities:

               1. Serum AST/SGOT (Aspartate transaminase / Serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase)
                  or ALT/SGPT (Alanine aminotransaminase / Serum glutamic pyruvate transaminase) &gt;
                  2.5 x ULN (upper limit of normal)

               2. Serum total bilirubin &gt; 1.5 x ULN (upper limit of normal). Higher levels are
                  acceptable if these can be attributed to active red blood cell precursor
                  destruction within the bone marrow (ie, ineffective erythropoiesis). Subjects are
                  excluded if there is evidence of autoimmune hemolytic anemia manifested as a
                  corrected reticulocyte count of &gt; 2% with either a positive Coombs' test or over
                  50% of indirect bilirubin

               3. Serum creatinine &gt; 2.5 x ULN (upper limit of normal)

               4. Absolute WBC (white blood cell) count = 20 x 109/L

         15. Known or suspected hypersensitivity to azacitidine, mannitol, or durvalumab, its
             constituents, or to any other humanized monoclonal antibody

         16. Pregnant, planning to become pregnant starting from 28 days prior to receiving CC-486
             or durvalumab, throughout your participation in the study, and for at least 90 days
             following your last dose of study treatment, or breast-feeding females

         17. Any significant medical condition, laboratory abnormality, or psychiatric illness that
             would prevent the subject from participating in the study

         18. Any condition including the presence of laboratory abnormalities, which places the
             subject at unacceptable risk if he/she were to participate in the study

         19. Any condition that confounds the ability to interpret data from the study, including
             known or suspected conditions other than MDS (MYELODYSPLASTIC SYNDROMES), associated
             with anemia

         20. Having received any prior MAb (monoclonal antibodies) against CTLA-4 (cytotoxic T
             lymphocyte-associated antigen), PD-1, or PD-L1 or having received other
             investigational MAbs (monoclonalantibodies) within 6 months

         21. Clinical evidence of central nervous system (CNS) or pulmonary leukostasis, or CNS
             leukemia

         22. Current or prior use of immunosuppressive medication within 14 days prior to the first
             dose of durvalumab. The following are exceptions to this criterion:

               1. Intranasal, inhaled, topical or local steroid injections (eg, intra-articular
                  injection);

               2. Systemic corticosteroids at physiologic doses not to exceed 10 mg/day of
                  prednisone or equivalent;

               3. Steroids as premedication for hypersensitivity reactions (eg, computed tomography
                  [CT] scan premedication).

         23. Active or prior documented autoimmune or inflammatory disorders (including
             inflammatory bowel disease [eg, colitis, Crohn's disease], diverticulitis with the
             exception of a prior episode that has resolved or diverticulosis, celiac disease,
             irritable bowel disease, or other serious gastrointestinal chronic conditions
             associated with diarrhea; systemic lupus erythematosus; Wegener's syndrome
             [granulomatosis with polyangiitis]; myasthenia gravis; Graves' disease; rheumatoid
             arthritis; hypophysitis, uveitis; etc) within the past 3 years prior to the start of
             treatment. The following are exceptions to this criterion:

               1. Subjects with vitiligo or alopecia;

               2. Subjects with hypothyroidism (eg, following Hashimoto syndrome) stable on hormone
                  replacement for = 3 months; or

               3. Subjects with psoriasis not requiring systemic treatment

         24. History of primary immunodeficiency

         25. Receipt of live, attenuated vaccine within 30 days prior to the first dose of
             durvalumab (NOTE: Subjects, if enrolled, should not receive live vaccine during the
             study and 30 days after the last dose of durvalumab).

         26. Active myeloproliferative neoplasms (MPN) and chronic myelomonocytic leukemia (CMML)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>6/07/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>194</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>11/10/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,SA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Westmead Hospital - Westmead</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Clayton</hospital>
    <hospital>Cabrini Hospital - Malvern</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Perth Hospital - Perth</hospital>
    <postcode>2145 - Westmead</postcode>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
    <postcode>3144 - Malvern</postcode>
    <postcode>4029 - Herston</postcode>
    <postcode>6000 - Perth</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Colorado</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Connecticut</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Illinois</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Iowa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Kansas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Kentucky</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Jersey</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Pennsylvania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Wisconsin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Brussel</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Bruxelles</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Liège</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Ottignies</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Marseille Cedex 9</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Paris</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Toulouse</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Dresden</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Dusseldorf</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Freiburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Halle</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Hannover</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Leipzig</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>München</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Allessandria</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Bologna</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Firenze</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Milano</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Rionero in Vulture</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Roma</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Olsztyn</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Warszawa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Wroclaw</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Granada</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Malaga</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Oviedo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Salamanca</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Sevilla</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Valencia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Boston</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Cambridge</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Chelmsford</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Leeds</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Manchester</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Middlesex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Southampton</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Celgene</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Evaluate the safety and efficacy of CC-486 and Durvalumab in Subjects with Myelodysplastic
      Syndromes who failed to achieve an objective response post iHMA treatment</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02281084</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>DU Lam, MD</name>
      <address>Celgene</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Director, Clinical Trial Disclosure</name>
      <address />
      <phone>1-888-260-1599</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>clinicaltrialdisclosure@celgene.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>