<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3895">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/04/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/04/2013</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01836146</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>International First-in-Human Study of the EnligHTN Generation 2 System in Patients With Drug-resistant Uncontrolled Hypertension</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle />
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>EnligHTN III</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>1202</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hypertension</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Renal Denervation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Hypertension</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - EnligHTN Renal Artery Ablation Catheter

Experimental: Renal Artery Ablation - 


Treatment: devices: EnligHTN Renal Artery Ablation Catheter


</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety Objective - To characterize the rate of serious procedural and device related adverse events from date of procedure through 6 months post procedure, as adjudicated by the Clinical Events Committee (CEC).</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Performance objective - To characterize the reduction of office Systolic Blood Pressure at 6 months post procedure as compared to baseline.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Ambulatory Blood Pressure - Characterization of the change in Ambulatory Blood Pressure parameters over time as compared to baseline</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month, 3 month, 6 month, 12 month, 18 month, 2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>New renal artery stenosis or aneurysm at the site of ablation - Characterization of renovascular safety as measured by new renal artery stenosis or aneurysm at the site of ablation over time as compared to baseline</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month, 3 month, 6 month, 12 month, 18 month, 2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Renal Function Change - Characterization of renal function change over time as compared to baseline as measured by changes in: eGFR, serum creatinine and cystatin C</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month, 3 month, 6 month, 12 month, 18 month, 2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Subject is = 18 and = 80 years of age at time of consent

          -  Subject must be able and willing to provide written informed consent

          -  Subject must be able and willing to comply with the required follow-up schedule

          -  Subject has office Systolic Blood Pressure = 160 mmHg at confirmatory visit

          -  Subject has a daytime mean Systolic Ambulatory Blood Pressure &gt; 135 mmHg during the
             two week screening period

          -  Subject has an office Systolic Blood Pressure that remains =160 mmHg despite the
             stable use of =3 antihypertensive medications concurrently at maximally tolerated
             doses, of which one is a diuretic or subject was previously on diuretic but documented
             to be diuretic intolerant, for a minimum of 14 days prior to the procedure and with an
             expectation to maintain for a minimum of 180 days post procedure.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Subject has significant renovascular abnormalities such as renal artery stenosis &gt; 30%
             in either renal artery

          -  Subject has undergone prior renal angioplasty, renal denervation, indwelling renal
             stents, and/or abdominal aortic stent grafts

          -  Subject has hemodynamically significant valvular heart disease as determined by the
             Study Investigator

          -  Subject has a life expectancy less than 12 months, as determined by a Study
             Investigator

          -  Subject is participating in another clinical study which has the potential to impact
             their hypertension management (pharmaceutical/device/homeopathic)

          -  Subject is pregnant, nursing, or of childbearing potential and is not using adequate
             contraceptive methods

          -  Subject has active systemic infection

          -  Subject has renal arteries with diameter(s) &lt; 4 mm in diameter or &lt;20 mm in length

          -  Subject has an estimated Glomerular Filtrate Rate (eGFR) &lt;45 mL/min per 1.73 m2 using
             the Modified Diet in Renal Disease (MDRD) formula

          -  Subject has Diabetes Mellitus Type I

          -  Subject has multiple main renal arteries in either kidney

          -  Subject has an identified secondary cause of hypertension (for example, including, but
             not limited to, Polycystic kidney disease, Cushing's syndrome, Aldosteronism)

          -  Subject has evidence of significant abdominal aortic aneurysm (defined as maximum
             diameter of &gt;4 cm)

          -  Subject has had a myocardial infarction, unstable angina pectoris or cerebrovascular
             accident less than 180 days prior to enrollment

          -  Subject is expected to have cardiovascular intervention within the next 180 days

          -  Subject has a condition which would interfere with the accurate interpretation of the
             study objectives including but not limited to a large arm diameter that is unable to
             accommodate the blood pressure cuff or arrhythmia that interferes with automatic pulse
             sensing.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/04/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>39</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/09/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St Andrews Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>St. Vincent's Hospital Melbourne - Fizroy</hospital>
    <hospital>Monash Heart/Southern Health - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode> - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode> - Fizroy</postcode>
    <postcode> - Melbourne</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Dunedin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>St. Jude Medical</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this First-in-Human Clinical investigation is to evaluate the safety and
      performance of the St. Jude Medical EnligHTN Generation 2 Renal Denervation System for the
      treatment of patients with drug-resistant uncontrolled hypertension.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01836146</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>