<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6094">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02908737</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Clinical Evaluation of Bass and Treble Controls for CI Subjects</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Clinical Evaluation of Bass and Treble Controls for CI Subjects</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>CLASS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>CLTD5640</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hearing Loss</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Ear</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Deafness</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - Bass and Treble

Experimental: Bass and Treble controls - Bass and Treble controls are clinician enabled and provide the recipient with access to the adjustment of low and high frequency sound balance, known as Bass and Treble respectively.


Treatment: devices: Bass and Treble
Bass and Treble controls are clinician enabled and provide the recipient with access to the adjustment of low and high frequency sound balance, known as Bass and Treble respectively

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Non-inferior speech perception with preferred Bass and Treble settings compared to the baseline Bass and Treble settings - Co-primary endpoint #1: This endpoint is to test that speech perception scores in noise with preferred Bass and Treble settings are non-inferior to the baseline settings. Subjects will be tested at visit one with their own settings (Baseline), and then again after four weeks use of the Bass and Treble feature. The speech signal will arrive from zero degrees azimuth at a level of 65 dB SPL, the noise will also arrive from zero degrees azimuth, however the noise will adapt according to subject responses.
o-primary endpoint #2: This endpoint is to test that speech perception scores in quiet with preferred Bass and Treble settings are non-inferior to the baseline settings. Subjects will be tested at visit one with their own settings (Baseline), and then again after four weeks use of the Bass and Treble feature. The speech signal will arrive from zero degrees azimuth at a level of 50 dB SPL.</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Non-inferior sentence recognition in four-talker babble noise with Bass and Treble values set to the minimum (-6 Bass, - 6 Treble) compared to the baseline condition when the speech and noise are from the front - Secondary endpoint #1: This endpoint is to test that speech perception scores in noise with Bass and Treble settings set to minimum (-6, -6) are non-inferior to the baseline settings. Subjects will be tested at visit one. The speech signal will arrive from zero degrees azimuth at a level of 65 dB SPL, the noise will also arrive from zero degrees azimuth, however the noise will adapt according to subject responses.</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Six years of age or older

          2. At least 3 months experience with the CP810, CP910 or CP920 sound processor

          3. At least 3 months experience with the CI24RE or CI500 series implant

          4. Willingness to participate in and to comply with all requirements of the protocol</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>100</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Unrealistic expectations on the part of the subject, regarding the possible benefits,
             risks and limitations that are inherent to the procedure and prosthetic device

          2. Additional disabilities that would prevent participation in evaluations</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>34</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/09/2016</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Sydney Cochlear Implant Centre - Sydney</hospital>
    <hospital>Cochlear Limited - Sydney</hospital>
    <postcode>2024 - Sydney</postcode>
    <postcode>2109 - Sydney</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Cochlear</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The clinical study is designed to evaluate the safety and effectiveness of recipient
      controlled Bass and Treble.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02908737</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Chris D Warren, Audiology</name>
      <address>Employee</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Saji Maruthurkkara, Audiology</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+61294253637</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>smaruthurkkara@cochlear.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>