<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5573">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/12/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/12/2010</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01260831</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluating Processes of Care &amp; the Outcomes of Children in Hospital (EPOCH)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluating Processes of Care &amp; the Outcomes of Children in Hospital (EPOCH): a Cluster Randomized Trial of the Bedside Paediatric Early Warning System</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>EPOCH</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>1000018562</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Critically Ill Children</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - Implementation of Bedside Paediatric Early Warning System
Other interventions - Hospital Standard of Care

Experimental: Intervention Hospitals - hospitals randomized to implement bedsidePEWS documentation system (vital sign assessment record)

Active Comparator: Control Hospitals - hospitals randomized to continue with their pre existing documentation system (vital sign assessment record)


Other interventions: Implementation of Bedside Paediatric Early Warning System
The Bedside Paediatric Early Warning System (Bedside PEWS) is a documentation-based system of care that will replace existing documentation systems for vital signs in inpatient ward areas in hospitals randomized to implement Bedside-PEWS. Frontline staff education within each hospital will occur over a period of three months preceding a 5 week run-in implementation phase, which will be followed by hospital-wide implementation. The Bedside-PEWS documentation record will become the primary method of documentation for vital signs and related data.

Other interventions: Hospital Standard of Care
Hospitals randomized to standard care will continue with established methods of care. This will include the use of calling criteria and/or the expert model to identify children at risk. As in intervention hospitals, existing MET-RRT practices, established staffing and documentation practices will continue.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>All Cause Hospital Mortality (Intervention Phase) - All cause hospital mortality includes all deaths of eligible inpatients who were cared for in an eligible inpatient ward and will be prospectively assessed for 52 weeks following the 5-week run in period at intervention hospitals.
The following sub-group analyses will be performed: [1] Hospital size. Hospitals with &gt;200 eligible inpatient ward beds will be one group and those with &lt;200 eligible inpatient ward beds the other. [2] Hospitals with and without medical emergency teams. [3] Hospitals with ECMO for children. [4] patients with urgent PICU admission initiated in an inpatient ward.</outcome>
      <timepoint>for 52 weeks starting at Week 31</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Significant Clinical Deterioration Events - This will be defined as the provision of significant respiratory or circulatory therapies or cardiopulmonary resuscitation in the 12 hours before transfer from inpatient ward, or death without DNR order in an inpatient ward.
The following sub-group analyses will be performed: [1] Hospital size. Hospitals with &gt;200 eligible inpatient ward beds will be one group and those with &lt;200 eligible inpatient ward beds the other. [2] Hospitals with and without medical emergency teams. [3] Hospitals with ECMO for children. [4] patients with urgent PICU admission initiated in an inpatient ward.</outcome>
      <timepoint>for 26 weeks starting at Week 0 (baseline) and for 52 weeks starting at week 31 (intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>For Hospitals:

          -  provide care for more than 200 inpatient admissions aged &lt;18 years and &gt;37 weeks
             gestational age in eligible inpatient wards each year

          -  have specialised paediatric physicians (including paediatricians, paediatric surgeons,
             other paediatric sub-specialists) and, one or more intensive care unit (PICU) that
             provides care for children. A PICU is a designated, staffed area for prolonged
             mechanical ventilation, invasive monitoring and circulatory support for children-
             including but not limited to neonates. Other areas designated for patients of
             increased acuity, such as 'constant observation' or 'high dependency' or 'step-down'
             units will be regarded as part of the PICU where the PICU staff physicians are wholly
             or jointly responsible for the care of children in these areas (can write orders in
             the chart).

          -  may or may not have a MET-RRT for children. A MET-RRT is defined as an identified team
             of one or more trained healthcare professionals who report to an on service PICU
             physician, and perform urgent consultations on hospital inpatients.

        For inpatient wards:

          -  areas where care is provided to patients who are admitted to the hospital, other than
             PICU, operating rooms, and other designated areas where anaesthetist-supervised
             procedures are performed. All eligible inpatient wards will participate in the study.

        For patients:

        Within eligible hospitals we will study patients older than 37 weeks gestational age and
        less than 18 years who are admitted to eligible inpatient wards, who receive care in an
        eligible inpatient area during the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>For hospitals:

          -  have plans to introduce a new 'medical emergency team' during the study, and where a
             severity of illness score (Brighton, Cardiff, PEWS, Bedside PEWS or other unpublished
             score) is used in ward areas

          -  hospitals where randomization is not deemed acceptable. These exclusion criteria
             ensure that major system changes including introduction of MET-RRT, new documentation
             systems, physician staffing, and hospital capacity will not bias results.

        For patients:

          -  those who are less than 37 weeks gestational age throughout their hospitalization

          -  are cared for exclusively in an NICU

          -  children who are admitted directly to a PICU and die before PICU discharge and thus
             have not received care in an eligible inpatient ward</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/01/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>144539</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/06/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Brussels</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Alberta</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>British Columbia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>New Brunswick</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Nova Scotia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Quebec</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ireland</country>
      <state>Dublin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Rome</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Rotterdam</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Hospital for Sick Children</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to evaluate the impact of Bedside Paediatric Early Warning
      System (Bedside-PEWS) on early identification of children at risk for near and actual
      cardiopulmonary arrest, hospital mortality, processes of care and PICU resource utilization.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01260831</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Christopher Parshuram, MD</name>
      <address>The Hospital for Sick Children</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>