<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3682">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/11/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/11/2012</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01726621</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>User Evaluation of the MiniMed 620G and 640G Insulin Pumps</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A User Evaluation of the MiniMed® 620G and 640G Insulin Pumps and Guardian® Link Transmitter</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>CEP267</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 1 Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - Medtronic MiniMed 620G or 640G Insulin Pump

Other: Insulin dependent diabetics - Subjects currently using an insulin pump transferred to use the Medtronic MiniMed 620G and 640G insulin pumps and Guardian Link transmitter


Treatment: devices: Medtronic MiniMed 620G or 640G Insulin Pump
Subjects to use the Medtronic MiniMed 620G or 640G Insulin Pump and Guardian Link transmitter to manage their diabetes for 4 - 6 weeks.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>User Acceptance of the New MiniMed 620G and 640G Insulin Pumps and Guardian Link Transmitter - Descriptive summary will be used to characterize the results of the study questionnaires. The questionnaire will use a Likert scale (rating of 1 to 7) to assess overall subject acceptance of the MiniMed 620G, 640G, and Guardian Link Transmitter. A response of 4 or greater on the Likert scale will be considered positive and indicate and product acceptance.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Four weeks of pump wear</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Subject is 7 years or older at time of screening

          -  Subject is current insulin pump user for at least 3 months

          -  Subject has the following Continuous Glucose Monitoring experience as determined by
             the Investigator:

               -  Has experience and is able to insert/change sensor by herself/himself and

               -  Has experience and can recharge the transmitter and

               -  Has experience and can read sensor data in real-time on her/his pump screen

          -  Subject has signed a Patient Informed Consent form and is willing to comply with the
             study procedures;

          -  Subject is willing to complete study questionnaires throughout the study

          -  Must have one of the following clinical diagnosis:

               -  Type 1 diabetes, for a minimum of 6 months prior to enrollment

               -  Insulin requiring type 2 diabetes, for a minimum of 6 months prior to enrollment</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>7</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>99</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Female subject has a positive urine pregnancy screening test.

          -  Female subject who plans to become pregnant during the course of study. If a woman
             becomes pregnant during participation, she will be withdrawn

          -  Subject has any condition that, in the opinion of the Investigator or qualified
             Investigational Center staff, may preclude him/her from participating in the study and
             completing study related procedures.

          -  Subject has impaired vision or hearing problems that could compromise the handling of
             the device as determined by Investigator or qualified Investigational Center staff

          -  Subject is actively participating in an investigational study (drug or device) wherein
             he/she has received treatment from an investigational study drug or investigational
             study device in the last 2 weeks.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/03/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>55</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/12/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>St Vincent Hospital and The University of Melbourne - Fitzroy</hospital>
    <hospital>The Royal Melbourne Hospital - Patkville</hospital>
    <postcode>3065 - Fitzroy</postcode>
    <postcode>3050 - Patkville</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Denmark</country>
      <state>Herlev</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Medtronic Diabetes</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This six center international study will include two United Kingdom National Health Service
      centers, two centers in Melbourne, Australia and one center each in Denmark and Spain. The
      objective of the study is to evaluate subject acceptance of the a new insulin pump and
      transmitter together with the accompanying training materials. Descriptive data from
      participant questionnaires and device uploads will be evaluated.

      Pediatric subjects between the ages of 7 - 18 years and adults from the age of 19 years of
      age upwards, who currently use an insulin pump in the management of their type 1 or type 2
      diabetes, will be invited to participate. Each subject will be trained on the study device
      and then use it for approximately six weeks. During this time there will be three in-clinic
      visits and four follow-up phone calls, scheduled at the subjects' convenience. At the end of
      this period, they will revert back to their original insulin pump and complete a
      questionnaire on the study pump training materials, features and usability.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01726621</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Pratik Choudhary, MBBS, MRCP</name>
      <address>King's College London</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>