<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4373">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/08/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/08/2009</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00962585</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy and Safety of S-equol on Vasomotor Symptoms in Menopausal Patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomized, Double Blind, Multicenter, Placebo Controlled, Proof of Concept Trial to Assess the Efficacy and Safety of 4 Weeks Treatment With AUS-131 (S-equol) on Vasomotor Symptoms in Menopausal Patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>AUS-CT03</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Menopause</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Placebo
Treatment: drugs - S-equol

Placebo Comparator: Placebo - Placebo

Experimental: S-equol 10 mg BID - S-equol 20 mg total daily dose

Experimental: S-equol 50 mg BID - S-equol 100 mg total daily dose

Experimental: S-equol 150 mg BID - S-equol 300 mg total daily dose


Treatment: drugs: Placebo


Treatment: drugs: S-equol
Eligible patients meeting all study entry criteria were randomly assigned to receive one of the following active treatments for 4 weeks:
S-equol 10 mg BID (20 mg total daily dose)
S-equol 50 mg BID (100 mg total daily dose)
S-equol 150 mg BID (300 mg total daily dose)

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Change in Frequency of Moderate to Severe Vasomotor Symptoms (MSVS) Baseline at Week 4 (2-week Period) - The primary efficacy endpoint for this study was the change from Baseline (Day 0) in the frequency of MSVS (difference between Baseline [2-week run-in period] and Week 4), where the baseline MSVS frequency was captured over 14 ± 2 day period. Moderate is defined as "sensation of heat with sweating, able to continue activity"; severe is defined as "sensation of heat with sweating, causing cessation of activity". Patients used the take-home daily diary to record MSVS information during the run-in period and treatment period and analyses were performed as specified.
Treatment group differences are estimated using least squares (LS) means and 95% confidence intervals based on the mean square error from the ANCOVA. LSMeans refer to overall adjusted mean frequency of MSVS.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks from Baseline (2-week run-in period)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Change in Frequency of MSVS From Baseline at Week 4 (1-week Period) - Change from Baseline in the frequency of MSVS (difference between Baseline [period following first 7 days of 2-week run-in period] and period following first 7 days of 2-week Week 4 period), where the Baseline MSVS frequency was captured at visit 3 (Day 0), in the period following the first 7 days, as per CRF. Note: this endpoint is identical to the primary endpoint, however, instead of a 14 ± 2 day period, the period following the first 7 days was used, at Baseline and visit 3.
Treatment group differences are estimated using least squares (LS) means and 95% confidence intervals based on the mean square error from the ANCOVA. LSMeans refer to overall adjusted mean frequency of MSVS.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks from Baseline (period following first 7 days of 2-week run-in period)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline (Day 0) in the Frequency of MSVS at Week 1 and Week 2 - The frequency of MSVS per week, at each of the protocol visits, was calculated as follows, for each patient: [# of Moderate+Severe hot flushes)/(Current protocol visit date-Previous protocol visit date (days)] * 7.
The ANCOVA procedure tested the following hypotheses:
H0: µ1 = µp versus HA: µ1 ? µp, where µ1 and µp denote the mean frequency of MSVS, adjusted for Baseline MSVS values, in the treatment and placebo groups, respectively.
LSMeans refer to the overall adjusted mean frequecy of MSVS.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 and 2 weeks from Baseline (Day 0)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline (Day 0) in the Severity of VMS as Recorded in the Patient Diary at Week 1, Week 2, and Week 4 - The severity of vasomotor symptoms per week at each of the protocol visits was calculated for each patient as follows: [(Sum of scores of Mild, Moderate, Severe hot flushes)/(Current protocol visit date - Previous protocol visit date (days)] * 7, where severity of vasomotor symptoms were scored as: 1 = mild, 2 = moderate and 3 = severe. Higher values represented worse severity.
LSMeans refer to the overall adjusted mean severity of VMS.
Hot Flush Classification: Mild: sensation of heat without sweating; Moderate: sensation of heat with sweating, able to continue activity; Severe: sensation of heat with sweating, causing cessation of activity.
Patients recorded the number of hot flushes (day and night) in their diaries related to the severity (mild/moderate/severe).</outcome>
      <timepoint>1, 2, and 4 weeks from Baseline (Day 0)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline (Day 0) in Vaginal pH at Week 2 and Week 4 - The pH scale measures how acidic or basic a substance is. The pH scale ranges from 0 to 14. A pH of 7 is neutral. A pH less than 7 is acidic. A pH greater than 7 is basic. The pH scale is logarithmic and as a result, each whole pH value below 7 is ten times more acidic than the next higher value.
Normal vaginal pH is 3.8 to 4.5, slightly acidic.
The LSMeans refer to overall adjusted mean pH.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 and 4 weeks from Baseline (Day 0)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Vaginal Maturation Index at Week 2 and Week 4 - The Vaginal Maturation Index was calculated by examining the maturation of the vaginal epithelium as adjudged by the cell types exfoliated. Parabasal cells are the least mature cells, intermediate cells display mild maturation, and superficial cells display the most maturity. The cell count is expressed as a percentage. The Vaginal Maturation Index was calculated as: 0.2*(parabasal cells, %)+0.6*(intermediate cells, %)+1.0*(superficial cells, %). This method is described in Menopause 2005;12(6):708-15.
The index serves as an objective means of evaluating hormonal secretion or response; lower values indicate more immature cells on the surface (atrophy), while higher values indicate more mature epithelium.
The LSMeans refer to overall adjusted mean percent of cells counted.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 and 4 weeks from Baseline (Day 0)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Estradiol Concentration at Weeks 2 and 4 - The LSMeans refer to overall adjusted mean estradiol concentration.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 and 4 weeks from Baseline (Day 0)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Progesterone Concentration at Week 2 and Week 4 - No repeated measures ANCOVA results are presented for change from Baseline in progesterone concentrations since the model did not converge.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 and 4 weeks from Baseline (Day 0)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Change in the Menopause Rating Scale Total Score From Baseline at Week 4 - MRS consists of 11 menopause symptoms. The scoring scheme is simple, i.e., the score increases point by point with increasing severity of subjectively perceived symptoms in each of the 11 items (severity 0 [no complaints] 4 scoring points [extremely severe symptoms]). The respondent provides her personal perception by checking one of 5 possible boxes of "severity" for each of the items. The composite score (total score) is the sum of the 11 item scores, which can range from 0 (no symptoms) to 44 (extremely severe symptoms). Low total scores represent less severe menopause symptoms while higher scores represent more severe symptoms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks from Baseline (Day 0)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Precentage Change in the Menopause Rating Scale Total Score From Baseline at Week 4 - Percentage change from Baseline at Week 4 = (Week 4 value - Day 0 value)/(Day 0 value) x 100. Note: MRS consists of 11 symptoms, where each symptom is assigned a score from 0 to 4 (0 = 'None' and 4 = 'Extremely severe').</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks from Baseline (Day 0)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  12 months of spontaneous amenorrhea, or 6 months of spontaneous amenorrhea with serum
             follicle stimulating hormone (FSH) concentrations &gt; 40 mIU/mL, or 6 weeks postsurgical
             bilateral oophorectomy with or without hysterectomy, or hysterectomy with 2 (measured
             14 days apart) serum FSH concentrations &gt; 40 mIU/mL.

          -  Is likely to experience at least 50 moderate to severe vasomotor symptoms ([MSVS] hot
             flushes and nocturnal sweating) per week while not receiving estrogen replacement
             therapy based on history of menopause, in the judgment of the investigator.

          -  Documented experiencing at least 50 MSVS per week during the 14 day baseline period
             before the Randomization Visit (Visit 3), based on the patient diary entries
             (calculated mean MSVS/week for the 14 day baseline period).

          -  If = 40 years of age, has a documented negative mammogram and a normal clinical breast
             examination with no findings indicative of breast malignancy.

          -  Has a body mass index (BMI) &lt; 35.0 kg/m2.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Female</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Has a known history of allergic reaction or clinically significant intolerance to
             ingredients of the study drug.

          -  Received any of the following:oral or dermal estrogen/progestin or selective estrogen
             receptor modulator (SERM) containing drug product therapy within 8 weeks before
             Screening, injectable or implantable estrogen/progestin therapy within 3 months before
             Screening, hormone releasing intrauterine device

          -  Had unexplained or otherwise abnormal vaginal bleeding within 6 months before
             Screening.

          -  Has a history of, or currently has, any of the following conditions: thrombophlebitis,
             thromboembolic disease, estrogen dependent neoplasia, or carcinoma of the breast.

          -  Has a history of any untreated or uncontrolled endocrine disorders (e.g.,
             hyperparathyroidism, uncontrolled hyperthyroidism).

          -  Has any clinically significant unstable cardiac, respiratory, neurological,
             immunological, hematological, hepatic, renal, endocrine, or gastric disease or any
             other condition that, in the opinion of the investigator, could compromise the
             patient's welfare, ability to communicate with the study staff, or otherwise
             contraindicate study participation.

          -  Has clinically significant depression or severe psychiatric disturbances.

          -  Has active liver disease with aspartate aminotransferase (AST) &gt; 3 times the upper
             limit of normal (ULN), alanine aminotransferase (ALT) &gt; 3 times ULN, unexplained
             alkaline phosphatase &gt; 3 times ULN, total bilirubin &gt; 2 times ULN, renal insufficiency
             with creatinine &gt; 1.7 mg/dL, or clinically significant abnormal hemoglobin, white
             blood cell count, or platelet count.

          -  Has an endometrial thickness = 4 mm.

          -  Has a history indicative of endometrial hyperplasia or cancer.

          -  Shows presence of any manifest premalignant or malignant disease except treated skin
             cancers (except melanoma).

          -  Has known or suspected history of alcoholism or drug abuse or misuse within the past 5
             years.

          -  Has resting systolic blood pressure (BP) &gt; 160 mmHg or &lt; 90 mmHg, or diastolic BP &gt; 90
             mmHg or &lt; 60 mmHg at Screening.

          -  Has a history of smoking more than 5 cigarettes daily within the year before
             Screening.

          -  Has tested positive on the urine drug screen. Patients who test positive at Screening
             and can produce documentation from their physician for the medication that caused the
             positive test may be considered for study enrollment at the discretion of the
             investigator.

          -  Has significant difficulties swallowing capsules or is unable to tolerate oral
             medication.

          -  Has participated in another clinical trial or received any investigational drug or
             device or investigational therapy within 30 days before Screening.

          -  Has a disorder that affects gastrointestinal absorption.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/06/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>169</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/11/2011</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,SA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Sydney Centre for Reproductive Health Research - Ashfield</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Hospital for Women - Randwick</hospital>
    <hospital>Women's Health Center, Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>Emeritus Research - Malvern East</hospital>
    <postcode>2131 - Ashfield</postcode>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>3144 - Malvern East</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Kentucky</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>South Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Utah</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Ausio Pharmaceuticals, LLC</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to assess the safety and effectiveness of S-equol in menopausal
      patients with hot flushes and night sweats.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00962585</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Michael A Thomas, MD</name>
      <address>University of Cincinnati</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>