<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6192">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/09/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/09/2008</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00763737</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Randomized Controlled Trial of Fetoscopic Endoluminal Tracheal Occlusion With a Balloon Versus Expectant Management During Pregnancy in Fetuses With Left Sided Congenital Diaphragmatic Hernia and Moderate Pulmonary Hypoplasia.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomized Trial of Fetoscopic Endoluminal Tracheal Occlusion (FETO) Versus Expectant Management During Pregnancy in Fetuses With Left Sided and Isolated Congenital Diaphragmatic Hernia and Moderate Pulmonary Hypoplasia.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>TOTAL moderate</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>2008-4634</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>B32220084540</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Congenital Diaphragmatic Hernia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Fetal Surgery</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Pulmonary Hypoplasia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: surgery - Fetoscopic Endoluminal Tracheal Occlusion

Experimental: 1 - prenatal FETO at 30-32+6 weeks and removal at 34-34+6 wks, followed by standardized postnatal care

No Intervention: 2 - expectant management during pregnancy followed by standardized neonatal care


Treatment: surgery: Fetoscopic Endoluminal Tracheal Occlusion
prenatal balloon placement at 30-32+6 weeks and removal at 34-34+6 wks

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Survival at discharge</outcome>
      <timepoint>at discharge from hospital</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>occurrence of bronchopulmonary dysplasia</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days of life</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Oxygen dependency at discharge</outcome>
      <timepoint>at discharge from hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Survival without oxygen dependency</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months of life</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Patients aged 18 years or more, who are able to consent

          -  Singleton pregnancy

          -  Anatomically and chromosomally normal fetus

          -  Left sided diaphragmatic hernia

          -  Gestation at randomization prior to 32 wks plus 5 d (so that occlusion is done at the
             latest on 32 wks plus 6 d)

          -  Estimated to have moderate pulmonary hypoplasia, defined prenatally as:

               -  O/E LHR 25-34.9% (included; irrespective of the position of the liver)

               -  O/E LHR 35-44.9% (included) with intrathoracic liver herniation as determined by
                  ultrasound or MRI

          -  Acceptance of randomization and the consequences for the further management during
             pregnancy and thereafter.

          -  The patients must undertake the responsibility for either remaining close to, or at
             the FETO center, or being able to travel swiftly and within acceptable time interval
             to the FETO center until the balloon is removed.

          -  Intended postnatal treatment center must subscribe to suggested guidelines for
             "standardized postnatal treatment".

          -  Provide written consent to participate in this RCT</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Female</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Maternal contraindication to fetoscopic surgery or severe medical condition in
             pregnancy that make fetal intervention risk full

          -  Technical limitations precluding fetoscopic surgery, such as severe maternal obesity,
             uterine fibroids or potentially others, not anticipated at the time of writing this
             protocol.

          -  Preterm labour, cervix shortened (&lt;15 mm at randomization) or uterine anomaly strongly
             predisposing to preterm labour, placenta previa

          -  Patient age less than 18 years

          -  Psychosocial ineligibility, precluding consent

          -  Diaphragmatic hernia: right-sided or bilateral, major anomalies, isolated left-sided
             outside the O/E LHR limits for the inclusion criteria

          -  Patient refusing randomization or to comply with return to FETO center during the time
             period the airways are occluded or for elective removal of the balloon</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/08/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>196</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/12/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Mater Mother's Hospital - Brisbane</hospital>
    <postcode>4101 - Brisbane</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Leuven</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Clamart</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Paris</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Bonn</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Milan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Rome</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Catalunya</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University Hospital, Gasthuisberg</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>King's College Hospital NHS Trust (UK)</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Hospital Clinic of Barcelona (ES)</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Hôpital Antoine Béclère, Clamart (FR)</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Hôpital Necker - Enfants Malades, Paris (FR)</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University Hospital, Bonn</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Mater Mother's Hospital, Brisbane (AUS)</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Ospedale Maggiore Policlinico, Milan (IT)</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Ospedale Pediatrico Bambino Gesù, Rome (IT)</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Mount Sinai Hospital, Toronto (CAN)</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Baylor College of Medicine/Texas Children's Hospital (US)</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Isolated Congenital Diaphragmatic Hernia (CDH) can be diagnosed in the prenatal period, and
      remains associated with an 30 % chance of perinatal death and morbidity mainly because of
      pulmonary hypoplasia and pulmonary hypertension. In addition, in the survivors there is a
      high rate of morbidity with evidence of bronchopulmonary dysplasia in more than 70% of cases.
      The risk for these can be predicted prenatally by the ultrasonographic measurement of the
      observed/expected lung area to head circumference ratio (O/E LHR) which is a measure of
      pulmonary hypoplasia. Also position of the liver is predictive of outcome.

      The proposing consortium has developed a prenatal therapeutic approach, which consists of
      percutaneous fetoscopic endoluminal tracheal occlusion (FETO) with subsequent removal of the
      balloon . Both procedures are performed percutaneously, there is now experience with more
      than 150 cases and it has been shown to be safe for the mother. We have witnessed an
      improvement of survival in fetuses with a predicted chance of survival of less than 30%
      (referred to as fetuses with severe pulmonary hypoplasia; O/E LHR &lt;25% and liver herniation)
      to 55% on average. Also there is an apparent reduction in morbidity with the rate of
      bronchopulmonary dysplasia decreasing from the estimated rate of more than 70% to less than
      40% in the same severity group .

      Further we have shown that results of FETO are predicted by LHR measurement prior to the
      procedure , so that better results can be expected in fetuses with larger lung size .
      Therefore we now aim to offer FETO to fetuses with moderate CDH (=O/E LHR 25-34.9%,
      irrespective of the liver position as well as O/E LHR 35-44.9% with intrathoracic herniation
      of the liver). When managed expectantly the estimated rate of postnatal survival is 60% or
      lower and the rate of broncho-pulmonary dysplasia in survivors is 33% or higher.

      This trial will test whether temporary fetoscopic tracheal occlusion rather than expectant
      management during pregnancy, both followed by standardized postnatal management, decreases
      the occurrence of bronchopulmonary dysplasia or increases survival. The balloon will be
      placed between 30 and 32+6 weeks, and will be removed between 34 and 34+6 weeks.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00763737</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Jani J, Nicolaides KH, Keller RL, Benachi A, Peralta CF, Favre R, Moreno O, Tibboel D, Lipitz S, Eggink A, Vaast P, Allegaert K, Harrison M, Deprest J; Antenatal-CDH-Registry Group. Observed to expected lung area to head circumference ratio in the prediction of survival in fetuses with isolated diaphragmatic hernia. Ultrasound Obstet Gynecol. 2007 Jul;30(1):67-71.
Doné E, Gucciardo L, Van Mieghem T, Jani J, Cannie M, Van Schoubroeck D, Devlieger R, Catte LD, Klaritsch P, Mayer S, Beck V, Debeer A, Gratacos E, Nicolaides K, Deprest J. Prenatal diagnosis, prediction of outcome and in utero therapy of isolated congenital diaphragmatic hernia. Prenat Diagn. 2008 Jul;28(7):581-91. doi: 10.1002/pd.2033. Review.
Deprest J, Jani J, Gratacos E, Vandecruys H, Naulaers G, Delgado J, Greenough A, Nicolaides K; FETO Task Group. Fetal intervention for congenital diaphragmatic hernia: the European experience. Semin Perinatol. 2005 Apr;29(2):94-103. Review.
Deprest J, Gratacos E, Nicolaides KH; FETO Task Group. Fetoscopic tracheal occlusion (FETO) for severe congenital diaphragmatic hernia: evolution of a technique and preliminary results. Ultrasound Obstet Gynecol. 2004 Aug;24(2):121-6. Erratum in: Ultrasound Obstet Gynecol. 2004 Oct;24(5):594.
Jani JC, Nicolaides KH, Gratacós E, Valencia CM, Doné E, Martinez JM, Gucciardo L, Cruz R, Deprest JA. Severe diaphragmatic hernia treated by fetal endoscopic tracheal occlusion. Ultrasound Obstet Gynecol. 2009 Sep;34(3):304-10. doi: 10.1002/uog.6450.
Deprest JA, Gratacos E, Nicolaides K, Done E, Van Mieghem T, Gucciardo L, Claus F, Debeer A, Allegaert K, Reiss I, Tibboel D. Changing perspectives on the perinatal management of isolated congenital diaphragmatic hernia in Europe. Clin Perinatol. 2009 Jun;36(2):329-47, ix. doi: 10.1016/j.clp.2009.03.004. Review.
Deprest JA, Hyett JA, Flake AW, Nicolaides K, Gratacos E. Current controversies in prenatal diagnosis 4: Should fetal surgery be done in all cases of severe diaphragmatic hernia? Prenat Diagn. 2009 Jan;29(1):15-9. doi: 10.1002/pd.2108.
Gregoir C, Engels AC, Gomez O, DeKoninck P, Lewi L, Gratacos E, Deprest JA. Fertility, pregnancy and gynecological outcomes after fetoscopic surgery for congenital diaphragmatic hernia. Hum Reprod. 2016 Sep;31(9):2024-30. doi: 10.1093/humrep/dew160. Epub 2016 Jul 4.
Snoek KG, Reiss IK, Greenough A, Capolupo I, Urlesberger B, Wessel L, Storme L, Deprest J, Schaible T, van Heijst A, Tibboel D; CDH EURO Consortium. Standardized Postnatal Management of Infants with Congenital Diaphragmatic Hernia in Europe: The CDH EURO Consortium Consensus - 2015 Update. Neonatology. 2016;110(1):66-74. doi: 10.1159/000444210. Epub 2016 Apr 15.
Nawapun K, Eastwood MP, Diaz-Cobos D, Jimenez J, Aertsen M, Gomez O, Claus F, Gratacós E, Deprest J. In vivo evidence by magnetic resonance volumetry of a gestational age dependent response to tracheal occlusion for congenital diaphragmatic hernia. Prenat Diagn. 2015 Nov;35(11):1048-56. doi: 10.1002/pd.4642. Epub 2015 Sep 29.
Deprest J, Brady P, Nicolaides K, Benachi A, Berg C, Vermeesch J, Gardener G, Gratacos E. Prenatal management of the fetus with isolated congenital diaphragmatic hernia in the era of the TOTAL trial. Semin Fetal Neonatal Med. 2014 Dec;19(6):338-48. doi: 10.1016/j.siny.2014.09.006. Epub 2014 Nov 11. Review.
Done E, Debeer A, Gucciardo L, Van Mieghem T, Lewi P, Devlieger R, De Catte L, Lewi L, Allegaert K, Deprest J. Prediction of neonatal respiratory function and pulmonary hypertension in fetuses with isolated congenital diaphragmatic hernia in the fetal endoscopic tracleal occlusion era: a single-center study. Fetal Diagn Ther. 2015;37(1):24-32. doi: 10.1159/000364805. Epub 2014 Nov 8.
DeKoninck P, Gomez O, Sandaite I, Richter J, Nawapun K, Eerdekens A, Ramirez JC, Claus F, Gratacos E, Deprest J. Right-sided congenital diaphragmatic hernia in a decade of fetal surgery. BJOG. 2015 Jun;122(7):940-6. doi: 10.1111/1471-0528.13065. Epub 2014 Sep 17.
Windrim R, Ryan G, Lebouthillier F, Campisi P, Kelly EN, Baud D, Yoo SJ, Deprest J. Development and use of a high-fidelity simulator for fetal endotracheal balloon occlusion (FETO) insertion and removal. Prenat Diagn. 2014 Feb;34(2):180-4. doi: 10.1002/pd.4284. Epub 2013 Dec 27.
Engels AC, DeKoninck P, van der Merwe JL, Van Mieghem T, Stevens P, Power B, Nicolaides KH, Gratacos E, Deprest JA. Does website-based information add any value in counseling mothers expecting a baby with severe congenital diaphragmatic hernia? Prenat Diagn. 2013 Nov;33(11):1027-32. doi: 10.1002/pd.4190. Epub 2013 Aug 29.
Dekoninck P, Gratacos E, Van Mieghem T, Richter J, Lewi P, Ancel AM, Allegaert K, Nicolaides K, Deprest J. Results of fetal endoscopic tracheal occlusion for congenital diaphragmatic hernia and the set up of the randomized controlled TOTAL trial. Early Hum Dev. 2011 Sep;87(9):619-24. doi: 10.1016/j.earlhumdev.2011.08.001.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jan A Deprest, MD PhD</name>
      <address>Universitaire Ziekenhuizen Leuven</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jan A Deprest, MD PhD</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+3216344215</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Jan.Deprest@uzleuven.be</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>