<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2726">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/04/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/04/2010</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01101282</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Does Positive Expiratory Pressure Mask Therapy Improve Recovery From Acute Exacerbations of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Does the Addition of Positive Expiratory Pressure (PEP) Mask Therapy to Usual Medical Care Improve Patients' Symptoms, Quality or Life and Risk of Future Exacerbations in Individuals With Acute Exacerbations of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD)?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>(not yet specified)</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pulmonary Disease, Chronic Obstructive</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Lung Diseases, Obstructive</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - Positive expiratory pressure (PEP) mask therapy

No Intervention: 'Usual care' - Participants will receive 'usual medical care' consisting of the following:
Medical management: Bronchodilators, corticosteroids, antibiotics and supplemental oxygen will be provided (where appropriate) in accordance with Australian and New Zealand COPD management guidelines (COPDX guidelines).
Non-invasive ventilation: if clinically indicated and prescribed in accordance with standardised hospital guidelines.
Physical rehabilitation: Participants will be assessed by a physiotherapist and prescribed appropriate exercises to facilitate a safe and timely discharge. Participants will perform physical rehabilitation according to a standardised protocol with an aim of maximising physical function at discharge.
Other allied health (e.g. occupational therapy, speech pathology, dietician) assessments and interventions, as required.

Experimental: 'Usual care' plus PEP mask therapy - This will comprise:
'Usual care'
PEP mask therapy


Treatment: devices: Positive expiratory pressure (PEP) mask therapy
PEP mask therapy will be performed once/day, supervised, by an experienced physiotherapist until hospital discharge or = 24 hours without sputum expectoration (whichever comes first). Written instructions shall also be provided, encouraging two more independent PEP mask sessions per day. Each session will comprise up to 5 cycles of 8-10 slightly active breaths, followed by 2 huffs (FET) and 2 coughs. A target pressure of 10-20 cms H20 during the middle of expiration shall be used (monitored via a pressure manometer).

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptom severity - Measured via the Breathlessness, Cough and Sputum Scale (BCSS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 48 hours of presenting to hospital (day 1)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptom severity - Measured via the BCSS</outcome>
      <timepoint>At hospital discharge (up to approx. day 10)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptom severity - Measured via the BCSS</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 weeks following hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptom severity - Measured via the BCSS</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months following hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disease-specific quality of life - Measured via the 4-week English (Australian) version of the St. George's Respiratory Questionnaire (SGRQ).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 48 hours of presenting to hospital (day 1)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disease-specific quality of life - Measured via the SGRQ</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 weeks following hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disease-specific quality of life - Measured via the SGRQ</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months following hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Need for assisted (non-invasive and/or invasive) ventilation during hospitalisation (within, and after 48 hours of presentation to hospital) - The number of participants needing non-invasive or invasive ventilation during their inpatient stay shall be assessed. As early non-invasive ventilation is commonly used for the management of acute exacerbations of COPD, this outcome shall be assessed both within and after 48 hours of presentation to hospital. This aims to differentiate usual care from clinical deterioration.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At hospital discharge (up to approx. day 10)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospital length of stay - Measured as number of days</outcome>
      <timepoint>At hospital discharge (up to approx. day 10)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to first exacerbation - Measured as number of days</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months following hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to first hospitalisation (due to respiratory illness) - Measured as number of days</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months following hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of acute exacerbations - Measured as number of events</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months following hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of hospitalisations (due to respiratory illness) - Measured as number of events</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months following hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total number of hospitalised days - Measured as number of hospitalised days</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months following hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lung function (spirometry) - e.g. FEV1, FVC, FEV1/FVC%</outcome>
      <timepoint>At hospital discharge (up to approx. day 10)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lung function (spirometry) - e.g. FEV1, FVC, FEV1/FVC%</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months following hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mortality (actual, all cause) - Measured as number of events</outcome>
      <timepoint>At hospital discharge (up to approx. day 10)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mortality (actual, all cause) - Measured as number of events</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months following hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mortality (predicted) - Measured via calculation of the BODE index. The BODE index is derived from: Body mass index, Obstruction severity (spirometry), Dyspnoea (MRC dyspnoea scale) and Exercise tolerance (6 minute walk test).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At hospital discharge (up to approx. day 10)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mortality (predicted) - Measured via BODE index</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months following hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion Criteria (all of the following criteria must be met):

          -  The primary reason for hospital admission is an acute exacerbation of clinically
             diagnosed COPD

          -  There is evidence of sputum expectoration or they are a chronic sputum producer
             ('regularly expectorates sputum on most days')

          -  They are able and willing to provide written, informed consent

          -  Recent (within the last 6 months) lung function data indicates obstructive lung
             disease (of any severity), according to the GOLD criteria: post-bronchodilator
             FEV1/FVC &lt; 0.7 (only if available)

          -  They have a smoking history of = 10 pack/years (only if diagnosis unclear)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion Criteria (none of the following criteria must be present):

          -  They are breathing via an artificial airway (e.g. endotracheal or tracheostomy tube)

          -  They have a more significant respiratory disease other than COPD (e.g. primary
             diagnosis of bronchiectasis, cystic fibrosis, interstitial lung disease, asthma, lung
             cancer)

          -  They have had recent (within the last 6 months) lung volume reduction procedure(s)
             (e.g. surgery, valve or stent insertion, or other), lung transplantation or
             pneumonectomy

          -  The intervention is contraindicated (including but not limited to evidence of
             undrained pneumothorax, significant frank haemoptysis, recent facial, oral,
             oesophageal or skull surgery/trauma, altered conscious state or inability to
             co-operate)

          -  They have poor oxygen saturation at rest (SpO2 &lt; 88%) despite supplemental oxygen
             delivered via nasal prongs

          -  They intend to continue performing established ACT routines throughout the study
             period

          -  It is more than 48 hours since being admitted as an inpatient to hospital.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>92</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/01/2013</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Austin Hospital - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>The Alfred Hospital - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3084 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3181 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>La Trobe University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>The Alfred</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Austin Hospital, Melbourne Australia</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to identify whether the addition of positive expiratory pressure (PEP) mask
      therapy to standard medical care improves clinically important outcomes in individuals with
      acute exacerbations of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease. It is hypothesized that those
      who receive the additional PEP mask therapy will show greater improvements than those who do
      not.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01101282</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Christian R Osadnik, Bachelor of Physiotherapy</name>
      <address>La Trobe University</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>