<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6338">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/02/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/02/2017</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT03067636</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Retraining Body and Brain to Conquer Compulsions</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Retraining the Body and Brain to Conquer Compulsions</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>20160437</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Compulsive Behavior</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Behaviour - Physical Exercise
Behaviour - Stress management training A
Behaviour - Stress management training B

Active Comparator: Physical exercise + stress management activity A - Eight week program of concurrent exercise and stress management training.

Active Comparator: Physical exercise + stress management activity B - Eight week program of concurrent exercise and stress management training.

No Intervention: Lifestyle as usual - Eight weeks period with no alteration of usual lifestyle.
Participants randomized to this arm are eligible for re-randomisation to one of the active conditions at the conclusion of week eight.


Behaviour: Physical Exercise
Physical exercise: Amount of time exercising gradually titrated from 90-minutes in week one to 180-minutes in week eight. Intensity titrated concurrently from 40 - 60% VO2 max in week one to 40 - 90% VO2 max in week eight. Eight week gym membership provided to all participants to facilitate engagement in exercise.

Behaviour: Stress management training A
Stress management training A: Daily stress management training for eight weeks with training activity delivered via app. Session lengths titrated from 10-minutes per day in the first week to 20-minutes per day in week eight.

Behaviour: Stress management training B
Stress management training B: Daily stress management training for eight weeks with training activity delivered via app. Session lengths titrated from 10-minutes per day in the first week to 20-minutes per day in week eight.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in hippocampal integrity - Composite score of hippocampal health indices, including volume (structural MRI) and neuronal NAA levels (MRS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (0 months), post (2 months)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in functional activation during reward processing - fMRI Monetary Incentive Delay Task</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (0 months), post (2 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in cortisol awakening reponse - Salivary cortisol</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (0 months), post (2 months), follow up (three months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in affective processing bias - BeanFest</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (0 months), post (2 months), follow up (three months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in risky decision making - Balloon Analogue Risk Task</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (0 months), post (2 months), follow up (three months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in behavioral compulsivity - Transdiagnositc YBOCS</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (0 months), post (2 months), follow up (three months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in psychosocial well being - Battery of self-report mental health and well being questionnaires assessing: symptoms of depression and anxiety, experiential avoidance, tolerance of uncertainly, impulsivity, obsession beliefs, well being, self efficacy, quality of life, and quality of inter-personal support.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (0 months), post (2 months), follow up (three months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in physical fitness - VO2 max</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (0 months), post (2 months), follow up (three months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Voluntary and able to provide informed consent,

          -  Endorse current behavioural compulsiveness in one of the following domains: alcohol
             consumption, gambling, eating, checking, washing/cleaning, ordering/arranging,

          -  Severity of compulsivity falls within mild-moderate range on transdiagnostic YBOCS,

          -  Level of physical activity fell within WHO Global Recommendations on Physical Activity
             for Health guidelines definitions of 'sedentary/inactive' across the prior three
             months, and for a minimum of four of the prior six months.

          -  Ability to adhere to study procedures.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Lifetime history of DSM-5 defined psychotic illness, severe substance use disorder,
             severe gambling disorder, binge eating disorder, bulimia nervosa,

          -  Current major depressive episode or anxiety disorder,

          -  History of neurological illness or moderate - severe brain injury,

          -  Have a major unstable medical illness or a chronic pain condition,

          -  Have a history of cardiovascular disease or musculoskeletal injury or disease that
             would preclude safe engagement in VO2 max testing or regular physical exercise,

          -  Lifetime diagnosis of learning difficulty, ADHD, other condition involving cognitive
             impairment as a primary feature,

          -  Severe claustrophobia, metallic implant within the body or other contraindication to
             MRI scanning,

          -  Shift work employment schedule within the prior 6-months,

          -  Endocrine disorder, adrenal dysfunction, autoimmune disorder, or other condition known
             to have a direct effect on the HPA axis,

          -  Psychoactive or glucocorticoid medications within the past month,

          -  Currently pregnant or lactating.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/06/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>90</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>20/12/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Monash University, Brain and Mental Health Lab - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3800 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Following the realisation that many aspects of the way we live our life, such as our diet,
      activity levels, and amount of screen time, can have a potent impact on mental health and
      brain functioning 'lifestyle' based interventions have become topical in medical research. In
      particular, much scientific attention has been devoted to the impact of physical exercise and
      various stress reduction techniques on mood disorders. We aim to extend this work and
      investigate their impact on compulsivity.

      We will do this by conducting a pilot proof-of-principal intervention study. The study will
      compare the impact of eight-weeks of:

        1. regular physical exercise + stress management activity A,

        2. regular physical exercise + stress management activity B,

        3. lifestyle as usual.

      The participant cohort will be adults who endorse mild-moderate behavioural compulsivity on
      one of the following domains:

        -  drinking alcohol

        -  gambling

        -  eating

        -  washing or cleaning

        -  checking

        -  ordering or arranging objects</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03067636</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>