<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6087">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02857270</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Study of LY3214996 Administered Alone or in Combination With Other Agents in Participants With Advanced/Metastatic Cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 1 Study of an ERK1/2 Inhibitor (LY3214996) Administered Alone or in Combination With Other Agents in Advanced Cancer</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>I8S-MC-JUAB</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>16419</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Advanced Cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Metastatic Melanoma</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Metastatic Non-small Cell Lung Cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Metastatic Pancreatic Ductal Adenocarcinoma</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Colorectal Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lung - Non small cell</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Bowel - Back passage (rectum) or large bowel (colon)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - LY3214996
Treatment: drugs - Midazolam
Treatment: drugs - Abemaciclib
Treatment: drugs - Nab-paclitaxel
Treatment: drugs - Gemcitabine

Experimental: LY3214996 Dose Escalation - LY3214996 given orally once a day (or twice a day) for 21 days.

Experimental: LY3214996 + Midazolam - (Preliminary Drug-Drug Interactions [DDI])
LY3214996 given orally (dose timing will be determined) and midazolam given orally on cycle 1 day 1 and cycle 1 day 16 (21 day cycles except cycle 1 only = 22 days).

Experimental: LY3214996 Monotherapy - LY3214996 given orally (dose timing will be determined) during each 21 day cycle.

Experimental: LY3214996 + Abemaciclib - Dose Escalation and Expansion- LY3214996 given orally (dose timing will be determined) and abemaciclib given orally (single dose given during lead in period) twice a day every 12 hours during 21 day cycle.

Experimental: LY3214996 + Nab-Paclitaxel + Gemcitabine - Dose Escalation and Expansion- LY3214996 given orally (dose timing will be determined) and nab-paclitaxel given intravenously (IV) on day 1, 8, and 15 and gemcitabine IV on day 1, 8, and 15 during each 28 day cycle.


Treatment: drugs: LY3214996
Administered orally

Treatment: drugs: Midazolam
Administered orally

Treatment: drugs: Abemaciclib
Administered orally

Treatment: drugs: Nab-paclitaxel
Administered IV

Treatment: drugs: Gemcitabine
Administered IV

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants with LY3214996 Dose Limiting Toxicities (DLTs)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cycle 1 (21 Days)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetics (PK): Area Under the Concentration-Time Curve (AUC) of LY3214996 Administered as Monotherapy and when Administered in Combination with Nab-Paclitaxel Plus Gemcitabine, and Abemaciclib</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cycle 1 Day 1 through Cycle 2 Day 1 (up to 28 Day Cycles)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PK: AUC of Gemcitabine when Administered with LY3214996</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cycle 1 Day 1 through Cycle 1 Day 15 (28 Day Cycles)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PK: AUC of Nab-Paclitaxel when Administered with LY3214996</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cycle 1 Day 1 through Cycle 1 Day 15 (28 Day Cycles)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PK: AUC of Abemaciclib and its Metabolites when Administered with LY3214996</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cycle 1 Day 1 through Cycle 2 Day 1 (up to 22 Day Cycles)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PK: AUC of Midazolam and its 1'-Hydroxymidazolam Metabolite when Administered Alone and in Combination with LY3214996</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cycle 1 Day 1 through Cycle 1 Day 16 (21 Day Cycles)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Objective Response Rate (ORR): Percentage of Participants With a Complete (CR) or Partial Response (PR)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to Measured Progressive Disease or Start of New Anti-Cancer Therapy (Estimated up to 6 Months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of Response (DoR)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Date of Complete Response (CR) or Partial Response (PR) to Date of Objective Disease Progression or Death Due to Any Cause (Estimated up to 12 Months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to First Response (TTR)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to Date of CR or PR (Estimated up to 6 Months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression Free Survival (PFS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to Progressive Disease or Death of Any Cause (Estimated up to 12 Months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Have advanced or metastatic cancer (solid tumors) and be an appropriate candidate for
             experimental therapy.

               -  Part B2: Have advanced/metastatic cancer carrying activating mitogen-activated
                  protein kinase (MAPK) pathway alteration

               -  Part B3: Have metastatic melanoma carrying BRAF mutation, refractory/relapsed
                  after treatment with Raf and/or MEK inhibitors

               -  Part B4: Have metastatic melanoma carrying NRAS mutation

               -  Part C: Have advanced unresectable cancer (dose escalation) and
                  advanced/unresectable/metastatic NSCLC carrying BRAF or RAS mutation and
                  colorectal cancer carrying RAS mutation (dose expansion)

               -  Part D: Have metastatic pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma (dose escalation and
                  dose expansion)

          -  Have discontinued previous treatments for cancer and have resolution, except where
             otherwise stated in the inclusion criteria, of all clinically significant toxic
             effects of prior chemotherapy, surgery, or radiotherapy to Grade =1 by National Cancer
             Institute (NCI) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE), Version 4.0.

          -  Have adequate organ function.

          -  Have a performance status of 0 to 1 on the Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG)
             scale.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Have serious preexisting medical conditions.

          -  Have a known human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection or known
             activated/reactivated hepatitis A, B, or C.

          -  Have symptomatic central nervous system malignancy or metastasis.

          -  Have current hematologic malignancies, acute or chronic leukemia.

          -  Have a second primary malignancy that in the judgment of the investigator or Lilly may
             affect the interpretation of results.

          -  Have prior malignancies. Participants with carcinoma in situ of any origin and
             participants with prior malignancies who are in remission and whose likelihood of
             recurrence is very low, as judged by the Lilly clinical research physician, are
             eligible for this study.

          -  Have a mean QT interval corrected for heart rate (QTc) of =470 milliseconds on
             screening electrocardiogram (ECG) as calculated using the Bazett's formula at several
             consecutive days of assessment.

          -  Have participated, within the last 28 days in a clinical trial involving an
             investigational product or are currently enrolled in a clinical trial involving an
             investigational product or any other type of medical research judged not to be
             scientifically or medically compatible with this study.

          -  Have previously completed or withdrawn from this study or any other study
             investigating an ERK1/2 inhibitor.

          -  If female, is pregnant, breastfeeding, or planning to become pregnant.

          -  Have history or findings of central or branch retinal artery or venous occlusion with
             significant vision loss or other retinal diseases that cause current visual impairment
             or would likely cause visual impairment over the time period of the study.

          -  Currently using concomitant medications that are strong inhibitors or inducers of
             CYP3A4.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/09/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>136</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/09/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>For additional information regarding investigative sites for this trial, contact 1-877-CTLILLY (1-877-285-4559, 1-317-615-4559) Mon - Fri from 9 AM to 5 PM Eastern Time (UTC/GMT - 5 hours, EST), or speak with your personal physician. - Nedlands</hospital>
    <hospital>For additional information regarding investigative sites for this trial, contact 1-888-545-5972 Mon - Fri, 9 AM to 4 PM or 1-877-CTLILLY (1-877-285-4559, 1-317-615-4559) Mon - Fri, 9 AM to 5 PM Eastern Time or speak with your personal physician. - Nedlands</hospital>
    <hospital>For additional information regarding investigative sites for this trial, contact 1-877-CTLILLY (1-877-285-4559, 1-317-615-4559) Mon - Fri from 9 AM to 5 PM Eastern Time (UTC/GMT - 5 hours, EST), or speak with your personal physician. - Sydney</hospital>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
    <postcode>2010 - Sydney</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Massachusetts</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Tennessee</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Villejuif</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Eli Lilly and Company</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to determine the safety of an extracellular signal regulated
      kinase (ERK1/2) inhibitor LY3214996 administered alone or in combination with other agents in
      participants with advanced cancer.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02857270</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Call 1-877-CTLILLY (1-877-285-4559) or 1-317-615-4559 Mon - Fri 9 AM - 5 PM Eastern time (UTC/GMT - 5 hours, EST)</name>
      <address>Eli Lilly and Company</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>There may be multiple sites in this clinical trial. 1-877-CTLILLY (1-877-285-4559) or</name>
      <address />
      <phone>1-317-615-4559</phone>
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>