<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3007">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/11/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/11/2010</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01249521</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Dual Targeting of Vascular Endothelial Growth Factor-A Together With Angiopoietins in Chemotherapy-naïve Metastatic Colorectal Cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Open Label Phase II Study Evaluating the Combination of Bevacizumab and AMG386 Without Chemotherapy as First Line Treatment of Advanced Colorectal Cancer</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Vengeance</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>03501</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Metastatic Colorectal Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Bowel - Back passage (rectum) or large bowel (colon)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - AMG386 and bevacizumab

Treatment: drugs: AMG386 and bevacizumab
AMG386 10mg/kg qw iv Bevacizumab 7.5mg/kg q3w iv

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disease control (ie non progression) at 6 months</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Toxicity</outcome>
      <timepoint>weekly</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall survival</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 monthly</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Response rate</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>i) Histological diagnosis of colorectal cancer ii) Metastatic disease that is not
        resectable iii) Age &gt; 18 years iv) Any patient in whom the investigator considers immediate
        cytotoxic chemotherapy is not required.

        v) Measurable and/or non-measurable disease as assessed by CT scan vi) ECOG performance
        status 0, 1 or 2. vii) No prior chemotherapy except for adjuvant chemotherapy. viii)
        Adequate bone marrow function with platelets &gt; 100 X 109/l; neutrophils &gt; 1.5 X 109/l ix)
        Adequate renal function, with calculated creatinine clearance &gt;40 ml/min (Cockcroft and
        Gault).

        x) Adequate hepatic function with serum total bilirubin &lt; 1.5 X upper limit of normal range
        xi) Life expectancy of at least 12 weeks xii) No other concurrent uncontrolled medical
        conditions xiii) No other malignant disease apart from non-melanotic skin cancer or
        carcinoma in situ of the uterine cervix or any other cancer treated with curative intent &gt;2
        years previously without evidence of relapse xiv) Women and partners of women of
        childbearing potential must agree to use adequate contraception xv) Written informed
        consent including consent for biomarker studies</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>i) Medical or psychiatric conditions that compromise the patient's ability to give informed
        consent or to complete the protocol ii) Uncontrolled hypertension iii) Prior treatment with
        VEGF inhibitors or angiopoietin inhibitors iv) Active bleeding disorders within the last 6
        months v) Participation in any investigational drug study within the previous 4 weeks vi)
        Patients with uncontrolled clinically significant cardiac disease, arrhythmias or angina
        pectoris vii) Patients with a history of arterial or venous thrombosis within the last 12
        months viii) Concurrent or prior (within 1 week before enrollment) anticoagulation therapy.
        The concurrent use of low molecular weight heparin or low dose warfarin (ie, 1 mg daily)
        for prophylaxis against thrombosis is acceptable while on study ix) Regular use of aspirin
        (&gt;325mg/day) or NSAIDs (low dose aspirin (&lt;325 mg/d), or occasional use of NSAIDs is
        acceptable) x) Treatment with immune modulators such as cyclosporine or tacrolimus within
        the previous 4 weeks xi) CNS metastases xii) Major surgical procedure within the last 28
        days xiii) Minor surgical procedure, placement of access device, or fine needle aspiration
        within the last 7 days xiv) Serious non-healing wound, ulcer or bone fracture xv) 24 hour
        urinary protein &gt; 1g/ 24 hours ( performed if urine dipstick &gt; 1+ ) xvi) Pregnancy or
        lactation</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/11/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Unknown status</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/11/2012</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3084 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Austin Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a clinical trial investigating the effectiveness and safety of the combination of the
      study drugs bevacizumab and AMG386 in patients with advanced (metastatic) chemotherapy-naive
      bowel (colorectal) cancer. Chemotherapy has a significant impact in metastatic bowel cancer
      in terms of maintenance of quality of life and extension of survival. However, ultimately
      tumours will develop resistance to these agents and further treatment options are urgently
      required.

      Angiogenesis is a process that results in the formation of new blood vessels. Similar to
      normal tissues, solid tumours require new blood vessels for growth and survival. Hence, drugs
      targeting angiogenesis may be useful treatment options for patients with bowel cancer.

      AMG386 and bevacizumab act on 2 different pathways relevant to angiogenesis. There is
      evidence from laboratory and animal studies to suggest that such a combination could be
      useful as a cancer treatment. Previous studies in humans have shown that AMG386 and
      bevacizumab can be combined safely.. This study aims to evaluate the effectiveness and safety
      of the combination of AMG386 and bevacizumab in patients with advanced bowel cancer.

      40 patients from approximately four hospitals in Australia will participate in this trial,
      with approximately 20 patients being enrolled at Austin Health. All participants will receive
      the same treatment.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01249521</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Niall Tebbutt</name>
      <address>Austin Health</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Effie Skrinos</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+61394963576</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>effie.skrinos@austin.org.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>