<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="405">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/10/2003</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/10/2003</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00071799</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Survival Study in Patients With High Risk Myelodysplastic Syndromes Comparing Azacitidine Versus Conventional Care</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Multicenter, Randomized, Open-label, Parallel-group, Phase 3 Trial of Subcutaneous Azacitidine Plus Best Supportive Care Versus Conventional Care Regimens Plus Best Supportive Care for the Treatment of Myelodysplastic Syndromes (MDS)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>AZA PH GL 2003 CL 001</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haematological diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other blood disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Azacitidine
Other interventions - Physician Choice

Experimental: Azacitidine - Study Drug plus best supportive care. Treatment with erythropoietin was not permitted

Active Comparator: Conventional Care - Physician choice of low dose cytarabine (plus best supportive care), standard chemotherapy (plus best supportive care) or best supportive care (only). Treatment with erythropoietin was not permitted


Treatment: drugs: Azacitidine
Azacitidine was injected subcutaneously (SC) at an initial dose of 75mg/m^2/day for 7 days. The 7-day dosing was repeated every 28 days with dose adjustment based on predefined hematology and renal laboratory results. Number of cycles: Azacitidine treatment was to be continued until the end of the study unless treatment was discontinued due to unacceptable toxicity, relapse after complete or partial response, transformation to AML or disease progression.

Other interventions: Physician Choice
Physician Choice was one of three options:
Best supportive care (BSC) alone,
Low-dose cytarabine subcutaneously for 14 days every 28 to 42 days, or
Standard chemotherapy administered for induction as a continuous intravenous infusion of cytarabine over 7 days plus an anthracycline (daunorubicin, idarubicin, or mitoxantrone) on Days 1, 2, and 3; and, for those eligible, 1 or 2 consolidation cycles administered as continuous intravenous infusions of cytarabine for 3 to 7 days with the same anthracycline that was used at induction on Days 1 and 2 (each cycle between 28 to 70 days from the start of the previous cycle).
All three options included best supportive care

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Kaplan-Meier Estimates for Median Time to Death From Any Cause - Kaplan-Meier estimates for the median months until death from any cause within the intent-to-treat population. Patients surviving at the end of the follow-up period were censored at the date of last contact. If a patient withdrew consent to follow-up or was lost to follow-up, the patient was censored as of the last date of contact.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 (randomization) to 42 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Summary of Subgroup Analyses for Kaplan-Meier Estimates for Time to Death From Any Cause - Kaplan-Meier estimates for the median months until death from any cause within the intent-to-treat population. Patients surviving at the end of the follow-up period were censored at the date of last contact. If a patient withdrew consent to follow-up or was lost to follow-up, the patient was censored as of the last date of contact.
Subgroups that were analyzed are age, gender, French-American-British (FAB) classification, World Health Organization (WHO) classification and International Prognostic Scoring System (IPSS) classification.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 (randomization) to 42 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants Who Died - Count of participants who died during the study</outcome>
      <timepoint>42 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Kaplan-Meier Estimate for Median Time to Transformation to Acute Myeloid Leukemia (AML) or Death From Any Cause, Whichever Occurred First - The time to transformation to AML or death from any cause (whichever occurred first) was defined as the number of days from the date of randomization until the date of documented AML transformation or death from any cause. Patients who did not transform to AML or die were censored at the date of last follow-up.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 (randomization) to 42 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Kaplan-Meier Estimates for Median Time to Transformation to Acute Myeloid Leukemia (AML) - The time to transformation to AML was defined as the number of days from the date of randomization until the date of documented AML transformation, defined as a bone marrow blast count = 30% independent of baseline bone marrow count. Patients who did not transform to AML were censored at the date of last follow-up or date of death.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 (randomization) to 42 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Summary of Participants' Red Blood Cell (RBC) Transfusion Status for Participants Who Were Transfusion Dependent at Baseline - Summary of dependence and independence from red blood cell (RBC) transfusion at baseline and during treatment, for patients who were dependent at baseline. A patient was considered transfusion independent at baseline if the patient had no transfusions during the 56 days prior to randomization. During study, a patient was considered transfusion independent during the on-treatment period if the patient had no transfusions during any 56 consecutive days or more. Otherwise, the patient was considered transfusion dependent.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 (randomization) to 42 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Summary of Participants' Red Blood Cell (RBC) Transfusion Status for Participants Who Were Transfusion Independent at Baseline - Summary of dependence and independence from red blood cell (RBC) transfusion at baseline and during treatment, for patients who were independent at baseline. A patient was considered transfusion independent at baseline if the patient had no transfusions during the 56 days prior to randomization. During study, a patient was considered transfusion independent during the on-treatment period if the patient had no transfusions during any 56 consecutive days or more. Otherwise, the patient was considered transfusion dependent.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 (randomization) to 42 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Summary of Participants' Platelet Transfusion Status for Participants Who Were Transfusion Dependent at Baseline - Summary of dependence and independence from platelet transfusion at baseline and during treatment for patients who were dependent at baseline. A patient was considered transfusion independent at baseline if the patient had no transfusions during the 56 days prior to randomization. During study, a patient was considered transfusion independent during the on-treatment period if the patient had no transfusions during any 56 consecutive days or more. Otherwise, the patient was considered transfusion dependent.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 (randomization) to 42 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Summary of Participants' Platelet Transfusion Status for Participants Who Were Transfusion Independent at Baseline - Summary of dependence and independence from platelet transfusion at baseline and during treatment for patients who were independent at baseline. A patient was considered transfusion independent at baseline if the patient had no transfusions during the 56 days prior to randomization. During study, a patient was considered transfusion independent during the on-treatment period if the patient had no transfusions during any 56 consecutive days or more. Otherwise, the patient was considered transfusion dependent.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 (randomization) to 42 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants Considered Hematologic Responders by Investigator Determinations Using International Working Group (IWG 2000) Criteria for Myelodysplastic Syndrome (MDS) - Investigator determined responses followed IWG criteria for
complete remission(CR): repeat bone marrow show &lt;5% myeloblasts, and peripheral blood evaluations lasting &gt;=2 months of hemoglobin(&gt;110 g/L), neutrophils(&gt;=1.5x10^9/L), platelets(&gt;=100x10^9/L), blasts (0%) and no dysplasia
partial remission(PR) is the same as CR for peripheral blood: bone marrow shows blasts decrease by &gt;=50% or a less advanced FAB classification from pretreatment
stable disease(SD) is a failure to achieve at least a partial remission, but with no evidence of progression for at least 2 months.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 to 42 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants Showing Hematologic Improvement Using International Working Group (IWG 2000) Criteria for Myelodysplastic Syndrome (MDS) Assessed by Independent Review Committee - IWG 2000 Criteria: Pretreatment=hemoglobin &lt;100g/L or RBC transfusion-dependent, platelet count &lt;100x10^9/L or platelet transfusion dependent, absolute neutrophil count &lt;1.5x10^9/L.
Erythroid response: Major-&gt;20g/L increase or transfusion independent. Minor- 10-20g/L increase or &gt;=50% decrease in transfusion requirements.
Platelet response: Major-absolute increase of &gt;=30x10^9/L or platelet transfusion independence. Minor-&gt;=50% increase.
Neutrophil response: Major-&gt;=100% increase or an absolute increase of &gt;0.5x10^9/L. Minor-&gt;=100% increase and absolute increase of &lt;0.5x10^9/L.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 to 42 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Disease Progression, Relapse After Complete or Partial Remission, or Death From Any Cause - The time to disease progression, relapse after complete or partial remission (CR, PR), or death from any cause was defined as the time from the date of randomization until the first date of documented disease progression, relapse after CR or PR, or death from any cause.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 (randomization) to 42 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of Any Hematologic Improvement - The duration of improvement was defined as the time from the date of hematologic improvement until the date of first documented progression or relapse after hematologic improvement or death from any cause.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 (randomization) to 42 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Infections Per Treatment Year Requiring Intravenous Antibiotics, Antifungals or Antivirals - The on-treatment adverse event rate of infection requiring IV antibiotics, antifungals, or antivirals per patient-years. The on-treatment period was considered the period from the date of randomization to the last treatment study visit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 (randomization) to 42 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants in Different Categories of Adverse Experiences During Core Study Period - Patient counts for a variety of subsets of adverse experiences for the core study period (day 1 to 42 months). The individual options for Conventional Care Regimens (Best Supportive Care Only, Low-Dose Cytarabine, and Standard Chemotherapy) are presented as separate treatments.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 (randomization) to 42 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Have a diagnosis of refractory anemia with excess blasts or refractory anemia with
             excess blasts in transformation according to the French-American-British
             classification system for myelodysplastic syndromes (MDS) and a relatively high risk
             of acute myeloid leukemia (AML) transformation, with an International Prognostic
             Scoring System score of INT-2 or High.

          -  Be 18 years of age or older

          -  Have a life expectancy of at least 3 months

          -  Be unlikely to proceed to bone marrow or stem cell transplantation therapy following
             remission

          -  Have serum bilirubin levels less than or equal to 1.5 times the upper limit of normal
             range for the laboratory

          -  Have serum glutamic-oxaloacetic transaminase (aspartate aminotransferase) or serum
             glutamic-pyruvic transaminase (alanine aminotransferase) levels less than or equal to
             2 times the upper limit of normal (unless these are considered to be related to
             transfusion-induced secondary hemosiderosis)

          -  Have serum creatinine levels less than or equal to 1.5 times the upper limit of normal</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Secondary myelodysplastic syndromes (MDS)

          -  Prior treatment with azacitidine;

          -  Prior history of acute myeloid leukemia (AML);

          -  Malignant disease diagnosed within prior 12 months;

          -  Metastatic disease;

          -  Hepatic tumors;

          -  Radiation, chemotherapy, cytotoxic therapy for non-MDS conditions within prior 12
             months;

          -  Prior transplantation or cytotoxic therapy to treat MDS;

          -  Serious medical illness likely to limit survival to 12 months or less;

          -  Treatment with erythropoietin or myeloid growth factors during prior 21 days or
             androgenic hormones during prior 13 days;

          -  Active HIV, viral hepatitis type B or C;

          -  Treatment with investigational drugs during prior 30 days;

          -  Within the 28-day screening period, documented red cell folate deficiency, as
             evidenced by red blood cell folate (not serum folate) or vitamin B12 deficiency</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/11/2003</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>358</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/07/2007</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,SA,VIC,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Liverpool Hospital - Liverpool</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal North Shore Hospital - St. Leonards</hospital>
    <hospital>The Newcastle Mater Miseriecordiae Hospital - Warratah</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane Hospital - Hersten</hospital>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>Peter MacCallum Cancer Institute - East Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>The Alfred Hospital - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>The Royal Perth Hospital - Perth</hospital>
    <postcode>2170 - Liverpool</postcode>
    <postcode>2065 - St. Leonards</postcode>
    <postcode>2298 - Warratah</postcode>
    <postcode>4029 - Hersten</postcode>
    <postcode>4102 - Woolloongabba</postcode>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>3002 - East Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3050 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3181 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>6847 - Perth</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Alabama</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Indiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Missouri</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Oregon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Pennsylvania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Wisconsin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Bulgaria</country>
      <state>Pleven</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Bulgaria</country>
      <state>Plovdiv</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Bulgaria</country>
      <state>Sofia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Bulgaria</country>
      <state>Varna</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czech Republic</country>
      <state>Brno</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czech Republic</country>
      <state>Hradec Kralove</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czech Republic</country>
      <state>Olomouc</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czech Republic</country>
      <state>Praha</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Angers</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Clichy</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Lille</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Lyon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Marseille</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Nantes</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Paris</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Rouen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Toulouse</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Berlin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Bonn</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Chemnitz</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Dresden</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Duisburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Dusseldorf</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Essen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Gottingen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Hamburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Kiel</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Ulm</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Athens</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Crete</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Ioannina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Patra</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Budapest</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Pecs</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Szeged</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Bologna</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Firenze</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Genova</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Milano</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Modena</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Roma</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>San Giovanni Rotondo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Sassari</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Amsterdam</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Nijmejen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Gdansk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Lodz</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Lublin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Warszawa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Wroclaw</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Moscow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>St. Petersburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Leon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Palma de Mallorca</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Salamanca</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Valencia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Goteborg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Lund</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Malmo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Stockholm</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Uppsala</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Bournemouth</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Manchester</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Norwich</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Oxford</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Truro</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Celgene Corporation</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to determine whether patients with high-risk myelodysplastic
      syndromes (MDS) treated with azacitidine have improved survival compared to conventional care
      treatments. The study will also assess the effect of treatments on response, duration of
      response, and transformation to acute myeloid leukemia (AML). The study will continue for 12
      months following last patient enrolled.

      See study AZA PH GL 2003 CL 001 E for information about the extension to this study.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00071799</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>CL Beach</name>
      <address>Celgene Corporation</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>