<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6669">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/08/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/08/2017</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT03261011</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Study of the Safety, Pharmacokinetics, and Antitumor Activity of AK104 in Subjects With Advanced Solid Tumors</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 1A/1B Multicenter, Open-label, Dose-escalation, and Dose-expansion Study to Evaluate the Safety, Pharmacokinetics, and Antitumor Activity of AK104 in Subjects With Advanced Solid Tumors</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>AK104-101</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Advanced Cancer</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - AK-104

Experimental: AK-104 - Single-arm


Other interventions: AK-104
Subjects will receive AK104 by intravenous administration.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of participants with adverse events (AEs) - An AE is defined as any untoward medical occurrence in a participant administered a pharmaceutical product temporally associated with the use of study treatment, whether or not considered related to the study treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From the time of informed consent signed through 90 days after the last dose of AK104, up to 2 years and 3 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of participants with a Dose Limiting Toxicity (DLT) - DLTs will be assessed during the first 4 weeks of treatment for dose-escalation phase and are defined as toxicities that meet pre-defined severity criteria, and assessed as having a suspected relationship to study drug, and unrelated to disease, disease progression, inter-current illness, or concomitant medications that occurs within the first cycle (4 weeks) of treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the first 4 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Objective response rate (ORR) - The ORR is defined as the proportion of subjects with confirmed CR or confirmed PR, based on RECIST Version 1.1.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 3 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disease control rate (DCR) - The DCR is defined as the proportion of subjects with CR, PR, or SD (subjects achieving SD will be included in the DCR if they maintain SD for =8 weeks) based on RECIST Version 1.1.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 3 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of response (DoR) - Duration of response is defined as the duration from the first documentation of objective response to the first documented disease progression or death due to any cause, whichever occurs first.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 3 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression-free survival (PFS) - Progression-free survival is defined as the time from the start of treatment with AK104 until the first documentation of disease progression or death due to any cause, whichever occurs first.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 3 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall survival (OS) - Overall survival is defined as the time from the start of treatment with AK104 until death due to any cause.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 3 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Area under the curve (AUC) of AK104 - The endpoints for assessment of PK of AK104 include serum concentrations of AK104 at different timepoints after AK104 administration.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From first dose of AK104 through 90 days after last dose of AK104; Up to 2 years and 3 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximum observed concentration (Cmax) of AK104 - The endpoints for assessment of PK of AK104 include serum concentrations of AK104 at different timepoints after AK104 administration.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From first dose of AK104 through to 90 days after last dose of AK104; Up to 2 years and 3 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Minimum observed concentration (Cmin) of AK104 at steady state - The endpoints for assessment of PK of AK104 include serum concentrations of AK104 at different timepoints after AK104 administration.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From first dose of AK104 through to 90 days after last dose of AK104; Up to 2 years and 3 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of subjects who develop detectable anti-drug antibodies (ADAs) - The immunogenicity of AK104 will be assessed by summarizing the number of subjects who develop detectable anti-drug antibodies (ADAs).</outcome>
      <timepoint>From first dose of AK104 through to 90 days after last dose of AK104; Up to 2 years and 3 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Written and signed informed consent and any locally required authorization obtained
             from the subject/legal representative.

          -  In dose-escalation cohorts (Phase 1a), histologically or cytologically documented
             advanced or metastatic solid tumor that is refractory/relapsed to standard therapies,
             or for which no effective standard therapy is available, or the subject refuses
             standard therapy.

          -  In the dose-expansion cohorts (Phase 1b), histologically or cytologically confirmed
             selected advanced solid tumors (to be determined). Subjects must have received no more
             than three prior lines of systemic therapy for advanced or metastatic disease.

          -  Subject must have at least one measurable lesion according to RECIST Version1.1.

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Score of 0 or 1.

          -  Available archived tumor tissue sample to allow for correlative biomarker studies. In
             the setting where archival material is unavailable or unsuitable for use, the subject
             must consent and undergo fresh tumor biopsy.

          -  Adequate organ function.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  History of severe hypersensitivity reactions to other mAbs.

          -  Prior exposure to any anti-PD-1, anti-PD-L1, anti-CTL4 antibody or any other antibody
             or drug targeting T-cell costimulation or checkpoint pathways such as ICOS, or
             agonists such as CD40, CD137, GITR, OX40 etc.

          -  Receipt of any immunotherapy, any conventional or investigational systemic anticancer
             therapy within 4 weeks prior to the first dose of AK104; in the case of mAbs, 6 weeks
             prior to the first dose of AK104.

          -  Any concurrent chemotherapy, immunotherapy, biologic or hormonal therapy for cancer
             treatment. Concurrent use of hormones for non-cancer-related conditions is acceptable.

          -  Subjects with a condition requiring systemic treatment with either corticosteroid (&gt;
             10 mg daily prednisone equivalents) or other immunosuppressive medications within 14
             days of study drug administration.

          -  Active or prior documented autoimmune disease within the past 2 years.

          -  Active or prior documented inflammatory bowel disease (eg, Crohn's disease, ulcerative
             colitis).

          -  History of primary immunodeficiency.

          -  History of organ transplant or hematopoietic stem cell that requires use of
             immunosuppressives.

          -  Known allergy or reaction to any component of the AK104 formulation.

          -  History of interstitial lung disease or non-infectious pneumonitis except for those
             induced by radiation therapies.

          -  Any condition that, in the opinion of the investigator, would interfere with
             evaluation of the investigational product or interpretation of subject safety or study
             results.

          -  Known history of tuberculosis.

          -  Known history of testing positive for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or known
             acquired immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS).

          -  Any positive test for hepatitis B or hepatitis C virus indicating acute or chronic
             infection except for subjects with HCC.

          -  An active infection requiring systemic therapy with the exception of anti-viral
             therapy for hepatitis as specified by the protocol.

          -  Receipt of live or attenuated vaccination within 30 days prior to the first dose of
             AK104.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>153</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/09/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Monash Health - Clayton</hospital>
    <hospital>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Linear Clinical Research/Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital - Nedlands</hospital>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
    <postcode>3002 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Akesobio Australia Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is to characterize the safety, tolerability, pharmacokinetics (PK),
      immunogenicity, pharmacodynamics (PD) and anti-tumor activity of AK104 as a single agent in
      adult subjects with advanced solid tumor malignancies. The study consists of a dose
      escalation phase (Phase 1a) to determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD), or recommended
      Phase 2 dose (RP2D) for AK104 as a single agent, and a dose expansion phase (Phase 1b) which
      will characterize treatment of AK104 as a single agent at the MTD or RP2D.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03261011</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Xiaoping Jin, PhD</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+86 (0760) 8987 3999</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>clinicaltrials@akesobio.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>