<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5704">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/09/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/09/2014</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02278263</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Tranexamic Acid in Knee Joint Surgery</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Tranexamic Acid in Knee Joint Surgery - a Randomised Controlled Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>TRACKS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>TRACKS Study</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Osteoarthritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Tranexamic Acid
Treatment: drugs - Normal saline (0.9% NaCl)

Placebo Comparator: Control - Application of 20ml of normal saline (NaCl 0.9%) topically after implantation of prosthesis and left to sit for two minutes, excess carefully suctioned followed by standard closure with no drains; application of 15ml of normal saline intravenously at the same time prior to release of tourniquet.

Experimental: Topical - Application of 1.5g in 20ml tranexamic acid topically after implantation of prosthesis with excess carefully suctioned followed by standard closure with no drains; application of 15ml of normal saline intravenously at the same time prior to release of tourniquet.

Experimental: Systemic - Application of 20ml of normal saline topically after implantation of prosthesis with excess carefully suctioned followed by standard closure with no drains; Application of tranexamic acid intravenously (1.5g/15ml) at the same time prior to release of tourniquet


Treatment: drugs: Tranexamic Acid
Given intravenously or topically

Treatment: drugs: Normal saline (0.9% NaCl)
Administered in all 3 groups

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood loss - The loss of Hb (in grams) was then estimated according to the formula:
Hb(loss)=BV (blood volume) x (Hbi-Hbe) x 0.001+Hbt
where Hb (loss) (g) is the amount of Hb lost, Hbi (g/L) the Hb concentration before surgery, Hbe (g/L) is the Hbe concentration on the third day after surgery, and Hbt (g) is the total amount of allogeneic Hb transfused. A unit of banked blood is considered to contain a minimum of 40g Hb (Blood component data sheet, NZBS). All units of blood are processed and stored in a nationally standardised manner. The blood loss (ml) was related to the patient's preoperative Hb value (g/L):
Blood loss =1000 x Hb(loss) /Hbi</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post operative day 3</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain - Using the Numeric rating scale (NRS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Postoperativley for the first 3 days after surgery, 4 times per day</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Function - Using the Oxford Knee Scores and range of movement (ROM)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Preop, 6 weeks and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life - Using Short Form Health Survey 12 (SF-12)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Preop, 6 weeks and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Complications - Deep vein thrombosis/pulmonary embolus (DVT/PE), death, myocardial infarction/cerebrovascular accident (MI/CVA), infection (deep and superficial), manipulation under anaesthesia (MUA), urinary tract infection (UTI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Postoperatively withn 30 days after surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Transfusion rates - Those patients receiving blood products. Standardised protocol is as follows:
The criterion for transfusion of blood products will be a haemoglobin &lt; 80g/L or a haemoglobin &lt;100g/L in a patient with ischaemic heart disease or with significant symptomatology</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants will be followed for the duration of their hospital stay expected to be an average of 3-5 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of stay (LOS) - Day of surgery is counted as Day 0.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Average length of stay is expected to be 3 to 5 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Readmission rates - Returning to hospital for &gt;24 hours admission</outcome>
      <timepoint>All readmissions to hospital 30 days after date of surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  All patients at the participating sites on the waiting list for a unilateral total
             knee joint replacement</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Patients with a history or risk of thrombosis

          -  Active thromboembolic disease such as deep vein thrombosis, pulmonary embolism and
             cerebral thrombosis

          -  Subarachnoid haemorrhage

          -  Hypersensitivity to tranexamic acid or any of its ingredients.

          -  Refusal of blood products

          -  Colour blindness

          -  Complex hematologic disorders requiring manipulation

          -  Coagulopathy

          -  Pregnant and Lactating Women

          -  Anti-coagulant therapy pre-operatively within 5 days of surgery (warfarin, dabigatran,
             heparin)

          -  Severe renal failure (eGFR &lt;29)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2>The people administering the treatment/s</masking2>
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/12/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Unknown status</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/12/2015</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Nelson</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Tauranga</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Andrew G Hill</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Total knee joint replacement surgery can lead to significant blood loss, which can affect
      recovery after surgery. Tranexamic acid (TXA) is a medication which stops the breakdown of
      blood clots and therefore prevents blood loss. The optimal use of TXA remains a point of
      debate. Growing interest in the topical application of TXA (directly into the surgical wound)
      has been suggested as an alternative way of administering TXA, and may demonstrate similar
      effectiveness as when it is given intravenously. Therefore, this multicentred, randomized
      controlled trial, aims to investigate the safety and effectiveness of both topical and
      intravenous administrations of TXA in total knee joint surgery. The investigators predict
      that both routes of administration will demonstrate similar results when compared to placebo.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02278263</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Carson JL, Duff A, Berlin JA, Lawrence VA, Poses RM, Huber EC, O'Hara DA, Noveck H, Strom BL. Perioperative blood transfusion and postoperative mortality. JAMA. 1998 Jan 21;279(3):199-205.
Alshryda S, Sarda P, Sukeik M, Nargol A, Blenkinsopp J, Mason JM. Tranexamic acid in total knee replacement: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Bone Joint Surg Br. 2011 Dec;93(12):1577-85. doi: 10.1302/0301-620X.93B12.26989. Review.
Sukeik M, Alshryda S, Haddad FS, Mason JM. Systematic review and meta-analysis of the use of tranexamic acid in total hip replacement. J Bone Joint Surg Br. 2011 Jan;93(1):39-46. doi: 10.1302/0301-620X.93B1.24984. Review.
Gandhi R, Evans HM, Mahomed SR, Mahomed NN. Tranexamic acid and the reduction of blood loss in total knee and hip arthroplasty: a meta-analysis. BMC Res Notes. 2013 May 7;6:184. doi: 10.1186/1756-0500-6-184.
CRASH-2 collaborators, Roberts I, Shakur H, Afolabi A, Brohi K, Coats T, Dewan Y, Gando S, Guyatt G, Hunt BJ, Morales C, Perel P, Prieto-Merino D, Woolley T. The importance of early treatment with tranexamic acid in bleeding trauma patients: an exploratory analysis of the CRASH-2 randomised controlled trial. Lancet. 2011 Mar 26;377(9771):1096-101, 1101.e1-2. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(11)60278-X.
Williams-Johnson JA, McDonald AH, Strachan GG, Williams EW. Effects of tranexamic acid on death, vascular occlusive events, and blood transfusion in trauma patients with significant haemorrhage (CRASH-2) A randomised, placebo-controlled trial. West Indian Med J. 2010 Dec;59(6):612-24.
Wind TC, Barfield WR, Moskal JT. The effect of tranexamic acid on blood loss and transfusion rate in primary total knee arthroplasty. J Arthroplasty. 2013 Aug;28(7):1080-3. doi: 10.1016/j.arth.2012.11.016. Epub 2013 Mar 28.
Wind TC, Barfield WR, Moskal JT. The effect of tranexamic acid on transfusion rate in primary total hip arthroplasty. J Arthroplasty. 2014 Feb;29(2):387-9. doi: 10.1016/j.arth.2013.05.026. Epub 2013 Jun 21.
Ishida K, Tsumura N, Kitagawa A, Hamamura S, Fukuda K, Dogaki Y, Kubo S, Matsumoto T, Matsushita T, Chin T, Iguchi T, Kurosaka M, Kuroda R. Intra-articular injection of tranexamic acid reduces not only blood loss but also knee joint swelling after total knee arthroplasty. Int Orthop. 2011 Nov;35(11):1639-45. doi: 10.1007/s00264-010-1205-3. Epub 2011 Jan 21.
Later AF, Sitniakowsky LS, van Hilten JA, van de Watering L, Brand A, Smit NP, Klautz RJ. Antifibrinolytics attenuate inflammatory gene expression after cardiac surgery. J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 2013 Jun;145(6):1611-6, 1616.e1-4. doi: 10.1016/j.jtcvs.2012.11.042. Epub 2013 Jan 16.
Robertshaw HJ. An anti-inflammatory role for tranexamic acid in cardiac surgery? Crit Care. 2008;12(1):105. doi: 10.1186/cc6210. Epub 2008 Jan 16.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jacob T Munro, MBChB, FRACS</name>
      <address>Department of Surgery, The University of Auckland</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Marinus Stowers, MBChB</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+64 9 2760044</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>msto062@aucklanduni.ac.nz</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>