<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3001">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/11/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/11/2010</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01247428</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>First-In-Human Trial of the MiStent Drug-Eluting Stent (DES) in Coronary Artery Disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A First-In-Human Trial of a New Novel DES (MiStent System) With Sirolimus and a Bioabsorbable Polymer for the Treatment of Patients With De Novo Lesions in the Native Coronary Arteries</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>DESSOLVE-I</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>MIS-FIH-2010-01</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Coronary Artery Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - MiStent SES

Experimental: MiStent SES - The MiStent SES is a device/drug combination comprised of two components; a stent and a drug product (sirolimus within an absorbable polymer coating).


Treatment: devices: MiStent SES
The MiStent SES is a device/drug combination comprised of two components; a stent and a drug product (sirolimus within an absorbable polymer coating).

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Angiographic In-Stent Late Lumen Loss - In-stent late lumen loss as measured by the angiographic core laboratory as the difference between the post-procedure minimal lumen diameters (MLD) in the treated segment (stented region) minus the MLD in the same region at follow-up.</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants Experiencing Major Adverse Cardiac Events (MACE) - Major Adverse Cardiac Events (MACE) defined as death, myocardial infarction (Q-wave and non-Q-wave) and target vessel revascularization (TVR)</outcome>
      <timepoint>240 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Device Success - Achievement of a final in-stent residual diameter stenosis of &lt;50% (by QCA), using the assigned device only</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lesion Success - Achievement of a final in-stent residual diameter stenosis of &lt;50% (by QCA) using any percutaneous method</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Procedural Success - Achievement of a final in-stent residual diameter stenosis of &lt;50% (by QCA) using the assigned device (including any adjunctive devices) without cardiac death, Myocardial infarction (MI) or repeat revascularization of the target lesion pre-hospital discharge</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total Mortality - Total mortality (cardiac and non-cardiac)</outcome>
      <timepoint>240 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total Myocardial Infarction (MI) - Q-wave MI (QWMI): requires one of the following criteria: the development of new abnormal Q waves in =2 contiguous ECG leads not present on the patient's baseline (i.e., before intervention) in association with a &gt;2x upper limit normal elevation of creatine kinase (CK) levels. In the absence of ECG data, the clinical events committee may adjudicate a Q-wave MI based on the clinical scenario and appropriate cardiac enzyme data; chest pain or other acute symptoms consistent with myocardial ischemia and new pathological Q waves in =2 contiguous ECG leads in the absence of timely cardiac enzyme data.
Non-Q-wave MI (NQWMI): the elevation of CK levels (=2 times ULN) with elevated CK-MB enzyme levels in the absence of new pathologic Q waves.</outcome>
      <timepoint>240 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinically-driven Target Lesion Revascularization (TLR) Rates - A revascularization is considered clinically driven if angiography at follow-up shows a percent diameter stenosis = 50% (Angiographic Core Laboratory QCA assessment) and if one of the following occurs:
A positive history of recurrent angina pectoris, presumably related to the target vessel;
Objective signs of ischemia at rest (ECG changes) or during exercise test (or equivalent), presumably related to the target vessel;
Abnormal results of any invasive functional diagnostic test (e.g., Doppler flow velocity reserve, fractional flow reserve);
A target lesion revascularization (TLR) with a diameter stenosis = 70% even in the absence of the above-mentioned ischemic signs or symptoms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>240 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinically-driven Target Vessel Revascularization (TVR) Rates - A revascularization is considered clinically driven if angiography at follow-up shows a percent diameter stenosis = 50% (Angiographic Core Laboratory QCA assessment) and if one of the following occurs:
A positive history of recurrent angina pectoris, presumably related to the target vessel;
Objective signs of ischemia at rest (ECG changes) or during exercise test (or equivalent), presumably related to the target vessel;
Abnormal results of any invasive functional diagnostic test (e.g., Doppler flow velocity reserve, fractional flow reserve);
A target vessel revascularization (TVR) with a diameter stenosis = 70% even in the absence of the above-mentioned ischemic signs or symptoms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>240 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Target Vessel Failure (TVF) - Target vessel failure (TVF) is defined as the composite endpoint of:
cardiac death,
target-vessel myocardial infarction (Q wave or non-Q wave), and
clinically indicated target vessel revascularization</outcome>
      <timepoint>240 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Target Lesion Failure (TLF) - Target lesion failure (TLF) is defined as the composite endpoint of:
cardiac death,
target-lesion myocardial infarction (Q wave or non-Q wave), and
clinically indicated target lesion revascularization</outcome>
      <timepoint>240 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stent Thrombosis - The presence of an intracoronary thrombus that originates in the stent or in the segments 5 mm proximal or distal to the stent post-procedure</outcome>
      <timepoint>240 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Angiographic Evaluation: In-stent Binary Restenosis - Binary Restenosis is defined as =50% luminal narrowing at follow-up angiography.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 months, 6 months, 8 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Angiographic Evaluation: In-stent Binary Restenosis - Binary Restenosis is defined as =50% luminal narrowing at follow-up angiography.</outcome>
      <timepoint>18 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intravascular Ultrasound (IVUS) Evaluation: % Neointimal Volume Obstruction - % neointimal volume obstruction is defined as the neointimal volume divided by stent volume.</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>IVUS Evaluation: % Neointimal Volume Obstruction - % neointimal volume obstruction is defined as the neointimal volume divided by stent volume.</outcome>
      <timepoint>18 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Optical Coherence Tomography (OCT) Evaluation: % Stent Strut Uncovered - % stent strut uncovered is defined as the ratio of uncovered struts to total struts in all cross-sections.</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>OCT Evaluation: % Stent Strut Uncovered - % stent strut uncovered is defined as the ratio of uncovered struts to total struts in all cross-sections.</outcome>
      <timepoint>18 M</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Male/female patients 18-85 years;

          2. Stable or unstable angina pectoris, ischemia, or silent ischemia;

          3. Planned single, de novo, types A, B1 and B2 coronary lesions;

          4. Target lesion located in a native coronary artery;

          5. Target lesion vessel diameter 2.5 to 3.5 mm amenable to treatment with a maximum 23 mm
             long stent;

          6. Target lesion &gt;50% diameter stenosis;

          7. Patients eligible for percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI);

          8. Acceptable candidate for myocardial revascularization surgery;

          9. A patient may have one additional critical non-target lesion.

         10. The patient will provide written informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Female of childbearing potential not on some form of birth control with a confirmed
             negative pregnancy test at baseline;

          2. Recent Q-wave myocardial infarction occurred &lt;72 hours prior to the index procedure.
             Recent myocardial infarction with elevated levels of cardiac markers;

          3. Left ventricular ejection fraction &lt;30%;

          4. Patients in cardiogenic shock;

          5. Cerebrovascular accident or transient ischemic attack within 6 months;

          6. Active GI bleed within three months;

          7. Any prior true anaphylactic reaction to contrast agents;

          8. Patient receiving/scheduled to receive chemotherapy within 30-days before or after the
             index procedure;

          9. Patient is receiving immunosuppressive therapy or has known life-limiting
             immunosuppressive/autoimmune disease;

         10. Renal dysfunction (creatinine &gt; 2.0 mg/dL or 177 µmol/L);

         11. Platelet count &lt;100,000 cells/mm³ or &gt;700,000 cells/mm³;

         12. White blood cell count &lt;3,000 cells/mm3;

         13. Hepatic disease;

         14. Heart transplant recipient;

         15. Known contraindication to dual antiplatelet therapy;

         16. Known hypersensitivity to sirolimus, cobalt-chromium, or to medications such as
             aspirin, heparin, and all three of the following: clopidogrel bisulfate (Plavix),
             ticlopidine (Ticlid), and Prasugrel (Effient);

         17. Life expectancy &lt;12 months;

         18. Any major medical condition that may interfere with the optimal participation of the
             patient in this study;

         19. Patient is currently participating/planning to participate in an investigational drug
             or another device study prior to completing 12-months follow-up;

         20. Target vessel(s) has been treated within 10 mm proximal or distal to target lesion
             with any type of PCI within a year prior to index procedure;

         21. Planned or actual target vessel(s) treatment with an unapproved device, directional or
             rotational coronary atherectomy, laser, cutting balloon, or transluminal extraction
             catheter prior to stent placement;

         22. Previous coronary intravascular brachytherapy;

         23. Planned coronary angioplasty or coronary artery bypass grafting (CABG)in the first 9
             months after the index procedure;

         24. Prior PCI of a non-target vessel must be at least 30 days prior to study enrollment;

         25. The intent to direct stent the target lesion;

         26. Angiographic  Assessed prior to stent placement;

               -  In-stent restenotic target lesion;

               -  More than one lesion requiring treatment in the target vessel;

               -  Target vessel diameter &lt;2.5 mm or &gt;3.5 mm;

               -  Target lesion not amenable to treatment with a 23 mm long stent;

               -  Unprotected coronary artery branch lesion (=50% DS);

               -  Target lesion located in a surgical bypass graft;

               -  Total vessel occlusion;

               -  Target lesion with ostial location;

               -  Target lesion located in a lateral branch bifurcation &gt;2.5mm or requiring lateral
                  branch stenting;

               -  Calcified target lesion that anticipates unsuccessful/impracticable predilation;

               -  Target vessel excessive tortuosity or proximal angulation (&gt;90 degrees);

               -  Thrombus present in target vessel;

               -  More than one non-target critical lesion;

        Non-target lesion to be treated during the index procedure meets any of the following
        criteria:

          -  Within the target vessel;

          -  Within a bypass graft;

          -  Left main location;

          -  Chronic total occlusion;

          -  Involves a complex bifurcation.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/11/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>30</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/03/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>St. Vincent's Hospital Melbourne - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode> - Melbourne</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Aalst</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Genk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Aukland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Micell Technologies</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The DESSOLVE I clinical trial is to assess the safety and performance of the
      sirolimus-eluting MiStent SES.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01247428</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>William Wijns, MD</name>
      <address>Cardiovascular Center, Onze-Lieve-Vrouwziekenhuis Aalst (OLV Hospital)</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>