<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2962">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/10/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/10/2010</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01227967</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparing the Efficacy, Safety, and Tolerability of Combination Antivirals (Amantadine, Ribavirin, Oseltamivir) Versus Oseltamivir for the Treatment of Influenza in Adults at Risk for Complications</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomized Double-Blind Phase 2 Study Comparing the Efficacy, Safety, and Tolerability of Combination Antivirals (Amantadine, Ribavirin, Oseltamivir) Versus Oseltamivir for the Treatment of Influenza in Adults at Risk for Complications</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>IRC003</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>10-I-0210</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>10-I-0210</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Influenza</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Amantadine, Ribavirin, Oseltamivir
Treatment: drugs - Oseltamivir

Experimental: Combination Therapy - Amantadine, Ribavirin, Oseltamivir

Active Comparator: Oseltamivir monotherapy - Oseltamivir


Treatment: drugs: Amantadine, Ribavirin, Oseltamivir
Subjects were prescribed the medication twice daily for 5 days, and each dose consisted of one capsule of Oseltamivir 75 mg, three capsules of Ribavirin 200 mg for total of 600 mg, and one capsule of Amantadine 100 mg.

Treatment: drugs: Oseltamivir
Subjects were prescribed the medication twice daily for 5 days, and each dose consisted of one capsule of Oseltamivir 75 mg.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants With Virus Detectable by Quantitative PCR (qPCR) in Nasopharyngeal (NP) Swabs - The central laboratory performed a qualitative PCR test on the NP sample from Day 0 in order to confirm influenza infection and to determine the influenza type and subtype. For participants with a positive influenza test result at Day 0 from this qualitative PCR testing, the laboratory then performed qPCR testing of subsequent samples to quantify viral shedding.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Day 3</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants by Virus Detection Status - Number of participants who had undetectable values (less than the limit of detection [LOD]), who had values between the LOD and the lower limit of quantification (LLOQ), and who had values =LLOQ</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Day 0, 3 and 7.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>qPCR Viral Shedding - Median, 25% and 75% percentile of the value of viral shedding (Results &lt;LOD were imputed as the LOD value, and Results &gt;= LOD, &lt;LLOQ were imputed as the LLOQ value.)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Day 0, 3 and 7</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants Shedding Virus - Number of participants with undetectable viral load at both Day 3 and Day 7; detectable at Day 3 and undetectable at Day 7; detectable at Day 7 (irrespective of whether or not detectable at Day 3).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At day 3 and 7.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Alleviation of Influenza Clinical Symptoms. - The assessed symptoms were cough, nasal obstruction (stuffy nose), sore throat, fatigue, headache, muscle aches, feverishness, rhinorrhea, nausea, vomiting, diarrhea. Duration of clinical symptoms is defined as the time from Day 0 to the first of two successive measurements at which all clinical symptoms are grade 0 (absent) or 1 (mild). A measurement is considered to be the 8AM or 8PM assessment during Days 0 to 7 (so two measurements are obtained per day) and then the daily assessment thereafter. Time will then be calculated in half-days through to Day 7. If a subject's first two assessments on (baseline assessment and first subsequent diary card assessment) satisfy this criterion, then the duration will be set to zero. For participants who did not have two successive records meeting this criterion, follow-up was censored for analysis purposes at the time of the last but one diary card record with symptoms evaluated.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From treatment initiation to Day 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Absence of Fever - Fever was considered present based on the diary cards if a subject reported a maximal temperature =38.0°C (for the period since the diary card was previously completed) or reported having taken an antipyretic drug (also for the period since the diary card was previously completed). Otherwise, fever was considered not present during the period since the diary card was previously completed, except that the evaluation was considered missing if either the temperature or the antipyretic drug use entry was not completed on the diary card. The duration of fever was defined as the time from Day 0 to the first of two successive assessments (through to Day 7) or to the first assessment (Day 8 onwards) at which no fever was present according to this definition.For participants who did not have two successive records meeting this criterion, follow-up was censored for analysis purposes at the time of the last but one diary card record with fever evaluated.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From treatment initiation to Day 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Resolution of All Symptoms AND Fever - The assessed symptoms were cough, nasal obstruction (stuffy nose), sore throat, fatigue, headache, muscle aches, feverishness, rhinorrhea, nausea, vomiting, diarrhea. Fever was considered present based on the diary cards if a subject reported a maximal temperature =38.0°C (for the period since the diary card was previously completed) or reported having taken an antipyretic drug (also for the period since the diary card was previously completed). Time to resolution of all clinical symptoms and fever is defined as the time from Day 0 to the first of two successive measurements at which all clinical symptoms are grade 0 (absent) or 1(mild) and no fever &gt;=38.0 C or antipyretic drug is reported. For participants who did not have two successive records meeting this criterion, follow-up was censored for analysis purposes at the time of the last but one diary card record with symptoms and fever evaluated.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From treatment initiation to Day 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Feeling as Good as Before the Onset of the Influenza Illness - Time to feeling as good as before influenza is defined as time to the first of two successive 'yes' responses to the question of 'feeling as good as you did before you had the flu'.For participants who did not have two successive records meeting this criterion, follow-up was censored for analysis purposes at the time of the last but one diary card record with question answered.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From treatment initiation to Day 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Return to Pre-influenza Function - Time to return to pre-influenza function is defined as the time from Day 0 to the first of two successive 'Yes' answers to the global assessment question 'Are you functioning as well as you were before you had the flu'.For participants who did not have two successive records meeting this criterion, follow-up was censored for analysis purposes at the time of the last but one diary card record with question answered.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From treatment initiation to Day 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Return of Physical Function to Pre-illness Leve - Time to return of physical function to pre-illness level was defined as the time from Day 0 to the first of two successive measurements at which the physical function score equals or is better than the pre-illness score (obtained by recall at enrollment).For subjects who did not have two successive records meeting this criterion, follow-up was censored for analysis purposes at the time of the last but one diary card record with physical function evaluated.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From treatment initiation to Day 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants With Clinical Failure at Day 5 - Clinical failure at Day 5 is defined as the need for continued (non-study) antiviral use after Day 5.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From treatment initiation to Day 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants Who Develop Bronchitis, Pneumonia, or Other Complications of Influenza After Day 0. - Participants were assessed for the signs/symptoms suggestive of one of the following complications: Sinusitis, Otitis Media ,Bronchitis / Bronchiolitis, Pneumonia and antibiotic use for reason other than above.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From treatment initiation to Day 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants Who Required New or Increased Use of Supplemental Oxygen - Percentage of participants who required new or increased use of supplemental oxygen</outcome>
      <timepoint>From treatment initiation to Day 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants Who Required Hospitalization. - The percentage of participants hospitalized by 28 days was estimated from the Kaplan-Meier curves.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From treatment initiation to Day 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>28-day Mortality - Number of deaths</outcome>
      <timepoint>From treatment initiation to Day 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Enrollment (Screening)

          1. Signed informed consent prior to initiation of any study procedures

          2. Presence of an underlying medical condition(s) that might increase risk of
             complications from influenza

          3. History of an influenza-like illness defined as:

               -  One or more respiratory symptom (cough, sore throat, or nasal symptoms) AND

               -  Either

               -  Fever (subjective or documented &gt;38 degrees C) OR

               -  1 or more constitutional symptom (headache, malaise, myalgia, sweats/chills or
                  fatigue)

          4. Onset of illness no more than 96 hours before screening defined as when the subject
             experienced at least one respiratory symptom, constitutional symptom, or fever

          5. Willingness to have samples stored

        Randomization

          1. Signed informed consent

          2. Presence of a medical condition(s) that had been associated with increased risk of
             complications from influenza

               -  Age 65 years of age or older

               -  Asthma

               -  Neurological and neuro-developmental conditions (including disorders of the
                  brain, spinal cord, peripheral nerve, and muscle such as cerebral palsy, epilepsy
                  [seizure disorders], stroke, moderate to severe developmental delay, muscular
                  dystrophy, or spinal cord injury) [though still able to provide informed consent
                  per inclusion criteria #1]

               -  Chronic lung disease (such as COPD and cystic fibrosis)

               -  Heart disease (such as congenital heart disease, congestive heart failure, and
                  coronary artery disease)

               -  Blood disorders (excluding genetic causes of anemia, as noted in the exclusion
                  criteria)

               -  Endocrine disorders (such as diabetes mellitus)

               -  Kidney disorders

               -  Liver disorders

               -  Metabolic disorders (such as inherited metabolic disorders and mitochondrial
                  disorders)

               -  Weakened immune system due to disease or medication (such as people with
                  HIV/AIDS, or cancer, chronic steroids or other medications causing immune
                  suppression)

               -  BMI = 40(kg/m²)

          3. Onset of illness no more than 96 hours before screening defined as when the subject
             experienced at least one respiratory symptom, constitutional symptom, or fever

          4. Positive test for influenza (either rapid antigen or PCR)

             - Results from influenza testing obtained for clinical indications within 12 hours
             before screening/enrollment may be used if available. Randomization may proceed in
             cases of discrepant results (one positive and one negative)

          5. One of the following to avoid pregnancy:

               -  Females who were able to become pregnant (i.e., are not postmenopausal, have not
                  undergone surgical sterilization, and are sexually active with men) must agree to
                  use at least 2 effective forms of contraception from the date of informed consent
                  through 6 months after the last dose of study drug. At least one of the methods
                  of contraception should be a barrier method

               -  Males who had not undergone surgical sterilization and are sexually active with
                  women must agree to use condoms plus have a partner use at least one additional
                  effective form of contraception from the date of informed consent through 6
                  months after the last dose of study drug

          6. Willingness to have samples stored

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        (for Enrollment or Randomization)

          1. Women who were pregnant or breast-feeding, and men whose female partner(s) was
             pregnant

          2. Inability to take oral medication or a history of gastrointestinal malabsorption that
             would preclude the use of oral medication.

          3. Hemoglobin &lt; 10 g/dL

          4. WBC &lt; 1.5 times 10(9)/L

          5. Neutrophils &lt; 0.75 x 10(9)/L

          6. Platelets &lt; 50 x 10(9)/L

          7. History of genetic hemoglobinopathy (e.g., thalassemia major or sickle cell anemia) or
             autoimmune hemolytic anemia

          8. Received more than 2 doses of any antiviral influenza medications since onset of
             influenza symptoms

          9. Received stavudine (d4T), didanosine (ddI), zidovudine (AZT), or azathioprine within
             30 days prior to study entry

         10. Creatinine clearance less than 60 mL/min (estimated by the Cockcroft-Gault equation
             using serum creatinine)

         11. History of autoimmune hepatitis

         12. Uncompensated liver disease (defined as AST &gt; 3 times site upper limit of normal
             (ULN), ALT &gt; 3 times ULN, or Direct Bilirubin &gt; 2 times ULN)

         13. Clinical signs of end-stage liver disease including jaundice, coagulopathy, portal
             hypertension, esophageal varices, ascites, peripheral edema, gastrointestinal
             bleeding, or encephalopathy

         14. Chronic liver disease categorized as Child-Pugh class C (Child-Pugh score 10-15)

         15. Known hypersensitivity to rimantadine, amantadine, ribavirin, oseltamivir, peramivir,
             or zanamivir

         16. Received live attenuated virus vaccine (influenza or other) within 3 weeks prior to
             study entry

         17. Use of any investigational drug within 30 days or 5 half-lives (whichever was longer)
             prior to study entry

         18. Participation in other research protocols that would require more than 100 mL of blood
             to be drawn in any 4-week period that overlaps with this study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria />
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/09/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>881</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>30/03/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Holdsworth House Med Practice - Darlinghurst</hospital>
    <hospital>Taylor Square Private Clinic - Darlinghurst</hospital>
    <hospital>Westmead Hospital - Westmead</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>Northside Clinic - Fitzroy North</hospital>
    <hospital>The Alfred Hospital - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>2010 - Darlinghurst</postcode>
    <postcode> - Westmead</postcode>
    <postcode>4029 - Herston</postcode>
    <postcode>3068 - Fitzroy North</postcode>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Alabama</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Arizona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Colorado</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Illinois</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Iowa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Kentucky</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Louisiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Maryland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Massachusetts</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Michigan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Missouri</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Nebraska</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Jersey</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Pennsylvania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>South Dakota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Tennessee</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Virginia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Argentina</country>
      <state>Buenos Aires</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Argentina</country>
      <state>Provincia de Buenos Aires</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Argentina</country>
      <state>Cordoba</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Argentina</country>
      <state>Santa Fe</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mexico</country>
      <state>México City</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mexico</country>
      <state>Tlalpan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Thailand</country>
      <state>Bangkok</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Thailand</country>
      <state>Khon Kaen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Thailand</country>
      <state>Nonthaburi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Seasonal influenza is responsible for many hospitalizations and deaths each year, despite
      effective antiviral treatments. Some individuals have medical conditions such as heart or
      lung diseases that make them particularly at risk of severe influenza infections that may
      result in hospitalization or death. Oseltamivir (Tamiflu) is used most often to treat flu,
      but there are still many hospitalizations, complications, and deaths even with treatment.
      This study evaluated the use of combination antivirals (amantadine, oseltamivir, and
      ribavirin) compared to oseltamivir alone in the treatment of influenza in an at-risk
      population.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01227967</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Thompson WW, Shay DK, Weintraub E, Brammer L, Cox N, Anderson LJ, Fukuda K. Mortality associated with influenza and respiratory syncytial virus in the United States. JAMA. 2003 Jan 8;289(2):179-86.
Monto AS. Vaccines and antiviral drugs in pandemic preparedness. Emerg Infect Dis. 2006 Jan;12(1):55-60.
Moscona A. Oseltamivir resistance--disabling our influenza defenses. N Engl J Med. 2005 Dec 22;353(25):2633-6.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>John Beigel, MD</name>
      <address>Leidos Biomedical Research, Inc. in support of Clinical Research Section, LIR, NIAID, Natinal Institutes of Health</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>