<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4739">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/10/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/10/2012</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01706094</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Head Position in Stroke Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Head Position in Stroke Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>HeadPoST-Pilot</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>HeadPoST1</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Ischemic Stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - Head Position

Experimental: lying flat head position - positioning the head of the bed at zero degrees during the first 48 hours from admission of patients with acute ischemic stroke Active Comparator: upright position of the head of the bed during 48 hours from admission of patients with acute ischemic stroke


Other interventions: Head Position
Head position during the first 48 hours from admission of patients with acute ischemic stroke.
This trial is organized as a cluster randomised trial to a policy of flat head position or upright head position. Clusters will be months, so that all patients admitted during a given month will be positioned either in the flat down head position (intervention) or upright head position (control). This will allow health teams to follow a monthly protocol without changing position between patients.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Increased mean cerebral blood flow velocity (CBFV) in the lying flat compared to the upright head position - The main efficacy outcome of the pilot phase is demonstration of increased mean cerebral blood flow velocity (CBFV) in the lying flat head position compared to the upright head position, as assessed by transcranial Doppler (TCD) to the medial cerebral arteries of patients with anterior circulation infarction.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>proportion of Serious adverse events. - Assessments of Serious adverse events at 7 days comparing between the two head positioning groups.</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Age 18 or more years old

          -  Patients with an acute stroke corresponding to anterior circulation, a CT scan ruling
             out intracranial hemorrhage, presenting within 12 hours from symptom onset

          -  NIHSS =1

          -  Susceptible to be tilted down to the flat position or to 30ยบ of the head

          -  There is uncertainty about the benefit/harm of head position during a minimum of 24
             hours.

          -  Informed consent given</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Contraindications to a flat head position (active vomiting, pneumonia, uncontrolled
             heart failure)

          -  Concomitant medical illness that would interfere with outcome assessment and follow-up

          -  Planned decompressive craniectomy or carotid endarterectomy.

          -  Absence of sonographic temporal window</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/01/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>92</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/10/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Sydney</hospital>
    <postcode> - Sydney</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Chile</country>
      <state>Region de Magallanes</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Chile</country>
      <state>Region Metropolitana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Clinica Alemana de Santiago</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>The George Institute</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A simplest manner to augment cerebral blood flow to irrigate the ischemic penumbra in acute
      ischemic stroke could be to place the patient in a 'lying flat' rather than upright head
      position. Given uncertainty over the balance of potential modest benefits and risks, and
      variability regarding the ideal head position policy for patients with acute ischemic stroke
      around the world, reliable randomized evidence is required to standardize clinical practice.

      The main objectives of this pilot phase clinical trial are to determine the feasibility,
      safety and potential efficacy of a large-scale cluster randomized clinical trial to assess
      whether a simple nursing care policy - 'lying flat head position' - provides beneficial
      effects as compared to the standard upright head position in patients with acute ischemic
      stroke. The main efficacy outcome of the pilot phase is demonstration of increased mean
      cerebral blood flow velocity in the flat down compared to the upright head position, as
      assessed by transcranial Doppler to the medial cerebral arteries of patients with anterior
      circulation infarction. Secondary efficacy objectives are to demonstrate that the flat down
      head position improves neurological status at 7 days and disability at 90 days.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01706094</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Veronica V Olavarria, MD, Msc</name>
      <address>Clinica Alemana de Santiago, Chile.</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>