<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3380">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/11/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/11/2011</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01483053</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Cardiovascular Effects of Agomelatine and Escitalopram in Patients With Major Depressive Disorder (MDD)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomised Trial Investigating the Cardiovascular Effects of Agomelatine and Escitalopram in Patients With Major Depressive Disorder.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>498/11</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Major Depressive Disorder (MDD)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Agomelatine
Treatment: drugs - Escitalopram

Active Comparator: Agomelatine - Participants who are randomly assigned to the agomelatine group will be treated with agomelatine oral tablets for twelve weeks. Participants will begin their agomelatine treatment at 25mg/day dosage, increasing to 50mg/day as clinically indicated.

Active Comparator: Escitalopram - Participants who are randomly assigned to the escitalopram group will be treated with escitalopram oral tablets for twelve weeks. Participants will begin their escitalopram treatment at 10mg/day dosage, increasing to 20mg/day as clinically indicated.


Treatment: drugs: Agomelatine
Participants who are randomly assigned to the agomelatine group will be treated with agomelatine oral tablets for twelve weeks. Participants will begin their agomelatine treatment at 25mg/day dosage, increasing to 50mg/day as clinically indicated.

Treatment: drugs: Escitalopram
Participants who are randomly assigned to the escitalopram group will be treated with escitalopram oral tablets for twelve weeks. Participants will begin their escitalopram treatment at 10mg/day dosage, increasing to 20mg/day as clinically indicated.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in markers of sympathetic nervous system activity. - The investigators will measure sympathetic nervous system activity via whole body noradrenaline spillover and microneurography. Data will be used to examine the relationship between the degree of sympathetic nervous system activity and early signs of cardiac structure and function abnormalities, insulin resistance, and morning surge in blood pressure. This may help in identifying MDD patients who are at an increased risk.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and following 12 weeks of antidepressant treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in the magnitude of morning surge in blood pressure. - The investigators will explore the association between sympathetic nervous system activity and stress reactivity to the morning surge in blood pressure in patients with MDD. Blood pressure data will be used to test the hypothesis that MDD patients with high sympathetic activity have greater morning surges in blood pressure than patients with normal sympathetic activity.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and following 12 weeks of antidepressant treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the association between sympathetic nervous system activity and left ventricular hypertrophy. - The investigators will measure the relationship between sympathetic nervous system activity and left ventricular mass in patients with MDD. ECG, ECHO and blood pressure data will be used to test the hypothesis that MDD patients with elevated sympathetic activity display early signs of LVH and diastolic dysfunction.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in insulin resistance. - The investigators will explore the association between sympathetic nervous system activity and stress reactivity to signs of insulin resistance in patients with MDD. Oral glucose tolerance data will be used to test the hypothesis that MDD patients with elevated sympathetic activity display early signs of insulin resistance.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and following 12 weeks of antidepressant treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline on markers of cardiac risk. - The investigators will explore the association between agomelatine/escitalopram treatment and markers of cardiac risk. They will test the hypothesis that agomelatine/escitalopram treatment has a favourable effect on blood pressure variability and morning surge in blood pressure, sympathetic stress reactivity and markers of insulin resistance.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and following 12 weeks of antidepressant treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Aged 18-65 years.

          -  Capable of understanding and willing to provide signed and dated written, voluntary
             informed consent in advance of any protocol-specific procedures.

          -  MDD or MDD with melancholia according to the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of
             Mental Disorders (DSM-IV) criteria. Patients with comorbid panic or anxiety disorders
             will be included if MDD is the primary diagnosis.

          -  Hamilton Depression (HAM D) &gt; 18.

          -  Beck Depression Inventory (BDI-II) &gt;18.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Aged &lt; 18 or &gt; 65 years.

          -  Current antidepressant treatment.

          -  Previous failed response to SSRI treatment at the maximum tolerated dose for at least
             4 weeks.

          -  Known or suspected hypersensitivity to either escitalopram or agomelatine or any of
             their ingredients.

          -  Current high suicide risk.

          -  Comorbid panic or anxiety disorders as the primary diagnosis.

          -  Pre-existing and/or current diagnosed heart disease.

          -  Comorbid medical conditions including type 1 diabetes, hepatic impairment (cirrhosis
             or active liver disease), medicated hypertension, epilepsy, bleeding disorders,
             alcohol/drug dependence, infectious blood diseases, psychotic disorders, personality
             disorders, eating disorders, mental retardation, dementia (ie, Mini Mental State
             Examination [MMSE] &lt; 23), or gastrointestinal illness or previous bariatric (weight
             loss) surgery that may impair antidepressant absorption.

          -  Participants on betablockers (for example, metoprolol).

          -  Participants currently taking the following contraindicated medications for
             agomelatine and/or escitalopram:

               -  Cytochrome (CYP) P450 1A2 inhibitors (e.g. fluvoxamine, ciprofloxacin)

               -  Monoamine Oxidase Inhibitors;

                    -  Irreversible non-selective monoamine oxidase inhibitors (MAOIs)

                    -  Reversible, selective MAO-A inhibitor (e.g. moclobemide)

                    -  Reversible, non-selective MAOI (e.g. linezolid)

               -  Pimozide

        Participants who are eligible to take part in the study are prohibited to take the
        contraindicated medications listed above for the entire duration of the study.

          -  Clinically significant abnormalities on examination or laboratory testing and
             clinically significant medical conditions not listed above that are serious and/or
             unstable.

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding women.

          -  Women of childbearing potential (WOCP) who are not using medically accepted
             contraception (ie, intrauterine devices [IUDs], hormonal contraceptives [oral, depot,
             patch or injectable], and double barrier methods such as condoms or diaphragms with
             spermicidal gel or foam). Women who are postmenopausal (ie, amenorrhea for at least 12
             consecutive months) or surgically sterile are not considered to be WOCP.

          -  Sexually active men with WOCP partners who are not using medically accepted
             contraception.

        Medically accepted contraception for women and sexually active men with WOCP partners will
        be continued throughout the study and for 30 days after the last antidepressant dose.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/01/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Unknown status</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/02/2015</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Monash Health - Clayton</hospital>
    <hospital>Alfred and Baker Medical Unit - Alfred Hospital - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Baker IDI Heart &amp; Diabetes Institute - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Baker IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Servier Laboratories (Australia) Pty Ltd</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>The Alfred</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Monash Medical Centre</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There is strong evidence that patients with major depressive disorder (MDD) are at increased
      risk of developing coronary heart disease (CHD). This elevated risk is independent of
      classical risk factors such as smoking, obesity, hypercholesterolemia, diabetes and
      hypertension. The risk of CHD is increased 1½-2 fold in those with minor depression and 3-4½
      fold in subjects with MDD. Put simply, the relative risk of developing CHD is proportional to
      the severity of the depression. While the mechanism of increased cardiac risk attributable to
      MDD is not known disturbances in autonomic function most likely do play a part.

      In untreated patients with MDD (with no underlying CHD) the investigators have identified
      that a marked sympathetic nervous activation and diminished heart rate variability (HRV)
      occurs in a proportion (approximately one third) of patients. Diminished HRV has been linked
      to increased incidence rates of acute cardiac events in conditions such as hypertension,
      diabetes and myocardial infarction. Importantly, whether treating depression actually
      improves the risk of: (1) CHD development or (2) recurrence of cardiac events in patients
      with existing CHD remains unknown.

      The investigators, and others, have provided a growing body of evidence linking elevated
      sympathetic activity and exaggerated sympathetic responses to stress to early stages of end
      organ dysfunction and markers of disease development. Of particular note, in addition to
      possible effects on HRV is the association of chronic sympathetic nervous activation to: (a)
      abnormal blood pressure regulation and (b) the development of insulin resistance.

      The investigators therefore plan to examine the cardiovascular effects of two different
      antidepressant medications, agomelatine and escitalopram, in patients with MDD. In addition,
      the investigators plan to investigate the effects these two medications have on sympathetic
      nervous system activity, blood pressure, HRV, endothelial function, metabolic and
      psychological effects.

      Findings from this study will assist us to identify of biological correlates of sympathetic
      nervous activation which will enable us to: (1) identify those at potentially increased
      cardiac risk, and (2) potentially implement additional therapeutic strategies in order to
      reduce cardiac risk. Indeed, it is not known whether antidepressant treatment alone would be
      sufficient to reverse any adverse effects of sympathetic nervous activation. This study aims
      to answer this important clinical question.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01483053</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Gavin Lambert</name>
      <address>Baker IDI Heart &amp; Diabetes Institute</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sarah Tremethick</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+61 3 8532 1145</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sarah.tremethick@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>