<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3914">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/04/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/04/2013</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01847534</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Supplemental Parenteral Nutrition in Critically Ill Adults: A Pilot Randomised Controlled Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Supplemental Parenteral Nutrition in Critically Ill Adults: A Pilot Randomised Controlled Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>ANZIC RC AD 003</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Multiple Organ Failure</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Critical Illness</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - Supplemental PN
Other interventions - Standard Care

Other: Standard Care - Standard care: Nutrition will be managed as per best practice and local policy including the use of small bowel feeding tubes, prokinetics and PN if required to meet nutrition needs.

Experimental: Supplemental PN - Supplemental PN to complete inadequate EN provision
Patients allocated to the supplemental PN (intervention) group will have PN commenced within 2 hours of randomisation. The starting dose of PN will be determined by the amount of energy received in the 24 hours prior to randomisation.
EN will be managed as per local protocol however EN must not be reduced based on the supplemental PN being administered.
The adequacy of nutrition provision from both PN and EN will be assessed at midday each day for 7 days or until ICU discharge. The dose of PN will be adjusted according to a prespecified schedule.


Other interventions: Supplemental PN


Other interventions: Standard Care


</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total energy amount delivered - The primary outcome for this pilot study is the total energy amount delivered from nutrition therapy (ie. from Enteral Nutrition (EN) and from supplemental PN, if delivered) over the first 7 days of the study period.</outcome>
      <timepoint>First 7 days of the study period</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients in intensive care who meet all of the following:

          -  Admitted to intensive care between 48 hours and 72 hours previously

          -  Mechanically ventilated at the time of enrollment and expected to remain ventilated
             until the day after tomorrow

          -  At least 16 years of age

          -  Have central venous access suitable for PN solution administration

          -  Have 1 or more organ system failure (respiratory, cardiovascular or renal) related to
             their acute illness defined as:

               1. Partial pressure of oxygen (PaO2) / Fraction of Inspired oxygen (FiO2) ratio =
                  300 mmHg

               2. Currently on 1 or more continuous vasopressor infusion which were started at
                  least 4 hours ago at a minimum dose of :

                    1. Dopamine greater than 5 mcg/kg/min

                    2. Noradrenaline = 0.1mcg/kg/min

                    3. Adrenaline = 0.1 mcg/kg/min

                    4. Any dose of total vasopressin

                    5. Milrinone &gt;0.25mcg/kg/min)

               3. Renal dysfunction defined as

                  In patients without known renal disease:

                    1. serum creatinine &gt; 171 mmol/l OR

                    2. Currently receiving renal replacement therapy

                       In patients with known renal disease:

                    3. an absolute increase of &gt; 50% in creatinine from baseline OR

                    4. Currently receiving renal replacement therapy

               4. Currently has an intracranial pressure monitor or ventricular drain in situ

               5. Currently receiving extracorporeal membrane oxygenation

               6. Currently has a ventricular assist device</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Both EN and PN cannot be delivered at enrollment (i.e. either an enteral tube or a
             central venous catheter cannot be placed or clinicians feel that EN or PN cannot be
             safely administered due to any other reason).

          -  Currently receiving PN

          -  Standard PN solutions cannot be delivered at enrolment (i.e. clinicians believe that a
             patient definitely needs a specific parenteral nutrition formulation (e.g.
             glutamine-supplementation or specific lipid formulation).

          -  Death is imminent or deemed highly likely in the next 96 hours.

          -  There is a current treatment limitation in place or the patient is unlikely to survive
             to 6 months due to underlying illness

          -  More than 80% of energy requirements have been satisfactorily delivered via the
             enteral route in the last 24 hours.

          -  Are known to be pregnant</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Supportive Care</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/02/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>100</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/07/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Alfred Hospital - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Geelong Hospital - Geelong</hospital>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode> - Geelong</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Christchurch</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Wellington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australian and New Zealand Intensive Care Research Centre</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Baxter Healthcare Corporation</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>One of the essential treatments for assisting patients in their recovery from illness is the
      provision of nutrition in a liquid form which is delivered into the stomach or as a fluid
      into the vein. Until recently the benefits of nutrition were undervalued in the critically
      ill, however, it has now become clear that targeted nutrition can positively affect a
      person's outcome. This is particularly important for patients who are significantly unwell
      and require increased amounts of nutrition to support recovery. Inadequate nutrition therapy
      leads them to rapidly lose weight, predominantly in the form of muscle loss which greatly
      contributes to their poor recovery.

      Whilst nutrition is essential for recovery, there are several issues with the delivery of
      nutrition via the stomach (the most commonly used method of delivering nutrition in the
      critically ill). For many reasons, patients are unable to tolerate large quantities of
      nutrition via the stomach and in addition to this there are hospital or procedural reasons
      for nutrition being turned off for lengthy periods of time. As such, this results in patients
      being delivered only about half of the nutrition that is planned. One potential way to
      overcome this is to deliver nutrition via the vein, whilst nutrition into the stomach
      continues, with the aim to meet the energy gap that is lost by inadequate nutrition via the
      stomach.

      In this study of 100 patients, we will deliver combined nutrition via the vein and stomach in
      50 patients and the other 50 patients will receive nutrition as per normal practice. We will
      measure important outcomes for these patients to determine if this allows us to meet
      significantly more of their nutrition needs. This study will also help us determine how best
      to design a larger study of this strategy.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01847534</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>