<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2427">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/07/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/07/2009</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00938639</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Clinical Trial of CSL's 2009 H1N1 Influenza Vaccine (CSL425) in Healthy Adults</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase II, Single-centre, Randomised, Observer-blind Study to Evaluate the Immunogenicity, Safety and Tolerability of CSL's Monovalent H1N1 Influenza Virus Vaccine in Healthy Adults Aged 18 to &lt; 65 Years.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>CSLCT-CAL-09-59</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Influenza Caused by the Novel Influenza A (H1N1) Virus</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - CSL425
Other interventions - CSL425

Experimental: CSL425 (15 mcg) - 15 mcg of haemagglutinin antigen per dose. 0.25 mL intramuscular injection into the deltoid region of the arm on Day 0 and Day 21

Experimental: CSL425 (30 mcg) - 30 mcg of haemagglutinin antigen per dose. 0.5 mL intramuscular injection into the deltoid region of the arm on Day 0 and Day 21


Other interventions: CSL425
CSL's 2009 H1N1 Influenza Vaccine, thimerosal 0.01% (weight/volume)

Other interventions: CSL425
CSL's 2009 H1N1 Influenza Vaccine, thimerosal 0.01% (weight/volume)

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Haemagglutination Inhibition (HI) and Microneutralisation (MN) Antibody Titre Seroconversion Rate After the First Vaccination - Antibody titre seroconversion was defined as participants with a pre-vaccination titre of less than 1:10 achieving a post-vaccination antibody titre of 1:40 or more; or participants with a pre-vaccination titre of 1:10 or more achieving a four-fold or greater increase in post-vaccination HI titre.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and 21 days after the first vaccination</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>HI and MN Antibody Titre Seroconversion Rate After the Second Vaccination - Antibody titre seroconversion was defined as participants with a pre-vaccination titre of less than 1:10 achieving a post-vaccination antibody titre of 1:40 or more; or participants with a pre-vaccination titre of 1:10 or more achieving a four-fold or greater increase in post-vaccination HI titre.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and 21 days after the second vaccination</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Geometric Mean Fold Increase (GMFI) in the HI and MN Antibody Titre After the First Vaccination - GMFI in antibody titre was defined as the geometric mean of the fold increase in the post-vaccination antibody titre over the pre-vaccination antibody titre.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and 21 days after the first vaccination</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>GMFI in the HI and MN Antibody Titer After the Second Vaccination - GMFI in antibody titre was defined as the geometric mean of the fold increase in the post-vaccination antibody titre over the pre-vaccination antibody titre.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and 21 days after the second vaccination</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants Achieving a HI or MN Antibody Titre of 1:40 or More After the First Vaccination</outcome>
      <timepoint>21 days after the first vaccination</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants Achieving a HI or MN Antibody Titre of 1:40 or More After the Second Vaccination</outcome>
      <timepoint>21 days after the second vaccination</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>HI and MN Antibody Titre Seroconversion Rate After the First Vaccination by Age Group - Antibody titre seroconversion was defined as participants with a pre-vaccination titre of less than 1:10 achieving a post-vaccination antibody titre of 1:40 or more; or participants with a pre-vaccination titre of 1:10 or more achieving a four-fold or greater increase in post-vaccination HI titre.
Adults were aged from 18 to 49 years; Older adults were aged from 50 to 64 years.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and 21 days after the first vaccination</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>HI and MN Antibody Titre Seroconversion Rate After the Second Vaccination by Age Group - Antibody titre seroconversion was defined as participants with a pre-vaccination titre of less than 1:10 achieving a post-vaccination antibody titre of 1:40 or more; or participants with a pre-vaccination titre of 1:10 or more achieving a four-fold or greater increase in post-vaccination HI titre.
Adults were aged from 18 to 49 years; Older adults were aged from 50 to 64 years.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and 21 days after the second vaccination</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>GMFI in the HI and MN Antibody Titre After the First Vaccination by Age Group - GMFI in antibody titre was defined as the geometric mean of the fold increase in the post-vaccination antibody titre over the pre-vaccination antibody titre.
Adults were aged from 18 to 49 years; Older adults were aged from 50 to 64 years.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and 21 days after the first vaccination</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>GMFI in the HI and MN Antibody Titre After the Second Vaccination by Age Group - GMFI in antibody titre was defined as the geometric mean of the fold increase in the post-vaccination antibody titre over the pre-vaccination antibody titre.
Adults were aged from 18 to 49 years; Older adults were aged from 50 to 64 years.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and 21 days after the second vaccination</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants Achieving a HI or MN Antibody Titre of 1:40 or More After the First Vaccination by Age Group - Adults were aged from 18 to 49 years; Older adults were aged from 50 to 64 years.</outcome>
      <timepoint>21 days after the first vaccination</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants Achieving a HI or MN Antibody Titre of 1:40 or More After the Second Vaccination by Age Group - Adults were aged from 18 to 49 years; Older adults were aged from 50 to 64 years.</outcome>
      <timepoint>21 days after the second vaccination</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants With a Baseline Titre Less Than 1:10 Achieving Seroconversion After Vaccination - The number of participants with a baseline titre less than 1:10 differed according to antibody assay (HI or MN) and is shown in the category titles accordingly. The total number of participants analysed includes all evaluable participants; however, the analysis is stratified by baseline titre and those participants with a baseline titre less than 1:10 are presented in this outcome measure while those with a baseline titre of 1:10 or more are presented in a separate outcome measure.
Antibody titre seroconversion was defined as participants with a pre-vaccination titre of less than 1:10 achieving a post-vaccination titre of 1:40 or more; or participants with a pre-vaccination titre of 1:10 or more achieving a four-fold or greater increase in post-vaccination HI titre.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and 21 days after each vaccination</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants With a Baseline Titre Greater Than or Equal to 1:10 Achieving Seroconversion After Vaccination - The number of participants with a baseline titre greater than or equal to 1:10 differed according to antibody assay (HI or MN) and is shown in the category titles accordingly. The total number of participants analysed includes all evaluable participants; however, the analysis is stratified by baseline titre and those participants with a baseline titre of 1:10 or more are presented in this outcome measure while those with a baseline titre less than 1:10 are presented in a separate outcome measure.
Antibody titre seroconversion was defined as participants with a pre-vaccination titre of less than 1:10 achieving a post-vaccination titre of 1:40 or more; or participants with a pre-vaccination titre of 1:10 or more achieving a four-fold or greater increase in post-vaccination HI titre (ie, a significant increase in antibody titre after vaccination).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and 21 days after each vaccination</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>GMFI in the HI Antibody Titre 180 Days After the Second Vaccination - The GMFI in antibody titre was calculated by taking the anti-logs of the means of the log transformed fold-increases in the antibody titre 180 days after the second vaccination over the antibody titre 21 days after the second vaccination.</outcome>
      <timepoint>21 days and 180 days after the second vaccination</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants Achieving a HI Antibody Titre of 1:40 or More 180 Days After the Second Vaccination</outcome>
      <timepoint>180 days after the second vaccination</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Frequency and Intensity of Solicited Local Adverse Events (AEs) After the First Vaccination - Solicited AEs included AEs that were specifically sought for. Grade 3 solicited AE definitions: Prevented normal daily activities; Size &gt; 100 mm for injection site redness, induration/swelling, and bruising.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 0 to Day 6 after the first vaccination</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of Solicited Local AEs After the First Vaccination - Solicited AEs included AEs that were specifically sought for.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 0 to Day 6 after the first vaccination and up to Day 20 after the first vaccination if AE is ongoing at Day 7</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Frequency and Intensity of Solicited Local AEs After the Second Vaccination - Solicited AEs included AEs that were specifically sought for. Grade 3 solicited AE definitions: Prevented normal daily activities; Size &gt; 100 mm for injection site redness, induration/swelling, and bruising.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 0 to Day 6 after the second vaccination</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of Solicited Local AEs After the Second Vaccination - Solicited AEs included AEs that were specifically sought for.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 0 to Day 6 after the second vaccination and up to Day 20 after the second vaccination if AE is ongoing at Day 7</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Frequency and Intensity of Solicited Systemic AEs After the First Vaccination - Solicited AEs included AEs that were specifically sought for. Grade 3 solicited AE definitions: Prevented normal daily activities; Temperature 102.2째F (39.0째C) or more for fevers.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 0 to Day 6 after the first vaccination</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of Solicited Systemic AEs After the First Vaccination - Solicited AEs included AEs that were specifically sought for.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 0 to Day 6 after the first vaccination and up to Day 20 after the first vaccination if AE is ongoing at Day 7</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Frequency and Intensity of Solicited Systemic AEs After the Second Vaccination - Solicited AEs included AEs that were specifically sought for. Grade 3 solicited AE definitions: Prevented normal daily activities; Temperature 102.2째F (39.0째C) or more for fevers.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 0 to Day 6 after the second vaccination</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of Solicited Systemic AEs After the Second Vaccination - Solicited AEs included AEs that were specifically sought for.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 0 to Day 6 after the second vaccination and up to Day 20 after the second vaccination if AE is ongoing at Day 7</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of Serious Adverse Events (SAEs), Adverse Events of Special Interest (AESIs), and New Onset of Chronic Illnesses (NOCIs) - An AESI was defined as an AE for which the association with seasonal influenza vaccine was unclear. A NOCI was defined as the diagnosis of a new medical condition that was chronic in nature, including those potentially controllable by medication (eg, diabetes, asthma).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 180 days after the last vaccination</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Frequency and Intensity of Unsolicited AEs - Unsolicited AEs included AEs other than those specifically sought for.
The grading definitions were:
Mild (Grade 1): Symptoms were easily tolerated and did not interfere with daily activities.
Moderate (Grade 2): Enough discomfort to cause some interference with daily activities.
Severe (Grade 3): Incapacitating, with inability to work or do usual activities.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 0 to Day 20 after vaccination; up to 180 days after the last vaccination for SAEs, AESIs, and NOCIs</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Male or female aged &gt;= 18 to &lt; 65 years at the time of providing informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>64</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Known hypersensitivity to a previous dose of influenza virus vaccine or allergy to
             eggs, chicken protein, thiomersal, neomycin, polymyxin, or any components of the Study
             Vaccine.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2>The people administering the treatment/s</masking2>
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>240</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/03/2010</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Study Site - Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Seqirus</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of the study is to determine whether CSL425 is a safe and effective vaccine for
      eliciting an immune response to H1N1 influenza in healthy adults.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00938639</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Director, Vaccines Clinical Development</name>
      <address>Seqirus</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>