<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3961">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/03/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/03/2013</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01871727</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Trial of E7777 in Persistent and Recurrent Cutaneous T-Cell Lymphoma</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Clinical Study to Demonstrate Safety and Efficacy of E7777 in Persistent or Recurrent Cutaneous T-Cell Lymphoma</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>E7777-G000-302</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Persistent or Recurrent Cutaneous T-Cell Lymphoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lymphoma (non Hodgkin's lymphoma) - High grade lymphoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lymphoma (non Hodgkin's lymphoma) - Low grade lymphoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - E7777

Experimental: E7777 - 


Treatment: drugs: E7777
administered by intravenous (i.v.) infusion over 60 minutes (+/-10 minutes) on 5 consecutive days during every cycle of 21 days

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dose-limiting toxicities (DLTs) in the Lead-in Part of the Study</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cycle 1 (21 days)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD) in the Lead-in Part of the Study</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Objective Response Rate (ORR) in the Main Phase of Study</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 until disease progression/recurrence, or up to 30 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of Response (DOR)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 until disease progression/recurrence, or up to 12 months (Lead-in) and Day 1 until disease progression/recurrence, or up to 30 months (Main Phase)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Response (TTR)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 12 months (Lead-in) and up to 30 months (Main Phase )</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Objective Response Rate (ORR)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 until disease progression/recurrence, up to 12 months (Lead-in) and Day 1 until disease progression/recurrence, up to 30 months (by using Prince (2010) criteria in Main Phase)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants with Any Adverse Event and Any Serious Adverse Event (SAE)</outcome>
      <timepoint>From first dose of the study drug until 30 days after the last dose, or up to 30 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximum Drug Concentration (Cmax) - Blood samples will be collected at pre-dose; 30 minutes (min) after the start of the infusion; at the end of the infusion; and 30, 60, 90, 120, 180, 240, and 300 min postinfusion stop. Sparse samples will be collected at pre-dose, at the end of the infusion, and between 60 and 180 min postinfusion.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 of Cycles 1, 3, 5,and 8 (Lead-in) and Day 1 of Cycles 1, 3, 5, and 8 for the first 12 participants and Day 1 of Cycle 1 for all other participants (Main Phase)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Area Under the Curve from Time 0 to Time t (AUC[0-t]) - Blood samples will be collected at pre-dose; 30 minutes (min) after the start of the infusion; at the end of the infusion; and 30, 60, 90, 120, 180, 240, and 300 min postinfusion stop. Sparse samples will be collected at pre-dose, at the end of the infusion, and between 60 and 180 min postinfusion.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 of Cycles 1, 3, 5,and 8 (Lead-in) and Day 1 of Cycles 1, 3, 5, and 8 for the first 12 participants and Day 1 of Cycle 1 for all other participants (Main Phase)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Area Under the Curve from Time 0 to Time Infinity (AUC[0-inf]) - Blood samples will be collected at pre-dose; 30 minutes (min) after the start of the infusion; at the end of the infusion; and 30, 60, 90, 120, 180, 240, and 300 min postinfusion stop. Sparse samples will be collected at pre-dose, at the end of the infusion, and between 60 and 180 min postinfusion.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 of Cycles 1, 3, 5,and 8 (Lead-in) and Day 1 of Cycles 1, 3, 5, and 8 for the first 12 participants and Day 1 of Cycle 1 for all other participants (Main Phase)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Terminal Elimination Half-life (t1/2) - Blood samples will be collected at pre-dose; 30 minutes (min) after the start of the infusion; at the end of the infusion; and 30, 60, 90, 120, 180, 240, and 300 min postinfusion stop. Sparse samples will be collected at pre-dose, at the end of the infusion, and between 60 and 180 min postinfusion.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 of Cycles 1, 3, 5,and 8 (Lead-in) and Day 1 of Cycles 1, 3, 5, and 8 for the first 12 participants and Day 1 of Cycle 1 for all other participants (Main Phase)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants Testing Positive for Anti-E7777 and Anti-IL-2 Antibodies</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline; 10. Day 1 of Cycles 1, 2, 3, 5, and 8 (for Anti-E7777 and Anti-IL-2); Anti-IL-2 is to be tested at 6 month and thereafter every year until antibody levels decrease to baseline levels</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants must meet all of the following criteria to be included in the study:

          1. Age greater than or equal to 18 years.

          2. Histopathologic diagnosis of CTCL (mycosis fungoides [MF] or Sezary Syndrome [SS]),
             confirmed by skin biopsy, or lymph node, or blood assessment, of current disease.

          3. CD25 assay-positive tumor, defined as detectable CD25 on greater than or equal to 20%
             of total lymphoid infiltrate in biopsied skin lesions by immunohistochemistry.

          4. CTCL disease stage at study entry as follows, according to ISCL/EORTC (Olsen 2011).

               -  Lead-In Phase: Stage IA - IV, except participants with CNS involvement.

               -  Main Study: Stage IA - IVA2 including lymph node disease N2 and N3

          5. History of prior therapies for CTCL as follows: must have had prior therapy, any
             number of prior therapies allowed.

             Topical treatments (except topical chemotherapy) and steroids are not considered as
             prior therapies.

          6. A minimum washout period of 4 weeks after previous CTCL therapy is recommended before
             the first dose of E7777.

             Participants must have recovered from any adverse effects from any previous CTCL
             therapy to CTCAE Grade &lt;2 before starting study drug. A shorter washout may be allowed
             if participant is experiencing progressive disease despite ongoing treatment

          7. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0, 1, or 2 in the Lead-In
             Phase and performance status of 0 or 1 in the Main Study.

          8. Life expectancy greater than or equal to 3 months in the Lead-In Phase and greater
             than or equal to 12 months in the Main Study.

          9. Adequate bone marrow reserves as evidenced by:

               -  platelets greater than or equal to 100,000/mm3 (100 x 10^9/L)

               -  clinically stable hemoglobin greater than or equal to 9 g/dL (90 g/L) and
                  hematocrit greater than or equal to 27% without transfusion support

         10. Normal hepatic function as evidenced by:

               -  bilirubin and alkaline phosphatase less than or equal to 1 x the upper limit of
                  normal (ULN).

               -  aspartate aminotransferase (AST) less than or equal to 75 U/L and alanine
                  aminotransferase (ALT) less than or equal to 100 U/L.

               -  albumin greater than or equal to 3.0 g/dL (30 g/L).

         11. Adequate renal function as evidenced by serum creatinine less than or equal to 1.8
             mg/dL (158 umol/L) OR calculated creatinine clearance greater than or equal to 50
             mL/min (per the Cockcroft-Gault formula) with less than 2+ protein OR 24- hour urine
             creatinine clearance greater than or equal to 50 mL/minute with 24- hour urine protein
             less than 1g.

         12. Provide written informed consent prior to any study-specific screening procedures.

         13. Females may not be lactating or pregnant at Screening or Baseline

         14. All females will be considered to be of childbearing potential unless they are
             postmenopausal or have been sterilized surgically

         15. Male participants must have had a successful vasectomy (confirmed azoospermia) or they
             and their female partner must meet the criteria above</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion Criteria

        Participants who meet any of the following criteria will be excluded from the study:

          1. Prior denileukin diftitox therapy

          2. Use of topical steroids within 14 days of Day 1 of initial therapy is not allowed

          3. Active malignancy (except for CTCL, definitively treated basal or squamous cell
             carcinoma of the skin, and carcinoma in-situ of the cervix) within the past 24 months.

          4. Serious intercurrent illness

          5. Significant cardiac disease requiring ongoing treatment, including congestive heart
             failure (CHF), severe coronary artery disease (CAD), cardiomyopathy, uncontrolled
             cardiac arrhythmia, unstable angina pectoris, or myocardial infarction (MI)

          6. Significant pulmonary symptoms or disease

          7. History of uncontrolled seizure disorder or active central nervous system disease

          8. Major surgery within 2 weeks of study enrollment

          9. Significant or uncontrolled infections requiring specific anti-infective therapy

         10. Known human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection; known active hepatitis B or
             hepatitis C infection

         11. Females who are pregnant (positive urine test) or breastfeeding

         12. Any history of a medical condition or a concomitant medical condition that, in the
             opinion of the investigator, would compromise the participant's ability to safely
             complete the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>9/05/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>90</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/06/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital> - East Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode> - East Melbourne</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Connecticut</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Illinois</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Jersey</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Eisai Inc.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this trial is to assess the efficacy and safety of E7777 (improved purity
      ONTAK) in patients with persistent and recurrent cutaneous T-cell lymphoma. A lead-in
      dose-finding part will be used to determine the dose of E7777 that should be used to test
      efficacy and safety.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01871727</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Chean Eng Ooi</name>
      <address>Eisai Inc.</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Eisai Medical Information</name>
      <address />
      <phone>1-888-274-2378</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>esi_medinfo@eisai.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>