<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2766">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/04/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/04/2010</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01124071</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Korean Diet Efficacy Clinical Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A 13 Week Study to Examine the Effectiveness of the Korean Diet on Weight, Blood Pressure, Metabolic Parameters and Disease Control in an Australian Overweight and Obese Population.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>11-2009/12124</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Behaviour - Provision of 2 Korean meals per day 6 days per week
Behaviour - Western Diet

Active Comparator: Korean Diet - Provision of 2 Korean meals per day, 6 days per week

Active Comparator: Western Diet - Lifestyle counseling, dietary advice, grocery vouchers


Behaviour: Provision of 2 Korean meals per day 6 days per week
At each participant's baseline visit, participant's will have an individualised lifestyle session addressing dietary and exercise goals and techniques to achieve weight loss. Participants in the Korean diet group will pick up lunch and evening meals Monday-Friday. Raw ingredients and cooking instructions will also be provided on friday for saturday meal preparation. Ongoing lifestyle sessions will be performed weekly for participants.

Behaviour: Western Diet
At each participant's baseline visit, participant's will have an individualised lifestyle session addressing dietary and exercise goals and techniques to achieve weight loss. Participants in the Western diet group will be provided with a Western recipe cookbook and food vouchers (weekly) to purchase the necessary ingredients for the Western meal preparation. Ongoing lifestyle sessions will be performed weekly for participants.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1. To investigate the acceptability of a Korean diet in overweight and obese Australians. - This will be determined at baseline and 4 week timepoints throughout the study by participants completing a Food Acceptability Questionnaire (FAQ). The FAQ addresses 10 components of food acceptability along a 7-point Likeart scale. The FAQ is a recognised instrument for testing food acceptability.</outcome>
      <timepoint>13 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2. To examine the differences in weight loss between the Korean diet intervention and the Western diet intervention in overweight and obese Australians. - This will be determined by assessing differences at baseline and 12 weeks for weight, BMI and percent BMI change.</outcome>
      <timepoint>13 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate changes in a number of indicators of metabolic disease in both groups - including anthropometry, Blood Glucose Levels, insulin sensitivity, lipid profiles, liver function, hormone function and inflammatory markers.</outcome>
      <timepoint>13 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Residents of metropolitan Sydney

          -  Aged 18-65 years

          -  BMI 25-45kg/m2</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Diabetes treated with oral medications or insulin

          -  Unstable angina or recent onset of cardiovascular disease

          -  Serious hepatic or renal disease

          -  serum transaminases (ALT or AST) &gt; 2.5 times upper limit of normal

          -  serum creatinine &gt; 1.5 times upper limit of normal or urinary microalbumin &gt;40 mg/L or
             eGFR &lt; 60ml/min/1.73m²

          -  Alcohol or illicit drug abuse

          -  Pregnant, breastfeeding, or planning pregnancy during the study

          -  Serious gastrointestinal disease (inflammatory bowel disease, active peptic ulcer,
             recent helicobacter pylori treatment)

          -  Treatment for an eating disorder, weight loss medications and other drugs that affect
             body weight e.g. some anti-psychotics, anti-depressants, or corticosteroids

          -  Hypothyroidism defined by elevated thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH) and low free
             thyroxine (fT4), or current hyperthyroidism under treatment

          -  Participation in another weight loss clinical trial within past 3 months

          -  Individuals who have lost &gt;10% weight within past 3 months

          -  Vegetarian eating practices

          -  Inability to cook or lack of facilities for home cooking

          -  Inability to read and write English

          -  Subjects who frequently change smoking habits or who have stopped smoking within 6
             months prior to screening</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/01/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>70</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Unknown status</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/04/2011</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The University of Sydney - Sydney</hospital>
    <postcode>2006 - Sydney</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Inje University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Korea Agro-Fisheries Trade Corporation, Seoul, Korea</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Ministry for Food, Agriculture, Forestry and Fisheries, Korea</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To determine:

        1. the acceptability of a Korean diet to an Australian overweight and obese population

        2. which Korean recipes are easily prepared

        3. the effect of a Korean diet on weight, blood pressure, and metabolic complications of
           obesity in this population.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01124071</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ian D Caterson, AM, MBBS, BSc(Med), PhD, FRACP</name>
      <address>University of Sydney</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>