<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3276">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/08/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/08/2011</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01423552</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pharmacology of Immunosuppressants Following Heart Transplantation</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Correlation of Immunosuppressant Pharmacokinetics, Pharmacodynamics, Pharmacogenomics and Outcomes Following Heart Transplantation</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>RRK4220</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Heart Transplantation</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Post-heart transplant - All patients undergoing heart transplantation at the Queen Elizabeth Hosptial Birmingham in the last 12 months or in the next year.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Correlation of immunosuppressant drug levels in different compartments with evidence of rejection - We will compare the levels of the drugs in different compartments of the body (in the blood, within white blood cells and within the heart muscle itself) with how well the drugs are working ie. how well the heart is functioning and the level of rejection seen on routine heart biopsies. Drug levels will be measured at C0 (trough) and C2 (peak).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Multiple timepoints in first 12 months after transplantation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Correlation of individual patient genetic and other factors with levels of immunosuppressant drugs in different compartments - We will also compare these results with patient genetic and other factors (eg. age, kidney function, use of other drugs) to better understand how these factors affect the levels of the drugs in different compartments of the body. Drug levels will be measured at C0 (trough) and C2 (peak).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Multiple timepoints in first 12 months after transplantation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  All patients undergoing heart transplantation</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Decline participation

          -  Previous transplantation of another organ and already receiving chronic
             immunosuppressive therapy</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/11/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Unknown status</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Basil Hetzel Institute for Medical Research - Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode> - Adelaide</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>West Midlands</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Nigel E. Drury</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The ongoing success of transplantation is largely due to the development of drugs to stop the
      patient's body from rejecting the new organ. In addition to steroids, two main types of drug
      are used to suppress the immune system following heart transplantation: calcineurin
      inhibitors (Ciclosporin-A or Tacrolimus) and mycophenolate. However, different patients
      respond in different ways to these drugs, with the same dose leading to different levels of
      the drug in the blood. This varies due to genetic and other factors such as age, kidney
      function and the use of other drugs. Therefore, the levels of immunosuppressive drugs in the
      blood are routinely measured and the dose adjusted accordingly. However, some patients still
      experience episodes of rejection despite apparently acceptable levels. In this study, the
      investigators will measure levels of the drugs (in the blood, in a type of white blood cell
      called T-cells and in the heart muscle) and the effectiveness of the drugs on T-cells. The
      investigators will compare these levels with patient genetic factors and the amount of
      rejection measured on heart biopsies. This will enable us to better understand how the blood
      and tissue levels of these drugs change with genetic and other factors in order to optimise
      immunosuppressive therapy and further improve outcomes from heart transplantation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01423552</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Robert S Bonser, MD FRCS</name>
      <address>University Hospital Birmingham</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Nigel E Drury, MRCS</name>
      <address />
      <phone>01216272890</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nigel.drury@uhb.nhs.uk</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>