<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5492">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/01/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/01/2008</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00606333</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparison of the Conor Sirolimus-eluting Coronary Stent to the Taxus Liberte Paclitaxel-eluting Coronary Stent in the Treatment of Coronary Artery Lesions</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomized, Multi-Center, Single-Blind Comparison of the Conor Cobalt Chromium Reservoir Based Stent With Sirolimus Elution Versus the TAXUS Liberte Paclitaxel-eluting Coronary Stent System in De Novo Native Coronary Artery Lesions</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>NEVO RES-I</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>CP-06</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Coronary Atherosclerosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - NEVO Sirolimus-eluting Coronary Stent System
Treatment: devices - Drug-eluting stent (TAXUS Liberte Paclitaxel-eluting Coronary Stent System)

Experimental: Investigational arm - Subjects randomized to treatment with the NEVO Sirolimus-eluting Coronary Stent System.

Active Comparator: Control Arm - Subjects randomized to treatment with the TAXUS Liberte Paclitaxel-eluting Coronary Stent System.


Treatment: devices: NEVO Sirolimus-eluting Coronary Stent System
Intervention will consist of percutaneous coronary intervention for treatment of a single coronary lesion using standard coronary intervention techniques. Intervention in this arm will include treatment with the Conor Cobalt Chromium Sirolimus-eluting Coronary Stent System. Subjects assigned to the IVUS sub-study population will undergo intravascular ultrasound evaluation immediately post-stenting.

Treatment: devices: Drug-eluting stent (TAXUS Liberte Paclitaxel-eluting Coronary Stent System)
Intervention will consist of percutaneous coronary intervention for treatment of a single coronary lesion using standard coronary intervention techniques. Intervention in this arm will include treatment with the TAXUS Liberte Paclitaxel-eluting Coronary Stent System. Subjects assigned to the IVUS sub-study population will undergo intravascular ultrasound evaluation immediately post-stenting.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Angiographic endpoint of in-stent late lumen loss as measured by QCA.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Target Lesion Failure defined as cardiac death that cannot be clearly attributed to a non-cardiac event or non-target vessel, target vessel related myocardial infarction or clinically driven target lesion revascularization.</outcome>
      <timepoint>hospital discharge, 30 days, 6 months and annually through five years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Target Vessel Failure defined as any myocardial infarction or cardiac death that cannot be attributed to a non-target vessel or any target vessel revascularization.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Hospital discharge, 30 days, 6 months and annually through five years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Major Adverse Cardiac Events defined as an adjudicated composite of death, emergent coronary artery bypass graft surgery, target lesion revascularization, or new myocardial infarction.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Hospital discharge, 30 days, 6 months and annually through five years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of stent thrombosis</outcome>
      <timepoint>Hospital discharge, 30 days, 6 months and annually through five years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of target lesion revascularization and target vessel revascularization.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Hospital discharge, 30 days, 6 months and annually through five years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Device Success</outcome>
      <timepoint>Procedural</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lesion success</outcome>
      <timepoint>Procedural</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Procedure Success</outcome>
      <timepoint>Hospital Discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Angiographic in-stent and in-segment binary restenosis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In-stent minimum lumen diameter</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percent volume obstruction of the stent by intravascular ultrasound evaluation</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient reported outcomes as measured by three standardized quality of life surveys.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 30 days, 6 months and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  18 years of age or older

          -  Eligible for percutaneous coronary intervention and coronary artery bypass graft
             surgery.

          -  Diagnosis of stable or unstable angina or silent ischemia

          -  Left ventricular ejection fraction &gt;30%

          -  The subject requires treatment of a single de novo lesion in a native coronary artery.

          -  Lesion to be treated is less than or equal to 28 mm in length in a vessel that is
             2.5-3.5mm diameter.

          -  The target lesion diameter stenosis is &gt;50% and &lt;100% by visual estimate.

          -  The target lesion is a minimum of 10 mm distance from any previously treated segment
             of the target vessel.

          -  The subject understands the study requirements, is willing to comply with all study
             procedures and has provided written informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  The subject has undergone coronary revascularization to any vessel within 30 days.

          -  The subject has undergone target vessel revascularization within 6 months.

          -  Treatment of more than one qualifying lesion is required at the time of enrollment, or
             is planned within 30 days following enrollment.

          -  The subject has known sensitivity to sirolimus, paclitaxel, the polymeric matrices,
             stainless steel or cobalt chromium.

          -  There is planned treatment of the target lesion with any device other than the
             pre-dilatation balloon angioplasty catheter.

          -  The subject had a myocardial infarction within 72 hours, or presents with CK elevation
             &gt; 2 times upper limit normal associated with elevated CK-MB.

          -  The subject is in cardiogenic shock.

          -  The subject had a cerebrovascular accident within the past 6 months.

          -  The subject has acute or chronic renal dysfunction (defined as creatinine &gt;2.0 mg/dl).

          -  The subject has a contraindication to aspirin or clopidogrel.

          -  The subject has thrombocytopenia (platelet count &lt; 100,000/mm3.

          -  The subject has had active gastrointestinal bleeding within the past 3 months.

          -  The subject has a known bleeding or hypercoagulable disorder.

          -  The subject has had prior anaphylactoid reaction to contrast agents or has contrast
             sensitivity that cannot be controlled with pre-medication.

          -  The subject is currently taking immunosuppressant therapy.

          -  The subject is currently, or has been treated wtih either Rapamune or paclitaxel
             within 12 months of the procedure.

          -  The subject is a female with a positive pregnancy test or is lactating.

          -  The subject has an active infection.

          -  The subject has co-morbidities that could interfere wtih completion of study
             procedures, or life expectancy less than 24 months.

          -  The subject is participating in another investigational drug or device trial that has
             not completed the primary endpoint or would interfere with the endpoints of this
             study.

        Angiographic Exclusion Criteria

          -  Left main disease &gt;50% diameter stenosis.

          -  The target lesion is ostial.

          -  The target lesion or target vessel are severely calcified.

          -  The target lesion involves a bifurcation with diseased branch vessel greater than or
             equal to 2.0 mm that would require intervention or protection.

          -  The target lesion has TIMI o or TIMI I flow.

          -  Angiographic evidence of thrombus.

          -  The target vessel has had prior stent placement.

          -  The patient has had prior coronary brachytherapy.

          -  There is angiographic restenosis of any previously treated segment of the target
             vessel, or atherosclerotic area wtih &gt;50% diameter stenosis outside of the target
             lesion.

          -  The subject has undergone prior CABG.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/03/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>394</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Terminated</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/10/2012</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Sao Paulo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Cordis Corporation</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Conor Medsystems</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to evaluate the safety and effectiveness of the Conor
      Sirolimus-eluting Coronary Stent System in the treatment of coronary artery disease (a single
      atherosclerotic lesion) in native coronary arteries. The study will evaluate the outcomes of
      a new drug-eluting stent compared to an approved drug-eluting stent.

      While Cordis made a business decision to no longer pursue NEVO development and
      commercialization, the patients will be followed up as per protocol. This includes performing
      all protocol required follow-up visits and the collection and reporting of all safety
      information.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00606333</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>John Ormiston, MB ChM</name>
      <address>Mercy Angiography Unit</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>