<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4492">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/06/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/06/2014</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02167100</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Patient Retention in HIV Medical Care in a Primary Care Practice in Australia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Patient Retention in HIV Medical Care in a Primary Care Practice in Australia</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>RiC</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>HIV Retention in Care</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>Retention in Care Audit</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>HIV</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Retained in Care - Each patient who had at least 2 practice visits separated by =90 days in a year involving HIV laboratory monitoring until 31st of March 2014.

Lost to follow-up (LTFU) - Each patient who had at 2 practice visits separated by =90 days in a year involving HIV laboratory monitoring but did not maintain regular attendance at HHMP until 31st March, 2014.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome measures are the rates of current linkage and retention in care for HIV-infected adults at Holdsworth House Medical Practice (HHMP) over a 5-year period</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 5 years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A secondary outcome measure is to determine the factors associated with loss to follow up (LTFU) in the study population over a 5-year period</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 5 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Documented HIV-1 infection

          -  Attendance during the study period for at least 2 visits &gt;3 months and &lt;12 months
             apart with measured laboratory virological or immunological markers (either on-site or
             at a co-management site)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Attendance by patient with HIV infection who does not have laboratory markers of HIV
             viral load or CD4 count measured

          -  Incomplete/inaccessible patient records to enable patient to meet inclusion criteria

          -  Initial visit after 1st January 2014</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing>Retrospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/06/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>1537</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/09/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Holdsworth House Medical Practice - Darlinghurst</hospital>
    <postcode>2010 - Darlinghurst</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Holdsworth House Medical Practice</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Gilead Sciences</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to determine linkage and retention in care in patients with HIV
      infection and reasons for loss to follow up Care in a High HIV-caseload Inner City Primary
      Care Practice in Sydney, Australia.

      The investigators hypothesise that patients attending HHMP will have higher rates of linkage
      and retention in care than the US HIV-infected population, and equivalent to Australian
      modelling.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02167100</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Hall HI, Halverson J, Wilson DP, Suligoi B, Diez M, Le Vu S, Tang T, McDonald A, Camoni L, Semaille C, Archibald C. Late diagnosis and entry to care after diagnosis of human immunodeficiency virus infection: a country comparison. PLoS One. 2013 Nov 5;8(11):e77763. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0077763. eCollection 2013.
Gardner EM, McLees MP, Steiner JF, Del Rio C, Burman WJ. The spectrum of engagement in HIV care and its relevance to test-and-treat strategies for prevention of HIV infection. Clin Infect Dis. 2011 Mar 15;52(6):793-800. doi: 10.1093/cid/ciq243. Review.
Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). Vital signs: HIV prevention through care and treatment--United States. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2011 Dec 2;60(47):1618-23.
Mugavero MJ, Lin HY, Willig JH, Westfall AO, Ulett KB, Routman JS, Abroms S, Raper JL, Saag MS, Allison JJ. Missed visits and mortality among patients establishing initial outpatient HIV treatment. Clin Infect Dis. 2009 Jan 15;48(2):248-56. doi: 10.1086/595705.
Das M, Chu PL, Santos GM, Scheer S, Vittinghoff E, McFarland W, Colfax GN. Decreases in community viral load are accompanied by reductions in new HIV infections in San Francisco. PLoS One. 2010 Jun 10;5(6):e11068. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0011068.
Fang CT, Hsu HM, Twu SJ, Chen MY, Chang YY, Hwang JS, Wang JD, Chuang CY; Division of AIDS and STD, Center for Disease Control, Department of Health, Executive Yuan. Decreased HIV transmission after a policy of providing free access to highly active antiretroviral therapy in Taiwan. J Infect Dis. 2004 Sep 1;190(5):879-85. Epub 2004 Jul 22.
Giordano TP, Visnegarwala F, White AC Jr, Troisi CL, Frankowski RF, Hartman CM, Grimes RM. Patients referred to an urban HIV clinic frequently fail to establish care: factors predicting failure. AIDS Care. 2005 Aug;17(6):773-83.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mark T Bloch, MBBS</name>
      <address>Holdsworth House Medical Practice</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>