<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3150">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/04/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/04/2011</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01345630</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparative Trial Of Maraviroc Versus Emtricitabine/Tenofovir Both With Darunavir/Ritonavir In Antiretroviral-Naive Patients Infected With CCR5 Tropic HIV 1</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Multicenter, Randomized, Double-Blind, Comparative Trial Of Maraviroc + Darunavir/Ritonavir Versus Emtricitabine/Tenofovir + Darunavir/Ritonavir For The Treatment Of Antiretroviral-Naive Hiv-Infected Patients With Ccr5-Tropic Hiv-1</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>MODERN</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>2010-021785-30</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>A4001095</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>HIV-1</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Maraviroc
Treatment: drugs - Emtricitabine/tenofovir
Treatment: drugs - darunavir/ritonavir 800/100 mg
Treatment: drugs - placebo for emtricitabine/tenofovir
Treatment: drugs - placebo for maraviroc

Experimental: Maraviroc - Maraviroc 150 mg once daily plus darunavir/ritonavir 800/100 mg once daily plus placebo for emtricitabine/tenofovir once daily.

Active Comparator: Emtricitabine/tenofovir - Emtricitabine/tenofovir 200/300 mg once daily plus darunavir/ritonavir 800/100 mg once daily plus placebo for maraviroc once daily.


Treatment: drugs: Maraviroc
Maraviroc tablet 150 mg once daily for 96 weeks.

Treatment: drugs: Emtricitabine/tenofovir
Emtricitabine/tenofovir tablet 200/300 mg once daily for 96 weeks.

Treatment: drugs: darunavir/ritonavir 800/100 mg
darunavir/ritonavir 800/100 mg

Treatment: drugs: placebo for emtricitabine/tenofovir
placebo for emtricitabine/tenofovir

Treatment: drugs: placebo for maraviroc
placebo for maraviroc

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants With Plasma HIV-1 RNA &lt;50 Copies/mL. - The proportion of participants who achieved HIV-1 RNA &lt;50 copies/mL at week 48 was assessed according to Food and Drug Administration's (FDA's) Missing, Switch, Discontinuation'=Failure (MSDF) Snapshot algorithm. The algorithm used the plasma HIV-1 RNA in the Week 48 visit window, followed the "virology-first principle" and considers a participant who has a missing plasma HIV-1 RNA, or switches to prohibited ARV regimen or discontinues from the study or study drug for any reason, or dies, as a failure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 48</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Frequency of Adverse Events (AE). - Number of participants with treatment-emergent non serious AEs</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 96</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With Grade 3 or 4 AEs - Number of participants with grade 3 or 4 AEs are presented here.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 96</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants Who Discontinued Due to AEs - Number of participants who discontinued due to AEs are reported here. Three participants (two from the MVC+DRV/r arm and one from the FTC/TDF+DRV/r arm) were not considered as discontinued due to AE because other reasons for discontinuation were prioritized for these participants.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 96</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Treatment-related AEs - Number of treatment-related AEs are presented here.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 96</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With Treatment-emergent Serious Adverse Events - Total number of participants with treatment-emergent serious adverse events are reported</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 96</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With Abnormal Laboratory Values - Number of participants with laboratory abnormalities are reported</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 96</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severity of Abnormal Laboratory Values - Number of participants who had clinically significant laboratory abnormalities of Grade 3 and Grade 4 according to DAIDS. Abnormality incidence of highest grade was reported for a labcode for each individual participant.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 96</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Relationship Between the Proportion of Participants With Plasma HIV-1 RNA &lt;50 Copies/mL at the Week 48 and the Screening Tropism Test (Genotype Test or ESTA). - The relationship of the proportion of participants achieving HIV-1 RNA &lt;50 copies/mL at Week 48 with the screening tropism test for the MVC containing regimen was analyzed. Virologic response for a participant at Week 48 was derived using the FDA's Snapshot MSDF algorithm. Difference in proportions of patients with plasma HIV-1 RNA &lt;50 copies/mL at week 48 between the maraviroc and the emtricitabine/tenofovir treatment arms, with two-sided 95% confidence interval, among patients who are R5 by genotype (including some who were originally randomized to ESTA and are R5 by genotype upon retesting), were calculated via the Maximum Likelihood method. The estimate was adjusted for the screening plasma HIV RNA level (&lt;100,000 vs. =100,000) copies/mL via the Mantel Haenszel (MH) method.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Virologic Outcomes at Week 48 Using Protocol-Defined Treatment Failure (PDTF). - Per the protocol participants who meet the following criteria were regarded as PDTFs requiring a confirmatory plasma HIV-1 RNA determination:  Decrease in plasma HIV-1 RNA &lt;1 log10 from baseline after Week 4 unless plasma HIV-1 RNA is &lt;50 copies/mL, or  Plasma HIV-1 RNA &gt;1.0 log10 above the nadir value after Week 4 where the nadir is the lowest plasma HIV-1 RNA concentration, or  Plasma HIV-1 RNA =50 copies/mL at any time after Week 24, or  Plasma HIV-1 RNA =50 copies/mL after suppression to &lt;50 copies/mL on two consecutive visits, or  Decrease in plasma HIV-1 RNA =2 log10 from baseline on or after Week 12 unless plasma HIV-1 RNA is &lt;400 copies/mL. Decrease in plasma HIV-1 RNA =2 log10 from baseline on or after Week 12 unless plasma HIV-1 RNA is &lt;50 copies/mL (before August 30 2012) or &lt;400 copies/mL (after August 30 2012).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tropism Change Between Screening or Baseline and PDTF - For participants meeting the PDTF criteria, tropism was assessed using the original randomized and alternate assays (ie, both genotype testing and ESTA). Data reported here corresponds to the timepoint at or after PDTF.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With Viral Resistance to Maraviroc (Maraviroc Treated Participants Only) in Participants Meeting PDTF Criteria. - For participants meeting the PDTF criteria, viral resistance to maraviroc for maraviroc treated participants was assessed in patients with R5 virus at failure. The resistance level is calculated by reference to a laboratory strain of virus that is analyzed in parallel with the clinical isolate to identify 50% inhibitory concentrations (IC50). The maximal percent inhibition is the percent inhibition that is achieved in a titration of the drug at high concentrations when the addition of more drug does not result in increased inhibition. Maximal percent inhibition is obtained in the same way as the titration for IC50, but the key measure is of the plateau height of percent inhibition, where increased concentration of maraviroc does not result in additional inhibition. This is consistent with the virus developing some ability to use maraviroc-bound CCR5 for entry. A significant change in IC50 is not required for this mechanism.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With Resistance to Nucleoside/Nucleotide Reverse Transcriptase Inhibitors (NRTI), Non-nucleoside Reverse Transcriptase Inhibitors (NNRTI), and Protease Inhibitors (PI) in Participants Meeting PDTF Criteria - For participants meeting the PDTF criteria, viral resistance (both genotypic and phenotypic) to NRTI, NNRTI, and PI's were assessed at Baseline and on-treatment. The assessment was performed using the overall (i.e. net) susceptibility score provided using the PhenoSense GT assay. The number of participants with successful assessments were 15/17 for the MVC+DRV/r arm and 3/3 for the FTC/TDF+DRV/r arm.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Absolute Change From Baseline in Immune Cell Function at Week 48: Lymphocyte Marker Cluster of Differentiation 4 (CD4, Cell/mm^3) - The differences in the magnitude of changes in CD4+ at Baseline and at Week 48 for maraviroc versus emtricitabine/tenofovir were compared.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percent Change From Baseline in Immune Cell Function at Week 48: Lymphocyte Activation Marker CD4 (%) - The differences in the magnitude of changes in CD4+ from Baseline through Week 48 for maraviroc versus emtricitabine/tenofovir were compared.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Absolute Change From Baseline in Immune Cell Function at Week 48: Lymphocyte Marker Cluster of Differentiation 8 (CD8, Cell/mm^3) - The differences in the magnitude of changes in CD8+ cell counts from baseline through Week 48 for maraviroc versus emtricitabine/tenofovir were compared.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percent Change From Baseline in Immune Cell Function at Week 48: Lymphocyte Activation Marker CD8 (%) - The differences in the magnitude of changes in CD8+ cell counts from Baseline through Week 48 for maraviroc versus emtricitabine/tenofovir were compared.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Absolute Change in CD4+/CD8+ Ratio From Baseline to Week 48 - The differences in the magnitude of changes in CD4+/CD8+ ratio from Baseline through Weeks 48 for maraviroc versus emtricitabine/tenofovir were compared.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in Peripheral Fat Distribution Using Dual Energy X-ray Absorptiometry [DEXA] Scan From Baseline and at Week 48. - A sub-study was conducted in which the participants underwent whole-body DEXA scans to evaluate peripheral fat tissue estimates for left and right arms and legs and truncal fat mass and truncal lean mass. Truncal abdominal fat were estimated from the DEXA scan field set on the torso. The effects on estimates of fat mass and lean mass were addressed by providing LSMs of change from baseline.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in Trunk to Limb Fat Distribution Using DEXA Scan From Baseline and at Week 48 - A sub-study was conducted in which the participants underwent whole-body DEXA scans to evaluate peripheral fat tissue estimates for left and right arms and legs and truncal fat mass and truncal lean mass. Truncal abdominal fat were estimated from the DEXA scan field set on the torso. The effects on estimates of fat mass and lean mass were addressed by providing LSMs of change from baseline.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in Bone Mineral Density (Using DEXA Scan and Serum Markers) From Baseline and at Week 48 - Total Hip BMD - Bone mineral density was evaluated by DEXA scan in a subset of participants who consented to these evaluations. The effects on BMD were addressed by providing LSMs of change from baseline bone mineral density of the lumbar spine (L1-L4), left total hip and femoral neck as measured by the DEXA scan.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in Bone Mineral Density (Using DEXA Scan and Serum Markers) From Baseline and at Week 48 - Femoral Neck BMD - Bone mineral density was evaluated by DEXA scan in a subset of participants who consented to these evaluations. The effects on BMD were addressed by providing LSMs of change from Baseline bone mineral density femoral neck as measured by the DEXA scan.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in Bone Mineral Density (Using DEXA Scan and Serum Markers) From Baseline and at Week 48 - AP Lumbar Spine (L1 - L4) BMD - Bone mineral density was evaluated by DEXA scan in a subset of participants who consented to these evaluations. The effects on BMD were addressed by providing LSMs of change from baseline bone mineral density of the lumbar spine (L1-L4) as measured by the DEXA scan.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Bone Turnover Markers From Baseline and at Week 48 - Blood Osteocalcin - Bone turnover marker, osteocalcin, was collected in the subset of participants participating in the DEXA scan sub-study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Bone Turnover Markers From Baseline and at Week 48 - Type 1 Collagen Peptide (CTX-1) - Bone turnover marker, C-telopeptide of type 1 collagen (CTx), was collected in the subset of participants participating in the DEXA scan sub-study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Plasma HIV-1 RNA equal to or greater than 1,000 copies/mL measured at the Screening
             Visit.

          -  CD4 count equal to or greater than 100 cells/mm3 at Screening.

          -  Have only R5 HIV 1 at Screening as verified by a randomized tropism assay.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Prior treatment with any other HIV antiretroviral therapy for more than 14 days at any
             time.

          -  Any evidence of genotypic/phenotypic resistance to darunavir, tenofovir, and
             emtricitabine.

          -  CXCR4 using virus detected using randomized tropism determination or repeated failure
             to obtain an interpretable tropism result.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/09/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>813</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Terminated</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/01/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>East Sydney Doctors - Darlinghurst</hospital>
    <hospital>Holdsworth House General Practice - Darlinghurst</hospital>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital - Darlinghurst</hospital>
    <hospital>Taylor Square Private Clinic - Surry Hills</hospital>
    <hospital>Brisbane Sexual Health and HIV Service - Brisbane</hospital>
    <hospital>Melbourne Sexual Health Centre - Carlton</hospital>
    <hospital>Clinical Research Unit, Infectious Diseases - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>2010 - Darlinghurst</postcode>
    <postcode>2010 - Surry Hills</postcode>
    <postcode>4000 - Brisbane</postcode>
    <postcode>3053 - Carlton</postcode>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Alabama</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Colorado</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Connecticut</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>District of Columbia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Georgia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Illinois</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Iowa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Louisiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Massachusetts</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Michigan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Minnesota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Missouri</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Nebraska</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Jersey</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Washington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Austria</country>
      <state>Wien</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Antwerpen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Brussels</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Bruxelles</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Gent</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Liege</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>British Columbia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Quebec</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Denmark</country>
      <state>Hvidovre</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Denmark</country>
      <state>Koebenhavn OE</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Denmark</country>
      <state>Odense</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Finland</country>
      <state>Helsinki</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Cedex 02</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Cedex 12</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Cedex 18</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Bordeaux cedex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Creteil</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Le Kremlin Bicetre</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>LYON Cedex 4</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Montpellier</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Nantes</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Paris Cedex 10</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Paris</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Strasbourg Cedex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Tourcoing</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Berlin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Bonn</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Frankfurt am Main</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Hamburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Koeln</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Muenchen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Budapest</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Milano</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Utrecht</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Bydgoszcz</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Warszawa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Wroclaw</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <state>Amadora</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <state>Lisboa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <state>Porto</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Puerto Rico</country>
      <state>Bayamon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Puerto Rico</country>
      <state>Ponce</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Puerto Rico</country>
      <state>Rio Piedras</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Puerto Rico</country>
      <state>San Juan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Alicante</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Cordoba</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Sevilla</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Goteborg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Malmo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Stockholm</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state>Basel</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state>Bern</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state>St. Gallen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state>Zurich</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Birmingham</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Brighton</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Edinburgh</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Manchester</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>ViiV Healthcare</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Pfizer</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to assess whether maraviroc administered once daily is
      non-inferior to emtricitabine/tenofovir also administered once daily each in combination with
      darunavir/ritonavir in the treatment of antiretroviral-naive patients as evaluated at Week 48
      of treatment.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01345630</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Pfizer CT.gov Call Center</name>
      <address>Pfizer</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>