<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5887">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/03/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/03/2015</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02389036</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Selective Decontamination of the Digestive Tract in Intensive Care Unit Patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Crossover, Cluster Randomised Controlled Trial of Selective Decontamination of the Digestive Tract in Intensive Care Unit Patients in Australian and New Zealand (SuDDICU-ANZ)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>SuDDICU-ANZ</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>GI-CCT070115</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Critical Illness</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Sepsis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Septic Shock</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Ventilator Associated Pneumonia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other inflammatory or immune system disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - SDD Paste
Treatment: drugs - SDD Suspension
Treatment: drugs - Intravenous Antibiotic

No Intervention: Control group- standard care - Standard care- In Australia and New Zealand there are no national guidelines so local policy is determined by each ICU. We are recommending (but not mandating) that control and SDD group management be in line with these national guidelines. We will recommend control and SDD group management is in line with current national standards of practice that may or may not include a VAP bundle. We will monitor record data regarding the nature and delivery of the control and SDD group co-interventions.

Experimental: SDD intervention group - The intervention will entail:
SDD paste: The six-hourly topical application of 0.5g paste, containing colistin 2%, tobramycin 2% and nystatin 2%, to the buccal mucosa and oropharynx.
SDD suspension: The six-hourly administration of 10 mls suspension containing 100 mg colistin/ polymixin, 80 mg tobramycin and 2 x 106 IU nystatin, to the gastrointestinal tract via the gastric / jejunal tube.
A four-day course of an intravenous antibiotic in patients not already receiving a therapeutic antibiotic


Treatment: drugs: SDD Paste
A six-hourly topical application of 0.5g paste, containing colistin 2%, tobramycin 2% and nystatin 2%,

Treatment: drugs: SDD Suspension
A six-hourly administration of 10 ml of a suspension containing 100 mg colistin, 80 mg tobramycin and 2 x 106 IU nystatin, to the gastrointestinal tract via a gastric/post-pyloric tube

Treatment: drugs: Intravenous Antibiotic
A four-day course of an intravenous antibiotic in patients not already receiving a therapeutic antibiotic

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospital Mortality - all-cause mortality at time of hospital discharge</outcome>
      <timepoint>Hospital discharge [up to 6 months after randomization</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total antibiotic usage - Total antibiotic usage (as daily defined doses) during ICU admission in all ICU admissions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>during ICU admission</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The incidence of antibiotic resistant organisms in cultures from blood or other sterile sites - The incidence of antibiotic resistant organisms in cultures from blood or other sterile sites during ICU admission in all ICU admissions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>during ICU admission</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The incidence of antibiotic-resistant organism in non-sterile clinical and surveillance specimens - The incidence of antibiotic-resistant organism in non-sterile clinical and surveillance specimens during ICU admission in all ICU admissions</outcome>
      <timepoint>during ICU admission</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The incidence of C. difficile infections - The incidence of C. difficile infections during ICU admission in all ICU admissions</outcome>
      <timepoint>during ICU admission</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in antibiotic resistance rates between study epochs (pre-trial, interperiod gap and post-trial) within groups - Changes in ARO rates between time epochs (pre-trial, trial, inter-period gap and post-trial) within groups. With control group data to give the secular trend in ARO with time and SDD group data studying the effects of SDD withdrawal from practice in the year after SDD delivery</outcome>
      <timepoint>Through out all study periods</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of mechanical ventilation - Duration that the patient is mechanically ventilated in the ICU</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of enrolment to ICU discharge within index hospital admission, assessed up to 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>ICU length of stay - The length of time a patient stays in the ICU</outcome>
      <timepoint>From the time of enrolment to ICU discharge, assessed up to 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospital length of stay - The total hospital length of stay for patient</outcome>
      <timepoint>From time of enrolment to hospital discharge within the index hospital admission, assessed up to 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Site inclusion for cluster study- A general ICU or complex of ICUs (medical, surgical,
        mixed) capable of treating mechanically ventilated critically ill adult patients.

        Patient inclusion criteria

          1. All patients who are mechanically ventilated via an endotracheal tube on admission to
             ICU and who are predicted to remain ventilated beyond the end of the calendar day
             after the day of ICU admission, or

          2. All patients who become mechanically ventilated via an endotracheal tube during their
             ICU stay and who are predicted to remain ventilated beyond the end of the calendar day
             after the day they are first ventilated, or

          3. All patients not already recruited who are receiving mechanical ventilation via an
             endotracheal tube and are expected to receive ongoing ventilation for a further 48
             hours or more despite an earlier prediction that ventilation would be discontinued
             earlier.

        Site exclusion criteria for cluster study-

          1. Unwilling or unable to follow trial protocols.

          2. Unable to capture the minimum data set required for the study.

          3. Isolated specialty ICUs not co-located with a general ICU, such as solely cardiac,
             neurological/neurosurgical and burns ICUs, but such specialty patients cared for in
             general ICUs will be included

          4. Specialty paediatric ICUs</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patient exclusion criteria

          1. Patients enrolled in a trial that would interact with the intervention

          2. Patients with a known allergy, sensitivity or interaction to trial topical
             intervention drugs

          3. Patients who are known or suspected to be pregnant

          4. Patients who are moribund and not expected to survive the next 12 hours

          5. Patients less than 16 years of age will not be enrolled in New Zealand</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/05/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>8000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/10/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The George Institute for Global Health - Sydney</hospital>
    <postcode>2000 - Sydney</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The George Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Introduction- Hospital acquired infections (HAI) are a major cause of morbidity and mortality
      and increase health care costs. Critically ill patients are particularly susceptible to these
      infections and have an even higher mortality. One intervention that has gained much interest
      in the medical literature for reducing infection rates and deaths from HAIs is selective
      decontamination of the digestive tract (SDD). SDD involves the application of antibiotic
      paste to the mouth, throat, stomach and a short course of intravenous antibiotics. The
      evidence supporting the use of SDD for saving lives and preventing infections is actually
      quite strong. However, health care professionals in many parts of the world have refrained
      from using SDD due to fears of the effects of overuse of antibiotics on the frequency of
      infections with resistant bacteria such as multi-resistant Gram negative organisms, MRSA and
      Clostridium difficile.

      SuDDICU-ANZ is a cross-over, cluster randomised trial comparing the effect of using selective
      decontamination of the digestive tract (SDD) plus standard care, to standard care alone on
      hospital mortality in patients receiving mechanical ventilation in the intensive care unit
      (ICU).

      Secondary outcomes include an ecological assessment and a long-term health economic analysis.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02389036</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>John Myburgh, MBBCh PhD</name>
      <address>The George Institute</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>John Myburgh, MBBCh PhD</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+61 2 8052 4348</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jmyburgh@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>