<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="1188">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/06/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/06/2006</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00334191</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Sodium Bicarbonate in Cardiac Surgery</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomised, Double Blind, Placebo Controlled Pilot Study of the Effect of Sodium Bicarbonate on Postoperative Renal Function and Oxidative Stress in Patients Undergoing Elective Cardiopulmonary Bypass.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>H2005/02249</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cardiac Surgery and Cardiopulmonary Bypass</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Sodium Bicarbonate
Treatment: drugs - Placebo

Treatment: drugs: Sodium Bicarbonate


Treatment: drugs: Placebo


</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients developing an increase in serum creatinine greater than 25% from baseline to peak level within first five postoperative days.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients developing an increase in serum creatinine greater than 50% from baseline to peak level within first five postoperative days.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relative change in serum creatinine,</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Urinary output,</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Use of renal replacement therapy (RRT),</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acute renal dysfunction,</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of ventilation,</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Chest tube drainage,</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Need for return to operating room,</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of post-operative atrial fibrillation (AF),</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of stay in the intensive care unit (ICU)</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of stay in hospital</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Age above 70 years

          -  Preexisting renal impairment (preoperative serum creatinine level &gt;120µmol/L

          -  New York Heart Association class III/IV or Moderate to poor left ventricular
             dysfunction

          -  Valve surgery or complex cardiac surgery

          -  Redo cardiac surgery

          -  Insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Age &lt;18 years

          -  Emergency cardiac surgery

          -  Planned off-pump cardiac surgery

          -  Enrolled in conflicting research study

          -  Known blood-borne infectious disease

          -  Chronic inflammatory disease on immunosuppression

          -  Chronic moderate to high dose corticosteroid therapy (&gt;10mg/d prednisone or
             equivalent)

          -  End stage renal disease (serum creatinine &gt;300µmol/L)

          -  Thiamine deficiency will be excluded on medical and dietary history.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/06/2006</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Austin Hospital - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3084 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Austin Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Many patients develop kidney failure after cardiac surgery. Although this kidney failure can
      usually be treated effectively, a longer stay in intensive care is often required. While many
      patients suffer no long term ill effects after developing post-operative kidney failure, some
      require long term kidney dialysis. We also know that patients who develop post-operative
      kidney failure are much more likely to die before they leave hospital.

      Why some people develop kidney failure after cardiac surgery is not known. However, doctors
      suspect that the process of cardiopulmonary bypass (where the functions of the heart and
      lungs are taken over by a machine during the operation, to allow the surgeon to operate)
      overactivates some of the same mechanisms the body uses to defend itself against severe
      infection.

      Many of the cell changes by which severe infection causes kidney failure also occur after
      cardiopulmonary bypass. One of the main overactive defence mechanisms is the release of
      highly toxic compounds derived from oxygen - a process called 'oxidative stress'.

      The investigators believe that sodium bicarbonate might reduce the oxidative stress, which
      occurs during cardiac surgery, and so prevent or decrease the kidney failure, which occurs in
      many patients.

      The investigators hope to give sodium bicarbonate (in similar doses to those used safely for
      treatment of acidosis) to patients during, and for 24 hours after cardiac surgery, and to
      compare the effects with patients who have not had sodium bicarbonate. The drug, or a
      placebo, will be given through the drip, which is present in all cardiac surgery patients.
      Whether a particular patient receives the drug or placebo will be decided at random, and
      neither the patient nor the investigators will know which has been given. We will measure
      kidney function before and after the operation using the standard blood tests.

      The investigators will also take four 20ml samples of blood, spaced before, during, and after
      the operation, from the arterial catheter routinely inserted in every patient. This blood
      would be used to measure oxidative stress, and also some of the proteins inside the blood
      cells, which are responsible for creating the toxic oxygen compounds. In this way we will
      discover not only the effect of sodium bicarbonate, but also the mechanism of that effect.

      Sodium bicarbonate is commonly used to treat metabolic acidosis in severe renal disease,
      circulatory insufficiency due to shock or severe dehydration and has been shown to be an
      effective drug in preventing contrast-induced nephropathy.

      Sodium bicarbonate is considered to be safe in the setting of intensive care treatment and is
      often used in the treatment of patients with metabolic acidosis without any discernible
      adverse clinical effects.

      This is a pilot study. If the drug proves effective in this context, further studies on a
      larger scale would be required to justify its general use.

      There will be no extra risk to a patient who participates in the study, and no discomfort
      other than that normally associated with cardiac surgery.

      Informed consent will be obtained from the patient prior to the operation by one of the
      investigators or the ICU research nurse. The clinical care of a patient who does not consent
      for any reason will not be affected.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00334191</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Rinaldo Bellomo, MD, FRACP</name>
      <address>Austin Health</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>