<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6469">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/01/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/01/2017</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT03064126</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>RANGER Paclitaxel Coated Balloon vs Standard Balloon Angioplasty</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>RANGER II SFA: A 3:1 Randomized Trial Comparing the Boston Scientific RANGER Paclitaxel Coated Balloon vs Standard Balloon Angioplasty for the Treatment of Superficial Femoral Arteries (SFA) and Proximal Popliteal Arteries (PPA)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>RANGER II SFA</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>S2062</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Peripheral Artery Disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Atherosclerosis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Artery Diseases, Peripheral</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Plaque, Atherosclerotic</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Occlusive Arterial Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - RANGER Paclitaxel Coated Balloon
Treatment: drugs - Paclitaxel
Treatment: surgery - Standard Balloon Angiplasty

Experimental: RANGER Paclitaxel Coated Balloon - RANGER Paclitaxel Coated Balloon Catheter angioplasty in the SFA/PPA at the index procedure.
Subjects will be randomized 3:1 to the drug coated or standard angioplasty balloon.

Active Comparator: Standard Balloon Angioplasty - Standard Balloon Catheter angioplasty in the SFA/PPA at the index procedure. Subjects will be randomized 3:1 to the drug coated or standard angioplasty balloon.


Treatment: devices: RANGER Paclitaxel Coated Balloon
A procedure that utilizes a balloon coated with paclitaxel (drug) which can open up a blocked blood vessel using a small, flexible plastic tube, or catheter, with a "balloon" at the end of it. When the tube is in place, it inflates to open the blood vessel, or artery, so that normal blood flow is restored. The tube is then removed. The blood vessels that will be treated in the RANGER II SFA study include the superficial femoral arteries and the proximal popliteal arteries.

Treatment: drugs: Paclitaxel
The RANGER Balloon is coated with the drug Paclitaxel.

Treatment: surgery: Standard Balloon Angiplasty
A procedure that utilizes an uncoated balloon which can open up a blocked blood vessel using a small, flexible plastic tube, or catheter, with a "balloon" at the end of it. When the tube is in place, it inflates to open the blood vessel, or artery, so that normal blood flow is restored. The tube is then removed. The blood vessels that will be treated in the RANGER II SFA study include the superficial femoral arteries and the proximal popliteal arteries.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Lesion Patency - Primary patency of the target lesion is determined by Peak Systolic Velocity Ratio (PSVR) = 2.4 (by duplex ultrasound (DUS)) and freedom from clinically-driven Target Lesion Revascularization (TLR) within 12 months from procedure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Major Adverse Events (MAEs) - MAE is defined as a composite of freedom from all-cause death through 1 month, target limb major amputation (defined as at or above the ankle) within 12 months, and/or Target Lesion Revascularization (TLR) within 12 months.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Technical Success of angioplasty procedure - Technical success defined as successful delivery, balloon inflation and deflation and retrieval of the intact trial device without burst below the rated burst pressure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 0</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Procedural Success of angioplasty procedure - Procedural success defined as residual stenosis of less than or equal to 50% (non-stented subjects) or less than or equal to 30% (stented subjects) by core laboratory evaluation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 0</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical Success rate assessment - Clinical success defined as procedural success without procedural complications including death, major target limb amputation, thrombosis of the target lesion, or clinically-driven TLR prior to discharge.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 0</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Major Adverse Events (MAE) assessment - MAEs are defined as all-cause death post-index procedure, TLR, and major target limb amputation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month, 6 months, 12 months, 24 months, 36 months, 48 month and 60 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of Death occurrence from any cause - Analysis of the number of deaths from any cause</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month, 6 months, 12 months, 24 months, 36 months, 48 months and 60 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinically-driven Target Vessel Revascularization (TVR) rates - Clinically-driven TVR is defined as any surgical or percutaneous rate of target vessel revascularizations that occur will be reported throughout the 60 month study follow up.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months, 12 months, 24 months, 36 months, 48 months and 60 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinically-driven Target Lesion revascularization (TLR) rates - Clinically-driven TLR is defined as any surgical or percutaneous intervention to the target lesion(s) after the index procedure. Analysis of the number of TLR that occur will be reported throughout the 60 month study follow up.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months, 12 months, 24 months, 36 months, 48 months and 60 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of Primary Sustained Clinical Improvement as assessed by changes in Rutherford Classification - Endpoint determined to be a success when there is an improvement in Rutherford Classification of one or more categories as compared to pre-procedure without the need for repeat TLR</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month, 6 months, 12 months, 24 months and 36 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of Secondary Sustained Clinical Improvement as assessed by changes in Rutherford Classification - Endpoint determined to be a success when there is an improvement in Rutherford Classification of one or more categories as compared to pre-procedure including those subjects with repeat TLR</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month, 6 months, 12 months, 24 months and 36 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of Hemodynamic Improvement as assessed by changes in Ankle Brachial Index (ABI) - Improvement of ABI by = 0.1 or to an ABI = 0.90 as compared to the pre-procedure value without the need for repeat revascularization.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month, 6 months, 12 months, 24 months, and 36 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Target Lesion Restenosis rate - Restenosis is defined as DUS peak systolic velocity ratio (SVR) &gt; 2.4 which suggests stenosis &gt;50%. Duplex-defined binary restenosis of the target lesion rates will be reported as the number of evaluable participants with TLR through 36 months.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month, 6 months, 12 months, 24 months, and 36 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Walking Improvement assessed by change in Six Minute Walk Test (6MWT) - The 6MWT measure the maximal walking distance that a patient achieves on a flat, hard surface within a period of 6 minutes. It evaluates the global and integrated responses of all physiological systems involved during exercise including the pulmonary and cardiovascular systems, systemic circulation, peripheral circulation, neuromuscular units and muscle metabolism. Comparison results will be reported through the 12 month follow up.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Screening, 6 months and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Walking Improvement assessed by change in Walking Impairment Questionnaire (WIQ) - The WIQ is a functional assessment questionnaire that evaluates walking ability with regard to speed, distance and stair climbing ability. It also assesses the reasons that walking ability might be limited. Range of scores include 0% (worst score) to 100% (best score). Scores will be reported though 36 month follow up.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month, 6 months, 12 months, 24 months and 36 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient Utility Values by change in EQ-5D - The EQ-5D questionnaire is a descriptive system of health-related quality of life questions that consists of five dimensions (mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort, anxiety/depression) each of which can take one of five responses. The responses record five levels of severity within each EQ-5D dimension. Results of responses will be reported through 36 months.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month, 6 months, 12 months, 24 months and 36 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in healthcare utilization over time rates - Investigators are asked to document any use of the healthcare system that occurs throughout the study. Reports of hospitalizations, re-hospitalizations, overall time spent hospitalized, treatment in hospitals (outpatient clinics) will occur with all enrolled patients through 60 month follow up.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Index Procedure (Day 0), 1 month, 6 months, 12 months, 24 months, 36 months, 48 months and 60 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Subject (or Legal Guardian) is willing and able to provide consent before any
             study-specific tests or procedures are performed and agree to attend all required
             follow-up visits;

          2. Subject at least 20 years of age;

          3. Chronic symptomatic lower limb ischemia defined as Rutherford classification 2, 3, or
             4;

          4. Target lesion is in the native SFA and/or PPA down to the P1 segment;

          5. Patent popliteal and infrapopliteal arteries, i.e., single vessel runoff or better
             with at least one of three vessels patent (less than 50 % stenosis) to the ankle or
             foot;

          6. Reference vessel diameter = 4 mm and = 8 mm by visual estimate;

          7. Angiographic evidence that target lesion consists of a single de novo, non-stented and
             non-atherectomy treated or restenotic lesion (or tandem lesions or a combination
             lesion as defined below) that is:

               -  = 70%-99% stenotic with total lesion length up to 180 mm by visual estimate.

               -  Occluded with total lesion length = 100 mm by visual estimate.

               -  If lesion is restenotic, most recent PTA treatment must be &gt; 3 months prior to
                  enrollment.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Life expectancy, documented in the Investigator's opinion, of less than 12 months;

          2. Hemorrhagic stroke or cardiac event (e.g. STEMI, unstable angina) within 6 months
             prior to enrollment;

          3. Known allergies or sensitivities to heparin, aspirin, other anticoagulant/antiplatelet
             therapies, and/or paclitaxel;

          4. Known hypersensitivity or contraindication to contrast dye that, in the opinion of the
             investigator, cannot be adequately pre-medicated;

          5. Chronic renal insufficiency with serum creatinine &gt; 2.0 mg/dL within 30 days of index
             procedure or treatment with dialysis;

          6. Platelet count &lt; 80,000 mm 3 or &gt; 600,000 mm 3 or history of bleeding diathesis;

          7. Receiving immunosuppressive therapy;

          8. Septicemia at the time of enrollment;

          9. Any major intervention planned within 30 days post index procedure;

         10. Presence of other hemodynamically significant outflow lesions in the target limb
             requiring intervention within 30 days of enrollment;

         11. Failure to successfully cross the target lesion with a guidewire;

         12. Failure to successfully pre-dilate the target vessel;

         13. Patient has lesion that requires the use of adjunctive primary treatment modalities
             (i.e. laser, atherectomy, scoring/cutting balloon, other debulking devices, etc.)
             during the index procedure;

         14. History of major amputation in the target limb;

         15. Target lesion or vessel has ever been previously treated with stent (e.g. in-stent
             restenosis) or surgery. Target lesion or vessel has been treated with atherectomy or a
             DCB in the past 12 months;

         16. Pregnant or breast feeding;

         17. Presence of aneurysm in the target vessel;

         18. Acute ischemia and/or acute thrombosis of the SFA/PPA prior to enrollment;

         19. Patient has significant inflow disease which cannot be treated prior to the target
             lesion treatment;

         20. Patient has perforated targeted vessel as evidenced by extravasation of contrast
             media;

         21. Patient has severe calcification that renders the lesion undilatable;

         22. Current participation in another investigational drug or device clinical trial that
             has not completed the primary endpoint at the time of randomization/enrollment or that
             clinically interferes with the current trial endpoints.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>2/03/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>396</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/11/2023</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Alabama</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Arizona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Colorado</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Connecticut</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Delaware</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>District of Columbia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Georgia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Hawaii</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Indiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Kentucky</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Louisiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Massachusetts</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Minnesota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Jersey</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Dakota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Oregon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>South Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Tennessee</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Utah</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>West Virginia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Wisconsin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Austria</country>
      <state>Graz</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Austria</country>
      <state>Vienna</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Genk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Gent</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Tienen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Alberta</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Quebec</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Bad Krozingen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Flensburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Heidelberg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Fukuoka</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Fukushima</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Hokkaido</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Hyogo-ken</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Kanagawa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Miyagi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Osaka</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Saitama</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Tokyo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Kyoto</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Hamilton</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Otahuhu</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Boston Scientific Corporation</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To evaluate the safety and effectiveness of the Ranger Paclitaxel Coated Balloon for
      treating lesions located in the superficial femoral and proximal popliteal arteries
      (SFA/PPA).</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03064126</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Litsky J, Chanda A, Stilp E, Lansky A, Mena C. Critical evaluation of stents in the peripheral arterial disease of the superficial femoral artery - focus on the paclitaxel eluting stent. Med Devices (Auckl). 2014 May 28;7:149-56. doi: 10.2147/MDER.S45472. eCollection 2014. Review.
Kakkar AM, Abbott JD. Percutaneous versus surgical management of lower extremity peripheral artery disease. Curr Atheroscler Rep. 2015;17(2):479. doi: 10.1007/s11883-014-0479-0. Review.
Razavi MK, Mustapha JA, Miller LE. Contemporary systematic review and meta-analysis of early outcomes with percutaneous treatment for infrapopliteal atherosclerotic disease. J Vasc Interv Radiol. 2014 Oct;25(10):1489-96, 1496.e1-3. doi: 10.1016/j.jvir.2014.06.018. Epub 2014 Aug 15. Review.
Laird JR, Katzen BT, Scheinert D, Lammer J, Carpenter J, Buchbinder M, Dave R, Ansel G, Lansky A, Cristea E, Collins TJ, Goldstein J, Jaff MR; RESILIENT Investigators. Nitinol stent implantation versus balloon angioplasty for lesions in the superficial femoral artery and proximal popliteal artery: twelve-month results from the RESILIENT randomized trial. Circ Cardiovasc Interv. 2010 Jun 1;3(3):267-76. doi: 10.1161/CIRCINTERVENTIONS.109.903468. Epub 2010 May 18.
Scheinert D, Duda S, Zeller T, Krankenberg H, Ricke J, Bosiers M, Tepe G, Naisbitt S, Rosenfield K. The LEVANT I (Lutonix paclitaxel-coated balloon for the prevention of femoropopliteal restenosis) trial for femoropopliteal revascularization: first-in-human randomized trial of low-dose drug-coated balloon versus uncoated balloon angioplasty. JACC Cardiovasc Interv. 2014 Jan;7(1):10-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jcin.2013.05.022.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Thomas Zeller, MD</name>
      <address>Universitaets-Herzzentrum</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Philip Ghizoni</name>
      <address />
      <phone>763-255-0036</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Philip.Ghizoni@bsci.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>