<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="1835">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/02/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/02/2008</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00622609</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Anti-MAG First Administration to Human</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Single-blind, Single Dose, Placebo Controlled, First Time in Human Study to Assess the Safety, Tolerability and Pharmacokinetics of Ascending Doses of GSK249320 in Healthy Volunteers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>MAG103114</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cerebrovascular Accident</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - GSK249320A
Treatment: drugs - Placebo

Experimental: Subjects receiving GSK249320A - Eligible subjects will receive escalating doses of GSK249320A in cohort 1 to 6 with a starting dose of 0.04 milligrams/kilograms up to the maximum dose of 25 milligrams/kilograms, administered as a slow intravenous infusion over 1 hour on Day 1.

Placebo Comparator: Subjects receiving placebo - Eligible subjects will receive single dose of sodium chloride in cohort 1 to 6, administered as a slow intravenous infusion over 1 hour on Day 1.


Treatment: drugs: GSK249320A
GSK249320A intravenous infusion will be formulated as 100 milligrams/milliliters in 2 milliliters vials (filled to 1 milliliter), in phosphate buffer and delivered by a syringe and programmable pump.

Treatment: drugs: Placebo
Sodium chloride intravenous infusion will be given as matching placebo.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and tolerability of GSK249320 including: adverse events,vital signs,ECG,continuous lead II ECG monitoring,safety laboratory assessments,clinical assessment of peripheral nerve function,nerve conduction testing</outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetic parametersAnti-GSK249320 antibody titres</outcome>
      <timepoint>At various timepoints from pre-dose to Week 52 follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetic parameters of ascending single IV doses of GSK249320: Cinf, AUC(0-24), AUC(0-t) and AUC(0-inf)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At various timepoints from pre-dose to Week 52 follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anti-GSK249320 Antibody titres: serum samples will be collected for anti-drug (anti-GSK249320) antibody confirmation, titration and neutralization testing</outcome>
      <timepoint>At various timepoints from pre-dose to Week 52 follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Non-compartmental pharmacokinetic parameters of GSK249320 : Tinf , lz, T1/2, CL and Vss</outcome>
      <timepoint>At various timepoints from pre-dose to Week 52 follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Novel candidate biomarkers and subsequently discovered biomarkers of the biological response associated with the action of GSK249320 may be identified by application of:</outcome>
      <timepoint>At various timepoints from pre-dose to Week 52 follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>RNA transcriptome analysis of blood samples</outcome>
      <timepoint>At various timepoints from pre-dose to Week 52 follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proteome analysis of plasma samples</outcome>
      <timepoint>At various timepoints from pre-dose to Week 52 follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Healthy adult men or women of non-child bearing potential (i.e. post-menopausal or
             surgically sterile e.g. hysterectomy or bilateral oophorectomy). If necessary,
             postmenopausal status will be confirmed by serum FSH and oestradiol concentrations at
             screening. Surgical sterility will be defined as females who have had a documented
             hysterectomy or bilateral oophorectomy.

          -  Between 18 and 60 years of age inclusive.

          -  Body weight &gt;/ 60 kg and BMI within the range 19-29.9 kg/m2 inclusive.

          -  Healthy as judged by responsible physician with no clinically significant abnormality
             identified on the medical or laboratory evaluation. A subject with a clinical
             abnormality or laboratory parameters outside the reference range for this age group
             may be included only if the Investigator considers that the finding will not introduce
             additional risk factors and will not interfere with the study procedures.

          -  A 12-lead ECG at pre-study screening which in the opinion of the Investigator or
             his/her designee has no abnormalities that will compromise safety in this study.

          -  Normal clinical neurological exam, normal QST results, and normal pattern of
             conduction latencies in medial, ulnar, sural, tibial and peroneal nerves at screening.

          -  Signed and dated written informed consent prior to admission to the study.

          -  The subject is able to understand and comply with protocol requirements, instructions
             and protocol-stated restrictions.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Positive drug/ alcohol screen at screening or baseline.

          -  Positive pre-study HIV, Hepatitis B surface antigen or positive Hepatitis C antibody
             result at screening.

          -  History of acute neuronal injury (central or peripheral) within the previous 12
             months, peripheral neuropathy or neuritis, neurodegenerative disorders or other
             neurological diseases, including conditions which are known or hypothesised to be
             associated with disruption in the blood-brain barrier (BBB).

          -  Considered to be at a high risk of developing a stroke including a history of carotid
             artery disease or surgery, transient ischaemic attacks, reversible ischaemic
             neurological deficits or other abnormalities of the brain vessels, including but not
             limited to berry aneurysms or arteriovenous malformations.

          -  History of regular alcohol consumption averaging &gt;7 drinks/week for women or &gt;14
             drinks/week for men. One drink is equivalent to (12 g alcohol) = 5 ounces (150 mL) of
             wine or 12 ounces (360 mL) of beer or 1.5 ounces (45 mL) of 80 proof distilled
             spirits) within 6 months of screening.

          -  Subjects who smoke 10 or more cigarettes per day. Subjects who smoke &lt;10 cigarettes
             per day may be admitted into the study but will be asked to refrain from smoking for
             at least 24 hours before the planned day of admission into the unit. They will NOT be
             allowed to smoke during their stay in the unit.

          -  The subject is unable to abstain from strenuous physical activity for 72 h prior to
             each clinic visit where safety lab tests are conducted.

          -  The subject has participated in a clinical trial and has received an investigational
             product within the following time period prior to the dosing day in the current study:
             30 days, 5 half-lives or twice the duration of the biological effect of the
             investigational product (whichever is longer).

          -  Use of prescription or non-prescription drugs, including vitamins, herbal and dietary
             supplements (including St John's Wort) within 7 days or 5 half-lives (whichever is
             longer) prior to the first dose of study medication.

          -  Where participation in study would result in donation of blood in excess of 500 mL
             within a 56 day period.

          -  Previous exposure to humanised antibody therapy for any reason.

          -  Unwillingness of the male subjects to abstain from sexual intercourse with pregnant or
             lactating women from the time of the first dose of study medication until five half
             lives following administration of the dose of study medication. This may be increased
             depending on PK analysis during the study.

          -  Unwillingness of the male subject to use a condom/spermicide in addition to having
             their female partner use another form of contraception such as an intra-uterine device
             (IUD), diaphragm with spermicide, oral contraceptives, injectable progesterone,
             subdermal implants or a tubal ligation if the woman could become pregnant from the
             time of the first dose of study medication until five half lives following
             administration of the last dose of study medication. The duration of the period during
             which contraception must be practiced may be modified during the study, depending on
             data emerging from PK analysis. The mean half-life predicted for GSK249320 is 30 days

          -  Female subjects with positive urine/serum pregnancy test result at screening or prior
             to first dose

          -  Status as a "vulnerable" subject, defined by the US Food and Drug Administration (FDA)
             Code of Federal Regulations; 45 CFR, Section 46, Subparts B and C.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/08/2007</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>46</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>9/04/2009</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Randwick, Sydney</hospital>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick, Sydney</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Maryland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>GlaxoSmithKline</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>GSK249320 is a monoclonal antibody directed against myelin associated glycoprotein (MAG), a
      protein that inhibits axonal regeneration. GSK249320 acts as a MAG antagonist, and through
      this activity it is hypothesised that it will enhance recovery from neuronal degeneration
      following acute axonal injury, which occurs in spinal cord injury or stroke.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00622609</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>GSK Clinical Trials</name>
      <address>GlaxoSmithKline</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>