<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="1948">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/04/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/04/2008</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00670501</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of Teriparatide in the Treatment of Postmenopausal Women With Osteoporosis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of LY333334 in the Treatment of Postmenopausal Women With Osteoporosis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>B3D-MC-GHAC</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>547</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Osteoporosis, Postmenopausal</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoporosis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Menstruation and menopause</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - teriparatide
Treatment: drugs - teriparatide
Treatment: drugs - Placebo
Treatment: drugs - Calcium Supplement
Treatment: drugs - Vitamin D Supplement

Experimental: 1 - LY333334 40 micrograms/day plus calcium and vitamin D

Experimental: 2 - LY333334 20 micrograms/day plus calcium and vitamin D

Placebo Comparator: 3 - Placebo plus calcium and vitamin D


Treatment: drugs: teriparatide
40 micrograms/day subcutaneous injection for 3 years with optional 2 year extension phase

Treatment: drugs: teriparatide
20 micrograms/day subcutaneous injection for 3 years with optional 2 year extension phase

Treatment: drugs: Placebo
Placebo for subcutaneous injection will be supplied in a prefilled injection device with a cartridge identical in appearance to the LY333334 device.

Treatment: drugs: Calcium Supplement
Approximately 1000 mg/day of elemental calcium will be supplied as open-label oral supplement

Treatment: drugs: Vitamin D Supplement
Approximately 400 to 1200 IU/day of vitamin D will be supplied as open-label oral supplement

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To demonstrate a reduction in the proportion of patients with new vertebral fractures (by spinal x-ray) following 3-year treatment with 20 and 40 micrograms/day of LY333334 plus calcium and vitamin D compared with calcium and vitamin D alone.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, randomization, 24 , 36, and 60 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To establish the effect of long-term treatment with LY333334 plus calcium and vitamin D, compared with calcium and vitamin D alone, on lumbar spine and hip BMD in postmenopausal women with osteoporosis</outcome>
      <timepoint>Lumbar Spine: Randomization -2wks, Randomization,( 3 &amp; 6 months in a subset of pts), 12 , 18 , 24 , 36 , 48 &amp; 60 months. Hip BMD: Randomization -2wks, Randomization, 12 , 24 , 36 , 48 &amp; 60 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To establish the effect of long-term treatment with LY333334 plus calcium and vitamin D, compared with calcium and vitamin D alone, on total body and radial (forearm) BMD in postmenopausal women with osteoporosis at selected study sites</outcome>
      <timepoint>Randomization, 12, 24, 36, 48 and 60 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To establish the effect of long-term treatment with LY333334 plus calcium and vitamin D, compared with calcium and vitamin D alone, on the rate of new vertebral fractures (by spinal x-ray) in postmenopausal women with osteoporosis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, randomization, 24 months, 60 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To establish the effect of treatment with LY333334 plus calcium &amp; vitamin D, compared with calcium &amp; vitamin D alone, by x-ray on the proportion of subjects experiencing new nonvertebral fractures alone &amp; new nonvertebral &amp; vertebral fractures combined.</outcome>
      <timepoint>As clinically needed throughout the trial</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the effect of long-term treatment with LY333334 plus calcium and vitamin D, compared with calcium and vitamin D alone, on height (via Harpenden stadiometer or other suitable stadiometer) in postmenopausal women with osteoporosis</outcome>
      <timepoint>Randomization, 12, 24, 36, 48, and 60 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the histomorphometric effects of LY333334 plus calcium &amp; vitamin D, compared with calcium &amp; vitamin D alone by biopsy, on the iliac crest (bone formation &amp; resorption, mineralization, and trabecular structure) in a subset of subjects.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Randomization, 12 and 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess effects of LY333334 plus calcium &amp; vitamin D, compared with calcium &amp; vitamin D alone, on biochemical markers of bone formation &amp; resorption (bone-specific alkaline phosphatase, PICP, urinary N-telopeptide, &amp; urinary free deoxypyridinolines)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Randomization, 1, 3, 6, 12, 24, 36, 48, and 60 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess population pharmacokinetics of LY333334 at selected study sites. Nonlinear mixed effect modeling [NONMEM])and or PTH(1-84) will be employed to evaluate serum concentrations of LY333334.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Months 1, 3, 6, 12, 18, 24, 30, 36 and 60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To quantify medical resources used by patients during the study so that a cost-effectiveness analysis can be performed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Randomization, 6, 12, 18, 24, 30, 36, 42, 48, 54, and 60 Months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the impact of LY333334 on health-related quality of life in postmenopausal women with osteoporosis. Quality of life instruments will be completed where translated and validated instruments are available.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Randomization, 12, 24, 36, 48, and 60 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To establish the safety of chronic administration of LY333334 in postmenopausal women with osteoporosis. Adverse events, physical examinations and laboratory tests will be used to assess safety in the patients.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Adverse Events: throughout the trial. Labs:Baseline, randomization, 1, 6, 12, 24, 36, 48, and 60 months. Physical Exams: 12, 24, 36, 48, and 60 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Ambulatory, postmenopausal women.

          -  A minimum of either one moderate or two mild atraumatic vertebral fractures, and a
             minimum of seven evaluable nonfractured vertebrae.

          -  Hip BMD or lumbar spine BMD measurement at least 1.0 standard deviation (SD) below the
             average bone mass for young, healthy women (T-score) only in patients with fewer than
             two moderate fractures or in patients previously treated with therapeutic doses of
             bisphosphonates or fluorides

          -  Normal or clinically nonsignificant abnormal laboratory values (serum calcium,
             PTH(1-84), &amp; urine calcium must be within normal limits at baseline; 25-hydroxyvitamin
             D must be between the lower limit of normal &amp; 3 times the upper limit of normal at
             baseline).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>30</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Female</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Fractures in areas of bone affected by diseases other than osteoporosis (for example,
             cancer or Paget's disease).

          -  Satisfactory baseline thoracic and lumbar spinal x-ray views cannot be obtained as
             determined by the centralized x-ray quality assurance center (for example, severe
             scoliosis or kyphosis).

          -  Current or recent (within 1 year prior to randomization) metabolic bone disorders
             other than postmenopausal osteoporosis, such as Paget's disease, renal osteodystrophy,
             osteomalacia, or any secondary causes of osteoporosis

          -  Current or recent (within 1 year prior to randomization) disease which affects bone
             metabolism, such as hypoparathyroidism, hyperparathyroidism, or hyperthyroidism.

          -  Currently suspected carcinoma or history of carcinoma in the 5 years prior to
             randomization.

          -  Nephrolithiasis or urolithiasis in the 2 years prior to randomization.

          -  Current or recent (within 1 year prior to randomization) sprue, inflammatory bowel
             disease, or malabsorption syndrome, or any indication of poor intestinal absorption of
             calcium, such as the combination of a low urinary calcium excretion and an elevated
             serum intact parathyroid hormone level.

          -  Poor medical or psychiatric risk for treatment with an investigational drug, in the
             opinion of the investigator.

          -  Treatment with androgens or other anabolic steroids in the 6 months prior to
             randomization.

          -  Treatment with calcitonins in the 2 months prior to randomization.

          -  Treatment with estrogen

          -  Treatment with progestins in the 3 calendar months prior to randomization, or for more
             than 2 months in the 12 calendar months prior to randomization.

          -  Treatment with corticosteroids.

          -  Treatment with fluorides in the 6 months prior to randomization or for more than 60
             days in the 24 months prior to randomization.

          -  Treatment with oral bisphosphonates in the 3 months prior to randomization or for more
             than 60 days in the 24 months prior to randomization; treatment with intravenous
             bisphosphonates in the 24 months prior to randomization.

          -  Treatment with vitamin D &gt;50,000 IU/week, or with any dose of calcitriol, analogs, or
             agonists in the 6 months prior to randomization. The 25-hydroxyvitamin D laboratory
             value at randomization must be between the lower limit of normal and three times the
             upper limit of normal.

          -  Treatment with coumarins and indandione derivatives in the 3 months prior to
             randomization; treatment with heparins &gt;10,000 U/day for more than 30 days in the 6
             months prior to randomization.

          -  Treatment with calcium- or aluminum-containing antacids

          -  Treatment with any other drug known to affect bone metabolism in the 6 months prior to
             randomization.

          -  Treatment with any investigational drug during the month prior to the calcium and
             vitamin D run-in phase. Treatment with investigational drugs in certain therapeutic
             classes during the month prior to the calcium &amp; vitamin D run-in phase.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2>The people administering the treatment/s</masking2>
    <masking3 />
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/08/1996</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>1637</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/04/1999</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>For additional information regarding investigative sites for this trial, contact 1-877-CTLILLY (1-877-285-4559, 1-317-615-4559) Mon - Fri from 9 AM to 5 PM Eastern Time (UTC/GMT - 5 hours, EST), or speak with your personal physician. - Nedlands</hospital>
    <postcode> - Nedlands</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Massachusetts</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Argentina</country>
      <state>Capital Federal</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Austria</country>
      <state>Graz</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Brussels</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Alberta</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czech Republic</country>
      <state>Praha</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Denmark</country>
      <state>Aarhus</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Finland</country>
      <state>Kuopio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Szeged</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Tel-Hashomer</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Arenzano</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Amsterdam</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Christchurch</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Norway</country>
      <state>Kristiansand</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Warszawa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Uppsala</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Eli Lilly and Company</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary objective of this study is to demonstrate a reduction in the proportion of new
      vertebral fractures in postmenopausal women with osteoporosis following 3-years of treatment
      with 20 and 40 mcg/day of teriparatide plus calcium and vitamin D compared with calcium and
      vitamin D alone.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00670501</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Call 1-877-CT LILLY (1-877-285-4559) or 1-317-615-4559 Mon-Fri 9 AM - 5 PM Eastern time (UTC/GMT - 5 hours, EST)</name>
      <address>Eli Lilly and Company</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>