<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2915">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/09/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/09/2010</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01202214</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Repeat Dose Safety Study for Compound to Treat Asthma</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomized, Single-Blind, Placebo Controlled, Dose Escalation Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, and Pharmacokinetics of GSK1440115 After a Single Dose and 7 Days of Repeat Dosing in Healthy Volunteers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>UR2114661</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Asthma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Asthma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - 1440115
Treatment: drugs - Placebo

Experimental: Active drug - 

Placebo Comparator: Placebo - 


Treatment: drugs: 1440115


Treatment: drugs: Placebo
matching placebo

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and tolerability assessments consisting of Adverse Events, ECGs, vital signs, clinical observations, and clinical laboratory tests</outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma drug concentration versus time curve [AUC (0-t), AUC [0-8], AUC(0-t)], maximum Cmax, tmax, and t1/2 of GSK1140115 as data permit</outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration of dosing</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure (BP) and heart rate (HR)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration of dosing</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Peak expiratory flow rate (PEFR)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration of Dosing</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Healthy as determined by a responsible and experienced physician, based on a medical
             evaluation including medical history, physical examination, laboratory tests and
             cardiac monitoring. A subject with a clinical abnormality or laboratory parameters
             outside the reference range for the population being studied may be included only if
             the Investigator and the GSK Medical Monitor agree that the finding is unlikely to
             introduce additional risk factors and will not interfere with the study procedures.

          2. Male or female between 18 and 65 years of age inclusive, at the time of signing the
             informed consent.

          3. A female subject is eligible to participate if she is of:

             - Non-childbearing potential defined as pre-menopausal females with a documented tubal
             ligation or hysterectomy; or postmenopausal defined as 12 months of spontaneous
             amenorrhea [in questionable cases a blood sample with simultaneous follicle
             stimulating hormone (FSH) &gt; 40 MlU/ml and estradiol &lt; 40 pg/ml (&lt;147 pmol/L) is
             confirmatory]. [Females on hormone replacement therapy (HRT) and whose menopausal
             status is in doubt will be required to use one of the contraception methods in Section
             8.1 if they wish to continue their HRT during the study. Otherwise, they must
             discontinue HRT to allow confirmation of post-menopausal status prior to study
             enrollment. For most forms of HRT, at least 2-4 weeks will elapse between the
             cessation of therapy and the blood draw; this interval depends on the type and dosage
             of HRT. Following confirmation of their post-menopausal status, they can resume use of
             HRT during the study without use of a contraceptive method.]

          4. Male subjects with female partners of child-bearing potential must agree to use one of
             the contraception methods listed in Section 8.1. This criterion must be followed from
             the time of the first dose of study drug until completion of the Follow-up Period.

          5. Capable of giving written informed consent, which includes compliance with the
             requirements and restrictions listed in the consent form.

          6. AST, ALT, alkaline phosphatase and bilirubin less than or equal to 1.5xULN (isolated
             bilirubin &gt;1.5xULN is acceptable if bilirubin is fractionated and direct bilirubin
             &lt;35%).

          7. QTcB or QTcF &lt; 450 msec; or QTc &lt; 480 msec in subjects with Bundle Branch Block.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. A positive pre-study Hepatitis B surface antigen or positive Hepatitis C antibody
             result within 3 months of Screening

          2. Current or chronic history of liver disease, or known hepatic or biliary abnormalities
             (with the exception of Gilbert's syndrome or asymptomatic gallstones).

          3. A positive pre-study drug/alcohol screen.

          4. A positive test for HIV antibody.

          5. Average systolic blood pressure of &lt; 100 mmHg at Screening.

          6. History of regular alcohol consumption within 6 months of the study defined as:

             - an average weekly intake of &gt;21 units for males or &gt;14 units for females. One unit
             is equivalent to 8 g of alcohol: a half-pint (~240 ml) of beer, 1 glass (125 ml) of
             wine or 1 (25 ml) measure of spirits.

          7. The subject has participated in a clinical trial and has received an investigational
             product within the following time period prior to the first dosing day in the current
             study: 30 days, 5 half-lives or twice the duration of the biological effect of the
             investigational product (whichever is longer).

          8. Use of prescription or non-prescription medications, vitamins, and dietary or herbal
             supplements (including St John's Wort) within 7 days (or 14 days if the medication is
             a potential enzyme inducer) or 5 half-lives (whichever is longer) prior to the first
             dose of study drug, unless in the opinion of the Investigator and GSK Medical Monitor
             the medication will not interfere with the study procedures or compromise subject
             safety.

          9. History of sensitivity to any of the study medications, or components thereof or a
             history of drug or other allergy that, in the opinion of the Investigator or GSK
             Medical Monitor, contraindicates their participation.

         10. Where participation in the study would result in donation of blood or blood products
             in excess of 500 mL within a 56 day period.

         11. Pregnant females as determined by positive serum or urine hCG test at Screening or
             prior to dosing.

         12. Lactating females.

         13. Unwillingness or inability to follow the procedures outlined in the protocol.

         14. Subject is mentally or legally incapacitated.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Basic Science</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/09/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>Investigational Site - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Accenture</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to describe the safety and tolerability of single and repeat
      oral doses of GSK1440115 in healthy volunteers.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01202214</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>