<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2968">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/10/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/10/2010</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01231516</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Study of GSK1349572 Versus Raltegravir (RAL) With Investigator Selected Background Regimen in Antiretroviral-Experienced, Integrase Inhibitor-Naive Adults</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomized, Double-blind Study of the Safety and Efficacy of GSK1349572 50 mg Once Daily Versus Raltegravir 400 mg Twice Daily, Both Administered With an Investigator-selected Background Regimen Over 48 Weeks in HIV-1 Infected, Integrase Inhibitor-Naïve, Antiretroviral-Experienced Adults</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>SAILING</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>111762</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Infection, Human Immunodeficiency Virus</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Acquired immune deficiency syndrome (AIDS / HIV)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - GSK1349572
Treatment: drugs - Raltegravir
Treatment: drugs - GSK1349572 Placebo
Treatment: drugs - Raltegravir Placebo

Experimental: GSK1349572 + Raltegravir Placebo - Subjects will receive GSK1349572 50mg once daily plus raltegravir placebo twice daily.

Active Comparator: Raltegravir + GSK1349572 Placebo - Subjects will receive raltegravir 400mg twice daily plus GSK1349572 placebo once daily.


Treatment: drugs: GSK1349572
50mg once daily

Treatment: drugs: Raltegravir
400mg twice daily

Treatment: drugs: GSK1349572 Placebo
Inactive placebo tablet once daily

Treatment: drugs: Raltegravir Placebo
Inactive placebo tablet twice daily

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants With HIV-1 RNA &lt;50 Copies/Milliliter (c/mL) at Week 48 - The percentage of participants with Plasma Human Immunodeficiency Virus-1 (HIV-1) Ribonucleic Acid (RNA) &lt;50 c/mL at Week 48 was assessed using the Missing, Switch or Discontinuation = Failure (MSDF), as codified by the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) "snapshot" algorithm. This algorithm treated all participants without HIV-1 RNA at Week 48 as nonresponders, as well as participants who switched their concomitant ART prior to Week 48 as follows: background ART substitutions non-permitted per protocol (one background ART substitution was permitted for safety or tolerability); background ART substitutions permitted per protocol unless the decision to switch was documented as being before or at the first on-treatment visit where HIV-1 RNA was assessed. Otherwise, virologic success or failure was determined by the last available HIV-1 RNA assessment while the participant was on-treatment in the randomized phase of the study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 48</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants (Par.) With Detectable Virus That Has Genotypic or Phenotypic Evidence of Treatment-emergent INI Resistance at Time of Protocol Defined Virology Failure (PDVF) - For par. meeting one of the criteria for PDVF, plasma samples collected at the time point of virologic failure and Baseline were tested to evaluate any potential genotypic and/or phenotypic evolution of resistance. PDVF was defined as (A) virologic non-response: a decrease in plasma HIV-1 RNA of &lt;1 log10 copies/mL by Week 16, with subsequent confirmation, unless plasma HIV-1 RNA is &lt;400 copies/mL; confirmed plasma HIV-1 RNA levels &gt;=400 copies/mL on or after Week 24 or (B) virologic rebound: confirmed rebound in plasma HIV-1 RNA levels to &gt;=400 copies/mL after prior confirmed suppression to &lt;400 copies/mL; confirmed plasma HIV-1 RNA levels &gt;1 log10 copies/mL above the nadir value, where nadir is &gt;=400 copies/mL.Treatment-emergent IN mutations are those detected at the time of PDVF but not at Baseline.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline until PDVF up to Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With Plasma HIV-1 RNA &lt;50 c/mL at Week 24 - The number of participants with Plasma Human Immunodeficiency Virus-1 (HIV-1) Ribonucleic Acid (RNA) &lt;50 c/mL at Week 24 was assessed using the Missing, Switch or Discontinuation = Failure (MSDF), as codified by the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) "snapshot" algorithm. This algorithm treated all participants without HIV-1 RNA at Week 24 as nonresponders, as well as participants who switched their concomitant ART prior to Week 24 as follows: background ART substitutions non-permitted per protocol (one background ART substitution was permitted for safety or tolerability); background ART substitutions permitted per protocol unless the decision to switch was documented as being before or at the first on-treatment visit where HIV-1 RNA was assessed. Otherwise, virologic success or failure was determined by the last available HIV-1 RNA measurement through Week 24 (within window) while the participant was on-treatment. The result below corresponds to the Week 24 interim analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With Plasma HIV-1 RNA &lt;400 c/mL at Week 24 and Week 48 - The number of participants with Plasma Human Immunodeficiency Virus-1 (HIV-1) Ribonucleic Acid (RNA) &lt;400 c/mL at the visit of interest was assessed using the Missing, Switch or Discontinuation = Failure (MSDF), as codified by the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) "snapshot" algorithm. This algorithm treated all participants without HIV-1 RNA at the visit of interest as nonresponders, as well as participants who switched their concomitant ART prior to the visit of interest as follows: background ART substitutions non-permitted per protocol (one background ART substitution was permitted for safety or tolerability); background ART substitutions permitted per protocol unless the decision to switch was documented as being before or at the first on-treatment visit where HIV-1 RNA was assessed. Otherwise, virologic success or failure was determined by the last available HIV-1 RNA measurment (within window) for the timepoint of interest while the participant was on-treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 24, Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Absolute Values and Change From Baseline in Cluster of Differentiation 4+ (CD4+) Cell Counts at Weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 24, 32, 40, and 48 - The absolute value for CD4+ cell count (cells per millimeters cubed [mm^3]) was assessed at Baseline (BL), Week 4, Week 8, Week 12, Week 16, Week 24, Week 32, Week 40 and Week 48. Change from Baseline was calculated as the post-Baseline value minus the Baseline value.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline; Weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 24, 32, 40, and 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With Indicated Post-Baseline HIV-associated Conditions, Excluding Recurrences, and Disease Progressions - Clinical disease progression (CDP) was assessed according to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) HIV-1 classification system. Category (CAT) A: one or more of the following conditions (CON), without any CON listed in Categories B and C: asymptomatic HIV infection, persistent generalized lymphadenopathy, acute (primary) HIV infection with accompanying illness or history of acute HIV infection. CAT B: symptomatic CON that are attributed to HIV infection or are indicative of a defect in cell-mediated immunity; or that are considered by physicians to have a clinical course or to require management that is complicated by HIV infection; and not included among CON listed in clinical CAT C. CAT C: the clinical CON listed in the AIDS surveillance case definition. Indicators of CDP were defined as: CDC CAT A at Baseline (BS) to a CDC CAT C event (EV); CDC CAT B at BS to a CDC CAT C EV; CDC CAT C at BS to a new CDC CAT C EV; or CDC CAT A, B, or C at BS to death.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Baseline (Day 1) until Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With the Indicated Post-Baseline Emergent Grade 1 to 4 Clinical Chemistry and Hematology Toxicities/Laboratory Adverse Events (AEs) - All Grade 1 to 4 post-Baseline-emergent chemistry toxicities included alanine aminotransferase (ALT), albumin, alkaline phosphatase (ALP), asparate aminotransferase (AST), carbon dioxide (CO2) content/bicarbonate, cholesterol, creatine kinase (CK), creatinine, hyperglycemia, hyperkalemia, hypernatremia, hypoglycemia, hypokalemia, hyponatremia, low density lipoprotein (LDL) cholesterol calculation, lipase, total bilirubin, and triglycerides. All Grade 1 to 4 post-Baseline-emergent hematology toxities included hemoglobin, platelet count, total neutrophils, and white blood cell count. The Division of AIDS (DAIDS) defined toxicity grades as follows: Grade 1, mild; Grade 2, moderate; Grade 3, severe; Grade 4, potentially life threatening; Grade 5, death. .</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Baseline until Week 48, including participants with post-treatment events occurring after Week 48 for participants not entering the post-Week 48 Open-Label phase of the study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>DTG PK Parameters Including Cmax, Cmin, C0, and C0_avg - The maximal concentration (Cmax), and the minimal concentration (Cmin) were assessed by population pharmacokinetic (PK) modeling using sparse PK samples which were collected as follows: one pre-dose sample and one post-dose sample at 1 to 3 hours/4 to 12 hours at Week 4, one pre-dose sample at Week 24, and one pre-dose sample and one post-dose sample at 1 to 3 hours/4 to 12 hours at Week 48. DTG predose concentration (C0) at Week 4, Week 24, and Week 48 as well as the average C0 (C0_avg) , Cmax and Cmin were estimated and reported here.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 4, Week 24, and Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>DTG PK Parameters Including AUC(0-tau) - AUC is defined as the area under the DTG concentration-time curve as a measure of drug exposure over time. AUC(0-tau) is defined as the area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time zero to time tau over a dosing interval at steady state, where tau is the length of the dosing interval of DTG. AUC was assessed by population pharmacokinetic (PK) modeling using sparse PK samples which were collected as follows: one pre-dose sample and one post-dose sample at 1 to 3 hours/4 to 12 hours at Week 4, one pre-dose sample at Week 24, and one pre-dose sample and one post-dose sample at 1 to 3 hours/4 to 12 hours at Week 48.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 4, Week 24, and Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Antiretroviral therapy (ART)-experienced, Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) -1
             infected adults at least 18 years of age.

          -  Women capable of becoming pregnant must use appropriate contraception during the study
             (as defined by the protocol).

          -  HIV-1 infection as documented by HIV-1 RNA &gt;400 copies/mL (c/mL) at Screening and with
             at least one consecutive HIV-1 RNA &gt;400 c/mL within the four months prior to Screening
             (unless the Screening HIV-1 RNA is &gt; 1000 c/mL where no additional plasma HIV-1 RNA
             assessment is needed).

          -  Have documented resistance (via Screening resistance test) to two or more different
             classes of antiretroviral agents. For subjects off ART for at least one month, if
             Screening resistance results provide a fully active agent and do not show two class
             resistance then historical resistance results from the subject's most recent
             resistance testing may be used, following consultation with the study virologist and
             /or medical monitor.

          -  Integrase inhibitor (INI)-naïve, defined as no prior exposure to any INI (e.g. RAL,
             elvitegravir, or GSK1349572).

          -  Able to provide written informed consent prior to Screening.

          -  French subjects: In France, subjects will be eligible for inclusion in this study only
             if either affiliated to or a beneficiary of a social security category.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Screening resistance test result indicates no fully active antiviral agents are
             available for design of the background regimen.

          -  Subject-virus does not yield results using genotype/phenotype/tropism at Screening
             (assay data is essential for eligibility determination).

          -  Women who are breastfeeding.

          -  Any evidence of an active AIDS-defining condition (except cutaneous Kaposi's sarcoma
             not requiring systemic therapy or CD4+ &lt;200c/mm3).

          -  Subjects with moderate to severe hepatic impairment as defined by Child-Pugh
             classification.

          -  Recent history (less than or equal to 3 months) of upper or lower gastrointestinal
             bleed, with the exception of anal or rectal bleeding.

          -  Anticipated need for hepatitis C therapy during the study.

          -  History or presence of allergy or intolerance to the study drugs or their components
             or drugs of their class.

          -  History of malignancy within the past 5 years or ongoing malignancy other than
             cutaneous Kaposi's sarcoma, basal cell carcinoma, or resected, non-invasive cutaneous
             squamous cell carcinoma; other localized malignancies require agreement between the
             investigator and study medical monitor for inclusion of the subject.

          -  Treatment with an HIV-1 immunotherapeutic vaccine within 90 days prior to Screening.

          -  Treatment with any of the following agents within 28 days of Screening: radiation
             therapy, cytotoxic chemotherapeutic agents, any immunomodulator.

          -  Treatment with any agent, other than licensed ART, which has documented activity
             against HIV-1 in vitro within 28 days of first dose of investigational product.

          -  Exposure to an experimental drug and/or experimental vaccine within either 28 days, 5
             half-lives of the test agent, or twice the duration of the biological effect of the
             experimental test agent - whichever is longer, prior to the first dose of IP.

          -  French subjects recruited at sites in France will be excluded if the subject has
             participated in any study using an investigational drug and/or vaccine within 60 days
             or 5 half-lives, or twice the duration of the biological effect of the experimental
             drug or vaccine - whichever is longer - prior to screening for the study or the
             subject plans to participate simultaneously in another clinical study.

          -  Any acute or verified Grade 4 laboratory abnormality.

          -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) &gt;5 times the upper limit of normal (ULN).

          -  ALT greater than or equal to 3xULN and bilirubin greater than or equal to 1.5xULN
             (with &gt;35% direct bilirubin).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2>The people administering the treatment/s</masking2>
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>26/10/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>724</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/06/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Darlinghurst</hospital>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>2010 - Darlinghurst</postcode>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Alabama</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Arizona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Arkansas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Connecticut</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>District of Columbia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Georgia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Illinois</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Indiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Iowa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Massachusetts</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Michigan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Minnesota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Missouri</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Nebraska</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Jersey</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Oklahoma</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Oregon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Pennsylvania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Rhode Island</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>South Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Utah</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Virginia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Washington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Argentina</country>
      <state>Buenos Aires</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Argentina</country>
      <state>Santa Fe</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Argentina</country>
      <state>Ciudad Autonoma de Buenos Aires</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Antwerpen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Brussels</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Charleroi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Leuven</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Liege</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Minas Gerais</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Paraná</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>São Paulo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Rio de Janeiro</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Salvador</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Santos</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Vitoria</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>British Columbia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Quebec</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Chile</country>
      <state>Región Metro De Santiago</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Chile</country>
      <state>Santiago</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Bordeaux</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Garches</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Le Kremlin Bicêtre cedex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Le Kremlin-Bicêtre Cedex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Lyon Cedex 03</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Marseille</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Nice</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Orléans</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Paris Cedex 10</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Paris Cedex 13</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Paris Cedex 20</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Paris Cedex 4</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Paris</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Strasbourg cedex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Tourcoing cedex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Athens</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Piraeus</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Rio, Patras</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Thessaloniki</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Budapest</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Emilia-Romagna</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Lazio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Lombardia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Piemonte</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Sardegna</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mexico</country>
      <state>Estado de México</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mexico</country>
      <state>Guanajuato</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mexico</country>
      <state>Jalisco</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mexico</country>
      <state>Distrito Federal</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mexico</country>
      <state>Mexico City</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Amsterdam</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Arnhem</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Rotterdam</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Chorzow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Romania</country>
      <state>Bucharest</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Romania</country>
      <state>Constanta</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Ekaterinburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Kazan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Krasnodar</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Moscow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>N.Novgorod</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Perm</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Ryazan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Saratov</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>St. Petersburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Toliyatti</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Volgograd</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Bloemfontein</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Dundee</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Durban</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>(Móstoles) Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Alcala de Henares</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Alicante</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Badalona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Cartagena (Murcia)</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Elche (Alicante)</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Granada</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Granollers (Barcelona)</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>La Coruña</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Mataró</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Murcia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Oviedo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Sabadell (Barcelona)</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>San Sebastián</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Sevilla</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Valencia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Kaohsiung</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Taichung</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Taipei</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Warwickshire</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Crumpsall, Manchester</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Liverpool</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Tooting, London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>ViiV Healthcare</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Shionogi</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>GlaxoSmithKline</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>ING111762 is a 48 week, randomized, double-blind, active-controlled, multicenter, parallel
      group, non-inferiority study. The study will be conducted in at least 688 HIV-1 infected
      antiretroviral experienced, integrase-naïve subjects. Subjects will be randomized 1:1 to
      receive GSK1349572 50 mg once daily or raltegravir (RAL) 400 mg twice daily, each added to an
      investigator selected background regimen consisting of at least one fully active agent plus
      no more than one second single agent which may or may not be active. Antiviral activity,
      safety, pharmacokinetics (PK), and development of viral resistance will be evaluated.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01231516</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Cahn P, Pozniak AL, Mingrone H, Shuldyakov A, Brites C, Andrade-Villanueva JF, Richmond G, Buendia CB, Fourie J, Ramgopal M, Hagins D, Felizarta F, Madruga J, Reuter T, Newman T, Small CB, Lombaard J, Grinsztejn B, Dorey D, Underwood M, Griffith S, Min S; extended SAILING Study Team. Dolutegravir versus raltegravir in antiretroviral-experienced, integrase-inhibitor-naive adults with HIV: week 48 results from the randomised, double-blind, non-inferiority SAILING study. Lancet. 2013 Aug 24;382(9893):700-8. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(13)61221-0. Epub 2013 Jul 3. Erratum in: Lancet. 2014 Jan 4;383(9911):30.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>GSK Clinical Trials</name>
      <address>ViiV Healthcare</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>