<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4765">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/12/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/12/2014</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02328872</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Compass - Randomised Controlled Trial of Primary HPV Testing for Cervical Screening in Australia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Compass - Randomized Controlled Trial of 5-yearly Cervical Screening With Primary HPV Testing Versus Cervical Screening With 2.5-yearly Liquid Based Cytology Testing, in HPV-Unvaccinated and HPV-Vaccinated Women in Australia</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Compass</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Exec-PP-12</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cancer of the Cervix</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cervical Intraepithelial Neoplasia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Cervical (cervix)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other reproductive health and childbirth disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Womb (Uterine or endometrial cancer)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - Molecular testing for HPV
Treatment: devices - Liquid Based Cytology

Experimental: Intervention (HPV Arm) - Molecular testing for HPV with partial genotyping for types 16/18, with referral of the HPV16/18-positive group for diagnostic evaluation, and secondary randomisation of women testing positive for other oncogenic HPV infection (not 16/18), to either image-read cytology screening or dual-stained (DS) cytology testing with p16/Ki67 - the "HPV arm". Screening performed 5 yearly.

Active Comparator: Control (LBC Arm) - Image-read liquid based cytology (LBC) screening with reflex HPV triage testing for low grade smears, the "LBC arm." Screening performed 2.5 yearly.


Treatment: devices: Molecular testing for HPV
Molecular testing for HPV with a test allowing partial genotyping for separate identification of types 16/18 from cervical samples. The technology used in this trial will be approved by the Therapeutic Goods Administration (TGA) Australia. It will identify the major HPV oncogenic genotypes in a pool and separately identify HPV 16 and 18. It will also satisfy performance criteria for relative sensitivity and specificity compared to Hybrid Capture 2 (HC2 ) as articulated by Meijer et al, 2009, Guidelines for human papillomavirus DNA test requirements for primary cervical cancer screening in women 30 years and older.

Treatment: devices: Liquid Based Cytology
The liquid based cytology (LBC) used in this trial will be will be approved by the Therapeutic Goods Administration (TGA) Australia for LBC and appropriately validated and (TGA approved) to perform human papillomavirus testing from a cytology sample.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cumulative CIN3+ (Cervical Intraepithelial Neoplasia Grade 3 or invasive cervical cancer) (ITT) - The primary outcome will be cumulative CIN3+ at 5 years following a 5 year HPV exit testing round in both arms, in women randomised to the HPV arm vs. women randomised to the LBC arm, adjusted for censoring after CIN2+ treatment. For the primary outcome, intention to treat analysis will be performed with closed loop testing for non-inferiority and superiority if non-inferiority is declared. Assuming a total average CIN3+ rate in the LBC arm (across unvaccinated and vaccinated women) of 0.6%, and an absolute non-inferiority margin of 0.22%, the trial will have &gt;90% power with 97.5% confidence to detect non-inferiority for the HPV arm, allowing for a 10% non-compliance rate. This sample is adequately powered to detect this margin should the LBC rates be higher than the assumed 0.6%.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Expected 5 year follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cumulative CIN3+ in baseline screen-negative women (ITT) - Cumulative CIN3+ in women presenting for routine screening randomised to the HPV arm who were HPV-negative at baseline, vs. CIN3+ in those randomised to the LBC arm and who were LBC-negative at baseline, adjusted for censoring after CIN2+ treatment and stratified by recruitment group (date of birth &gt;=July 1st 1980 and &lt;1st July 1980). Intention to treat analysis will be performed with closed loop testing for non-inferiority and superiority if non-inferiority is declared.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Expected 5 year follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cumulative CIN3+ in baseline screen-negative women (per protocol) - Cumulative CIN3+ in women presenting for routine screening randomised to the HPV arm who were HPV-negative at baseline, vs. CIN3+ in those randomised to the LBC arm and who were LBC-negative at baseline and at 2.5 years, adjusted for censoring after CIN2+ treatment and stratified by recruitment group (date of birth &gt;=July 1st 1980 and &lt;1st July 1980). Per-protocol analysis will be performed in women screened and followed up within a defined tolerance period according to protocol recommendations.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Expected 5 year follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cumulative CIN2+ in baseline screen-negative women (ITT) - Cumulative CIN2+ in women randomised to the HPV arm who were HPV-negative at baseline, vs. CIN2+ in women who were randomised to the LBC arm and were LBC-negative at baseline, adjusted for censoring after CIN2+ treatment and stratified by recruitment group (date of birth &gt;=July 1st 1980 and &lt;1st July 1980).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Expected 5 year follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Baseline CIN2+ and CIN3+ - Cross-sectional outcomes for CIN 2+ and CIN3+ detection in each arm, stratified by recruitment group (date of birth &gt;=July 1st 1980 and &lt;1st July 1980).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Following recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>CIN2+ in women randomised to HPV testing at baseline with other oncogenic HPV - CIN2+ in women randomised to HPV testing at baseline who have other HPV (not 16/18), stratified by recruitment group (date of birth &gt;=July 1st 1980 and &lt;1st July 1980).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Expected 12-24 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>CIN2+ and CIN3+ in women who have an abnormal test result at baseline - CIN2+ and CIN3+ in women who have an abnormal test result at baseline, adjusted for censoring after CIN2+ treatment and stratified by recruitment group (date of birth &gt;=July 1st 1980 and &lt;1st July 1980).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Expected 5 year follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>CIN2+ and CIN3+ in women who were in follow-management for a previous abnormality at baseline - CIN2+ and CIN3+ in women who were in follow-management for a previous abnormality at baseline, adjusted for censoring after CIN2+ treatment and stratified by recruitment group (date of birth &gt;=July 1st 1980 and &lt;1st July 1980).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Expected 5 year follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Australian female residents aged 25-69 years who are attending for routine cervical
             screening.

          -  Participants may have been previously enrolled in the Compass Pilot but must have been
             discharged to routine screening. Women may also be in follow-up management for a
             previous abnormality or unsatisfactory cytology.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>25</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>69</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Female</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Previous total hysterectomy (uterus and cervix).

          -  The presence of symptoms or signs for which cervical cancer must be excluded.

          -  Currently undergoing treatment for cervical cancer.

          -  Currently enrolled in the Compass Pilot Study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Screening</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/01/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>121000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/12/2023</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Victorian Cytology Service - Carlton</hospital>
    <postcode>3053 - Carlton</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Victorian Cytology Service</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Cancer Council New South Wales</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Compass is a randomised controlled trial of primary HPV testing for cervical cancer screening
      in Australia. A pilot study involving 5,000 women was carried out in 2013-2014. The trial
      will involve recruiting 121,000 women from primary health clinics. Women aged 25-69,
      attending for cervical screening or for routine follow-up will be invited to participate in
      the 2-arm trial. A liquid-based cytology (LBC) sample will be taken from consenting women and
      sent to VCS Pathology. Women will be randomised in a 1:2 parallel group allocation to LBC and
      HPV arms using randomisation with the minimisation procedure, with stratification by birth
      cohort according to whether offered HPV vaccination in Australia's national publicly-funded
      HPV vaccination program (date of birth &gt;=July 1st 1980 and &lt;1st July 1980). In the LBC
      (active control) arm, women will undergo 2.5 yearly image read cytology screening with reflex
      HPV triage testing for low grade cytology. In the HPV (intervention) arm women will undergo 5
      yearly HPV screening with partial genotyping enabling separate identification of HPV16 and
      HPV18 and referral of this group for diagnostic evaluation, and secondary randomisation of
      "intermediate risk" women testing positive for oncogenic HPV (but not HPV 16 or 18) to either
      image read LBC screening or dual-stained (DS) cytology testing with p16/Ki67. The laboratory
      reports issued to practitioners will specify the recommended management for women, according
      to study arm and test results.Participating women will be flagged on the Victorian Cervical
      Cytology Registry (VCCR) and clinical outcomes will be tracked via the VCCR. Data linkage
      between the VCCR and the National HPV Vaccination Program Register will be performed in order
      to integrate vaccination and screening histories for trial participants. Participants will be
      followed for an anticipated 5 years from the time of recruitment and the primary outcome is
      based on the total cumulative detection of CIN3+ after exit testing at 5 years.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02328872</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Karen Canfell, BE, D.Phil.</name>
      <address>Cancer Council New South Wales</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Karen Canfell, BE, D.Phil.</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+61 2 9334 1726</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>karen.canfell@nswcc.org.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>