<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5253">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/02/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/02/2009</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00850538</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Role of Bone in Knee Osteoarthritis (OA)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Role of Bone and Its Measurement in Knee Osteoarthritis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NEBH 2008-018</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Osteoarthritis, Knee</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: other - MRI
Treatment: surgery - Primary Total Knee Replacement

Treatment: other: MRI
1.5T MRI exam of signal knee with knee coil (estimated time: 35 minutes)

Treatment: surgery: Primary Total Knee Replacement
Fluid, bone, and meniscus specimens obtained from total joint replacement will be collected.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With Viable Specimens for Genetic Analysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>Tissue samples collected at time of surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  subjects having primary knee replacement surgery with 1 participating surgeon at NEBH
             (principal investigator)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  subjects having a revision knee replacement instead of a primary knee replacement

          -  contraindications for MRI

          -  pregnancy</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>101</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/04/2013</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>University of Sydney - Sydney</hospital>
    <postcode>02120 - Sydney</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The New England Baptist Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of the study is to investigate protein and gene expression among damaged knee
      tissues. We will perform MRI's on subjects prior to total knee replacement to identify the
      location of bone marrow lesions. Connective tissues including tendon, ligament, and meniscus
      specimens normally discarded from total joint replacements will be used for live cell
      harvest, and protein and gene expression analyses of tissue or cultured cells.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00850538</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Burr DB. The importance of subchondral bone in the progression of osteoarthritis. J Rheumatol Suppl. 2004 Apr;70:77-80. Review.
Felson DT, Chaisson CE, Hill CL, Totterman SM, Gale ME, Skinner KM, Kazis L, Gale DR. The association of bone marrow lesions with pain in knee osteoarthritis. Ann Intern Med. 2001 Apr 3;134(7):541-9.
Felson DT, McLaughlin S, Goggins J, LaValley MP, Gale ME, Totterman S, Li W, Hill C, Gale D. Bone marrow edema and its relation to progression of knee osteoarthritis. Ann Intern Med. 2003 Sep 2;139(5 Pt 1):330-6.
Lo GH, Hunter DJ, Zhang Y, McLennan CE, Lavalley MP, Kiel DP, McLean RR, Genant HK, Guermazi A, Felson DT. Bone marrow lesions in the knee are associated with increased local bone density. Arthritis Rheum. 2005 Sep;52(9):2814-21.
Hunter DJ, Zhang Y, Niu J, Goggins J, Amin S, LaValley MP, Guermazi A, Genant H, Gale D, Felson DT. Increase in bone marrow lesions associated with cartilage loss: a longitudinal magnetic resonance imaging study of knee osteoarthritis. Arthritis Rheum. 2006 May;54(5):1529-35.
Zanetti M, Bruder E, Romero J, Hodler J. Bone marrow edema pattern in osteoarthritic knees: correlation between MR imaging and histologic findings. Radiology. 2000 Jun;215(3):835-40.
Neuhold A, Hofmann S, Engel A, Leder K, Kramer J, Haller J, Plenk H. Bone marrow edema of the hip: MR findings after core decompression. J Comput Assist Tomogr. 1992 Nov-Dec;16(6):951-5.
Plenk H Jr, Hofmann S, Eschberger J, Gstettner M, Kramer J, Schneider W, Engel A. Histomorphology and bone morphometry of the bone marrow edema syndrome of the hip. Clin Orthop Relat Res. 1997 Jan;(334):73-84.
Reinus WR, Fischer KC, Ritter JH. Painful transient tibial edema. Radiology. 1994 Jul;192(1):195-9.
Hunter DJ, Lo GH, Gale D, Grainger AJ, Guermazi A, Conaghan PG. The reliability of a new scoring system for knee osteoarthritis MRI and the validity of bone marrow lesion assessment: BLOKS (Boston Leeds Osteoarthritis Knee Score). Ann Rheum Dis. 2008 Feb;67(2):206-11. Epub 2007 May 1. Review.
Kornaat PR, Bloem JL, Ceulemans RY, Riyazi N, Rosendaal FR, Nelissen RG, Carter WO, Hellio Le Graverand MP, Kloppenburg M. Osteoarthritis of the knee: association between clinical features and MR imaging findings. Radiology. 2006 Jun;239(3):811-7.
Hayes CW, Jamadar DA, Welch GW, Jannausch ML, Lachance LL, Capul DC, Sowers MR. Osteoarthritis of the knee: comparison of MR imaging findings with radiographic severity measurements and pain in middle-aged women. Radiology. 2005 Dec;237(3):998-1007. Epub 2005 Oct 26.
Simkin PA. Bone pain and pressure in osteoarthritic joints. Novartis Found Symp. 2004;260:179-86; discussion 186-90, 277-9. Review.
Mach DB, Rogers SD, Sabino MC, Luger NM, Schwei MJ, Pomonis JD, Keyser CP, Clohisy DR, Adams DJ, O'Leary P, Mantyh PW. Origins of skeletal pain: sensory and sympathetic innervation of the mouse femur. Neuroscience. 2002;113(1):155-66.
Hukkanen M, Konttinen YT, Rees RG, Gibson SJ, Santavirta S, Polak JM. Innervation of bone from healthy and arthritic rats by substance P and calcitonin gene related peptide containing sensory fibers. J Rheumatol. 1992 Aug;19(8):1252-9.
Hunter DJ, Gerstenfeld L, Bishop G, Davis AD, Mason ZD, Einhorn TA, Maciewicz RA, Newham P, Foster M, Jackson S, Morgan EF. Bone marrow lesions from osteoarthritis knees are characterized by sclerotic bone that is less well mineralized. Arthritis Res Ther. 2009;11(1):R11. doi: 10.1186/ar2601. Epub 2009 Jan 26.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>David Hunter, MD</name>
      <address>University of Sydney</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>