<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="1864">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/02/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/02/2008</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00630305</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Endothelial Bleb Response With Toric Lenses</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of the Short-Term Corneal Endothelial Response to Wear of Toric Soft Contact Lenses in Asian Eyes</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>JJO0717</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>CR-0726</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Ametropia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - alphafilcon A toric
Treatment: devices - lotrafilcon B toric
Treatment: devices - senofilcon A toric

Other: Session A - Subjects were first randomized to a session and then randomized to receive one of four lens sequences for that session. Each subject participated in all four sessions. Session A only contains senofilcon A toric and alphafilcon A toric lenses.

Other: Session B - Subjects were first randomized to a session and then randomized to receive one of four lens sequences for that session. Each subject participated in all four sessions. Session B only contains senofilcon A toric and alphafilcon A toric lenses.

Other: Session C - Subjects were first randomized to a session and then randomized to receive one of four lens sequences for that session. Each subject participated in all four sessions. Session C only contains senofilcon A toric and lotrafilcon B toric lenses.

Other: Session D - Subjects were first randomized to a session and then randomized to receive one of four lens sequences for that session. Each subject participated in all four sessions. Session D only contains senofilcon A toric and lotrafilcon B toric lenses.


Treatment: devices: alphafilcon A toric
Subjects that were randomized to receive alphafilcon A toric during one of the four sessions (Sessions A, B, C and D).

Treatment: devices: lotrafilcon B toric
Subjects that were randomized to receive lotrafilcon B toric during one of the four sessions (Sessions A, B, C and D).

Treatment: devices: senofilcon A toric
Subjects that were randomized to receive senofilcon A toric during one of the four sessions (Sessions A, B, C and D).

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Endothelial Bleb Areas on Cornea: Session A- Open Eye - Mean area of endothelial blebs in the following corneal locations: Central, Nasal, Temporal, Inferior, Superior. A masked observer performed the analysis by subjectively selecting a region in a given image that provided an optimal balance of maximum area and clarity of cell outlines. Blebs were then outlined manually and the software calculated the area of blebs. The different sessions are reported showing results for each lens according to the lens worn in the contralateral (contra) eye.Open eye sessions simulated the subjects normal ocular behavior during waking hours; closed eye sessions simulated ocular activity during duration of closed eye activity, such as sleeping. Results are reported as the mean percent difference between the stated test (senofilcon A) and the control lens (alphafilcon A, lotrafilcon B), after 20 minutes of wear, for each testing scenario.</outcome>
      <timepoint>20 minutes post-lens insertion</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Endothelial Bleb Areas on Cornea: Session B- Closed Eye - Mean area of endothelial blebs in the following corneal locations: Central, Nasal, Temporal, Inferior, Superior. A masked observer performed the analysis by subjectively selecting a region in a given image that provided an optimal balance of maximum area and clarity of cell outlines. Blebs were then outlined manually and the software calculated the area of blebs. The different sessions are reported showing results for each lens according to the lens worn in the contralateral (contra) eye.Open eye sessions simulated the subjects normal ocular behavior during waking hours; closed eye sessions simulated ocular activity during duration of closed eye activity, such as sleeping. Results are reported as the mean percent difference between the stated test (senofilcon A) and the control lens (alphafilcon A, lotrafilcon B), after 20 minutes of wear, for each testing scenario.</outcome>
      <timepoint>20 minutes post-lens insertion</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Endothelial Bleb Areas on Cornea: Session C- Open Eye - Mean area of endothelial blebs in the following corneal locations: Central, Nasal, Temporal, Inferior, Superior. A masked observer performed the analysis by subjectively selecting a region in a given image that provided an optimal balance of maximum area and clarity of cell outlines. Blebs were then outlined manually and the software calculated the area of blebs. The different sessions are reported showing results for each lens according to the lens worn in the contralateral (contra) eye.Open eye sessions simulated the subjects normal ocular behavior during waking hours; closed eye sessions simulated ocular activity during duration of closed eye activity, such as sleeping. Results are reported as the mean percent difference between the stated test (senofilcon A) and the control lens (alphafilcon A, lotrafilcon B), after 20 minutes of wear, for each testing scenario.</outcome>
      <timepoint>20 minutes post-lens insertion</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Endothelial Bleb Areas on Cornea: Session D- Closed Eye - Mean area of endothelial blebs in the following corneal locations: Central, Nasal, Temporal, Inferior, Superior. A masked observer performed the analysis by subjectively selecting a region in a given image that provided an optimal balance of maximum area and clarity of cell outlines. Blebs were then outlined manually and the software calculated the area of blebs. The different sessions are reported showing results for each lens according to the lens worn in the contralateral (contra) eye.Open eye sessions simulated the subjects normal ocular behavior during waking hours; closed eye sessions simulated ocular activity during duration of closed eye activity, such as sleeping. Results are reported as the mean percent difference between the stated test (senofilcon A) and the control lens (alphafilcon A, lotrafilcon B), after 20 minutes of wear, for each testing scenario.</outcome>
      <timepoint>20 minutes post-lens insertion</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Successful soft contact lens wear in daily mode for a minimum of 1 month prior to
             start of the study without experiencing difficulties or contact lens related
             complications.

          2. At least 18 years of age and mentally competent to sign an informed consent form.

          3. Healthy eyes and no use of ocular medication.

          4. Similarity of optical parameters between eyes.

          5. Physical appearance typical of Asian eyes</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. A medical or ocular condition that may influence the outcome of this trial.

          2. Current use of ocular/systemic medication that may influence the outcome of this
             trial.

          3. Failure to wear soft lenses for 2 weeks prior to the start of the study.

          4. Current enrolment or participation in another clinical study.

          5. Current state of pregnancy or breastfeeding

          6. Anisometropia greater than 1.00D (equivalent sphere).

          7. Unequal acuities between eyes (greater than 1 line)

          8. Unequal corneal curvatures (&gt;1.00D)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/01/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>37</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/07/2008</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Brennan Consultants 110 Auburn Rd - Auburn Village</hospital>
    <postcode>3122 - Auburn Village</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Johnson &amp; Johnson Vision Care, Inc.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Evaluate the short-term corneal response of oxygen deprivation when using toric contact
      lenses. The response will be noted by endothelial bleb formation in both open eye and closed
      eye state.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00630305</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Noel A Brennan, McOptom PhD</name>
      <address>Brennan Consultants</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>