<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4827">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/08/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/08/2014</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02228369</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Oral Epidermal Growth Factor Receptor Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitors, AZD3759 or AZD9291, in Patients Who Have Advanced Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase I, Open-label, Multicentre Study to Assess the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics and Preliminary Anti-Tumour Activity of AZD3759 or AZD9291 in Patients With EGFR Mutation Positive Advanced Stage Non Small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>BLOOM</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>D6030C00001</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>EGFR Mutation Positive Advanced Non Small Cell Lung Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lung - Mesothelioma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lung - Non small cell</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lung - Small cell</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - AZD3759
Treatment: drugs - AZD9291

Experimental: Daily dose of AZD3759 - Daily oral dose of AZD3759

Experimental: Daily Dose of AZD9291 - Daily oral dose of AZD9291


Treatment: drugs: AZD3759
Starting dose 50 mg, administered twice daily. If tolerated subsequent cohorts will test increasing doses of AZD3759, until a maximum tolerated dose or an effective dose is defined

Treatment: drugs: AZD9291
AZD9291 160mg once daily

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and Tolerability (The number of patients with each AE by system organ class, preferred term and CTCAE grade) - Adverse events will be collected from Informed consent until the end of the follow-up period which is defined as 28 days (+7 days) after study treatment is discontinued.Physical exam (screening, single dosing day, Day 1 of every 3-week cycle of multiple dosing and treatment discontinuation). ECG and vital signs (screening, Day 1 and 2 of Cycle 0 for AZD3759 cohorts, Day 8 of Cycle 1 for AZD3759 cohorts, Day 1 of every 3-week cycle, treatment discontinuation, and if occurrence of any cardiac adverse event). Lab variables (screening, first dosing day, Day 1, 8 and 15 of multiple dosing, Day 1 of every 3-week cycle and treatment discontinuation). Eye exam (at screening and study drug discontinuation and upon occurrence of any visual AE). Echocardiogram or multigated radionuclide angiography (at screening,whenever necessary as clinically indicated throughout the study for AZD3759 cohorts.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Informed consent until the end of the follow-up period which is defined as 28 days (+7 days) after study treatment is discontinued.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma concentration of AZD3759 and metabolite and pharmacokinetics parameters after single dose of AZD3759(Cmax, tmax, terminal rate constant, half life, AUC, clearance, volume of distribution, mean residence time) - The parent drug and N-demethylated metabolite in plasma samples will be analyzed: pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 24, 48, hour in Day 1; 24hour in Day 2 and 48hour in Day 3.
AUC: Area Under Curve</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cycle 0 Day 1 to 3 in Part A patients.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma,urine,cerebrospinal fluid concentration of AZD3759 and metabolite and pharmacokinetics parameters after multiple dosing(Cmax,ss, tmax,ss, Cmin,ss, AUCss, CLss/F). - The parent drug and N-demethylated metabolite in plasma samples from all patients will be analyzed: pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12hour on Cycle 1 Day 8 and Cycle 3 Day 1 . The parent drug and N-demethylated metabolite in urine samples from Part A patients will be analyzed: 0-12h at Cycle 1 Day 8. The parent drug and N-demethylated metabolite in cerebrospinal fluid samples will be analyzed: pre-dose of Cycle 1 Day 8 in brain metastasis patients; pre-dose of Cycle 1 Day 8 and Cycle 3 Day 1 in leptomeningeal metastasis patients. AUCss: Area Under Curve Steady State CLss: Clearance Steady State</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples: Cycle 1 Day 8 and Cycle 3 Day 1 in all patients. Urine samples: 0-12h at Cycle 1 Day 8 in Part A. CSF samples: pre-dose of Cycle 1 Day 8 in BM; Pre-dose of Cycle 1 Day 8 and Cycle 3 Day 1 in LM</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma,urine, cerebrospinal fluid concentration of AZD3759 and metabolite and pharmacokinetics parameters after multiple dosing (extent of accumulation, renal clearance, time dependency of pharmacokinetics and amount of drug excreted) - The parent drug and N-demethylated metabolite in plasma samples from all patients will be analyzed: pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12hour on Cycle 1 Day 8 and Cycle 3 Day 1. The parent drug and N-demethylated metabolite in urine samples from Part A patients will be analyzed: 0-12h at Cycle 1 Day 8. The parent drug and N-demethylated metabolite in cerebrospinal fluid samples will be analyzed: pre-dose of Cycle 1 Day 8 in brain metastasis patients; pre-dose of Cycle 1 Day 8 and Cycle 3 Day 1 in leptomeningeal metastasis patients.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples: Cycle 1 Day 8 and Cycle 3 Day 1 in all patients. Urine samples: 0-12h at Cycle 1 Day 8 in Part A patients. CSF samples: pre-dose of Cycle 1 Day 8 and Cycle 3 Day 1 in Part B patients .</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma, cerebrospinal fluid concentration of AZD9291 and metabolite and pharmacokinetics parameters after multiple dose of AZD9291(Cmax,ss, tmax,ss, Cmin,ss, AUCss, CLss/F). - The parent drug and metabolites in plasma samples from all patients treated with AZD9291 will be analyzed: pre-dose of Cycle 1 Day 1, 8, 15; pre-dose, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 24hour on Cycle 2 Day 1. The parent drug and metabolites in cerebrospinal fluid samples will be analyzed: pre-dose of Cycle 2 Day 1 in brain metastasis patients; pre-dose of Cycle 2 Day 1 and Cycle 3 Day 1 in leptomeningeal metastasis patients . AUCss: Area Under Curve Steady State CLss: Clearance Steady State</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples: Cycle 1 Day 1, 8, 15 and Cycle 2 Day 1. Cerebrospinal fluid samples: pre-dose of Cycle 2 Day 1 and pre-dose of Cycle 3 Day 1.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma, cerebrospinal fluid concentration of AZD9291 and metabolites and pharmacokinetics parameters after multiple dosing (extent of accumulation, renal clearance, time dependency of pharmacokinetics and amount of drug excreted) - The parent drug and metabolites in plasma samples from all patients treated with AZD9291 will be analyzed: pre-dose of Cycle 1 Day 1, 8, 15; pre-dose, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 24hour on Cycle 2 Day 1. The parent drug and metabolites in cerebrospinal fluid samples will be analyzed: pre-dose of Cycle 2 Day 1 in brain metastasis patients; pre-dose of Cycle 2 Day 1 and Cycle 3 Day 1 in leptomeningeal metastasis patients . AUCss: Area Under Curve Steady State CLss: Clearance Steady State</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples: Cycle 1 Day 1, 8, 15 and Cycle 2 Day 1. Cerebrospinal fluid samples: pre-dose of Cycle 2 Day 1 and pre-dose of Cycle 3 Day 1.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall survival follow up for all expansion patients - After 28-day follow-up visit, patients will be followed for overall survival via telephone every 6 weeks until death, lost to follow-up or consent withdrawal</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 6 weeks after the 28- day safety follow-up visit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>4b-hydroxy cholesterol in Part B patients with BM - Blood collection at pre-dose of Cycle 0 Day 1 and Cycle 1 Day 15 to evaluate if AZD3759 affects 4b-hydroxy cholesterol which is an endogenous marker of CYP enzyme induction</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-dose of Cycle 0 Day 1 and Cycle 1 Day 15</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The effect of food on the pharmacokinetics of a single dose of AZD3759 in plasma - Pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12 hour of Cycle 0 Day 1and Day 4; 24 hour of Cycle 0 Day 2 and Day 4.A Mixed Effects model with treatment (fed/fasted) and period as fixed effects and patient as a random effect will be used to compare AUC/Cmax in the fed state with AUC/Cmax in the fasted state.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cycle 0 Day 1 to Day 4 in Part B patients with BM</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cerebrospinal fluid response rate for patients with LM and/or BM - Cerebrospinal fluid collection at screening and every 6 weeks until progression to evaluate the cerebrospinal fluid response rate which is defined as the percentage of leptomeningeal metastasis patients who have at least one cerebrospinal fluid response (100% clearance of tumour cells from cerebrospinal</outcome>
      <timepoint>Screening and every 6 weeks (relative to first dose of multiple dosing) until progression, expected average 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes from baseline in central nervous system symptoms (analyzed from QLQ-BN20) in patients with LM treated with AZD3759 /AZD9291 - Quality of life questionnaire-Brain Cancer 20 questionnaire completed by patients at screening, Day 1 of every 3-week cycle and treatment discontinuation. Use relevant symptom questions to evaluate improvement of central nervous system symptoms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Screening, Day 1 of every 3-week cycle and treatment discontinuation, expected average 6 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes from baseline in neurological exam in patients with LM treated with AZD3759 /AZD9291 - Neurological exam will be performed: screening, single dosing day, Day 1 of every 3-week cycle of multiple dosing and treatment discontinuation</outcome>
      <timepoint>Screening, Day 1 of every 3-week cycle and treatment discontinuation, expected average 6 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of Objective Response Rate (ORR) - ORR assessed through the number of patients who achieve a disease response (i.e. complete response or partial response) assessed according to modified RECIST 1.1 criteria for central nervous system disease, extracranial disease and overall disease</outcome>
      <timepoint>Screening within 28days of treatments start and then every 6 weeks ± 1week(relative to first dose of multiple dosing) until objective disease progression or withdrawal from study,expected average 6 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of Disease Control Rate (DCR) - DCR assessed through the number of patients who achieve a best response of confirmed CR, confirmed PR or responding, or stable disease according to modified RECIST 1.1 criteria for central nervous system disease, extracranial disease, leptomeningeal disease and overall disease</outcome>
      <timepoint>Screening within 28days of treatments start and then every 6 weeks ± 1week(relative to first dose of multiple dosing) until objective disease progression or withdrawal from study,expected average 6 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of Response Rate (RR) - RR assessed through the number of patients who have at least one confirmed response of Complete Response or Responding prior to any evidence of progression according to modified RECIST 1.1 criteria for leptomeningeal disease</outcome>
      <timepoint>Screening within 28days of treatments start and then every 6 weeks ± 1week(relative to first dose of multiple dosing) until objective disease progression or withdrawal from study,expected average 6 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of Progression Free Survival (PFS) - PFS assessed through change in tumour size (as well as assessment of non-target lesions and appearance of any new lesions) according to modified RECIST 1.1 criteria for Part B patients with brain metastasis and patients with leptomeningeal metastasis</outcome>
      <timepoint>Screening within 28days of treatments start and then every 6 weeks ± 1week(relative to first dose of multiple dosing) until objective disease progression or withdrawal from study,expected average 6 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Best Leptomeningeal Metastasis (LM) assessment for AZD9291 LM patients - Best LM assessment via LANO criteria through the number of patients with LM present at baseline, without a requirement for confirmation. LANO assessments will be mapped to RECIST-like scores and performed via central imaging reading.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Screening within 28days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Obtained written informed consent

          2. Male or female aged at least 18 years. Aged at least 20 if Japanese.

          3. Histologically or cytologically confirmed diagnosis of NSCLC with single activating
             EGFR mutations (L858R or Exon19Del).

          4. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status of 0 to1. For LM patients, 0 to
             2 is acceptable.

          5. In Part A, prior treatment with at least one line of a single agent EGFR TKI and at
             least 1 line of chemotherapy.

          6. In Part B-BM expansion, patients must have not received any EGFR TKI and have
             asymptomatic brain metastasis, either found during screening process which does not
             require local treatment in the opinion of the investigator or local treatment has been
             given (surgery or radiation), patient must be stable without corticosteroid and/or
             anti-convulsants treatment for at least 2 weeks before study enrollment. For Part B-LM
             expansion, patients who received previous EGFR TKI treatment must have stable
             extracranial disease;EGFR TKI treatment naïve patients can also be enrolled into
             AZD9291 cohorts, or AZD3759 cohorts if efficacy signal seen in Part A and agreed by
             Safety Review Committee.

          7. For patients with neither LM nor measurable BM: At least one measurable extracranial
             lesion. For patients with measurable BM but without LM: at least one measurable
             intracranial lesion

          8. For patients with LM: Confirmed diagnosis of LM by positive CSF cytology.

          9. Male patients should be willing to use barrier contraception, i.e., condoms, until 3
             months after last study drug is taken.

         10. Females should agree to use adequate contraceptive measures, should not be breast
             feeding and must have a negative pregnancy test prior to start of dosing if of
             child-bearing potential or must have evidence of non-child-bearing potential

         11. In Part B-AZD9291 LM expansion (sub-cohort of T790M+ LM patients), patients must have
             central confirmation of T790M+ mutation status from a sample taken after documented
             progression on the last treatment administered prior to enrolling in the study.
             Patients must have received prior therapy with an EGFR TKI and may also have received
             additional lines of treatment. Stable extracranial disease is not required.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. For patients with LM and/or BM, CNS complications that require urgent neurosurgical
             intervention

          2. For patient with LM, inability to undergo collection of CSF

          3. Treatment with an EGFR TKI (e.g., erlotinib or gefitinib) within 8 days or
             approximately 5 x half-life, whichever is the longer, of the first dose of study
             treatment.

          4. Any cytotoxic chemotherapy,or other anticancer drugs for the treatment of advanced
             NSCLC from a previous treatment regimen within 14 days of the first dose of study
             treatment

          5. Radiotherapy with a wide field of radiation within 4 weeks or radiotherapy with a
             limited field of radiation for palliation within 1 week of the first dose of study
             treatment with the exception of patients receiving radiation to more than 30% of the
             bone marrow which must be completed within 4 weeks of the first dose of study
             treatment.

          6. Patients currently receiving (or unable to stop use at least 1 week prior to receiving
             the first dose of AZD3759/AZD9291) medications or herbal supplements known to be
             potent inhibitors or inducers of cytochrome P450 3A4/5 and potential inhibitors of
             cytochrome P450 2C8 (for patients to be enrolled into AZD9291 cohorts only).

          7. Past medical history of interstitial lung disease, drug-induced interstitial lung
             disease, radiation pneumonitis which required steroid treatment, or any evidence of
             clinically active interstitial lung disease.

          8. Known intracranial haemorrhage which is unrelated to tumour

          9. Refractory nausea and vomiting if not controlled by supportive therapy, chronic
             gastrointestinal diseases, inability to swallow the formulated product or previous
             significant bowel resection that would preclude adequate absorption of AZD3759/AZD9291

         10. Any evidence of severe or uncontrolled systemic diseases, including uncontrolled
             hypertension and active bleeding diatheses

         11. Inadequate bone marrow reserve or organ function

         12. Clinically significant ECG abnormalities or any factors that increase the risk of
             corrected QT interval prolongation or risk of arrhythmic events

         13. Prior history of whole brain radiotherapy (only applicable for AZD3759 BM expansion)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>5/11/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>108</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>3/08/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>Research Site - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>Research Site - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Seongnam-si</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Seoul</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Taipei</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>AstraZeneca</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is the first time in patient study to assess the safety, tolerability and preliminary
      efficacy of AZD3759 in patients with advanced Non Small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC) In this
      study, patients with Leptomeningeal Metastasis and Brain Metastasis may also be enrolled to
      assess the anti-tumour efficacy, safety, pharmacokinetics and potential biological activity
      of AZD9291</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02228369</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Pamela Yang, M.D. PhD</name>
      <address>Building 2, 199 Liangjing Road, Zhangjiang Hi-tech Park, Shanghai 201203, China</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>