<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5641">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/11/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/11/2012</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01734733</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Open-label Investigation of the Safety and Clinical Effects of NTCELL in Patients With Parkinson's Disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase I/IIa, Open-label Investigation of the Safety and Clinical Effects of NTCELL [Immunoprotected (Alginate-Encapsulated) Porcine Choroid Plexus Cells for Xenotransplantation] in Patients With Parkinson's Disease</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>LCT/PD-012</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Parkinson's Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Parkinson's disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - NTCELL

Experimental: NTCELL - 


Other interventions: NTCELL


</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>the safety of xenotransplantation of NTCELL - measured by the incidence of adverse events, clinical laboratory tests (including xenogeneic viral analysis), physical examination, review by infectious disease physician</outcome>
      <timepoint>26 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Brain metabolism as demonstrated on PET with [18F]-fluorodopa measured at 26 weeks post-implant 1 compared with baseline</outcome>
      <timepoint>26 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Brain metabolism as demonstrated on PET with [11C]-tetrabenazine measured at 26 weeks post-implant 1 compared with baseline</outcome>
      <timepoint>26 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Scores measured by the Unified Parkinson's Disease Rating Scale (UPDRS Parts I, II, III, IV - Parts II and III will be performed in the 'off' and 'on' state) over 26 weeks post-implant 1 compared with the baseline scores</outcome>
      <timepoint>26 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Modified Hoehn and Yahr stages over 26 weeks post-implant 1 compared with the baseline stages</outcome>
      <timepoint>26 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Scores measured by the Unified Dyskinesia Rating Scale (UDysRS Parts I, II, III, IV - Parts III and IV will be performed in the 'off' and 'on' state) over 26 weeks post-implant 1 compared with the baseline scores</outcome>
      <timepoint>26 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Times for hand-arm movement between 2 points (tapping test) in accordance with the CAPSIT-PD protocol (Defer et al. 1999) over 26 weeks post-implant 1 compared with the baseline times</outcome>
      <timepoint>26 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Scores measured by the modified walking test in accordance with the CAPSIT-PD protocol (Defer et al. 1999) (walking 4.5m back and forth instead of 7m back and forth) over 26 weeks post-implant 1 compared with the baseline scores</outcome>
      <timepoint>26 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Scores measured by the Parkinson's Disease Questionnaire (PDQ-39) over 26 weeks post-implant 1 compared with the baseline scores</outcome>
      <timepoint>26 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Scores measured by neuropsychological tests at 26 weeks post-implant 1 compared with the baseline scores - TESTS USED
National Adult Reading Test
Speed and Capacity of Language Processing Test
Boston Naming Test
Trail Making Test A
Trail Making Test B
WMS IV Logical Memory I
WMS IV Logical Memory II
RAVLT List Learning
RAVLT Short Delay Recall
RAVLT Long Delay Recall
Rey Complex Figure Copy
Rey Complex Figure Delayed Recall
WAIS IV Digit Span
WAIS IV Matrix Reasoning
WAIS IV Symbol Search
WAIS IV Coding
DKEFS Word Fluency
DKEFS Category Fluency
DKEFS Category Switching
DKEFS Colour Naming
DKEFS Word Reading
DKEFS Inhibition
DKEFS Inhibition/switching
Mini Mental State Examination
Montreal Cognitive Assessment
HADS Anxiety
HADS Depression</outcome>
      <timepoint>26 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychiatric assessment at 26 weeks post-implant 1 compared with the baseline psychiatric assessment</outcome>
      <timepoint>26 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>To be assessed at the Week -10 to -4 Visit

          -  Adults (males or females) in the age range 40 to 70 years

          -  Diagnosis of Parkinson's disease (minimum duration of 5 years) in accordance with the
             London Brain Bank criteria

          -  Patients diagnosed with idiopathic Parkinson's disease

          -  Stable medication for Parkinson's for at least 1 month

          -  Patients with advanced and fluctuating Parkinson's disease who have met the criteria
             for DBS and who have been accepted for DBS at Auckland City Hospital. These criteria
             include exhaustion of available medication treatments for Parkinson's disease, normal
             brain MRI, intact cognitive, psychological and psychiatric function, appropriate carer
             support, and competence and willingness to consent to the placement of deep brain
             probes

          -  If female, no childbearing capability (those who are more than 2 years postmenopausal
             or have undergone voluntary sterilisation can be considered for enrolment)

          -  Provision of written informed consent. Patients will be required to agree to comply
             with all tests and visits specified in the protocol, and they (and their
             partners/close contacts) will also be required to consent to long-term microbiological
             monitoring, which is an integral part of the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>To be assessed at the Week -10 to -4 Visit

        Note: the criteria for acceptance for DBS would exclude patients with comorbidities that
        normally would exclude them from similar studies, including uncontrolled depression,
        dementia, focal neurological deficits, or secondary parkinsonism. Specific exclusion
        criteria in this category are:

          -  Any history of central nervous system infection

          -  Significant dementia as determined by neuropsychological assessment

          -  Focal neurological defects

          -  Evidence of significant medical or psychiatric disorders

          -  Secondary parkinsonism

          -  Severe autonomic symptoms

          -  Atypical Parkinson's disease

          -  History of substance abuse

          -  Body mass index (BMI) =30 kg/m2 or =20 kg/m2

          -  Serious comorbid conditions that are likely to affect participation in the study,
             including:

               -  Previous coronary heart disease manifesting as non-ST elevation myocardial
                  infarction (NSTEMI), Q-wave infarction or unstable angina; coronary artery bypass
                  graft (CABG); or percutaneous angioplasty

               -  Previous cerebrovascular disease manifesting as transient ischaemic attacks
                  (TIAs) or stroke

               -  Peripheral vascular disease with foot ulcer and/or previous amputation

               -  History of New York Heart Association (NYHA) class II, III or IV congestive heart
                  failure (CHF) and/or chronic atrial fibrillation

               -  Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) or asthma with previous
                  hospitalisation for decompensation; a requirement for mechanical ventilation at
                  any stage; or long-term treatment with oral corticosteroids

               -  Liver disease with abnormal liver function tests defined as serum bilirubin =20
                  µmol/L, and/or ALT =100 U/L, and/or GGT =100 U/L, and/or albumin &lt; 35 g/L

               -  Haematological disorders, including haemoglobin =110 g/L or platelet count &lt; 80 x
                  109/L

               -  Kidney disease, defined as serum creatinine &gt; 130 µmol/L in men and &gt; 110 µmol/L
                  in women and/or haematuria and/or active urinary sediment or casts

               -  Peptic ulcer disease and/or history of previous gastrointestinal bleeding

               -  Malignancy other than basal cell carcinoma

               -  History of epilepsy

               -  Untreated hypothyroidism

               -  Known adrenal insufficiency

        Other exclusion criteria:

          -  Past history of brain surgery for Parkinson's disease

          -  Poor candidate for any surgery

          -  HIV antibody and/or risk factors for HIV infection

          -  Positive hepatitis C antibody, positive hepatitis B surface antigen, and hepatitis B
             core antibody

          -  Current administration of immunosuppressive medications (e.g. cyclosporin, tacrolimus,
             sirolimus, mycophenolate mofetil, muromonab-CD3, daclizumab, basiliximab,
             antithymocyte globulin, interferons) for other disease conditions

          -  Inability to travel on aeroplane to Vancouver (for PET scan)

          -  Any other condition that, in the opinion of the Investigator, may interfere with
             adherence to the study protocol.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>4</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/06/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Living Cell Technologies</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To assess the safety of xenotransplantation of NTCELL [immunoprotected
      (alginate-encapsulated) choroid plexus cells] in patients with Parkinson's disease, assessed
      over the duration of the study, by monitoring the occurrence of adverse events and serious
      adverse events, including clinical and laboratory evidence of xenogeneic infection in
      transplant recipients and their partners/close contacts. Subsequent safety follow-up will
      include lifelong monitoring for clinical and laboratory evidence of xenogeneic infection.

      To assess the clinical effects of NTCELL [immunoprotected (alginate-encapsulated) choroid
      plexus cells] in patients with Parkinson's disease. This will be quantified by testing the
      secondary endpoints of the trial as described below (see Endpoints/Outcome Measures).</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01734733</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Barry Snow, MBChB</name>
      <address>Auckland City Hospital</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>