<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3582">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/06/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/06/2012</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01628354</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Study to Investigate the Safety and Efficacy of Ranibizumab in Patients With Choroidal Neovascularisation Due to Causes Other Than Age Related Macular Degeneration</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Study to Investigate the Safety and Efficacy of Lucentis (Ranibizumab) in Patients With CNV Due to Causes Other Than AMD and in Patients Where Pigment Epithelial Detachments Are the Primary Manifestation of Their AMD.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>RHG</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Choroidal Neovascularization</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Retinal Pigment Epithelial Detachment</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haematological diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other blood disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Ranibizumab

Treatment: drugs: Ranibizumab
All patients will receive an intravitreal injection of ranibizumab 0.5 mg at baseline (visit 1; month 0) then a subsequent intravitreal injection at month 1 (visit 2) and month 2 (Visit 3). Patients will be reviewed every month thereafter for 12 months at which time it will be determined whether the patient requires retreatment with ranibizumab 0.5 mg based on measurements of visual acuity, Optical coherene tomography (OCT) findings and clinical appearance. A drop of vision of &gt;5 letters or increase in retinal thickness of &gt;100 um on OCT will trigger re-treatment as long as 14 days has elapsed since last treatment.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean change from baseline in best corrected visual acuity</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean change from baseline in retinal thickness</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean number of ranibizumab injections required over 12 months</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ocular and systemic adverse events</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Patients presenting with choroidal neovascular membrane secondary to causes other than
             AMD or patients with Pigment epithelial detachments secondary to AMD where there is
             demonstrated progression of the disease.

          -  Total lesion area &lt; 12 disc areas.

          -  Total area of CNV within the lesion must be &gt; 50% of total lesion area in the first
             category of recruits, but not in those with PEDs.

          -  Best corrected visual acuity of 20/40 to 20/320 in the study eye.

          -  Willing and able to give informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Prior treatment in the study eye with, external-beam radiation therapy, subfoveal
             focal laser photocoagulation, vitrectomy, or transpupillary thermotherapy or other
             anti VEGF treatments.

          -  History of submacular surgery or other surgical intervention in the study eye,
             glaucoma filtration surgery, corneal transplant surgery,

          -  Laser photocoagulation (juxtafoveal or extrafoveal) in the study eye within one month
             preceding baseline,

          -  Extracapsular extraction of cataract with phacoemulsification within three months
             preceding baseline, or a history of post-operative complications within the last 12
             months preceding baseline in the study eye (uveitis, cyclitis, etc.),

          -  History of uncontrolled glaucoma in the study eye (defined as intraocular pressure =
             25 mmHg despite treatment with anti-glaucoma medication),

          -  Aphakia with absence of the posterior capsule in the study eye,

          -  Active intraocular inflammation (grade trace or above) in the study eye,

          -  Any active infection involving ocular adnexa including infectious conjunctivitis,
             keratitis, scleritis, endophthalmitis, as well as idiopathic or autoimmune-associated
             uveitis in either eye,

          -  Vitreous hemorrhage or history of rhegmatogenous retinal detachment or macular hole
             (Stage 3 or 4) in the study eye,

          -  Presence of a retinal pigment epithelial tear involving the macula in the study eye,

          -  Subfoveal fibrosis or atrophy in the study eye.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/02/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>49</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/04/2010</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Victorian Eye and Ear Hospital - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3002 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The investigators hypothesize that it is safe and effective to treat patients with choroidal
      neovascularisation (abnormal blood vessels growing under the retina) secondary to causes
      other than age related macular degeneration (AMD) and pigment epithelial detachments
      (blisters of fluid under the retina) secondary to AMD with ranibizumab (Lucentis).

      These groups of patients have to date been excluded from the multicentre trials demonstrating
      significant benefit of Ranibizumab in the treatment of AMD.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01628354</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Robyn H Guymer, PhD</name>
      <address>University of Melbourne</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>