<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3567">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/06/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/06/2012</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01617629</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Ovarian Cancer Vaccine for Patients Who Have Progressed During the CAN-003 Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An Open-Label Safety Trial of Cvac (Autologous Dendritic Cells Pulsed With Recombinant Human Fusion Protein Coupled to Oxidized Polymannose) for Epithelial Ovarian Cancer Patients Who Have Progressed During the CAN-003 Study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>CAN-003X</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>CAN-003X</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Epithelial Ovarian Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ovarian and primary peritoneal</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - MUC1 Dendritic Cell Vaccine (Cvac)

Experimental: Cvac Treatment Group - Patients will receive MUC1 Dendritic Cell Vaccine (Cvac) treatment.


Other interventions: MUC1 Dendritic Cell Vaccine (Cvac)
The recommended dosing regimen for CAN-003X is every 4 weeks for the first 3 doses and then every 12 weeks for 3 doses, for a total of 6 doses over 44 weeks (Regimen A, applicable to CAN-003 observational Standard of Care patients and CAN-003 Cvac patients that have progressed prior to the fourth dose of Cvac).
Patients who received more than 3 doses of Cvac in CAN-003 should continue with the CAN-003 dosing schedule (Regimen B; Cvac every 4 weeks for a total of 7 doses and then every 8 weeks for 3 doses, for a total of 10 doses over approximately 48 weeks)

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety will be measured through review of the number and type of adverse events associated with Cvac at all timepoints for each patient and across patients.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 Year of active dosing</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Female patients = 18 years old with histologically confirmed Stage III or IV
             epithelial ovarian, primary peritoneal, or fallopian tube cancer who were enrolled in
             CAN-003

          -  Able and willing to undergo MNC collection (if required for patients who do not have
             available Cvac doses)

          -  Were enrolled in CAN-003 and met protocol criteria for progressive disease

          -  Wish to remain in the study and, in the investigator's judgment, the potential benefit
             of Cvac treatment outweighs the risk

          -  Must be non-pregnant and, if of childbearing potential, must use adequate birth
             control (hormonal or barrier method of birth control or abstinence) for the duration
             of the study and for 3 months after study completion

          -  Able to provide written informed consent

          -  White blood cell count (WBC) = 3.0 K/µL, absolute neutrophil count = 1.5 K/µL,
             hemoglobin = 9.0 g/dL, and platelets =100,000/mm3</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Female</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Pregnant or breastfeeding

          -  Other medical conditions which preclude study participation, in the opinion of the
             investigator

          -  Receiving treatment with any other investigational product</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/12/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>9</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/04/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Greenslopes Private Hospital - Greenslopes</hospital>
    <postcode>4120 - Greenslopes</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Indiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Washington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Prima BioMed Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this trial is to assess the safety profile of Cvac for epithelial ovarian
      cancer patients who were enrolled in the Cvac clinical trial CAN-003 and are no longer
      eligible for study participation due to disease progression.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01617629</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Apostolopoulos V, McKenzie IF. Cellular mucins: targets for immunotherapy. Crit Rev Immunol. 1994;14(3-4):293-309. Review.
Apostolopoulos V, McKenzie IF, Pietersz GA. Breast cancer immunotherapy: current status and future prospects. Immunol Cell Biol. 1996 Oct;74(5):457-64. Review.
Desai J, Mitchell P, Loveland B, et al. A phase I trial of dendritic cells pulsed with MUC1 peptide in patients with solid tumours. Proc ASCO 2002; 21:15b (A1868).
Apostolopoulos V, Karanikas V, Haurum JS, McKenzie IF. Induction of HLA-A2-restricted CTLs to the mucin 1 human breast cancer antigen. J Immunol. 1997 Dec 1;159(11):5211-8.
Grossi M, Quinn MA, Thursfield VJ, Francis PA, Rome RM, Planner RS, Giles GG. Ovarian cancer: patterns of care in Victoria during 1993-1995. Med J Aust. 2002 Jul 1;177(1):11-6.
Jemal A, Siegel R, Ward E, Hao Y, Xu J, Murray T, Thun MJ. Cancer statistics, 2008. CA Cancer J Clin. 2008 Mar-Apr;58(2):71-96. doi: 10.3322/CA.2007.0010. Epub 2008 Feb 20.
Liu PY, Alberts DS, Monk BJ, Brady M, Moon J, Markman M. An early signal of CA-125 progression for ovarian cancer patients receiving maintenance treatment after complete clinical response to primary therapy. J Clin Oncol. 2007 Aug 20;25(24):3615-20.
Meyer T, Rustin GJ. Role of tumour markers in monitoring epithelial ovarian cancer. Br J Cancer. 2000 May;82(9):1535-8. Review.
Ozols RF, Rubin SC, Thomas G, et al. Epithelial ovarian cancer. In: Hoskins WJ, Perez CA, Young RC, eds. Principles and Practice of Gynecologic Oncology, 4th ed. Philadelphia: Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins. 2005:919-922.
Rustin GJ, Nelstrop AE, Bentzen SM, Bond SJ, McClean P. Selection of active drugs for ovarian cancer based on CA-125 and standard response rates in phase II trials. J Clin Oncol. 2000 Apr;18(8):1733-9.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Heidy Gray, MD</name>
      <address>University of Washington</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>