<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4535">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/07/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/07/2014</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02193555</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Visual Performance of Prototype Contact Lens Designs</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Visual Performance of Prototype Contact Lens Designs</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>CRTC2014-02</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Presbyopia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Refractive Error</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - Etafilcon A, Senofilcon A

Other: Non-presbyopic group - Non-presbyopic group: age ranging from 7 to 39 years
At each scheduled lens fitting visit, subjects will be allocated one pair of CLs to correct their refractive error. One pair of control (Acuvue 1- Day Moist, etafilcon A) or prototype (Iteration X, etafilcon A) CLs will be allocated for each lens fitting/assessment visit. Lenses will be worn for approximately 1 hour per visit.
For each fitting visit, lenses will be fitted bilaterally.

Other: Presbyopic group - Presbyopic group: age 40 and above
At each scheduled lens fitting visit, subjects will be allocated one pair of CLs to correct their refractive error. One pair of control (Acuvue Oasys for Presbyopia, senofilcon A) or prototype (Iteration X, etafilcon A) CLs will be allocated for each lens fitting/assessment visit. Lenses will be worn for approximately 1 hour per visit.
For each fitting visit, lenses will be fitted bilaterally.


Treatment: devices: Etafilcon A, Senofilcon A
1 pair of either test or control lenses will be fitted on the subject for up to 1 hour of lens wear per visit (total of 2 fitting visits).

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Visual performance - Visual acuity</outcome>
      <timepoint>After about 20 minutes of lens wear</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subjective responses - Subjective ratings of vision</outcome>
      <timepoint>After about 40 minutes of lens wear</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Able to read and comprehend English and give informed consent as demonstrated by
             signing a record of informed consent.

          -  Be at least 7 years old, male or female.

          -  Willing to comply with the wearing and clinical trial visit schedule as directed by
             the Investigator.

          -  Have ocular health findings considered to be "normal" and which would not prevent the
             participant from safely wearing contact lenses.

          -  Correctable to at least 6/12 (20/40) or better with both eyes with contact lenses.

          -  Be suitable and willing to wear contact lenses.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>7</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Any pre-existing ocular irritation, injury or condition (including infection or
             disease) of the cornea, conjunctiva or eyelids that would preclude contact lens
             fitting and safe wearing of contact lenses.

          -  Any systemic disease that adversely affects ocular health e.g. diabetes, Graves'
             disease, and auto immune diseases such as ankylosing spondylitis, multiple sclerosis,
             Sjögrens syndrome and systemic lupus erythematosus. Conditions such as systemic
             hypertension and arthritis do not automatically exclude prospective participants.

          -  Use of or a need for concurrent category S3 and above ocular medication at enrolment
             and/or during the clinical trial.

          -  Use of or a need for any systemic medication or topical medications which may alter
             normal ocular findings / are known to affect a participant's ocular health /
             physiology or contact lens performance either in an adverse or beneficial manner at
             enrolment and/or during the clinical trial.

          -  Eye surgery within 12 weeks immediately prior to enrolment for this trial.

        NB: Systemic antihistamines are allowed on an "as needed basis", provided they are not used
        prophylactically during the trial and at least 24 hours before the clinical trial product
        is used.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>91</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/11/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Brien Holden Vision Institute, Clinical Research Trials Center - Sydney</hospital>
    <postcode>2052 - Sydney</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Brien Holden Vision</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to assess the visual performance of prototype soft contact lens
      designs compared to a commercially available contact lens</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02193555</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Morgan PB, Efron N. A decade of contact lens prescribing trends in the United Kingdom (1996-2005). Cont Lens Anterior Eye. 2006 May;29(2):59-68. Epub 2006 Mar 31.
Stapleton F, Keay L, Edwards K, Naduvilath T, Dart JK, Brian G, Holden BA. The incidence of contact lens-related microbial keratitis in Australia. Ophthalmology. 2008 Oct;115(10):1655-62. doi: 10.1016/j.ophtha.2008.04.002. Epub 2008 Jun 5.
Anstice NS, Phillips JR. Effect of dual-focus soft contact lens wear on axial myopia progression in children. Ophthalmology. 2011 Jun;118(6):1152-61. doi: 10.1016/j.ophtha.2010.10.035. Epub 2011 Jan 26.
Sankaridurg P, Holden B, Smith E 3rd, Naduvilath T, Chen X, de la Jara PL, Martinez A, Kwan J, Ho A, Frick K, Ge J. Decrease in rate of myopia progression with a contact lens designed to reduce relative peripheral hyperopia: one-year results. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 2011 Dec 9;52(13):9362-7. doi: 10.1167/iovs.11-7260.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jiyoon Chung, BOptom</name>
      <address>Brien Holden Vision Institute</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>