<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6377">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/03/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/03/2014</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02080871</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Study of the Gore VIABAHN BX for Treatment of Occlusive Disease in the Iliac Arteries.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of the Gore(R) Viabahn(R) Balloon Expandable Endoprosthesis (VIABAHN BX) for the Treatment of Occlusive Disease in the Common and External Iliac Arteries.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>VBXFLEX</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>BES 10-07</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Peripheral Arterial Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - Stenting of the Common and/or External Iliac Arteries

Experimental: Iliac Stenting - Balloon expandable stenting of iliac occlusive disease


Treatment: devices: Stenting of the Common and/or External Iliac Arteries
Balloon expandable stenting of iliac occlusive disease.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite of Major Adverse Events (MAEs) - Composite of: Device or procedure-related death, Myocardial Infarction, Target Lesion Revascularization, and Amputation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>9 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acute Procedural Success - Defined as less than or equal to 30% residual stenosis prior to procedure completion and no device- or procedure-related SAEs before discharge.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>30-Day Clinical Success - Defined as an improvement of at least one Rutherford Category at the 30-day visit as compared to pre-procedure and no device- or procedure-related SAEs within 30 days of the index procedure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 Days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Patency - Defined as blood flow in the treated segment(s), without reintervention.</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 Days, 9 and 12 Months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Assisted Patency - Defined as blood flow maintained with or without reintervention in the originally treated segment(s).</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 Days, 9 and 12 Months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Patency - Defined as presence of blood flow, with or without reintervention, in the originally treated segment(s).</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 Days, 9 and 12 Months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Freedom from Target Lesion(s) Revascularization (TLR) - Defined as a revascularization occurring within the treated segment(s) by means of a percutaneous vascular intervention, surgical bypass, thrombolysis, or other invasive means.</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 Days and 9, 12, 24 and 36 Months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Freedom from Clinically-Driven Target Lesion Revascularization (CD-TLR) - Defined as revascularization occurring within the treated segment(s), with evidence of new ischemic signs (worsening of Rutherford Category from Baseline that is clearly referable to the target lesion) and target lesion diameter stenosis of &gt; 50% as determined by duplex ultrasound or angiography.</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 Days and 9, 12, 24 and 36 Months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Freedom from Target Vessel Revascularization (TVR) - Defined as a revascularization of the vessel treated at the time of the index procedure by means of a percutaneous vascular intervention, surgical bypass, thrombolysis, or other invasive means.</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 Days and 9, 12, 24 and 36 Months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Freedom from Clinically-Driven Target Vessel Revascularization (CD-TVR) - Defined as a revascularization of the vessel treated at the time of the index procedure with evidence of new ischemic signs (worsening of Rutherford Category from Baseline that is clearly referable to the target vessel) and target vessel stenosis &gt; 50% as determined by duplex ultrasound or angiography, or the lesion diameter stenosis is &gt; 70% in the absence of clinical or functional ischemia.</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 Days and 9, 12, 24 and 36 Months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Rutherford Category - Change in Rutherford Category from pre-procedure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 Days and 9, 12, 24 and 36 Months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Ankle Brachial Index (ABI) - Change in ABI from pre-procedure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 Days and 9, 12, 24 and 36 Months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Functional Status - Change in functional status from pre-procedure. This will be measured using the EQ-5D questionnaire and the Walking Impairment Questionnaire (WIQ).</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 Days and 9, 12, 24 and 36 Months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Patient is at least 18 years old;

          2. Patient is male, infertile female, or female of childbearing potential practicing an
             acceptable method of preventing pregnancy;

          3. Patient or legal representative is willing to give written informed consent;

          4. Patient is capable of complying with protocol requirements, including all follow-up
             visits;

          5. Patient has symptomatic claudication or rest pain without tissue loss (Rutherford
             Categories 2-4).

          6. Patient has de novo or restenotic target lesion(s) in the common and/or external iliac
             artery;

          7. Patient has one or more regions of stenosis = 50% in the target vessel, based on
             visual estimate;

          8. Patient has a target vessel diameter visually estimated to be approximately between 5
             mm and 13 mm;

          9. Patient has adequate ipsilateral blood flow including at least one sufficient (&lt;50%
             stenotic) infrapopliteal run-off vessel not requiring intervention (per side to be
             intervened on).

         10. Patient has a total target lesion length visually estimated to be =110 mm which can be
             treated with a maximum of three VIABAHN BX endoprostheses;

         11. Patient has no more than two discrete ipsilateral lesions that can be treated with no
             more than three VIABAHN BX endoprostheses [OR] Patient has bilateral disease
             consisting of only one target lesion per side that can be treated with no more than a
             total of three VIABAHN BX endoprostheses;

         12. Patient has the device advanced across the target lesion(s) and positioned for
             deployment.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Patient has a life expectancy of less than 1 year;

          2. Patient has a known allergy to stent graft components, including stainless steel or
             heparin;

          3. Patient has a known intolerance to antiplatelet, anticoagulant, or thrombolytic
             medications that would prevent compliance with the protocol;

          4. Patient has a condition (unrelated to the study) that is expected to require
             indefinite, or lifelong, anticoagulation

          5. Patient has an uncorrected bleeding disorder (platelet count &lt; 80,000/µL);

          6. Patient has severe chronic renal insufficiency (serum creatinine level &gt; 2.5mg/dL) and
             not on hemodialysis;

          7. Patient has a known hypercoagulability that cannot be corrected;

          8. Patient has evidence of a blood borne infection;

          9. Patient has had vascular access/catheterization in the lower extremity within 30 days
             of study enrollment;

         10. Patient has had a previous or planned coronary intervention within 30 days prior to
             enrollment in this study or required at time of study procedure;

         11. Patient has had a previous or planned bypass surgery in the target leg, or a bypass
             that occurs at the time of the index procedure;

         12. Patient is currently participating in this or another investigative clinical study.

         13. Patient has a stent or stent graft located within or immediately adjacent (=5mm) to
             study lesion(s);

         14. Patient has evidence of angiographically visible thrombus within or adjacent to the
             target lesion(s);

         15. Patient has aneurysmal dilation proximal or distal to the target lesion(s) that would
             interfere with the placement of the device;

         16. Patient has a target lesion requiring atherectomy or any ablative device to facilitate
             stent delivery;

         17. Patient has a target lesion situated in such a way that an implanted device will
             prevent blood flow or perfusion to the internal iliac artery if patent.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>134</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/08/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Arizona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Connecticut</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>District of Columbia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Illinois</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Iowa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Kentucky</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Minnesota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Jersey</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Dakota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Pennsylvania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Rhode Island</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>South Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Tennessee</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Virginia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>W.L.Gore &amp; Associates</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Evaluation of the Gore(R) VIABAHN BX for the treatment of arterial occlusive disease in the
      common and/or external iliac arteries.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02080871</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jean Bismuth, MD</name>
      <address>The Methodist Hospital System</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>