<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="1704">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/10/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/10/2007</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00538057</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparing Two Respiratory Drugs When Used In Combination And Separately From A Novel Inhaler Device In Healthy Subjects</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomised, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled, Four-way Crossover Study to Compare the Pharmacodynamics and Pharmacokinetics of GW685698X and GW642444M When Administered Separately and in Combination as a Single Dose From a Novel Dry Powder Device in Healthy Subjects</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>HZA105871</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Asthma</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - GW685698X &amp; GW642444M

Experimental: arm 1 - study drug


Treatment: drugs: GW685698X &amp; GW642444M
study drug

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximum heart rate</outcome>
      <timepoint>over 4 hours after dosing.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure</outcome>
      <timepoint>changes over 12 hours.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Electrocardiogram</outcome>
      <timepoint>changes over 12 hours.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in peak expiry flow rate</outcome>
      <timepoint>changes over 24 hours.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in serum cortisol concentration</outcome>
      <timepoint>changes over 24 hours.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in plasma drug concentration (AUC, Cmax, t1/2, tmax)</outcome>
      <timepoint>over 48 hours after dosing.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in blood potassium levels</outcome>
      <timepoint>within 4 hours of drug dosing.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean heart rate</outcome>
      <timepoint>over 4 hours after dosing</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria:

          -  Healthy adults aged between 18 and 60 years.

          -  Male subjects or female subjects of non child bearing potential.

          -  Body weight at least 50 kg and BMI within the range of 19-31 kg/m2 inclusive.

          -  No significant abnormality from ECG at screening.

          -  FEV1 at least 90% predicted and FEV1 / FVC ratio at least 0.7 at screening.

          -  Current non-smokers who have not used any tobacco products in the 12 month period
             preceding the screening visit and have a pack history of equal to or less than 5 pack
             years.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria:

          -  Systolic blood pressure above 145 mmHg or a diastolic pressure above 85 mmHg unless
             the Investigator confirms that it is satisfactory for their age.

          -  The subject has been treated for or diagnosed with depression within six months of
             screening or has a history of significant psychiatric illness.

          -  Subjects who have suffered an upper or lower respiratory tract infection within 4
             weeks of the screening visit.

          -  Liver function tests (AST, ALT or ALP) greater than 1.5 of the upper limit of
             laboratory reference range.

          -  History of sensitivity to any of the study medications, or components thereof or a
             history of drug or other allergy that, in the opinion of the physician responsible,
             contraindicates their participation.

          -  History of milk protein allergy.

          -  The subject has taken prescription or non-prescription drugs, including vitamins,
             herbal and dietary supplements (including St John's Wort) within 7 days (or 14 days if
             the drug is a potential enzyme inducer) or 5 half-lives (whichever is the longer)
             prior to the first dose of study medication, unless in the opinion of the Investigator
             and Sponsor the medication will not interfere with the study procedures or compromise
             subject safety.

          -  The subject has taken oral corticosteroids less than 8 weeks before the screening
             visit

          -  The subject has taken inhaled, intranasal or topical steroids less than 4 weeks before
             the screening visit

          -  History of alcohol/drug abuse or dependence within 12 months of the study.

          -  The subject has participated in a clinical trial and has received a drug or a new
             chemical entity within 30 days or 5 half-lives, or twice the duration of the
             biological effect of any drug (whichever is longer) prior to the first dose of current
             study medication.

          -  Exposure to more than four new chemical entities within 12 months prior to the first
             dosing day.

          -  The subject has donated a unit (450mL) of blood within the previous 16 weeks or
             intends to donate within 16 weeks after completing the study.

          -  A positive pre-study Hepatitis B surface antigen or positive Hepatitis C antibody
             result within 3 months of screening.

          -  The subject has tested positive for HIV antibodies.

          -  The subject has a positive pre-study urine drug screen.

          -  Positive CO or alcohol breath test at screening or on admission to the Unit.

          -  History of any adverse reaction including immediate or delayed hypersensitivity to any
             ICS, ß2-agonist or sympathomimetic drug. gefitinib or erlotinib) is permitted. Use of
             bevacizumab must have ended at least 40 days prior to date of first dose of study
             drug.

          -  Any anti-cancer therapy (surgery, tumor embolization, chemotherapy, radiation therapy,
             immunotherapy, biological therapy, or hormonal therapy) currently or within 14 days
             prior to date of first dose of study drug.

          -  Any ongoing toxicity from prior anti-cancer therapy that is greater than Grade 1
             and/or that is progressing in severity.

          -  Known immediate or delayed hypersensitivity reaction or idiosyncracy to drugs
             chemically related to pazopanib.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>2/10/2007</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>16</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/12/2007</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Randwick, Sydney</hospital>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick, Sydney</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>GlaxoSmithKline</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A combination of the corticosteroid GW685698X and the long-acting ß2-agonist GW642444M is
      being developed for once daily administration for the maintenance treatment of asthma and
      COPD. GW642444M and GW685698X will be simultaneously co-administered from a single device and
      compared with GW642444M and GW685698X administered separately in order to determine whether
      co-administration affects the safety, tolerability, pharmacodynamic and/or pharmacokinetics
      of either compound.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00538057</trialwebsite>
    <publication>This study has not been published in the scientific literature.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>GSK Clinical Trials</name>
      <address>GlaxoSmithKline</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>