<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3702">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/11/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/11/2012</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01743521</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>DAA Based Therapy for Recently Acquired Hepatitis C (DARE-C)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Direct Acting Antiviral (DAA) Based Therapy for Recently Acquired Hepatitis C</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>DARE-C</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>VX-950HCP4010</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>VHCRP1102</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hepatitis C, Chronic</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - TPV/PEG-IFN/RBV

Experimental: Group A - 8 weeks total therapy - 8 weeks total therapy of TPV/PEG-IFN/RBV if undetectable HCV RNA after 2 weeks of therapy

Experimental: Group B - 12 weeks total therapy - 12 weeks total therapy of TPV/PEG-IFN/RBV if undetectable HCV RNA after 4 weeks of therapy

Experimental: Group C - 24 weeks total therapy - 24 weeks total therapy - TPV/PEG-IFN/RBV for 12 weeks + PEG-IFN/RBV for 12 weeks if undetectable HCV RNA after 8 weeks of therapy


Treatment: drugs: TPV/PEG-IFN/RBV
Drug Telaprevir (TPV): dosed 1125mg twice daily (given as three 375 mg film-coated tablets) orally, except in the situation where a patient is on efavirenz in which case the dose of telaprevir will be 1125mg three times daily.
Drug Ribavirin (RBV): 1000mg or 1200mg p.o daily in split doses (1000mg for patients weighing &lt;75kg and 1200mg for patients weighing = 75kg).
Drug PEG-IFN (other name: Pegasys): 180mcg in 0.5ml (pre-filled syringes) administered subcutaneously once weekly.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>SVR12 (Sustain Virological Response, HCV RNA Undetectable 12 Weeks Post-treatment) - Proportion of subjects achieving SVR 12 (negative qualitative HCV RNA 12 weeks after therapy completion)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks post-treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>SVR24 - To evaluate the proportion of patients with undetectable HCV RNA 24 weeks after therapy completion (SVR24)</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 weeks post-treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Undetectable HCV RNA (ETR) - To evaluate the proportion of patients with undetectable HCV RNA at end of treatment (ETR)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Wk 8 (Group A), Wk 12 (Group B), Wk 24 (Group C)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Undetectable HCV RNA (Week 1) - To evaluate the proportion of patients with undetectable HCV RNA at week 1 of therapy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 1 of therapy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Undectectable HCV RNA (Week 2) - To evaluate the proportion of patients with undetectable HCV RNA at week 1 of therapy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 2 of therapy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Undetectable HCV RNA (Week 3) - To evaluate the proportion of patients with undetectable HCV RNA at week 3 of therapy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 3 of therapy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Undetectable HCV RNA (Week 4) - To evaluate the proportion of patients with undetectable HCV RNA at week 4 of therapy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 4 of therapy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Decrease in Absolute Neutrophil Count (ANC) =0.75</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Wk 8 (Group A), Wk 12 (Group B), Wk 24 (Group C)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Decrease in Platelets &lt;50</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Wk 8 (Group A), Wk 12 (Group B), Wk 24 (Group C)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Hemoglobin at End of Treatment - To evaluate indicators of toxicity during telaprevir based therapy</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Wk 8 (Group A), Wk 12 (Group B), Wk 24 (Group C)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resistance-associated Variants - To examine the emergence of resistance-associated variants during telaprevir based therapy for early chronic infection</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Wk 8 (Group A), Wk 12 (Group B), Wk 24 (Group C)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Baseline Resistance-associated Variants - To correlate the presence and frequency of baseline resistance-associated variants (RAVs) with the response of Telaprevir based therapy for early chronic HCV infection.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Wk 8 (Group A), Wk 12 (Group B), Wk 24 (Group C)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma Ribavirin Levels - To correlate plasma ribavirin levels with treatment outcome and changes in haemoglobin during therapy</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Wk 8 (Group A), Wk 12 (Group B), Wk 24 (Group C)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>CD4 and HIV RNA - In HIV positive participants to evaluate changes in CD4 counts and HIV RNA during telaprevir based therapy</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Wk 8 (Group A), Wk 12 (Group B), Wk 24 (Group C)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gene IL28B Polymorphism - To examine treatment outcome by IL28B polymorphism</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Provision of written, informed consent.

          2. HCV genotype 1 infection

          3. Quantifiable HCV RNA at screening and baseline (&gt;10,000 IU/ml)

          4. Recent hepatitis C infection with an estimated duration of Infection &gt;6 months and =
             18 months defined as A) i) First anti-HCV antibody or HCV RNA positive within the
             previous 6 months and ii) Documented anti-HCV antibody negative or HCV RNA negative
             within the 24 months prior to anti-HCV antibody positive result OR B) i) First
             anti-HCV antibody or HCV RNA positive within the previous 6 months and ii) acute
             clinical hepatitis (jaundice or ALT&gt; 10 X ULN) within the 12 months prior to first
             positive HCV antibody or HCV RNA with no other cause of acute hepatitis identifiable

          5. Compensated liver disease (Child-Pugh A)

          6. Negative pregnancy test at screening and 24 hours prior to the first dose of study
             drugs.

          7. If heterosexually active, a female subject of childbearing potential and a
             nonvasectomized male subject who has a female partner of childbearing potential must
             agree to use 2 effective contraceptives from screening onwards until 6 months (female
             subject) or 7 months (male subject) after RBV therapy has ended. Note: Hormonal
             contraceptives may be continued but may not be reliable during telaprevir dosing and
             for 2 months following cessation of telaprevir. Therefore, subjects should agree to
             use 2 effective non-hormonal methods of contraception during telaprevir combination
             therapy and for 2 months after the last intake of telaprevir. As of two months after
             completion of telaprevir hormonal contraceptives can again be used as one of the two
             required effective methods of birth control.

          8. Subject is judged to be medically stable on the basis of physical examination, medical
             history and vital signs.

          9. Adequate English to provide written, informed consent and to provide reliable
             responses to the study interview

        Additional inclusion criteria for HIV positive individuals

          -  Confirmed HIV infection &gt; 6 months duration

          -  CD4 &gt; 200 cells/mm3 and HIV &lt; 50 c/ml on stable antiretroviral therapy (ART) at least
             3 months prior to treatment

          -  Or

          -  CD4 &gt;= 500 cells/mm3 and HIV viral load (VL) &lt; 100,000 not on ART

          -  If on ART must be taking a regimen containing an accepted* combination of the
             following drugs: tenofovir ( TDF), lamivudine ( 3TC), emtricitabine (FTC), efavirenz
             (EFV), abacavir (ABC), raltegravir (RAL), etravirine (ETV), rilpivirine (RIL),
             ritonavir boosted atazanavir (r/ATZ) * Combination must be supported by current HIV
             treatment guidelines</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Individuals considered by the study investigators to be unlikely to participate in
             intensive follow-up and/or unwilling to provide extra blood samples

          -  Current injecting drug use (any injecting within previous 4 weeks)

          -  Standard exclusions to Pegylated-interferon (PEG-IFN), Ribavirin (RBV) and Telaprevir
             (TPV) therapy</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/01/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>14</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/01/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital - Sydney</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>2010 - Sydney</postcode>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Kirby Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Janssen-Cilag Ltd.</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To examine the safety and efficacy of response guided triple therapy (PEG-IFN, Ribavirin,
      Telaprevir) for the treatment of early chronic Hepatitis C Virus (HCV) infection.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01743521</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Gail Matthews, MbChB, PhD</name>
      <address>Kirby Institute</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>