<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3655">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/10/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/10/2012</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01700647</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Breath Testing in Early and Late Larynx Cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Breath Testing in Laryngeal Cancer- Comparing in Situ Cancer and Advanced Cancer</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>HREC/11/QRBW/471</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Larynx Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Head and neck</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - Breath test- sampling using ENose
Other interventions - Laryngoscopy and bronchoscopy

smoking controls - patients referred for bronchoscopy who have detailed axamination and do not have any dysplasia proven by bronchoscopy and laryngoscopy Breath test- sampling using ENose

In Situ carcinoma larynx - Biopsy proven in situ carcinoma larynx proven by laryngoscopy and bronchoscopy Breath test- sampling using ENose

Advanced Larynx Cancer - Biopsy proven stage 3/4 larynx cancer proven by laryngoscopy and bronchoscopy Breath test- sampling using ENose


Other interventions: Breath test- sampling using ENose
Patients give a sample of breath ( slow vital capacity breath, collected in Tedlar bag and immediately analysed and discarded)

Other interventions: Laryngoscopy and bronchoscopy
Detailed assessment of larynx and bronchus mucosa including autofluoresecence to fully define dysplasias if present or exclude them.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Difference in breath test signal for diagnosis - Statistical differences can be obtained using software in the Enose- Mahlobinis distance after Principle component analysis of breath signals to separate controls from in situ cancer and from advanced cancer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Individual VOCs identified by MSGC - Samples of breath will be analysed for differences in abundance of individual VOCs</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  those with known larynx cancer (either in situ or advanced)

          -  patients with smoking history referred for bronchoscopy or laryngoscopy</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  other solid tumours

          -  inability to undergo bronchoscopy/laryngoscopy</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/10/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>30</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/10/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane and Womens Hospital - Brisbane</hospital>
    <postcode>4029 - Brisbane</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>It is possible to test a sample of breath from a patient, run it through a machine, and find
      out certain diseases in the patient without needing to do Xrays. It is sort of like
      a"breathalyser".In the future it is hoped this type of testing will be common, and allow
      certain conditions to be picked up early. One of these conditions is Cancer of the Larynx
      (voice box). It is not in wide use yet however a study has shown it is very effective in
      detecting Larynx cancer.

      This breath test has detected cancers at a stage when they CAN be seen on Xrays or looking in
      with cameras. However the larger the cancer ultimately the worse it is for the patient. It
      would therefore be much better to have the breath test find patients with cancers at a much
      smaller size. It is interesting that the cancers which the breath test HAVE found all have
      the same breath test signal, regardless of size. This means even smaller cancers may have the
      same signal. These small cancers are only 1-2 mm thick, and when found at this size almost
      all can be cured. We want to find a group of patients who have these early cancers and
      compare it to breath test result in patients who have large obvious cancers. These patients
      will be compared to other patients who have are negative for larynx cancer who also have a
      breath test. We want to prove that their breath test will be negative.

      You have been referred either because you have symptoms (such as cough or hoarse voice) and
      need a scope to look into the airways, OR your specialist has identified a spot on the larynx
      which needs a biopsy (sample) and then possible treatment, The spot may or may not be cancer-
      that is why the biopsy is needed. After that the correct treatment would be considered
      depending on the result, that is, whether it is a cancer or not. If possible we would like to
      take a test of your breath before the biopsy. Alternatively we can take a breath test 2 weeks
      after a biopsy.

      In summary this study is trying to show whether the breath test is the same in patients who
      have large cancers as patients with small cancers invisible on XRay and only found with
      careful magnification by scopes looking in. If we can show these findings it will demonstrate
      great potential for the breath test to find many more cancers which are truly curable.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01700647</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Hakim M, Billan S, Tisch U, Peng G, Dvrokind I, Marom O, Abdah-Bortnyak R, Kuten A, Haick H. Diagnosis of head-and-neck cancer from exhaled breath. Br J Cancer. 2011 May 10;104(10):1649-55. doi: 10.1038/bjc.2011.128. Epub 2011 Apr 19.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>David I Fielding, FRACP MD</name>
      <address>Royal Brisbane and Womens Hospital</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>