<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3784">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/01/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/01/2013</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01777269</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Prospective Sexual Function Study for BPH Subjects</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Prospective Study of Sexual Function in Sexually Active Men Treated for BPH</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>2012-002047-26</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>116115</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Prostatic Hyperplasia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other renal and urogenital disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Dutasteride plus tamsulosin
Treatment: drugs - Placebo

Experimental: Duodart - Fixed dose combination of dutasteride 0.5mg and tamsulosin 0.4mg. A capsule once daily during 12 months

Placebo Comparator: Sugar Pill - A capsule once daily during 12 months


Treatment: drugs: Dutasteride plus tamsulosin
Take 1 capsule daily

Treatment: drugs: Placebo
Take one capsule daily

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes From Baseline (BL) in Total Score From the Full Men's Sexual Health Questionnaire (MSHQ) at 12 Months - Total MSHQ score is composed of 3 domain scores: Erection score(ES)=sum of score for Questions (Q) 1 to 3(ranges from 0 to 15), Ejaculation score(EjS)=sum of scores for Q5 to 11(ranges from 1 to 35), Satisfaction score(SS)=sum of scores for Q13 to 18(ranges from 6 to 30). Total MSHQ score=ES+EjS+SS. The total MSHQ score ranges from 7-80, with higher scores indicating greater sexual function. Change from BL at scheduled post-BL time points were analyzed using a mixed model repeated measures (MMRM) analysis method with an Observed Cases approach. Values are expressed as adjusted mean along with standard error. The MMRM analysis included fixed categorical effects of treatment, visit and treatment by visit interaction and the continuous fixed covariates of BL total score and BL score by visit interaction. BL is defined as earliest double-blind (DB) treatment start date if the par. took at least one dose of DB study drug; change from BL was calculated as Month 12 value(s) minus BL value(s)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Scores From the Full Men's Sexual Health Questionnaire (MSHQ) at 1, 3, 6 and 9 Months - Total MSHQ score is composed of 3 domain scores: ES=sum of score for Q 1 to 3(ranges from 0 to 15), EjS=sum of scores for Q5 to 11(ranges from 1 to 35), SS=sum of scores for Q13 to 18(ranges from 6 to 30). Total MSHQ score=ES+EjS+SS and the score ranges from 7-80, with higher scores indicating greater sexual function. Change from BL at scheduled post-BL time points were analysed using MMRM analysis method with an Observed Cases approach. Values are expressed as adjusted mean along with standard error. The MMRM analysis included fixed categorical effects of treatment, visit and treatment by visit interaction and the continuous fixed covariates of BL total score and BL score by visit interaction. BL is defined as earliest DB treatment start date if the par. took at least one dose of DB study drug; change from BL was calculated as Month 1, 3, 6, 9 values minus BL value(s). Only those par with non-missing change from baseline data were analysed (presented as n=X,X in the category titles)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Month 1, 3, 6, and 9</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants Reaching Various Thresholds of Change in Total MSHQ From Baseline at 12 Months - Participants reaching thresholds of change in total MSHQ were assessed. Threshold values are defined as multiplicative factor. Threshold included +10 points, +20 points, +25 points, -10 points, -20 points, -25 points; where "+" indicates improvement and "-"indicates worsening. Treatment comparisons were done based on categories defined by these thresholds using Mantel-Haenszel test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Erectile Dysfunction (ED) at 1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 Months - Erection scale is a domain of MSHQ to assess erectile dysfunction. ES is the sum of score for questions 1 to 3. The score ranges from 0 (no erection) to 15 (strong erection). Change from BL at the scheduled post-baseline time points were analyzed using MMRM analysis method with an Observed Cases approach. Values are expressed as adjusted mean along with standard error. The MMRM analysis included fixed categorical effects of treatment, visit and treatment by visit interaction and the continuous fixed covariates of BL total score and BL score by visit interaction. BL is defined as earliest DB treatment start date if the par. took at least one dose of DB study drug; change from BL was calculated as Month 1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 values minus BL value(s). Only those par with non-missing change from baseline data were analysed (presented as n=X,X in the category titles)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Month 1, 3, 6, 9 and 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Ejaculatory Dysfunction (EjD) at 1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 Months - Ejaculation scale is a domain of MSHQ to assess ejaculatory dysfunction. EjS is the sum of score for questions 5 to 11. The score ranges from 1 (could not ejaculate) to 35 (strong ejaculation). Change from BL at the scheduled post-baseline time points were analyzed using MMRM analysis method with an Observed Cases approach. Values are expressed as adjusted mean along with standard error. The MMRM analysis included fixed categorical effects of treatment, visit and treatment by visit interaction and the continuous fixed covariates of BL total score and BL score by visit interaction. BL is defined as earliest DB treatment start date if the par. took at least one dose of DB study drug; change from BL was calculated as Month 1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 values minus BL value(s). Only those par with non-missing change from baseline data were analysed (presented as n=X,X in the category titles)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Month 1, 3, 6, 9 and 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Satisfaction Score at 1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 Months - Satisfaction scale is a domain of MSHQ to assess sexual relationship. SS is the sum of score for questions 13 to 18. The score ranges from 6 (extremely dissatisfied) to 30 (extremely satisfied). Change from BL at the scheduled post-baseline time points were analyzed using MMRM analysis method with an Observed Cases approach. Values are expressed as adjusted mean along with standard error. The MMRM analysis included fixed categorical effects of treatment, visit and treatment by visit interaction and the continuous fixed covariates of BL total score and BL score by visit interaction. BL is defined as earliest DB treatment start date if the par. took at least one dose of DB study drug; change from BL was calculated as Month 1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 values minus BL value(s). Only those par with non-missing change from baseline data were analysed (presented as n=X,X in the category titles)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Month 1, 3, 6, 9 and 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in International Prostate Symptom Score (IPSS) Scores Using the Observed Cases Approach at 2 Weeks, 1, 3, 6, 9, and 12 Months - The IPSS questionnaire is a 7-item self-administered questionnaire designed to quantify urinary symptoms: Q1, incomplete emptying; Q2, frequency; Q3, intermittency; Q4, urgency; Q5, weak stream; Q6, straining; Q7, nocturia. The score can range from 0 to 35: mild (0 to 7), moderate (8 to 19), or severe (20 to 35). Change from BL were analyzed using MMRM analysis method with an Observed Cases approach. Values are expressed as adjusted mean along with standard error. The MMRM analysis included fixed categorical effects of treatment, visit and treatment by visit interaction and the continuous fixed covariates of BL total score and BL score by visit interaction. BL is defined as earliest DB treatment start date if the par. took at least one dose of DB study drug; change from BL was calculated as Week 2, Months 1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 values minus BL value(s). Only those par with non-missing change from baseline data were analysed (presented as n=X,X in the category titles)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Month 1, 3, 6, 9 and 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Quality of Life (BPH Impact Index -BII Scores) at 2 Weeks, 1, 3, 6, 9, and 12 Months - The BPH Impact Index (BII) is a 4-item, self-administered questionnaire evaluating the impact of urinary problems on overall health and activity. Total scores range from 0 to 13; higher scores represent increased perceived impact of benign prostatic hyperplasia-lower urinary tract symptoms on overall health. Change from BL were analyzed using MMRM analysis method with an Observed Cases approach. Values are expressed as adjusted mean along with standard error. The MMRM analysis included fixed categorical effects of treatment, visit and treatment by visit interaction and the continuous fixed covariates of BL total score and BL score by visit interaction. BL is defined as earliest DB treatment start date if the subject took at least one dose of DB study drug; change from BL was calculated as Week 2, Months 1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 values minus BL value(s). Only those par with non-missing change from baseline data were analysed (presented as n=X,X in the category titles)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Month 1, 3, 6, 9 and 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Perception of Treatment Benefit/Satisfaction With Treatment (Patient Perception of Study Medication - PPSM Questionnaire Scores) at 2 Weeks, 1, 3, 6, 9, and 12 Months - Patient Perception of Study Medication (PPSM) is a 12-item questionnaire designed to quantify the participant's perceptions and satisfaction with the effect of study treatment on control of their urinary symptoms. The total PPSM score ranges from 7 to 49, with higher scores indicating lower satisfaction. Change from BL were analyzed using MMRM analysis method with an Observed Cases approach. Values are expressed as adjusted mean along with standard error. The MMRM analysis included fixed categorical effects of treatment, visit and treatment by visit interaction and the continuous fixed covariates of BL total score and BL score by visit interaction. BL is defined as earliest DB treatment start date if the subject took at least one dose of DB study drug; change from BL was calculated as Week 2, Months 1, 3, 6, 9, 12 values minus BL value(s). Only those par with non-missing change from baseline data were analysed (presented as n=X,X in the category titles)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 2, Month 1, 3, 6, 9 and 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Total MSHQ Scores From Baseline at 12 Months Among Participants With IPSS Improvement of &gt;=2 Points and &gt;=3 Points - Total MSHQ score is composed of 3 domain scores: ES+EjS+SS and the score ranges from 7-80, with higher scores indicating greater sexual function. Par. with change from baseline in total MSHQ scores with good BPH symptomatic response (measured by improvement in IPSS)were analysed. Change from BL at the scheduled post-baseline time points were analyzed using MMRM analysis method with an Observed Cases approach. Values are expressed as adjusted mean along with standard error. The MMRM analysis included fixed categorical effects of treatment, visit and treatment by visit interaction and the continuous fixed covariates of BL total score and BL score by visit interaction. BL is defined as earliest DB treatment start date if the par. took at least one dose of DB study drug; change from BL was calculated as Month 12 value(s) minus BL value(s). Only those par with non-missing change from baseline data were analysed (presented as n=X,X in the category titles)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Month 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Total MSHQ Scores From Baseline at 12 Months Among Participants With IPSS Improvement of &gt;=25 Percent - Participants with change from baseline in total MSHQ scores with good BPH symptomatic response (measured by improvement in IPSS)were analysed.Change from BL at the scheduled post-baseline time points were analyzed using MMRM analysis method with an Observed Cases approach. Values are expressed as adjusted mean along with standard error. The MMRM analysis included fixed categorical effects of treatment, visit and treatment by visit interaction and the continuous fixed covariates of BL total score and BL score by visit interaction. BL is defined as earliest DB treatment start date if the par. took at least one dose of DB study drug; change from BL was calculated as Month 12 value(s) minus BL value(s). Only those par with non-missing change from baseline data were analysed (presented as n=X,X in the category titles)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Month 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Males aged =50 years.

          -  Men must be sexually active. A man is considered sexually active if he has been
             engaged in sexual activity with a partner during the past 4 weeks (at least once) and
             plans to be active during the next 4 weeks (unless due to travel or other practical
             reasons). Men should confirm that they are in a stable relationship and expect to
             maintain their sexual activity over the next year.

          -  A confirmed clinical diagnosis of BPH.

          -  International Prostate Symptom Score (IPSS) =12 at Visit 1 (screening), with bother
             score 4 or less (score from the IPSS Quality of Life question 8).

          -  Prostate volume =30 cc (by transrectal ultrasonography; TRUS). Measurement should be
             available by the baseline visit and should have been made /arranged at the screening
             visit or within the previous 6 months.

          -  Total serum prostate specific antigen (PSA =1.5 ng/mL (see exclusion criteria 1) at
             Visit 1 (screening).

          -  Willing and able to give signed written informed consent and comply with study
             procedures, including the ability to participate in the study for the full 1 year (or
             18 months if necessary because of a persistent sexual AE).

          -  Fluent and literate in local language with the ability to read, comprehend and record
             information on the MSHQ, IPSS, PPSM, BPH Impact Index (BII) and C-SSRS questionnaires.

          -  Able to swallow and retain oral medication.

          -  Men with a female partner of childbearing potential must either agree to use effective
             contraception or have had a prior vasectomy. Contraception must be used from 2 weeks
             prior to administration of the first dose of study treatment until at least 5
             half-lives for the drug (45 days) plus 3 months (i.e. a total of 4.5 months) to allow
             clearance of any altered sperm after the last dose of study treatment.

          -  French subjects: In France, a subject will be eligible for inclusion in this study
             only if either affiliated to or a beneficiary of a social security category.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Male</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Total serum PSA &gt;10.0 ng/mL at Visit 1 (screening).

          -  History or evidence of prostate cancer (e.g. positive biopsy or ultrasound, suspicious
             DRE and/or rising PSA). Subjects with suspicious ultrasound or DRE who have had a
             negative biopsy within the preceding 6 months and stable PSA are eligible for the
             study.

        Note: If total serum PSA is &gt;4ng/mL and unless PSA value has been stable for at least the
        past 2 years, the investigator should make every appropriate effort to exclude the
        possibility of prostate cancer, including consideration of prostate biopsy.

        Excluded medication and therapies

          -  Current or prior use (within the periods given) of the following prohibited
             medications

          -  Any prior use of a 5a-reductase inhibitor (finasteride or dutasteride),

          -  Anti-cholinergics (e.g. oxybutynin, propantheline, tolerodine, solifenacin or
             darifenacin) within 1 month prior to visit 2 (baseline)

          -  An alpha-adrenoreceptor blocker (i.e. indoramin, prazosin, terazosin, tamsulosin,
             alfuzosin and doxazosin) within 1 month prior to visit 2 (baseline)

          -  Use of any drugs with anti-androgenic properties (e.g. spironolactone, flutamide,
             bicalutamide, cimetidine, ketoconazole, progestational agents) within the 6 months
             prior to visit 1 (screening).

          -  Use of any drugs noted for propensity to cause gynaecomastia, or which could affect
             prostate volume, within 6 months prior to Visit 1 (screening).

          -  Use of any investigational or marketed study drug within 30 days or 5 half-lives of
             the drug in question, (whichever is longer), preceding visit 2 (baseline).

          -  Current use (at the baseline visit or within the prior 1month) of:

          -  PDE-5 inhibitors for Erectile Dysfunction.

          -  Anabolic steroids.

          -  Drugs known or thought to have an interaction with tamsulosin, e.g. cimetidine and
             warfarin.

          -  Use of phytotherapy for BPH within 2 weeks prior to Visit 1 (screening) and/or
             predicted to need phytotherapy during the study.

          -  History of a known (immediate or delayed) hypersensitivity reaction or idiosyncratic
             reaction to drugs chemically related to the study medication or excipients that, in
             the opinion of the Investigator or GSK, contraindicate their participation.

          -  Previous prostatic surgery (including TURP, balloon dilatation, thermotherapy and
             stent replacement) or other invasive or minimally invasive procedures to treat BPH.

        Recent Medical Procedures

        - History of flexible/rigid cystoscopy or other instrumentation of the urethra within 7
        days prior to Visit 1 (screening). Catheterisation (&lt;10F) is acceptable with no time
        restriction.

        Medical history

          -  Presence of structural abnormalities in the Lower Urinary Tract or sexual organs (e.g.
             urethral stricture, Peyronie's Disease etc) that may cause LUTS or sexual dysfunction.

          -  History of AUR.

          -  Post-void residual volume &gt;100 mL (suprapubic ultrasound) at Visit 1 (screening) or a
             recorded PVR above this level on any previous examination. Measurement should be
             available by the baseline visit and should have been made /arranged at the screening
             visit or within the previous 6 months.

          -  Any causes other than BPH, which may in the judgement of the investigator, result in
             urinary symptoms (e.g. neurogenic bladder, bladder neck contracture, urethral
             stricture, bladder malignancy, acute or chronic prostatitis, or acute or chronic
             urinary tract infections).

          -  History of 'first dose' hypotensive episode on initiation of alpha-1-adrenoreceptor
             antagonist therapy.

          -  History of postural hypotension, dizziness, vertigo or any other signs and symptoms of
             orthostasis, which in the opinion of the investigator could be exacerbated by
             tamsulosin and result in putting the subject at risk of injury.

          -  History of breast cancer or clinical breast examination finding of unclear origin or
             suggestive of malignancy.

          -  Prior history of malignancies (other than basal cell carcinoma or squamous cell
             carcinoma of the skin) within the past 5 years. Subjects with an earlier history of
             malignancy who have had no evidence of disease for at least the past 5 years are
             eligible.

          -  History of hepatic impairment or abnormal liver function tests at Visit 1 (screening)
             (defined as ALT, AST or alkaline phosphatase &gt;2 times the ULN, or total bilirubin &gt;1.5
             times the ULN (unless associated with predominantly indirect bilirubin elevation or
             Gilbert's syndrome).

          -  History of renal insufficiency, or serum creatinine &gt;1.5 times the upper limit of
             normal at Visit 1 (screening).

          -  Any unstable, serious co-existing medical condition(s) including, but not limited to,
             myocardial infarction, coronary bypass surgery, unstable angina, cardiac arrhythmias,
             clinically evident congestive heart failure, or cerebrovascular accident within 6
             months prior to the Screening visit; uncontrolled diabetes or peptic ulcer disease
             which is uncontrolled by medical management.

          -  History or current evidence of drug or alcohol abuse within the previous 12 months.

          -  History or presence of any serious and/or unstable pre-existing psychiatric disorder
             or other conditions that in the opinion of the Investigator or GSK Medical Monitor,
             could interfere with subject's safety, obtaining informed consent, compliance to the
             study procedures, or confound the results of the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2>The people administering the treatment/s</masking2>
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>18/02/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>489</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>5/04/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,SA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Randwick</hospital>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Sydney</hospital>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Wahroonga</hospital>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Kippa-Ring</hospital>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Malvern</hospital>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
    <postcode>2000 - Sydney</postcode>
    <postcode>2076 - Wahroonga</postcode>
    <postcode>4029 - Herston</postcode>
    <postcode>4021 - Kippa-Ring</postcode>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
    <postcode>3144 - Malvern</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Garches</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Nantes cedex 2</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Nîmes cedex 9</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Orleans</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Paris Cedex 13</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Thouars</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Bayern</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Brandenburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Hessen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Niedersachsen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Nordrhein-Westfalen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Sachsen-Anhalt</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Sachsen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Schleswig-Holstein</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Berlin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Eisleben</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Argos</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Athens</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Larisa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Budapest</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Debrecen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Miskolc</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Nyíregyháza</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Szentes</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Almere</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Beek</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Doetinchem</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>EDE</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Eindhoven</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Sneek</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Utrecht</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Winterswijk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Alcazar de San Juan (Ciudad Real)</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Bormujo (Sevilla)</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Cadiz</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Coslada</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Getafe/Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Granada</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Guadalajara</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Marbella</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Mendaro, Guipuzcoa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Murcia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Toledo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Vitoria- Gasteiz</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>GlaxoSmithKline</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is an European double-blind, placebo controlled parallel group comparison of DUODART
      (fixed dose combination of dutasteride 0.5mg and tamsulosin 0.4mg, one capsule daily) and
      placebo.

      PRIMARY OBJECTIVE:

      To assess the change in sexual function from baseline to 1 year in sexually active men with
      at least moderate BPH who are treated with DUODART, compared to men treated with placebo .</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01777269</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>GSK Clinical Trials</name>
      <address>GlaxoSmithKline</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>