<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2016">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/06/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/06/2008</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00702910</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Study to Investigate the Effect of Inhaling Single Doses of Different Formulations of GW642444M in Asthmatic Patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomised, Single-dose, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled, 5-way Crossover Study to Investigate the Efficacy, Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics of Inhaled Doses of GW642444M With and Without Magnesium Stearate in Asthmatic Patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>B2C111401</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pulmonary Disease, Chronic Obstructive</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Placebo
Treatment: drugs - GW642444
Treatment: drugs - Magnesium Stearate

Experimental: GW642444M/lactose - GW642444M/lactose 6.25, 25 and 100 microgram, single inhaled dose for two days treatment in each treatment sequence (crossover design)

Experimental: GW642444M/MgSt - GW642444M/MgSt 6.25, 25 and 100 microgram, single inhaled dose for two days treatment in each treatment sequence (crossover design)

Placebo Comparator: Placebo - Placebo containing lactose, single inhaled dose for two days treatment in each treatment sequence (crossover design)


Treatment: drugs: Placebo
comparator

Treatment: drugs: GW642444
investigational drug or placebo

Treatment: drugs: Magnesium Stearate
Magnesium Stearate

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean change from baseline (pre-dose) FEV1 in trough (mean of the FEV1 values obtained 23 and 24 hours after dosing) FEV1</outcome>
      <timepoint>on going</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean change from baseline (pre-dose) in FEV1 (i.e. derive separate responses for each FEV1 obtained over 24 hours after dosing).</outcome>
      <timepoint>on going</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>General safety and tolerability, including adverse events, laboratory safety tests (haematology, clinical chemistry and urinalysis), vital signs and, 12-lead ECG.</outcome>
      <timepoint>on going</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weighted mean and maximum value (0 - 4 h) QTc(B)</outcome>
      <timepoint>on going</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weighted mean and maximum value (0 - 4 h) QTc(F)</outcome>
      <timepoint>on going</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weighted mean and maximum value (0 - 4 h) supine heart rate</outcome>
      <timepoint>on going</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weighted mean and maximum value (0 - 4 h) supine systolic blood pressure</outcome>
      <timepoint>on going</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weighted mean and minimum value (0 - 4 h) supine diastolic blood pressure</outcome>
      <timepoint>on going</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weighted mean and maximum value glucose (0 - 4 h)</outcome>
      <timepoint>on going</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weighted mean and minimum value potassium (0 - 4 h)</outcome>
      <timepoint>on going</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Single dose derived plasma pharmacokinetic parameters (AUC(0-t), Cmax, tmax) for GW642444 and GI179710 (triphenylacetate counterion)</outcome>
      <timepoint>on going</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Estimate GW642444 concentration (Cmax) -systemic pharmacodynamic relationship for PD parameters, including heart rate, potassium &amp; glucose levels</outcome>
      <timepoint>on going</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Subjects with a documented history of persistent asthma, with the exclusion of other
             significant pulmonary diseases (e.g. chronic bronchitis, emphysema, bronchiectasis,
             cystic fibrosis or bronchopulmonary dysplasia).

          -  Male subjects or female subjects aged between 18 to 70 years.

          -  A female subject is eligible to participate if she is of:

               -  Non-childbearing potential defined as pre-menopausal females with a documented
                  tubal ligation or hysterectomy; or postmenopausal defined as 12 months of
                  spontaneous amenorrhea [in questionable cases a blood sample with simultaneous
                  follicle stimulating hormone (FSH) &gt; 40 MlU/ml and estradiol &lt; 40 pg/ml (&lt; 140
                  pmol/L) is confirmatory.

               -  Child-bearing potential and agrees to use one of the contraception methods listed
                  in Section 8.1 for an appropriate period of time (as determined by the product
                  label or investigator) prior to the start of dosing to sufficiently minimize the
                  risk of pregnancy at that point. Female subjects must agree to use contraception
                  until 2 days post last-dose.

          -  Subjects who are current non-smokers, who have not used any inhaled tobacco products
             (snuff is permitted) in the 12 month period preceding the screening visit and who have
             a pack history of = 10 pack years.

          -  Subjects with clinically stable, mild to moderate persistent asthma within the 4 weeks
             preceding the screening visit and with a screening pre-bronchodilator FEV1 = 60 %
             predicted as defined in the GINA guidelines [Global Initiative for Asthma (GINA),
             2006] (having abstained from bronchodilators for the required period). Predicted
             values are based on the ECCS 1993 normal ranges.

          -  Body weight = 50 kg and body mass index (BMI) within the range 19 - 29.9 kg/m2

          -  During the screening visit, subjects must demonstrate the presence of reversible
             airway disease, defined as an increase in FEV1 of = 12.0% over baseline and an
             absolute change of = 200 mL within 30 minutes following a single 400 mcg salbutamol
             dose.

          -  ECG criteria as per protocol

          -  Subjects who are currently taking ICS at a total daily dose of 200 to 500 mcg of FP or
             equivalent ICS.

          -  Subjects who are able and willing to give written informed consent to take part in the
             study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Subjects who have a past or present disease, which as judged by the Investigator and
             the Medical Monitor, which may affect the safety of the subject or outcome of this
             study.

          -  A screening Holter ECG tracing that reveals clinically concerning arrhythmias.

          -  Subjects who have suffered an upper or lower respiratory tract infection within 4
             weeks of the screening visit

          -  Subjects with a history of life-threatening asthma, defined as an asthma episode that
             required intubation and/or was associated with either respiratory arrest or hypoxic
             seizures.

          -  Asthma exacerbations requiring treatment with oral corticosteroids: any exacerbations
             within 3 months of the screening visit or two or more exacerbations within 6 months of
             the screening visit or admittance to hospital for an asthma exacerbation within 1 year
             of the screening visit.

          -  Subjects classified as suffering from severe asthma as defined by the ATS guidelines

          -  Subjects who have taken high doses of an inhaled corticosteroid (&gt; 500 mcg FP/day or
             equivalent) within 8 weeks of the screening visit or oral steroids within 12 weeks of
             the screening visit.

          -  Subjects who have changed their inhaled corticosteroid treatment within the last 6
             weeks before screening or can be expected to do so during the study.

          -  The subject has participated in a clinical trial and has received an investigational
             product within the following time period prior to the first dosing day in the current
             study: 30 days, 5 half-lives or twice the duration of the biological effect of the
             investigational product (whichever is longer).

          -  Exposure to more than four NCE's within 12 months prior to the first dosing day

          -  Any adverse reaction including immediate or delayed hypersensitivity to any ß2 agonist
             or sympathomimetic drug, or known or suspected sensitivity to the constituents of
             GW642444 inhalation powder (e.g., lactose, milk protein, magnesium stearate).

          -  Subjects with a positive pre-study Hepatitis B surface antigen, positive Hepatitis C
             antibody or HIV result (if tested as per site SOPs) within 3 months of the start of
             the study.

          -  Neurological or psychiatric disease or history of drug or alcohol abuse which would
             interfere with the subject's proper completion of the protocol requirements, including
             compliance.

          -  Abuse of alcohol is defined as an average weekly intake of greater than 21 units or an
             average daily intake of greater than 3 units (males) or defined as an average weekly
             intake of greater than 14 units or an average daily intake of greater than 2 units
             (females).

          -  1 unit is equivalent to a half pint (220 mL) of beer or 1 measure (25 mL) of spirits
             or 1 glass (125 mL) of wine.

          -  The subject has a positive pre-study urine drug test screen. A minimum list of drugs
             that will be screened for include amphetamines, barbiturates, cocaine, opiates,
             cannabinoids and benzodiazepines.

          -  The subject has a positive pre-study alcohol or smoking breath or urinary test.

          -  Where participation in the study would result in donation of blood in excess of 500 mL
             within a 56 day period.

          -  Subjects with clinically relevant findings on laboratory safety tests.

          -  Subjects with laboratory values outside the reference range may be included if the
             Investigator and medical monitor agree that these findings would not put the subject
             at risk or interfere with the objectives of the study.

          -  Subjects with known hypersensitivity to salbutamol or any ingredient in this
             preparation

          -  Subjects who have taken P-gp inhibitors and CYP 450 3A4 inhibitors (e.g. Ketoconazole)
             within 6 weeks or theophyllines within 2 weeks of the screening visit.

          -  Inability to use the novel dry powder inhaler.

          -  Pregnant females as determined by positive hCG (serum or urine) test at screening or
             prior to dosing.

          -  Lactating females.

          -  Unwillingness or inability to follow the procedures outlined in the protocol.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>27/04/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>24</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>4/10/2008</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Auchenflower</hospital>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Clayton</hospital>
    <postcode>4066 - Auchenflower</postcode>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Wellington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>GlaxoSmithKline</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will involve the use of a new medicine called GW642444 being developed for the
      treatment of asthma and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD). The purpose of the
      study is to see how safe and how well tolerated the study drug is when inhaled in two
      different formulations as a fine powder by asthmatic patients. In addition, the study is
      designed to examine the effect of the study drug on the lungs, how the study drug affects
      parts of the body other than the lungs and to see how the body affects the study drug when it
      is given in single doses.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00702910</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Kempsford R, Norris V, Siederer S. Vilanterol trifenatate, a novel inhaled long-acting beta2 adrenoceptor agonist, is well tolerated in healthy subjects and demonstrates prolonged bronchodilation in subjects with asthma and COPD. Pulm Pharmacol Ther. 2013 Apr;26(2):256-64. doi: 10.1016/j.pupt.2012.12.001. Epub 2012 Dec 8.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>GSK Clinical Trials</name>
      <address>GlaxoSmithKline</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>