<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="688">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/09/2005</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/09/2005</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00147680</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Uterine Papillary Serous Cancer (UPSC) Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Prospective, Non-randomised Phase 2 Clinical Trial of Carboplatin Plus Paclitaxel With Sequential Radical Pelvic Radiotherapy for Uterine Serous Papillary Cancer</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>UPSC - 001</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Uterine Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Womb (Uterine or endometrial cancer)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Paclitaxel, Carboplatin

Treatment: drugs: Paclitaxel, Carboplatin


</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the safety and efficacy of the combination of paclitaxel and carboplatin plus/minus (+/-) pelvic radiotherapy in the treatment of UPSC</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To observe the patterns of recurrence following the administration of the combination of paclitaxel and carboplatin +/- pelvic radiotherapy in the treatment of UPSC</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the quality of life (QOL), overall survival and disease free survival</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Patients with histologically confirmed UPSC at surgical stage 1b to 4 disease. The
             serous-papillary component of the specimen must be at least 30 percent. Patients with
             surgical stage 1a disease should not be enrolled.

          -  Females aged &gt;= 18 years old.

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0, 1, or 2.

          -  Patients may not have received any prior chemotherapy regimens for UPSC.

          -  Patients must have adequate bone marrow, renal, hepatic and neurologic function.

          -  Patients must be informed of the investigational nature of the study and sign an
             informed consent form.

          -  Patients with previous malignancy are eligible only if the patient has been
             disease-free for &gt;= 5 years.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Female</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Patients with pre-existing &gt;= grade 2 neurotoxicity.

          -  Patients with uncontrolled hypertension, (systolic blood pressure &gt;180 mm Hg or
             diastolic blood pressure &gt;100 mm Hg) or uncontrolled cardiac arrhythmia or diabetes
             mellitus

          -  Patients with a history of other malignancy within the last 5 years that could affect
             the diagnosis or assessment of UPSC.

          -  Patients who have a history of serious cardiac disease that is not adequately
             controlled are not allowed. Patients with documented myocardial infarction within 6
             months preceding study entry; congestive heart failure; unstable angina; a clinically
             significant pericardial effusion; or arrhythmias are also ineligible.

          -  Patients with an active serious infection or other serious underlying medical
             condition that would otherwise impair their ability to receive protocol treatment.

          -  Serious medical or psychiatric illnesses that would prevent informed consent. Dementia
             or significantly altered mental status that would prohibit the understanding and/or
             giving of informed consent.

          -  Patients with prior significant allergic reactions to drugs containing cremophor, such
             as cyclosporine, or vitamin K are not eligible. A significant reaction may be defined
             as, but is not limited to, the description of grade &gt;= 3 allergic reactions using the
             Common Toxicity Criteria (CTC). Patients with known hypersensitivity to paclitaxel,
             carboplatin or Cremophor EL.

          -  Patients who have received prior whole pelvis radiotherapy.

          -  Patients with uncontrolled pelvic inflammatory disease that would contraindicate
             pelvic radiotherapy.

          -  Patients who are pregnant or breast-feeding.

          -  Patients receiving other investigational therapy.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/09/2004</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/10/2009</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>QCGC, Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>Mater Adult Public Hospital - South Brisbane</hospital>
    <postcode>4029 - Herston</postcode>
    <postcode>4101 - South Brisbane</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Queensland Centre for Gynaecological Cancer</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will be an open, non-randomised, clinical phase 2 trial, which will involve 30
      women diagnosed with uterine papillary serous cancer. The researchers will investigate the
      effect of four cycles of paclitaxel/carboplatin, followed by whole pelvic external beam
      radiotherapy to a standard pelvis field (50.4 Gy) with or without a para-aortic boost with
      respect to the safety and efficacy of treatment, and patterns of recurrence.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00147680</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Andreas Obermair</name>
      <address>QCGC</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>