<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="1116">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/03/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/03/2006</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00310388</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Open-Label Extension Study of the Phase 3 VRX-RET-E22-302 Double-Blind Trial. 115097</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Multicenter, Open-Label, Long-Term, Safety, Tolerability and Efficacy Study of Retigabine in Adult Epilepsy Patients With Partial-Onset Seizures (Extension of Study VRX-RET-E22-302)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>EUDRACT No. 2006-000956-42</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>VRX-RET-E22-304</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Epilepsy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Epilepsy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Retigabine (INN), Ezogabine (USAN)

Experimental: Retigabine (INN), Ezogabine (USAN) - Retigabine (Ezogabine): all subjects


Treatment: drugs: Retigabine (INN), Ezogabine (USAN)
Film-coated tablets containing 50 mg, 100 mg, or 300 mg of retigabine per tablet. Dosage and frequency will be specific to each patient so long as the patients receives between 600 and 1200 mg of retigabine per day. The duration will be until the completion of the trial, or until the patient withdraws from the trial.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in systolic blood pressure (SBP) and diastolic blood pressure (DBP) for supine and standing position - SBP and DBP measurements for supine and standing position were obtained at Baseline(Month 0) and Month 1, 3, 6, 9, 12, 16, 20, 24. For the standing position measurement, participant was asked to stand for approximately 2 minutes before taking the measurements. The change from Baseline was obtained by subtracting the Baseline value from the post-randomization value. Baseline was Month 0 value.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Month 0) and Month 1, 3, 6, 9, 12, 16, 20, 24</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in supine and standing pulse rate - Pulse rate measurements for supine and standing position were obtained at Baseline(Month 0) and Month 1, 3, 6, 9, 12, 16, 20, 24. For the standing position measurement, participant was asked to stand for approximately 2 minutes before taking the measurements. The change from Baseline was obtained by subtracting the Baseline value from the post-randomization value. Baseline was Month 0 value.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline(Month 0) and Month 1, 3, 6, 9, 12, 16, 20, 24</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in body weight - Weight measurements were obtained at Baseline(Month 0) and Month 1, 3, 6, 9, 12, 16, 20, 24. For measuring weight, participants were asked to be in ordinary indoor clothing (without shoes). The change from Baseline was obtained by subtracting the Baseline value from the post-randomization value. Baseline was Month 0 value.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline(Month 0) and Month 1, 3, 6, 9, 12, 16, 20, 24</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in body temperature - Temperature measurements were obtained at Baseline(Month 0) and Month 1, 3, 6, 9, 12, 16, 20, 24. The change from Baseline was obtained by subtracting the Baseline value from the post randomization value. Baseline was Month 0 value.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline(Month 0) and Month 1, 3, 6, 9, 12, 16, 20, 24</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in Hematology parameters- Basophils, Eosinophils, lymphocytes, Monocytes, Neutrophils, platelet count and white blood corpusles (WBC) - Blood samples were collected for the measurement of hematology parameters at Baseline(Month 0) and Month 1, 3, 6, 9, 12, 16, 20, 24. Change from baseline in Basophils, Eosinophils, lymphocytes, Monocytes, Neutrophils, platelet count and WBC is presented. The change from Baseline was obtained by subtracting the Baseline value from the post randomization value. Baseline was Month 0 value.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline(Month 0) and Month 1, 3, 6, 9, 12, 16, 20, 24</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in Hematology parameters- Hematocrit - Blood samples were collected for the measurement of hematology parameters at Baseline(Month 0) and Month 1, 3, 6, 9, 12, 16, 20, 24. Change from baseline in hematocrit is presented.The change from Baseline was obtained by subtracting the Baseline value from the post randomization value. Baseline was Month 0 value.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline(Month 0) and Month 1, 3, 6, 9, 12, 16, 20, 24</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in Hematology parameters- Hemoglobin - Blood samples were collected for the measurement of hematology parameters at Baseline(Month 0) and Month 1, 3, 6, 9, 12, 16, 20, 24. Change from baseline in hemoglobin is presented. The change from Baseline was obtained by subtracting the Baseline value from the post randomization value. Baseline was Month 0 value.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline(Month 0) and Month 1, 3, 6, 9, 12, 16, 20, 24</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in Hematology parameters- red blood corpuscles(RBC) - Blood samples were collected for the measurement of hematology parameters at Baseline(Month 0) and Month 1, 3, 6, 9, 12, 16, 20, 24. Change from baseline in RBC is presented. The change from Baseline was obtained by subtracting the Baseline value from the post randomization value. Baseline was Month 0 value.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline(Month 0) and Month 1, 3, 6, 9, 12, 16, 20, 24</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in clinical chemistry: Alkaline Phosphatase, alanine transaminase (ALT), aspartate transaminase (AST) - Blood samples were collected for the measurement of clinical chemistry parameters at Baseline(Month 0) and Month 1, 3, 6, 9, 12, 16, 20, 24. Change from baseline in Alkaline Phosphatase, ALT and AST is presented. The change from Baseline was obtained by subtracting the Baseline value from the post randomization value. Baseline was Month 0 value.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline(Month 0) and Month 1, 3, 6, 9, 12, 16, 20, 24</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in clinical chemistry : bicarbonate, BUN, calcium, chloride, cholesterol, non-fasting glucose, phosphorus, potassium, sodium - Blood samples were collected for the measurement of clinical chemistry parameters at Baseline(Month 0) and Month 1, 3, 6, 9, 12, 16, 20, 24. Change from baseline in bicarbonate, BUN, calcium, chloride, cholesterol, non-fasting glucose, phosphorus, potassium, sodium is presented. The change from Baseline was obtained by subtracting the Baseline value from the post randomization value. Baseline was Month 0 value.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline(Month 0) and Month 1, 3, 6, 9, 12, 16, 20, 24</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in clinical chemistry: Total Bilirubin, Creatinine, Uric acid - Blood samples were collected for the measurement of clinical chemistry parameters at Baseline(Month 0) and Month 1, 3, 6, 9, 12, 16, 20, 24. Change from baseline in total bilirubin, creatinine and uric acid is presented. The change from Baseline was obtained by subtracting the Baseline value from the post randomization value. Baseline was Month 0 value.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline(Month 0) and Month 1, 3, 6, 9, 12, 16, 20, 24</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in clinical chemistry: Total protein - Blood samples were collected for the measurement of clinical chemistry parameters at Baseline(Month 0) and Month 1, 3, 6, 9, 12, 16, 20, 24. Change from baseline in total protein is presented. The change from Baseline was obtained by subtracting the Baseline value from the post randomization value. Baseline was Month 0 value.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline(Month 0) and Month 1, 3, 6, 9, 12, 16, 20, 24</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>ECG parameters assessment: PR interval, QRS interval, QT interval, and QTc interval - A 12-lead ECG was performed at Month 1, 3, 6, 9, 12 and 24. The ECG parameters assessed were PR interval, QRS interval, QT interval, and QTc interval. QT intervals were corrected using both Bazett's and Fridericia's formulas. Increases in Bazett's QTc interval of &gt;60 from baseline or QTc interval of &gt;500 anytime during the was confirmed on a repeat ECG.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Month 1, 3, 6, 9, 12 and 24</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of participants with abnormal Physical and neurological examinations - Physical examination included skin, head, eyes, ears, nose, throat, mouth, neck, heart, lungs, breast, abdomen, genitalia, extremities and other. Neurological examination included level of consciousness, level of appearance, mental status, speech, vision, eye movements, jaw movements and facial sensation, facial motor, hearing, swallowing, pharynx, larynx, sternocleidomastoid, trapezius, tongue, biceps, brachioradials, triceps, knee, ankle, plantar, general movement, muscle bulk, muscle fasciculation, trunk, muscle strength upper extremities, muscle strength lower extremities, muscle tone upper extremities, muscle tone lower extremities, gait, hopping, romberg, nystagmus, tremor, finger-nose, heel-shin, rapid rhythmic movements, upper extremities pain/ temperature, upper extremities light touch, upper extremities position, upper extremities vibration, lower extremities pain/ temperature, lower extremities light touch, lower extremities position and lower extremities vibration.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Month 24</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of participants with Adverse Events (AEs) and Serious Adverse Events (SAEs) - An AE is defined as any untoward medical occurrence that occurred during the course of the trial after study treatment had started. An adverse event was therefore any unfavourable and unintended sign, symptom, or disease temporally associated with the use of study drug, whether or not considered related to the study drug. An SAE is any untoward medical occurrence that at any dose results in death, are life threatening, requires hospitalization or prolongation of hospitalization or results in disability/incapacity, and congenital anomaly/birth defect.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 24 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in American Urological Association (AUA) Symptom Index Scores During Open-Label Retigabine Treatment - AUA symptom index scores questionnaire had 7 questions. Responses to each of the 7 questions were scored 0 (not at all), 1 (less than 1 time), 2 (less than half the time), 3 (about half the time), 4 (more than half the time) and 5 (almost always), for a total possible score of 35. The total score for all questions was classified as mild (0-7), moderate (8-19) or severe (&gt;19). Question 7 was scored as 0 (none), 1 (1 time), 2 (2 times), 3 (3 times), 4 (4 times) and 5 (5 times or more). Total score was range was 0-49.The change from Baseline was obtained by subtracting the Baseline value from the post randomization value. Baseline was Month 0 value.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (month 0) and Month 1, 3 and 12</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Post-Void Residual Urine Volume by Study Time Point - A post-void residual bladder ultrasound to assess urinary retention was performed at Baseline (month 0) and Month 1, 3 and 12. The change from Baseline was obtained by subtracting the Baseline value from the post randomization value. Baseline was Month 0 value.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (month 0) and Month 1, 3 and 12</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in Quality of life, evaluated through the Quality of Life in Epilepsy-Problems (QOLIE-31-P) - The Quality of Life in Epilepsy Inventory-Form 31 (QOLIE-31-P) is an adaptation of the original QOLIE-31 instrument that includes 30 items grouped into 7 multi-item subscales: Seizure Worry (5 items), Overall Quality of Life (2 items), Emotional Well-being (5 items), Energy/Fatigue (4 items), Cognitive Functioning (6 items), Medication Effects (3 items) and Daily Activities/Social Functioning (5 items), and a Health Status item. In addition to the 31 items, the QOLIE-31-P contains 7 items asking the participants to rate the degree of 'distress' related to the topic of each subscale. The subscale scores, the total score and the Health Status item score were calculated according to the scoring algorithm defined by the author with scores ranging from 0 to 100 and higher scores indicating better function. The change from Baseline was obtained by subtracting the Baseline value from the post randomization value. Baseline was Month 0 value.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Month 0) and Month 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage change in the monthly seizure rate from the baseline (Study 302) phase to the open-label treatment phase - Monthly total seizure rates observed during the open-label extension period was compared to the monthly total seizure rates observed during the Baseline phase of the double-blind study VRX-RET-E22-302. Percent change from baseline was calculated as post randomization value divided by the baseline value and multiplied by 100. Baseline was Month 0 value of VRX-RET-E22-302 study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Month 0) and Month 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of participants who were responders (participants experiencing = 50% reduction in seizure frequency) from baseline to open-label treatment phase - Responders were defined as participants with =50% reduction in 28-day total partial seizure frequency from Baseline in Study 302 to data cutoff in this Study 304. Number of participants who were responders are presented.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Month 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Patient has successfully completed the Maintenance and Transition phases of Study
             VRX-RET-E22-302 for the treatment of partial-onset seizures

          -  Patient is expected to benefit from participation in the study in the opinion of the
             Investigator.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Patient meets any of the withdrawal criteria in the previous VRX-RET-E22-302 study or
             is experiencing an ongoing serious adverse event.

          -  Patient is receiving any investigational drug or using any experimental device in
             addition to Retigabine for treatment of epilepsy or any other medical condition.

          -  Patient has any other condition that would prevent compliance with the study
             procedures or proper reporting of adverse events.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>5/07/2006</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>376</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>19/04/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,SA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Institute of Clniical Neurosciences - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>North Coast Neurology Centre - Maroochydore</hospital>
    <hospital>Flinders Medical Centre - Bedford Park</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Austin &amp; Repatriation Medical Centre - West Heidelberg</hospital>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>4558 - Maroochydore</postcode>
    <postcode>5041 - Bedford Park</postcode>
    <postcode>3050 - Parkville</postcode>
    <postcode>3081 - West Heidelberg</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Antwerp</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Brugge</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Leuven</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Ottignies</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Levallois-Perret</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Lyon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Rennes Cedex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Tain L'Hermitage, 26</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>BY</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>HE</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>RP</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Bonn</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Muenchen, BY</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Ulm, BW</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Ret</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Budapest</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Beer Yaakov</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Haifa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Holon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Nahariya</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Ramat Gan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Rechovot</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Tel Aviv</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Plock</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Warszawa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Zgierz</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Bialystok</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Gdansk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Lublin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Kazan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Moscow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>St. Petersburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Gauteng</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>W Cape</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>WC</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Belville, W Cape</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>BleomFontein, Free State</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Durban, KZ-Natal</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Johannesburg, Gauteng</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Port Elisabeth, E Cape</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Bilbao</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Granada</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>San Sebastian</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Zaragoza</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ukraine</country>
      <state>Dnepropetrovsk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ukraine</country>
      <state>Kharkov</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ukraine</country>
      <state>Kiev</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ukraine</country>
      <state>Odessa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Mersyd</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Blackpool</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Glasgow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>GlaxoSmithKline</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This Phase 3 trial is an open-label extension study of the placebo-controlled, double-blind
      VRX-RET-E22-302 trial. Patients who have completed the VRX-RET-E22-302 trial and who meet
      inclusion and exclusion criteria will be treated with 600-1200 mg/day of retigabine as an
      adjunct therapy to their current antiepileptic drugs (AEDs) or vagal nerve stimulation.
      Treatment will be continued until the subject withdraws from the study or until the program
      is discontinued. Patients will be recruited from 55-60 sites in Europe, Israel, Australia,
      and South Africa. The primary objective of the study is to evaluate the safety and
      tolerability of long-term therapy with retigabine administered as adjunctive therapy in adult
      epilepsy patients with partial-onset seizures, who completed the double-blind Study
      VRX-RET-E22-302. Secondary objectives are: to evaluate efficacy of long-term treatment with
      retigabine and patient quality of life and to evaluate whether retinal pigmentation,
      unexplained vision loss, pigmentation of non-retinal ocular tissue, and discoloration of
      nails, lips, skin or mucosa change over time after discontinuation of retigabine.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00310388</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>GSK Clinical Trials</name>
      <address>GlaxoSmithKline</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>