<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5678">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/03/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/03/2014</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02095691</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>RENABLATE-II Feasibility Study of Catheter Based Renal Denervation to Treat Resistant Hypertension - 157</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Prospective, Multi-center, Non-Randomized, Feasibility Study of Catheter Based Renal Denervation to Treat Resistant Hypertension (RENABLATE-II - 157)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>RENABLATE-II</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>RENABLATE-II</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hypertension, Renal</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Hypertension</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other renal and urogenital disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - Celsius® ThermoCool® Renal Denervation

Experimental: Resistant Hypertension - The Celsius® ThermoCool® Renal Denervation catheter will serve to treat resistant hypertension.


Treatment: devices: Celsius® ThermoCool® Renal Denervation
The investigational device is indicated for the treatment of resistant hypertension by renal denervation.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of Major Adverse Events That Occurred Within 30 Days Post-procedure. - Major adverse events include Acute myocardial infarction; Death from progressive heart failure, death from aortic or peripheral artery disease, from renal failure and sudden cardiac death; New-onset heart failure; Stroke; Aortic or lower limb revascularization procedure; Lower limb amputation; Beginning dialysis; Hospital admission for hypertensive emergency unrelated to non-adherence or non-persistence with drugs at each follow up visit; Hospitalization for atrial fibrillation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days post-procedure</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of Adverse Cardiovascular and Renal Events Within the 12 Month Follow-up Visit - These adverse events include renal artery stenosis (=60% diameter reduction confirmed by MRI or renal angiography); peri-procedural renal artery dissection or perforation requiring intervention, serious arterial access site related complications requiring intervention or prolonging hospitalization; =25% reduction between baseline and 12 months in renal function measured by the estimated Glomerular Filtration Rate (eGFR), as well as composite of major adverse cardiovascular and/or renal events.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months post-procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Change in Office Systolic Blood Pressure and Diastolic Blood Pressure From Baseline to 1 ,3, 6 and 12 Months Post Procedure - Office systolic blood pressure (SBP) and diastolic blood pressure (DBP) measures were summarized to assess the reduction in blood pressure from baseline visit to post baseline at 1, 3, 6, and 12 months. Negative values for change represent reductions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months post-procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of Subjects Achieving Target Systolic Blood Pressure (SBP) at 1, 3, 6 and 12 Months Post Procedure - The pre-specified target SBP is defined as SBP &lt;130 mmHg. This endpoint is defined at each of 1, 3, 6 and 12 months post procedure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months post-procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of Subjects Achieving a = 10 mmHg Reduction in Systolic Blood Pressure (SBP) at 1, 3, 6 and 12 Months Post Procedure - Incidence of subjects achieving a 10 mmHg or more reduction in Systolic Blood Pressure (SBP) at 1, 3, 6 and 12 months post procedure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months post-procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Subject has a systolic blood pressure = 140 mmHg based on an average of 3 office blood
             pressure readings measured according to the BP guidelines.

          2. Subject is adhering to a stable drug regimen of at least 3 different classes of
             anti-hypertensive medications, including a diuretic (with no changes for a minimum of
             2 weeks prior to enrollment) at optimal dose and is expected to be maintained for at
             least 6 months.

          3. Subject is &gt; 18 and &lt; 85 years of age.

          4. Subject agrees to have all study procedures performed, and is competent and willing to
             provide written, informed consent to participate in this study.

        Key</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. A secondary cause of hypertension, e.g. "white coat" hypertension (assessed by 24 h
             ABPM at physician's discretion), primary aldosteronism, pheochromocytoma, renal artery
             stenosis, drug induced-hypertension, Adult Polycystic kidney Disease, renal cell
             carcinoma, pyelonephritis, glomerulonephritis, coarctation of the aorta, acromegaly,
             Cushing's Syndrome, Conn's (primary hyperaldosteronism), polyarteritis nodosum,
             systemic sclerosis, parenchymal kidney disease, obstructive sleep apnoea based on a
             workup performed within the 12 months preceding enrollment.

          2. Subject has aorto-ilio-femoral artery anatomy not suitable for treatment with the
             investigational device(s).

          3. Subject has main renal arteries that are &lt; 20 mm in length or &lt; 4 mm in diameter.

          4. Subject has a prior history of any renal artery intervention including but not limited
             to balloon angioplasty, stenting, renal denervation or surgery.

          5. Subject has an estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) of &lt; 45mL/min/1.73m2, using
             the MDRD formula.

          6. Subject has type 1 diabetes mellitus.

          7. Subject has history of Myocardial Infarction, unstable angina pectoris, or a
             cerebrovascular accident in the 6 months period prior to enrolment, or documented
             widespread atherosclerosis, intravascular thrombosis or unstable plaques.

          8. Subject has hemodynamically significant valvular heart disease for which reduction of
             blood pressure would be considered hazardous.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/10/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>19</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/04/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czech Republic</country>
      <state>Prague</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Bari</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Biosense Webster, Inc.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a prospective, multi-center, non-randomized, feasibility study to assess the safety
      and effectiveness of renal artery sympathetic denervation using the investigational devices
      in subjects with resistant hypertension.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02095691</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>