<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3086">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/02/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/02/2011</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01301625</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>MitraClip System in Australia and New Zealand</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Prospective Single Arm Clinical Trial Evaluating the MitraClip System in Australia and New Zealand</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>MitraClipANZ</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Protocol #M10-001</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Mitral Regurgitation</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - MitraClip Implant

MitraClip Implant - Eligible patients undergoing a MitraClip procedure in Australia and New Zealand


Treatment: devices: MitraClip Implant
Percutaneous mitral valve repair using MitraClip implant.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Echocardiographic Endpoints - MR Severity Grade Regurgitant Volume Regurgitant Fraction Left Ventricle End Diastolic Volume (LVEDV) Left Ventricular End Systolic Volume (LVESV) Left Ventricular End Diastolic Dimension (LVIDd) Left Ventricular End Systolic Dimension (LVIDs) LV Ejection Fraction (LVEF) Mitral Valve Area Mitral Valve Gradient Left Atrial Volumes</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 12 months after implant procedure</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical Endpoints - Mortality NYHA Functional Class Six-Minute Walk Test (6MWT) distance QOL Assessment (Minnesota Living with Heart Failure Questionnaire) Mitral valve surgery, including reason for and type of surgery Second MitraClip device intervention, including reason for intervention Re-hospitalizations Reason for rehospitalization (i.e., heart failure, other cardiac, non-cardiac) Number of rehospitalizations Number of days rehospitalized</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 12 months after procedure</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Age 18 years or older.

          -  MR = 3+ .

          -  Transseptal catheterization and femoral vein access feasible.

          -  Placement of the MitraClip device on mitral leaflets feasible.

          -  Mitral valve orifice area = 4.0 cm2.

          -  Written informed consent obtained.

          -  The patient agrees to return for follow-up visits.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Need for emergency surgery, other cardiac surgery.

          -  Coronary artery disease (CAD), atrial fibrillation (AF), other valve disease.

          -  Prior mitral valve repair surgery, mechanical prosthetic valve, or ventricular assist
             device (VAD).

          -  Active endocarditis or rheumatic heart disease; leaflets degenerated from endocarditis
             or rheumatic disease.

          -  Transesophageal echocardiography (TEE) contraindicated.

          -  Known hypersensitivity or contraindication to trial or procedure medications which
             cannot be managed medically.

          -  Currently participating in investigational drug trial or another device trial that has
             not yet completed the primary endpoint or that interferes with the MitraClip System
             ANZ Clinical Trial.

          -  Pregnant or planning pregnancy within next 12 months.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/11/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>78</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Terminated</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/09/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,SA,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St. Vincent's Hospital Sydney - Darlinghurst</hospital>
    <hospital>Macquarie University Hosptial - North Ryde</hospital>
    <hospital>North Shore Private Hospital - St Leonards</hospital>
    <hospital>The Prince Charles Hospital - Chermside</hospital>
    <hospital>Flinders Medical Centre - Bedford Park</hospital>
    <hospital>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital - Nedlands</hospital>
    <postcode>2010 - Darlinghurst</postcode>
    <postcode>2109 - North Ryde</postcode>
    <postcode>2065 - St Leonards</postcode>
    <postcode>4032 - Chermside</postcode>
    <postcode>5042 - Bedford Park</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Evalve</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Abbott</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary objective of the MitraClip System ANZ Clinical Trial is to gather real-world
      clinical and health-economic outcome data to support the long-term safety, efficacy and
      economic value of the MitraClip System in the continuum of therapies for treating MR.
      Specifically, the following clinical and economic data will be collected: New York Heart
      Association (NYHA) Functional Class, Six-Minute Walk Test (6MWT) distance, quality of life
      (QOL) information, echocardiographic measures of left ventricular size and function, and data
      associated with the index hospitalization, rehospitalizations, concomitant medications and
      discharge facility to support the MitraClip System economic analysis.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01301625</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Mauri L, Garg P, Massaro JM, Foster E, Glower D, Mehoudar P, Powell F, Komtebedde J, McDermott E, Feldman T. The EVEREST II Trial: design and rationale for a randomized study of the evalve mitraclip system compared with mitral valve surgery for mitral regurgitation. Am Heart J. 2010 Jul;160(1):23-9. doi: 10.1016/j.ahj.2010.04.009.
Whitlow PL, Feldman T, Pedersen WR, Lim DS, Kipperman R, Smalling R, Bajwa T, Herrmann HC, Lasala J, Maddux JT, Tuzcu M, Kapadia S, Trento A, Siegel RJ, Foster E, Glower D, Mauri L, Kar S; EVEREST II Investigators. Acute and 12-month results with catheter-based mitral valve leaflet repair: the EVEREST II (Endovascular Valve Edge-to-Edge Repair) High Risk Study. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2012 Jan 10;59(2):130-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2011.08.067.
Tamburino C, Ussia GP, Maisano F, Capodanno D, La Canna G, Scandura S, Colombo A, Giacomini A, Michev I, Mangiafico S, Cammalleri V, Barbanti M, Alfieri O. Percutaneous mitral valve repair with the MitraClip system: acute results from a real world setting. Eur Heart J. 2010 Jun;31(11):1382-9. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehq051. Epub 2010 Mar 18.
Ussia GP, Barbanti M, Tamburino C. Feasibility of percutaneous transcatheter mitral valve repair with the MitraClip system using conscious sedation. Catheter Cardiovasc Interv. 2010 Jun 1;75(7):1137-40. doi: 10.1002/ccd.22415.
Jönsson A, Settergren M. MitraClip catheter-based mitral valve repair system. Expert Rev Med Devices. 2010 Jul;7(4):439-47. doi: 10.1586/erd.10.23.
Argenziano M, Skipper E, Heimansohn D, Letsou GV, Woo YJ, Kron I, Alexander J, Cleveland J, Kong B, Davidson M, Vassiliades T, Krieger K, Sako E, Tibi P, Galloway A, Foster E, Feldman T, Glower D; EVEREST Investigators. Surgical revision after percutaneous mitral repair with the MitraClip device. Ann Thorac Surg. 2010 Jan;89(1):72-80; discussion p 80. doi: 10.1016/j.athoracsur.2009.08.063.
Geidel S, Ostermeyer J, Lass M, Schmoeckel M. Complex surgical valve repair after failed percutaneous mitral intervention using the MitraClip device. Ann Thorac Surg. 2010 Jul;90(1):277-9. doi: 10.1016/j.athoracsur.2009.12.048.
Kalarus Z, Kukulski T, Lekston A, Streb W, Sikora J, Nadziakiewicz P, Gasior M, Polonski L, Zembala M. [Methodology and safety of transvascular reduction of severe ischaemic mitral insufficiency with MitraClip in high-surgical-risk patients - first three cases in Poland]. Kardiol Pol. 2010 Jun;68(6):729-35. Polish.
Lim DS, Kunjummen BJ, Smalling R. Mitral valve repair with the MitraClip device after prior surgical mitral annuloplasty. Catheter Cardiovasc Interv. 2010 Sep 1;76(3):455-9. doi: 10.1002/ccd.22547.
Ciobanu A, Bennett S, Azam M, Clark A, Vinereanu D. Incremental value of three-dimensional transoesophageal echocardiography for guiding double percutaneous MitraClip ® implantation in a 'no option' patient. Eur J Echocardiogr. 2011 Feb;12(2):E11. doi: 10.1093/ejechocard/jeq118. Epub 2010 Sep 27.
Tamburino C, Immè S, Barbanti M, Mulè M, Pistritto AM, Aruta P, Cammalleri V, Scarabelli M, Mangiafico S, Scandura S, Ussia GP. Reduction of mitral valve regurgitation with Mitraclip® percutaneous system. Minerva Cardioangiol. 2010 Oct;58(5):589-98.
Borgia F, Di Mario C, Franzen O. Adenosine-induced asystole to facilitate MitraClip placement in a patient with adverse mitral valve morphology. Heart. 2011 May;97(10):864. doi: 10.1136/hrt.2010.208132. Epub 2010 Oct 29.
Luk A, Butany J, Ahn E, Fann JI, St Goar F, Thornton T, McDermott L, Madayag C, Komtebedde J. Mitral repair with the Evalve MitraClip device: histopathologic findings in the porcine model. Cardiovasc Pathol. 2009 Sep-Oct;18(5):279-85. doi: 10.1016/j.carpath.2008.07.001. Epub 2008 Aug 13.
Herrmann HC, Kar S, Siegel R, Fail P, Loghin C, Lim S, Hahn R, Rogers JH, Bommer WJ, Wang A, Berke A, Lerakis S, Kramer P, Wong SC, Foster E, Glower D, Feldman T; EVEREST Investigators. Effect of percutaneous mitral repair with the MitraClip device on mitral valve area and gradient. EuroIntervention. 2009 Jan;4(4):437-42.
Feldman T, Kar S, Rinaldi M, Fail P, Hermiller J, Smalling R, Whitlow PL, Gray W, Low R, Herrmann HC, Lim S, Foster E, Glower D; EVEREST Investigators. Percutaneous mitral repair with the MitraClip system: safety and midterm durability in the initial EVEREST (Endovascular Valve Edge-to-Edge REpair Study) cohort. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2009 Aug 18;54(8):686-94. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2009.03.077.
Rogers JH, Yeo KK, Carroll JD, Cleveland J, Reece TB, Gillinov AM, Rodriguez L, Whitlow P, Woo YJ, Herrmann HC, Young JN. Late surgical mitral valve repair after percutaneous repair with the MitraClip system. J Card Surg. 2009 Nov-Dec;24(6):677-81. doi: 10.1111/j.1540-8191.2009.00901.x. Epub 2009 Jul 24.
Silvestry FE, Rodriguez LL, Herrmann HC, Rohatgi S, Weiss SJ, Stewart WJ, Homma S, Goyal N, Pulerwitz T, Zunamon A, Hamilton A, Merlino J, Martin R, Krabill K, Block PC, Whitlow P, Tuzcu EM, Kapadia S, Gray WA, Reisman M, Wasserman H, Schwartz A, Foster E, Feldman T, Wiegers SE. Echocardiographic guidance and assessment of percutaneous repair for mitral regurgitation with the Evalve MitraClip: lessons learned from EVEREST I. J Am Soc Echocardiogr. 2007 Oct;20(10):1131-40. Epub 2007 Jun 13.
Herrmann HC, Rohatgi S, Wasserman HS, Block P, Gray W, Hamilton A, Zunamon A, Homma S, Di Tullio MR, Kraybill K, Merlino J, Martin R, Rodriguez L, Stewart WJ, Whitlow P, Wiegers SE, Silvestry FE, Foster E, Feldman T. Mitral valve hemodynamic effects of percutaneous edge-to-edge repair with the MitraClip device for mitral regurgitation. Catheter Cardiovasc Interv. 2006 Dec;68(6):821-8.
Feldman T, Foster E, Glower DD, Kar S, Rinaldi MJ, Fail PS, Smalling RW, Siegel R, Rose GA, Engeron E, Loghin C, Trento A, Skipper ER, Fudge T, Letsou GV, Massaro JM, Mauri L; EVEREST II Investigators. Percutaneous repair or surgery for mitral regurgitation. N Engl J Med. 2011 Apr 14;364(15):1395-406. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1009355. Epub 2011 Apr 4. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2011 Jul 14;365(2):189. Glower, Donald G [corrected to Glower, Donald D].
Ladich E, Michaels MB, Jones RM, McDermott E, Coleman L, Komtebedde J, Glower D, Argenziano M, Feldman T, Nakano M, Virmani R; Endovascular Valve Edge-to-Edge Repair Study (EVEREST) Investigators. Pathological healing response of explanted MitraClip devices. Circulation. 2011 Apr 5;123(13):1418-27. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.110.978130. Epub 2011 Mar 21.
Siegel RJ, Biner S, Rafique AM, Rinaldi M, Lim S, Fail P, Hermiller J, Smalling R, Whitlow PL, Herrmann HC, Foster E, Feldman T, Glower D, Kar S; EVEREST Investigators. The acute hemodynamic effects of MitraClip therapy. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2011 Apr 19;57(16):1658-65. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2010.11.043.
Grayburn PA, Roberts BJ, Aston S, Anwar A, Hebeler RF Jr, Brown DL, Mack MJ. Mechanism and severity of mitral regurgitation by transesophageal echocardiography in patients referred for percutaneous valve repair. Am J Cardiol. 2011 Sep 15;108(6):882-7. doi: 10.1016/j.amjcard.2011.05.013. Epub 2011 Jul 7.
Nor Aripin KN, Sammons HM, Choonara I. Published pediatric randomized drug trials in developing countries, 1996-2002. Paediatr Drugs. 2010 Apr 1;12(2):99-103. doi: 10.2165/11316260-000000000-00000.
Auricchio A, Schillinger W, Meyer S, Maisano F, Hoffmann R, Ussia GP, Pedrazzini GB, van der Heyden J, Fratini S, Klersy C, Komtebedde J, Franzen O; PERMIT-CARE Investigators. Correction of mitral regurgitation in nonresponders to cardiac resynchronization therapy by MitraClip improves symptoms and promotes reverse remodeling. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2011 Nov 15;58(21):2183-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2011.06.061.
Conradi L, Treede H, Franzen O, Seiffert M, Baldus S, Schirmer J, Meinertz T, Reichenspurner H. Impact of MitraClip therapy on secondary mitral valve surgery in patients at high surgical risk. Eur J Cardiothorac Surg. 2011 Dec;40(6):1521-6. doi: 10.1016/j.ejcts.2011.03.007. Epub 2011 Apr 15.
Divchev D, Kische S, Paranskaya L, Schneider H, Rehders T, Ortak J, Akin I, Turan G, Turan CH, Steinhoff G, Nöldge-Schomburg G, Nienaber CA, Ince H. In-hospital outcome of patients with severe mitral valve regurgitation classified as inoperable and treated with the MitraClip® device. J Interv Cardiol. 2012 Apr;25(2):180-9. doi: 10.1111/j.1540-8183.2011.00688.x. Epub 2011 Dec 21.
Franzen O, van der Heyden J, Baldus S, Schlüter M, Schillinger W, Butter C, Hoffmann R, Corti R, Pedrazzini G, Swaans MJ, Neuss M, Rudolph V, Sürder D, Grünenfelder J, Eulenburg C, Reichenspurner H, Meinertz T, Auricchio A. MitraClip® therapy in patients with end-stage systolic heart failure. Eur J Heart Fail. 2011 May;13(5):569-76. doi: 10.1093/eurjhf/hfr029. Epub 2011 Apr 6.
Gaemperli O, Moccetti M, Surder D, Biaggi P, Hurlimann D, Kretschmar O, Buehler I, Bettex D, Felix C, Luscher TF, Falk V, Grunenfelder J, Corti R. Acute haemodynamic changes after percutaneous mitral valve repair: relation to mid-term outcomes. Heart. 2012 Jan;98(2):126-32. doi: 10.1136/heartjnl-2011-300705. Epub 2011 Oct 7.
Pleger ST, Mereles D, Schulz-Schönhagen M, Krumsdorf U, Chorianopoulos E, Rottbauer W, Katus HA, Bekeredjian R. Acute safety and 30-day outcome after percutaneous edge-to-edge repair of mitral regurgitation in very high-risk patients. Am J Cardiol. 2011 Nov 15;108(10):1478-82. doi: 10.1016/j.amjcard.2011.06.069. Epub 2011 Sep 3.
Rudolph V, Knap M, Franzen O, Schlüter M, de Vries T, Conradi L, Schirmer J, Treede H, Wegscheider K, Costard-Jäckle A, Meinertz T, Reichenspurner H, Baldus S. Echocardiographic and clinical outcomes of MitraClip therapy in patients not amenable to surgery. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2011 Nov 15;58(21):2190-5. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2011.07.047.
Schillinger W, Athanasiou T, Weicken N, Berg L, Tichelbäcker T, Puls M, Hünlich M, Wachter R, Helms HJ, Seipelt R, Schöndube FA, Hasenfuss G. Impact of the learning curve on outcomes after percutaneous mitral valve repair with MitraClip and lessons learned after the first 75 consecutive patients. Eur J Heart Fail. 2011 Dec;13(12):1331-9. doi: 10.1093/eurjhf/hfr141. Epub 2011 Oct 24. Erratum in: Eur J Heart Fail. 2012 Jun;14(6):679.
Treede H, Schirmer J, Rudolph V, Franzen O, Knap M, Schluter M, Conradi L, Seiffert M, Koschyk D, Meinertz T, Baldus S, Reichenspurner H. A heart team's perspective on interventional mitral valve repair: percutaneous clip implantation as an important adjunct to a surgical mitral valve program for treatment of high-risk patients. J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 2012 Jan;143(1):78-84. doi: 10.1016/j.jtcvs.2011.09.033. Epub 2011 Oct 27.
Ussia GP, Cammalleri V, Sarkar K, Scandura S, Immè S, Pistritto AM, Caggegi A, Chiarandà M, Mangiafico S, Barbanti M, Scarabelli M, Mulè M, Aruta P, Tamburino C. Quality of life following percutaneous mitral valve repair with the MitraClip System. Int J Cardiol. 2012 Mar 8;155(2):194-200. doi: 10.1016/j.ijcard.2011.08.853. Epub 2011 Sep 28.
Chan PH, Di Mario C, Franzen O. Dissociation between anatomical and functional results after MitraClip implantation. Int J Cardiol. 2012 Mar 8;155(2):175-6. doi: 10.1016/j.ijcard.2011.10.047. Epub 2011 Nov 9.
Rogers JH, Bolling SF. Editorial comment: Surgery after MitraClip therapy: you can't win them all. Eur J Cardiothorac Surg. 2011 Dec;40(6):1526-8. doi: 10.1016/j.ejcts.2011.04.024. Epub 2011 Jun 12.
Turi ZG, Rosenbloom M. An option for the high-comorbidity patient with mitral regurgitation. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2012 Jan 10;59(2):140-2. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2011.09.049.
Altiok E, Becker M, Hamada S, Reith S, Marx N, Hoffmann R. Optimized guidance of percutaneous edge-to edge repair of the mitral valve using real-time 3-D transesophageal echocardiography. Clin Res Cardiol. 2011 Aug;100(8):675-81. doi: 10.1007/s00392-011-0296-1. Epub 2011 Mar 3.
Bergsland J, Mujanovic E, Elle OJ, Mirtaheri P, Fosse E. Minimally invasive repair of the mitral valve: technological and clinical developments. Minim Invasive Ther Allied Technol. 2011 Apr;20(2):72-7. doi: 10.3109/13645706.2011.554843. Review.
Biner S, Perk G, Kar S, Rafique AM, Slater J, Shiota T, Hussaini A, Chou S, Kronzon I, Siegel RJ. Utility of combined two-dimensional and three-dimensional transesophageal imaging for catheter-based mitral valve clip repair of mitral regurgitation. J Am Soc Echocardiogr. 2011 Jun;24(6):611-7. doi: 10.1016/j.echo.2011.02.005. Epub 2011 Mar 23.
Buch MH, Trento A, Kar S. Is there a role for surgeons in transcatheter mitral valve procedures? Curr Opin Cardiol. 2011 Mar;26(2):99-105. doi: 10.1097/HCO.0b013e32834398a0. Review.
Chiam PT, Ruiz CE. Percutaneous transcatheter mitral valve repair: a classification of the technology. JACC Cardiovasc Interv. 2011 Jan;4(1):1-13. doi: 10.1016/j.jcin.2010.09.023. Review.
Cikirikcioglu M, Cherian S, Schussler O, Kalangos A. Regarding "The EVEREST II Trial: design and rationale for a randomized study of the Evalve MitraClip system compared with mitral valve surgery for mitral regurgitation". Am Heart J. 2011 Jul;162(1):e11-2; author reply e13. doi: 10.1016/j.ahj.2011.04.004. Epub 2011 Jun 12.
Cleland JG, Coletta AP, Freemantle N, Clark AL. Clinical trials update from the American College of Cardiology Meeting 2011: STICH, NorthStar, TARGET, and EVEREST II. Eur J Heart Fail. 2011 Jul;13(7):805-8. doi: 10.1093/eurjhf/hfr077.
Dixon SR, Grines CL, O'Neill WW. The year in interventional cardiology. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2010 May 18;55(20):2272-86. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2010.02.024. Review.
Dudiy Y, Jelnin V, Ruiz CE. Percutaneous mitral valve treatment. Minerva Cardioangiol. 2011 Oct;59(5):507-18.
Farouque HM, Clark DJ. Percutaneous mitral valve leaflet repair for mitral regurgitation: NICE guidance. Heart. 2010 Mar;96(5):385-7. doi: 10.1136/hrt.2009.183269.
Feldman T, Cilingiroglu M. Percutaneous leaflet repair and annuloplasty for mitral regurgitation. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2011 Feb 1;57(5):529-37. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2010.10.012. Review.
George JC, Varghese V, Dangas G, Feldman TE. Percutaneous mitral valve repair: lessons from the EVEREST II (Endovascular Valve Edge-to-Edge REpair Study) and beyond. JACC Cardiovasc Interv. 2011 Jul;4(7):825-7. doi: 10.1016/j.jcin.2011.05.010.
Goldberg SL, Feldman T. Percutaneous mitral valve interventions: overview of new approaches. Curr Cardiol Rep. 2010 Sep;12(5):404-12. doi: 10.1007/s11886-010-0130-9. Review.
Hussaini A, Kar S. Percutaneous mitral valve repair: potential in heart failure management. Curr Heart Fail Rep. 2010 Mar;7(1):22-6. doi: 10.1007/s11897-010-0006-8. Review.
Jilaihawi H, Hussaini A, Kar S. MitraClip: a novel percutaneous approach to mitral valve repair. J Zhejiang Univ Sci B. 2011 Aug;12(8):633-7. doi: 10.1631/jzus.B1101009. Review.
Lam YY, Lee PW, Yong G, Yan BP. Investigational devices for mitral regurgitation: state of the art. Expert Rev Med Devices. 2011 Jan;8(1):105-14. doi: 10.1586/erd.10.52. Review.
Maisano F, Godino C, Giacomini A, Denti P, Arendar I, Buzzatti N, Canna GL, Alfieri O, Colombo A. Clinical trial experience with the MitraClip catheter based mitral valve repair system. Int J Cardiovasc Imaging. 2011 Dec;27(8):1155-64. doi: 10.1007/s10554-011-9872-8. Epub 2011 Apr 19. Review.
Maisano F, Alfieri O, La Canna G. Percutaneous mitral repair with the MitraClip. Ann Fr Anesth Reanim. 2011 May;30 Suppl 1:S33-7. doi: 10.1016/S0750-7658(11)70008-9. Review.
Maisano F, Godino C, Giacomini A, Denti P, Buzzatti N, Arendar I, Colombo A, Alfieri O, La Canna G. Patient selection for MitraClip therapy impaired left ventricular systolic function. Minerva Cardioangiol. 2011 Oct;59(5):455-71. Review.
Maisano F, La Canna G, Colombo A, Alfieri O. The evolution from surgery to percutaneous mitral valve interventions: the role of the edge-to-edge technique. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2011 Nov 15;58(21):2174-82. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2011.07.046. Review.
Ong SH, Beucher H, Mueller R, Gerckens U, Boekstegers P. Percutaneous double-valve interventions for aortic stenosis and pure mitral regurgitation. Am J Cardiol. 2011 Sep 15;108(6):893-5. doi: 10.1016/j.amjcard.2011.05.017. Epub 2011 Jul 2.
Padala M, Keeling WB, Guyton RA, Thourani VH. Innovations in therapies for heart valve disease. Circ J. 2011;75(5):1028-41. Epub 2011 Apr 9. Review.
Rogers JH, Franzen O. Percutaneous edge-to-edge MitraClip therapy in the management of mitral regurgitation. Eur Heart J. 2011 Oct;32(19):2350-7. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehr101. Epub 2011 May 23. Review.
Saroul C, Keller G, Benaissa M, Lehot JJ. [Anesthesia for minimally invasive cardiac procedure]. Ann Fr Anesth Reanim. 2011 May;30 Suppl 1:S38-43. doi: 10.1016/S0750-7658(11)70009-0. French.
Seeburger J, Katus HA, Pleger ST, Krumsdorf U, Mohr FW, Bekeredjian R. Percutaneous and surgical treatment of mitral valve regurgitation. Dtsch Arztebl Int. 2011 Dec;108(48):816-21. doi: 10.3238/arztebl.2011.0816. Epub 2011 Dec 2. Review.
Taramasso M, Cioni M, Giacomini A, Michev I, Godino C, Montorfano M, Colombo A, Alfieri O, Maisano F. Emerging approaches of transcatheter valve repair/insertion. Cardiol Res Pract. 2010 Jul 25;2010. pii: 540749. doi: 10.4061/2010/540749.
Taylor J. The percutaneous approach to mitral valve repair. Eur Heart J. 2011 Feb;32(3):249-51. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehq463.
Vahanian A, Himbert D, Brochet E, Messika-Zeitoun D. Percutaneous mitral valve repair: the beginning of the end or the end of the beginning? F1000 Med Rep. 2010 Mar 25;2. pii: 21. doi: 10.3410/M2-21.
Van Mieghem NM, Piazza N, Anderson RH, Tzikas A, Nieman K, De Laat LE, McGhie JS, Geleijnse ML, Feldman T, Serruys PW, de Jaegere PP. Anatomy of the mitral valvular complex and its implications for transcatheter interventions for mitral regurgitation. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2010 Aug 17;56(8):617-26. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2010.04.030. Review.
Walenta K, Sinning JM, Werner C, Böhm M. Hotline update of clinical trials and registries presented at the at the European Society of Cardiology Congress in Paris 2011. Clin Res Cardiol. 2011 Nov;100(11):955-71. doi: 10.1007/s00392-011-0370-8. Epub 2011 Sep 30.
Yuksel UC, Kapadia SR, Tuzcu EM. Percutaneous mitral repair: patient selection, results, and future directions. Curr Cardiol Rep. 2011 Apr;13(2):100-6. doi: 10.1007/s11886-010-0158-x. Review.
Altiok E, Paetsch I, Jahnke C, Brehmer K, Reith S, Becker M, Marx N, Hoffmann R. Percutaneous edge-to-edge mitral valve repair: assessment of immediate post-procedural treatment effect using color 3-dimensional transesophageal echocardiography and cardiac magnetic resonance imaging. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2011 Sep 6;58(11):e21. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2010.11.088.
Barbanti M, Ussia GP, Tamburino C. Percutaneous treatment of aortic stenosis and mitral regurgitation in the same patient: first human cases description. Catheter Cardiovasc Interv. 2011 Oct 1;78(4):650-5. doi: 10.1002/ccd.23015. Epub 2011 Jul 25.
Bekeredjian R, Mereles D, Pleger S, Krumsdorf U, Katus HA, Rottbauer W. Large atrial thrombus formation after MitraClip implantation: is anticoagulation mandatory? J Heart Valve Dis. 2011 Mar;20(2):146-8.
Conradi L, Treede H, Baldus S, Seiffert M, Blankenberg S, Reichenspurner H. [Treating mitral regurgitation: a surgical and interventional update]. Herz. 2011 Dec;36(8):677-85. doi: 10.1007/s00059-011-3531-7. German.
Franzen O, von Samson P, Dodge-Khatami A, Geffert G, Baldus S. Percutaneous edge-to-edge repair of tricuspid regurgitation in congenitally corrected transposition of the great arteries. Congenit Heart Dis. 2011 Jan-Feb;6(1):57-9. doi: 10.1111/j.1747-0803.2010.00428.x.
Franzen O, Seiffert M, Baldus S, Conradi L, Schirmer J, Kubik M, Meinertz T, Reichenspurner H, Treede H. Percutaneous mitral valve repair as a bail-out strategy for patients with severe mitral regurgitation after cardiac surgery. J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 2011 Jul;142(1):227-30. doi: 10.1016/j.jtcvs.2010.10.037. Epub 2011 Jan 17.
Ihlemann N, Franzen O, Jørgensen E, Hansen PB, Hassager C, Møller JE, Søndergaard L. Promising results after percutaneous mitral valve repair. Dan Med Bull. 2011 Jul;58(7):A4299.
Kische S, Nienaber C, Ince H. Use of four MitraClip devices in a patient with ischemic cardiomyopathy and mitral regurgitation: "zipping by clipping". Catheter Cardiovasc Interv. 2012 Nov 15;80(6):1007-13. doi: 10.1002/ccd.23431. Epub 2012 Jan 10.
Kluge JG, Hagendorff A, Pfeiffer D, Jurisch D, Tarr A. Active infective prosthetic endocarditis after percutaneous edge-to-edge mitral valve repair. Eur J Echocardiogr. 2011 Sep;12(9):710. doi: 10.1093/ejechocard/jer062. Epub 2011 Jul 23.
Madder RD, Safian RD, Gallagher M, Senter SR, Hanzel GS. The first report of transcatheter aortic valve implantation and percutaneous mitral valve repair in the same patient. JACC Cardiovasc Interv. 2011 Jul;4(7):824. doi: 10.1016/j.jcin.2011.05.009.
Mayr NP, Martin K, Hausleiter J, Brown A, Tassani P. Ventilation manoeuvres facilitate MitraClip placement. Heart. 2011 Oct;97(20):1717; author reply 1717. doi: 10.1136/heartjnl-2011-300587. Epub 2011 Jul 31.
Paranskaya L, Turan I, Kische S, Nienaber C, Ince H. Rapid pacing facilitates grasping and MitraClip implantation in severe mitral leaflet prolapse. Clin Res Cardiol. 2012 Jan;101(1):69-71. doi: 10.1007/s00392-011-0384-2. Epub 2011 Nov 19.
Sürder D, Altwegg L, Hürlimann D, Felix C, Grünenfelder J, Corti R. Percutaneous double valve intervention. Eur Heart J. 2011 Mar;32(5):636. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehq378. Epub 2010 Nov 23.
Van den Branden BJ, Post MC, Swaans MJ, Rensing BJ, Eefting FD, Plokker HW, Jaarsma W, Van der Heyden JA. Percutaneous mitral valve repair using the edge-to-edge technique in a high-risk population. Neth Heart J. 2010 Sep;18(9):437-43.
Van den Branden BJ, Swaans MJ, Post MC, Rensing BJ, Eefting FD, Jaarsma W, Van der Heyden JA. Redo mitral valve clipping after partial clip detachment. JACC Cardiovasc Interv. 2010 Feb;3(2):251-2. doi: 10.1016/j.jcin.2009.09.018.
Zuern CS, Schreieck J, Weig HJ, Gawaz M, May AE. Percutaneous mitral valve repair using the MitraClip in acute cardiogenic shock. Clin Res Cardiol. 2011 Aug;100(8):719-21. doi: 10.1007/s00392-011-0324-1. Epub 2011 May 24.
Alfieri O, Denti P. Alfieri stitch and its impact on mitral clip. Eur J Cardiothorac Surg. 2011 Jun;39(6):807-8. doi: 10.1016/j.ejcts.2011.01.017. Epub 2011 Feb 25.
Asgar AW, Khairy P. Percutaneous repair or surgery for mitral regurgitation. N Engl J Med. 2011 Jul 7;365(1):90; author reply 91. doi: 10.1056/NEJMc1105564#SA1.
Gorman RC, Gillespie MJ, Gorman JH 3rd. Percutaneous repair or surgery for mitral regurgitation. N Engl J Med. 2011 Jul 7;365(1):90-1; author reply 91. doi: 10.1056/NEJMc1105564#SA2.
Murphy MO, Ahmed K, Athanasiou T. Surgery for chronic ischemic mitral regurgitation - which mitral intervention? Expert Rev Cardiovasc Ther. 2011 May;9(5):587-97. doi: 10.1586/erc.11.50. Review.
Osório J, Fuster V. Valve interventions-a word of caution. Nat Rev Cardiol. 2010 Jul;7(7):355. doi: 10.1038/nrcardio.2010.83.
Otto CM, Verrier ED. Mitral regurgitation--what is best for my patient? N Engl J Med. 2011 Apr 14;364(15):1462-3. doi: 10.1056/NEJMe1102013. Epub 2011 Apr 4.
Skipper ER, Accola KD, Sade RM. Must surgeons tell mitral valve repair candidates about a new percutaneous repair device that is only available elsewhere? Ann Thorac Surg. 2011 Oct;92(4):1163-9. doi: 10.1016/j.athoracsur.2011.04.096.
Thompson KA, Philip KJ, Simsir S, Schwarz ER. The new concept of ''interventional heart failure therapy'': part 2--inotropes, valvular disease, pumps, and transplantation. J Cardiovasc Pharmacol Ther. 2010 Sep;15(3):231-43. doi: 10.1177/1074248410369111. Epub 2010 Jul 1. Review.
Vahanian A, Iung B. 'Edge to edge' percutaneous mitral valve repair in mitral regurgitation: it can be done but should it be done? Eur Heart J. 2010 Jun;31(11):1301-4. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehq088. Epub 2010 Apr 11.
Vahanian A, Iung B, Himbert D, Nataf P. Changing demographics of valvular heart disease and impact on surgical and transcatheter valve therapies. Int J Cardiovasc Imaging. 2011 Dec;27(8):1115-22. doi: 10.1007/s10554-011-9804-7. Epub 2011 Feb 24. Review.
van den Heuvel AF, Alfieri O, Mariani MA. MitraClip in end-stage heart failure: a realistic alternative to surgery? Eur J Heart Fail. 2011 May;13(5):472-4. doi: 10.1093/eurjhf/hfr038.
Altiok E, Becker M, Hamada S, Grabskaya E, Reith S, Marx N, Hoffmann R. Real-time 3D TEE allows optimized guidance of percutaneous edge-to-edge repair of the mitral valve. JACC Cardiovasc Imaging. 2010 Nov;3(11):1196-8. doi: 10.1016/j.jcmg.2010.07.010.
Avanzini A, Donzella G, Libretti L. Functional and structural effects of percutaneous edge-to-edge double-orifice repair under cardiac cycle in comparison with suture repair. Proc Inst Mech Eng H. 2011 Oct;225(10):959-71.
Delgado V, Kapadia S, Marsan NA, Schalij MJ, Tuzcu EM, Bax JJ. Multimodality imaging before, during, and after percutaneous mitral valve repair. Heart. 2011 Oct;97(20):1704-14. doi: 10.1136/hrt.2011.227785. Review.
Ewe SH, Klautz RJ, Schalij MJ, Delgado V. Role of computed tomography imaging for transcatheter valvular repair/insertion. Int J Cardiovasc Imaging. 2011 Dec;27(8):1179-93. doi: 10.1007/s10554-011-9830-5. Epub 2011 Feb 26. Review.
Lin BA, Forouhar AS, Pahlevan NM, Anastassiou CA, Grayburn PA, Thomas JD, Gharib M. Color Doppler jet area overestimates regurgitant volume when multiple jets are present. J Am Soc Echocardiogr. 2010 Sep;23(9):993-1000. doi: 10.1016/j.echo.2010.06.011. Epub 2010 Aug 8.
Pedrazzini GB, Klimusina J, Pasotti E, Moccetti T, Faletra FF. Complications of percutaneous edge-to-edge mitral valve repair: the role of real-time three-dimensional transesophageal echocardiography. J Am Soc Echocardiogr. 2011 Jun;24(6):706.e5-7. doi: 10.1016/j.echo.2010.08.017. Epub 2010 Sep 26.
Siegel RJ, Luo H, Biner S. Transcatheter valve repair/implantation. Int J Cardiovasc Imaging. 2011 Dec;27(8):1165-77. doi: 10.1007/s10554-011-9833-2. Epub 2011 Feb 23.
Franzen O, Baldus S, Rudolph V, Meyer S, Knap M, Koschyk D, Treede H, Barmeyer A, Schofer J, Costard-Jäckle A, Schlüter M, Reichenspurner H, Meinertz T. Acute outcomes of MitraClip therapy for mitral regurgitation in high-surgical-risk patients: emphasis on adverse valve morphology and severe left ventricular dysfunction. Eur Heart J. 2010 Jun;31(11):1373-81. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehq050. Epub 2010 Mar 10.
Yong ZY, Bouma BJ, Koch KT, Baan J. Immediate reduction of mitral regurgitation by percutaneous mitral valve repair with the MitraClip®. Neth Heart J. 2010 Dec;18(12):606.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>David Muller, MD</name>
      <address>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney, Australia</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>