<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6696">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/09/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/09/2017</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT03277105</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Study of Subcutaneous Versus (vs.) Intravenous Administration of Daratumumab in Participants With Relapsed or Refractory Multiple Myeloma</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 3 Randomized, Multicenter Study of Subcutaneous vs. Intravenous Administration of Daratumumab in Subjects With Relapsed or Refractory Multiple Myeloma</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>2017-000206-38</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>CR108342</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Multiple Myeloma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cancer types</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Dara SC
Treatment: drugs - Dara IV

Experimental: Dara SC - Participants will receive a fixed dose of daratumumab as 1800 milligram (mg) subcutaneously (Dara SC) co-formulated with recombinant human hyaluronidase (rHuPH20) 2000 Unit per milliliter (U/mL), once weekly in Cycle 1 and 2, every 2 weeks in Cycle 3 to 6, every 4 weeks in Cycle 7 and thereafter until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity or the end of study. The duration for each cycle is 4 weeks.

Active Comparator: Dara IV - Participants will receive daratumumab for intravenous infusion (Dara IV) 16 mg/kg by once weekly in Cycle 1 and 2, every 2 weeks in Cycle 3 to 6, every 4 weeks at Day 1 in Cycle 7 and thereafter until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity or the end of study.


Treatment: drugs: Dara SC
Participants will receive a fixed dose of Dara SC as 1800 mg daratumumab with rHuPH20 2000 U/mL, once weekly in Cycle 1 and 2, every 2 weeks in Cycle 3 to 6, every 4 weeks in Cycle 7 and thereafter until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity or the end of study.

Treatment: drugs: Dara IV
Participants will receive Dara IV 16 mg/kg once weekly at in Cycle 1 and 2, every 2 weeks in Cycle 3 to 6, every 4 weeks in Cycle 7 and thereafter until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity or the end of study.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Response Rate (ORR) - The ORR is defined as the proportion of participants who achieve partial response (PR) or better according to international myeloma working group (IMWG) criteria, during or after study treatment. IMWG criteria for PR: greater than or equal to (&gt;=) 50 percent (%) reduction of serum M-protein and reduction in 24-hour urinary M-protein by &gt;=90% or to lesss than (&lt;) 200 mg/24 hours, If the serum and urine M-protein are not measurable, a decrease of &gt;=50% in the difference between involved and uninvolved free light chain (FLC) levels is required in place of the Mprotein criteria, If serum and urine M-protein are not measurable, and serum free light assay is also not measurable, &gt;=50% reduction in bone marrow plasma cells (PCs) is required in place of M-protein, provided baseline bone marrow plasma cell percentage was &gt;=30%. In addition to the above criteria, if present at baseline, a &gt;=50% reduction in the size of soft tissue plasmacytomas is also required.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months after last participant randomized (approximately 2 years)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximum Trough Concentration (Ctrough) of Daratumumab - Maximum Ctrough is defined as the serum predose concentration of daratumumab on Cycle 3 Day 1.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cycle 3 (each cycle 28 days) Day 1</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of participants With Infusion-Related Reactions (IRR) - The Percentage of Participants with infusion reactions will be reported.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months after last participant randomized (approximately 2 years)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression-Free Survival (PFS) - PFS is defined as time from date of randomization to either progression of disease (PD), death due to any cause, whichever occurs first. According to IMWG criteria: Increase of 25% from lowest response value in any one of the following: Serum M component (absolute increase must be &gt;=0.5 gram per deciliter (g/dL), Urine M-component (absolute increase must be &gt;=200 mg/24 hours), Participants without measurable serum and urine Mprotein levels: difference between involved and uninvolved free light chain (FLC) levels (absolute increase must be &gt;10 milligrams per deciliter (mg/dL), participants without measurable serum and urine M-protein levels and without measurable disease by FLC levels, bone marrow PC% (absolute percentage must be &gt;=10%), definite development of new bone lesions or soft tissue plasmacytomas or increase in size of bone lesions or tissue plasmacytomas and development of hypercalcemia (serum calcium &gt;11.5 mg/dL) that can be attributed solely to PC proliferative disorder.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months after last participant randomized (approximately 2 years) and 18 months after the last participant randomized (approximately 3 years)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Very Good Partial Response (VGPR) or Better Rate - The VGPR or better rate, defined as the proportion of participants achieving VGPR and complete response (CR) (including stringent complete response [sCR]) according IMWG criteria during or after the study treatment. IMWG criteria for VGPR: Serum and urine M-component detectable by immunofixation but not on electrophoresis, or greater than equal to (&gt;=) 90 percent (%) reduction in serum M-protein plus urine M-protein &lt;100 milligram (mg)/24 hours, CR: Negative immunofixation on the serum and urine, disappearance of any soft tissue plasmacytomas and &lt;5% plasma cellS (PCs) in bone marrow. sCR: CR plus normal free light chain (FLC) ratio, and absence of clonal PCs by immunohistochemistry (IHC), immunofluorescencea or 2- to 4 color flow cytometry.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months after last participant randomized (approximately 2 years) and 18 months after the last participant randomized (approximately 3 years)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Complete Response (Including sCR) or Better Rate - Complete response is based on serum M-Protein assessments. IMWG criteria for CR: Negative immunofixation on the serum and urine, and disappearance of any soft tissue plasmacytomas, and &lt;5% PCs in bone marrow. sCR: CR plus normal FLC ratio, and absence of clonal PCs by IHC, immunofluorescencea or 2- to 4 color flow cytometry.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months after last participant randomized (approximately 2 years) and 18 months after the last participant randomized (approximately 3 years)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Next Treatment - Time to next therapy is defined as the time from randomization to the start of the first subsequent anti-cancer therapy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months after last participant randomized (approximately 2 years) and 18 months after the last participant randomized (approximately 3 years)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Survival (OS) - OS is defined as the time from the date of randomization to the date of the participant's death.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months after last participant randomized (approximately 2 years) and 18 months after the last participant randomized (approximately 3 years)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient-Reported Satisfaction With Therapy - Patient-reported satisfaction with therapy is defined as the mean of responses to 7 of 9 questions in the modified cancer therapy satisfaction questionnaire (modified-CTSQ). Modified-CTSQ contain 9 items specific to satisfaction with therapy and for comparison of IV with SC administration. Satisfaction with therapy is calculated based on 7-items using 5-point verbal rating scale, 1, never; 5, always. Scores will be averaged and transformed to a 0-100 scale; higher scores represent better health.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months after last participant randomized (approximately 2 years) and 18 months after the last participant randomized (approximately 3 years)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of Response - Duration of response is defined as date of onset of first response until date of disease progression or death.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months after last participant randomized (approximately 2 years) and 18 months after the last participant randomized (approximately 3 years)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to response - Time to response is defined as the time from randomization until onset of first response.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months after last participant randomized (approximately 2 years) and 18 months after the last participant randomized (approximately 3 years)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Evidence of a response (Partial response [PR] or better based on investigator's
             determination of response by international myeloma working group [IMWG] criteria) to
             at least 1 prior treatment regimen

          -  Received at least 3 prior lines of therapy including a proteasome inhibitor (PI)
             (greater than or equal to [&gt;=] 2 cycles or 2 months of treatment) and an
             immunomodulatory drug (IMiD) (&gt;=2 cycles or 2 months of treatment) in any order during
             the course of treatment (except for participants who discontinued either of these
             treatments due to a severe allergic reaction within the first 2 cycles/months). A
             single line of therapy may consist of 1 or more agents, and may include induction,
             hematopoietic stem cell transplantation, and maintenance therapy. Radiotherapy,
             bisphosphonate, or a single short course of corticosteroids (no more than the
             equivalent of dexamethasone 40 milligram/day [mg/day] for 4 days) would not be
             considered prior lines of therapy

          -  Documented multiple myeloma as defined by the criteria below:

               1. Multiple myeloma diagnosis according to the IMWG diagnostic criteria

               2. Measurable disease at Screening as defined by any of the following:

                    1. Immunoglobulin(Ig) G multiple myeloma: serum M-protein level &gt;=1.0 g/dL or
                       urine M-protein level &gt;=200 mg/24 hours; or

                    2. IgA, IgD, IgE, IgM multiple myeloma: serum M-protein level &gt;=0.5 gram per
                       deciliter (g/dL) or urine M-protein level &gt;=200 mg/24 hours; or

                    3. Light chain multiple myeloma without measurable disease in the serum or the
                       urine: Serum immunoglobulin free light chain (FLC) &gt;=10 mg/dL and abnormal
                       serum immunoglobulin kappa lambda FLC ratio

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status score of 0, 1, or 2

          -  Meet the clinical laboratory criteria as specified in the protocol

          -  Women of childbearing potential must have a negative urine or serum pregnancy test at
             screening within 14 days prior to randomization</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Received daratumumab or other anti-CD38 therapies previously

          -  Received anti-myeloma treatment within 2 weeks or 5 pharmacokinetic half-lives of the
             treatment, whichever is longer, before the date of randomization. The only exception
             is emergency use of a short course of corticosteroids (equivalent of dexamethasone 40
             mg/day for a maximum of 4 days before treatment

          -  Received autologous stem cell transplant within 12 weeks before the date of
             randomization, or the participant has previously received allogeneic stem cell
             transplant (regardless of timing)

          -  Plans to undergo a stem cell transplant prior to progression of disease on this study
             (these participants should not be enrolled to reduce disease burden prior to
             transplant)

          -  History of malignancy (other than multiple myeloma) within 3 years before the date of
             randomization (exceptions are squamous and basal cell carcinomas of the skin and
             carcinoma in situ of the cervix, or breast, or other non-invasive lesion, that in the
             opinion of the investigator, with concurrence with the sponsor's medical monitor, is
             considered cured with minimal risk of recurrence within 3 years)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>480</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>8/10/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>Monash Health, Monash Medical Centre - Clayton</hospital>
    <hospital>St. Vincent's Hospital Melbourne - Fitzroy</hospital>
    <hospital>Alfred Health - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Fiona Stanley Hospital - Murdoch</hospital>
    <hospital>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital - Nedlands</hospital>
    <hospital>Calvary Mater Newcastle Hospital - New South Wales</hospital>
    <hospital>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital - Woodville South</hospital>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
    <postcode>3065 - Fitzroy</postcode>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>6150 - Murdoch</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
    <postcode>2298 - New South Wales</postcode>
    <postcode>5011 - Woodville South</postcode>
    <postcode>4102 - Woolloongabba</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Massachusetts</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Missouri</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Barretos</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Florianópolis</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Jaú</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Joinville</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Passo Fundo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Porto Alegre</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Rio De Janeiro</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Salvador</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Sao Paulo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>São José Do Rio Preto</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>São Paulo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Alberta</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>British Columbia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Nova Scotia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Quebec</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Brno</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Hradec Kralove</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Olomouc</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Ostrava</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Plzen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Praha 10</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Praha 2</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Caen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Lille Cedex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Nantes Cedex 1</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Pessac</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Pierre-Bénite</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Poitiers</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Vandoeuvre Les Nancy</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Athens Attica</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Hadera</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Haifa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Jerusalem</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Nahariya</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Petah Tikva</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Ramat Gan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Rehovot</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Tel Aviv</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Busan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Goyang-Si</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Incheon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Seoul</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Ulsan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Brzozow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Bydgoszcz</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Chorzów</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Gdynia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Krakow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Legnica</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Lublin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Poznan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Warszawa Ul</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Badalona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Girona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Granada</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>La Laguna</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Leon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Pamplona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Pozuelo De Alarcon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Salamanca</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Valencia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Falun</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Helsingborg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Huddinge</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Lund</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Stockholm</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Umea</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Uppsala</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Changhua</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Taichung City</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Taichung</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Tainan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Taipei</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Taoyuan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ukraine</country>
      <state>Cherkassy</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ukraine</country>
      <state>Dnepropetrovsk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ukraine</country>
      <state>Ivano-Frankivsk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ukraine</country>
      <state>Kharkiv</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ukraine</country>
      <state>Kiev</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ukraine</country>
      <state>Lviv</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ukraine</country>
      <state>Poltava</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ukraine</country>
      <state>Zaporizhzhya</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Blackpool</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Bournemouth</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Leicester</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Manchester</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Nottingham</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Surrey</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Wolverhampton</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to show that subcutaneous (SC) administration of daratumumab
      co-formulated with recombinant human hyaluronidase PH20 (Dara SC) is non-inferior to
      intravenous (IV) administration of daratumumab (Dara IV) in terms of the overall response
      rate (ORR) and maximum trough concentration (Ctrough).</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03277105</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC Clinical Trial</name>
      <address>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Study contact</name>
      <address />
      <phone>844-434-4210</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>JNJ.CT@sylogent.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>