<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5858">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/04/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/04/2016</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02751632</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Staged Treatment in Early Psychosis Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Staged Treatment in Early Psychosis (STEP): A Sequential Multistage Randomized Clinical Trial (SMART) of Interventions for Ultra High Risk (UHR) of Psychosis Patients.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>STEP</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>1U01MH105258-01</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>2015.173</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Psychotic Disorders</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Personality Disorders</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Psychosis and personality disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Behaviour - Support and Problem Solving Therapy
Behaviour - Cognitive Behavioural Case Management
Treatment: drugs - Fluoxetine
Treatment: drugs - Placebo
Behaviour - 3-monthly monitoring

Experimental: Step 1-Regular SPS Therapy - Support and Problem Solving Therapy delivered to all study participants over a six-week period with a minimum of three sessions.

Experimental: Responders- Monthly SPS Therapy - Participants are randomised to receive monthly Support and Problem Solving Therapy for up to 12 months.

Experimental: Responders- 3-monthly monitoring - Participants are randomised to be monitored for risk every 3 months for up to 12 months.

Experimental: Step 2- Regular SPS Therapy - Participants are randomised to receive regular sessions of Support and Problem Solving Therapy, with a minimum of six sessions delivered over an 18-week period.

Experimental: Step 2- Regular CBCM - Participants are randomised to receive regular sessions of Cognitive Behavioural Case Management, with a minimum of six sessions delivered over an 18-week period.

Experimental: Step 3- Regular CBCM + Fluoxetine - Participants are randomised to receive either Cognitive Behavioural Case Management plus an antidepressant medication for six months .

Placebo Comparator: Step 3- Regular CBCM+ placebo - Participants are randomised to receive Cognitive Behavioural Case Management plus placebo medication for six months.


Behaviour: Support and Problem Solving Therapy
Support and Problem Solving Therapy involves providing participants with emotional support and helping them to resolve their problems in day-to-day life.

Behaviour: Cognitive Behavioural Case Management
CBCM has a number of different elements including: strategies to help with stress management; therapy that targets thinking and behavioural patterns; practical assistance, as well as yoga and mindfulness.

Treatment: drugs: Fluoxetine
Participants will commence on 1 capsule of fluoxetine 20 mg, to be taken in the morning. The medication can be increased to fluoxetine 40 mg daily if there has been a poor clinical response after the first 6 weeks of treatment.

Treatment: drugs: Placebo
Participants will commence on 1 capsule of the placebo pill, to be taken in the morning. The medication can be increased to 2 placebo capsules if there has been a poor clinical response after the first 6 weeks of treatment.

Behaviour: 3-monthly monitoring
Study participants will be contacted on a 3-monthly basis by a study clinician who will be assessing the participant's risk.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Global Functioning Scale Score - To test the effect of a sequential treatment approach consisting of SPS/SPS and SPS/CBCM on functioning levels of UHR patients.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months from baseline (end of Step 2)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Global Functioning Scale Score - To test the effect of a sequential treatment approach consisting of SPS, CBCM and antidepressant medication on functioning levels of UHR patients.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months from baseline (end of Step 3)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comprehensive Assessment of At Risk Mental State score - To test the effect of a sequential treatment approach consisting of SPS, CBCM and antidepressant medication on transition to psychotic disorder.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 and 24 months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comprehensive Assessment of At Risk Mental State score - To test the effect of a sequential treatment approach on UHR status (maintenance versus remission).</outcome>
      <timepoint>1.5, 6, 12 and 24 months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Scale for Assessment of Negative Symptoms score - To test the effect of a sequential treatment approach in UHR patients on level of negative psychotic symptoms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1.5, 6, 12 and 24 months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comprehensive Assessment of At Risk Mental State score - To test relapse rates (to UHR+ status) in the relapse prevention/responder arm of the trial (SPS v monitoring).</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the first 12 months from baseline.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Montgomery Asberg Depression Rating Scale score - To test the effect of a sequential treatment approach in UHR patients on level and depressive symptoms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1.5, 6, 12 and 24 months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comprehensive Assessment of At Risk Mental State score - To test the effect of a sequential treatment approach in UHR patients on level of positive psychotic symptoms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1.5, 6, 12 and 24 months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>INCLUSION CRITERIA

          -  Age 12 -25 years (inclusive) at entry.

          -  Ability to speak adequate English (for assessment purposes).

          -  Ability to provide informed consent.

          -  Meeting one or more Ultra High Risk for psychosis groups as defined below:

        Group 1: Vulnerability Group

        Family history of psychosis in first degree relative OR Schizotypal Personality Disorder
        (as defined by Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM) IV in identified
        patient

        AND

        Drop in Functioning:

        Recency: Change in functioning occurred within last year Impact: Social and Occupational
        Functioning Assessment Scale (SOFAS) score at least 30% below previous level of functioning
        and sustained for at least one month.

        OR

        Sustained low functioning:

        Recency: For the past 12 months or longer Impact: SOFAS score of 50 or less.

        Group 2: Attenuated Psychotic Symptoms Group 2a) Subthreshold intensity:

        Intensity: Global Rating Scale Score of 3-5 on Unusual Thought Content subscale, 3-5 on
        Non-Bizarre Ideas subscale, 3-4 on Perceptual Abnormalities subscale and/or 4-5 on
        Disorganised Speech subscales of the Comprehensive Assessment of At Risk Mental States
        (CAARMS).

        Frequency: Frequency Scale Score of 3-6 on Unusual Thought Content, Non-Bizarre Ideas,
        Perceptual Abnormalities and/or Disorganised Speech subscales of the CAARMS

        Duration: symptoms present for at least one week

        Recency: symptoms present in past year

        2b) Subthreshold frequency:

        Intensity: Global Rating Scale Score of 6 on Unusual Thought Content subscale, 6 on
        Non-Bizarre Ideas subscale, 5-6 on Perceptual Abnormalities subscale and/or 6 on
        Disorganised Speech subscales of the CAARMS

        Frequency: Frequency Scale Score of 3 on Unusual Thought Content, Non-Bizarre Ideas,
        Perceptual Abnormalities and/or Disorganised Speech subscales of the CAARMS

        Recency: symptoms present in past year

        Group 3: Brief Limited Intermittent Psychotic Symptoms Intensity: Global Rating Scale Score
        of 6 on Unusual Thought Content subscale, 6 on Non-Bizarre Ideas subscale, 5 or 6 on
        Perceptual Abnormalities subscale and/or 6 on Disorganised Speech subscales of the CAARMS

        Frequency: Frequency Scale Score of 4-6 on Unusual Thought Content, Non-Bizarre Ideas,
        Perceptual Abnormalities and/or Disorganised Speech subscales

        Duration: Symptoms present for less than one week and spontaneously remit on every
        occasion.

        Recency: symptoms present in past year

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA

          -  Past history of a psychotic episode of one week or longer, whether treated with
             antipsychotic medications or not.

          -  Attenuated psychotic symptoms only present during acute intoxication.

          -  Organic brain disease known to cause psychotic symptoms, e.g. temporal lobe epilepsy.

          -  Any metabolic, endocrine or other physical illness, e.g. thyroid disease, with known
             neuropsychiatric consequences.

          -  Diagnosis of a serious developmental disorder, e.g. Severe Autism Spectrum Disorder.

          -  Premorbid Intelligence Quotient (IQ) &lt;70 and a documented history of developmental
             delay or intellectual disability.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>12</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>25</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria />
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/04/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>500</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/04/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Headspace - Craigieburn</hospital>
    <hospital>Headspace - Glenroy</hospital>
    <hospital>Orygen Youth Health Clinical Program - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Headspace - Sunshine</hospital>
    <hospital>Headspace - Werribee</hospital>
    <postcode>3064 - Craigieburn</postcode>
    <postcode>3046 - Glenroy</postcode>
    <postcode>3052 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3020 - Sunshine</postcode>
    <postcode>3030 - Werribee</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Orygen Youth Health Research Centre</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Government body</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A sequential multistage randomised clinical trial (SMART) to produce evidence to guide a
      step-wise clinical approach for the treatment of ultra high risk patients and reduction of
      risk for psychosis and other deleterious clinical and/or functional outcomes.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02751632</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Patrick McGorry, MD, PhD</name>
      <address>Orygen Youth Research Centre</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Barnaby Nelson, PhD</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+61 3 9342 2825</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>barnaby.nelson@orygen.org.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>