<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2793">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/05/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/05/2010</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01134263</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Study of a Tetravalent Dengue Vaccine in Healthy Adults in Australia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Lot-to-Lot Consistency and Bridging Study of a Tetravalent Dengue Vaccine in Healthy Adults in Australia</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>U1111-1114-7646</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>CYD17</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Dengue Fever</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Dengue Hemorrhagic Fever</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - Live, attenuated, recombinant dengue serotypes 1, 2, 3, &amp; 4 virus
Other interventions - Live, attenuated, recombinant dengue serotypes 1, 2, 3, &amp; 4 virus
Other interventions - Live, attenuated, recombinant dengue serotypes 1, 2, 3, &amp; 4 virus
Other interventions - Live, attenuated, recombinant dengue serotypes 1, 2, 3, &amp; 4 virus
Other interventions - Placebo: NaCl 0.9%

Experimental: Group 1 - CYD Dengue vaccine - Phase III Lot 1

Experimental: Group 2 - CYD Dengue vaccine - Phase III Lot 2

Experimental: Group 3 - CYD Dengue vaccine - Phase III Lot 3

Experimental: Group 4 - CYD Dengue vaccine - Phase II Lot

Placebo Comparator: Group 5 - NaCl 0.9%


Other interventions: Live, attenuated, recombinant dengue serotypes 1, 2, 3, &amp; 4 virus
0.5 mL, Subcutaneous (SC)

Other interventions: Live, attenuated, recombinant dengue serotypes 1, 2, 3, &amp; 4 virus
0.5 mL, Subcutaneous (SC)

Other interventions: Live, attenuated, recombinant dengue serotypes 1, 2, 3, &amp; 4 virus
0.5 mL, Subcutaneous (SC)

Other interventions: Live, attenuated, recombinant dengue serotypes 1, 2, 3, &amp; 4 virus
0.5 mL, Subcutaneous (SC)

Other interventions: Placebo: NaCl 0.9%
0.5 mL, Subcutaneous (SC)

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Information concerning the immunogenicity of different lots of CYD Dengue vaccine in terms of antibody levels against each of the four dengue virus serotype strains contained in the CYD dengue vaccine.</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days post-dose 3 vaccination</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Information concerning the safety (in terms of solicited injection site and systemic reactions and unsolicited adverse events) of the CYD dengue vaccine in all subjects after each dose.</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days and up to 6 months post-vaccination</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Aged 18 to 60 years on the day of inclusion

          -  Informed consent form has been signed and dated

          -  Able to attend all scheduled visits and to comply with all trial procedures

          -  For a woman of childbearing potential, use of an effective method of contraception, or
             abstinence from at least 4 weeks prior to the first vaccination until at least 4 weeks
             after the last vaccination (i.e., for 14 months).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Known pregnancy, or a positive urine pregnancy test

          -  History of flavivirus infection or vaccination or prolonged habitation in a dengue
             endemic area

          -  Currently breastfeeding a child

          -  Participation in another clinical trial investigating a vaccine, drug, medical device,
             or medical procedure in the 4 weeks preceding the first trial vaccination

          -  Planned participation in another clinical trial during the present trial period

          -  Planned receipt of any vaccine in the 4 weeks following any trial vaccination, except
             for pandemic influenza vaccination

          -  Receipt of blood or blood-derived products in the past 3 months, which might interfere
             with assessment of the immune response

          -  Known or suspected congenital or acquired immunodeficiency; or receipt of
             immunosuppressive therapy such as anti-cancer chemotherapy or radiation therapy within
             the preceding 6 months; or long-term systemic corticosteroid therapy (prednisone or
             equivalent for more than 2 consecutive weeks within the past 3 months)

          -  Self-reported seropositivity for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)

          -  Known systemic hypersensitivity to any of the vaccine components, or history of a
             life-threatening reaction to the vaccine used in the trial or to a vaccine containing
             any of the same substances

          -  Deprived of freedom by an administrative or court order, or in an emergency setting,
             or hospitalized involuntarily

          -  Current alcohol abuse or drug addiction that might interfere with the ability to
             comply with trial procedures

          -  Chronic illness that, in the opinion of the Investigator, is at a stage where it might
             interfere with trial conduct or completion

          -  Identified as a site employee of the Investigator or study center, with direct
             involvement in the proposed study or other studies under the direction of that
             Investigator or study center, as well as family members (i.e., immediate, husband,
             wife and their children, adopted or natural) of the site employees or the Investigator

        Temporary Contraindications:

        A prospective subject must not be included in the study until the following conditions
        and/or symptoms are resolved:

          -  Febrile illness (temperature = 38.0°C) or moderate or severe acute illness/infection
             (according to Investigator's judgment) on the day of vaccination

          -  Receipt of any vaccine in the 4 weeks preceding the first trial vaccination, except
             for pandemic influenza vaccination, which may be received at least two weeks before
             study vaccines Vaccination should be postponed within the timeframe for vaccination
             indicated in the tables of study procedures or until enrolment is ongoing at the site.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/10/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>712</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/02/2013</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital> - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital> - Carina Heights</hospital>
    <hospital> - Enoggera</hospital>
    <hospital> - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <hospital> - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital> - Subiaco</hospital>
    <hospital> - Westmead</hospital>
    <postcode>SA 5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>QLD 4152 - Carina Heights</postcode>
    <postcode>QLD 4051 - Enoggera</postcode>
    <postcode>VIC 3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
    <postcode>QLD 4006 - Herston</postcode>
    <postcode>QLD 4029 - Herston</postcode>
    <postcode>WA 6008 - Subiaco</postcode>
    <postcode>NSW 2145 - Westmead</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Sanofi Pasteur, a Sanofi Company</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to demonstrate that different CYD Dengue vaccine lots
      manufactured using the same method and in the same location but at different times produce an
      equivalent immunological response.

      Primary Objective

        -  To demonstrate that three different Phase III lots of CYD Dengue vaccine induce an
           equivalent immune response in terms of post-Dose 3 geometric mean titers (GMTs) against
           the four parental serotypes.

      Secondary Objectives:

        -  To demonstrate that data from one Phase II lot and pooled data from Phase III lots of
           CYD Dengue vaccine show an equivalent immune response in terms of post-Dose 3 GMTs
           against the four parental serotypes.

        -  To describe the safety (in terms of solicited injection site and systemic reactions and
           unsolicited adverse events) of the CYD Dengue vaccine in all subjects after each dose.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01134263</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Medical Director</name>
      <address>Sanofi Pasteur Inc.</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>