<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="1110">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/03/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/03/2006</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00307697</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Letter Intervention in Primary Care Patients to Improve Depression and Anxiety Disorders</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomised Controlled Trial of a Letter Intervention in Primary Care Patients to Improve Depression and Anxiety Disorders</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>PMHT-01/06</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: surgery - receipt of copy of psychiatic assessment letter

Treatment: surgery: receipt of copy of psychiatic assessment letter


</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>score on a depression/anxiety rating scale at 1 month and 3 months</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>score on a quality of life scale at 1 month and 3 months</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  diagnosis of primary depressive or anxiety disorder

          -  gender (males and females both eligible)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  primary substance abuse disorder (though co-morbid substance abuse will not be an
             exclusion criterion)

          -  significant personality disorder

          -  psychosis

          -  high suicidal risk or risk of harm to others

          -  inability to speak and read English to a standard that allows independent completion
             of the questionnaires

          -  under 18 years of age

          -  incapable of giving consent

          -  significant medical condition

          -  clinician discretion</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Factorial</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/06/2006</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/09/2007</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Primary Mental Health and Early Intervention Team - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3181 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Bayside Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Beyondblue (The National Depression Initiative)</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Currently patients thought to have anxiety or depression by their GPs are referred to the
      Primary Mental Health Team (PMHEIT) for psychiatric assessment. This assessment consists of a
      one-hour interview with a senior psychiatry registrar or psychiatrist, who then writes a
      letter to the referring GP. The letter contains diagnostic information and management
      recommendations. It is not current practice to send a copy of this letter to the patient. We
      hypothesize that patients who receive a copy of the psychiatric assessment letter that is
      sent to GPs will improve adherence to treatment recommendations; and that patients who
      receive a copy of the letter will have improved outcomes.

      GPs will be asked to agree to the participation of their patients. Participants will be
      persons over the age of 18 years who are referred to the PMHEIT for assessment and who
      receive primary diagnoses of depression or anxiety. After the assessment interview, the
      patient will be given an explanatory letter and a consent form. Consenting patients will
      complete the Depression and Anxiety Stress Scales (DASS) and a SF12 questionnaire to measure
      the level of disability they are experiencing due to their mental condition.

      Participants will be randomly allocated into two groups: a control group who will not receive
      a copy of the assessment letter, and an experimental group who will be mailed a copy of the
      same information that their GP receives. The registrar who conducts the assessment and writes
      the report will not know to which group each participant has been assigned. Thus, the content
      of the letter will not be affected by knowledge that the patient will or will not see it. The
      letter will be sent simultaneously to the referring GP and to experimental group
      participants. To ensure confidentiality, the letter will be sent by registered mail.

      Three weeks later, participants will be mailed a copy of the DASS. After a week, they will be
      contacted by phone and asked for their DASS responses. They will also be asked a brief series
      of questions regarding their adherence to the treatment recommendations given in their
      assessment letter. When adherence is partial or absent, the interviewer will attempt to
      ascertain the reason. This procedure will be repeated at 3 months, except that assessment on
      the SF12 will also take place.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00307697</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Asch R, Price J, Hawks G. Psychiatric out-patients' reactions to summary letters of their consultations. Br J Med Psychol. 1991 Mar;64 ( Pt 1):3-9.
Dale, J., Tadros, G., Adams, S., &amp; Deshpande, N. (2004). Do patients really want copies of their GP letters? A questionnaire survey of older adults and their carers. Psychiatric Bulletin, 28, 199 - 200.
Jelley D, van Zwanenberg T, Walker C. Copying letters to patients. Concerns of clinicians and patients need to be addressed first. BMJ. 2002 Dec 7;325(7376):1359.
Marzanski, M., Musunuri, P., &amp; Coupe, T. (2005). Copying letters to patients: A study of patients' views. Psychiatric Bulletin, 29, 56 - 58.
Nandhra, H., Murray, G., Hymas, N., &amp; Hunt, N. (2004). Medical records: Doctors' and patients' experiences of copying letters to patients. Psychiatric Bulletin, 28, 40 - 42.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Michael McGartland, MClinPsych</name>
      <address>The Alfred</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>