<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5024">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/03/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/03/2015</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02474134</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparison Study of PF530 and Betaferon in Healthy Subjects</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 1 Double-Blind, Randomised, Two-Treatment Cross-over Study Comparing the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics, and Pharmacodynamics of PF530 and Betaferon Administered by Subcutaneous Injection in Healthy Adult Volunteers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>PF530-101</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Multiple Sclerosis</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Interferon beta-1b (PF530, Betaferon)

Other: PF530/Betaferon - Single subcutaneous injection of two interferon beta-1b products (PF530 and Betaferon) 0.25 mg

Other: Betaferon/PF530 - Single subcutaneous injection of two interferon beta-1b products (Betaferon and PF530) 0.25 mg


Treatment: drugs: Interferon beta-1b (PF530, Betaferon)
Single subcutaneous administration

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse event (AE) and serious adverse event (SAE) incidence</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 Days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum area-under-the-curve (AUC) of PF530 and Betaferon</outcome>
      <timepoint>72 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum maximum concentration (Tmax) of PF530 and Betaferon</outcome>
      <timepoint>72 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum half-life (t1/2) of PF530 and Betaferon</outcome>
      <timepoint>72 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum neopterin</outcome>
      <timepoint>168 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum myxovirus resistance protein A</outcome>
      <timepoint>168 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Females of childbearing potential must agree to use two effective methods of birth
             control, practice complete abstinence, or confirm sterilization of monogamous male
             partner

          -  Males must have had a documented vasectomy, practice complete abstinence or use a
             condom and refrain from sperm.

          -  Participant is free from clinically significant illness or disease as determined by
             medical and surgical history, physical examination, 12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG)
             and clinical laboratory assessments.

          -  Able to understand and sign the written Informed Consent Form</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Female subjects who are pregnant or lactating.

          -  History of any significant cardiovascular, hepatic, renal, pulmonary, hematologic,
             gastrointestinal, endocrine, immunologic, dermatologic, neurologic, metabolic,
             psychological, musculoskeletal disease or malignancies unless deemed not clinically
             significant by the Principal Investigator.

          -  Previous treatment with any interferon product, including investigational use.

          -  Participants with a history of malignant disease, including solid tumours and
             hematologic malignancies (except basal cell and squamous cell carcinomas of the skin
             that have been completely excised and are considered cured).

          -  Positive screening test for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV).

          -  Positive screening test for hepatitis C antibody (HCV Ab) or current hepatitis B
             infection (defined as positive for hepatitis surface antigen [HBsAg] at Screening).
             Participants with immunity to hepatitis B (defined as negative HBsAg and positive
             hepatitis B surface antibody [HBsAb]) are eligible to participate in the study.

          -  History of epilepsy, seizure disorder or any unexplained black-outs.

          -  History of hypersensitivity or intolerance to paracetamol or non-steroidal
             anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAID) that would preclude the use of at least 1 of these
             during the study.

          -  History of severe allergic or anaphylactic reactions or a known allergy to any
             component of the interferon ß-1b formulation.

          -  History of drug or alcohol abuse less than or equal to 12 months prior to Screening.

          -  History of tobacco use less than or equal to 6 months prior to Screening.

          -  A positive test for drugs of abuse or alcohol during Screening or prior to dosing.

          -  Unwilling or unable to abstain from alcohol from 7 days prior to dosing until
             end-of-study assessments.

          -  Use of any prescription medication, over-the-counter medication, or herbal
             supplements/products during Screening or throughout study, unless approved by both the
             Principal Investigator and the Sponsor.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/03/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>12</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/10/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>CMAX - Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Pfenex, Inc</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to compare the safety, tolerability, and blood levels of two
      interferon beta-1b products, Betaferon and PF530, in healthy volunteers.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02474134</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sepehr Shakib, MD</name>
      <address>CMAX, A Division of IDT Australia, Limited</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>