<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6021">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/06/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/06/2016</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02868580</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Safety and Tolerability of Antiretroviral (Triumeq) in Patients With Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis (ALS).</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Phase 2a Open Label Study, Safety and Tolerability of Combination Antiretroviral Therapy (Triumeq) in Participants With Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis (ALS) - The Lighthouse Project.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Lighthouse</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>CUR-101</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Neurodegenerative diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human Genetics and Inherited Disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other human genetics and inherited disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Triumeq

Experimental: Single arm open label - All subjects will receive open label Triumeq following a lead-in phase. Triumeq is abacavir 600mg, lamivudine 300mg, dolutegravir 50mg


Treatment: drugs: Triumeq
Triumeq, a combination of dolutegravir, abacavir and lamivudine is an anti-retroviral therapy indicated for people with HIV-1 infection.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of participants with treatment related adverse events as defined CTCAE V4.0. - Safety will be measured by Number of Participants With Abnormal Laboratory Values and/or Adverse Events That Are Related to Treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 year</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>ALS Functional Rating Scale-Revised (ALSFRS-R) scoring - Efficacy will be measured by the change in scores of the ALS Functional Rating Scale-Revised (ALSFRS-R) conducted at screening, twice within the lead-in phase and at four weekly intervals during the study until end of treatment or early termination.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With Abnormal Laboratory Values for Neurophysiological Index (NI) Related to Treatment. - A neurophysiological index (NI) measurement will be calculated according to the parameters of Compound Muscle Action Potential amplitude/DML x Frequency % to determine the index score.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of participants with abnormal Sniff Nasal Inspiratory Pressure (SNIP) Test results - The SNIP test results will be calculated according to the Pn(sn) as a percentage of predicted value according to treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>one year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of participants with abnormal forced vital capacity (FVC) test results as measured by hand-held spirometry - The FVC test results will be measured in liters and reported according to percentage of predicted values for participants on treatment</outcome>
      <timepoint>One year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of participants with abnormal quantitative hand muscle testing as measured by dynanometry. - The quantitative hand muscle strength will be assessed by 3 Measurements on Grip Strength and Pinch Grip: measurement in kilograms</outcome>
      <timepoint>One year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of participants with abnormal scores on the Columbia Suicide Severity Score C-SSRS). - The C-SSRS is a measure of suicidal ideation and behavior. It is a composite numerical scale divided into sections and used to assess selected parameters over time in participants on treatment. The scoring system is both binomial and rating scale and is reported according to different aspects of the assessment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>One year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Subjects must meet all of the following inclusion criteria to be eligible to participate in
        this study:

          -  Age 18-75 years at the time of the screening visit

          -  Able to provide informed consent and comply with study procedures

          -  Sporadic ALS diagnosed as probable, laboratory-supported probable or definite
             according to the World Federation of Neurology El Escorial revised criteria as
             determined by a neurologist with neuromuscular sub-specialty training

          -  Diagnosis &lt;24 months from date of enrolment

          -  (Forced) Vital capacity at least 60% of predicted value for gender, height and age at
             the screening visit

          -  Must be on a stable dose of riluzole for at least 30 days prior to the screening
             visit.

          -  Subject has established care with a neurologist at one of the four specialized ALS
             clinics involved in the study and will maintain this clinical care throughout the
             study.

          -  Subjects can participate in clinical registries, but will be excluded to this protocol
             if they are participating in a clinical trial involving additional or investigative
             treatment exposure.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>A participant will be excluded if he or she has any of the following:

          -  Dependence on mechanical ventilation at the time of screening

          -  Gastrostomy at the time of screening

          -  Absence of Upper Motor Neuron Signs

          -  Participation in any other investigational drug trial or using investigational drug
             (within 12 weeks prior to screening)

          -  Known hypersensitivity to dolutegravir, abacavir or lamivudine, or to any of the
             excipients

          -  Presence of the HLA-B*5701 allele at screening

          -  Presence of a monogenic cause of ALS (e.g. known mutation in SOD1, expansion in
             c9orf72 etc.)

          -  History of positive test or positive result at screening for HIV

          -  Subjects positive for Hepatitis B at screening (+HBsAg), or anticipated need for
             Hepatitis C virus (HCV) therapy during the study*;

          -  Women must not be able to become pregnant (post menopausal for &gt;1 year, surgically
             sterile, adequate contraception) or breastfeed for the duration of the study. Women of
             childbearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test at screening and be
             non-lactating

          -  Other interventional clinical trial

          -  Subject is taking medication contraindicated with Triumeq. Dofetilide (or pilsicainide
             [available in Japan]) is prohibited as DTG may inhibit its renal tubular secretion
             resulting in increased dofetilide concentrations and potential for toxicity.

          -  Presence of any of the following clinical conditions at the time of screening:

        Drug or alcohol abuse Unstable medical disease (such as unstable angina or chronic
        obstructive pulmonary disease), or active infectious disease (such as Hepatitis B or C or
        tuberculosis), or current malignancy Unstable psychiatric illness defined as psychosis or
        untreated major depression within 90 days of the screening visit. This exclusion criteria
        is based on a prior psychiatric diagnosis that is unstable as determined by the subject's
        treating Psychiatrist Dementia as previously diagnosed by a medical practitioner

         Safety Laboratory Criteria at the screening visit: Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) &gt;5
        times the upper limit of normal (ULN), OR ALT &gt;3xULN Total bilirubin, lactate,
        triglycerides, amylase, or lipase greater than 2.0 times the upper limit of normal Subject
        has creatinine clearance of &lt;50 mL/min via Cockroft-Gault method Subjects with moderate to
        severe hepatic impairment (Class B or greater) as determined by Child-Pugh classification;
        Absolute neutrophil count of &lt; 1 x 109/L Platelet concentration of &lt; 100 x 109/L
        Haemoglobin &lt; 100g/L</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/10/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>40</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/06/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Macquarie Neurology - North Ryde</hospital>
    <hospital>Westmead Hospital - Parramatta</hospital>
    <hospital>Brain and Mind Centre - Sydney</hospital>
    <hospital>Calvary Health Care Bethlehem - Caulfield South</hospital>
    <postcode>2109 - North Ryde</postcode>
    <postcode>2150 - Parramatta</postcode>
    <postcode>2050 - Sydney</postcode>
    <postcode>3162 - Caulfield South</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Neuroscience Trials Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Macquarie University, Australia</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Westmead Hosptial</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Calvary Health Care Bethlehem</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>The University of Sydney - Brain and Mind Centre</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a phase 2a open label, multicentre design study to investigate the safety of Triumeq
      in patients with ALS at 24 weeks post treatment. In this phase 2a study the investigators aim
      to determine whether a combination of anti-retroviral therapy, Triumeq (dolutegravir 50mg,
      abacavir 600mg, lamivudine 300mg) is tolerated and safe in patients with ALS. As secondary
      outcomes, ALSFRS-R, ALSQOL, physical examination, neurophysical parameters and respiratory
      and muscle function will be evaluated. Blood and urine samples will be stored for possible
      future analysis for viral activity. Subjects will be screened for the study after signing an
      approved Informed consent document.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02868580</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Julian Gold, MD</name>
      <address>The Albion Centre</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>