<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5169">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/09/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/09/2015</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02559258</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Escalating Single Dose Study of Epsi- Gam in Healthy Normal Subjects</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase I, Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Escalating Single Dose Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics of Epsi- Gam in Healthy, Cat-, Dust Mite-, or Bermuda Grass-Allergic Subjects</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>TUN001-101</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Allergy and Immunology</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - 0.1 mg/kg epsi-gam or placebo (6:2)
Treatment: drugs - 0.3 mg/kg epsi-gam or placebo (6:2)
Treatment: drugs - 1.0 mg/kg epsi-gam or placebo (6:2)
Treatment: drugs - 3 mg/kg epsi-gam or placebo (6:2)
Treatment: drugs - 10 mg/kg epsi-gam or placebo (6:2)

Experimental: Cohort 1 - 

Experimental: Cohort 2 - 

Experimental: Cohort 3 - 

Experimental: Cohort 4 - 

Experimental: Cohort 5 - 


Treatment: drugs: 0.1 mg/kg epsi-gam or placebo (6:2)
administered as a single intravenous infusion on Day 1, infused over 30 minutes

Treatment: drugs: 0.3 mg/kg epsi-gam or placebo (6:2)
administered as a single intravenous infusion on Day 1 infused over 30 minutes

Treatment: drugs: 1.0 mg/kg epsi-gam or placebo (6:2)
administered as a single intravenous infusion on Day 1 infused over 30 minutes

Treatment: drugs: 3 mg/kg epsi-gam or placebo (6:2)
administered as a single intravenous infusion on Day 1 infused over 60 minutes

Treatment: drugs: 10 mg/kg epsi-gam or placebo (6:2)
administered as a single intravenous infusion on Day 1 infused over 120 minutes

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and tolerability will be assessed by monitoring AEs (frequency and severity) and SAEs, vital signs, PFTs - ECGs, clinical laboratory values (including clinically significant changes from baseline) from blood and urine samples, performing physical examinations and pregnancy tests and reviewing concomitant medications.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From start of study drug administration through Day 57 (+/- 2 days)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Eligible subjects must meet all of the following inclusion criteria:

          1. Be informed of the nature of the study and provide written informed consent prior to
             undergoing screening procedures.

          2. Be a healthy male of any race or ethnicity, at least 18 years of age and no more than
             65 years of age, inclusively, OR

          3. Be a healthy female of any race or ethnicity of non-childbearing potential, at least
             18 years of age and no more than 65 years of age, inclusively, OR

          4. Be a healthy non-pregnant, non-lactating female of any race or ethnicity of
             childbearing potential, at least 18 years of age and no more than 65 years of age,
             inclusive, with a negative pregnancy test who agrees to use 2 medically acceptable
             forms of birth control from Screening through 57 days after receiving study drug.

          5. Have a Body Mass Index (BMI) within the range of 18.5 to 30.0 kg/m2.

          6. Have a history of allergic reactivity to cats, dust mite, or Bermuda grass as
             expressed by allergic symptoms including rhinitis.

          7. Standardized cat allergenic extract (10,000 BAU/mL, ALK- Abello), dust mite allergenic
             extract (10,000 AU/mL, ALK- Abello), dust mite allergenic extract (10,000 AU/mL, ALK-
             Abello), or Bermuda grass allergenic extract (10,000 BAU/mL, ALK- Abello) elicits a
             wheal at least 5 mm up to approximately 10-15 mm in diameter that exceeds two diluent
             controls by at least 4 mm.

          8. Have allergen-specific IgE for cat, dust mite, or Bermuda grass as measured by
             ImmunoCAP® with a Class rating of 1 or greater.

          9. Histamine reactivity of 3 mm or greater, with surrounding erythema, on testing using a
             standardized epicutaneous delivery device.

         10. Be able and willing to discontinue any first and second generation antihistamine use
             beginning at least 7 days prior to undergoing initial screening skin puncture tests
             and throughout study participation.

         11. Have baseline spirometry (FEV1, FVC, FEF 25%-75%) with FEV1 = 80% predicted and other
             values within the normal range.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Subjects who meet any of the following criteria must be excluded:

          1. Diluent control elicits a wheal = 3 mm on testing.

          2. History of severe systemic allergic reactions to cats, dust mite, or Bermuda grass

          3. Clinical history of persistent asthma

          4. Dermatographism or any skin disorder (i.e., atopic dermatitis) that would make skin
             testing or proper interpretation impractical.

          5. Chronic urticaria.

          6. Underlying heart, liver, kidney, or lung disease or any other medical condition such
             that the subject would be at increased risk for a poor outcome should a generalized
             allergic or other reaction occur.

          7. Any abnormal laboratory value(s) considered to be clinically significant by the
             Investigator.

          8. Use of systemic corticosteroids within the past three months prior to initial
             screening.

          9. Use of topical corticosteroids on the area(s) to undergo skin tests within the past
             three weeks prior to initial screening.

         10. Use of systemic beta-blocking or ACE-inhibiting agents within the past three weeks
             prior to initial screening.

         11. Use of tricyclic antidepressants within the past three weeks prior to initial
             screening.

         12. Use of H2 antagonists within 24 hours prior to initial screening.

         13. Use of any agents known or likely to interact with adrenaline.

         14. Use of omalizumab (Xolair®) within the past six months prior to enrolment.

         15. Pregnant females as determined by a positive serum or urine hCG test.

         16. Lactating females.

         17. Participation in another experimental drug or device trial and receipt of an
             investigational product within the past 30 days, five half-lives or twice the duration
             of the biochemical effect of the investigational product (whichever is longer) prior
             to dosing in the present study.

         18. Any mental impairment as judged by the Investigator that would limit ability to comply
             with study requirements.

         19. History of infection with, or positive screen for, Hepatitis B (HBsAg, Hepatitis B
             Surface Antigen), Hepatitis C (HCVAb, Hepatitis C Antibody), or Human Immunodeficiency
             Virus (HIV 1 or 2).

         20. Positive urine screen for drugs of abuse. Positive ethanol breath test.

         21. Concurrent disease or condition, that, in the opinion of the Investigator, places the
             subject at high risk of poor treatment compliance or of not completing the study.

         22. Has smoked or consumed nicotine-containing products within past 3 months prior to
             receiving study drug or has a positive urine test for cotinine, and does not agree to
             refrain from smoking for the duration of the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2>The people administering the treatment/s</masking2>
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/08/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>5</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Terminated</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/05/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Q-Pharm - Brisbane</hospital>
    <postcode>4006 - Brisbane</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Tunitas Therapeutics, Inc.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Tunitas Therapeutics Australia Pty Ltd</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a single-center, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, single-dose, dose-
      escalation study in otherwise healthy cat-, dust mite-, or Bermuda grass-allergic male and
      female subjects. There will be five dosing cohorts (0.1, 0.3, 1.0, 3.0 and 10.0 mg/kg), with
      eight subjects in each cohort, randomized to either epsi-gam (6 subjects) or placebo (2
      subjects) for a total of 40 subjects. The first cohort will receive the starting dose of 0.1
      mg/kg epsi-gam or placebo and subsequent cohorts will be recruited sequentially to receive
      escalating doses of epsi-gam or placebo.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02559258</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>