<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5011">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/06/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/06/2015</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02468687</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>NMP in Relapsed / Refractory Myeloma</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase I, Open Label Dose Escalation Trial of Orally Administered N-methyl-pyrrolidone (NMP) in Patients With Relapsed or Refractory Myeloma</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>HREC/14/MH/159</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Multiple Myeloma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cancer types</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - N-methyl-pyrrolidone

Other: N-methyl-pyrrolidone - NMP dose escalation in accelerated phase and standard phase


Treatment: drugs: N-methyl-pyrrolidone
NMP will be taken each morning as a single daily dose of oral suspension at a concentration of 50mg/ml on an empty stomach at least 30 minutes prior to food.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse events to establish the Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD) - Each patient will be monitored for adverse events during the first cycle of NMP treatment (28 days) to establish the maximum tolerated dose</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Optimum biological dose (OBD) - The maximum changes in correlative biomarkers will be tested at the specific time-points. Descriptive statistics will be used to analyse data from correlative studies and summarized in graphical or tabular formats as appropriate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety of the repeated dosing of NMP by oral administration - possible toxicities - To assess safety, the numbers and rates (with confidence intervals) of patients experiencing any haematological and non-haematological and specific grade 3+ adverse events experienced at each given dose level and schedule of NMP will be calculated, over the full treatment period and by cycle</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetic properties of NMP after oral administration - Pick plasma concentrations (Cmax) of NMP</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose,0.5,1,2,4,8, 24 hours post dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Response rate measured using IMWG criteria - Patients will be evaluated for response after every 28 day cycle for the first 6 cycles of treatment and thereafter every 2 months in follow up using the IMWG criteria for multiple myeloma.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months up to 2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to progression from start of treatment - Patients will be assessed for disease progression weekly in Cycle 1, then monthly on D1 of each cycle during treatment for the first 6 months and then monthly until disease progression, next anti-cancer treatment or death. Time to progression from start of treatment will be estimated using Kaplan Meier survival curves.</outcome>
      <timepoint>up to 3.5 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Histologically confirmed diagnosis of plasma cell myeloma defined by WHO 2008 criteria

          2. Measurable disease as defined by at least one of:

               -  serum M protein =5g/L

               -  urine M protein = 200mg/24hrs

               -  involved serum free light chain = 100mg/L

               -  measurable (by imaging at the discretion of the investigator) soft tissue
                  plasmacytoma

          3. Relapsed, refractory or intolerant of both bortezomib and lenalidomide

        Definitions:

          -  refractory at least 4 weeks of therapy administered, with less than a partial response
             by IMWG criteria

          -  relapsed from previous response (PR or greater) to therapy, with subsequent disease
             progression as defined as development of bone marrow dysfunction (fall in Hb of 20g/L
             or platelet count &lt;100 x 109/L) due to increased bone marrow plasmacytosis

          -  OR new lytic bone lesions

          -  OR increase in serum M protein of 5g/L

          -  OR absolute increase of involved serum free light chain of &gt;250mg/L

          -  intolerant: grade 2 or higher toxicity unresponsive to dose adjustment 4. Prior
             autologous stem cell transplant, unless ineligible for transplant by the discretion of
             the investigator.

             5. age =18 years 6. ECOG performance status &lt;2 7. The following values within 7 days
             of commencing NMP (blood transfusions prior to study entry are permitted)

          -  Haemoglobin &gt;80g/L

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt;1.0 x 109/L

          -  Platelet count = 25 x 109/L

          -  Creatinine clearance &gt;30ml/min (by Cockcroft/Gault)

          -  Bilirubin = 3x upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  ALT = 3 x ULN

          -  Left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) =45% (by gated cardiac blood pool scan or
             echocardiography) 9. Life expectancy &gt; 3 months 10. Able to give written informed
             consent 11. In the opinion of the investigator, willing and able to comply with
             required study procedures 12. Able to take oral medications (no malabsorptive
             condition)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Pregnant or breastfeeding female patients

          2. Female of child bearing potential unwilling or unable to use two methods of
             contraception

          3. Received chemotherapy, immunotherapy or biological therapy within two weeks of
             enrolment. Prednisolone up to 20mg per day permitted for non-myeloma indications.

          4. Patients with a history of another malignancy within 2 years of the baseline visit,
             excluding treated non-melanotic skin cancer and in-situ carcinoma.

          5. Patients with known CNS involvement unless previously treated and well controlled for
             a period of =3 months AND which do not require the use of steroids.

          6. Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to:

               -  Active or uncontrolled infection, including active HIV or viral (A, B or C)
                  hepatitis. NOTE: Patients with controlled infection on antibiotic or antifungal
                  therapy are eligible i.e. the patient should be afebrile for at least 72 hours
                  and be haemodynamically stable.

               -  Impaired cardiac function, including any of the following:

                    -  Myocardial infarction within previous 3 months prior to starting study

                    -  Symptomatic congestive heart failure (New York Heart Association Class III,
                       IV)

                    -  Symptomatic coronary artery disease

                    -  Cardiac arrhythmia not controlled by medication

                    -  Clinically significant resting bradycardia (&lt;50 beats per minute)

                    -  Long QT syndrome or a known family history of long QT syndrome or QTc &gt; 450
                       msec on baseline ECG (using the QTcF formula). If QTcF &gt;450 msec and
                       electrolytes are not within normal ranges, electrolytes should be corrected
                       and then the patient re-screened for QTc

                    -  Inability to monitor the QT/QTc interval on ECG

                    -  Other clinically significant uncontrolled heart disease (e.g. unstable
                       angina or uncontrolled hypertension)

               -  Impaired hepatic or renal impairment (see inclusion criteria)

               -  Uncontrolled diarrhoea, nausea or vomiting

          7. concomitant exposure to another investigational agent</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/08/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/02/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3002 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre, Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Melbourne Health</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study will evaluate if the N-methyl-pyrrolidone (NMP) can be safely administered to
      humans at doses, which induce measurable immunological and anti-tumour effects in patients
      with myeloma who are resistant to or intolerant of lenalidomide and bortezomib.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02468687</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>David Ritchie, Prof</name>
      <address>Melbourne Health</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>