<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3208">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/06/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/06/2011</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01383096</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Study To Investigate The Relative Bioavailability of OZ439 Formulations In Healthy Volunteers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase I Study To Investigate The Relative Bioavailability of OZ439 Formulations In Healthy Volunteers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>MMV_OZ439_11_001</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Healthy Volunteers</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - OZ439 mesylate 800mg Powder in Bottle for Oral Suspension
Treatment: drugs - OZ439 mesylate 400mg Prototype Solution Formula 1
Treatment: drugs - OZ439 mesylate 800mg Prototype Solution Formula 1
Treatment: drugs - OZ439 mesylate 800mg Prototype Solution Formula 2

Active Comparator: Cohort 1 - Treatment A: OZ439 800mg PIB, fed - OZ439 800 mg (as free base) as powder in a bottle (PIB)for reconstitution in a suspension prior to administration. Administered 30 minutes after a standard fatty breakfast.

Experimental: Cohort 1 - Treatment D: OZ439 800 mg Prototype F1 fasted - OZ439 800 mg (as free base) as a prototype solution formulation 1. Administered fasted.

Experimental: Cohort 2 - Treatement H: OZ439 800 mg Prototype F2 fasted - OZ439 800 mg (as free base) as a prototype solution formulation 2. Administered fasted.

Experimental: Cohort 3 - Treatement K: OZ439 400mg Prototype F1 fasted - Best Prototype Solution - OZ439 400 mg as prototype solution formulation 1. Administered fasted.

Experimental: Cohort 1 - Treatement B: OZ439 800mg PIB fasted - OZ439 800 mg (as free base) as powder in a bottle (PIB) for reconstitution in a suspension prior to oral administration. Administered fasted.

Experimental: Cohort 1 - Treatment C:OZ439 800mg PIB with milk - OZ439 800 mg (as free base) as powder in a bottle (PIB) for reconstitution in a suspension prior to oral administration. Administered following 200 mL milk.

Experimental: Cohort 3 - Treatment J: OZ439 800mg Prototype F1 fasted - Best Prototype Solution - OZ439 800 mg (as free base) as prototype solution formulation 1. Administered fasted.

Experimental: Cohort 1 - Treatement E: OZ439 800mg Prototype F1 with milk - OZ439 800 mg (as free base) as a prototype solution formulation 1. Administered with milk.

Experimental: Cohort 2 - Treatement F: OZ439 800 mg PIB fasted - OZ439 800 mg (as free base) as powder in a bottle (PIB) for reconstitution in a suspension prior to oral administration. Administered fasted.

Experimental: Cohort 2 - Treatement G: OZ439 800mg PIB with milk - OZ439 800 mg (as free base) as powder in a bottle (PIB) for reconstitution in a suspension prior to oral administration. Administered following 200 mL milk.

Experimental: Cohort 2 - Treatement I: OZ349 800mg Prototype F2 with milk - OZ439 800 mg (as free base) as a prototype solution formulation 2. Administered with milk.


Treatment: drugs: OZ439 mesylate 800mg Powder in Bottle for Oral Suspension
OZ439 800 mg (as free base) as powder in a bottle for reconstitution in a suspension prior to oral administration

Treatment: drugs: OZ439 mesylate 400mg Prototype Solution Formula 1
OZ439 400 mg (as free base) as a prototype solution formulation 1

Treatment: drugs: OZ439 mesylate 800mg Prototype Solution Formula 1
OZ439 800 mg (as free base) as a prototype solution formulation 1

Treatment: drugs: OZ439 mesylate 800mg Prototype Solution Formula 2
OZ439 800 mg (as free base) as a prototype solution formulation 2

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>OZ439 Cmax - The maximum observed plasma drug concentrations (Cmax)</outcome>
      <timepoint>1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 12, 24, 48, 72, 96 and 168 hours post dosing</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>OZ439 AUC0-8 - Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from zero to infinity (AUC0-8)</outcome>
      <timepoint>1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 12, 24, 48, 72, 96 and 168 hours post dosing</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>OZ439 t1/2 - Apparent terminal half life (t1/2)</outcome>
      <timepoint>1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 12, 24, 48, 72, 96 and 168 hours post dosing</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Healthy male and female volunteers between 18 and 55 years (inclusive).
             Post-menopausal women with amenorrhoea for at least 2 years are eligible confirmed by
             FSH level &gt;/ = 25microlU/ml

          -  Body mass Index between 18 and 30 kg/m2, inclusive; and body weight &gt; 50 kg.

          -  Healthy as determined by pre-study medical history, physical examination (including
             body temperature), 12 Lead ECG.

          -  Male volunteers must agree to use a double barrier method of contraception including
             abstinence, condom plus diaphragm or condom plus IUD or condom plus stable
             oral/transdermal/injectable hormonal contraceptive by female partner for at least 14
             days prior to the time of the first dose of study drug through 90 days after the last
             dose of study drug and must also agree to not donate sperm for 90 days after the last
             dose of study drug. Vasectomy with zero sperm count for 6 months minimum prior to the
             first dose of study drug is an acceptable form of contraception

          -  Clinical laboratory tests at screening within the reference ranges or if outside the
             normal range not clinically significant. ALT, AST and total bilirubin must be within
             the normal range

          -  Able and willing to give written informed consent

          -  Willing and able to adhere to the lifestyle guideline requirements

          -  Willing and able to be confined to the Clinical Research Unit as required by the
             protocol</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Evidence of or history of clinically significant oncologic, pulmonary, hepatic,
             cardiovascular, hematologic, metabolic, neurological, immunologic, nephrologic,
             endocrine, psychiatric disease, or current infection

          -  Evidence of or history of clinically significant gastrointestinal (excluding
             appendectomy and cholecystectomy) disease or current infection.

          -  Any condition that could possibly affect drug absorption, e.g. gastrectomy, diarrhea

          -  History of post-antibiotic colitis

          -  Pregnancy or breastfeeding

          -  QTc greater than 450 msec for males and females as corrected by the Fredricia's
             formula or evidence or history of abnormal cardiac rhythm

          -  History of drug or alcohol abuse within the past 2 years prior to Screening

          -  Tobacco users (includes stopping smoking less than 90 days prior to screening.
             "Tobacco use" includes smoking and the use of snuff and chewing tobacco, and other
             nicotine containing products

          -  Received an investigational drug or participated in another research study within 30
             days of the first dose of study drug in any part of the study

          -  Use of prescription drugs within 14 days prior to the first dose of study drug in
             Period 1, or need for any antibiotic during the study

          -  Received any non prescription medications, vitamins, herbal supplements or dietary
             supplements within 7 days of the first dose of study drug in Period 1, unless prior
             approval is granted. Excluded from this list is intermittent use of acetaminophen at
             doses of up to 2 g/day

          -  Consumed alcohol within 72 hours of Day -1 in any part of the study, or have a
             positive alcohol screen at screening or each admission

          -  Consumed fruit juice or ate grapefruit within 7 days prior to the first dose of study
             drug in any part of the study

          -  Positive test for human immunodeficiency virus, hepatitis B surface antigen or
             anti-hepatitis C virus

          -  Positive urine drug screen at Screening or admission

          -  History of intolerance or hypersensitivity to artemisinins

          -  Likelihood of requiring treatment during the study period with drugs not permitted by
             the study protocol

          -  Volunteers who have donated blood or experienced significant blood loss within 90 days
             of screening

          -  Hemoglobin &lt; 13.5 g/dL for males and &lt; 12.5 g/dL for females

          -  Any concern by the investigator regarding the safe participation of the volunteer or
             any reason the investigator considers the volunteer inappropriate for participation</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/04/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>52</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/08/2012</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>AMREP Centre for Clinical Studies - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>VIC 3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Medicines for Malaria Venture</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Nucleus Network Ltd</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>INC Research</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is designed to assess prototype formulations compared to the aqueous dispersion of
      Active Pharmaceutical Ingredient used in Phase I and Phase IIa studies to date. It is hoped
      that the bioavailability of OZ439 can be enhanced in the fasted state to be close to that
      observed when given after food. This will improve the utility of OZ439 in the field as well
      as decreasing the cost of treatment (by decreasing the dose of OZ439 required) which is very
      important for an antimalarial drug product destined for use in developing counties.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01383096</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Peter Peter Hodsman, MD</name>
      <address>AMREP Centre for Clinical Studies, Nucleus Network, 89 Commercial Road, Melbourne, VIC 3004 Australia</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>