<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2689">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/03/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/03/2010</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01081574</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pharmacokinetic Study of Bilastine in Children From 2 to &lt; 12 Years of Age With Either Allergic Rhinoconjunctivitis (AR) or Chronic Urticaria (CU)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Multicentre, International, Adaptive, Open-label, Repeated Administration Pharmacokinetic Study of Bilastine in Children From 2 to &lt;12 Years of Age With Allergic Rhinoconjunctivitis or Chronic Urticaria</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>2009-012013-22</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>BILA 3009/PED</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Allergic Rhinoconjunctivitis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Urticaria</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dermatological conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other skin conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Allergies</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Bilastine

Experimental: 10 mg Bilastine once daily for 7 days - 10 mg Bilastine dispersible oral tablet


Treatment: drugs: Bilastine
10 mg/qd/ 7 days.Oral dispersible tablets

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary objective is to assess the pharmacokinetics of bilastine in children (aged 2 to &lt;12 years) with allergic rhinoconjunctivitis (seasonal allergic rhinitis and/or perennial allergic rhinitis [SAR/PAR]) or chronic urticaria (CU) - Determination of plasma concentrations versus time (between 1 and 6 samples per subject at various time intervals after dosing according to an optimised sampling protocol) in order to perform a population pharmacokinetic analysis.
For Group A, samples of venous blood will be just prior to dose administration, and at 0.25, 0.5, 0.8, 1.0, 1.2, 1.5, 3.0, 4.0, 6.0, 8.0, 10.0, 12.0, and 24.0 hours after dose administration.
For Group B samples of venous blood will be just prior to dose administration, and at 0.25, 0.5, 1.0, 1.5, 3.0, 6.0, 8.0, 10.0, and 12.0 hours after dose administration.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 day (visit 3, Day 7)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary objectives are to describe the safety and tolerability of a repeated administration of bilastine in the aforementioned paediatric subset with allergic rhinoconjunctivitis (SAR/PAR) or chronic urticaria (CU). - Safety will be assessed during the study by monitoring adverse events (AEs), clinical laboratory test results (urinalysis, blood chemistry, and haematology), vital signs (including blood pressure, respiration, temperature, and heart rate, supine and standing), electrocardiogram (ECG) results, and abnormal findings upon physical examination.</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Either sex aged from = 2 to &lt; 12 years of age. Female subjects must not be of child
             bearing potential.

          2. Height and weight within a majority range (e.g., 25th through 75th percentile) of the
             subject's age and sex as provided in national tables.

          3. Documented history of SAR/PAR or CU at the time of inclusion. Subjects must be
             symptomatic at screening as judged by the investigator.

          4. A documented positive skin prick test or IgE test (RAST) for at least one seasonal or
             perennial allergen in children with AR obtained within the 12 months prior to
             inclusion.

          5. Excepting AR or CU, judged to be in general good health based on medical history,
             physical examination and clinical laboratory tests, with a QTc duration on the ECG
             recorded at screening within the normal range (= 440 msec).

          6. Written informed consent signed by the legal representative of the minor (his/her
             parent(s) or a person legally appointed if different from parent(s)) and, where
             applicable, assent signed by the child, according to local regulations.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>2</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>11</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Female subjects of childbearing potential. If menarche occurs after study enrolment
             and during the dosing period, the subject should be discontinued from the treatment
             and followed up for safety as per protocol. Occurrence of menarche in the course of
             the study should always be documented.

          2. Intake of another investigational medication in another clinical study within 30 days
             prior to the first study drug intake.

          3. Clinically significant ECG abnormalities as judged by the investigator (e.g.,
             Wolff-Parkinson-White [WPW] syndrome, long QT syndrome).

          4. Known allergy/hypersensitivity to the study drug or its inactive ingredients.

          5. Any clinical conditions or circumstances that in the opinion of the investigator would
             make the subject unsuitable for the study (e.g., hepatic impairment, renal impairment,
             mental impairment, cardiac disease).

          6. Subjects with known positive Hepatitis B surface antigen (Hbs Ag), or Hepatitis C
             antibody or who are known to be human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) positive. No
             testing will be required for this study.

          7. Subjects who are expected to take during the study period or have taken any of the
             following medications prior to inclusion in the study and have not complied with the
             specified wash out period of 7 days unless otherwise noted:

               -  Oral corticosteroids.

               -  Oral antihistamines: loratadine, desloratadine, and fexofenadine.

               -  Anti-leukotrienes

               -  Amoxicillin, benzylpenicillin, and macrolide antibiotics and imidazolic
                  antifungals (systemic)

               -  Omeprazol

               -  Aspirin, ibuprofen

               -  Carbamazepine

               -  St. John's Wort (15 days)

          8. Hypersensitivity to H1 antihistamines or benzimidazoles.

          9. Ingestion of citrus fruits and cranberries or any fruit juice or any other well known
             PgP or organic anion transporter polypeptide (OATP) inhibitor, inducer, or substrate
             (see Appendix C) within 7 days prior to first dose of study medication.

         10. Mentally disabled minors or Minors who by official order have been institutionalised
             (e.g., in orphanages) must be excluded from participation.

         11. Minors who explicitly refuse to take part in the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/01/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>36</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/06/2012</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Children's Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children - Subiaco</hospital>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
    <postcode>6840 - Subiaco</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Berlin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Franfurt</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Kiel</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Stockholm</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Uppsala</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Faes Farma, S.A.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The conduct of this clinical trial is aimed at determining the most suitable dose regimen for
      children in different age groups, and secondarily to assess the safety and tolerability of
      bilastine in this paediatric population subset.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01081574</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Jauregizar N, de la Fuente L, Lucero ML, Sologuren A, Leal N, Rodríguez M. Pharmacokinetic-pharmacodynamic modelling of the antihistaminic (H1) effect of bilastine. Clin Pharmacokinet. 2009;48(8):543-54. doi: 10.2165/11317180-000000000-00000.
Zuberbier T, Oanta A, Bogacka E, Medina I, Wesel F, Uhl P, Antépara I, Jáuregui I, Valiente R; Bilastine International Working Group. Comparison of the efficacy and safety of bilastine 20 mg vs levocetirizine 5 mg for the treatment of chronic idiopathic urticaria: a multi-centre, double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled study. Allergy. 2010 Apr;65(4):516-28. doi: 10.1111/j.1398-9995.2009.02217.x. Epub 2009 Oct 23.
Horak F, Zieglmayer P, Zieglmayer R, Lemell P. The effects of bilastine compared with cetirizine, fexofenadine, and placebo on allergen-induced nasal and ocular symptoms in patients exposed to aeroallergen in the Vienna Challenge Chamber. Inflamm Res. 2010 May;59(5):391-8. doi: 10.1007/s00011-009-0117-4. Epub 2009 Nov 27.
Kuna P, Bachert C, Nowacki Z, van Cauwenberge P, Agache I, Fouquert L, Roger A, Sologuren A, Valiente R; Bilastine International Working Group. Efficacy and safety of bilastine 20 mg compared with cetirizine 10 mg and placebo for the symptomatic treatment of seasonal allergic rhinitis: a randomized, double-blind, parallel-group study. Clin Exp Allergy. 2009 Sep;39(9):1338-47. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2222.2009.03257.x. Epub 2009 May 4.
Bachert C, Kuna P, Sanquer F, Ivan P, Dimitrov V, Gorina MM, van de Heyning P, Loureiro A; Bilastine International Working Group. Comparison of the efficacy and safety of bilastine 20 mg vs desloratadine 5 mg in seasonal allergic rhinitis patients. Allergy. 2009 Jan;64(1):158-65. doi: 10.1111/j.1398-9995.2008.01813.x.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ulrich Wahn, Prof. Dr.</name>
      <address>International Coordinating Investigator. Charité - Universitätsmedizin Berlin (Germany)</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>