<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6161">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/11/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/11/2016</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02953054</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Dexmedetomidine Transdermal System (DMTS) for Post-Operative Analgesia Following Bunionectomy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Single-Dose Evaluation of the Dexmedetomidine Transdermal System for Post-Operative Analgesia Following Bunionectomy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>DMTS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>TPU-DMT-02-1503</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pain, Postoperative</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - DMTS
Treatment: drugs - Placebo

Active Comparator: DMTS - DMTS applied to the upper arm

Placebo Comparator: Placebo - Placebo patches to match DMTS applied to the upper arm


Treatment: drugs: DMTS
DMTS applied before surgery and worn for 72 hours

Treatment: drugs: Placebo
Matching patches that have no active drug applied before surgery and worn for 72 hours.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time-interval weighted summed pain intensity (SPI), measured using the 11 point (0 to 10) numeric rating scale (NRS) at designated time points from 4 to 24 hours following surgery (NRSSPI).</outcome>
      <timepoint>From 4 to 24 hours following surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time-interval weighted summed pain intensity over various time intervals</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 72 hours after surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of subjects using opioid rescue pain medication</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 72 hours after surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The time to first use of rescue pain medication</outcome>
      <timepoint>intraoperative</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Voluntarily provide written informed consent.

          2. Male or female, = 18 years of age.

          3. Scheduled to undergo a primary unilateral first metatarsal bunionectomy repair.

          4. Have a physical status classification of 1 or 2 per the American Society of
             Anesthesiology.

          5. Non-smoker for at least 1 year prior to screening; non-smoking is defined by cessation
             of smoking and use of all other tobacco and nicotine products (including chewing
             tobacco, snuff, e-cigarettes, nicotine patches, etc.).

          6. Female subjects are eligible only if all the following apply:

               1. Not pregnant, not lactating, and not planning to become pregnant during the study

               2. Surgically sterile; or at least 2 years postmenopausal; or have a monogamous
                  partner who is surgically sterile; or have a same gender sex partner; or is
                  practicing double-barrier contraception; or practicing abstinence; or using an
                  insertable, injectable, transdermal, or combination oral contraceptive

          7. Male subjects with female sex partners must be surgically sterile or commit to the use
             of a reliable method of birth control.

          8. Have a body weight &gt; 50 kg, and body mass index of 22 to 38 kg/m2, inclusive.

          9. Able to understand the study procedures, comply with all study procedures, and agree
             to participate in the study program for its full duration.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Have a known sensitivity to dexmedetomidine or any excipient in the DMTS/placebo or to
             any peri- or postoperative medication whose use is required in this study.

          2. Have a skin abnormality (eg, scar, tattoo) or unhealthy skin condition (eg, burns,
             wounds) at the patch application site, according to examination by the investigator at
             screening or admission to the clinic prior to surgery.

          3. Have a clinically significant abnormal clinical laboratory test value.

          4. Have history of or positive test results for the human immunodeficiency virus (HIV),
             hepatitis B, or hepatitis C.

          5. Have a history or clinical manifestations of: a significant renal, hepatic,
             cardiovascular, metabolic, neurologic, or psychiatric condition; congestive heart
             failure, peptic ulcer, gastrointestinal bleeding, or other condition that would
             preclude participation in the study.

          6. Have a history of migraine or frequent headaches, seizures, or are currently taking
             anticonvulsants.

          7. Have another painful physical condition that may confound the assessments of
             postoperative pain.

          8. Have a history of syncope or other syncopal attacks.

          9. Have evidence of a clinically significant 12-lead ECG abnormality.

         10. Have a history of alcohol abuse or prescription/illicit drug abuse.

         11. Have positive results on the urine drug screen or alcohol breath test indicative of
             illicit drug or alcohol use at screening and/or clinic check-in.

         12. Have a history or evidence of clinically significant orthostatic hypotension.

         13. Have a resting heart rate of &lt; 50 beats per minute or systolic blood pressure &lt; 100
             mmHg.

         14. Have been receiving or have received opioid therapy chronically for &gt; 2 weeks within
             the month prior to dosing of the study drug.

         15. Use concurrent therapy that could interfere with the evaluation of efficacy or safety,
             such as any drugs which in the investigator's opinion may exert significant analgesic
             properties or act synergistically with dexmedetomidine.

         16. Have had an upper respiratory tract infection within 14 days prior to dosing of the
             study drug.

         17. Have utilized oral or injectable corticosteroids within 14 days prior to dosing of the
             study drug (intranasal and topical corticosteroid use during this time period is
             allowed).

         18. Have received any investigational product within 30 days prior to dosing of the study
             drug.

         19. Have previously received DMTS in a clinical trial.

         20. Sensitivity to opioids, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, or antibiotics.

         21. In the opinion of the investigator or designee, is considered unsuitable for study
             entry and/or is unlikely to comply with the study protocol for any reason.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2>The people administering the treatment/s</masking2>
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>22/01/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>88</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>3/07/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Nucleus Network LTD - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Linear Clinical Research - Nedlands</hospital>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Teikoku Pharma USA, Inc.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Premier Research Group plc</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to evaluate whether the DMTS, compared with a placebo patch,
      will provide adequate pain relief during the first 3 days following bunionectomy surgery.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02953054</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Gertler R, Brown HC, Mitchell DH, Silvius EN. Dexmedetomidine: a novel sedative-analgesic agent. Proc (Bayl Univ Med Cent). 2001 Jan;14(1):13-21.
Kivistö KT, Kallio A, Neuvonen PJ. Pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of transdermal dexmedetomidine. Eur J Clin Pharmacol. 1994;46(4):345-9.
Némethy M, Paroli L, Williams-Russo PG, Blanck TJ. Assessing sedation with regional anesthesia: inter-rater agreement on a modified Wilson sedation scale. Anesth Analg. 2002 Mar;94(3):723-8; table of contents.
American Society of Anesthesiologists Task Force on Acute Pain Management. Practice guidelines for acute pain management in the perioperative setting: an updated report by the American Society of Anesthesiologists Task Force on Acute Pain Management. Anesthesiology. 2012 Feb;116(2):248-73. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e31823c1030.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>James Song, MS, MBA</name>
      <address>Teikoku Pharma USA, Inc.</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>