<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3977">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/01/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/01/2013</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01767467</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Study to Assess the Safety and Immunogenicity of GlaxoSmithKline (GSK) Biologicals' Herpes Zoster Subunit (HZ/su) Vaccine in Adults Aged 18 Years and Older With Blood Cancers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Study to Evaluate Safety and Immunogenicity of GSK Biologicals' Herpes Zoster Vaccine GSK1437173A in Adults Aged 18 Years and Older With Haematologic Malignancies</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>2012-003438-18</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>116428</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Herpes Zoster</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - Herpes zoster vaccine (GSK 1437173A)
Treatment: drugs - Placebo

Experimental: Vaccine Group - Subjects will receive the candidate HZ vaccine (GSK 1437173A).

Placebo Comparator: Placebo Group - Subjects will receive the placebo vaccine.


Other interventions: Herpes zoster vaccine (GSK 1437173A)
2 doses administered intramuscularly (IM) in deltoid region of non-dominant arm. Dose 1 administered at Day 0. Dose 2 administered 1-2 months post Dose 1.

Treatment: drugs: Placebo
2 doses administered intramuscularly (IM) in deltoid region of non-dominant arm. Dose 1 administered at Day 0. Dose 2 administered 1-2 months post Dose 1.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Vaccine Response Rates (VRR) for Anti-gE Antibody ELISA Concentrations - Vaccine response rate was the number of subjects with a vaccine response. Vaccine response was defined as:
For initially seronegative subjects, antibody concentration at Month 2 = 4 fold the cut-off for Anti-gE (4x97 mIU/mL) For initially seropositive subjects, antibody concentration at Month 2 = 4 fold the pre-vaccination antibody concentration This analysis was performed in subjects with haematologic malignancies excluding subjects with Non-Hodgkin B-cell Lymphoma and Chronic Lymphocytic Leukaemia.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Month 2</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adjusted Geometric Mean Concentration of Anti-gE Antibodies - The Adjusted geometric mean concentration was measured in all subjects excluding those with Non-Hodgkin B-cell Lymphoma and Chronic Lymphocytic Leukaemia.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Month 2</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Any and Grade 3 Solicited Local Symptoms. - Assessed solicited local symptoms were pain, redness and swelling. Any = occurrence of the symptom regardless of intensity grade. Grade 3 pain = pain that prevented normal activity. Grade 3 redness/swelling = redness/swelling spreading beyond 100 millimeters (mm) of injection site. Since the study is ongoing, results for the individual groups are blinded. Hence results were presented per the total number of subjects.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 7 days (Days 0-6) after each vaccination</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Any, Grade 3 and Related Solicited General Symptoms. - Assessed solicited general symptoms were arthralgia, fatigue, fever [defined as axillary temperature equal to or above 37.5 degrees Celsius (°C)], headache, myalgia, shivering and sweating. Any = occurrence of the symptom regardless of intensity grade. Grade 3 symptom = symptom that prevented normal activity. Grade 3 fever = fever &gt; 39.0 °C. Related = symptom assessed by the investigator as related to the vaccination.</outcome>
      <timepoint>during the 7-day (Days 0-6) post-vaccination period</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Any, Grade 3 and Related Unsolicited Adverse Events (AEs). - An unsolicited AE covers any untoward medical occurrence in a clinical investigation subject temporally associated with the use of a medicinal product, whether or not considered related to the medicinal product and reported in addition to those solicited during the clinical study and any solicited symptom with onset outside the specified period of follow-up for solicited symptoms. Any was defined as the occurrence of any unsolicited AE regardless of intensity grade or relation to vaccination. Grade 3 AE = an AE which prevented normal, everyday activities. Related = AE assessed by the investigator as related to the vaccination.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 30 days (Days 0-29) after each vaccination</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Serious Adverse Events (SAEs). - Serious adverse events (SAEs) assessed include medical occurrences that result in death, are life threatening, require hospitalization or prolongation of hospitalization or result in disability/incapacity.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From first vaccination up to 30 days post last vaccination</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects Reporting Any Potential Immune-mediated Diseases (pIMDs) - Potential immune-mediated diseases (pIMDs) are a subset of AEs that include autoimmune diseases and other inflammatory and/or neurologic disorders of interest which may or may not have an autoimmune aetiology.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 30 days post last vaccination</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Days With Solicited Local Symptoms</outcome>
      <timepoint>within 7 days (Days 0-6) after each vaccination</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Days With Solicited General Symptoms</outcome>
      <timepoint>within the 7 days (Day 0-6) after each vaccination</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Occurrence of Confirmed HZ Cases</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Month 0 until study end</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Antibody Titer Equal to or Above Cut-off - This parameter was assessed in all vaccinated subjects excluding subjects with Non-Hodgkin B-cell Lymphoma. The cut-off value is 97 mIU/mL.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Month 2</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anti-gE Antibody Concentration - Concentrations were presente as geometeric mean concentrations (GMCs) and expressed as milli-international units per milliliter (mIU/mL).This parameter was assessed in all vaccinated subjects excluding subjects with Non-Hodgkin B-cell Lymphoma.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Month 2</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Concentrations of Anti-gE Antibodies - Antibody concentrations given in enzyme linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) units per millilitre (EU/mL) were expressed as Geometric Mean Concentrations (GMCs) in all subjects.
Note: results for Month 13 were not yeat available at the time of this posting.We will update them once they become available.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Month 0, Month 1, Month 2 and Month 13</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Vaccine Response Rates (VRR) for Anti-gE Antibody ELISA Concentrations - The vaccine response rate (VRR) was defined as the percentage of subjects who have at least a 4-fold increase in the anti-gE Ab concentration as compared to the pre-vaccination anti-gE Ab concentration, for subjects who are seropositive at baseline or, at least a 4-fold increase in the anti-gE Ab concentration as compared to the anti-gE Ab cut-off value for seropositivity, for subjects who are seronegative at baseline. Vaccine response was measured in all subjects.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Month 1, Month 2 and Month 13</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Frequency of gE -Specific Cluster of Differentiation 4+ T Cells (CD4+) Expressing at Least 2 Activation Markers - Among markers expressed were interferon-gamma (IFN-?), interleukin-2 (IL-2), tumour necrosis factor-alpha (TNF-a) and cluster of differentiation 40 ligand (CD40L), as determined by in vitro intracellular cytokine staining (ICS). Note: results for Month 13 were not yeat available at the time of this posting.We will update them once they become available.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Month 0, Month 1, Month 2 and Month 13</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Vaccine Response Rates (VRR) for gE-specific CD4 [2+] T-cells, Expressing at Least 2 Activation Markers. - Among markers expressed were IFN-?, IL-2, TNF-a and CD40L, as determined by in vitro ICS. Vaccine response defined as:
For initially subjects with pre-vaccination T cell frequencies below the threshold, at least a 2-fold increase as compared to the threshold (2x&lt;320&gt; Events/106 CD4+ T cells) For initially subjects with pre-vaccination T cell frequencies above the threshold, at least a 2-fold increase as compared to pre-vaccination T cell frequencies</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Month 1, Month 2 and Month 13</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anti-gE Humoral Immunogenicity in Subjects With Confirmed HZ and Matched Controls</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Month 0 and at Month 2</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects With Serious Adverse Events (SAEs) - Serious adverse events (SAEs) assessed include medical occurrences that result in death, are life threatening, require hospitalization or prolongation of hospitalization or result in disability/incapacity.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From first vaccination up to 6 months post last vaccination</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects Reporting Any Potential Immune-mediated Diseases (pIMDs) - Potential immune-mediated diseases (pIMDs) are a subset of AEs that include autoimmune diseases and other inflammatory and/or neurologic disorders of interest which may or may not have an autoimmune aetiology</outcome>
      <timepoint>From first vaccination up to 6 months post last vaccination</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Subjects who the investigator believes can and will comply with the requirements of
             the protocol.

          -  Written informed consent obtained from the subject.

          -  A male or female, aged 18 years or older at the time of study entry.

          -  Subject who has been diagnosed with one or more haematologic malignancies prior to the
             first vaccination and who is receiving, is scheduled to receive or has just finished
             immunosuppressive cancer therapy to treat this condition.

          -  Life expectancy greater than or equal to 12 months, as assessed by the investigator.

          -  Female subjects of non-childbearing potential may be enrolled in the study.

               -  Non-childbearing potential is defined as pre-menarche, current tubal ligation,
                  hysterectomy, ovariectomy or post-menopause.

          -  Female subjects of childbearing potential may be enrolled inthe study, if the subject:

               -  has practiced adequate contraception for 30 days prior to vaccination, and

               -  has a negative pregnancy test on the day of vaccination, and

               -  has agreed to continue adequate contraception during the entire treatment period
                  and for 2 months after completion of the vaccination series.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Subject diagnosed with chronic lymphocytic leukaemia (CLL) who is receiving only oral
             cancer therapy (subject receiving intra-venous cancer therapy for CLL or intra-venous
             cancer therapy in combination with oral therapy may be enrolled).

          -  Subject receiving radiotherapy alone as treatment for his/her haematologic malignancy.

          -  Planned haematopoietic stem cell transplant (HCT) during the study period. (If a HCT
             occurred prior to enrolment in the study, the subject may not receive study vaccine
             until at least 50 days after the transplant procedure).

          -  Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection by clinical history.

          -  Use of any investigational or non-registered product other than the study vaccine
             within 30 days preceding the first dose of study vaccine/placebo, or planned use
             during the study period. However, the investigational use of a registered product to
             treat the subject's underlying disease, is allowed.

          -  Previous vaccination against HZ or varicella within the 12 months preceding the first
             dose of study vaccine/placebo.

          -  Planned administration during the study of a HZ or varicella vaccine (including an
             investigational or non-registered vaccine) other than the study vaccine.

          -  Occurrence of a varicella or HZ episode by clinical history within the 12 months
             preceding the first dose of study vaccine/placebo.

          -  History of any reaction or hypersensitivity likely to be exacerbated by any component
             of the vaccine.

          -  Administration or planned administration of a live vaccine in the period starting 30
             days before the first dose of study vaccine and ending 30 days after the last dose of
             study vaccine.

          -  Administration or planned administration of a non-replicating vaccine within 8 days
             prior to or within 14 days after either dose of study vaccine.

          -  Pregnant or lactating female.

          -  Female planning to become pregnant or planning to discontinue contraceptive
             precautions before Month 3 (i.e., 2 months after the last dose of study
             vaccine/placebo).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2>The people administering the treatment/s</masking2>
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/03/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>568</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>6/01/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,TAS,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Darlinghurst</hospital>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Hobart</hospital>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Coburg</hospital>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Wodonga</hospital>
    <postcode>2010 - Darlinghurst</postcode>
    <postcode>7000 - Hobart</postcode>
    <postcode>3058 - Coburg</postcode>
    <postcode>3690 - Wodonga</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Illinois</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Indiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Massachusetts</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Minnesota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Washington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Wisconsin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Antwerpen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Brugge</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Bruxelles</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Hasselt</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Jette</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Leuven</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>New Brunswick</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Nova Scotia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Praha 2</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Finland</country>
      <state>Helsinki</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Finland</country>
      <state>Tampere</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Montpellier cedex 5</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Mulhouse</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Nantes cedex 1</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Pessac cedex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Périgueux cedex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Rouen cedex 1</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <state>Hong Kong</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Emilia-Romagna</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Friuli-Venezia-Giulia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Piemonte</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Busan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Daegu</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Incheon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Jellanamdo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Jeonju</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Kyunggi-do</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Seoul</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Christchurch</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Hamilton</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Pakistan</country>
      <state>Lahore</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Pakistan</country>
      <state>Multan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Panama</country>
      <state>Panama</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Chorzow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Opole</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Slupsk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Ekaterinburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Nizhniy Novgorod</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Petrozavodsk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>St'Petersburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>St-Petersburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>St. Petersburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Singapore</country>
      <state>Singapore</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Majadahonda (Madrid)</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Pozuelo de Alarcón/Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Santander</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Eskilstuna</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Karlskrona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Malmö</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Uppsala</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Kaohsiung</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Taichung</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Taipei</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Taoyuan Hsien</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>Ankara</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Kent</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Lanarkshire</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Wiltshire</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Bournemouth</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Headington, Oxford</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>GlaxoSmithKline</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to evaluate the safety and immunogenicity of GSK Biologicals'
      vaccine GSK1437173A in subjects aged 18 years and older with blood cancers. The study will
      evaluate safety-related events and antibody and cellular immune responses to the study
      vaccine, as compared to placebo.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01767467</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>GSK Clinical Trials</name>
      <address>GlaxoSmithKline</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>