<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2219">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/12/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/12/2008</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00811213</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>SensAwake Sleep Quality Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>SASQT: SensAwake Sleep Quality Trial A Study to Test the Efficacy of the SensAwake Modification to Automatically Titrating Continuous Positive Airway Pressure to Reduce Wake After Sleep Onset in Patients With Moderate to Severe Obstructive Sleep Apnea.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>SASQT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>FP-08E-108</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Sleep Apnea, Obstructive</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sleep apnoea</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - SleepStyle 200 Auto Series with SensAwake
Treatment: devices - SleepStyle 200 Auto Series with out SensAwake

Experimental: 1 - Auto adjusting Continuous Postive Aiway Pressure (CPAP) Device with SensAwake technology enabled

Active Comparator: 2 - Auto adjusting Continuous Postive Aiway Pressure (CPAP) Device with SensAwake technology disabled


Treatment: devices: SleepStyle 200 Auto Series with SensAwake
Auto adjusting Continuous Postive Aiway Pressure (CPAP) Device with SensAwake technology enabled

Treatment: devices: SleepStyle 200 Auto Series with out SensAwake
Auto adjusting Continuous Postive Aiway Pressure (CPAP) Device with SensAwake technology disabled

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Wake After Sleep Onset (WASO) between treatment with standard APAP and APAP modified by the addition of the SensAwake modification</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 Night</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sleep Efficiency</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 night</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Slow Wave Sleep</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 night</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Aged 18-65 years with moderate-to-severe OSA (Apnea Hypopnea index equal to or greater
             than 15 per hour).

          -  Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS) scores 0-15 inclusive (normal to moderately severe
             daytime sleepiness).

          -  Fluency in both written and spoken English.

          -  Do not have unstable psychiatric disease.

          -  No other significant sleep disorder.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Participants prescribed and fitted with any PAP device in the past 2 years.

          -  Unstable cardiovascular disease (untreated or resistant hypertension acceptable).

          -  Inability to tolerate CPAP due to nasal obstruction or claustrophobia as determined by
             the study investigator.

          -  Any known factor or disease that might interfere with treatment compliance, study
             conduct or interpretation of the results such as psychiatric disease, history of non
             compliance to medical regimens, or unwillingness to comply with study requirements.

          -  Participation in another clinical trial in the previous month.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/10/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>45</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/08/2009</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research - Sydney</hospital>
    <postcode>2037 - Sydney</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Fisher and Paykel Healthcare</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The SensAwake modification to the Fisher and Paykel automatically titrating positive airway
      pressure (APAP) device aims to sense whether the patient is awake via respiratory patterns
      that differentiate between sleep and wake. Upon sensing that the patient is awake the device
      is able to reduce positive airway pressure PAP aiming to improve patient comfort which should
      result in more consolidated sleep. This study will investigate Obstructive Sleep Apnea (OSA)
      and a automatically Adjusting Positive Airway Pressure (APAP) device with new technology
      called SensAwake. This requires experimental confirmation in a randomised controlled trial.
      Double-blind randomised crossover trial comparing WASO on standard APAP with WASO using APAP
      modified by the addition of the SensAwake modification on consecutive nights in participants
      with moderate-to-severe OSA.

      A total number of 45 participants will be recruited from an OSA population, aged 18-65.
      Participants will consist of male and female patients diagnosed with moderate-severe OSA
      (Apnea Hypopnea Index (AHI) greater than or equal to 15 per hour. Eligible participants,
      according to the protocol approved by the HREC, providing written informed consent will be
      enrolled into the study. Patients will be enrolled sequentially according to the
      randomisation list. Patients will be randomised to APAP or APAP with the addition of the
      SensAwake modification. The investigator and study staff will be blinded to the treatment of
      any participant.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00811213</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Brendon Yee, MBChB</name>
      <address>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>