<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="910">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/10/2005</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/10/2005</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00234169</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Study of Peripheral Blood Progenitor Cells Mobilisation (PBPC) With VTP195183 Plus Granulocyte-Colony Stimulating Factor (G-CSF) Compared to Mobilisation With G-CSF Alone</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase I/II Study of Peripheral Blood Progenitor Cells Mobilisation With VTP195183 Plus G-CSF Compared to Mobilisation With G-CSF Alone in Patients With Multiple Myeloma and Lymphoma.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>05/09</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Multiple Myeloma</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Lymphoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lymphoma (non Hodgkin's lymphoma) - High grade lymphoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lymphoma (non Hodgkin's lymphoma) - Low grade lymphoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cancer types</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - VTP195183

Treatment: drugs: VTP195183
VTP195183: 60mg/m2 orally daily G-CSF: 10mcg/kg/day subcutaneously Provision is made for dose reduction of VTP195183 in the event of unexpected dose-limiting toxicities G-CSF10mcg/kg/day will commence on day 1 and will continue until the peripheral blood (PB) CD34+ count falls below baseline, or below 5 x 106/L, whichever happens first.
Patients will be treated with VTP195183 alone at 60mg/m2/day from day 1 to day 7. On day 8 VTP195183 will be continued and G-CSF10mcg/kg/day will be added. VTP195183 plus G-CSF will continue until the peripheral blood (PB) CD34+ count falls below baseline, or below 5 x 106/L, whichever happens first.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PB CD34+ kinetics using VTP195183 plus G-CSF</outcome>
      <timepoint>up to 28 days post study drug administration</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The toxicity of VTP195183 pretreatment when used with G-CSF</outcome>
      <timepoint>within 28 days of study drug administration</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Age 18-70

          2. Histologically proven multiple myeloma or lymphoma

          3. Intent of treating physician to proceed to high dose therapy and autologous
             transplantation

          4. Not currently receiving thalidomide (within 1 week of commencing VTP195813 or G-CSF),
             cytotoxic agents or high dose prednisolone or Dexamethasone (at doses greater than 15
             mg prednisolone or equivalent per day)

          5. Multiple myeloma patients must be taking regular bisphosphonate therapy

          6. Absolute neutrophil count between 1.5 and 10 x 109/L

          7. ECOG performance status ? 2

          8. Life expectancy of at least 2 months

          9. Written informed consent signed by patient or legally authorized representative</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Active infection or a fever &gt; 38.2 degrees C (fever due to B symptoms in lymphoma
             patients will not exclude a patient)

          2. Use within the previous 30 days of other vitamin A preparations within the last 30
             days (including oral vitamin supplements, oral retinoids for acne or other skin
             disorders, bexarotene, or topical vitamin A preparations)

          3. Pregnancy or breast feeding. Women of child-bearing potential, admitted to the trial
             must take adequate measures to prevent conception (at least two different forms of
             contraception during the study and for at least one month after completion of study
             drugs) and are to undergo a pregnancy test

          4. Significant non-malignant disease including HIV infection, uncontrolled hypertension
             (diastolic blood pressures &gt; 115 mmHg), unstable angina

          5. Known allergy to E.coli-derived products

          6. Current treatment with tetracycline antibiotics</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/10/2005</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>30</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/01/2008</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Peter MacCallum Cancer centre - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3002 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre, Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>The Leukemia and Lymphoma Society</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Hematopoietic stem cells (HSC) are used to support the administration of high dose
      chemotherapy for a range of human cancers. For a safe HSC transplantation, a minimum of 5
      million HSC per kilogram are required. HSC are collected from the bone marrow by using drugs
      such as G-CSF (filgrastim) which 'mobilize' them from the bone marrow into the bloodstream.
      HSC are collected from the bloodstream using an apheresis machine. Between 5 and 60% of
      patients fail to mobilize the minimum HSC dose required for safe transplantation, and this
      trial is investigating a way to enhance mobilization to overcome this problem. This trial
      aims to determine if a new vitamin A derivative is capable of enhancing HSC mobilization when
      used in conjunction with G-CSF. Patients will undergo two mobilization procedures. They will
      be given G-CSF alone, or a combination of the study drug plus G-CSF, and their stem cells
      will be collected. A comparison group of patients will be given G-CSF alone for both
      mobilizations. Stem cells collected from patients in this trial will be frozen and stored
      until they are required for transplantation into that patient. At that time, patients will be
      monitored for how well they recover from their high dose chemotherapy and HSC
      transplantation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00234169</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kirsten Herbert, MBBS</name>
      <address>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre, Australia</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>