<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3480">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/11/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/11/2011</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01545817</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Everolimus Post Pazopanib Treatment in Metastatic or Advanced Renal Cell Carcinoma</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Continuous Access to Advanced and Metastatic Renal Cell Carcinoma Therapy With Everolimus Post Pazopanib Treatment</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>CATChEz</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>114907</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Carcinoma, Renal Cell</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Non melanoma skin cancer</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Pazopanib followed by everolimus

Experimental: Pazopanib followed by everolimus - First line pazopanib, followed by second line everolimus


Treatment: drugs: Pazopanib followed by everolimus
all patients will receive Pazopanib (800 mg once daily orally continuous dosing) until disease progression then second line everolimus (10 mg once daily orally continuous dosing)

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Median progression free survival on everolimus - Median progression free survival on everolimus as second line treatment post pazopanib as first line</outcome>
      <timepoint>Everolimus treatment until earliest date of disease progression or death, assessed up to 30 months after the last patient has been enrolled</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression free survival proportion at three and six months after first everolimus dose</outcome>
      <timepoint>Initiation of everolimus treatment until earliest date of disease progression or death, assessed at three and six months after first everolimus dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Objective Response Rate to everolimus therapy</outcome>
      <timepoint>Initiation of everolimus treatment until time of confirmed best response, assessed up to 30 months after the last patient has been enrolled</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Objective response rate to pazopanib therapy</outcome>
      <timepoint>Initiation of pazopanib treatment until time of confirmed best response, assessed up to 30 months after the last patient has been enrolled</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall survival of patients treated with second-line everolimus therapy</outcome>
      <timepoint>Initiation of everolimus dose until death, assessed up to 30 months after the last patient has been enrolled</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall survival for the study for patients receiving at least one dose of pazopanib followed by everolimus</outcome>
      <timepoint>Initiation of pazopanib until death for patients receiving at least one dose of pazopanib followed by everolimus, assessed up to 30 months after the last patient has been enrolled</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Median progression free survival of patients treated with pazopanib</outcome>
      <timepoint>Initiation of pazopanib until progression or death whichever comes first, provided this occurs prior to the commencement of everolimus and within 6 months of last dose of pazopanib, assessed up to 30 months after the last patient has been enrolled</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of grade 3 or 4 adverse events attributable to everolimus</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of first dose of everolimus to approximately one month after discontinuation of everolimus</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>All grade 3 or 4 adverse events attributable to pazopanib and everolimus treatments</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of first dose of pazopanib to approximately one month after discontinuation of everolimus</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Written informed consent

          2. Diagnosis of renal cell carcinoma with clear-cell component histology.

          3. Locally advanced/metastatic renal cell carcinoma

          4. Measurable lesion (RECIST 1.1) on physical exam or as CT/MRI

          5. No prior systemic therapy for advanced/metastatic RCC

          6. Karnofsky performance scale &gt;=70

          7. Age &gt;=18 years

          8. A female is eligible to enter and participate in this study if she is of:
             non-childbearing/agrees to use adequate contraception

          9. A male with female partner of childbearing potential must have vasectomy/agree to use
             effective contraception from two weeks prior to administration of the 1st dose of
             study treatment for a period of time after the last dose of study treatment

         10. Adequate organ function

         11. Able to swallow and retain orally administered medication and must not have clinically
             significant GIT abnormalities that may alter absorption

             Additional criterion for inclusion in the everolimus treatment:

         12. The date of disease progression must be within six months of stopping pazopanib or
             during treatment with pazopanib

         13. Measurable lesion at Everolimus C1D1 Scan (everolimus baseline) as per the RECIST 1.1
             criteria

         14. Patients with radiotherapy prior to Everolimus treatment period will be eligible only
             if all below requirements are fulfilled:

               -  The last radiotherapy fraction is delivered &gt; 4 weeks prior to first dose of
                  everolimus

               -  The radiotherapy is not considered to be a second line treatment

               -  The previously irradiated lesion(s) are not considered as target lesion(s) for
                  everolimus RECIST 1.1 assessment

               -  The radiotherapy field is not sufficiently close to the target lesion(s) so as to
                  interfere with everolimus RECIST 1.1 assessments

               -  There is no ongoing toxicity that is &gt; Grade 1 and/or that is progressing in
                  severity

        16.Patients with central nervous system (CNS) progression or metastases during Pazopanib
        treatment period, will be eligible only if all below requirements are fulfilled:

          -  Are asymptomatic and neurologically stable shown by no requirement for steroids (to
             control CNS symptoms) or enzyme-inducing anticonvulsants within 4 weeks prior to start
             of everolimus

          -  If the lesion was previously been treated locally (by surgery ± radiotherapy,
             radiosurgery, or gamma knife) the last local treatment should be at least &gt; 4 weeks
             prior to start of everolimus

          -  Lesions that have been previously irradiated or in an area subjected to other
             loco-regional therapy are not considered as target lesion(s) for everolimus RECIST 1.1
             assessment

          -  Have no presence of any non-healing wound</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Pregnant/lactating

          2. History of another malignancy (unless have been disease-free for 3 years)

          3. History or clinical evidence of Central nervous system metastases (unless have
             previously-treated CNS metastases and who meet both of the following criteria: a) are
             asymptomatic and b) have no requirement for steroids or enzyme-inducing
             anticonvulsants in prior 6 month time interval.

          4. Clinically significant gastrointestinal abnormalities including, but not limited to:
             malabsorption syndrome, major resection of the stomach or small bowel that could
             affect the absorption of study drug, active peptic ulcer disease, known intraluminal
             metastatic lesion/s with suspected bleeding, Inflammatory bowel disease, ulcerative
             colitis, or other gastrointestinal conditions with increased risk of perforation,
             history of abdominal fistula, gastrointestinal perforation, or intra abdominal abscess

          5. Moderate to severe hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh Class C)

          6. Any serious and/or unstable pre-existing medical, psychiatric, or other conditions
             that could interfere with patient's safety, obtaining informed consent or compliance
             to the study.

          7. Subjects receiving chronic treatment with corticosteroids/other immunosuppressive
             agents

          8. Subjects with a known history of HIV seropositivity

          9. Subjects with active bleeding, bleeding diathesis or on oral anti-vitamin K medication
             (except low dose coumadin)

         10. Presence of any severe or uncontrolled medical conditions/infection.

         11. Currently receiving chemotherapy, immunotherapy or radiotherapy

         12. Corrected QT interval (QTc) &gt; 480 milliseconds

         13. History of any one or more of the following cardiovascular conditions within the past
             12 months: cardiac angioplasty or stenting, myocardial infarction, unstable angina,
             coronary artery by-pass graft surgery, symptomatic peripheral vascular disease, Class
             III or IV congestive heart failure, as defined by the New York Heart Association

         14. Poorly controlled hypertension (defined as systolic blood pressure of &gt;=140mmHg or
             diastolic blood pressure of &gt;=90mmHg).

         15. History of cerebrovascular accident including transient ischemic attack, pulmonary
             embolism or untreated deep venous thrombosis (DVT) within the past 6 months (unless
             recent DVT have been treated with therapeutic anti-coagulating agents for at least 6
             weeks)

         16. Major surgery or trauma within 28 days prior to first dose of study drug and/or
             presence of any non-healing wound, fracture, or ulcer.

         17. Evidence of active bleeding or bleeding susceptibility.

         18. Known endobronchial lesion and/or lesions infiltrating major pulmonary vessels that
             increase the risk of pulmonary hemorrage

         19. Recent haemoptysis in excess of 2.5ml within eight weeks of first dose of study drug.

         20. Use of an investigational agent, including an investigational anti-cancer agent,
             within 30 days or 5 half-lives, whichever is longer, prior to the first dose of study
             drug.

         21. Any ongoing toxicity from prior anti-cancer therapy that is &gt;Grade 1 and/or that is
             progressing in severity, except alopecia.

         22. Known immediate or delayed hypersensitivity reaction or idiosyncrasy to drugs
             chemically related to pazopanib or everolimus, to other rapamycin derivatives or to
             any other excipients.

             Additional criterion for exclusion in the everolimus treatment:

         23. The subject is felt by the investigator to be unsuitable (on the basis of health,
             compliance, or for any other reason) for inclusion in the study.

         24. Presence of any severe and/or uncontrolled medical conditions</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/04/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>74</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Terminated</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/11/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,QLD,SA,VIC,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Novartis Investigative Site - Garran</hospital>
    <hospital>Novartis Investigative Site - Kogarah</hospital>
    <hospital>Novartis Investigative Site - Auchenflower</hospital>
    <hospital>Novartis Investigative Site - Southport</hospital>
    <hospital>Novartis Investigative Site - Elizabeth Vale</hospital>
    <hospital>Novartis Investigative Site - Kurralta Park</hospital>
    <hospital>Novartis Investigative Site - Woodville</hospital>
    <hospital>Novartis Investigative Site - Footscray</hospital>
    <hospital>Novartis Investigative Site - Frankston</hospital>
    <hospital>Novartis Investigative Site - Nedlands</hospital>
    <hospital>Novartis Investigative Site - Perth</hospital>
    <postcode>2606 - Garran</postcode>
    <postcode>2217 - Kogarah</postcode>
    <postcode>4066 - Auchenflower</postcode>
    <postcode>4215 - Southport</postcode>
    <postcode>5112 - Elizabeth Vale</postcode>
    <postcode>5037 - Kurralta Park</postcode>
    <postcode>5011 - Woodville</postcode>
    <postcode>3011 - Footscray</postcode>
    <postcode>3199 - Frankston</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
    <postcode>6001 - Perth</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Gyeonggi-do</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Seoul</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Novartis</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Study to determine the efficacy, safety and tolerability of first-line pazopanib followed by
      second-line everolimus in metastatic and advanced renal cell carcinoma</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01545817</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>