<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2234">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/01/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/01/2009</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00829153</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>U Clip Study - Study to Compare U Clip Anastomosis With Conventional Continuous Prolene Anastomosis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Pilot, Randomised, Blinded Study to Compare U Clip Anastomosis With Conventional Continuous Prolene Anastomosis for Creating of Autologous Arteriovenous Fistulae</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>H8974</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Haemodialysis</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - U Clip
Treatment: surgery - Conventional prolene anastomosis

Experimental: U clip - Anastomosis with U clips

Active Comparator: 2 - Prolene anastomosis


Treatment: devices: U Clip
Interuppted nitional clips

Treatment: surgery: Conventional prolene anastomosis
Continuous prolene anastomosis

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A functioning fistula which is used for haemodialysis on three or more occasions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Until commencement of dialysis with the fistula</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fistula patency as assessed clinically.</outcome>
      <timepoint>For the life of the fistula</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Need for fistula intervention in order to maintain patency.</outcome>
      <timepoint>For the life of the fistula</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Requirement for AV fistula creation for haemodialysis

          2. Pre operative upper limb venous and arterial duplex scan showing intended arterial
             lumen diameter of 2mm or more and vein diameter of 3mm or more.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Use of prosthetic graft for fistula creation.

          2. Donor arterial lumen diameter less then 2mm

          3. Recipient venous diameter less than 3mm.

          4. Proximal venous thrombosis.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2>The people administering the treatment/s</masking2>
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/01/2007</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Unknown status</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>Launceston general Hospital - Launceston</hospital>
    <postcode> - Launceston</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Hobart Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The requirements for haemodialysis are increasing. There is now acceptance that the most
      durable AV fistulae are those created from the patients own veins. Use of the radiocephalic
      arteriovenous fistula as an autologous vascular access dates back to the 1960's. (Brescia MJ,
      Cimino JE. Appel K, Hurwich BJ. Chronic hemodialysis using venipuncture and a surgically
      created arteriovenous fistula. N Engl J Med 1966; 275: 1089 - 1092.) Once established, it has
      good long term survival and a low complication rate. However, the success rate at creation of
      a useable AV fistula are not good. In a meta-analysis published in 2005, the primary failure
      rate of a radiocephalic fistula was 15.3% and the primary and secondary patency rates were
      62.5% and 66.0% at one year. (Rooijens PPGM, Tordoir JHM, Stijnen T, Burgmans JPJ, Smet AAEA
      and Yo TI. Radiocephalic wrist arteriovenous fistula for hemodialysis: meta-analysis
      indicates a high primary failure rate. Eur J Vasc Endovasc Surg 2004; 28, 583-589). Reasons
      for this are multiple but it appears as though the main determinants are the quality of the
      patients veins and the technical skill of the surgeon. Low patency rates are also seen in
      females and those with small veins and arteries. Creating an anastomosis between a small vein
      and artery is technically challenging. This is traditionally preformed with a continuous
      prolene suture. Recently, Medtronic have been marketing the U Clip Anastomotic Device. This
      is a self closing devise which could be called a vascular clip. Reported advantages of this
      clip include better patency rates and faster operations. However, to our knowledge there is
      no randomised evidence to support this with regards to AV fistulas.

      The vascular anastomosis originally developed by Alexis Carrel used interrupted sutures. Over
      time this was replaced by a continuous suture technique which was felt to be quicker and had
      similar patency rates. However, microvascular, paediatric and neurovascular surgeons have
      shown that there are advantages to an interrupted technique. (Hattori H, Killen DA, Green JW.
      Influence of suture material and technic on patency of anastomosed arteries of less than
      1.5mm. Am Surg. 1970; 36: 352 - 354. Cobbett JR. Microvascular surgery. Surg Clin N Am. 1962;
      47: 521.). The reasons for the improved patency with interrupted anastomoses are firstly
      increased anastomotic compliance and flow rate and secondly elimination of the pursestring
      effect and puckering seen with continuous sutures.

      In a prospective but non randomised study to compare interrupted U clips with historical
      published results, the patency rate of coronary anastomoses was 100% at 6 months using the U
      clips compare to a patency rate of 90 -100% in the published series. (Wolf RK, Alderman EL,
      Caskey MP et al. Clinical and six month angiographic evaluation of coronary arterial graft
      interrupted anastomoses by use of a self closing clip device: a multicentre prospective
      clinical trial. J Thorac cardiovasc Surg 2003; 126(1): 168 - 178.)

      Reports from single centres have concluded that the U Clips offer the opportunity to create
      superior interrupted anastomoses for AV fistula, even in patients who would otherwise be
      considered poor candidates for fistula creation. (Ross JR. Creation of native arteriovenous
      fistulas with interrupted anastomoses using a self closing clip device - one clinics
      experience. Journal of vascular Access 2002; 3: 140 - 146). In this report with small
      numbers, the radiocephalic fistulas had an 8 week maturation rate of 93%. Of the 28 patients
      having a radiocephalic fistula, 10 had veins of between 1.0 - 1,5mm diameter.

      The aim of this pilot study will be to assess if there is a clinical difference in the
      maturation rates of autologous AV fistulae when a clipped anastomosis is compared to a
      conventional prolene anastomosis.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00829153</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Stuart R walker, MBBS</name>
      <address />
      <phone>03 6227064</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>stuart.walker@dhhs.tas.gov.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>