<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4364">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/11/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/11/2012</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01744808</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerance, and Pharmacokinetic and Pharmacodynamic Profile Of 1 SR Formulation of EB-1020</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 1 Study To Investigate the Pharmacokinetics of SR Formulations; and the Food Effect, Safety, Tolerance, Pharmacokinetic and Pharmacodynamic Profile Of 1 SR Formulation of EB-1020 In Young Healthy Subjects</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>EB-1020-102</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Normal, Healthy Volunteers</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - EB-1020 IR
Treatment: drugs - EB-1020 SR1
Treatment: drugs - EB-1020 SR2
Treatment: drugs - EB-1020 SR3
Other interventions - Placebo

Active Comparator: EB-1020 SR1 - Sustained release formulation

Active Comparator: EB-1020 SR2 - Sustained Release Formulation

Active Comparator: EB-1020 SR3 - Sustained Release Formulation

Active Comparator: EB-1020 IR - Immediate Release Formulation

Placebo Comparator: Placebo - Placebo Formulation


Treatment: drugs: EB-1020 IR
Immediate release

Treatment: drugs: EB-1020 SR1
sustained release

Treatment: drugs: EB-1020 SR2
Sustained release

Treatment: drugs: EB-1020 SR3
Sustained release

Other interventions: Placebo
Placebo formulation

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cmax - Pharmacokinetic parameters</outcome>
      <timepoint>up to 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tmax - Pharmacokinetic parameter</outcome>
      <timepoint>up to 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>AUC - Pharmacokinetic parameter</outcome>
      <timepoint>up to 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Effect of food on Cmax</outcome>
      <timepoint>up to 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Aged 18-45 years inclusive

          2. Body weight with the normal range for height (body mass index [BMI] between 19-30
             kg/m2 inclusive)

          3. If female, be of non-child bearing potential (surgically sterile, post-menopausal for
             12 months or receiving a stable dose of implanted or injectable contraceptive for at
             least 3 months with last dose of injectable contraceptive within 2 months).
             Non-surgical menopause history must be confirmed by follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH)
             and luteinizing hormone (LH) levels as defined by established lab ranges.

          4. Be in general good health without clinically significant medical history

          5. Have clinical laboratory test results that are within the laboratory reference range;
             or if out of range are not clinically relevant and are acceptable to the Investigator
             and Sponsor medical representative

          6. Negative Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV), Hepatitis B and Hepatitis Screening test

          7. Able and willing to give written informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Receipt of any investigational agent or drug within 3 months of entry into the study

          2. Use of prescription drugs within 4 weeks prior to first dosing. Subjects who have used
             over the counter medication excluding paracetamol, topical over the counter
             medications and routine vitamins but including megadose (intake of 20 to 600 times the
             recommended daily dose) vitamin therapy within 7 days of first dosing, unless agreed
             as non-clinically relevant by the Principal Investigator and Sponsor

          3. A history of, or current evidence for, suicidal ideation, based upon clinical
             interview and a psychiatric questionnaire

          4. A history of known or suspected seizures, spasms, infantile spasms, febrile
             convulsions, unexplained significant and recent loss of consciousness or history of
             significant head trauma with loss of consciousness or a family history (first degree
             relative) of epilepsy or seizures (fits)

          5. A history of sleep problems in the last 3 months

          6. A history of relevant atopy or drug hypersensitivity

          7. A history (within the last 5 years) or evidence of alcohol or drug abuse. Subject who
             consume more than 14 units (female) or 21 (male) units of alcohol a week (unit = 1
             glass (125 mL) of wine = 1 measure of spirits = ½ pint of beer) will also be
             ineligible

          8. A positive urine test for drugs of abuse or alcohol at Screening or on the day of
             admittance to the Study Unit

          9. A history of smoking in the last 3 months

         10. Have a significant infection (such as influenza) or known inflammatory process on
             screening or admission

         11. Have acute gastrointestinal symptoms at the time of screening or admission (e.g.
             nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, heartburn )

         12. Have previously received EB-1020

         13. Be vegetarians, vegans or have medical dietary restrictions

         14. Any major surgical procedure within one month of entry into the study

         15. Have difficulties communicating reliably with the Investigator or appear unlikely to
             co-operate with the requirements of the study in the investigator's judgment.

         16. Any other condition which in the view of the Investigator is likely to interfere with
             study or put the subject at risk.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/02/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>54</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/02/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Nucleus Network Ltd. - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Neurovance, Inc.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To investigate whether there is a food-effect with oral administration with EB-1020 as well
      as to obtain information on the safety, and tolerability of EB-1020 in a range of doses.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01744808</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>