<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3791">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/01/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/01/2013</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01781572</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Phase Ib/II Study of LEE011 in Combination With MEK162 in Patients With NRAS Mutant Melanoma</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase Ib/II, Multicenter, Open Label, Study of LEE011 in Combination With MEK162 in Adult Patients With NRAS Mutant Melanoma</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>CMEK162X2114</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Locally Advanced or Metastatic NRAS Mutant Melanoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Malignant melanoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - LEE011 and MEK162
Treatment: drugs - LEE011 and MEK162
Treatment: drugs - LEE011 and MEK162
Treatment: drugs - LEE011 and MEK162

Experimental: Phase Ib - The phase Ib is the dose escalation part where successive cohorts of 3-6 newly enrolled patients receiving various dose pairs considering the recommendation from an adaptive BLRM incorporating the EWOC principle until MTD(s)/RP2D is defined. Patients with either measurable or evaluable disease will be eligible. If multiple alternate dosing schedules are explored in parallel, the allocation of patients will proceed in an alternating fashion. Approximately 40 patients are expected to be treated during the phase Ib part of the study.

Experimental: Phase II - The Phase II part will begin once the MTD(s)/RP2D have been determined in the Phase Ib in order to assess antitumor activity of the LEE011and MEK162 combination. Data from enrolled patients will also be used to better characterize the safety, tolerability and PK profile of the two agents. Patients enrolled in the Phase II part of the study are required to have measurable disease. Approximately 40 patients will be treated in this part.


Treatment: drugs: LEE011 and MEK162
MEK162 will be administered orally twice daily on a continuous dosing schedule. LEE011 will be administered orally once daily for 21 days followed by a 1 week break (28-day cycle).

Treatment: drugs: LEE011 and MEK162
Once the MTD(s)/RP2D have been determined for each tested dose schedule, the phase II part will begin at the RP2D on the chosen schedule in order to assess antitumor activity of the LEE011 and MEK162 combination.

Treatment: drugs: LEE011 and MEK162
MEK162 will be administered orally twice daily and LEE011 will be administered orally once daily for 3 weeks followed by a 1 week break (28-day cycle).

Treatment: drugs: LEE011 and MEK162
MEK162 will be administered orally twice daily and LEE011 will be administered once daily for 2 weeks followed by a 1 week break (21-day cycle).

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of dose limiting toxicities (Phase Ib) - To estimate the maximum tolerate doses (MTDs) and/or identify the RP2D and schedule of LEE011 and MEK162 combination.</outcome>
      <timepoint>first 28 days of treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Objective response rate (ORR) (phase II) - ORR is the proportion of patients with best overall response of complete response (CR) or partial response (PR) by month 2 assessed according to RECIST 1.1 criteria. ORR is done to describe the anti-tumor activity of LEE011 and MEK162 combination.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, every 2-4 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma concentration-time profile (AUCtau) of LEE011 and MEK162 (phase Ib) - To Characterize the PK profiles of LEE011 and MEK162 as well as any other significant metabolites identified (Phase Ib).</outcome>
      <timepoint>up to 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma concentration-time profile (AUCtau,ss) of LEE011 and MEK162 (phase Ib) - To Characterize the PK profiles of LEE011 and MEK162 as well as any other significant metabolites identified (Phase Ib).</outcome>
      <timepoint>up to 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma concentration-time profile (Cmin,ss) of LEE011 and MEK162 (phase Ib) - To Characterize the PK profiles of LEE011 and MEK162 as well as any other significant metabolites identified (Phase Ib).</outcome>
      <timepoint>up to 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma concentration-time profiles of LEE011 and MEK162 (phase Ib) - Evaluation of PK parameters, including but not limited to AUCtau, AUCtau,ss, Cmin,ss, Cmax, Cmax,ss ,Tmax, Tmax,ss, accumulation ratio (Racc), and T1/2,acc, CL/F in cycle 1-6. (Phase Ib).</outcome>
      <timepoint>up to 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma concentration-time profile (Cmax) of LEE011 and MEK162 (phase Ib) - To Characterize the PK profiles of LEE011 and MEK162 as well as any other significant metabolites identified (Phase Ib).</outcome>
      <timepoint>up to 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma concentration-time profile (Cmax,ss) of LEE011 and MEK162 (phase Ib) - To Characterize the PK profiles of LEE011 and MEK162 as well as any other significant metabolites identified (Phase Ib).</outcome>
      <timepoint>up to 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma concentration-time profile (Tmax) of LEE011 and MEK162 (phase Ib) - To Characterize the PK profiles of LEE011 and MEK162 as well as any other significant metabolites identified (Phase Ib).</outcome>
      <timepoint>up to 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma concentration-time profile (Tmax,ss) of LEE011 and MEK162 (phase Ib) - To Characterize the PK profiles of LEE011 and MEK162 as well as any other significant metabolites identified (Phase Ib).</outcome>
      <timepoint>up to 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma concentration-time profile (accumulation ration, Racc) of LEE011 and MEK162 (phase Ib) - To Characterize the PK profiles of LEE011 and MEK162 as well as any other significant metabolites identified (Phase Ib).</outcome>
      <timepoint>up to 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma concentration-time profile (T1/2, acc) of LEE011 and MEK162 (phase Ib) - To Characterize the PK profiles of LEE011 and MEK162 as well as any other significant metabolites identified (Phase Ib).</outcome>
      <timepoint>up to 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma concentration-time profile (CL/F) of LEE011 and MEK162 (phase Ib) - To Characterize the PK profiles of LEE011 and MEK162 as well as any other significant metabolites identified (Phase Ib).</outcome>
      <timepoint>up to 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of adverse drug reactions - Safety and tolerability will be characterized through the incidence and severity of adverse drug reactions, serious adverse drug reactions, changes in hematology and chemistry values, vital signs, electrocardiograms (ECGs), dose interruptions, dose reduction and dose intensity.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Approximately 12 months after FPFV</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of Response (DoR) - Phase ll - To assess clinical safety as per RECIST 1.1. Evaluation will occur continuously throughout the trial until progression, or death due to underlying cancer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Approximately 12 months after the FPFV</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Progression (TTP) - Phase ll - To assess clinical safety as per RECIST 1.1. Evaluation will occur continuously throughout the trial until progression, or death due to underlying cancer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Approximately 12 months after the FPFV</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression Free Survival (PFS) - Phase ll - To assess clinical safety as per RECIST 1.1. Evaluation will occur continuously throughout the trial until progression, or death due to underlying cancer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Approximately 12 months after the FPFV</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Survival (OS) - Phase ll - To assess clinical safety as per RECIST 1.1. Evaluation will occur continuously throughout the trial until progression, or death due to underlying cancer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Approximately 12 months after the FPFV</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Best Overall Response (BOR) - Phase ll - To assess clinical safety according to RECIST 1.1. Evaluation will occur continuously throughout the trial until progression, or death due to underlying cancer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Approximately 12 months after the FPFV</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Patients must have an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of
             0 - 1.

          -  Patients enrolled into phase Ib may be enrolled with evaluable disease only. Patients
             enrolled into the phase II expansion must have at least one measurable lesion as
             defined by RECIST 1.1 criteria for solid tumors.

          -  Patients must have adequate organ function, as defined by the following parameter

               1. Absolute Neutrophil Count (ANC) = 1.5 x 109/L.

               2. Hemoglobin (Hgb) = 9 g/dL.

               3. Platelets = 75 x 109/L without transfusions within 21 days before 1st treatment.

               4. PT/INR and aPTT = 1.5 ULN.

               5. Serum creatinine =1.5 ULN.

               6. Serum total bilirubin = 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN).

               7. AST and ALT = 3 x ULN, except in patients with tumor involvement of the liver who
                  must have AST and ALT = 5 x ULN.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Presence of any brain metastases detected by MRI or CT with i.v. contrast of the brain
             at screening.

          -  Uncontrolled arterial hypertension despite medical treatment

          -  Impaired cardiac function or clinically significant cardiac diseases, including any of
             the following:

               1. Left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) &lt; 50% as determined by multiple gated
                  acquisition scan (MUGA) or echocardiogram (ECHO).

               2. Congenital long QT syndrome or family history of unexpected sudden cardiac death.

               3. QTcF corrected with Frederica's or Bazett's formula QTcB &gt;450 ms for males and
                  &gt;470 ms for females on screening ECG.

               4. Angina pectoris = 3 months prior to starting study drug

               5. Acute myocardial infarction = 3 months prior to starting study drug

               6. Clinically significant resting bradycardia

               7. History or presence of ventricular tachyarrhythmia

               8. Unstable atrial fibrillation (ventricular response &gt;100 bpm)

               9. Complete left bundle branch block

              10. Right bundle branch block and left anterior hemi block (bifascicular block)

              11. Obligate use of a cardiac pacemaker or implantable cardioverter defibrillator

              12. Any other clinically significant heart disease

          -  Patients who are currently receiving treatment with agents that are known to cause QTc
             prolongation in humans.

          -  Patients who have neuromuscular disorders that are associated with elevated CK (e.g.,
             inflammatory myopathies, muscular dystrophy, amyotrophic lateral sclerosis, spinal
             muscular atrophy) or elevated baseline CK levels (= Grade 2)

          -  Patients who are currently receiving treatment with agents that are metabolized
             predominantly through CYP3A4 and that have a narrow therapeutic window.

          -  Patients with concurrent severe and/or uncontrolled concurrent medical conditions that
             could compromise participation in the study (i.e. uncontrolled diabetes mellitus,
             clinically significant pulmonary disease, clinically significant neurological
             disorder, active or uncontrolled infection).

          -  History or current evidence of retinal vein occlusion (RVO) or current risk factors
             for RVO (e.g. uncontrolled glaucoma or ocular hypertension, history of hyperviscosity
             or hypercoagulability syndromes).

        Other protocol related inclusion/exclusion criteria may apply.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/06/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/11/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Array BioPharma Investigative Site 1003 - North Sydney</hospital>
    <hospital>Array BioPharma Investigative Site 1002 - Westmead</hospital>
    <hospital>Array BioPharma Investigator Site 1001 - East Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>2060 - North Sydney</postcode>
    <postcode>2145 - Westmead</postcode>
    <postcode> - East Melbourne</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Michigan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Tennessee</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Essen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Gera</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Hannover</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Muenchen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Napoli</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>the Netherlands</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Nijmegen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Array BioPharma</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In the phase Ib, the primary purpose is to establish the maximum tolerated dose
      (MTD)(s)/recommended phase ll dose (RP2D) and schedule of LEE011 and MEK162 orally
      administered combination. Once the MTD(s)/RP2D have been determined for each tested schedule,
      additional patients will be enrolled in the phase II portion of the study at the RP2D on the
      chosen schedule in order to assess the anti-tumor activity of the combination in addition to
      continued evaluation of safety.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01781572</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Clinical Trial Call Center</name>
      <address>Array BioPharma, Inc.</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>