<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6529">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/05/2017</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT03158688</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Study of Carfilzomib, Daratumumab and Dexamethasone for Patients With Relapsed and/or Refractory Multiple Myeloma.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomized, Open-label, Phase 3 Study Comparing Carfilzomib, Dexamethasone, and Daratumumab to Carfilzomib and Dexamethasone for the Treatment of Patients With Relapsed or Refractory Multiple Myeloma CANDOR Study of Carfilzomib ANd Daratumumab fOr Relapsed Myeloma</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>CANDOR</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>2016-003554-33</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>20160275</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Relapsed or Refractory Multiple Myeloma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cancer types</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Dexamethasone
Treatment: drugs - Daratumumab
Treatment: drugs - Carfilzomib

Active Comparator: Arm 2 - Carfilzomib and Dexamethasone - Carfilzomib will be dosed twice weekly as an intravenous (IV) infusion and Dexamethasone will be taken orally or by IV infusion weekly. The IV administration of dexamethasone must be given on carfilzomib IV infusion days. The required order of administrationon Arm 2 is as follows: dexamethasone then carfilzomib.
For days when dexamethasone is given in the absence of carfilzomib IV infusion, it may be given orally (PO).

Active Comparator: Arm 1 - Carfilzomib, Dexamethasone and Daratumumab - Carfilzomib will be dosed twice weekly as an intravenous (IV) infusion. Daratumumab will be administered as an IV infusion - on days 1 and 2 of cycle 1 at 8 mg/kg dose each day; then at 16 mg/kg dose once weekly as a single infusion for the remaining doses of the first 2 cycles; then every 2 weeks for 4 cycles (cycles 3 to 6), and then every 4 weeks for the remaining cycles or until disease progression. Dexamethasone 40 mg will be taken orally or by IV infusion weekly. The IV administration of dexamethasone must be given on carfilzomib and/or daratumumab IV infusion days. On days when more than 1 investigational product is administered, the required order of administration is as follows: dexamethasone, pre-infusion medications for daratumumab, carfilzomib, daratumumab, and post-infusion medications for daratumumab.


Treatment: drugs: Dexamethasone
Dexamethasone 40 mg will be taken orally or by IV infusion weekly. The IV administration of dexamethasone must be given on carfilzomib and/or daratumumab IV infusion days. Dexamethasone IV will be given on successive days at a split dose of 20 mg each treatment day on weeks with carfilzomib and/or daratumumab infusions. All subjects regardless of age will be required to receive 20 mg of dexamethasone on days 1 and 2 of cycle 1 (as a preinfusion medication for daratumumab infusion) followed by 20 mg of methylprednisolone or equivalent on the third day.

Treatment: drugs: Daratumumab
Daratumumab will be administered as an IV infusion. On days 1 and 2 of cycle 1, daratumumab will be administered at a split-dose of 8 mg/kg in 500 mL normal saline. The dose of 16 mg/kg in 500 mL normal saline will be given once weekly as a single infusion for the remaining doses of the first 2 cycles (ie, days 8, 15, and 22 of cycle 1; and days 1, 8, 15, and 22 of cycle 2), then every 2 weeks for 4 cycles (cycles 3 to 6), and then every 4 weeks for the remaining cycles or until disease progression. The administration may be within ± 2 days for each scheduled dose.

Treatment: drugs: Carfilzomib
Carfilzomib will be administered as an intravenous (IV) infusion. On days when more than 1 investigational product is administered, the required order of administration is as follows: dexamethasone, pre-infusion medications for daratumumab, carfilzomib, daratumumab, and post infusion medications for daratumumab.
Carfilzomib will be dosed twice weekly over 30 ± 5 minutes, on days 1, 2, 8, 9, 15, and 16 of each 28-day cycle. The administration may be within ± 2 days for each scheduled dose. The dose will be 20 mg/m2 on cycle 1 days 1 and 2 and 56 mg/m2 beginning on cycle 1 day 8 and thereafter.
Each subject's first dose of carfilzomib will be calculated based upon baseline body surface area (BSA). Dose should be capped based on a BSA of 2.2 m2.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression Free Survival (PFS) - Compare carfilzomib, dexamethasone, and daratumumab (KdD) to carfilzomib and dexamethasone (Kd) in terms of progression free survival (PFS) in patients with multiple myeloma who have relapsed after 1 to 3 prior therapies.</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Response Rate (ORR) - Overall Response Rate (ORR; defined as the proportion of best overall response of stringent complete response [sCR], complete response [CR], very good partial response [VGPR], and partial response [PR]).</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 Months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of minimal residual disease negative-complete response - Rate of minimal residual disease negative-complete response (MRD[-]CR) in bone marrow aspirates at 12 months (± 4 weeks) as determined by Next-Generation sequencing (NGS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 Months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of response (DOR)</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 Months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall survival (OS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 Months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to next treatment</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 Months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>time to progression (TTP)</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 Months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to response</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 Months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Persistence of MRD[-]CR</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 Months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Complete response rate (CRR)</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 Months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>MRD[-] rate - MRD[-]CR rate, MRD[-]CR defined as achievement of CR by IRC per International Myeloma Working Group-Uniform Response Criteria (IMWG-URC) and MRD[-] status as assessed by NGS (at a 10-5 level, pending analytical validation) at 12 months</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 Months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life questionnaire - core 30 items - Quality of life questionnaire - core 30 items (QLQ-C30).</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 Months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life (QoL) measured by European Organization - Quality of Life (QoL) measured by European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) QLQ-C30 version 3 questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 Months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subject incidence of treatment-emergent adverse events</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 Months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Criteria 1 Relapsed or progressive multiple myeloma after last treatment

          -  Criteria 2 Males or females = 18 years of age

          -  Criteria 3 Measurable disease with at least 1 of the following assessed within 21 days
             prior to randomization:

               -  IgG multiple myeloma: serum monoclonal paraprotein (M-protein) level

                    -  1.0 g/dL,

               -  IgA, IgD, IgE multiple myeloma: serum M-protein level = 0.5 g/dL,

               -  urine M-protein = 200 mg/24 hours,

               -  in subjects without detectable serum or urine M- protein, serum free light chain
                  (SFLC) = 100 mg/L (involved light chain) and an abnormal serum kappa lambda ratio

          -  Criteria 4 Received at least 1 but not more than 3 prior lines of therapy for multiple
             myeloma (induction therapy followed by stem cell transplant and
             consolidation/maintenance therapy will be considered as 1 line of therapy, see
             Appendix E for guidance)

          -  Criteria 5 Prior therapy with carfilzomib is allowed as long as the patient had at
             least a PR to most recent therapy with carfilzomib, was not removed due to toxicity,
             did not relapse within 60 days from discontinuation of carfilzomib, and will have at
             least a 6-month carfilzomib treatment-free interval from last dose received until
             first study treatment. (Patients may receive maintenance therapy with drugs that are
             not proteasome inhibitors or CD38 antibodies during this 6-month carfilzomib treatment
             free interval)

          -  Criteria 6 Prior therapy with anti-CD38 antibodies is allowed as long as the patient
             had at least a PR to most recent therapy with CD38 antibody, was not removed due to
             toxicity, did not relapse within 60 days from intensive treatment (at least every
             other week) of CD38 antibody therapy, and will have at least a 6 month CD38 antibody
             treatment-free interval from last dose received until first study treatment

          -  Other inclusion criteria may apply</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Criteria 1 Waldenström macroglobulinemia

          -  Criteria 2 Multiple myeloma of IgM subtype

          -  Criteria 3 POEMS syndrome (polyneuropathy, organomegaly, endocrinopathy, monoclonal
             protein, and skin changes)

          -  Criteria 4 Plasma cell leukemia (&gt; 2.0 x 109/L circulating plasma cells by standard
             differential)

          -  Criteria 5 Myelodysplastic syndrome

          -  Criteria 6 Known moderate or severe persistent asthma within the past 2 years

          -  Criteria 7 Known chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) with a FEV1 &lt; 50% of
             predicted normal

          -  Criteria 8 Active congestive heart failure (New York Heart Association [NYHA] Class
             III to IV), symptomatic ischemia, uncontrolled arrhythmias, clinically significant
             electrocardiogram (ECG) abnormalities, screening ECG with corrected QT interval (QTc)
             of &gt; 470 msec, pericardial disease, or myocardial infarction within 4 months prior to
             randomization

          -  Other exclusion criteria may apply</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>13/06/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>450</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>17/06/2022</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,SA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Research Site - Westmead</hospital>
    <hospital>Research Site - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>Research Site - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <hospital>Research Site - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>Research Site - East Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Research Site - Fitzroy, VIC</hospital>
    <hospital>Research Site - Geelong</hospital>
    <hospital>Research Site - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>2145 - Westmead</postcode>
    <postcode>4029 - Herston</postcode>
    <postcode>4102 - Woolloongabba</postcode>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>3002 - East Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3065 - Fitzroy, VIC</postcode>
    <postcode>3220 - Geelong</postcode>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Georgia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Illinois</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Indiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Mississippi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>South Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Antwerpen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Brussel</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Charleroi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Gent</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Leuven</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Alberta</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Athens</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Seoul</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Lublin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Nizhny Novgorod</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Petrozavodsk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Saratov</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Changhua</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>Ankara</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>Izmir</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>Samsun</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Manchester</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Amgen</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Compare carfizomib, dexamethasone, and daratumumab (KdD) to Carfilzomib and dexamethasone
      (Kd) in terms of progression free survival (PFS) in patients with multiple myeloma who have
      relapsed after 1 to 3 prior therapies.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03158688</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>MD</name>
      <address>Amgen</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Amgen Call Center</name>
      <address />
      <phone>866-572-6436</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>medinfo@amgen.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>