<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="1966">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/05/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/05/2008</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00678392</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Axitinib (AG 013736) As Second Line Therapy For Metastatic Renal Cell Cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Axitinib (Ag-013736) As Second Line Therapy For Metastatic Renal Cell Cancer: Axis Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>AXIS TRIAL</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>A4061032</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Kidney Neoplasms</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Axitinib (AG-013736)
Treatment: drugs - Sorafenib

Experimental: Axitinib - 

Active Comparator: Sorafenib - 


Treatment: drugs: Axitinib (AG-013736)
axitinib will be given at a starting dose of 5 mg twice daily [BID] with continuous dosing

Treatment: drugs: Sorafenib
sorafenib will be given at a dose of 400 mg twice daily [BID] with continuous dosing

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression-Free Survival (PFS) - PFS was defined as the time in months from start of study treatment to the first documentation of objective tumor progression of disease (PD) or to death due to any cause, whichever occurs first. PD was assessed by response evaluation criteria in solid tumors (RECIST) version 1.0. PD: &gt;=20 percent (%) increase in the sum of the longest dimensions (LD) of the target lesions taking as a reference the smallest sum of the LD recorded since the start of treatment or unequivocal progression in non-target lesions or the appearance of 1 or more new lesions. Occurrence of a pleural effusion or ascites was also considered PD if demonstrated by cytological investigation and it was not previously documented. New bone lesions not previously documented were considered PD if confirmed by computed tomography/magnetic resonance imaging or X-ray.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From initiation of treatment up to follow-up period (up to 3 years)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Survival (OS) - OS was defined as the duration from start of study treatment to date of death due to any cause. OS was calculated as (months) = (date of death minus the date of first dose of study medication plus 1) divided by 30.4. For participants who were alive, overall survival was censored on last date the participants were known to be alive.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From initiation of treatment up to follow-up period (up to 3 years)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Objective Response Rate (ORR) - ORR = percentage of participants with confirmed complete response (CR) or confirmed partial response (PR) according to RECIST version 1.0 recorded from first dose of study treatment until PD or death due to any cause. CR: disappearance of all target, non target lesions and no appearance of new lesions, documented on 2 occasions separated by at least 4 weeks. PR: at least 30 % decrease in sum of LD of target lesions taking as reference baseline sum of LD, without progression of non target lesions, no appearance of new lesions. PD: &gt;=20% increase in sum of LD of the target lesions taking as a reference smallest sum of LD recorded since the start of treatment or unequivocal progression in non-target lesions or appearance of 1 or more new lesions. Occurrence of pleural effusion or ascites if demonstrated by cytological investigation, not previously documented. New bone lesions not previously documented if confirmed by computed tomography/magnetic resonance imaging or X-ray.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From initiation of treatment up to follow-up period (up to 3 years)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of Response (DR) - DR: time from first documentation of objective tumor response (CR or PR), that was subsequently confirmed, to the first documentation of PD or to death due to any cause, whichever occurred first as per RECIST version 1.0, a) CR: disappearance of all target, non target lesions and no appearance of new lesions, documented on 2 occasions separated by at least 4 weeks, b) PR: at least 30 % decrease in sum of LD of target lesions taking as reference baseline sum of LD, without progression of non target lesions, no appearance of new lesions, c) PD: &gt;=20% increase in sum of LD of the target lesions taking as a reference smallest sum of LD recorded since the start of treatment or unequivocal progression in non-target lesions or appearance of 1 or more new lesions. Occurrence of pleural effusion or ascites if demonstrated by cytological investigation, not previously documented. New bone lesions not previously documented if confirmed by computed tomography/magnetic resonance imaging or X-ray.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From initiation of treatment up to follow-up period (up to 3 years)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants With Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events (AEs) and Serious Adverse Events (SAEs) - An AE was any untoward medical occurrence in a participant who received study drug without regard to possibility of causal relationship. SAE was an AE resulting in any of the following outcomes or deemed significant for any other reason: death; initial or prolonged inpatient hospitalization; life- threatening experience (immediate risk of dying); persistent or significant disability/incapacity; congenital anomaly. A treatment emergent AE was defined as an event that emerged during the treatment period that was absent before treatment, or worsened during the treatment period relative to the pretreatment state. AEs included both serious and non-serious AEs.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From initiation of treatment up to follow-up period (up to 3 years)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants With Adverse Events (AEs) by Severity - An AE was any untoward medical occurrence in a participant who received study drug without regard to possibility of causal relationship. Severity of the AEs was graded according to the National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 3.0. Grade 1= mild; Grade 2= moderate; Grade 3= severe; Grade 4= life-threatening or disabling; Grade 5= death related to AE.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From initiation of treatment up to follow-up period (up to 3 years)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants With Treatment-Related Adverse Events (AEs) and Serious Adverse Events (SAEs) - An AE was any untoward medical occurrence attributed to study drug in a participant who received study drug. SAE was an AE resulting in any of the following outcomes or deemed significant for any other reason: death; initial or prolonged inpatient hospitalization; life -threatening experience (immediate risk of dying); persistent or significant disability/incapacity; congenital anomaly. AEs included both serious and non -serious AEs.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From initiation of treatment up to follow-up period (up to 3 years)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With Clinically Significant Laboratory Abnormalities: Hematology - Hematology laboratory test included hemoglobin, platelet count, white blood cells count, neutrophils and lymphocytes. Abnormalities were assessed by CTCAE Grade Version 2 for severity: Grade 1= mild; Grade 2= moderate; Grade 3= severe and Grade 4= life-threatening or disabling.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From initiation of treatment up to follow-up period (up to 3 years)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With Clinically Significant Laboratory Abnormalities: Biochemistry - Biochemistry laboratory test included parameters: alanine aminotransferase, alkaline phosphatase, amylase, aspartate aminotransferase, bicarbonate, bilirubin, creatinine, hypercalcemia, hyperglycemia, hyperkalemia, hypernatremia, hypoalbuminemia, hypocalcemia, hypoglycemia, hypokalemia, hyponatremia, hypophosphatemia and lipase. Abnormalities were assessed by CTCAE Grade Version 2 for severity: Grade 1= mild; Grade 2= moderate; Grade 3= severe and Grade 4= life-threatening or disabling.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From initiation of treatment up to follow-up period (up to 3 years)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With Clinically Significant Laboratory Abnormalities: Urinalysis - Urinalysis included urine blood/ hemoglobin, glucose and protein. Abnormalities were assessed by CTCAE Grade Version 2 for severity: Grade 1= mild; Grade 2= moderate; Grade 3= severe and Grade 4= life-threatening or disabling.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From initiation of treatment up to follow-up period (up to 3 years)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy Kidney Symptom Index-15 (FKSI-15) Score - FKSI was used to assess quality of life (QoL) for those diagnosed with renal cell cancer and consisted of 15 items (lack of energy, side effects, pain, losing weight, bone pain, fatigue, enjoying life, short of breath, worsened condition, appetite, coughing, bothered by fevers, ability to work, hematuria and sleep). Each of the 15 items was answered on a 5-point Likert-type scale ranging from 0 to 4 (0= not at all, 1= a little bit, 2= somewhat, 3= quite a bit, 4= very much). Total FKSI score = sum of the 15 item scores; total range: 0 - 60; 0 (no symptoms) to 60 (very much); higher scores indicate greater presence of symptoms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Predose on Cycle 1 Day 1) , Day 1 of each cycle until Cycle 21, End of treatment (Day 670) and Follow-up visit (Day 698)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy Kidney Symptom Index-Disease Related Symptoms (FKSI-DRS) Score - FKSI-DRS was used to assess quality of life for those diagnosed with renal cell cancer and consisted of 9 items (lack of energy, pain, losing weight, bone pain, fatigue, short of breath, coughing, bothered by fevers, and hematuria). Each of the 9 items was answered on a 5-point Likert-type scale ranging from 0 to 4 (0= not at all, 1= a little bit, 2= somewhat, 3= quite a bit, 4= very much). Total FKSI-DRS score = sum of the 9 item scores; total range: 0 - 36; 0 (no symptoms) to 36 (very much); higher scores indicate greater presence of symptoms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Predose on Cycle 1 Day 1) , Day 1 of each cycle until Cycle 21, End of treatment (Day 670) and Follow-up visit (Day 698)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Euro Quality of Life Questionnaire- 5 Dimension (EQ-5D): Health State Profile Utility Score - EQ-5D: participant rated questionnaire to assess health-related quality of life in terms of a single utility or index score. Health state profile component assesses level of health for 5 domains: mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort, and anxiety/depression. Each domain was rated on a 3-point response scale (1= no problems, 2= some/moderate problems and 3= extreme problems). Scoring formula developed by EuroQol Group assigned a utility value for each domain in the profile. Score were transformed and resulted in a total score range of 0 to 1, with higher scores indicating better health.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Predose on Cycle 1 Day 1) , Day 1 of each cycle until Cycle 21, End of treatment (Day 670) and Follow-up visit (Day 698)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Euro Quality of Life Questionnaire- 5 Dimension (EQ-5D): Visual Analog Scale (VAS) - EQ-5D: participant rated questionnaire to assess health-related quality of life in terms of a single index value. VAS component: participants rated their current health state on a scale from 0 (worst imaginable health state) to 100 (best imaginable health state); higher scores indicate a better health.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Predose on Cycle 1 Day 1) , Day 1 of each cycle until Cycle 21, End of treatment (Day 670) and Follow-up visit (Day 698)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Histologically or cytologically confirmed renal cell cancer with a component of clear
             cell subtype, with metastasis

          -  Evidence of measurable disease

          -  Must have failed one prior systemic first-line regimen for metastatic renal cell
             cancer</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Prior treatment for metastatic renal cell cancer with more that one systemic first
             line therapy

          -  Major surgery less than 4 weeks or radiation less than 2 weeks of starting study drug</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/09/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>723</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/02/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,SA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Canberra Hospital, Medical Oncology - Garran</hospital>
    <hospital>Ashford Cancer Centre Research - Kurralta Park</hospital>
    <hospital>Ballarat Oncology &amp; Haematology Services - Ballarat</hospital>
    <hospital>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre - East Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Heidelberg Repatriation Hospital, Austin Health - Heidelberg West</hospital>
    <hospital>Austin Hospital, Austin Health - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <postcode>2605 - Garran</postcode>
    <postcode>5037 - Kurralta Park</postcode>
    <postcode>3350 - Ballarat</postcode>
    <postcode>3002 - East Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3081 - Heidelberg West</postcode>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Colorado</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>District of Columbia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Georgia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Idaho</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Illinois</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Indiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Massachusetts</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Michigan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Minnesota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Missouri</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Nevada</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Jersey</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Oregon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Pennsylvania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>South Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Tennessee</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Virginia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Washington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Austria</country>
      <state>Wien</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>RJ</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>RS</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>SP</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Alberta</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>British Columbia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>New Brunswick</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Newfoundland and Labrador</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Jiangsu</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Shaanxi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Beijing</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Guangzhou</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Shanghai</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Tianjin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Cedex 08</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Bordeaux Cedex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>CRETEIL Cedex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Marseille Cedex 09</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Paris Cedex 15</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Rennes</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>St Herblain Cedex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Tours Cedex 1</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Vandoeuvre les Nancy</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Villejuif Cedex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Aachen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Berlin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Essen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Hannover</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Mainz</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Muenchen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Oldenburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Attiki</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Macedonia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>India</country>
      <state>Haryana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>India</country>
      <state>Kerala</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>India</country>
      <state>Maharashtra</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>India</country>
      <state>Punjab</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>India</country>
      <state>Rajasthan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ireland</country>
      <state>Dublin 24</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Arezzo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Aviano (PN)</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Brescia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Cremona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Genova</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Milano</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Napoli</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Padova</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Pavia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Roma</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Rozzano (MI)</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Hokkaido</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Ibaraki</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Osaka</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Shizuoka</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Tokyo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Yamaguchi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Akita</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Chiba</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Fukuoka</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Kumamoto</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Tokushima</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Yamagata</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Gyeonggi-do</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Busan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Seoul</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Wielkopolska</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Gdansk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Poznan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Warszawa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Wroclaw</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Kaluga Region</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Moscow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>St. Petersburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Singapore</country>
      <state>Singapore</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Slovakia</country>
      <state>Bratislava</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Slovakia</country>
      <state>Zilina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Navarra</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Malaga</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Sevilla</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Zaragoza</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Linkoping</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Umea</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Vaxjo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Kaohsiung Hsien</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Taichung</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Taipei</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Taoyuan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>England</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Middlesex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Bebington, Wirral</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Birmingham</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Bournemouth</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Bristol</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Cambridge</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Glasgow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Oxford</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Surrey</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Pfizer</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study is designed to demonstrate that axitinib (AG-013736) is superior to sorafenib in
      delaying tumor progression in patients with metastatic renal cell cancer after failure of one
      first line regimen.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00678392</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Pfizer CT.gov Call Center</name>
      <address>Pfizer</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>