<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4581">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/08/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/08/2014</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02215447</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Feasibility Study Of NAB-Paclitaxel In Combination With Carboplatin As First Line Treatment Of Gastrointestinal Neuroendocrine Carcinomas</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Feasibility Study Of NAB-Paclitaxel In Combination With Carboplatin As First Line Treatment Of Gastrointestinal Neuroendocrine Carcinomas</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>NABNEC</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>ALCC 14.01</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Gastrointestinal Neuroendocrine Carcinomas</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Non melanoma skin cancer</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Neuroendocrine tumour (NET)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - NAB paclitaxel
Treatment: drugs - Carboplatin

Experimental: NAB-Paclitaxel with carboplatin - NAB paclitaxel (100 mg/m2 IVI) every week (d1,8,15) in three weekly cycle. Carboplatin (AUC=5 IVI) (d1) in three weekly cycle. Study treatment will continue until progressive disease, unacceptable toxicity, or ceased by patient or clinician preference.


Treatment: drugs: NAB paclitaxel
100 mg/m2 i.v. every week (d1,8,15) in three weekly cycle Number of Cycles: until progression or unacceptable toxicity develops.

Treatment: drugs: Carboplatin


</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Response rate - The objective tumour response rate (partial or complete response as defined by Response Evaluation Criteria In Solid Tumors (RECIST) criteria version 1.1) via CT until the date of first documented progression or date of death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 36 months</outcome>
      <timepoint>From date of registration until the date of first documented progression or date of death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 36 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression free survival - The rate of progression free survival (PFS). (PFS defined from time of registration to disease progression as defined by Response Evaluation Criteria In Solid Tumors (RECIST) criteria version 1.1).</outcome>
      <timepoint>From date of registration until the date of first documented progression or date of death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 36 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall survival - Overall survival (OS) (death from any cause).</outcome>
      <timepoint>From date of registration until date of death from any cause, assessed up to 36 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rates of adverse events as defined by NCI- Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) V4.0</outcome>
      <timepoint>During study drug administration until 30 days after last study drug dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Male or female with unresectable neuroendocrine carcinoma

          -  Age =18 yrs

          -  Histologically proven neuroendocrine carcinoma (NEC) as defined by the WHO
             Classification of Tumours of the Digestive System, 4th Ed - including tumours mixed
             with other malignancies (i.e. MANEC or mixed NEC/SCC). The features of small versus
             large cell NEC carcinoma will need to be documented.

          -  Tumour sufficiently Fluorodeoxyglucose (FDG)-avid (SUVmax minimum 3.5) on the initial
             staging PET

          -  Patients with advanced and/ or metastatic disease

          -  Measurable disease as assessed by CT scan of the chest, abdomen and pelvis as per
             RECIST v 1.1, within 21 days prior to commencement of study treatment

          -  ECOG performance status 0-1

          -  Adequate haematological, renal and hepatic function (neutrophils =2 × 109/L, platelets
             =100 × 109/L, hemoglobin =100g/L, total bilirubin = 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN),
             aspartate aminotransferase and alanine aminotransferase =2.5 × ULN, alkaline
             phosphatases =2.5 ULN, creatinine = 1.5 ULN)

          -  Signed, written informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  NECs confirmed not to be from gastrointestinal primaries and NETs of lower grades
             (Ki67&lt;20)

          -  Suspected pulmonary origin of the NET e.g., FDG-PET avid lung lesions in patients with
             NEC liver metastases.

          -  Known hypersensitivity to NAB paclitaxel

          -  External beam radiotherapy to solitary target lesions. Patients who have received
             local radiotherapy of non-target lesions for local symptom control within the last 4
             weeks must have recovered from any adverse effects of radiotherapy prior to starting
             treatment.

          -  Prior intrahepatic 90Ymicrospheres such as SIR-Spheres

          -  Major surgery/surgical therapy for any cause within 1 month or surgical therapy of
             loco-regional metastases within the last 3 months prior to starting treatment

          -  Severe cardiovascular, hepatic, neurologic or renal comorbid conditions

          -  Previous cytotoxic chemotherapy, or targeted therapy, or biotherapy for NEC (prior
             Somatostatin analogs (SSAs) are allowed)

          -  History of hepatitis B or C

          -  Sensory/motor neuropathy = to grade 2, as defined by NCI CTCAE 4.0

          -  Pregnancy, lactation, or inadequate contraception. Women must be post-menopausal,
             infertile, or use a reliable means of contraception. Women of childbearing potential
             must have a negative pregnancy test done within 7 days prior to registration. Men must
             have been surgically sterilised or use a (double if required) barrier method of
             contraception</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/05/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>4</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/10/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal North Shore Hospital - St Leonards</hospital>
    <hospital>Barwon Health - Geelong</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>2065 - St Leonards</postcode>
    <postcode>3220 - Geelong</postcode>
    <postcode>3050 - Parkville</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Barwon Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Specialised Therapeutics Australia</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Deakin University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Australasian Gastro-Intestinal Trials Group</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Gastrointestinal Neuroendocrine Tumours (NETs) are gaining increasing recognition as a highly
      prevalent disease, responsive to a number of therapies, some of which are proven in modern
      randomised controlled trials, but many of which still require high quality clinical trial
      evidence to confirm their effectiveness and guide their use in practice. This study is the
      first prospective trial to evaluate modern combination chemotherapy. The study will determine
      whether Carboplatin and Paclitaxel NAB is a suitable combination for comparison in a
      subsequent randomised controlled phase III international trial.

      Given the paucity of randomized studies in NETs, there are no clear evidence based
      guidelines. Patients are treated according to guidelines established for small cell lung
      cancer, incorporating platinum (cisplatin or carboplatin) based doublet treatment with
      etoposide. Although these tumors are initially highly chemosensitive, the natural history of
      this disease is such that relapses occur early, which ultimately leads to a very poor
      prognosis. Almost all clinical trials investigating cytotoxic chemotherapy in NETs are small
      single arm studies and guidelines are derived from expert opinion and from extrapolating
      results from small cell lung cancer studies. Prospective clinical trials in this group of
      patients needs to be conducted to establish an evidence based standard of care and to improve
      the prognosis of this highly aggressive group of tumors.

      Participants will receive albumin bound paclitaxel (ABRAXANE®) 100 mg/m2 administered as an
      intravenous infusion over 30 minutes on Days 1, 8, and 15 of each 21 day cycle. Carboplatin
      will be given at an Area Under the Curve (AUC) = 5 mg/min/mL on Day 1 only of each 21 day
      cycle administered over 30 mins, beginning immediately after the completion of albumin bound
      paclitaxel administration. Participants can continue treatment at the investigator's
      discretion until disease progression, development of an unacceptable toxicity, or withdrawal
      of consent.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02215447</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mustafa Khasraw, MD</name>
      <address>Barwon Health</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>