<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3265">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/08/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/08/2011</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01420783</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Study With SAR302503 in Patients With Polycythemia Vera or Essential Thrombocythemia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomized Phase II, Open-Label Study of the Efficacy and Safety of Orally Administered SAR302503 in Patients With Polycythemia Vera (PV) or Essential Thrombocythemia (ET) Who Are Resistant or Intolerant to Hydroxyurea</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>2011-001847-58</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>ARD12042</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hematopoietic Neoplasm</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haematological diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other blood disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Leukaemia - Acute leukaemia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Leukaemia - Chronic leukaemia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - SAR302503

Experimental: SAR302503 100 mg - once daily X 28 days

Experimental: SAR302503 200 mg - once daily X 28 days

Experimental: SAR302503 400 mg - once daily X 28 days

Experimental: SAR302503 600 mg - once daily X 28 days


Treatment: drugs: SAR302503
Pharmaceutical form:capsule
Route of administration: oral

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dose Ranging Phase: Proportion of PV patients with absence of phlebotomy and hematocrit below 45% and proportion of ET patients with a platelet count = 400 x 10x9/L for a minimum of 3 months during the first 8 cycles of therapy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PV Dose Expansion Phase: Proportion of PV patients with absence of phlebotomy eligibility beginning at Day 1 of Cycle 4 visit and continuing through Day 1 of Cycle 6 visit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>ET Dose Ranging Phase (only 600 mg dose group): Proportion of ET patients with a platelet count =400 x 10x9/L beginning at Day 1 of Cycle 4 visit and continuing through Day 1 of Cycle 6 visit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of PV patients with absence of phlebotomy eligibility beginning at Day 1 of Cycle 4 visit through Cycle 8 (for PV dose expansion phase only).</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of ET patients with platelet count =400 x 10x9/L beginning at Day 1 of Cycle 4 visit and continuing through Cycle 8.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Characterization of clinicohematologic response (CR, PR, and no Response) defined by European LeukemiaNet beginning at Day 1 of Cycle 6 visit through Cycle 8.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percent change in spleen volume (per Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI)) at the end of Cycles 4 and 8 or end of treatment (EOT) relative to baseline.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients with a = 35% reduction in spleen volume (per Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI)) at the end of Cycles 4 and 8 or end of treatment (EOT) relative to baseline.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of participants who have changes in histological, cytogenetic, and molecular responses in bone marrow.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Response (defined as either a 2-point improvement in or resolution of a symptom present at baseline) at the end of Cycles 1, 4, and 8 or end of treatment (EOT), as measured by the Myeloproliferative Neoplasm Symptom Assessment Form (MPN-SAF).</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cumulative Distribution Function of responses between treatment groups at the end of Cycles 1, 4, and 8 or EOT on the MPN-SAF.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>For each MPN-associated symptom present at baseline on the MPN-SAF, proportion of patients with resolution of that symptom at the end of Cycles 1, 4, and 8.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To measure generic health-related quality of life and utility values using the EQ-5D questionnaire after completion of 8 cycles of therapy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Characterization of the safety profile of SAR302503, including the frequency, duration, and severity of adverse events graded using the National Cancer Institute (NCI) - CTCAE version 4.03, clinical laboratory parameters, ECG, and vital signs.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria:

          -  Has had a diagnosis of hydroxyurea resistant or intolerant polycythemia vera (PV) or
             essential thrombocythemia (ET) documented at Screening.

          -  Polycythemia vera or essential thrombocythemia defined according to the revised WHO
             criteria.

          -  Polycythemia vera resistance or intolerance to hydroxyurea is defined as polycythemia
             vera patients on hydroxyurea with a hematocrit &gt;45%, or phlebotomy twice in the last 6
             months and at least once in the last 3 months.

          -  Essential thrombocythemia resistance or intolerance to hydroxurea is defined as
             essential thrombocythemia patients on HU with platelet count &gt;600 x 10x9/L.

        Dose Expansion Phase (polycythemia vera) and 600 mg/day group (essential thrombocythemia):

          -  Has had a diagnosis of polycythemia vera or essential thrombocythemia according to the
             revised WHO 2008 criteria.

          -  PV patients must be resistant or intolerant to hydroxyurea.

          -  ET patients must be resistant or intolerant to hydroxyurea.

          -  Provide written informed consent to participate.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria:

          -  Less than 18 years of age.

          -  Participation in any study of an investigational agent (drug, biologic, device) within
             30 days prior to initiation of study drug, unless during non-treatment phase. (Prior
             treatment with another JAK2 inhibitor is allowed.)

          -  Unwilling to comply with scheduled visits, treatment plans, laboratory assessments,
             and other study-related procedures.

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status (PS) of 3 or 4 at study
             entry.

          -  Splenectomy.

          -  Active malignancy other than polycythemia vera or essential thrombocythemia, except
             adequately treated basal cell carcinoma and squamous cell carcinoma of the skin,
             cervical carcinoma in situ, or other malignancies that have been stable and off
             therapy for =5 years.

          -  Major surgery within 28 days or radiation within 3 months prior to initiation of study
             drug.

          -  Active acute infection requiring antibiotics.

          -  Known human immunodeficiency virus or acquired immunodeficiency syndrome-related
             illness.

          -  Uncontrolled congestive heart failure (New York Heart Association Classification 3 or
             4), angina, myocardial infarction, cerebrovascular accident, coronary/peripheral
             artery bypass surgery, transient ischemic attack, or pulmonary embolism within 3
             months prior to initiation of study drug.

          -  Any severe acute or chronic medical, neurological, or psychiatric condition or
             laboratory abnormality that may increase the risk associated with study participation
             or study drug administration, may interfere with the informed consent process and/or
             with compliance with the requirements of the study, or may interfere with
             interpretation of study results and, in the Investigator's opinion, would make the
             patient inappropriate for entry into this study.

          -  Inadequate organ function.

          -  Known active (acute or chronic) Hepatitis A, B, or C; and Hepatitis B and C carriers.

          -  Prior history of chronic liver disease (eg, chronic alcoholic liver disease,
             autoimmune hepatitis, sclerosing cholangitis, primary biliary cirrhosis,
             hemachromatosis, non-alcoholic steatohepatitis [NASH]).

          -  Concomitant treatment with or use of drugs or herbal agents known to be at least
             moderate inhibitors or inducers cytochrome P450 3A4 (CYP3A4).

          -  Presence of any gastric or other disorder that would inhibit absorption of oral
             medication.

          -  Known hypersensitivity to any excipients in the study drug formulation.

          -  Women of childbearing potential, unless using effective contraception while on study
             drug.

          -  Men who partner with a woman of childbearing potential, unless they agree to use
             effective contraception while on study drug.

        The above information is not intended to contain all considerations relevant to a patient's
        potential participation in a clinical trial.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/10/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>81</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/05/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>Investigational Site Number 036001 - Clayton</hospital>
    <hospital>Investigational Site Number 036002 - Kingswood</hospital>
    <hospital>Investigational Site Number 036004 - Kogarah</hospital>
    <hospital>Investigational Site Number 036003 - Randwick</hospital>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
    <postcode>2747 - Kingswood</postcode>
    <postcode>2217 - Kogarah</postcode>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Arizona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Michigan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Minnesota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Missouri</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Montreal</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Toronto</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Vancouver</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Brest</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Marseille</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Paris Cedex 10</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Frankfurt Am Main</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Mannheim</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Bologna</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Firenze</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Orbassano</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Seongnam</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Seoul</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Badalona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Valencia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Belfast</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Birmingham</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Sanofi</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Primary Objective:

        -  Dose Ranging Phase: To evaluate the efficacy of daily oral doses of 100, 200, and 400 mg
           SAR302503 in patients with PV and ET who are resistant or intolerant to hydroxyurea (per
           European LeukemiaNet criteria) for :

             -  Inducing absence of phlebotomy and a hematocrit below 45% for a minimum of 3 months
                in patients with polycythemia vera, and

             -  Reduction of platelet count to =400 x 10x9/L for a minimum of 3 months in patients
                with essential thrombocythemia.

        -  PV Dose Expansion Phase and ET Dose Ranging Phase (only 600 mg dose group): To evaluate
           the efficacy of daily oral SAR302503 in patients with PV and ET who are resistant or
           intolerant to hydroxyurea (per European LeukemiaNet criteria) for:

             -  Inducing absence of phlebotomy eligibility beginning at Day 1 of Cycle 4 visit and
                continuing through Day 1 of Cycle 6 visit in patients with PV, and

             -  Reduction of platelet count to =400 x 10x9/L beginning at Day 1 of Cycle 4 visit
                and continuing through Day 1 of Cycle 6 visit in patients with ET.

      Secondary Objectives:

        -  To evaluate the safety of SAR302503.

        -  To evaluate the efficacy of SAR302503 in patients with PV who are resistant or
           intolerant to hydroxyurea for inducing absence of phlebotomy eligibility.

        -  To evaluate the efficacy of SAR302503 in patients with ET who are resistant or
           intolerant to hydroxyurea for reduction of platelet counts.

        -  To evaluate the efficacy of SAR302503 in inducing complete and partial responses
           beginning at Day 1 of Cycle 6 visit through Cycle 8.

        -  To evaluate splenic response as measured by spleen volume using MRI or CT.

        -  To evaluate the pharmacokinetics of SAR302503 after single and repeat doses.

        -  To evaluate the pharmacodynamics of SAR302503 as measured by changes in JAK2V617F allele
           burden in patients with JAK2V617F mutation, and STAT3 phosphorylation inhibition.

        -  To measure improvement in baseline myeloproliferative neoplasm (MPN)-associated
           symptoms, as well as overall impact on quality of life.

        -  To measure generic health-related quality of life and utility value using the EuroQol
           Group (EQ-5DTM) questionnaire.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01420783</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Clinical Sciences &amp; Operations</name>
      <address>Sanofi</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>