<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2502">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/09/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/09/2009</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00981630</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Study of Live Attenuated ChimeriVax-Japanese Encephalitis Vaccine</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised, Double-blind, Placebo Controlled Phase II, Dose-ranging Study of the Safety, Tolerability and Immunogenicity of Live Attenuated ChimeriVax-JE Vaccine (Lyophilised)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>H-040-007</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Japanese Encephalitis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - Live attenuated Japanese encephalitis virus
Other interventions - Live attenuated Japanese encephalitis virus
Other interventions - Live attenuated Japanese encephalitis virus
Other interventions - ChimeriVax diluent (Placebo)

Experimental: ChimeriVax-JE Dose Level 1 - Participants received ChimeriVax-JE (Japanese Encephalitis) a dose of 3.0 log10 Plaque-forming units (PFU) on Day 0.

Experimental: ChimeriVax-JE Dose Level 2 - Participants received ChimeriVax-JE a dose of 4.0 log10 PFU on Day 0.

Experimental: ChimeriVax-JE Dose Level 3 - Participants received ChimeriVax-JE a dose of 5.0 log10 PFU on Day 0.

Placebo Comparator: Placebo - Participants received ChimeriVax diluent, 0.5 mL on Day 0.


Other interventions: Live attenuated Japanese encephalitis virus
0.5 mL,Subcutaneous

Other interventions: Live attenuated Japanese encephalitis virus
0.5 mL, Subcutaneous

Other interventions: Live attenuated Japanese encephalitis virus
0.5 mL, Subcutaneous

Other interventions: ChimeriVax diluent (Placebo)
0.5 mL, Subcutaneous

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants Who Seroconverted to the Respective Homologous JE Vaccine Strain, 28 Days After Completion of the Primary Immunization Schedule With One of 3 Doses of ChimeriVax-JE Vaccine or A Placebo - Antibodies were measured using 50% plaque reduction neutralization test (PRNT50) for measurement of neutralizing antibodies against homologous ChimeriVax-JE and wild type JE virus strains. Seroconversion was defined as a titer = 1:20 at post vaccination timepoints for subjects who were seronegative at baseline, or = 4 fold rise from baseline.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 11 and Day 30 post-vaccination</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants Who Seroconverted to Wild Type JE Virus Strains After Primary Immunization Schedule With One of 3 Doses of ChimeriVax-JE Vaccine or a Placebo - Antibodies were measured using 50% plaque reduction neutralization test (PRNT50) for measurement of neutralizing antibodies against homologous ChimeriVax-JE and wild type JE virus strains. Seroconversion was defined as a titer = 1:20 at post vaccination time points for subjects who were seronegative at baseline, or = 4 fold rise from baseline.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 30 post-vaccination</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants Reporting Solicited Local Injection Site and Treatment Related Adverse Events Post Vaccination With One of 3 Doses of ChimeriVax-JE Vaccine or Placebo - Local Injection Site Adverse Events (AEs): Pain, Erythema, Reaction, Hemorrhage, Induration, Paresthesia. Treatment Related Systemic AEs: Fever, Chills, Malaise, Fatigue, Headache, Myalgia, Arthralgia, Nausea, Vomiting, Diarrhea, Rash. Other AEs as reported spontaneously.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 0 (post-vaccination) up to Day 30 post-vaccination</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Geometric Mean Titers to Japanese Encephalitis (Homologous Virus) Following Primary Immunization Schedule With One of 3 Doses of ChimeriVax-JE Vaccine or a Placebo - Antibodies were measured using 50% plaque reduction neutralization test (PRNT50) for measurement of neutralizing antibodies against homologous ChimeriVax-JE virus strains.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 11 and Day 30 post-vaccination</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Geometric Mean Titers to Japanese Encephalitis (Wild Type JE Virus Strains) Following Primary Immunization Schedule With One of 3 Doses of ChimeriVax-JE Vaccine or a Placebo - The Japanese Encephalitis (Wild Type JE Virus Strains) antibodies were measured using PRNT50 for measurement of neutralizing antibodies against homologous ChimeriVax-JE and wild type JE virus strains.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 30 post-vaccination</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants With Japanese Encephalitis (Homologous Virus) Seropositivity Over Time Following Primary Immunization Schedule With One of 3 Doses of ChimeriVax-JE Vaccine or Placebo - Antibodies were measured using 50% plaque reduction neutralization test (PRNT50) for measurement of neutralizing antibodies against homologous ChimeriVax-JE virus strains. Seropositivity was defined as a titer &lt; 1:10.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 30 up to 12 months post-vaccination</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion Criteria :

          -  All aspects of the protocol explained and written informed consent obtained from the
             participant.

          -  Aged =18 to &lt; 49 years.

          -  In good general health, without significant medical history, physical examination
             findings, or clinically significant abnormal laboratory results.

          -  Participant must be available for the study duration, including all planned follow-up
             visits.

          -  Participant must agree to take the following precautions to avoid insect bites for 7
             days following vaccination by using N,N-diethyl-meta-toluamide (DEET)-containing
             insect repellent, where appropriate.

          -  For female participants: Negative pregnancy tests at Screening and Day 0, in
             conjunction with a menstrual and contraceptive history indicating a low probability of
             pregnancy in the opinion of the physician. Females of childbearing potential will be
             required to be correctly using an efficacious hormonal method of contraception or
             intrauterine device for at least 1 month before randomisation and during the on-study
             phase to Day 30. Barrier methods of contraception will not be considered acceptable
             for study entry. Female participants of child-bearing potential will sign an agreement
             that contraception will be correctly practised during the specified periods and will
             specify the method used. Female participants unable to become pregnant must have this
             documented (e.g., tubal ligation, hysterectomy or postmenopausal [at least one year
             since last menstrual period]).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>48</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion Criteria :

          -  A history of vaccination or infection to Japanese encephalitis (JE) or yellow fever
             (YF) or other flaviviruses (including Japanese encephalitis, tick-borne encephalitis,
             St Louis encephalitis, West Nile virus, dengue fever, Murray Valley encephalitis).
             Previous vaccination will be determined by history (interview of subject).

          -  Previous or current military service.

          -  History of residence in or travel to flavivirus endemic areas in the tropics (Cape
             York region of Northern Queensland, India, Southeast Asia, Central America, Caribbean
             or South America) for periods of 4 weeks or more.

          -  Known or suspected immunodeficiency (e.g., human immunodeficiency virus [HIV]
             infection, primary immunodeficiency disorder, leukemia, lymphoma), use of
             immunosuppressive or antineoplastic drugs (corticosteroids &gt; 10 mg prednisone, or
             equivalent, in the last three months or during the trial (up to Day 30).

          -  History of thymoma, thymic surgery (removal) or myasthenia gravis.

          -  Clinically significant abnormalities on laboratory assessment (i.e., meeting the mild,
             moderate or severe criteria described in the toxicity gradings for laboratory values).

          -  Anaphylaxis or other serious adverse reactions characterised by urticaria or
             angioedema to foods, hymenoptera (bee family) stings, or drugs (including vaccines).

          -  Transfusion of blood or treatment with any blood product, including intramuscular or
             intravenous serum globulin within six months of the Screening Visit or up to Day 30.

          -  Administration of another vaccine or antiviral within 30 days preceding the screening
             visit or up to Day 30 (these subjects will be rescheduled for vaccination at a later
             date).

          -  Physical examination indicating any clinically significant medical condition.

          -  Body temperature &gt; 38.1°C (100.6°F) or acute illness within 3 days prior to
             inoculation (participant may be rescheduled).

          -  Intention to travel out of the area prior to the study visit on Day 30.

          -  Seropositive to hepatitis C virus or HIV or positive for Hepatitis B Surface Antigen.

          -  Lactation or intended pregnancy in female subjects.

          -  Excessive alcohol consumption, drug abuse, significant psychiatric illness.

          -  A known or suspected physiological or structural condition that compromises the
             integrity of the blood-brain barrier (e.g., significant hypertensive cerebrovascular
             disease, trauma, ischaemia, infection, inflammation of the brain).

          -  Intention to increase normal exercise routine, participate in contact sports or
             strenuous weight lifting or to initiate vigorous exercise from Screening until after
             Day 30.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2>The people administering the treatment/s</masking2>
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/11/2004</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>128</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/11/2007</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD,SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital> - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital> - Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>QLD 4006 - Herston</postcode>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Sanofi</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to assess the safety, tolerability, and immunogenicity of a new
      formulation of lyophilised ChimeriVax-JE, given at three dose levels, compared with placebo.

      Primary Objectives:

      Safety:

        -  To obtain safety and tolerability data for a single subcutaneous vaccination with
           ChimeriVax-JE, at three dose levels, in healthy adult volunteers (18-49 years old).

      Immunogenicity:

        -  To obtain data on the antibody response to a single subcutaneous vaccination with
           ChimeriVax-JE, at three dose levels, in healthy adult volunteers without prior Japanese
           encephalitis immunity.

        -  To assess the durability of immune response up to 12 months following a single
           subcutaneous vaccination with ChimeriVax-JE, at three dose levels.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00981630</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Medical Director</name>
      <address>Sanofi Pasteur Inc.</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>