<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4465">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/04/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/04/2014</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02158442</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Technology That Permits Focal Dose of Antibiotics to be Delivered to Lower Limb(s) of Diabetic Patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomized Study Comparing Clinical and Microbiological Efficacy of Timentin Delivered Via Percutaneous Isolated Limb Perfusion (PILP) or Intravenous Infusion in Diabetic Subjects With Moderate to Severe Lower Limb Infection</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>O-PILP-C01 - Part B</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Infection</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sexually transmitted infections</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: surgery - Percutaneous Isolated Limb Perfusion (PILP) delivery
Treatment: drugs - Timentin

Experimental: Treatment Group - The Treatment Group received intravenous Timentin prior to their PILP procedure.

Active Comparator: Control Group - The Control Group received standard dosings of intravenous Timentin plus other standard care.


Treatment: surgery: Percutaneous Isolated Limb Perfusion (PILP) delivery
The Percutaneous Isolated Limb Perfusion (PILP) delivery intervention procedure enables the use of existing antibiotic therapies in a more targeted and aggressive fashion; it addresses limitations associated with the use of conventional antibiotic drug delivery. As part of the procedure, the circulation of the limb is isolated separately from the general circulatory system enabling the delivery of antibiotic at high therapeutic doses that are not achievable when standard doses are administered intravenously.

Treatment: drugs: Timentin
The Control Group will receive standard dosings of intravenous Timentin plus other standard care.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Efficacy of Timentin Delivered by PILP Procedure (Treatment Group) Versus Intravenous Delivery (Control Group) at Reducing Microbiological Load in Subjects With Diabetes, and Significant Wound Infection of the Lower Limb. - Reduction in microbiological load, including assessment of CFU, infection type and antibiotic sensitivity between the two groups over time. To compare the efficacy of Timentin delivered by PILP procedure (Treatment Group) versus intravenous delivery (Control Group) at reducing microbiological load in subjects with diabetes, and significant wound infection of the lower limb.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 3</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  M or F subjects 18 - 90 years old

          -  Subject has pre-existing diabetes diagnosis

          -  Subject has significant infection below the ankle of soft tissue and may include bone,
             and IV antibiotics are needed in order to salve limb or life

          -  Consequence of infected wound would require Std of Care share debridement

          -  Subject willing and able to provide written informed consent

          -  Subject willing and able to comply with requirements of study protocol including
             pre-defined follow-up evaluations

          -  PROCEDURAL INCLUSION CRITERIA: successful cannulation of the femoral artery and vein
             and placement of the venous support device</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>90</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Allergy to contrast media

          -  Known bleeding disorder including thrombocytopenia

          -  Recent AMI or elevated Troponin levels within last 30 days

          -  Penicillin sensitivity; Timentin sensitivity

          -  Female subjects known to be or suspected to be pregnant or lactating

          -  Subject unable to comply with instructions; especially to remain supine for duration
             of recirculation procedure

          -  Subjects who have participated in any other clinical trial or taken investigational
             drug within 30 days of study enrollment

          -  The PI determines the subject is not an appropriate subject for the study

          -  PROCEDURAL EXCLUSION CRITERIA: Subjects anatomy interferes with or is expected to
             prohibit successful cannulation of the femoral vessels or placement of the venous
             support device

          -  Known severe proximal femoral artery vascular disease precluding placement of
             perfusion catheters</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/10/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>15</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/03/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>3050 - Parkville</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Osprey Medical, Inc</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The use of the Percutaneous Isolated Limb Procedure (PILP) which enables the use of existing
      antibiotic therapies in a more targeted and concentrated fashion in patients with diabetes
      who have a significant lower limb infection and it is deemed that IV antibiotics are needed
      in order to salvage the limb or life.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02158442</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Paul Wraight, Assoc. Prof.</name>
      <address>Royal Melbourne Hospital, Head, Diabetic Foot Unit</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>