<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6172">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/11/1999</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/11/1999</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00001038</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Study of Valacyclovir Hydrochloride in the Prevention of Life-Threatening Cytomegalovirus Disease in HIV-Infected Patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomized, Double-Blind Trial of Valacyclovir Hydrochloride (BW 256U87) Prophylaxis for Opportunistic Cytomegalovirus End-Organ Disease in Patients With Advanced HIV Infection (&lt; 100 CD4+ Lymphocytes)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>FDA 104C</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>ACTG 204</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cytomegalovirus Infections</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>HIV Infections</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sexually transmitted infections</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Acquired immune deficiency syndrome (AIDS / HIV)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Valacyclovir hydrochloride
Treatment: drugs - Acyclovir

Treatment: drugs: Valacyclovir hydrochloride


Treatment: drugs: Acyclovir


</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes />
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion Criteria

        Concurrent Medication:

        Recommended:

          -  PCP prophylaxis.

        Allowed:

          -  Any antiretroviral therapies available by prescription or through expanded access or
             Treatment IND programs, including combination or sequential use.

          -  Chemotherapy for Kaposi's sarcoma, lymphoma, or other malignancies IF patient is
             hematologically stable for at least 30 days prior to study entry.

          -  Discrete courses of oral or parenteral acyclovir for VZV or HSV infection, not to
             exceed 21 days per episode (may co-enroll on ACTG 169). For recurrent episodes,
             open-label acyclovir for a total of 60 days over a 12-month period is allowed. Study
             drug is interrupted.

          -  Supportive therapies available by prescription, expanded access, or Treatment IND
             programs, such as G-CSF, GM-CSF, and erythropoietin.

          -  Other medications necessary for the patient's welfare, at the discretion of the
             investigator.

        Patients must have:

          -  HIV infection or AIDS-defining conditions.

          -  CD4+ count &lt; 100 cells/mm3.

          -  IgG antibodies to CMV.

          -  No active CMV disease or history of CMV end-organ disease.

          -  Consent of parent or guardian if less than 18 years of age.

          -  Ability to comply with protocol.

        NOTE:

          -  Patients may be co-enrolled in ACTG primary infection Phase II/III studies, ACTG
             opportunistic infection protocols, or treatment protocols or similar studies sponsored
             by other research networks as long as those studies do not violate the restrictions
             placed on concomitant therapies and toxicity management.

        Prior Medication:

        Allowed:

          -  PCP prophylaxis.

          -  Any antiretroviral therapies available by prescription or through expanded access or
             Treatment IND programs, including combination or sequential use.

          -  Chemotherapy for Kaposi's sarcoma, lymphoma, or other malignancies.

          -  Acyclovir.

          -  Supportive therapies available by prescription, expanded access, or Treatment IND
             programs, such as G-CSF, GM-CSF, and erythropoietin.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>13</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion Criteria

        Co-existing Condition:

        Patients with the following symptoms and conditions are excluded:

          -  Nausea or vomiting that precludes oral dosing.

          -  Ocular media opacities that preclude adequate visualization of fundi.

          -  Pregnancy.

          -  Known hypersensitivity to acyclovir.

          -  Known lactose intolerance.

        Concurrent Medication:

        Excluded:

          -  Systemic interferons and immunomodulators (including CMV hyperimmune serum/globulin
             and chronic corticosteroids at doses in excess of physiologic replacement).

          -  Probenecid.

          -  Investigational or marketed agents with potential activity against CMV, herpes
             simplex, and/or Varicella zoster, EXCEPT as specifically allowed.

        Patients with the following prior condition are excluded:

          -  Pre-existing necrotizing retinopathy that may interfere with a subsequent diagnosis of
             CMV retinitis.

        Prior Medication:

        Excluded:

          -  Prior ganciclovir, foscarnet, or any investigational anti-CMV agent including use of
             foscarnet for acyclovir-resistant herpes.

          -  Interferons, immunomodulators (other than colony stimulating factors), or CMV
             hyperimmune globulin within 30 days prior to study entry.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>Saint Vincent's Hosp Med Centre - Sydney</hospital>
    <postcode> - Sydney</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Alabama</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Colorado</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Connecticut</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Illinois</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Indiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Maryland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Massachusetts</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Missouri</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Pennsylvania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Washington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Alberta</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Quebec</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Denmark</country>
      <state>Hvidore</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Paris Cedex 12</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Berlin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Rome</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Stockholm</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state>Bern</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Glaxo Wellcome</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>PRIMARY: To evaluate the efficacy of valacyclovir hydrochloride (BW 256U87) in the prevention
      of cytomegalovirus (CMV) end-organ disease in HIV/CMV co-infected patients with CD4+
      lymphocytes &lt; 100 cells/mm3. To assess the impact of BW 256U87, high-dose oral acyclovir and
      low-dose oral acyclovir on survival.

      SECONDARY: To evaluate the effect of BW 256U87 on quality of life, the safety of the drug
      administered concurrently with standard antiretroviral agents and other essential therapies
      for the treatment and prevention of opportunistic diseases, and the efficacy of BW 256U87 in
      suppressing activation of other herpesviruses. To evaluate serologic and virologic risk
      factors for the development of CMV disease, including assessment of HIV activation, and the
      risk of developing drug-resistant CMV, HSV, and VZV.

      Gastrointestinal absorption of acyclovir is not high enough to prevent CMV disease in
      patients with advanced HIV disease, although there is evidence that high doses of the drug
      may extend survival. Valacyclovir, a prodrug that is rapidly converted to acyclovir after
      oral administration, has a higher absorption rate and may therefore provide inhibitory
      activity against CMV.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001038</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Feinberg JE, Hurwitz S, Cooper D, Sattler FR, MacGregor RR, Powderly W, Holland GN, Griffiths PD, Pollard RB, Youle M, Gill MJ, Holland FJ, Power ME, Owens S, Coakley D, Fry J, Jacobson MA. A randomized, double-blind trial of valaciclovir prophylaxis for cytomegalovirus disease in patients with advanced human immunodeficiency virus infection. AIDS Clinical Trials Group Protocol 204/Glaxo Wellcome 123-014 International CMV Prophylaxis Study Group. J Infect Dis. 1998 Jan;177(1):48-56.
Fry J, Coakley D, Power M, Feinberg J. International collaborative clinical trials: the ACTG 204 experience. Int Conf AIDS. 1996 Jul 7-12;11(2):276 (abstract no ThB4146)
Griffiths PD, Feinberg J. Detection of cytomegalovirus in samples from patients enrolled in ACTG 204 / Glaxo Wellcome 123-014. Conf Retroviruses Opportunistic Infect. 1996 Jan 28-Feb 1;3rd:54
Brosgart C, Fisher E, Pulling C, Chaloner K, Cohn D, Elsadr W, Verheggen R, Schmetter B, Alston B. Prevalence of asymptomatic CMV retinitis (CMVR) in AIDS patients. Conf Retroviruses Opportunistic Infect. 1999 Jan 31-Feb 4;6th:152 (abstract no 453)
Fisher E, Brosgart C, Cohn D, Chaloner K, Pulling C, Alston B, Schmetter B, El-Sadr W. Placebo (PLC)-controlled, multicenter trial of adefovir dipivoxil (ADV) in patients (pt) with HIV disease. . Conf Retroviruses Opportunistic Infect. 1999 Jan 31-Feb 4;6th:160 (abstract no 491)
Feinberg JE, Bell WR, Chulay JD. A thrombotic microangiopathy (TMA)-like syndrome in patients with advanced HIV disease in a cytomegalovirus (CMV) prophylaxis trial (ACTG 204). Conf Retroviruses Opportunistic Infect. 1997 Jan 22-26;4th:196 (abstract no 715)
Sprenger HG, Law G, Pastoor G, Postma S, Schirm J, Weits J, The TH. Cytomegalovirus antigenemia (CMVAg) compared with other CMV tests during phase III study of valaciclovir (VACV) for CMV prophylaxis in advanced HIV disease (ACTG 204 study). Int Conf AIDS. 1996 Jul 7-12;11(2):285 (abstract no ThB4200)
Bell WR, Chulay JD, Feinberg JE. Manifestations resembling thrombotic microangiopathy in patients with advanced human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) disease in a cytomegalovirus prophylaxis trial (ACTG 204). Medicine (Baltimore). 1997 Sep;76(5):369-80.
Emery V, Sabin C, Feinberg J, Grywacz M, Knight S, Griffiths P. Quantitative effects of valaciclovir on the replication of cytomegalovirus in patients with advanced HIV disease. Conf Retroviruses Opportunistic Infect. 1999 Jan 31-Feb 4;6th:153 (abstract no 459)
Weinberg A, Schneider SA, Clark JC. Acyclovir (ACV) and valacyclovir (VAL) prophylaxis of AIDS patients does not alter cytomegalovirus (CMV) susceptibility to ganciclovir (GCV) or foscarnet (FOS). Program Abstr Intersci Conf Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 1996 Sep 15-18:202 (abstract no I87)
Nokta MA, Holland F, De Gruttola V, Emery VC, Jacobson MA, Griffiths P, Pollard RB, Feinberg JE; AIDS Clinical Trials Group, Protocol 204/GlaxoWellcome 123-014, International CMV Prophylaxis Study Group. Cytomegalovirus (CMV) polymerase chain reaction profiles in individuals with advanced human immunodeficiency virus infection: relationship to CMV disease. J Infect Dis. 2002 Jun 15;185(12):1717-22. Epub 2002 May 31.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Feinberg J</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>