<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6537">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/06/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/06/2017</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT03178851</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Cobimetinib (Targeted Therapy) Plus Atezolizumab (Immunotherapy) in Participants With Advanced Melanoma Whose Cancer Has Worsened During or After Treatment With Previous Immunotherapy and Atezolizumab Monotherapy in Participants With Previously Untreated Advanced Melanoma</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase Ib Study Evaluating Cobimetinib Plus Atezolizumab in Patients With Advanced BRAF V600 Wild-Type Melanoma Who Have Progressed During or After Treatment With Anti-PD-1 Therapy and Atezolizumab Monotherapy in Patients With Previously Untreated Advanced BRAF V600 Wild-Type Melanoma</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>2016-004402-34</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>CO39721</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Malignant Melanoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Malignant melanoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - Atezolizumab
Treatment: drugs - Cobimetinib
Other interventions - Atezolizumab
Other interventions - Atezolizumab

Experimental: Cohort A - Participants with disease progression on or after treatment with an anti-PD-1 agent will receive cobimetinib and atezolizumab treatment during 28-day cycles.

Experimental: Cohort B - Participants with disease progression on or after treatment with an anti-PD-1 agent will receive cobimetinib prior to initiating atezolizumab treatment during Cycle 1. During subsequent 28-day cycles participants will initiate both atezolizumab and cobimetinib on Day 1 of each cycle. Participants in this cohort will undergo tumor biopsies before and during treatment.

Experimental: Cohort C - Participants with advanced melanoma, who have not received previous treatment, will receive atezolizumab monotherapy during 21-day cycles.


Other interventions: Atezolizumab
Atezolizumab, 840 mg intravenously every two weeks (Q2W) on Days 1 and 15 of each 28-day cycle, until loss of clinical benefit

Treatment: drugs: Cobimetinib
Cobimetinib, 60 mg orally once daily (QD) on Days 1-21 of each 28-day cycle, until loss of clinical benefit

Other interventions: Atezolizumab
Atezolizumab, 840 mg intravenously on Day 15 of Cycle 1; thereafter Q2W on Days 1 and 15 of Cycle 2 and all subsequent 28-day cycles, until loss of clinical benefit

Other interventions: Atezolizumab
Atezolizumab, 1200 mg intravenously every three weeks (Q3W) on Day 1 of each 21-day cycle, until loss of clinical benefit

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Objective Response Rate (ORR) - ORR is defined as the percentage of participants with confirmed objective response (OR). Confirmed OR is defined as complete response (CR) or partial response (PR) on two consecutive occasions = 4 weeks apart, as determined by the investigator according to Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) v1.1. CR is defined as disappearance of all target lesions. PR is defined as at least a 30% decrease in the sum of diameters of target lesions, taking as reference the baseline sum of diameters.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to approximately 2 years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disease Control Rate (DCR) - DCR is defined as the percentage of participants with CR, PR, or stable disease (SD) at 16 weeks. Per RECIST v1.1, CR is defined as disappearance of all target lesions. PR is defined as at least a 30% decrease in the sum of diameters of target lesions, taking as reference the baseline sum of diameters. SD is defined as neither sufficient shrinkage to qualify for PR nor sufficient increase to qualify for disease progression, taking as reference the smallest sum on study. Disease progression is defined as at least a 20% increase in the sum of diameters of target lesions, taking as reference the smallest sum on study including baseline, or the appearance of one or more new lesions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 16</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of Response (DOR) - DOR is defined as the time from the first occurrence of documented OR to disease progression, as determined by the investigator according to RECIST v1.1, or death from any cause, whichever occurs first. Disease progression is defined as at least a 20% increase in the sum of diameters of target lesions, taking as reference the smallest sum on study including baseline; or the appearance of one or more new lesions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to approximately 2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Survival (OS) - OS is defined as the time from Cycle 1, Day 1 to death from any cause.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to approximately 2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression-Free Survival (PFS) - PFS is defined as the time from Cycle 1, Day 1 to the first occurrence of disease progression, as determined by the investigator according to RECIST v1.1, or death from any cause, whichever occurs first. Disease progression is defined as at least a 20% increase in the sum of diameters of target lesions, taking as reference the smallest sum on study including baseline; or the appearance of one or more new lesions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to approximately 2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clearance of Atezolizumab - Clearance is the process of drug elimination from the body.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cohort A: Cycle 1, Day 1 - pre-dose, 30 minutes (min) post-dose. Cohort B: Cycle 1, Day 15 - pre-dose, 30 min post-dose. Cohorts A and B: Cycles 2, 3, 4, 8, 12, and 16 - pre-dose, discontinuation, 120 days after last dose. Each cycle is 28 days.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clearance of Cobimetinib - Clearance is the process of drug elimination from the body.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cohort A: Cycle 1, Day 1 - 2-4 hours (hr) post-dose, Cycle 1, Day 15 - pre-dose, 2-4 hr post-dose. Cohort B: Cycle 1, Day 15 - pre-dose, 2-4 hr post-dose. Each cycle is 28 days.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants with Adverse Events - An adverse event is any untoward medical occurrence in a participant administered a pharmaceutical product and which does not necessarily have to have a causal relationship with the treatment. An adverse event can therefore be any unfavorable and unintended sign (including an abnormal laboratory finding, for example), symptom, or disease temporally associated with the use of a pharmaceutical product, whether or not considered related to the pharmaceutical product. Preexisting conditions which worsen during a study are also considered as adverse events.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to approximately 2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from Baseline in Percentage of Participants with Anti-drug Antibodies (ADAs) to Atezolizumab - To evaluate the immune response to atezolizumab the percentage of participants with ADAs to atezolizumab will be determined at baseline and during the study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cohorts A and C: Cycle 1, Day 1 pre-dose. Cohort B: Cycle 1, Day 15 pre-dose. Cohorts A, B and C: Cycles, 2, 3, 4, 8, 12, and 16 pre-dose, discontinuation, 120 days after last dose. Cohorts A and B: each cycle is 28 days. Cohort C: each cycle is 21 days.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria

        Disease-Specific  Cohorts A and B:

          -  Histologically confirmed Stage IV (metastatic) or unresectable Stage IIIc BRAF V600 WT
             (locally advanced) melanoma

          -  Documentation of BRAF V600 mutation-negative status in melanoma tumor tissue (archival
             [&lt; 5 years old] or newly obtained) through use of a clinical mutation test approved by
             the local health authority

          -  Measurable disease according to Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST)
             v1.1

          -  Disease progression on or after treatment with a programmed death (PD)-1 inhibitor
             either as monotherapy or in combination with other agent(s)

        Additional Disease-Specific Inclusion Criteria in Cohort B (Biopsy Cohort):

          -  Progressed on or after anti-PD-1 therapy within 12 weeks before study start

          -  Received a minimum of two cycles of anti-PD-1 therapy

          -  Meet the following criteria for resistance to an anti-PD-1 agent: primary resistance
             defined as disease progression, according to RECIST v1.1, as best response; secondary
             resistance defined as disease progression after initial confirmed response according
             to RECIST v1.1

          -  Consent to undergo tumor biopsies of accessible lesions, before and during treatment
             and at radiographic progression, for biomarker analyses.

          -  Have at least two accessible lesions that are amenable to excisional, punch, or
             core-needle (minimum three cores and minimum diameter 18 gauge; however, 16 gauge is
             desirable) biopsy without unacceptable risk of a major procedural complication.

        Disease-Specific  Cohort C:

          -  Histologically confirmed Stage IV (metastatic) or unresectable Stage IIIc BRAFV600-WT
             (locally advanced) melanoma

          -  Naive to prior systemic anti-cancer therapy for melanoma

          -  Documentation of BRAFV600 mutation-negative status in melanoma tumor tissue (archival
             [&lt; 5 years old] or newly obtained) through use of a clinical mutation test approved by
             the local health authority

          -  A representative, formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded (FFPE) tumor specimen in a
             paraffin block (preferred) or 20 slides containing unstained, freshly cut, serial
             sections must be submitted along with an associated pathology report prior to study
             entry.

          -  Measurable disease according to RECIST v1.1.

        General 

          -  Ability to comply with the study protocol, in the investigator's judgment

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status of 0 or 1

          -  Available and adequate baseline tumor tissue sample

          -  Life expectancy = 18 weeks

          -  Adequate hematologic and end-organ function, defined by laboratory test results,
             obtained within 14 days before initiation of study treatment

          -  For women of childbearing potential: abstinent or use an effective form of
             contraceptive method for at least 3 months for cobimetinib and at least 5 months for
             atezolizumab

          -  For men: abstinent or use contraceptive measures and agreement to refrain from
             donating sperm for at least 3 months after cobimetinib and atezolizumab</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria

          -  Prior treatment with a mitogen activated-protein kinase (MAPK) inhibitor

          -  Ocular melanoma

          -  Major surgical procedure other than for diagnosis within 4 weeks before initiation of
             study treatment, or anticipation of need for a major surgical procedure during the
             course of the study

          -  Traumatic injury within 2 weeks before initiation of study treatment

          -  Palliative radiotherapy within 14 days before initiation of study treatment

          -  Active malignancy (other than BRAF V600 mutation-negative melanoma) or malignancy
             within 3 years

          -  Treatment with any anti-cancer agent 14 days prior to Cycle, Day 1 other than aPD-1
             based therapy

          -  Adverse events from prior anti-cancer therapy that have not resolved to Grade = 1
             except for alopecia

          -  For Cohort C only: any prior anti-cancer therapy for advanced melanoma

          -  History or evidence of ongoing serous retinopathy or retinal vein occlusion (RVO) at
             baseline

          -  History of clinically significant cardiac dysfunction

          -  Active or untreated central nervous system (CNS) metastases

          -  History of metastases to brain stem, midbrain, pons, or medulla, or within 10
             millimeter (mm) of the optic apparatus (optic nerves and chiasm)

          -  History of leptomeningeal metastatic disease

          -  Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection

          -  Active tuberculosis

          -  Severe infection within 4 weeks before initiation of study treatment

          -  Signs or symptoms of infection within 2 weeks before initiation of study treatment

          -  Treatment with oral or intravenous (IV) antibiotics within 2 weeks prior to Day 1 of
             Cycle 1

          -  Active or chronic viral hepatitis B or C infection

          -  Active or history of autoimmune disease or immune deficiency

          -  Prior allogeneic stem cell or solid organ transplantation

          -  History of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis, organizing pneumonia (e.g., bronchiolitis
             obliterans), drug-induced pneumonitis, or idiopathic pneumonitis, or evidence of
             active pneumonitis on screening chest computed tomography (CT) scan

          -  Treatment with systemic immunosuppressive medications

          -  Current severe, uncontrolled systemic disease other than cancer

          -  Any Grade &gt;/=3 hemorrhage or bleeding event within 28 days of Day 1 of Cycle 1

          -  History of stroke, reversible ischemic neurological defect, or transient ischemic
             attack within 6 months prior to Day 1

          -  Anticipated use of any concomitant medication during or within 7 days before
             initiation of study treatment that is known to cause QT prolongation

          -  Any psychological, familial, sociological, or geographic condition that may hamper
             compliance with the protocol and follow-up after treatment discontinuation

          -  History of malabsorption or other clinically significant metabolic dysfunction that
             may interfere with absorption of oral study treatment

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding, or intending to become pregnant during the study

          -  Known clinically significant liver disease

          -  Any other disease, metabolic dysfunction, physical examination finding, or clinical
             laboratory finding that contraindicates the use of an investigational drug, may affect
             the interpretation of the results, or may render the participant at high risk for
             treatment complications

          -  Treatment with a live, attenuated vaccine within 4 weeks before initiation of study
             treatment, or anticipation of need for such a vaccine during the course of the study

          -  Known hypersensitivity to any component of the atezolizumab or cobimetinib
             formulations

          -  History of severe allergic, anaphylactic, or other hypersensitivity reactions to
             chimeric or humanized antibodies or fusion proteins

          -  Treatment with any other investigational agent or participation in another clinical
             study with therapeutic intent

          -  Inability or unwillingness to swallow pills

          -  Requirement for concomitant therapy or food that is prohibited during the study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>19/06/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>92</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/11/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Blacktown Hospital - Blacktown</hospital>
    <hospital>Melanoma Institute Australia - North Sydney</hospital>
    <hospital>Greenslopes Private Hospital; Clinic Pharmacy - Greenslopes</hospital>
    <hospital>Peter Maccallum Cancer Centre - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>NSW 2148 - Blacktown</postcode>
    <postcode>2060 - North Sydney</postcode>
    <postcode>4120 - Greenslopes</postcode>
    <postcode>3000 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Arizona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Colorado</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Michigan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Missouri</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Tennessee</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>RJ</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>RS</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Cape Town</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Centurion</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Johannesburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Port Elizabeth</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Pretoria</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Navarra</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Sevilla</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Hoffmann-La Roche</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will evaluate the preliminary efficacy, safety, and pharmacokinetics of
      cobimetinib and atezolizumab in participants with advanced BRAF V600-wild type (WT),
      metastatic, or unresectable locally advanced melanoma who have progressed on prior anti-PD-1
      therapy. In addition, this study will evaluate the efficacy, safety, and pharmacokinetics of
      atezolizumab monotherapy in participants with BRAFV600-WT metastatic or unresectable locally
      advanced melanoma, who have not been previously treated.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03178851</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Clinical Trials</name>
      <address>Hoffmann-La Roche</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Reference Study ID Number: CO39721 www.roche.com/about_roche/roche_worldwide.htm</name>
      <address />
      <phone>888-662-6728 (U.S. only)</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>global-roche-genentech-trials@gene.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>