<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3102">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/03/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/03/2011</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01311791</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Randomized, Controlled Study to Evaluate Algisyl-LVR as a Method of Left Ventricular Augmentation for Heart Failure</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomized, Controlled Study to Evaluate the Safety and Cardiovascular Effects of Algisyl-LVR as a Method of Left Ventricular Augmentation in Patients With Dilated Cardiomyopathy (AUGMENT-HF)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>AUGMENT-HF</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>LSH-10-001</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Heart Failure</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Dilated Cardiomyopathy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - Algisyl-LVR
Treatment: drugs - Standard medical therapy

Experimental: Algisyl-LVR - Algisyl-LVR device (implants) administered during a surgical procedure.

Active Comparator: Standard Medical Therapy - as per protocol


Treatment: devices: Algisyl-LVR
Algisyl-LVR device (implants) administered during a surgical procedure

Treatment: drugs: Standard medical therapy
as defined per protocol

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>peak VO2 - The primary effectiveness endpoint will be a comparison of change in Peak VO2 from baseline to 6 months of follow-up between the Algisyl-LVR and medically managed arms with the intention to prove superiority in improvement in Peak VO2 associated with the Algisyl-LVR study group as compared to the medically managed study group. Evaluation of the cardiopulmonary exercise testing will be conducted by a central, blinded core laboratory.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>30 day all cause mortality - The primary safety objective is to estimate the 30 day cardiac mortality associated with the implantation of the Algisyl-LVR device and qualitatively compare the observed rate to literature estimates for similar patients undergoing cardiac surgeries comparable in risk to implantation of the Algisyl-LVR</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. The patients must be able and willing to give written informed consent

          2. The patients will be adult (age = 18 years and = 79 years) males or females

          3. The patients must be on stable, evidence-based therapy for heart failure

             * Note: CRT or CRT-D are acceptable co-therapy, if placed &gt; 3 months before
             randomization or the investigator does not anticipate within 6 months after
             randomization

          4. The patients will have a left ventricular ejection fraction equal to or less than 35%
             via echocardiography, cardiac catheterization, radionuclide scan, or magnetic
             resonance imaging (measured within the last 30 days)

          5. The patients will have a left ventricular end diastolic dimension indexed to body
             surface area (LVEDDi) of 30 to 40mm/m2 (LVEDD/BSA) (measured within the last 30 days)

          6. Patients must have symptomatic heart failure with a Peak VO2 of 9.0 - 14.5 ml/min/kg
             (performed using a bicycle ergometer). Patients must perform two CPX tests (within 30
             days of randomization and performed at least 20 hours apart) that differ by no more
             than 15% in the observed value for Peak VO2 and have a mean value of 9.0 - 14.5
             ml/min/kg from these two tests.

          7. Patient's surgical risk must be considered reasonable and the evaluation of surgical
             risk should include review of coronary and left ventricular angiography

          8. If female, the patients must be (a) post-menopausal, (b) surgically sterile, or (c)
             using adequate birth control and have a negative serum pregnancy test within 7 days
             prior to administration of study device</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>79</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Patients for whom it is planned to receive CABG, MVR, heart transplantation or LVAD
             within the next 6 months.

          2. Patients presenting with cardiogenic shock.

          3. Patients who have undergone a previous mid-sternotomy surgical procedure are excluded
             unless the surgeon's assessment is that the left sided limited thoracotomy is feasible
             and considered reasonable surgical risk.

          4. Patients presenting with a restrictive cardiomyopathy such as due to amyloidosis,
             sarcoidosis, or hemochromatosis

          5. Patient with a history of constrictive pericarditis

          6. Patients with a Q wave myocardial infarction (MI) within the last 30 days

          7. Patients with a recent history of stroke (within 60 days prior to the surgical
             procedure)

          8. A left ventricular (LV) wall thickness of the LV free-wall, at the mid-ventricular
             level, of less than 8 mm (screening echocardiography must confirm a minimum wall
             thickness of 8 mm)

          9. Patients with a serum creatinine &gt; 2.5 mg/dL

         10. Clinically significant liver enzyme abnormalities, i.e., AST(SGOT) and ALT (SGPT) more
             than 2.5 times the upper limit of normal

         11. History of severe COPD (i.e., FEV 1&lt; 1 liter or FEV1 &lt; 50% predicted)

         12. The patients will not be receiving concurrently an investigational Product in another
             clinical trial or have received an investigational Product in another clinical trial
             in the 30 days prior to enrollment

         13. A life expectancy of less than 1 year or any other condition that, in the opinion of
             the clinical investigator, might compromise any aspect of the trial</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/08/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>78</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/05/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Heart Center at the Alfred - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Berlin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Dresden</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Kiel</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Ulm</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Milanese (MI)</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Bergamo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Cremona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Milan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Padova</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Rome</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Nieuwegein</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Romania</country>
      <state>Bucharest</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>LoneStar Heart, Inc.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a pilot study to evaluate the safety and efficacy of the Algisyl-LVR device. The
      purpose of this study is to investigate Algisyl-LVR employed as a method of left ventricular
      augmentation and restoration in patients with dilated cardiomyopathy. Algisyl-LVR will be
      injected into the myocardium under direct visualization during the surgical procedure.

      This study will evaluate the concept that direct mid left ventricular (LV) intramyocardial
      injections of Alginate hydrogel implants into the free wall of the failing LV will reduce LV
      size, restore LV shape, lower LV wall stress and improve global LV function.

      The Primary Efficacy Endpoint of the study is the change in Peak VO2 (maximum oxygen uptake)
      from baseline to 6 months of follow-up. The Primary Safety Endpoint of the study is to
      estimate the 30 day mortality associated with the implantation of the Algisyl-LVR device

      The hypothesis of the study is that there is a statistically significant difference in change
      in Peak VO2 from baseline to 6 month follow-up when the medically managed arm is compared to
      the Algisyl-LVR arm, i.e. the Algisyl LVR arm is superior to medical management.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01311791</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Maurizio Volterani, MD</name>
      <address>IRCCS San Raffaele Pisana</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>