<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4199">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/11/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/11/2013</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02004223</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Early Investigation of High Precision Radiotherapy Prior to Commencing Standard Radiotherapy for Prostate Cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Phase I Dose Escalation Study of Stereotactic BOOST for Prostate cancER</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>BOOSTER</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>13-NSCCRO-P001</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Prostate Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Prostate</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: other - Dose escalation using stereotactic boost

Experimental: Dose escalation using stereotactic boost - Dose level allocation - Participants will be allocated to the current dose level, or if the current dose level has been filled and acceptable toxicity has been established, they will be enrolled into the next dose level


Treatment: other: Dose escalation using stereotactic boost
This is a dose escalation study. Participants will be allocated to the current dose level, or if the current dose level has been filled and acceptable toxicity has been established, they will be enrolled into the next dose level.
The first dose level will be 20Gy in 2 fractions to PTV and 25Gy to Gross Target Volume (GTV) if identified. The second dose level will be 22Gy in 2 fractions to PTV and 27.5Gy to GTV if identified. The dose level will be 24 Gy in 2 fractions to PTV and 30Gy to GTV if identified.
Following stereotactic boost, all participants will receive 46Gy in 23 fractions radiotherapy to the prostate / seminal vesicles +/- lymph nodes.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acute toxicity - Portion of patients with grade 3 or greater genitourinary or gastrointestinal toxicity assessed using the Modified Radiation Therapy Oncology Group (RTOG) Toxicity Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed up to 12 weeks post treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Late toxicity - At a median follow up of 18 months, Kaplan Meir statistics will be used to estimate the 2 year late Gastrointestinal and Genitourinary Toxicity using the modified RTOG scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to five years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cumulative toxicity rate: - The cumulative incidence of treatment related Grade 2 or higher GI or GU toxicity allowing for competing risk (death without prior toxicity event) and loss to follow up (censoring).</outcome>
      <timepoint>From the date of treatment completion assessed up to 5 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Biochemical failure (PSA failure) - Nadir PSA at three months and over duration of follow-up. This will be compared to historical controls from our prospective database stratified by initial PSA and androgen deprivation use / duration (nil vs. short term vs. long term).
When patients have reached a median follow-up of 24 months and 48 months, actuarial Kaplan Meir statistics will be used to estimate the 3 year and 5 year freedom from biochemical failure (FFBF) using the Nadir + 2.0 definition.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 5 years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life - Patient reported QOL using the validated EPIC SF-36 questionnaire will be collected at baseline, 3 months, 9 months and 21-24 months. Analysis will be performed (a) using the mean scores, with a 10 point deterioration deemed clinically significant and (b) as a change from baseline per individual patient using the 21-24 month questionnaire. A 10-20 point deterioration will be deemed mild-moderate and a &gt;20 point deterioration will be deemed significant. Kaplan Meir statistics will be used to estimate the proportion of patients with a =10 point, or =20 point deterioration at appropriate time points.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From baseline assessed up to 5 years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Histologically proven prostate adenocarcinoma

          -  PSA obtained within three months prior to enrollment.

          -  International Prostate Symptom Score (I-PSS) score &lt;15

          -  No contraindication to MRI (pacemaker, severe claustrophobia)

          -  Patient must be able to have fiducial markers placed in the prostate (if on
             anticoagulants, must be cleared by LMO or cardiologist).

          -  ECOG performance status 0-2

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>35</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Male</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Previous pelvic radiotherapy

          -  Prior total prostatectomy

          -  Unwilling or unable to give informed consent

          -  Unwilling or unable to complete quality of life questionnaires.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/01/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/12/2023</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Northern Sydney Cancer Centre, Royal North Shore Hospital - St Leonards</hospital>
    <postcode>2065 - St Leonards</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal North Shore Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Current standard treatment for prostate cancer involves giving patients approximately 40
      doses of radiotherapy, one dose per day over an 8 week period. The purpose of this study is
      to assess the effects of giving two separate high doses of a special type of precision
      radiotherapy to the prostate and then 5 weeks (instead of 8 weeks) of standard radiotherapy.

      Hypothesis: It is safe to give patients an extra two doses of high-precision radiotherapy
      prior to commencing a shorter period of standard radiotherapy for prostate cancer.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02004223</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Thomas N Eade, MBBS</name>
      <address>Royal North Shore Hospital</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Thomas N Eade, MBBS</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+61 2 9463 1300</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Thomas.Eade@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>