<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3912">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/05/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/05/2013</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01846039</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>JUVÉDERM VOLUMA® to Enhance the Appearance of the Asian Nose</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Prospective, Open-label Study of the Safety and Efficacy of JUVÉDERM VOLUMA® to Enhance the Aesthetic Appearance of the Asian Nose</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>VOLXC-AP-ND-001</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Asian Nose Enhancement</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - Crosslinked hyaluronic acid gel

Experimental: JUVÉDERM VOLUMA® - Participants treated with JUVÉDERM VOLUMA® up to 3 mLs administered by intradermal injection.


Treatment: devices: Crosslinked hyaluronic acid gel
Up to 3 mL administered by intradermal injection

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants With a = 1 Grade Improvement on the Assessment of Aesthetic Improvement Scale (AAIS) as Assessed by the Central Evaluating Physician at Day 113 - The independent central evaluating physician evaluated the improvement of the participant's nose as compared to Baseline using the AAIS 5-point scale: -2 (much worse) to +2 (much improved) at Day 113. The percentage of participants with a = 1 grade improvement from Baseline is reported.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Day 113</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants With a = 1 Grade Improvement on the AAIS as Assessed by the Patient at Day 113 - The participant evaluated the improvement of their nose as compared to Baseline using the AAIS 5-point scale: -2 (much worse) to +2 (much improved) at Day 113. The percentage of participants with a = 1 Grade Improvement from Baseline is reported.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Day 113</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants With a = 1 Grade Improvement on the AAIS as Assessed by the Central Evaluating Physician - The independent central evaluating physician evaluated the improvement of the participant's nose compared to Baseline using the AAIS 5-point scale: -2 (much worse) to +2 (much improved) at Days 239 and 421. The percentage of participants with a = 1 grade improvement from Baseline is reported.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Days 239 and 421</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants With a = 1 Grade Improvement on the AAIS as Assessed by the Patient - The participant evaluated the improvement of their nose as compared to Baseline using the AAIS 5-point scale: -2 (much worse) to +2 (much improved) at Days 239 and 421. The percentage of participants with a = 1 grade improvement from Baseline is reported</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Days 239 and 421</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants Satisfied or Very Satisfied Based on the Nose Satisfaction Scale (NSS) - Participants assessed their satisfaction with the appearance of their nose at Days 113, 239 and 421 using the NSS 5-point scale: -2 (very dissatisfied) to 2 (very satisfied). The percentage of participants who rated themselves as satisfied or very satisfied is reported.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 113, 239 and 421</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants Satisfied or Very Satisfied Based on the Treatment Satisfaction Scale (TSS) - Participants assessed their satisfaction with the study drug (VOLUMA) treatment at Days 113, 239 and 421 using the TSS 5-point scale: -2 (very dissatisfied) to 2 (very satisfied). The percentage of participants satisfied or very satisfied with study drug treatment is reported.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 113, 239 and 421</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants Who Would Recommend VOLUMA Treatment of the Nose to Others</outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 113, 239 and 421</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Asian subjects aged 20 years of age or older with dissatisfaction of their aesthetic
             appearance due to structural features of their nose

          -  Subjects who, in the opinion of the Investigator, can achieve a clinically meaningful
             aesthetic correction of their nose with VOLUMA® treatment</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  -Subjects requiring filler treatment in or around the tip of the nose or between the
             eyebrows (glabellar region) to achieve a good aesthetic outcome

          -  prior nasal surgery, including grafts, implants or filler injection to the nose area

          -  Subjects with a history of sinusitis or rhinitis

          -  Subjects unlikely to achieve a meaningful aesthetic result with the prescribed dosage
             regimen of the study product.

          -  Subjects receiving botulinum toxin treatment for any indication within 3 months of the
             study or planning to receive botulinum toxin during the study

          -  Subjects who have previously received aesthetic treatment in the forehead, glabellar,
             and/or nose area with any dermal filler

          -  Subjects with a history of any significant adverse events caused by dermal fillers

          -  Subjects with a history of allergic responses to lidocaine or fillers

          -  Subjects who are pregnant or breastfeeding or wish to become pregnant during the study

          -  Subjects of child-bearing age who are not prepared to practice an adequate form of
             contraception during the course of the study

          -  Subjects with traumatic scars in the treatment area or a history of active
             inflammation, infection, cancerous lesion, or an unhealed wound in the treatment area

          -  Subjects requiring dental or oral surgery, including dental implants, during the study
             period

          -  Subjects with a history of bleeding disorders

          -  Subjects who are smokers

          -  Subjects using blood thinning products within 10 days of the screening visit

          -  Subjects with a history of connective tissue disease (e.g., rheumatoid arthritis,
             lupus, scleroderma, etc) causing skin scarring

          -  Subjects with a history of untreated epilepsy or other significant medical conditions

          -  Subjects with a history of alcoholism or drug abuse of dependence

          -  Subjects participating or likely to participate in another clinical trial within 30
             days of screening or during the 1 year period of the study

          -  Subjects with any other medical condition, which in the opinion of the Investigator,
             might compromise the subject's ability to tolerate the injection procedure or comply
             with requirements of the study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/04/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>29</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/08/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital> - Sydney</hospital>
    <hospital> - Gold Coast</hospital>
    <postcode> - Sydney</postcode>
    <postcode> - Gold Coast</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Allergan</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A prospective, open-label, observational study of the safety and efficacy of JUVÉDERM VOLUMA®
      to enhance the aesthetic appearance of the Asian nose.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01846039</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Medical Director</name>
      <address>Allergan</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>