<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4835">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/06/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/06/2014</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02176967</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Response and Biology-Based Risk Factor-Guided Therapy in Treating Younger Patients With Non-high Risk Neuroblastoma</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Utilizing Response- and Biology-Based Risk Factors to Guide Therapy in Patients With Non-high-risk Neuroblastoma</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NCI-2014-00677</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>ANBL1232</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Ganglioneuroblastoma</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Localized Resectable Neuroblastoma</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Localized Unresectable Neuroblastoma</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Recurrent Neuroblastoma</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Regional Neuroblastoma</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Stage 4 Neuroblastoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Neuroendocrine tumour (NET)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Children's - Other</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Children's - Brain</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Brain</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - Clinical Observation
Treatment: drugs - Carboplatin
Treatment: drugs - Etoposide
Treatment: drugs - Cyclophosphamide
Treatment: drugs - Doxorubicin Hydrochloride
Other interventions - Laboratory Biomarker Analysis
Other interventions - Pharmacological Study

Experimental: Group A (clinical observation) - Patients undergo clinical observation for 96 weeks in the absence of disease progression.

Experimental: Group B (clinical observation, first-line chemotherapy) - Patients undergo clinical observation for 3 years in the absence of disease progression. Upon disease progression, patients undergo surgery or receive first-line chemotherapy comprising carboplatin IV over 1 hour on day 1 (courses 1, 2, 4, 6, and 7), etoposide IV over 1 hour on days 1-3 (courses 1, 3, 4, 5, and 7), cyclophosphamide IV over 1 hour on day 1 (courses 2, 3, 5, 6, and 8), and doxorubicin hydrochloride IV over 15 minutes on day 1 (courses 2, 4, 6 and 8). Treatment with chemotherapy repeats every 21 days for 2-8 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Once a PR or better is achieved, patients undergo clinical observation for 3 years.

Experimental: Group C (clinical observation, first-line chemotherapy) - Patients at high risk for deterioration and a poor outcome immediately receive first-line chemotherapy as in Group B. All other patients undergo clinical observation for 3 years in the absence of disease progression. Upon disease progression, patients receive first-line chemotherapy as in Group B. Once a PR or better is achieved, patients undergo clinical observation for 3 years.


Other interventions: Clinical Observation
Undergo clinical observation

Treatment: drugs: Carboplatin
Given IV

Treatment: drugs: Etoposide
Given IV

Treatment: drugs: Cyclophosphamide
Given IV

Treatment: drugs: Doxorubicin Hydrochloride
Given IV

Other interventions: Laboratory Biomarker Analysis
Correlative studies

Other interventions: Pharmacological Study
Optional correlative studies

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>OS (Strata 1-4) - Will be addressed by a one-sample, one-sided log-rank test comparison of the overall survival of patients in each individual stratum to the benchmark 3-year OS rate of 99%. If the log-rank test does not detect a statistically significant reduction from 99% and if the EFS interim monitoring rule is not triggered, then it may be assumed that a 3-year OS rate consistent with 99% has been maintained within each stratum.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From the date of enrollment until death or until last contact if the patient is alive, assessed up to 3 years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>EFS (Stratum 5) - If the 3-year EFS rate observed for patients in Stratum 5 is statistically significantly greater than the constant benchmark 3-year EFS rate of 70% observed for comparable Group D patients in the historical study A3961 using a one-sample, one-sided log-rank test and the EFS interim monitoring rule is not triggered, then it may be assumed that the target 3-year EFS has been achieved and the augmented regimen in this study is superior to that on the previous study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From the date of enrollment until the first relapse, progressive disease, secondary malignancy, or death or until last contact if none of these occur, assessed up to 3 years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to intervention or tumor progression - Will be assessed by a descriptive analysis for the cohort of patients with localized tumors who progress after an initial period of observation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 5 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Type of intervention required - Will be assessed by a descriptive analysis for the cohort of patients with localized tumors who progress after an initial period of observation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 5 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Site of progression - Will be assessed by a descriptive analysis for the cohort of patients with localized tumors who progress after an initial period of observation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 5 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetic (PK) profile of carboplatin and etoposide in patients with stage Ms disease, including peak concentration, area under the curve, clearance, volume of distribution, half-life, and mean residence time - The coefficient of variation will be calculated to quantify the degree of inter-patient and intra-patient variability of etoposide and carboplatin PK. The relationship between patient characteristics will be assessed graphically in an exploratory fashion and with regression models and if appropriate, Spearman's rank correlation coefficient will be used. Correlations between PK parameters and the symptom score and hepatic and renal dysfunction will be explored. Logistic regression models adjusting for patient level covariates will be explored.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-dose, 1, 2, 4, 8, and 24 hours on days 1 and 2 of either course 1 or 7</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Genomic profile of tumors - Will be assessed by determining the presence or absence of each segmental aberration (segmental loss at 1p, 3p, 4p, or 11q or segmental gain at 1p, 2p, or 17q), both at initial biopsy and at the time of subsequent biopsy or surgical resection, and correlating with patient characteristics using a chi-squared test and with outcome using a log-rank test. In cases with specimens from diagnosis and at the time of subsequent biopsy/resection, the profiles will be compared focusing on changes in the copy number pattern.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to time of biopsy or surgical resection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Histology of tumor specimens - Will be assessed by a descriptive analysis of the histology of tumor specimens obtained at the time of subsequent biopsy or surgical resection.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to time of biopsy or surgical resection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Salvage rate (OS) of patients with tumor relapse or disease progression - Will be assessed by calculating the overall survival for the cohort of patients with tumor relapse or disease progression.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From the date of enrollment until death or until last contact if the patient is alive, assessed up to 5 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Procedural complication rate - Will be assessed by determining the complication rate for each type of procedure (initial biopsy and resection [intraoperative and postoperative]) and correlating the occurrence of surgical complications with the degree of surgical resection using a Wilcoxon rank-sum test (to account for the ordering of the surgical resection categories).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 60 days after surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of reduction in IDRF in L2 tumors - Will be assessed by computing the proportion of patients with L2 tumors for which each particular IDRF and any IDRF is present at diagnosis and then absent after observation or chemotherapy. In addition, McNemar's test for paired observations will be applied to determine whether there is a difference in the proportion of each IDRF and any IDRF present before and after observation or chemotherapy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 5 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Patients must be:

               -  &lt; 12 months (&lt; 365 days) of age at diagnosis with INRG stage L1; or

               -  &lt; 18 months (&lt; 547 days) of age at diagnosis with INRG stage L2 or stage Ms
                  neuroblastoma/ganglioneuroblastoma

          -  Enrollment on ANBL00B1 is required for all newly diagnosed patients

          -  Patients must have newly diagnosed v-myc avian myelocytomatosis viral oncogene
             neuroblastoma derived homolog (MYCN) non-amplified neuroblastoma (International
             Classification of Diseases for Oncology [ICD-O] morphology 9500/3) or MYCN
             non-amplified ganglioneuroblastoma verified by histology

          -  Patients must meet the specified criteria for one of the treatment groups defined
             below; genomic features include MYCN gene amplification, segmental chromosome
             aberrations (somatic copy number loss at 1p, 3p, 4p, or 11q or somatic copy number
             gain at 1q, 2p, or 17q) and deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) index

               -  "Favorable" genomic features are defined by one or more whole-chromosome gains or
                  hyperdiploid tumor (DNA index &gt; 1) in the absence of segmental chromosome
                  aberrations as defined above

               -  "Unfavorable" genomic features are defined by the presence of any segmental
                  chromosome aberration (somatic copy number loss at 1p, 3p, 4p, or 11q or somatic
                  copy number gain at 1q, 2p, or 17q) or diploid tumor (DNA index = 1); this
                  includes copy neutral loss of heterozygosity (LOH)

               -  Only patients with MYCN non-amplified tumors are eligible for this study

          -  Group A: patients &lt; 12 months (&lt; 365 days) of age with newly diagnosed INRG stage L1
             neuroblastoma/ganglioneuroblastoma who meet the following criteria:

               -  Greatest tumor diameter &lt; 5 cm of adrenal or non-adrenal origin

               -  Patients with non-adrenal primaries are eligible, but must have positive uptake
                  on metaiodobenzylguanidine (MIBG) scan or elevated catecholamine metabolites
                  (urine or serum) to support the diagnosis of neuroblastoma

               -  No prior tumor resection or biopsy

          -  Group A will be further split into two subsets, which are mutually exclusive, for
             statistical purposes

               -  Group A1:

                    -  &gt; 6 months and &lt; 12 months of age with an adrenal primary tumor &lt; 5 cm in
                       greatest diameter OR

                    -  Patients less than 6 months of age with an adrenal primary tumor &gt; 3.1 and &lt;
                       5 cm in greatest diameter OR

                    -  &lt; 12 months of age with a non-adrenal primary site &lt; 5 cm in greatest
                       diameter

               -  Group A2: =&lt; 6 months of age with an adrenal primary site and tumor =&lt; 3.1 cm in
                  greatest diameter.

          -  Group B: patients &lt; 18 months (&lt; 547 days) of age with newly diagnosed INRG stage L2
             neuroblastoma/ganglioneuroblastoma who meet the following criteria:

               -  No life threatening symptoms or no impending neurologic or other organ function
                  compromise (e.g. epidural or intraspinal tumors with existing or impending
                  neurologic impairment, periorbital or calvarial-based lesions with existing or
                  impending cranial nerve impairment, anatomic or mechanical compromise of critical
                  organ function by tumor [abdominal compartment syndrome, urinary obstruction,
                  etc.])

               -  No prior tumor resection, tumor biopsy ONLY

               -  Only patients with both favorable histology and favorable genomic features will
                  remain on study as part of Group B; the institution will be notified of
                  histologic and genomic results within 3 weeks of specimen submission on ANBL00B1

          -  Group C: patients &lt; 18 months (&lt; 547 days) of age with newly diagnosed INRG stage Ms
             neuroblastoma/ganglioneuroblastoma

          -  No prior radiotherapy or chemotherapy, with the exception of dexamethasone, which is
             allowed

          -  All patients and/or their parents or legal guardians must sign a written informed
             consent

          -  All institutional, Food and Drug Administration (FDA), and National Cancer Institute
             (NCI) requirements for human studies must be met</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>17</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Months</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Patients with MYCN amplified tumors are not eligible

          -  Group B and C patients who do not enroll on ANBL1232 within 4 weeks of definitive
             diagnostic procedure

          -  Group A and C patients, not required to undergo tumor biopsy, who do not enroll on
             ANBL1232 within 4 weeks of confirmatory imaging study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>621</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>John Hunter Children's Hospital - State of New South Wales</hospital>
    <hospital>The Children's Hospital at Westmead - Westmead</hospital>
    <hospital>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children - Perth</hospital>
    <postcode>2310 - State of New South Wales</postcode>
    <postcode>2145 - Westmead</postcode>
    <postcode>6008 - Perth</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Alabama</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Alaska</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Arkansas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Colorado</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Connecticut</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Delaware</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>District of Columbia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Georgia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Illinois</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Indiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Iowa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Kentucky</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Louisiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Maryland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Massachusetts</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Michigan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Minnesota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Mississippi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Missouri</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Nebraska</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Nevada</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Hampshire</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Jersey</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Mexico</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Dakota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Oklahoma</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Oregon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Pennsylvania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Rhode Island</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>South Dakota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Tennessee</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Utah</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Virginia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Washington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>West Virginia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Wisconsin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Nova Scotia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Children's Oncology Group</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Government body</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This phase III trial studies how well response and biology-based risk factor-guided therapy
      works in treating younger patients with non-high risk neuroblastoma. Sometimes a tumor may
      not need treatment until it progresses. In this case, observation may be sufficient.
      Measuring biomarkers in tumor cells may help plan when effective treatment is necessary and
      what the best treatment is. Response and biology-based risk factor-guided therapy may be
      effective in treating patients with non-high risk neuroblastoma and may help to avoid some of
      the risks and side effects related to standard treatment.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02176967</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Holly Meany, MD</name>
      <address>Children's Oncology Group</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>