<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6227">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/04/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/04/2016</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02751931</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Open-label Phase 3 Study With Mirabegron in Children From 3 to Less Than 18 Years of Age With Neurogenic Detrusor Overactivity</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An Open-label, Baseline-controlled, Multicenter, Phase 3 Dose-titration Study Followed by a Fixed-dose Observation Period to Evaluate Efficacy, Safety and Pharmacokinetics of Mirabegron in Children and Adolescents From 3 to Less Than 18 Years of Age With Neurogenic Detrusor Overactivity (NDO) on Clean Intermittent Catheterization (CIC)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Crocodile</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>2015-002876-25</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>178-CL-206A</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Neurogenic Detrusor Overactivity</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Mirabegron

Experimental: Mirabegron - Participants will receive daily dosage of mirabegron as single tablets or suspension (2 dose strengths)


Treatment: drugs: Mirabegron
Oral

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in MCC based on filling urodynamics - Maximum cystometric capacity (MCC)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and week 24</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in MCC - Based on urodynamic assessments</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and week 4</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in bladder compliance (?V/?P) - Based on urodynamic assessments</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, week 4 and week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in number of overactive detrusor contractions (&gt; 15 cm H20) until end of filling - Based on urodynamic assessments</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, week 4 and week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in detrusor pressure at end of filling - Based on urodynamic assessments</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, week 4 and week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in filling volume until first overactive detrusor contraction (&gt; 15 cm H20) - Based on urodynamic assessments</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, week 4 and week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in average catheterized volume per catheterization - Obtained from the e-diary</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, week 2, week 4, week 8, week 12, week 24, week 36 and week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in maximum catheterized volume - Obtained from the e-diary</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, week 2, week 4, week 8, week 12, week 24, week 36 and week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in maximum catheterized daytime volume - Obtained from the e-diary</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, week 2, week 4, week 8, week 12, week 24, week 36 and week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in average morning catheterized volume - Obtained from the e-diary and based on first catheterization after subject woke up</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, week 2, week 4, week 8, week 12, week 24, week 36 and week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in mean number of leakage episodes - Obtained from the e-diary, episodes per day, day and night time</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, week 2, week 4, week 8, week 12, week 24, week 36 and week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in number of dry days - Obtained from the e-diary, leakage free days per 7 days, day and night time</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, week 2, week 4, week 8, week 12, week 24, week 36 and week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in PIN-Q - Obtained from patient reported questionnaires. Pediatric Incontinence Questionnaire (PIN-Q)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, week 24 and week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in PGI-S - Obtained from patient reported questionnaires. Patient Global Impression of Severity (PGI-S) Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, week 24 and week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>CGI-C assessment - Obtained from clinician reported questionnaires. Clinician Global Impression of Change (CGI-C) Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>CGI-C assessment - Obtained from clinician reported questionnaires. Clinician Global Impression of Change (CGI-C) Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Study drug acceptability - Obtained from patient reported questionnaires to assess among others palatability and taste of the study drug</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Study drug acceptability - Obtained from patient reported questionnaires to assess among others palatability and taste of the study drug</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence and severity of TEAEs - Treatment-emergent adverse events (TEAEs)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in vital signs measured via clinic measurements: systolic and diastolic blood pressure</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline up to week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in vital signs measured via clinic measurements: pulse rate</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline up to week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in vital signs measured via clinic measurements: body temperature</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, week 4, week 12, week 24 and week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in vital signs measured via SBPM: systolic and diastolic blood pressure - Self blood pressure measurement (SBPM)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline up to week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in vital signs measured via SBPM: pulse rate</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline up to week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in clinical laboratory tests: hematology</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, week 12 and week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in clinical laboratory tests: biochemistry</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, week 12 and week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in clinical laboratory tests: urinalysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, week 4, week 12, week 24 and week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in ECG parameters - Electrocardiogram (ECG)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, week 4, week 12, week 24 and week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in upper urinary tract ultrasound assessment</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in eGFR - Estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, week 12 and week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetics of mirabegron in plasma: Cmax - Two different sampling days at steady state within the specified timeframe. Maximum (peak) plasma drug concentration (Cmax)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 4, week 8, week 12, week 24, week 36 and/or week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetics of mirabegron in plasma: tmax - Two different sampling days at steady state within the specified timeframe. Time to reach maximum (peak) plasma concentration following drug administration (tmax)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 4, week 8, week 12, week 24, week 36 and/or week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetics of mirabegron in plasma: AUC24 - Two different sampling days at steady state within the specified timeframe. Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time zero to 24 h (AUC24)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 4, week 8, week 12, week 24, week 36 and/or week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetics of mirabegron in plasma: Ctrough - Two different sampling days at steady state within the specified timeframe. Measured plasma concentration of the drug at the end of a dosing interval at steady state (Ctrough)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 4, week 8, week 12, week 24, week 36 and/or week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetics of mirabegron in plasma: CL/F - Two different sampling days at steady state within the specified timeframe. Apparent total clearance of the drug from plasma after oral administration (CL/F)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 4, week 8, week 12, week 24, week 36 and/or week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetics of mirabegron in plasma: Vz/F - Two different sampling visits at steady state within the specified timeframe. Apparent volume of distribution after nonintravenous administration (Vz/F)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 4, week 8, week 12, week 24, week 36 and/or week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Study drug acceptability at week 4 - Obtained from patient reported questionnaires to assess among others palatability and taste of the study drug</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 4</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Subject has a body weight of greater than or equal to 11 kg.

          -  Subject suffers from NDO confirmed by urodynamic investigation at baseline. The
             diagnosis of NDO must be confirmed by the presence of at least 1 involuntary detrusor
             contraction &gt; 15 cm H2O from baseline detrusor pressure, and/or a decrease in
             compliance leading to an increase in baseline detrusor pressure of &gt; 20 cm H2O.

          -  Subject has been using CIC for at least 4 weeks prior to visit 1/screening.

          -  Subject has a current indication for drug therapy to manage NDO.

          -  Subject is able to take the study drug in accordance with the protocol</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>3</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>17</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Subject has a known genitourinary condition (other than NDO) that may cause overactive
             contractions or incontinence or kidney/bladder stones or another persistent urinary
             tract pathology that may cause symptoms.

          -  Subject has one of the following gastrointestinal problems: partial or complete
             obstruction, decreased motility such as paralytic ileus, subjects at risk of gastric
             retention.

          -  Subject has a urinary indwelling catheter within 4 weeks prior to visit 1/screening.

          -  Subject has a surgically treated underactive urethral sphincter

          -  Subject has vesico-ureteral reflux grade 3 to 5.

          -  Subject has undergone bladder augmentation surgery.

          -  Subject receives electrostimulation therapy, if started within 30 days before visit
             1/screening or is expected to start during the study period. Subjects who are on an
             established regimen may remain on this for the duration of the study.

          -  Subject suffers from a symptomatic urinary tract infection (UTI) at baseline
             (symptomatic is defined as pain, fever, hematuria, new onset foul-smelling urine). If
             present at visit 1/screening or diagnosed between visit 1/screening and visit
             3/baseline, the UTI should be treated successfully (clinical recovery) prior to
             baseline. If a symptomatic UTI is present at baseline, all baseline assessments are
             allowed to be postponed for a maximum of 7 days until the UTI is successfully treated
             (clinical recovery).

          -  Subject has a (mean) resting pulse rate &gt; 99th percentile [Fleming et al, 2011].

          -  Subject has an established hypertension and a systolic or diastolic blood pressure
             greater than the 99th percentile of the normal range determined by sex, age and
             height, plus 5mmHg [NIH 2005].

          -  Subject has a risk of QT prolongation (e.g., hypokalemia, long QT syndrome [LQTS]; or
             family history of LQTS, exercise-induced syncope).

          -  Subject has severe renal impairment (eGFR according to Larsson equation &lt; 30 mL/min).

          -  Subject's aspartate aminotransferase (AST) or alanine aminotransferase (ALT) is
             greater than or equal to 2 times the upper limit of normal (ULN) or total bilirubin
             (TBL) greater than or equal to 1.5 times the ULN according to age and sex.

          -  Subject has a history or presence of any malignancy prior to visit 1/screening.

          -  Subject has known or suspected hypersensitivity to mirabegron, any of the excipients
             used in the current formulations or previous severe hypersensitivity to any drug.

          -  Subject has participated in another clinical trial (and/or has taken an
             investigational drug within 30 days (or 5 half-lives of the drug, or the limit set by
             national law, whichever is longer) prior to visit 1/screening.

          -  Subject uses any of the following prohibited medications (after start of washout):

               -  Any medication, other than the study drug used, for the management of NDO;

               -  Any drugs that are sensitive CYP2D6 substrates with a narrow therapeutic index or
                  sensitive P-glycoprotein (P-gp) substrates

               -  Any strong CYP3A4 inhibitors if the subject has a mild to moderate renal
                  impairment (eGFR 30 - 89 mL/min).

          -  Subject has been administered intravesical botulinum toxin; except if given &gt; 4 months
             prior to visit 1/screening and the subject experiences symptoms comparable to those
             existing prior to the botulinum toxin injections.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>17/06/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>63</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/08/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Site AU61002 - Randwick</hospital>
    <hospital>Site AU61001 - Park Ville VIC</hospital>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
    <postcode>3052 - Park Ville VIC</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Gent</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Colombia</country>
      <state>Valle del Cauca</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Denmark</country>
      <state>Aarhus N</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Denmark</country>
      <state>Copenhagen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Jordan</country>
      <state>Amman</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Jordan</country>
      <state>Irbid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Seoul</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Lithuania</country>
      <state>Vilnius</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <state>Georgetown</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <state>Kuala Lumpur</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mexico</country>
      <state>Mexico City</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Norway</country>
      <state>Bergen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Philippines</country>
      <state>Quezon City</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Gdansk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Warszawa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Romania</country>
      <state>Bucuresti</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Serbia</country>
      <state>Nis</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Serbia</country>
      <state>Novi Sad</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Slovakia</country>
      <state>Bratislava</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Slovakia</country>
      <state>Martin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>New Taipei City</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Taipei</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>Ankara</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>Bursa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Astellas Pharma Europe B.V.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A study to evaluate the efficacy, safety and tolerability, and pharmacokinetics of mirabegron
      after multiple-dose administration in the pediatric population.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02751931</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Medical Monitor</name>
      <address>Astellas Pharma Europe B.V.</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Clinical Science</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+31 (0) 71 5455 050</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>astellas.registration@astellas.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>