<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4161">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/09/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/09/2013</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01984801</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Study to Investigate the Irritation Potential of GSK1940029 Gel</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Single-Blind Study to Evaluate the Irritation Potential of Repeat Topical Applications of GSK1940029 Gel on the Intact Skin of Healthy Human Subjects and Acne Patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>117225</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acne Vulgaris</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dermatological conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - 0.3% GSK1940029 gel
Treatment: drugs - 1% GSK1940029 gel
Treatment: drugs - 0.3%/1% vehicle gel only
Other interventions - Sterile distilled water
Other interventions - 0.5% SLS in sterile distilled water
Other interventions - 0.1% SLS in sterile distilled water
Other interventions - Patch only

Experimental: Part 1 - Each of the following 6 treatments will be randomized to one of 6 designated locations on either upper arm or other locations, such as the lower or upper back, within each healthy subject: (A) 200 mg of 0.3% GSK1940029 gel, (B) 200 mg of 1% GSK1940029 gel, (C) 200 mg of 0.3%/1% vehicle gel only, (D) 200 µL of sterile distilled water, (E) Patch only, and (F) 200 µL of 0.5% SLS in sterile distilled water, Each treatment will be applied using individual patches, daily for 2 days

Experimental: Part 2 - Each of the following 6 treatments will be randomized to one of 6 designated locations on either upper arm or other locations, such as the lower or upper back, within each healthy subject: (A) 200 mg of 0.3% GSK1940029 gel, (B) 200 mg of 1% GSK1940029 gel, (C) 200 mg of 0.3%/1% vehicle gel only, (D) 200 µL of sterile distilled water, (E) Patch only, and (F) 200 µL of 0.1% SLS in sterile distilled water. Each treatment will be applied using individual patches, daily for 21 days

Experimental: Part 3 - Each acne patient will apply a thin coat of one or two concentration of GSK1940029 gel or vehicle to acne affected facial/neck skin by hand, once daily for 28 days


Treatment: drugs: 0.3% GSK1940029 gel
200 mg of the gel will be applied to individual patches by using a spatula

Treatment: drugs: 1% GSK1940029 gel
200 mg of the gel will be applied to individual patches by using a spatula

Treatment: drugs: 0.3%/1% vehicle gel only
200 mg of the gel will be applied to individual patches by using a spatula

Other interventions: Sterile distilled water
200 µL of the solution will be applied to individual patches by using a pipette or syringe

Other interventions: 0.5% SLS in sterile distilled water
200 µL of the solution will be applied to individual patches by using a pipette or syringe

Other interventions: 0.1% SLS in sterile distilled water
200 µL of the solution will be applied to individual patches by using a pipette or syringe

Other interventions: Patch only
Only patch will be applied

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary cutaneous irritation scores - The patch/test sites will be evaluated for irritation potential and will be graded using a grading scale based on scales developed by Hill Top Research, Inc and cited by the United States (US) Food and Drug Administration (FDA) in the Draft Guidance for Industry: Skin Irritation and Sensitization Testing of Generic Transdermal Drug Products, December 1999</outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 2, 3 4 and 5 of Part 1</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cumulative cutaneous irritation scores - Visual evaluations of the patch/test sites will be performed for irritation potential approximately 24 hours after each patch application, and will be graded using a grading scale based on scales developed by Hill Top Research, Inc and cited by the US FDA in the Draft Guidance for Industry: Skin Irritation and Sensitization Testing of Generic Transdermal Drug Products, December 1999</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 2 to Day 22 of Part 2</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Facial irritation scores - The Facial Irritation Scoring System will be based on the Draize Scoring System with an additional Sensation of Burning/Stinging category</outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 1, 7, 14, 21, 28, 29 and at FU (Days 35-42) of Part 3</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lanman-Maibach irritation classifications - The derived cumulative irritation scores will be interpreted using the Lanman-Maibach classification system</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 2 to Day 22 of Part 2</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tolerability of GSK1940029 as assessed by Clinical monitoring/observation</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Day 17 of Part 1, Up to Day 36 of Part 2, and Up to Day 42 of Part 3</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tolerability of GSK1940029 as assessed by adverse events (AEs)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Day 17 of Part 1, Up to Day 36 of Part 2, and Up to Day 42 of Part 3</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and tolerability of GSK1940029 as assessed by clinical laboratory tests - Clinical laboratory tests will include hematology, chemistry and urinalysis parameters</outcome>
      <timepoint>Screening, Days 1, 4, and FU (Days 10 to 17) of Part 1. Screening, Days 1, 8, 22, and FU (Days 29 to 36) of Part 2. Screening, Days 1, 7, 14, 21, 29, and FU (Days 35 to 42) of Part 3.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and tolerability of GSK1940029 as assessed by vital signs measurements - Vital signs measurements will include systolic and diastolic blood pressure and heart rate</outcome>
      <timepoint>Screening, Days 1, 2, and FU (Days 10 to 17) of Part 1. Screening, Days 1, 2 and FU (Days 29 to 36) of Part 2. Screening, Days 1, 2 and FU (Days 35 to 42) of Part 3</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and tolerability of GSK1940029 as assessed by clinical monitoring/observation</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to Day 17 of Part 1, Up to Day 36 of Part 2, and Up to Day 42 of Part 3</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ocular tolerability of topical applications of GSK1940029 - Eye examination will be performed. Ocular evaluations will include slit lamp examination with fluorscein, tear film breakup time, visual acuity and ocular surface disease index</outcome>
      <timepoint>Screening, Days 1, 5, and FU (Days 10 to 17) of Part 1. Screening, Days 1, 22, and FU (Days 29 to 36) of Part 2. Screening, Days 1, 7, 14, 21, 29, and FU (Days 35 to 42) of Part 3.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma GSK1940029 pharmacokinetics (PK) - Blood samples for PK analysis of GSK1940029 will be collected. PK parameters will include Area under the concentration-time curve: from time zero (pre-dose) to last time of quantifiable concentration within a subject across all treatments [AUC(0-t)] and from time zero (pre-dose) extrapolated to infinite time [AUC(0-infinity)]; maximum observed concentration (Cmax); time of occurrence of cmax (tmax); and terminal phase half-life (t1/2) as data permit</outcome>
      <timepoint>Part 3 Only - Days 1 and 28: pre-dose, 2, 4, and 8 hours post-dose; Day 2: pre-dose; and Day 29: 24 hour post-Day 28 dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Male or female between 18 and 65 years of age inclusive, at the time of signing the
             informed consent.

          -  Healthy as determined by a responsible and experienced physician, based on a medical
             evaluation including medical history, physical examination, laboratory tests and
             cardiac monitoring for Parts 1 and 2 only.

          -  Moderate/Moderate to Severe acne patients, otherwise healthy as determined by a
             responsible and experienced physician, based on a medical evaluation including medical
             history, physical examination, laboratory tests and cardiac monitoring for Part 3
             only.

          -  A subject with a clinical abnormality or laboratory parameters outside the reference
             range for the population being studied may be included only if the Investigator and
             the GlaxoSmithKline (GSK) Medical Monitor agree that the finding is unlikely to
             introduce additional risk factors and will not interfere with the study procedures.

          -  A female subject is eligible to participate if she is of: Non-childbearing potential
             defined as pre-menopausal females with a documented tubal ligation or hysterectomy
             [for this definition, "documented" refers to the outcome of the
             investigator's/designee's review of the subject's medical history for study
             eligibility, as obtained via a verbal interview with the subject or from the subject's
             medical records]; or postmenopausal defined as 12 months of spontaneous amenorrhea [in
             questionable cases a blood sample with simultaneous follicle stimulating hormone (FSH)
             &gt; 40 milli international units (MIU)/millilitres (mL) and estradiol &lt;40 picograms
             (pg)/mL (&lt;147 picomoles [pmol]/liter [L]) is confirmatory]. Females on hormone
             replacement therapy (HRT) and whose menopausal status is in doubt will not be allowed.

          -  Male subjects with female partners of child-bearing potential must agree to use one of
             the contraception methods. This criterion must be followed from the time of the first
             dose of study medication until after study follow-up visit.

          -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT), alkaline phosphatase and bilirubin &lt;=1.5x upper limit
             of normal (ULN) (isolated bilirubin &gt;1.5xULN is acceptable if bilirubin is
             fractionated and direct bilirubin &lt;35%).

          -  Based on single or averaged assessments, QT duration corrected for heart rate (QTc)
             &lt;450 msec; or QTc &lt;480 msec in subjects with bundle branch block.

          -  Capable of giving written informed consent, which includes compliance with the
             requirements and restrictions listed in the consent form</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  A positive pre-study Hepatitis B surface antigen or positive Hepatitis C antibody
             result within 3 months of screening

          -  Current or chronic history of liver disease, or known hepatic or biliary abnormalities
             (with the exception of Gilbert's syndrome for all study Parts and asymptomatic
             gallstones for Parts 1 and 2 only). Subjects with a history of gall stones,
             asymptomatic gallstones or cholecystectomy will be excluded.

          -  A positive pre-study drug/alcohol screen.

          -  A positive test for Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) antibody.

          -  History of regular alcohol consumption within 6 months of the study defined as: an
             average weekly intake of &gt;14 standard drinks. One standard drink is equivalent to 10
             grams (g) of alcohol: 285 mL of beer, 100 mL of wine or 30 mL of 40% alcohol by volume
             distilled spirits.

          -  History of or current meibomian gland dysfunction or dry eye disease

          -  History or presence of significant skin disorder (such as but not limited to severe
             (extensive) atopic dermatitis, severe eczema, psoriasis or skin cancer) that would in
             any way confound interpretation of the study results, or subjects who present with
             damaged skin including sunburn, moles, uneven skin tones, scar tissue, tattoos, body
             piercings, sunburn, branding or other disfiguration on or near the intended site of
             application which could interfere with the grading. Acne is allowed for Part 3.

          -  History of cutaneous photodisorder, such as photoallergic reaction or polymorphic
             light eruption. History of cold urticaria and reactions to extreme temperatures.

          -  History of allergy to soaps, lotions, cosmetics, tape/adhesives, petrolatum or latex
             or topical drugs of same class as the study medication.

          -  History of sensitivity to any of the study medications, or components thereof or a
             history of drug or other allergy that, in the opinion of the investigator or GSK
             Medical Monitor, contraindicates their participation.

          -  History of sensitivity to heparin or heparin-induced thrombocytopenia.

          -  History of severe, chronic asthma or significant allergies (including food, drug or
             cutaneous allergies). Subjects with the presence or a history of atopy (seasonal
             allergies, allergic rhinitis) or mild (limited) eczema will be allowed to participate
             in the study, although applications at sites with active eczema will not be allowed.

          -  Use of topical medications such as but not limited to retinoids, steroids, and
             transdermal hormone replacement therapies on or near the intended site of application
             within 8 weeks prior to dosing through treatment follow up, for Parts 1 and 2 only or
             within 2 weeks period to dosing for Part 3. Use of other topical preparations such as
             those containing vitamins, supplements or herbal within 2 weeks prior to dosing
             through treatment follow up.

          -  Unable to refrain from the use of topical medications from the initial dose of study
             medication through follow-up.

          -  Foreseeable intensive Ultraviolet (UV) exposure during the study (solar or artificial)
             as follows: subjects must not be exposed to direct sunlight for sun tanning or exposed
             to skin tanning devices (e.g. sunbed) for the duration of the study.

          -  Participation in any patch test for cumulative irritation or sensitization within 4
             weeks preceding the first dose of study medication.

          -  Exposure to more than four new chemical entities within 12 months prior to the first
             dosing day.

          -  The subject has participated in a clinical trial and has received an investigational
             product within the following time period prior to the first dosing day in the current
             study: 30 days, 5 half-lives or twice the duration of the biological effect of the
             investigational product (whichever is longer).

          -  Unable to refrain from the use of prescription or non-prescription drugs, including
             vitamins, herbal and dietary supplements (including St John's Wort) within 7 days (or
             14 days if the drug is a potential enzyme inducer) or 5 half-lives (whichever is
             longer) prior to the first dose of study medication, unless in the opinion of the
             Investigator and GSK Medical Monitor the medication will not interfere with the study
             procedures or compromise subject safety.

          -  Where participation in the study would result in donation of blood or blood products
             in excess of 500 mL within a 56 day period.

          -  Unwillingness or inability to follow the procedures outlined in the protocol.

          -  Subject is mentally or legally incapacitated.

          -  Unable to refrain from consumption of red wine, seville oranges, grapefruit or
             grapefruit juice and/or pummelos, exotic citrus fruits, grapefruit hybrids or fruit
             juices from 7 days prior to the first dose of study medication</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>14/10/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>54</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>10/04/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>GlaxoSmithKline</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The proposed indication for GSK1940029 is topical treatment of acne, the early clinical plan
      will evaluate the irritation potential of GSK1940029 (Study SCD117225 - 3 Part study); and
      safety, tolerability and pharmacokinetics of GSK1940029 (Study SCD117226 - 2 Part study),
      after topical administration on healthy subjects and acne patients. Study SCD117225 will be a
      randomized, single-blind, three part study, to evaluate the primary irritation potential
      (Part 1), cumulative irritation potential (Part 2) of two concentrations of GSK1940029 gel
      applied to the intact skin of healthy subjects, and the facial irritation potential of one or
      two concentrations of GSK1940029 applied to the face of acne patients (Part3). In Part 1 and
      Part 2 the following 6 treatments will be applied using individual patches: (A) 200
      milligrams (mg) of 0.3% GSK1940029 gel, (B) 200 mg of 1% GSK1940029 gel, (C) 200 mg of
      0.3%/1% vehicle gel only (vehicle control), (D) 200 microliters (µL) of sterile distilled
      water (negative irritant control), (E) 200 µL of - 0.5% sodium lauryl sulfate (SLS) in
      sterile distilled water for Part 1/0.1% SLS in sterile distilled water for Part 2 (positive
      irritant control), and (F) Patch only (patch control). Each treatment will be randomized to
      one of six designated locations on either upper arm or other locations, such as the lower or
      upper back, within each subject. The same treatment will be reapplied to the same location on
      subsequent days. Each treatment will be applied daily for 2 days in Part 1, and daily for 21
      days in Part 2. In Part 3, each patient will apply a thin coat of one or two concentration of
      GSK1940029 gel or vehicle to acne affected facial/neck skin by hand, once daily for 28 days.
      Parts within Study SCD117225 and Study SCD117226 will have interdependencies. No significant
      primary irritation signal in Study SCD117225 Part 1 would allow initiation of Study SCD117226
      Part 1 (single dose application). Once safety, tolerability and exposure information are
      determined in Study SCD117226 Part 1, Part 2 of Study SCD117225 may be initiated along with
      Part 2 (14-day repeat dose application). No significant cumulative irritation signal (study
      SCD117225 Part 2) in combination with adequate 14-day safety (study SCD117226 Part 2) would
      allow initiation of Part 3 of Study SCD117225.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01984801</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>GSK Clinical Trials</name>
      <address>GlaxoSmithKline</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>