<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2839">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/07/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/07/2010</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01162720</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Short- Versus Long-duration Tourniquet Use During Total Knee Replacement (TKR)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Feasibility of Tourniquet Use During Cement Fixation Only for TKR Surgery</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>2008-15</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>FairfieldHJCD</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Arthroplasty, Replacement, Knee</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: surgery - Long duration tourniquet
Treatment: surgery - Short duration tourniquet

Experimental: Short duration tourniquet - Patients allocated to this group will have the pneumatic tourniquet applied to the index limb for approximately 20-30 minutes during cement fixation of the prosthesis.

Active Comparator: Long duration tourniquet - Patients randomised to this arm will have the tourniquet applied from commencement of surgery and removed just prior to skin closure.


Treatment: surgery: Long duration tourniquet
Patients randomised to this arm will have the tourniquet applied at the commencement of surgery and removed prior to wound closure.

Treatment: surgery: Short duration tourniquet
Patients assigned to this arm will have the tourniquet applied during cement fixation of the prosthesis only (ie removed just prior to wound closure).

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Oxford Knee score - Oxford knee score is a disease-specific patient perceived knee pain and function survey. It will be collected at baseline (within 2 months of surgery), and then at 10, 26 and 52 weeks post surgery.</outcome>
      <timepoint>10 weeks post surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Donor blood transfusion rate - The use of donor blood transfusion in the intra-operative and acute post-operative (hospitalisation) period will be recorded. Criteria for donor blood transfusion is according to the hospital's restrictive transfusion practices.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within the acute hospitalisation period (from Day 0 (surgery day), to day of discharge)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Knee range of motion (ROM) - Knee ROM will be assessed photographically according to a method developed by some of the investigators. Photographs taken of the patient's knee in end passive flexion and end passive extension will obtained from the patient in supine. ROM will be measured off the photographs.</outcome>
      <timepoint>ROM will be assessed pre-operatively (within 2 months of surgery), on day 4 post surgery, and at 2, 10,26 and 52 weeks post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quadriceps lag - Quadriceps lag will be assessed with the patient in supine. As for ROM, lag will be measured off photographs. It will be calculated as the difference between full passive knee extension and active extension. Passive end extension will be assessed as previously described. Active extension will be obtained in the same position, but with a towel (or suitable object) under the knee. The patient will attempt to raise their heel off the bed. The knee extension range measured when doing this is called the active extension range.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Lag will be assessed on Day 4 post surgery, and at 2, 10, 26 and 52 weeks post surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>timed stair test - Time (sec)to walk up 10 stairs. Time to walk down 10 stairs. Power will also be calculated from the time together with body weight and step height. The test is not strictly a power test (particularly at 2 weeks)as walking aids/rails can be used as required.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at 2, 10,26 and 52 weeks post-surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Knee pain - Knee pain measured using a 10cm visual analogue scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured on Day 4 post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Analgesic consumption - The morphine equivalent will be calculated from both PCA and oral analgesic consumption.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured over course of acute care (summation of day 0 to day of discharge)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  primary, unilateral knee replacement;

          -  capacity to understand the protocol;</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  inability to read English;

          -  current warfarin therapy (or similar);

          -  significant PVD, peripheral arterial disease or diabetes rendering tourniquet use
             undesirable;

          -  evidence of chronic or recent DVT in index limb;

          -  thigh circumference &gt; 100 cm (approximately);

          -  Jehovah's Witness (ie refusal to receive donor blood)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Supportive Care</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/11/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>65</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Terminated</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/12/2010</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Fairfield Hospital - Sydney</hospital>
    <postcode>2176 - Sydney</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Fairfield Hospital, Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To establish whether a short duration of tourniquet application (from cement fixation to
      cement setting)is associated with better patient functional outcomes compared to a long
      duration of tourniquet application (from surgical incision to cement setting).

      It is hypothesised that tourniquet application during cement fixation only (approximately of
      20-30 min duration) will be associated with less pain and impairment than a longer tourniquet
      application (&gt; 45 minutes).</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01162720</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Rama KR, Apsingi S, Poovali S, Jetti A. Timing of tourniquet release in knee arthroplasty. Meta-analysis of randomized, controlled trials. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2007 Apr;89(4):699-705. Review.
Barwell J, Anderson G, Hassan A, Rawlings I. The effects of early tourniquet release during total knee arthroplasty: a prospective randomized double-blind study. J Bone Joint Surg Br. 1997 Mar;79(2):265-8. Erratum in: J Bone Joint Surg Br 1997 Jul;79(4):693. Barwell NJ [corrected to Barwell J].
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jay Dave, MBBS</name>
      <address>Surgeon at Fairfield Hospital</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>