<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4969">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/04/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/04/2015</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02444611</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Trial Investigating the Influence of BCG and Hepatitis B Immunisation at Birth on Neonatal Immune Responses: The Early Life Vaccines and Immunity Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomised, Controlled Trial Investigating the Influence of BCG (Bacillus Calmette-Guérin) and Hepatitis B Immunisation at Birth on Neonatal Immune Responses</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ELVIS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>VAC/01 ELVIS</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Innate Immune Response</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - BCG Vaccine
Treatment: drugs - Hepatitis B Vaccine

Active Comparator: Group 1 - BCG vaccine, 0,05ml intradermally at birth

Active Comparator: Group 2 - BCG vaccine, 0,05ml intradermally at birth Hepatitis B vaccine, 5 micrograms, intramuscularly at birth

Active Comparator: Group 3 - Hepatitis B vaccine, 5 micrograms, intramuscularly at birth

No Intervention: Group 4 - No birth vaccines


Treatment: drugs: BCG Vaccine
intradermal vaccination

Treatment: drugs: Hepatitis B Vaccine
intramuscular vaccination

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cytokine concentrations (pg/ml) in response to in-vitro stimulation with a range of antigens - Four hours after blood samples are collected, they will be stimulated with different concentrations of infective antigens for 20hrs. (eg killed S.aureus, S. pneumoniae, E. Coli, Haemophilus Influenza B, Group B streptococcus, C. albicans), BCG, Hepatitis B sAg). Cytokine expression will be analysed in supernatants by Luminex -based multiplex assays.
The cytokines that will be measured:
Interleukin-1 beta, Interleukin-1ra, Interleukin-6, Interleukin-8, Macrophage/Monocyte Chemoattractant Protein-1(MCP-1), Macrophage Inflammatory Protein (MIP) -1 alpha, MIP-1 beta, Interferon(IFN) gamma, Interleukin-10, Macrophage migration inhibitory factor (MIF), Monokine induced by interferon (MIG), Tumour necrosis factor (TNF) alpha</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 (+-4) days post randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  English speaking parent

          -  Planned travel to a TB (Tuberculosis) endemic country within the infant's first 5
             years of life

          -  An informed consent form must be signed and dated by the infant's mother after the
             nature of the study has been explained and prior to any study assessments/procedures

          -  The infant's mother has screened negative for HIV during this pregnancy

          -  The infant's mother has screened negative for Hepatitis B during this pregnancy

          -  There is no known household contact infected with Hepatitis B

          -  Born no earlier than eight weeks before estimated date of delivery

          -  Birth weight &gt;1500g

          -  Delivered vaginally

          -  Singleton pregnancy</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>3</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Days</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Known or suspected HIV infection

          -  Treatment with corticosteroids or other immunosuppressive therapy, including
             monoclonal antibodies against tumour necrosis factor---alpha (TNF---alpha) (e.g.
             infliximab, etanercept, adalimumab).

          -  Born to a mother treated with bDMARDs (biological Disease- Modifying Anti-Rheumatic
             drugs) (e.g. TNF---alpha blocking monoclonal antibodies) in the 3rd trimester

          -  Congenital cellular immunodeficiencies including specific deficiencies of the
             interferon gamma pathway

          -  Malignancies involving bone marrow or lymphoid systems

          -  Serious underlying illness including severe malnutrition

          -  Medically unstable

          -  Generalised septic skin disease and skin conditions such as eczema, dermatitis and
             psoriasis

          -  Significant febrile illness

        Also excluded are infants with:

          1. A mother who is immunosuppressed;

          2. A mother who has received Intravenous immunoglobulins during her pregnancy

          3. A family history of immunodeficiency;

          4. Consanguineous parents.

          5. Mother who is having a planned Caesarean Section

          6. A home address more than 40 minutes drive from the Mercy hospital for Women and are
             unwilling to return to hospital for infant blood sampling</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Basic Science</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/03/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>185</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/06/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Mercy Hospital for Women - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Murdoch Childrens Research Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Royal Children's Hospital</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Mercy Hospital for Women, Australia</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Neonatal morbidity and mortality from infectious diseases is of global concern. Childhood
      disease-specific immunisation is irrefutably linked to the decline in deaths from these
      targeted infections over the last century. However, neonatal immunisation is limited, in
      part, by the impaired adaptive immune function in this age group.

      There is now an expanding body of evidence for heterologous ('non-specific') effects of
      various vaccines used in childhood. This refers to the immunomodulatory capabilities of
      vaccines to influence immune outcomes beyond the vaccine's specific targeted disease. The
      underlying immunological mechanisms responsible for these effects are incompletely
      understood, but evidence is mounting that the innate immune system is central to these
      observed effects.

      This study is a randomised controlled trial designed to determine the influence of two
      commonly administered neonatal immunisations, BCG and Hepatitis B vaccine, given at birth, on
      the neonatal immune responses to non-specific antigens.

      The investigators will recruit 200 newborns at the Mercy Hospital for Women in Melbourne,
      Australia over a 1-year period. These babies will be allocated randomly to one of 4 groups,
      receiving these 2 vaccines in different combinations, at 2 set time points. (at birth and 1
      week post randomisation) A blood sample will be taken at 1-week post randomisation for in
      vitro immunological analyses.

      This study will improve current understanding of the influence of vaccines on neonatal
      immunity and will help develop strategies exploiting beneficial heterologous ('non-specific')
      effects to improve protection against infection in the very young.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02444611</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Nigel Curtis, MBBS,PHD</name>
      <address>Royal Children's Hospital</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>