<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2344">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/04/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/04/2009</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00891423</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Study of Meropenem Standard 30 Minute Infusion Versus Prolonged 3 Hour Infusion in Intensive Care Unit (ICU) Patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomised Controlled Crossover Pilot Study of Meropenem Standard 30 Minute Infusion Versus Prolonged 3 Hour Infusion in Intensive Care Patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>MERO001</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>ACTRN</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>H2008/03406</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Sepsis</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Meropenem short infusion
Treatment: drugs - Meropenem extended infusion

Active Comparator: Meropenem short infusion - Meropenem 1g infused over 30 minutes
every 8 hours if calculated CrCL greater than or equal to 50 mL/min OR
every 12 hours if calculated CrCL less than 50 mL/min or hemofiltration

Experimental: Meropenem extended infusion - Meropenem 500mg infused over 3 hours
every 8 hours if calculated CrCL greater than or equal to 50 mL/min OR
every 12 hours if calculated CrCL less than 50 mL/min or hemofiltration


Treatment: drugs: Meropenem short infusion


Treatment: drugs: Meropenem extended infusion


</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time above MIC</outcome>
      <timepoint>01/31/2010</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Adult intensive care patients

          -  Predicted duration of treatment 3 days or more</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Predicted duration of treatment less than 3 days

          -  Hypersensitivity to meropenem or other beta-lactams

          -  Consent unable to be obtained by participant or next of kin

          -  Suspected or proven bacterial meningitis</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/04/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>10</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/01/2010</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3084 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Austin Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Meropenem is a powerful antibiotic used in intensive care for people who have very serious
      infections. Meropenem is rapidly removed from the blood by the kidneys and it is very
      expensive. In very ill patients in intensive care, it is uncertain how best to give this
      antibiotic. Studies have suggested that a smaller dose given over a longer period of time,
      results in blood levels of meropenem that are just as good as when a higher dose is given
      over a shorter period of time. This direct comparison has not been tested in intensive care
      patients. It is important to know this because if giving a lesser amount more slowly is just
      as good, then doctors will choose to give meropenem this way. To establish whether this is
      the case, the investigators plan to conduct an initial (pilot) study in ten intensive care
      patients at Austin hospital.

      Adult (age 18 years or older) patients in intensive care who have a serious infection being
      treated with the antibiotic, meropenem for three days or more will be able to participate in
      this study. The decision to start meropenem will be made by the intensive care doctors and
      they will give it in the usual way for 24 hours.

      The investigators will then in a random way (like tossing of a coin), give the participant
      meropenem either in the usual way (1 gram infused over 30 minutes) or give them a smaller
      amount, but over a longer period of time (500 milligrams infused over 3 hours). This will be
      done for 24 hours. They will then receive meropenem in the alternative way for another 24
      hours. After this time the intensive care doctors will decide how meropenem will continue to
      be given.

      Blood levels of meropenem will be measured to see if they are the same when meropenem is
      given in each of the two different ways. During each different way of giving meropenem, 7
      blood samples will need to be taken. Ten mls (or one spoonful) of blood will be required for
      each measurement. Blood levels will be taken through monitoring lines, which will be already
      present.

      Other information will also be collected about the participant during this study. This will
      include their age, gender, height, weight, information about what other medical conditions
      they have and measurements of how well their kidneys are functioning.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00891423</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Paul JOHNSON</name>
      <address>Austin Health</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>