<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2285">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/03/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/03/2009</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00863499</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>International Study to Predict Optimised Treatment in Attention Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>International Study to Predict Optimised Treatment Response to Short or Long Acting Methylphenidate in Children and Adolescents With Attention Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>iSPOT-A</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Attention Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Short Acting Methylphenidate
Treatment: drugs - Long Acting Methylphenidate

Active Comparator: A - Short Acting methylphenidate

Active Comparator: B - Long Acting Methylphenidate

No Intervention: C - Healthy Controls


Treatment: drugs: Short Acting Methylphenidate
Dosage: 5 mg twice daily (before breakfast and lunch) with gradual increments of 5 to 10 mg weekly. Daily dosage above 60 mg is not recommended.

Treatment: drugs: Long Acting Methylphenidate
Dosage: 9 to 20 mg once daily in the morning (with or without food) with gradual increments of 9 to 20 mg weekly. Daily dosage above 60 mg is not recommended.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine whether the genetic-brain-cognition function markers (or combination of markers) 'normalize' with acute drug treatment in ADHD.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine whether markers of acute treatment prediction are also predictive of functional outcome over 6-12 months.</outcome>
      <timepoint>52 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Subjects who have signed an informed consent or assent form where required and/or
             whose parent or legal guardian has provided written informed consent.

          -  Subjects who meet DSM-IV criteria for primary diagnosis of ADHD at study entry, as
             determined by a psychiatrist, physician or clinical psychologist in conjunction with
             the clinical work-up undertaken by trained research assistants, as defined by The Mini
             International Neuropsychiatric Interview for Children and Adolescents (MINI Kid).

          -  Subjects who score at least 6 Inattentive or Hyperactive/impulsive items &gt;1 on the
             Attention Deficit / Hyperactivity Disorder Rating Scale.

          -  Subjects who are stimulant naïve or stimulant free (defined as no stimulant medication
             in the previous 7 days*).

          -  Subjects who are 6-17 years of age (with an emphasis to enrol at least a third of the
             subjects who are = 13 years of age).

          -  Subjects who are fluent and literate in English (and/or Dutch in The Netherlands).

               -  coming off the stimulant medication for 7 days may place the participant at
                  increased risk, therefore, the participant may have this washout period reduced
                  to that defined in the drug package insert or 5 times the medication half life.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>17</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Known contra-indication or intolerance to the use of methylphenidate as defined in the
             product package insert (including previous treatment failure at the highest
             recommended dose).

          -  Pregnancy and females of child bearing potential who are not using a form of
             contraception and are at risk of becoming pregnant during the study.

          -  Known medical condition, disease or neurological disorder which might, in the opinion
             of investigator/s, interfere with the assessments to be made in the study or put ADHD
             patients at increased risk when exposed to optimal doses of the drug treatment. For
             example, a diagnosis of epilepsy would exclude a patient from this trial.

          -  History of physical brain injury or blow to the head that resulted in loss of
             consciousness for at least 10 minutes or at least 5minutes within the last two years.
             Prior treatment with methylphenidate or any other stimulant medication in the past 7
             days.

          -  Known past or present substance dependence, including alcohol, as determined by The
             Mini International Neuropsychiatric Interview for Children and Adolescents (MINI Kid).

          -  Participation in an investigational study within four months of the baseline visit in
             which subjects have received an experimental drug/device that could affect the primary
             end points of this study.

          -  Use of any psychological or counselling therapy or CNS medication that cannot be
             washed out prior to participation or use of any psychological or counselling therapy
             between the baseline and week 6 (or Early Termination) visits.

          -  Subjects who, in the opinion of the investigator, have a severe impediment to vision,
             hearing and/or hand movement, which is likely to interfere with their ability to
             complete the testing batteries.

          -  Subjects who, in the opinion of the investigator, are unable and/or unlikely to
             comprehend and follow the study procedures and instructions.

          -  Presence of any other co-morbid primary DSM IV disorder.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Health Services Research</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/10/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1344</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/07/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Brain Dynamics Centre - Westmead</hospital>
    <postcode>2145 - Westmead</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Jersey</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Gelderland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>BRC Operations Pty. Ltd.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of the iSPOT-A study is to:

        1. identify brain, genetic and cognitive markers of Attention Deficit/Hyperactivity
           Disorder, and

        2. identify brain, genetic and cognitive markers that predict treatment response to
           short-acting methylphenidate in children and adolescents diagnosed with Attention
           Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00863499</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Barbara A. Cohen, PhD</name>
      <address>Center for Healing the Human Spirit</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>