<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2156">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/10/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/10/2008</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00781261</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Osteonecrosis of the Hip and Bisphosphonate Treatment</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomised Controlled Trial of Bisphosphonate Therapy in Osteonecrosis of the Hip</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>BONES</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>570989</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Osteonecrosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Zoledronic Acid
Treatment: drugs - Placebo

Placebo Comparator: Control - Subjects in the control group will receive a placebo drug for a 1 year period

Active Comparator: Zoledronic Acid - Subjects in this intervention group will be given 5mg Zoledronic acid as a single injection


Treatment: drugs: Zoledronic Acid
Subjects in the intervention group B will be given 5mg Zoledronic acid as a single injection.

Treatment: drugs: Placebo
Subjects in the control group will receive a placebo drug for a similar period

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>reducing pain and disability in the hip</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>reducing progression to femoral head collapse and the need for surgical intervention</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. aged between 18-90 years,

          2. symptoms of pain and disability in at least one hip joint, or

          3. positive MRI findings stage I or II on the ARCO classification</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>90</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. previous hip joint surgery on the affected hip

          2. severe pain and disability at rest if treating clinician has recommended surgery

          3. radiographic or MRI findings suggestive for stage III and IV on the ARCO
             classification

          4. any iv bisphosphonate within the prior 2 years or any prior use of bisphosphonate
             preparations, except according to the washout schedule:

               -  2 years (if use &gt; 48 weeks),

               -  1 year (if used &gt; 8 weeks but &lt; 48 weeks)

               -  6 months (if used &gt; 2 weeks but &lt; 8 weeks)

               -  2 months (if used &lt; 2 weeks)

          5. active primary hyperparathyroidism

          6. hypothyroidism, not appropriately controlled with long-term thyroxine therapy

          7. history of iritis or uveitis, except due to trauma, and resolved for &gt; 2 years prior
             to study

          8. self-reported history of diabetic nephropathy or retinopathy (if diabetic, Hb A1c &gt;
             10%)

          9. urine dipstick greater than or equal to 2+ protein at screening

         10. AST or ALT greater than twice the upper limit of normal and/or alkaline phosphatase
             greater than twice the upper limit of normal

         11. serum calcium &gt; 2.75 mmol/L (11.0 mg/dL) or &lt; 2.00 mmol/L (8.0 mg/dL)

         12. serum 25-hydroxyvitamin D concentrations &lt; 15 ng/L m) baseline renal insufficiency
             (calculated creatinine clearance less than 40 mL/min and serum creatinine greater than
             175 mol/L) at V1

         13. a history of invasive malignancy of any organ system, treated or untreated, in the
             past five years; excluding, basal cell or squamous cell carcinoma of the skin, colonic
             polyps with non-invasive malignancy which have been removed, ductal carcinoma in-situ
             (DCIS), and carcinoma in-situ (CIS) of the uterine cervix

         14. any candidate patient with severe dental problems or current dental infections and/or
             any candidate patient with recent or impending dental surgery within three months of
             dosing

         15. women of childbearing potential not using the contraception method(s) specified in
             this study (specify), as well as women who are breastfeeding</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2>The people administering the treatment/s</masking2>
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/08/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Unknown status</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/12/2013</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,SA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal North Shore Hospital, Department of Rheumatology - Sydney</hospital>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Brisbane</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane and Womens Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>Cabrini Hospital - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>2065 - Sydney</postcode>
    <postcode>4102 - Brisbane</postcode>
    <postcode>4029 - Herston</postcode>
    <postcode>5011 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>3144 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Novartis</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Osteonecrosis of the hip is an important cause of musculoskeletal disability and finding
      therapeutic solutions has proven to be challenging. Osteonecrosis means death of bone which
      can occur from the loss of the blood supply or some other means. Although any age group may
      develop osteonecrosis, most patients are between 20 and 50 years old. The most common risk
      factor is a history of high steroid treatment for some medical condition. The next most
      common associated condition is a history of high alcohol use. There are some cases of
      osteonecrosis that occur in patients that are otherwise completely healthy with no detectable
      risk factors.

      In the earliest stage of the disease, x-rays appear normal and the diagnosis is made using
      MRI. The advanced stages of osteonecrosis begin when the dead bone starts to fail
      mechanically through a process of microfractures of the bone. As the disease progresses, the
      surface begins to collapse until, finally the integrity of the joint is destroyed. A wide
      range of surgical treatments with variable success rates have been proposed for the treatment
      of the osteonecrosis to preserve joint integrity, including core decompression, whereby the
      venous hypertension that ensues is lessened and revascularisation may be induced leading to
      bone repair. Nonsurgical treatment options are limited and usually result in a poor
      prognosis. Early stage disease can be treated with protected weight bearing and
      physiotherapy, however some studies have shown protected weight bearing to be associated with
      a greater than 85% rate of femoral head collapse. Unfortunately most studies indicate that
      the risk for disease progression is greater with nonsurgical treatment than with surgical
      intervention. There are no established pharmaceuticals for the prevention of treatment of
      osteonecrosis. Evidence is increasing that the nitrogen containing bisphosphonates may be
      beneficial in the treatment of osteonecrosis. One bisphosphonates (alendronate) has been
      evaluated in 60 patients diagnosed with osteonecrosis of the hip. Recent clinical studies
      have shown very promising results. All patients had symptomatic improvement after one year.
      Although the follow up time ranged from 3 months to 5 years, only 6 patients progressed to
      the point of needing surgery.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00781261</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Philip Sambrook, Prof</name>
      <address>University of Sydney</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Monique Macara</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+61294631888</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>monique.macara@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>