<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5506">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/06/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/06/2008</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00697424</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparison of Breathing Events Detected by the SleepStyle 200 Auto Continuous Positive Airway Pressure (CPAP) Device to Attended Polysomnography</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Investigation of Methods to Detect Respiratory Irregularities in Obstructive Sleep Apnea (OSA)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>AKY/03/07/166</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>FPHHC254a</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Sleep Apnea, Obstructive</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sleep apnoea</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - SleepStyle 200 Auto Series CPAP Humidifier

Experimental: 1 - All subjects will be placed on continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) therapy during a full night sleep study or polysomnography (PSG). The subjects will spend 2 hours on sub-therapeutic CPAP 4 cmH2O of pressure and the remainder on there therapeutic pressure. Values reported on the device will be compared to scored values from manual scoring of the sleep study.


Treatment: devices: SleepStyle 200 Auto Series CPAP Humidifier
The device will record on internal software perceived sleep disordered breathing events. Events will also be scored manually on the polysomnography (PSG. Results will then be compared.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Apnea Hypopnea Index</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of the sleep study.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Respiratory Disturbance Index (RDI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of the sleep study (PSG)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Apnea Hypopnea Index (AHI) &gt;15 from diagnostic night

          -  =18 years of age</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Contraindicated for CPAP use</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/05/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/11/2008</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Fisher and Paykel Healthcare</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Obstructive Sleep Apnoea (OSA) is a common sleep-breathing disorder affecting around 2-4% of
      the population and is characterised by loud snoring, periodic collapse of the upper airway
      particular to sleep, sleep fragmentation, and sometimes daytime sleepiness. Health
      consequences include impaired cognitive functioning, quality of life, mood, and increased
      cardiovascular disease risk. Epidemiological studies have demonstrated that increased
      morbidity and mortality in a dose response manner with increasing severity of sleep
      disordered breathing.

      The standard treatment for OSA is nasal Continuous Positive Airway Pressure (CPAP), which
      consists of pressurized air applied to the nose via a mask. Generally a single, optimal
      pressure is prescribed for a patient based on a full night or partial night study during
      which the pressure is adjusted by a technician until all sleep disordered breathing (SDB)
      events are abolished. Despite therapy efficacy, compliance to CPAP therapy is sub-optimal.

      Due to low compliance it has become common for healthcare providers to follow up subject
      therapy efficacy through reporting software inherent in many current CPAP devices. Healthcare
      providers can use this reported data to make appropriate treatment decisions. For this reason
      the data needs to be accurate. The SleepStyle 200 Auto Series CPAP humidifier is an auto
      adjusting CPAP which stores comprehensive compliance data. The aim of this study is to
      compare the reliability of the SleepStyle 200 Auto Series CPAP data to laboratory-based PSG
      in detecting sleep disordered breathing.

      Hypothesis: The SleepStyle 200 Auto Series reporting features accurately detects indices of
      sleep disordered breathing.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00697424</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jessica R Hayward, Msc</name>
      <address>Fisher &amp; Paykel Healthcare</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>