<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6067">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02892058</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Self-assessment of Flare in Osteoarthritis of Lower Limbs</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Development of a Tool for the Self-assessment of Flare in Patients With Osteoarthritis of Lower Limbs</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>FLARE-OA</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>FLARE-OA</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Osteoarthritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions />
    <comparator />
    <control />
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ability of a FLARE-OA self-questionnaire to detect flare episodes in knee or hip osteoarthritis - patient-reported outcome questionnaire for the self-assessment of flare in osteoarthritis. The questionnaire will be developed during the first part of the study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in ability of a FLARE-OA self-questionnaire to detect flare episodes in knee or hip osteoarthritis during a 6 months period - patient-reported outcome questionnaire for the self-assessment of flare in osteoarthritis. The questionnaire will be developed during the first part of the study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 3 and 6 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evolution of the quality of life during a 6 months period with the standardized OAKHQOL questionnaire - Osteoarthritis knee and hip quality of life questionnaire (OAKHQOL) self-assessment questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>up to 3 and 6 month</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evolution of the functional limitation related to knee osteoarthritis during a 6 months period with the standardized KOOS questionnaire - Knee injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS) patient questionnaire. Standardized answer options are given (5 Likert boxes) and each question is assigned a score from 0 to 4.</outcome>
      <timepoint>up to 3 and 6 month</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evolution of the functional limitation related to hip osteoarthritis during a 6 months period with the standardized HOOS questionnaire - Hip disability and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (HOOS) patient questionnaire. Standardized answer options are given (5 Likert boxes) and each question gets a score from 0 to 4.</outcome>
      <timepoint>up to 3 and 6 month</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain intensity measure - Self-reported pain intensity using a numerical rating scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>up to 3 and 6 month</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  with clinical and radiological hip or knee OA confirmed by a physician,

          -  whatever their status regarding flare of OA. The intention of the Flare-OA tool is not
             to detect current flare only, but also a flare that may have occurred before the
             encounter with the health care professional. Therefore patient will not be selected on
             flare, and patients with flare will not be excluded.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>45</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Patients who never experienced nor currently report having a flare of OA

          -  Patients with both hip and knee OA</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/04/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>600</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/06/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>Institute of Bone and Joint Research - University of Sydney - Sydney</hospital>
    <postcode> - Sydney</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Toronto</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Besançon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Brest</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Dijon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Fort de France</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Grenoble</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Nantes</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Paris</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Poitiers</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Vandoeuvre-les-Nancy</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Central Hospital, Nancy, France</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The need for a tool to measure flare in lower limb osteoarthritis (OA of the hip and knee) is
      justified by the opportunities for development of clinical trials targeting hip and knee OA
      long-term treatment (slow acting drug, disease modifying drug) and short-term treatment of
      symptoms. Such treatments are currently under development and will likely bring important
      changes in the treatment of patients. The development of a Flare-OA tool would be essential
      to capture the occurrence of flare, and to implement and adapt treatment strategies.

      This project was elaborated with the aims to:

        1. define the construct through development of a conceptual framework

        2. use the conceptual framework to inform the development of a patient-reported outcome
           measure, Flare-OA tool, for people with OA

        3. evaluate the psychometric properties of the new measure using the OMERACT (Outcome
           Measures in Rheumatology) filter 2.0 and Rasch measurement methods.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02892058</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Francis GUILLEMIN</name>
      <address>CHRU NANCY, CIC 1433 Epidémiologie Clinique</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>