<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4413">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/03/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/03/2012</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01550484</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Trial of 18F-AV-133 Positron Emission Tomography (PET) Imaging to Differentiate Subjects With Parkinson's Disease (PD) From Other Movement Disorders</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An Open Label, Multicenter Study, Evaluating the Safety and Efficacy of 18F-AV-133 PET Imaging to Identify Subjects With Dopaminergic Degeneration Among Subjects Presenting to a Movement Disorders Specialty Clinic With an Uncertain Diagnosis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>18F-AV-133-B04</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Parkinson's Disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Primary Parkinsonism</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Lewy Body Parkinson's Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Parkinson's disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - 18F-AV-133

Treatment: drugs: 18F-AV-133
222 MBq (6 mCi)

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sensitivity of visual read of AV-133 PET scan vs. standard of truth - Sensitivity will be calculated as the percent of true positives which are correctly identified
An expert, consensus diagnosis of PD performed by a panel of movement disorders specialists will be used as the standard of truth.</outcome>
      <timepoint>18 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Specificity of visual read of AV-133 PET scan vs. standard of truth - Specificity will be calculated as the percent of true negatives which are correctly identified.
An expert, consensus diagnosis of PD performed by a panel of movement disorders specialists will be used as the standard of truth.</outcome>
      <timepoint>18 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Inter-rater reliability of the visual read - Fleiss' kappa</outcome>
      <timepoint>18 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intra-rater reliability of the visual read - Intra-class kappa</outcome>
      <timepoint>18 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Probability of progressive motor skill impairment - Compare rates of progressive impairment using PD rating scale in subjects with positive AV-133 PET scan vs. progressive impairment in subjects with negative AV-133 PET scan</outcome>
      <timepoint>18 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Males or females = 40 years of age;

          -  Presenting (within the last 3 months) for an initial evaluation to a movement
             disorders specialist with signs or symptoms suggestive of a movement disorder;

          -  The subject's signs or symptoms were previously evaluated by a physician who was not a
             movement disorders specialist during the previous six months;

          -  Absence of an established clinical movement disorder diagnosis;

          -  Symptoms mild in intensity, this includes Hoehn &amp; Yahr = 2 (Exceptions are allowed for
             subjects who meet criteria for Hoehn &amp; Yahr stage 3 due to early onset of postural
             instability and/or gait impairment out of proportion to his/her other Parkinson signs
             and symptoms);

          -  Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA) score = 22;

          -  Can tolerate imaging visit procedures; and

          -  Provide written informed consent prior to study entry.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Have been referred to the movement disorders clinic primarily for the purpose of
             disease management (no diagnostic uncertainty exists on the part of the non-specialist
             or referring physician);

          -  Have a previous movement disorder diagnosis given by a movement disorders specialist
             prior to the time of enrollment;

          -  Have received a total of more than 90 days treatment with dopaminergic medications,
             including direct dopamine agonists or precursors (levodopa) or have received a total
             of more than 180 days treatment with MAO-B inhibitors, amantadine, anticholinergics or
             primidone or beta-blockers prescribed for treatment of tremor or signs of
             parkinsonism;

          -  Have had a sustained and clinically meaningful response to anti-parkinsonian
             medications;

          -  Are currently taking or have taken MAO-B inhibitors in the past 4 weeks;

          -  Have a known CNS structural lesion such as stroke or tumor that likely accounts for
             their symptoms;

          -  Have clinically meaningful cognitive impairment or dementia (mild cognitive problems
             as might be expected in the earliest stages of PD are not exclusionary);

          -  Have current clinically significant cardiovascular disease or clinically important
             abnormalities on screening ECG (including but not limited to QTc &gt; 450 msec);

          -  Are currently taking medications that are known to cause QT-prolongation;

          -  Are currently taking medications with narrow therapeutic windows (e.g. warfarin or
             other anticoagulant therapies);

          -  Are currently taking tetrabenazine (TBZ), amphetamine type drugs;

          -  Have a current clinically significant endocrine or metabolic disease, pulmonary, renal
             or hepatic impairment, or cancer (excluding localized basal cell carcinoma and in situ
             prostate cancer) that would interfere with completion of the study;

          -  Have a recent history (within the past year) of alcohol or substance abuse or
             dependence;

          -  Are females of childbearing potential who are not surgically sterile, not refraining
             from sexual activity or not using reliable contraception. Females must not be pregnant
             (negative serum beta-hCG at the time of screening and negative urine beta-hCG on the
             day of imaging), must not be breastfeeding at screening, must avoid becoming pregnant
             and use adequate contraceptive methods for 14 days prior to and 24 hours after
             administration of 18F-AV-133 for injection;

          -  Have had prior intracranial surgery; and

          -  Are receiving any investigational medications, or have participated in a trial with
             investigational medications within the last 30 days.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/04/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>170</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/03/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Research Site - Sydney</hospital>
    <postcode>2109 - Sydney</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Arizona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Connecticut</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Kansas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Louisiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Maryland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Massachusetts</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Missouri</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Nevada</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Pennsylvania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Rhode Island</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Avid Radiopharmaceuticals</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to determine whether 18F-AV-133 PET scans can be used to
      differentiate subjects with Parkinson's Disease from other movement disorders.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01550484</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Chief Medical Officer</name>
      <address>Avid Radiopharmaceuticals</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>