<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6707">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/09/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/09/2017</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT03283826</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Phase 1 Study to Evaluate the Safety of ATA188 in Subjects With Progressive and Relapsing-Remitting Multiple Sclerosis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An Open-Label Phase 1 Study to Evaluate the Safety of ATA188 in Subjects With Progressive and Relapsing-Remitting Multiple Sclerosis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>ATA188-MS-101</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Relapsing Remitting Multiple Sclerosis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Primary Progressive Multiple Sclerosis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Secondary Progressive Multiple Sclerosis</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - ATA188

Experimental: Progressive or RRMS - Adult subjects with either progressive forms of MS (Population A) or with Relapsing Remitting Multiple Sclerosis (Population B) will be enrolled. Subjects will receive 2 cycles of treatment with each cycle consisting of a 15-day treatment period (with 3 infusions, each given approximately 7 days apart, on Days 1, 8 [±2 days], and 15 [±2 days]). After the third infusion of Cycle 1, subjects will enter a 20-day observation period with weekly visits, and after the third infusion of Cycle 2, subjects will enter a follow-up period with 11 monthly (every 28 ±5 days) visits. Together, subjects will be observed for at least 1 year after the first dose of ATA188.


Treatment: drugs: ATA188
Allogeneic EBV-directed T-cell therapy

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of adverse events and clinically significant changes in laboratory tests, ECGs, and vital signs - Safety and tolerability</outcome>
      <timepoint>Approximately 2 months per subject</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Recommended Phase 2 dose of ATA188 monotherapy - Dose finding</outcome>
      <timepoint>Approximately 1 year</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in the number of Gd-enhancing and new or enlarging T2 lesions on brain MRI scans for subjects with RRMS - Changes in MRI activity</outcome>
      <timepoint>Approximately 9 months per subject</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in expanded disability status scale (EDSS) score - Change in disability</outcome>
      <timepoint>Approximately 9 months per subject</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in annualized relapse rate (ARR) for subjects with RRMS - Change in clinical disease activity</outcome>
      <timepoint>Approximately 9 months per subject</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>A subject will be considered eligible to participate in this study if all of the following
        are satisfied:

          1. History of MS, with progressive forms of MS or RRMS as defined by the 2010 Revised
             McDonald criteria [53] for the diagnosis of MS.

               1. Subjects with progressive forms of MS must have no new Gd-enhancing lesions
                  within 12 months of providing informed consent

               2. Subjects with RRMS must have failed a health authority approved treatment

          2. Positive EBV serology

          3. Availability of appropriate partially HLA-matched and restricted ATA188 cell product

          4. Males and females of the following ages:

               1. 18 to 65 years of age for subjects with progressive forms of MS

               2. 18 to 45 years of age for subjects with RRMS

          5. EDSS scores as follows:

               1. 3.0 to 6.5 for subjects with progressive forms of MS

               2. 2.0 to 5.5 for subjects with RRMS

          6. Willing and able to provide written informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>A subject will not be eligible to participate in the study if any of the following criteria
        are met:

          1. Active clinical relapse between providing informed consent and enrollment (ie, date of
             the first dose of ATA188)

          2. Concurrent serious uncontrolled or unresolved medical condition, such as infection,
             limiting protocol compliance or exposing the subject to unacceptable risk

          3. Positive serology and/or nucleic acid testing (NAT) for human immunodeficiency virus
             (HIV)

          4. Serology and/or NAT indicating active hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection or carrier
             status for HBV (Note: A positive serology for HBV indicating a previous but cleared
             infection with HBV is not an exclusion criterion)

          5. Serology and/or NAT indicating active hepatitis C virus (HCV) infection

          6. Positive serology for syphilis or human T cell lymphotrophic virus I/II (HTLV)

          7. Significant non-malignant disease (eg, severe cardiac or respiratory dysfunction)

          8. Uncontrolled psychosis, uncontrolled depression or suicide risk, substance dependence,
             or any other psychiatric condition that may compromise the ability to participate in
             this trial

          9. Clinically significant abnormalities of full blood count, renal function, or hepatic
             function:

               -  Elevated liver function tests, including total bilirubin (TBILI) &gt; 1.5× the upper
                  limit of normal (ULN; unless subject has documented Gilbert's disease), aspartate
                  aminotransferase (AST) or alanine aminotransferase (ALT) &gt; 3.0×ULN

               -  Subjects with both a creatinine &gt; 1.5×ULN and an estimated creatinine clearance
                  of &lt; 60 mL/min (using the Cockcroft-Gault equation)

               -  Hemoglobin &lt; 10 g/dL; platelet &lt; 100×109/L; absolute neutrophil count &lt; 1.5×109/L

         10. Any contraindication to MRI and/or Gd, eg, any object that is reactive to strong
             static magnetic, pulsed-gradient fields including any metallic fragments or foreign
             body (eg, aneurysm clip(s), pacemakers, electronic implants, shunts)

         11. Prior cancers, except successfully treated non-melanoma skin cancer or carcinoma in
             situ of the cervix, with a = 5% chance of recurrence within 12 months of providing
             informed consent

         12. Immunomodulatory therapy as follows:

               1. Any previous treatment with a B-cell depleting agent

               2. Any previous treatment with alemtuzumab

               3. Treatment with corticosteroids within 2 weeks of providing informed
                  consentTreatment with glatiramer acetate or interferon (IFN)ß within 4 weeks of
                  providing informed consent

               4. Treatment with dimethyl fumarate within 4 weeks of providing informed consent

               5. Treatment with fingolimod within 2 months of providing informed consent

               6. Treatment with natalizumab, methotrexate, azathioprine, or cyclosporine within 6
                  months of providing informed consent

               7. Treatment with teriflunomide within 12 months of providing informed consent
                  unless patient has completed an accelerated clearance with cholestyramine

               8. Treatment with mitoxantrone, cyclophosphamide, cladribine, rituximab or any other
                  immunosuppressant or cytotoxic therapy (other than steroids) within 12 months of
                  providing informed consent, or determined by the treating physician to have
                  residual immune suppression from these treatments

         13. Antithymocyte globulin or similar anti-T cell antibody therapy = 4 weeks of providing
             informed consent

         14. Female of childbearing potential unwilling to use a highly effective method of
             contraception (ie, one that results in pregnancy less than 1% per year when used
             consistently and correctly), eg, implants, injectables, combined oral contraceptives,
             some intrauterine contraceptive devices, sexual abstinence, or a vasectomized partner,
             and/or unwilling to refrain from donating eggs while undergoing treatment with ATA188
             and for 3 months after the last dose OR Men with a female partner of childbearing
             potential unwilling to use a highly effective contraceptive measure and/or unwilling
             to refrain from donating sperm while undergoing treatment with ATA188 and for 3 months
             after the last dose

         15. Women who are breastfeeding

         16. Pregnancy

         17. Inability to comply with study procedures

         18. Previous treatment with EBV T cell therapy</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>19/10/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/03/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <postcode>4029 - Herston</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Atara Biotherapeutics</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a multicenter, open-label, two-population, single-arm study with a sequential
      dose-escalation and dose-expansion in adult subjects with progressive forms of multiple
      sclerosis (MS) and an in adult subjects with relapsed remitting multiple sclerosis (RRMS).</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03283826</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Pender MP, Csurhes PA, Smith C, Beagley L, Hooper KD, Raj M, Coulthard A, Burrows SR, Khanna R. Epstein-Barr virus-specific adoptive immunotherapy for progressive multiple sclerosis. Mult Scler. 2014 Oct;20(11):1541-4. doi: 10.1177/1352458514521888. Epub 2014 Feb 3.
Pender MP, Csurhes PA, Burrows JM, Burrows SR. Defective T-cell control of Epstein-Barr virus infection in multiple sclerosis. Clin Transl Immunology. 2017 Jan 20;6(1):e126. doi: 10.1038/cti.2016.87. eCollection 2017 Jan. Erratum in: Clin Transl Immunology. 2017 Jun 16;6(6):e147.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Tap Maniar, MD</name>
      <address>Atara Biotherapeutics</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Atara Biotherapeutics</name>
      <address />
      <phone>(805) 603-4856</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>clinicaltrials@atarabio.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>