<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6196">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/11/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/11/2016</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02975947</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of Warmed Humidified CO2 on Peritoneum During Laparotomy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of Intraoperative Humidified CO2 Insufflation in Open Laparotomy Colorectal Surgery Patients: a Randomized Controlled Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>HREC/12/CRGH/196</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Peritoneal Inflammation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Peritoneum; Injury</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other inflammatory or immune system disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - Humidified, warmed CO2 insufflation of open peritoneum using Fisher &amp; Paykel's HUMIGARD (Fisher &amp; Paykel Healthcare Ltd, Auckland, New Zealand)
Treatment: devices - Standard heating

Active Comparator: Control Group - Standard intraoperative warming measures including heated blankets, heating with forced warmed air, warming of fluids, and insulation of limbs and head.

Experimental: Study Group - The study group will receive warmed (37°C), humidified (98% RH) carbon dioxide delivered into the open peritoneal cavity.


Treatment: devices: Humidified, warmed CO2 insufflation of open peritoneum using Fisher &amp; Paykel's HUMIGARD (Fisher &amp; Paykel Healthcare Ltd, Auckland, New Zealand)
The study group will receive warmed (37°C), humidified (98% RH) carbon dioxide into the open peritoneal cavity using the Fisher &amp; Paykel's HUMIGARD system (Fisher &amp; Paykel Healthcare Ltd, Auckland, New Zealand). This will create a local atmosphere of 100% carbon dioxide (warmed, humidified) in the open peritoneal cavity.

Treatment: devices: Standard heating
Standard intraoperative warming measures including heated blankets, heating with forced warmed air, warming of fluids, and insulation of limbs and head

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Inflammatory cytokine level in the peritoneal biopsy samples - Peritoneal samples will be taken when the peritoneal cavity is being opened (at beginning of operation), and also when the peritoneal cavity is being closed (at end of the operation). The change in the level of inflammatory cytokines in between these two time points will be measured</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the moment of time when: (1) peritoneal cavity is being opened, (2) when peritoneal cavity is being closed (expected average of 2 hours after peritoneal cavity is first opened)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intraoperative temperature at 30 minutes from start of operation - Temperature readings during the operation will be taken. Both core body temperature (esophageal) and intraperitoneal temperature will be measured.</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 minutes from start of operation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intraoperative temperature at 60 minutes from start of operation - Temperature readings during the operation will be taken. Both core body temperature (esophageal) and intraperitoneal temperature will be measured.</outcome>
      <timepoint>60 minutes from start of operation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postoperative Analgesia requirement for pain - Postoperative pain as measured by MEDD (Morphine Equivalent Daily Dose)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time from when the patient is moved out of operating theater to when the patient is no longer an inpatient in the hospital ward (discharged), with an expected average of 1 week</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of in-patient hospital stay - number of days patient stayed postoperatively in hospital</outcome>
      <timepoint>duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 1 week</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anastomotic leaks - The occurrence of anastomotic leak in the 6 months after the surgery</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Adults above age 18.

          -  Elective patients.

          -  Pathologies: colorectal carcinoma, polyposis syndromes, diverticular diseases,
             prolapses, and patients with inflammatory bowel disease undergoing elective resection.

          -  For colorectal carcinoma, all patients whether they are having curative or palliative
             surgery will be included.

          -  Patients undergoing open elective colectomy, with or without stoma formation/ bowel
             anastomosis.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Patients undergoing acute surgery (emergency surgery).

          -  Patients undergoing Laparoscopic colectomy (multiport, single incision and also hand
             assisted) as all these patients receive heated humidified CO2.

          -  For COPD patients, the exclusion criteria would be patients: (1) On home oxygen, (2)
             Type 2 respiratory failure (CO2 retainers) (3) FEV1&lt;1L, or FEV1/FVC &lt;50% of predicted</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/08/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>40</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/06/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Concord Repatriation General Hospital - Sydney</hospital>
    <postcode>2138 - Sydney</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Concord Repatriation General Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The operating theatre is deliberately made to be cold and dry to prevent bacteria from
      growing. The problem with this is that during open abdominal surgery, the intestine and the
      overlying peritoneum is exposed to cold dry air. Surgeons try to stop the bowel/peritoneum
      from drying by applying warmed saline packs periodically to the bowel. However, this is not
      always possible. Sometimes, the surgeon has to perform an important component of the
      procedure (attach bowel/blood vessels together etc) and the bowel/peritoneum visibly dries.
      When bowel/peritoneum dries damage occurs, inducing inflammation. Inflamed bowel/peritoneum
      causes the bowel to stick together and form adhesions. Bowel adhesions can cause bowel
      obstruction. This vicious cycle is repeated when the patient undergoes repetitive open
      abdominal operations.

      This study aimed to be the first human study to:

        1. Demonstrate that peritoneal inflammation occurs during open abdominal surgery and also
           to demonstrate that pro-inflammatory cells (polymorphs, macrophages) are activated
           during the progress of the operation. This study aims to show that mRNA(using Q-PCR) is
           increased for pro-inflammatory cytokines. This study also aim to show that
           proinflammatory cytokines (Interleukin(IL)-1,2,6,9,10, and TNF by ELISA/confirmed using
           Western Blotting) are elevated during the course of the operation.

        2. Demonstrate that the mechanism of bowel/peritoneal inflammation is causally related to
           the bowel/peritoneum drying (dessication).

      This study will attempt to prove this by using humidified, warmed carbon dioxide gas which
      will warm and moisten the peritoneum/bowel. It is proposed that this will arrest the
      peritoneal injury and the inflammation. The investigators will attain peritoneal samples
      during open colorectal operations. The investigators will obtain samples at the beginning and
      end of the operation. This study design is a randomized controlled trial, where half the
      patients will receive humidified, warmed carbon dioxide gas during surgery, and the other
      half will get standard open surgery without carbon dioxide. 40 patients will be recruited in
      this study. Half (20) will get CO2, and other half (20) will get standard open surgery.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02975947</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>