<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3915">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/04/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/04/2013</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01849094</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluating the Safety, Pharmacokinetics and Haemodynamic Effect of a Slow Release Oral Formulation of Milrinone</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle />
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>DK-MIL-1</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Healthy</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Heart Failure</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Milrinone 6mg
Treatment: drugs - milrinone 10mg ER
Treatment: drugs - milrinone 14mg

Experimental: Milrinone 6mg - single oral dose of 6mg ER milrinone tablet (Part A).
1. single intravenous infusion of milrinone (per Alfred Hospital protocol. 50ug/kg loading dose over 15 mins followed by infusion at 0.375 ug/kg/min for 6 hrs) - Part B.

Active Comparator: Milrinone 10mg ER - single oral dose of 10 mg ER milrinone tablet (Part A) single oral dose of 10 mg ER milrinone tablet (Part B)

Active Comparator: Milrinone 14mg - single oral dose of 14 mg ER milrinone tablet (Part A) single dose of 14 mg ER milrinone tablet 4. single oral dose of 18 mg ER milrinone tablet (if the group average plasma milrinone levels is less than 150 ug/L with 15 mg dose) - (Part B)


Treatment: drugs: Milrinone 6mg
Administration of study medications, PK sampling If Part B - add on 6 hour haemodynamic invasive measurements

Treatment: drugs: milrinone 10mg ER
Administration of study medications, PK sampling If Part B - add on 6 hour haemodynamic invasive measurements

Treatment: drugs: milrinone 14mg
Administration of study medications, PK sampling If Part B - add on 6 hour haemodynamic invasive measurements

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetic profile - to demonstrate stable plasma levels - Laboratory Analysis: Plasma milrinone concentration</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 0.25, 0.5, 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12 and 24 hours</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(Heart Failure cohort) - to demonstrate evidence of haemodynamic benefit - ECG and Blood pressure and HR Monitoring Swan Ganz insertion for haemodynamic measurements (RA volume , RVSP, CO, PA, PAWP)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Part A: Healthy volunteers; Part B: Heart failure patients Inclusion Criteria - Part A
             Healthy Volunteers

        Participants must:

          1. Provide written informed consent prior to any study procedure and agree to adhere to
             all protocol requirements

          2. Be aged between 18 to 45 years old inclusive at the time of consent

          3. Be in good general health without clinically significant medical history

          4. Have a body mass index (BMI) between 19- 30 kg/m2 inclusive

          5. Documented 12-lead ECG with no clinically significant abnormalities, as determined by
             the Investigator

          6. No clinically significant abnormalities in screening or Day 0 laboratory tests, as
             determined by the Investigator;

          7. Female subjects of reproductive potential must have a negative serum pregnancy (ß-HCG)
             test at screening and a negative urine pregnancy test at Day 0 prior to dosing. Female
             subjects must also be non-lactating

          8. Negative Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV), Hepatitis B and Hepatitis C Screening
             test results

        Inclusion Criteria - Part B Heart Failure Patients

        Participants must:

          1. Provide written informed consent prior to any study procedure and agree to adhere to
             all protocol requirements

          2. Heart Failure patients with LVEF less than45%

          3. NYHA II-III

          4. Stable medications (for greater than 48hrs)

          5. Systolic BP greater than 90</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Male</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Exclusion Criteria - Part A Healthy Volunteers

        Participants will not be enrolled if they meet any of the following criteria:

          1. If female, pregnant or lactating

          2. Receipt of any investigational agent or drug within 30 days or 5 half-lives (whichever
             is longer) prior to the first dose of Investigational product

          3. Use of prescription drugs within 4 weeks prior to first dosing. Subjects who have used
             over the counter medication excluding paracetamol, topical over the counter
             medications and routine vitamins but including megadose (intake of 20 to 600 times the
             recommended daily dose) vitamin therapy within 7 days of first dosing, unless agreed
             as non-clinically relevant by the Principal Investigator

          4. No clinically relevant findings in the medical history, laboratory examination and
             physical examination, especially with regards to cardiovascular system and renal
             function

          5. A positive urine test for drugs of abuse or alcohol at Screening or on the day of
             admittance to the Study Unit

          6. Normal dietary habits

          7. Any major surgical procedure within one month of entry into the study

          8. Have difficulties communicating reliably with the Investigator or unlikely to
             co-operate with the requirements of the study.

          9. Any other condition which in the view of the Investigator is likely to interfere with
             study or put the subject at risk.

        Exclusion Criteria - Part B Heart Failure Patients

          1. Unstable heart failure including NYHA IV symptoms

          2. Treatment with intravenous inotropes or mechanical circulatory support.

          3. Unstable rhythm including frequent non-sustained ventricular tachycardia or poorly
             controlled atrial fibrillation (ventricular rate &gt;100).

          4. Severe renal impairment Cr&gt;200umol/L or dialysis.

          5. Life-threatening haematological, hepatic or pulmonary disease.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/05/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>9</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/12/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Alfred Hospital - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Nucleus Network - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Alfred</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To determine the pharmacokinetic profile of a new (extended release) formulation of milrinone
      and to demonstrate evidence of hemodynamic effect

      Primary: Pharmacokinetic profile - to demonstrate stable plasma levels Secondary (HF cohort)
      - to demonstrate evidence of haemodynamic benefit

      Study Design: Open label</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01849094</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>