<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4078">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/01/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/01/2013</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01783015</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Study of Etanercept in Subjects With Rheumatoid Arthritis Who Have Had an Inadequate Response to Adalimumab or Infliximab Plus Methotrexate</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled Study Of The Safety And Efficacy Of Etanercept In Subjects With Rheumatoid Arthritis Who Have Had An Inadequate Response To Adalimumab Or Infliximab Plus Methotrexate</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>SERUM</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>2012-003644-71</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>B1801355</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Rheumatoid Arthritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Rheumatoid arthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Etanercept
Treatment: drugs - Etanercept
Treatment: drugs - Placebo
Treatment: drugs - Placebo

Experimental: Group A - Subjects who are mAb ADA positive

Experimental: Group B - Subjects who are mAb ADA negative

Placebo Comparator: Group C - Subjects who are mAb ADA positive

Placebo Comparator: Group D - Subjects who are mAb ADA negative


Treatment: drugs: Etanercept
Etanercept 50 mg once-weekly

Treatment: drugs: Etanercept
Etanercept 50 mg once-weekly

Treatment: drugs: Placebo
Etanercept placebo once-weekly

Treatment: drugs: Placebo
Etanercept placebo once-weekly

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in the Disease Activity Score Based on a 28 Joint Count (DAS28-C-reactive Protein [CRP]) at Week 12. - DAS28 calculated from the number of swollen joints (SJC) and painful joints (PJC) using the 28 joints count, the c-reactive protein (CRP) and Subject General Health Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) assessment (participant rated health assessment with scores ranging 0 to 100; higher scores indicate worse health status).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in the DAS28 at Week 24 - DAS28 calculated from the number of SJC and PJC using the 28 joints count, the CRP and and Subject General Health VAS assessment (participant rated health assessment with scores ranging 0 to 100; higher scores indicate worse health status).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With DAS28 &lt;3.2 - Number of participants with DAS28 &lt;3.2. A score of &lt; 3.2 implied low disease activity.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With DAS28 &lt;2.6 - Number of Participants with DAS28 &lt;2.6. A DAS28 &lt; 2.6 implies remission.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants Achieving American College of Rheumatology 20% (ACR20) Response - ACR20 response: greater than or equal to (=) 20 percent (%) improvement in tender joint count; = 20% improvement in swollen joint count; and = 20% improvement in at least 3 of 5 remaining ACR core measures: participant's assessment of pain; Subject Global Assessment (SGA) of disease activity; Physician Global Assessment (PGA) of disease activity; self-assessed disability (disability index of the Health Assessment Questionnaire [HAQ]); and CRP.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants Achieving American College of Rheumatology 50% (ACR50) Response - ACR50 response: greater than or equal to (=) 50 percent (%) improvement in tender or swollen joint counts and = 50% improvement in 3 of the 5 remaining ACR core measures: participant's assessment of pain; SGA of disease activity; PGA of disease activity; subject's assessment of functional disability via a HAQ; and CRP.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants Achieving American College of Rheumatology 70% (ACR70) Response - ACR70 response: greater than or equal to (=) 70 percent (%) improvement in tender or swollen joint counts and = 70% improvement in 3 of the 5 remaining ACR core measures: participant's assessment of pain; SGA of disease activity; PGA of disease activity; subject's assessment of functional disability via a HAQ; and CRP.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants Achieving American College of Rheumatology 90% (ACR90) Response - ACR90 response: greater than or equal to (=) 90 percent (%) improvement in tender or swollen joint counts and = 90% improvement in 3 of the 5 remaining ACR core measures: participant's assessment of pain; SGA of disease activity; PGA of disease activity; subject's assessment of functional disability via a HAQ; and CRP.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants Achieving European League Against Rheumatism (EULAR) Good and/or Moderate Response. - The Disease Activity Score Based on 28-joints Count based (DAS28-based) EULAR response criteria were used to measure individual response as none, good, and moderate, depending on the extent of change from baseline and the level of disease activity reached. Good responders: change from baseline &gt;1.2 with DAS28 =&lt; 3.2; moderate responders: change from baseline &gt;1.2 with DAS28 &gt;3.2 to =&lt;5.1 or change from baseline &gt;0.6 to =&lt;1.2 with DAS28 =&lt;5.1; non-responders: change from baseline =&lt; 0.6 or change from baseline &gt;0.6 and =&lt;1.2 with DAS28 &gt;5.1.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants Achieving Low Disease Activity or Remission Based on Clinical Disease Activity Index (CDAI) - The CDAI is the numerical sum of 4 outcome parameters: tender joint count (TJC) and SJC based on a 28-joint assessment, SGA and PGA assessed on 0-10 point scale; higher scores=greater affliction due to disease activity. CDAI total score = 0-76. CDAI &lt;= 2.8 indicates disease remission, &gt;2.8 to 10 = low disease activity, &gt;10 to 22 = moderate disease activity, and &gt;22 = high disease activity.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants Achieving Low Disease Activity or Remission Based on Simplified Disease Activity Index (SDAI). - The SDAI is the numerical sum of five outcome parameters: TJC) and SJC based on a 28-joint assessment, SGA and PGA assessed on 0-10 point scale; higher scores=greater affliction due to disease activity, and CRP (mg/dL). SDAI total score= 0-86. SDAI &lt;=3.3 indicates disease remission, &gt;3.4 to 11 = low disease activity, &gt;11 to 26 = moderate disease activity, and &gt;26 = high disease activity.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in CDAI - Change from Baseline in CDAI scores was to be calculated. The CDAI is the numerical sum of 4 outcome parameters: TJC and SJC based on a 28-joint assessment, SGA and PGA assessed on 0-10 point scale; higher scores=greater affliction due to disease activity. CDAI total score = 0-76. CDAI &lt;= 2.8 indicates disease remission, &gt;2.8 to 10 = low disease activity, &gt;10 to 22 = moderate disease activity, and &gt;22 = high disease activity.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 weeks, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in SDAI. - Change from Baseline in SDAI scores were to be calculated. The SDAI is the numerical sum of five outcome parameters: TJC and SJC based on a 28-joint assessment, SGA and PGA assessed on 0-10 point scale; higher scores=greater affliction due to disease activity, and CRP (mg/dL). SDAI total score= 0-86. SDAI &lt;=3.3 indicates disease remission, &gt;3.4 to 11 = low disease activity, &gt;11 to 26 = moderate disease activity, and &gt;26 = high disease activity.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 weeks, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Number of Tender/Painful Joints - Change from Baseline in the number of tender/painful joints using the 28 joint count including shoulders, elbows, wrists, metacarpophalangeal joints, proximal interphalangeal joints, and knees was to be calculated.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 weeks, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Number of Swollen Joints - Change from Baseline in the number of swollen joints including shoulders, elbows, wrists, metacarpophalangeal joints, proximal interphalangeal joints, and knees was to be calculated.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 weeks, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Physician Global Assessment of Disease Activity - Change from Baseline in the PGA scores was to be estimated. The Study Physician estimated the participant's overall disease activity over the last 2 to 3 days using a scale between 0 (no disease activity) and 10 (extreme disease activity).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 weeks, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Subject Global Assessment of Disease Activity - Change from Baseline in Subject Global Assessment of Disease Activity was to be estimated. Participants were to assess their overall disease activity over the last 2 to 3 days using a scale between 0 (no disease activity) and 10 (extreme disease activity).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 weeks, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Subject General Health VAS. - Subject General Health VAS assessment (participant rated health assessment with scores ranging 0 to 100; higher scores indicate worse health status).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 weeks, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Subject Pain - Subject Pain was to be measured on a 0 to 100 mm Visual Analog Scale (VAS), with 0 mm = no pain and 100 mm = most severe pain.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 weeks, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in CRP - The test for CRP is a laboratory measurement for evaluation of an acute phase reactant of inflammation through the use of an ultrasensitive assay. A decrease in the level of CRP indicates reduction in inflammation and therefore improvement.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 weeks, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Health Assessment Questionnaire Disability and Discomfort Scales (HAQ-DI) - Health Assessment Questionnaire-Disability Index (HAQ-DI): participant-reported assessment of ability to perform tasks in 8 categories of daily living activities: dress/groom; arise; eat; walk; reach; grip; hygiene; and common activities over past week. Each item scored on 4-point scale from 0 to 3: 0=no difficulty; 1=some difficulty; 2=much difficulty; 3=unable to do. Overall score was computed as the sum of domain scores and divided by the number of domains answered. Total possible score range 0-3 where 0 = least difficulty and 3 = extreme difficulty.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 weeks, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Euro Quality of Life (Qol) EQ-5 Dimensions Questionnaire (EQ-5D) - The EuroQol-5 Dimensions (EQ-5D) is a participant-completed questionnaire designed to assess health related quality of life. There are 2 components to the EQ-5D: a Health State Profile and a VAS. For the Health State Profile, participants recorded their level of current health for 5 domains comprising a health profile: mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort, and anxiety/depression. Scores from the 5 domains may be used to calculate a single index value, also known as a utility score. On the VAS participants were asked to rate their current health on a scale from 0 to 100 mm, where 0 represented the "worst imaginable health state" and 100 represented the "best imaginable health state." In addition to a summary of mean changes, 1 categorical endpoint each based on EQ-5D utility score and 1 based on the VAS were derived and analyzed: EQ-5D utility score improvement =0.05 and EQ-5D VAS score &gt;82.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 weeks, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Short Form-36 Health Survey (SF-36) - The 36-Item Short Form Health Survey (SF-36) is widely used 36-item questionnaire that measures general health-related quality of life in the following 8 domains: physical function, role limitations due to physical health, bodily pain, general health perception, vitality, social functioning, role limitation due to emotional problems, and mental health. Scores for the 8 domains range from 0 to 100 where higher scores are better.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 weeks, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Patient Acceptable Symptom State (PASS) - The Patient Acceptable Symptom State (PASS) was a participant-completed form in which participants were asked to "Think about all the ways your rheumatoid arthritis (RA) has affected you during the last 48 hours. If you were to remain in the next few months as you were during the last 48 hours, would this be acceptable or unacceptable to you?" The participant indicated a response of either "acceptable" or "unacceptable".</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 weeks, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Vectra Disease Activity Levels - The change from Baseline in Vectra disease activity levels was to be estimated. The assessment measures serum protein biomarkers associated with RA. It has a range from 1-100 with lower scores indicating the better outcome.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 weeks, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With Positive Etanercept Anti-drug Antibody Status - Blood samples (6 mL) were collected at the baseline, Week 12, and Week 24 visits, or upon early withdrawal, to provide a minimum of 1 mL serum each for ETN ADA and ETN neutralizing antibody analyses. Samples which were positive for ETN anti-drug antibodies were then also tested for ETN neutralizing antibodies.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 weeks, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With Positive Etanercept Neutralizing Anti-drug Antibody Status - Blood samples (6 mL) were collected at the baseline, Week 12, and Week 24 visits, or upon early withdrawal, to provide a minimum of 1 mL serum each for ETN ADA and ETN neutralizing antibody analyses. Samples which were positive for ETN anti-drug antibodies were then also tested for ETN neutralizing antibodies.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 weeks, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Met the 1987 ACR Revised Criteria for RA

          2. A history of inadequate response to infliximab or adalimumab in combination with
             methotrexate.

          3. A stable dose of oral methotrexate for at least 6 weeks before the baseline visit.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>79</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. ACR functional class IV

          2. Prior treatment with etanercept; both infliximab and adalimumab; or any
             immunosuppressive biologic agent other than infliximab or adalimumab.

          3. Discontinuation of infliximab or adalimumab for a primary reason other than inadequate
             efficacy response.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/09/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>16</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Terminated</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/08/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>RK Will Pty Ltd - Victoria Park</hospital>
    <postcode>6100 - Victoria Park</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Bruxelles</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Montpellier</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <state>New Territories</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <state>Tseung Kwan O, NT</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Haifa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Kfar Saba</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Izhevsk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Kazan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Moscow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Málaga</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Sevilla</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Pfizer</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The first 12 weeks of this study will compare the efficacy of etanercept 50 mg once-weekly to
      placebo in subjects with rheumatoid arthritis who have not responded well to infliximab or
      adalimumab plus methotrexate. This comparison will be performed for all subjects and
      separately for subjects who are anti-drug antibody positive for one of these medications.
      From week 12 to week 24, all subjects will receive etanercept 50 mg once-weekly. The effect
      of anti-drug antibody status on the efficacy of etanercept as well as the safety profile of
      etanercept in these subjects will also be evaluated throughout the study.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01783015</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Pfizer CT.gov Call Center</name>
      <address>Pfizer</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>