<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3888">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/03/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/03/2013</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01822119</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Clinical Performance of a Transcutaneous Bone Conduction Hearing Solution (Baha® Attract System)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Clinical Performance of a Transcutaneous Bone Conduction Hearing Solution (Baha® Attract System). A Multicentre, Open, Prospective Clinical Investigation. 3 Months Investigation With a 6 Months Follow-up</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>CBAS5484</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Deafness</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Hearing Loss</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Hearing Loss, Conductive</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Ear</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Deafness</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - Baha Attract System

Experimental: Baha Attract System - This transcutaneous solution is based on a magnet coupling using magnets on both side of the skin;
One implant magnet
One external magnet on which a sound processor is attached, i.e. the Sound Processor magnet (SP magnet)


Treatment: devices: Baha Attract System


</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hearing Performance, PTA4 at 12 Weeks - The change in pure-tone thresholds in free field measured by the difference in pure tone average PTA4 (Mean of thresholds at 500, 1000, 2000 and 4000 Hz) from the pre-operative unaided condition to the aided situation with the Baha Attract System at week 12.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline before surgery and 12 weeks after surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hearing Performance, PTA4 at 36 Weeks - The change in pure-tone thresholds in free field measured by the difference in pure tone average PTA4 (Mean of thresholds at 500, 1000, 2000 and 4000 Hz) from the pre-operative unaided condition to the aided situation with the Baha Attract System at week 36.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline before surgery and 36 weeks after surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hearing Performance, Individual Frequencies - The change in pure-tone thresholds in free field measured by the difference at individual frequencies from the pre-operative unaided condition to the aided situation with the Baha Attract System at week 36.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline before surgery and 36 weeks after surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hearing Performance, PTA4, Sound Processor on Softband Versus Baha Attract at 36 Weeks - The change in pure-tone thresholds in free field measured by the difference in pure tone average PTA4 (Mean of thresholds at 500, 1000, 2000 and 4000 Hz) from the pre-operative aided situation with the Sound Processor on a softband to the aided situation with Baha Attract System at week 36.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline before surgery and 36 weeks after surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hearing Performance, Individual Frequencies, Sound Processor on Softband Versus Baha Attract at 36 Weeks - The change in pure-tone thresholds in free field measured by the difference in hearing levels of individual frequencies from the pre-operative aided situation with the Sound Processor on a softband to the aided situation with Baha Attract System at week 36.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline before surgery and 36 weeks after surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hearing Performance, Speech in Quiet, Unaided Versus Baha Attract at 36 Weeks - The change in hearing performance, speech in quiet from the pre-operative unaided condition to the aided situation with the Baha Attract System at week 36.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline before surgery and 36 weeks after surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hearing Performance, Speech in Quiet, Aided With the Sound Processor on a Softband Versus Baha Attract at 36 Weeks - The change in hearing performance, speech in quiet from the pre-operative aided situation with the Sond Processor on a softband to the aided situation with the Baha Attract System at week 36.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline before surgery and 36 weeks after surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hearing Performance, Speech in Noise, Unaided Versus Baha Attract at 36 Weeks - The change in hearing performance, speech in noise from the pre-operative unaided condition to the aided situation with the Baha Attract System at week 36.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline before surgery and 36 weeks after surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hearing Performance, Speech in Noise, Aided With the Sound Processor on a Softband Versus Baha Attract at 36 Weeks - The change in hearing performance, speech in noise from the pre-operative aided situation with the Sond Processor on a softband to the aided situation with the Baha Attract System at week 36.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline before surgery and 36 weeks after surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Abbreviated Profile of Hearing Aid Benefit (APHAB) - Change of APHAB scoring from the unaided pre-operative situation to the aided situation with Baha Attract at 36 weeks. APHAB questionnaire is a 24-item self-assessment inventory that evaluates the benefit experienced by the patient when using hearing amplification compared to the unaided situation. APHAB produces a Global score and scores for four subscales: ease of communication (EC), reverberation (RV), background noise (BN), and aversiveness (AV). The absolute APHAB scale is between 0 and 100%, where 0% indicates no problem and 100% indicates always problem. The change from unaided to aided hearing is presented. A positive value indicates an improvement, a negative value an impairment. This scale applies to all reported scores.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline before surgery and 36 weeks after surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Conductive hearing loss in the implanted ear. Bone conduction thresholds with a pure
             tone average of 500, 1000, 2000 and 3000 Hz &lt;30 decibel (dB) hearing level (HL)

          -  Single-sided Sensorineural Deafness (SSD). Bone conduction thresholds with a pure tone
             average of 500, 1000, 2000 and 3000 Hz &lt;30 dB hearing level (HL) in the best ear

          -  Signed informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Uncontrolled diabetes as judged by the investigator

          -  Condition that could jeopardize osseointegration and/or wound healing, e.g.
             osteoporosis, psoriasis and use of corticosteroids

          -  Unable to follow investigational procedures, e.g. to complete quality of life scales

          -  Less than 4mm of soft tissue pre-operatively

          -  Participation in another investigation with pharmaceuticals and/or device

          -  Condition that may have an impact on the outcome of the investigation as judged by the
             investigator

          -  Subjects that have received radiation therapy at the same side of the skull where the
             Baha Attract will be positioned

          -  Suitable implant position for the Baha BI300 implant system (4 mm and 3 mm) not found
             during surgery due to insufficient bone quality and/or bone thickness</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/03/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>27</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/02/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The HEARing CRC &amp; HearWorks, University of Melbourne - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3010 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Chile</country>
      <state>Santiago</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <state>Hong Kong</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Haifa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Cochlear Bone Anchored Solutions</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The rationale behind this clinical performance investigation is to collect data regarding the
      usability of the Baha Attract System in patients with hearing impairment that are candidates
      for Baha surgery:

        -  To describe the expected hearing performance with the Baha Attract in comparison to
           unaided hearing thresholds or a pre-test situation using a sound processor together with
           a softband

        -  Which sound processor to select, i.e. BP100 vs BP110

        -  Improve the fitting process for the sound processor

        -  Selection of sound processor magnet at time of fitting and over time</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01822119</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Robert Cowan, A/Professor</name>
      <address>The HEARing CRC &amp; HearWorks, University of Melbourne</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>