<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5996">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/04/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/04/2016</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02850718</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Pivotal Study of the Bioequivalence of Oral Viagra® and a Test Sublingual Sildenafil Wafer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Pivotal Study of the Bioequivalence of Oral Viagra® and a Test Sublingual Sildenafil Wafer</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>SIL-003</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Erectile Dysfunction</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other renal and urogenital disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other reproductive health and childbirth disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Sublingual Sildenafil
Treatment: drugs - Oral Sildenafil

Experimental: Period 1: Sublingual wafer - Subjects receive receive a single dose of 50 mg sublingual sildenafil followed by plasma sampling for 14 hours.

Active Comparator: Period 2: Oral comparator - Subjects receive a single dose of 50 mg oral sildenafil (Viagra) followed by plasma sampling for 14 hours.


Treatment: drugs: Sublingual Sildenafil
50 mg sildenafil sublingual wafer.

Treatment: drugs: Oral Sildenafil
50 mg oral sildenafil (Viagra)

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sildenafil plasma concentrations</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of patients with treatment-related adverse events</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Voluntarily provides signed, written, and dated informed consent prior to any
             study-specific procedures.

          2. Healthy male volunteers aged 18-50 years inclusive.

          3. In good general health without clinically significant haematological, cardiac,
             respiratory, renal, endocrine, gastrointestinal, psychiatric, hepatic, or malignant
             disease, as determined by the Principal Investigator.

          4. Sufficient access for venous cannulation to withdraw blood as per the study design.

          5. Body mass index (BMI) of =19 to = 30kg/m2 (inclusive).

          6. Participant is deemed able to read and understand English in order to communicate with
             research staff and complete protocol required questionnaires and forms.

          7. Able to refrain from smoking while at the research unit.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Male</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Past history of hypersensitivity to sildenafil, any of its excipients, or severe
             allergic or anaphylactic reaction to any other drug.

          2. A medical condition that, in the opinion of the Investigator, may adversely impact the
             participant's ability to complete the study, including but not limited to:

               1. History of priapism;

               2. History of easy fainting or symptomatic postural hypotension;

               3. Standing or supine systolic blood pressure &lt; 90mmHg or diastolic blood pressure &lt;
                  50mm Hg or postural drop of &gt;30mm Hg;

               4. History of myocardial infarction or clinically significant cardiac disease
                  including cardiac arrhythmia;

               5. History of retinitis pigmentosa or optic neuropathy or other risk factors of
                  non-arteritic anterior ischaemic optic neuropathy (NAION);

               6. History or evidence of hypertension - defined as three BP readings (at rest)
                  within 15 minutes of systolic blood pressure =140 mm Hg or diastolic blood
                  pressure =90 mmHg. Note: serial blood pressure readings are only required if the
                  initial reading is elevated;

               7. Anaemia (haemoglobin &lt; lower limit of normal for sex).

          3. Clinically significant 12-lead ECG abnormalities at the screening visit as determined
             by the Investigator.

          4. Concomitant consumption of any other medication regularly, with the exception of
             vitamins or minerals.

          5. Consumption of drugs with either enzyme-inducing properties, such as rifampicin and St
             John's Wort, within 3 weeks prior to the initial dose of study drug and throughout the
             treatment phase or CYP3A4 inhibitors, such as erythromycin and clarithromycin, within
             5 half-lives prior to the initial dose of study drug and throughout the treatment
             phase.

          6. Previous known or suspected drug abuse (including analgesic drugs or tranquilizers) or
             dependence, as defined by DSM-IV, or history of alcohol abuse or excessive intake of
             alcohol, defined as regular weekly intake of &gt;15 units for men and &gt;10 units for women
             (1 unit= 25ml spirits,125ml wine, 250ml beer or lager).

          7. Positive results on the urine drug screen indicative of illicit drug abuse or
             inconsistent with medication history, or alcohol breath test indicative of alcohol
             abuse.

          8. History of hepatitis B or C, or other forms of non-infectious liver disease.

          9. Clinically significant abnormalities in clinical chemistry, haematology, urinalysis,
             or serology results at screening that, in the opinion of the Investigator, puts the
             volunteer at risk for study participation.

         10. Clinically significant plasma AST, ALT and ALP tests (defined as =1.5 times the upper
             limit of normal).

         11. Positive serology for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), hepatitis B virus (HBV) or
             hepatitis C virus (HCV) infection at screening.

         12. Prevalent abnormality in the oral cavity which may alter sublingual drug absorption
             (e.g. recurrent oral ulceration, lichen planus, or xerostomia).

         13. Any other condition which, in the opinion of the Investigator, makes the volunteer
             unsuitable for the study.

         14. Unwillingness or inability to comply with the requirements of this protocol, including
             the presence of any condition (physical, mental, or social) that is likely to affect
             the participant's ability to return for follow up visits on schedule.

         15. Member or relative of study staff or the Sponsor directly involved in the study.

         16. Previous participation in this study.

         17. Has received another investigational agent or new chemical entity (defined as a
             compound which has not been approved for marketing) within 30 days prior to the
             Screening visit.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/03/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>48</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/05/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Linear Clinical Research - Perth</hospital>
    <postcode>6009 - Perth</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>iX Biopharma Ltd.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Linear Clinical Research</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A comparative bioequivalence study in 48 healthy male volunteers of oral Viagra and a test
      sublingual sildenafil wafer.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02850718</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>