<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2423">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/07/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/07/2009</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00935987</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Safety and Efficacy Study of CYT387 in Primary Myelofibrosis (PMF) or Post-polycythemia Vera (PV) or Post-essential Thrombocythemia (ET)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase I/II, Open-Label, Dose-Escalation Study Evaluating the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics of Orally-Administered CYT387 in Primary Myelofibrosis or Post-Polycythemia Vera or Post-Essential Thrombocythemia Myelofibrosis.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>CCL09101</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Primary Myelofibrosis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Post-Polycythemia Vera Myelofibrosis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Post-Essential Thrombocythemia Myelofibrosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human Genetics and Inherited Disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other human genetics and inherited disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Leukaemia - Chronic leukaemia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haematological diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other blood disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - CYT387

Experimental: CYT387 - 


Treatment: drugs: CYT387
For the Part 1 dose-escalation portion of the study, patients will be assigned to dose levels in successive cohorts starting with a dose in the first cohort of 100 mg/day. CYT387 will be orally self-administered as a single daily dose beginning on Day 1 of the study, and thereafter at approximately the same time each day of the 28-day cycle. It is recommended that all doses be preceded by a 2-hour fast from food and beverages, and be followed by a 1-hour post-dose fast from food and beverages.
Twenty additional patients will be assigned to a 150 mg BID (twice daily) dosing schedule. CYT387 will be orally self-administered twice-daily with doses approximately 10-12 hours apart beginning on Day 1 of the study, and thereafter at approximately the same times each day of the 28-day cycle.
For the Part 2 dose confirmation portion of the study, patients will be assigned to either 150 mg or 300 mg QD (once daily) dose groups.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and tolerability, dose-limiting toxicities (DLTs) and maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of orally-administered CYT387 in patients with PMF or post-ET/PV MF.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Ongoing throughout therapy up until 30 days after last dose of CYT387</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Objective Response Rate (ORR), as measured by complete response (CR) rate, partial response (PR) rate and clinical improvement (CI) rate according to International Working Group for Myelofibrosis Research and Treatment (IWG-MRT) consensus criteria - The Objective Response Rate (ORR), as measured by complete response (CR) rate, partial response (PR) rate and clinical improvement (CI) rate according to International Working Group for Myelofibrosis Research and Treatment (IWG-MRT) is to be measured at the end of every cycle of therapy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to study completion</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetics of CYT387 in patients with PMF or post-ET/PV MF - The pharmacokinetics (PK) of CYT387 in patients with PMF or post-ET/PV MF is to be assessed on Day 1 and Day 28 in Cycle 1 of therapy</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to end of Cycle 1</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Effect of CYT387 on bone marrow or peripheral blood cytogenetic findings in patients with PMF or post-ET/PV MF. - The effect of CYT387 on bone marrow or peripheral blood cytogenetic findings in patients with PMF or post-ET/PV MF is to be assessed at the end of every third cycle of therapy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to study completion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Effect of CYT387 on peripheral blood granulocyte JAK2V617F allele burden in patients with PMF or post-ET/PV MF. - The effect of CYT387 on peripheral blood granulocyte JAK2V617F allele burden in patients with PMF or post-ET/PV MF is to be assessed at the end of each cycle of therapy (in relevant patients only)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to study completion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Effect of CYT387 on peripheral blood endogenous myeloid colony formation in patients with PMF or post-ET/PV MF. - The effect of CYT387 on peripheral blood endogenous myeloid colony formation in patients with PMF or post-ET/PV MF is to be assessed at the end of each cycle of therapy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to study completion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Effect of CYT387 on plasma levels of inflammatory, fibrogenic and angiogenic cytokines in patients with PMF or post-ET/PV MF - The effect of CYT387 on plasma levels of inflammatory, fibrogenic and angiogenic cytokines in patients with PMF or post-ET/PV MF is to be assessed at the end of each cycle of therapy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to study completion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacodynamic correlates of CYT387 activity in patients with PMF or post-ET/PV MF who are receiving treatment with CYT387. - The pharmacodynamic correlates of CYT387 activity in patients with PMF or post-ET/PV MF who are receiving treatment with CYT387 are to be assessed on Day 1 of Cycles 1, 3, 6 and 9.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to Cycle 9</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Diagnosis of PMF or post-polycythemia Vera (PV) or post-essential Thrombocythemia (ET)
             MF as per revised World Health Organization (WHO) criteria.

          -  High-risk or Intermediate-2 risk MF (as defined by the International Prognostic
             Scoring System [IPSS]; Appendix 13.6); or intermediate-I risk MF (IPSS) associated
             with symptomatic splenomegaly/hepatomegaly and/or unresponsive to available therapy.

          -  Must be at least 18 years of age with life expectancy of = 12 weeks.

          -  Must be able to provide informed consent and be willing to sign an informed consent
             form.

          -  Must have an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0, 1 or
             2.

          -  Must have evidence of acceptable organ function within 7 days of initiating study drug
             as evidenced by the following:

               -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) or alanine aminotransferase (ALT) = 2.5 x upper
                  limit of normal (ULN) (or = 5 x ULN if in the investigator's opinion the
                  elevation is due to extramedullary hematopoiesis)

               -  Bilirubin = 2.0 x ULN or direct bilirubin &lt; 1.0

               -  Serum creatinine = 2.5 x ULN

               -  Absolute neutrophil count = 500/µL

               -  Platelet count = 50,000/µL

          -  Females of childbearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test within 4 days of
             initiating study drug.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Any chemotherapy (eg, hydroxyurea), immunomodulatory drug therapy (eg, thalidomide),
             immunosuppressive therapy, corticosteroids &gt; 10 mg/day prednisone or equivalent, or
             growth factor treatment (eg, erythropoietin) within 14 days prior to initiation of
             study drug.

          -  Incomplete recovery from major surgery within four weeks of study entry.

          -  Radiation therapy within four weeks of study entry.

          -  Women of childbearing potential, unless surgically sterile for at least 3 months (ie,
             hysterectomy), OR postmenopausal for at least 12 months (FSH &gt; 30 U/mL), OR unless
             they agree to take appropriate precautions to avoid pregnancy (with at least 99%
             certainty) from screening through end of study. Permitted methods for preventing
             pregnancy must be communicated to study subjects and their understanding confirmed.

          -  Men who partner with a woman of childbearing potential, unless they agree to take
             appropriate precautions to avoid pregnancy (with at least 99% certainty) from
             screening through to the end of study. Permitted methods for preventing pregnancy must
             be communicated to study subjects and their understanding confirmed.

          -  Females who are pregnant or are currently breastfeeding.

          -  Known positive status for HIV.

          -  Clinically active hepatitis B or C.

          -  Diagnosis of another malignancy unless free of disease for at least three years
             following therapy with curative intent. Patients with early-stage basal cell or
             squamous cell skin cancer, cervical intraepithelial neoplasia, cervical carcinoma in
             situ or superficial bladder cancer may be eligible to participate at the
             Investigator's discretion.

          -  Any acute active infection.

          -  Cardiac dysrhythmias requiring treatment, or prolongation of the QTc (Fridericia)
             interval to &gt; 450 msec for males or &gt; 470 msec for females at prestudy screening,
             unless attributable to pre-existing bundle branch block.

          -  Presence of = Grade 2 peripheral neuropathy.

          -  Uncontrolled congestive heart failure (New York Heart Association Classification 3 or
             4), uncontrolled or unstable angina, myocardial infarction, cerebrovascular accident,
             or pulmonary embolism within 3 months prior to initiation of study drug.

          -  Uncontrolled inter current illness or any concurrent condition that, in the
             Investigator's opinion, would jeopardize the safety of the patient or compliance with
             the protocol.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/11/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>166</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/04/2012</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Melbourne Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>3050 - Parkville</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Massachusetts</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Minnesota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Quebec</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Gilead Sciences</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study seeks to (i) determine a safe and tolerated dose of CYT387 given to patients with
      PMF, post-PV or post-ET and, (ii) assess the effectiveness of orally-administered CYT387 as a
      treatment for PMF, post-PV or post-ET.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00935987</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ayalew Tefferi, MD</name>
      <address>Mayo Clinic</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>