<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4067">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/08/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/08/2013</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01927510</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>TEAM: A Trial of Early Activity and Mobility in ICU</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Pilot Randomised Controlled Trial of Early Mobilisation in Critically Ill Patients to Improve Functional Recovery and Quality of Life.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>TEAM-RCT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NCT01674608</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Critically Ill</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Behaviour - Early mobilisation

Experimental: early mobilisation - intervention of early mobilisation

No Intervention: Control - Standard care


Behaviour: Early mobilisation


</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Highest daily level of activity measured using the ICU mobillity scale - ICU Mobility Scale - ranges from 0 (Nothing/Lying in Bed) to 10 (Walking Independently without a Gait Aid)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration of ICU stay (an average of 10 days)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total Duration of Active Mobilisation</outcome>
      <timepoint>Radomisation to removal of invasive ventilation (an average of 7 days)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean (or Median) Daily Duration of Active Mobilisation - Measured in minutes, any mobilisation activity where the patient can use their own muscle force to assist the movement.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Randomisation to removal of invasive ventilation (daily for an average of 7 days)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total Duration of Active Mobilisation - Pt will be free of Mechanical Ventilation, Vasopressors and Continuous Renal Replacement Therapy for 24 Hours</outcome>
      <timepoint>Randomisation to ICU discharge, an average of 10 days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean (or Median) Daily Duration of Active Mobilisation - Pt will be free of Mechanical Ventilation, Vasopressors and Continuous Renal Replacement Therapy for 24 Hours (approximately 10 days)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Randomisation to Time of Final Listing for Ward Discharge, an average of 10 days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of Patients achieving each Category of Highest Level of Mobilisation on Each Day - Measured using the ICU mobility scale (0-10)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Randomisation to Extubation, an average of 7 days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical Function - Highest level of activity, measured using the IADL</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months from randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Recruitment Rates</outcome>
      <timepoint>Entirety of Study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Staff Utilisation Costs - Number of staff required for mobilisation, minutes spent with the patient on active mobilisation activities, and type of staff such as assistant, physiotherapist or nurse, and specific equipment used during mobilisation ie: tilt table/standing frame.</outcome>
      <timepoint>ICU admission (approximately 10 days)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ventilator and IC free days at Day 28 - Intensive care free defined as ward ready; free of inotropes, RRT and mechanical ventilation for 24 hours and remaining free of these supports until the time of actual ICU discharge</outcome>
      <timepoint>Randomisation to Day 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health related quality of life - EQ5D measured using a trained, blinded assessor via telephone interview</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 Months after ICU admission</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Return to previous work level - Has the participant returned to the work level prior to critical illness?</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months from randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Adults &gt; or + to 18 years old admitted to the ICU

          -  Invasively ventilated and expected to be ventilated the day after tomorrow

          -  Written informed consent from person responsible/ net of kin (or consent as per
             individual HREC if delayed or telephone consent is acceptable)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. INSTABILITY A. Cardiovascular

               -  Unresolved rhythm disturbance with any bradycardia requiring pharmacological
                  support

               -  Any tachycardia with ventricular rate &gt; 150 beats/min

               -  Lactacte &gt; 4.0 due to inadequate tissue perfusion

               -  Any external mechanical cardiovascular support (eg. VA ECMO or intra-aortic
                  balloon pump)

               -  Norad &gt; 0.2mcg/kg/min (or unit equivalent) or any dose of norad between 0.1 and
                  0.2mcg/kg/min with more than a 25% increase in last 6 hours

               -  Cardiac index &lt; 2.0L/min/m^2

             B. Respiratory

               -  FiO2 &gt; 0.6

               -  PEEP &gt; 15

               -  Requirement for hypoxaemic rescue interventions eg. NO, prone, ECMO,
                  prostacyclin, HFOV

               -  RR &gt; 45

          2. Proven or suspected actue brain injury such as stroke, sub-arachnoid haemorrhage,
             encephalitis, or moderate to severe traumatic brain injury

          3. Proven or suspected actue spinal cord injury

          4. Proven or suspected Guillain-Barre Syndrome

          5. Second or subsequent ICU admission during a single hospital admission

          6. Unable to follow simple verbal commands in English

          7. Death inevitable and imminent

          8. Inability to walk without assistance of another person prior to onset of acute illness
             necessitating ICU admission

          9. Cognitive impairment prior to current acute illness

         10. Agitation which int he opinion of the treating clinician precludes safe implementation
             of EGDM

         11. Written rest in bed orders due to documented injury or process the precludes
             mobilisation such as suspected or proven instability of spine or pelvis

         12. In the opinion of the treating clinician it is unsafe to commence EGDM

         13. Has met all the inclusion criteria with no concomitant exclusion criteria for a period
             of more than 48 hours</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/08/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>50</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/02/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <hospital>The Alfred Hospital - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Fremantle Hospital - Fremantle</hospital>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>6160 - Fremantle</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Wellington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australian and New Zealand Intensive Care Research Centre</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Australian and New Zealand Intensive Care Society Clinical Trials Group</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Patients in the intensive care unit (ICU) traditionally receive bed rest as part of their
      care. They develop muscle weaknesses even after only a few days of mechanical ventilation
      that may prolong their time in ICU and in hospital, delay functional recovery and delay their
      return home and to work. Weakness may be avoided with simple strategies of early exercise in
      ICU. This pilot study aims to test the hypothesis that early mobilisation may improve
      functional recovery in this patient group and gather pilot data to support a larger
      randomised trial across Australia and New Zealand.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01927510</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Carol L Hodgson, PhD</name>
      <address>Australian and New Zealand Intensive Care Research Centre</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>