<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4591">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/08/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/08/2014</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02223624</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of an Eccentric Exercise Program on Quality of Life and Function in People With Chronic Heart Failure.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of an Eccentrically Biased Aerobic Exercise Program on Quality of Life and Functional Capacity in People With Chronic Heart Failure: A Randomized Controlled Trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>LR 49.2013</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>LR49.2013 FHEC13/260 LaTrobeU</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Heart Failure</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - walking and light weights
Other interventions - eccentric aerobic exercise
Other interventions - concentric aerobic exercise

Experimental: eccentric aerobic exercise group - Eccentric aerobic exercise group: Participants in this group will participate in an eccentric aerobic exercise rehabilitation program for a total of eight weeks, two sessions per week. Outcome measurements will be taken post exercise program and also after a 3 month follow-up period. Each session will be approximately 60 minutes in duration and include approximately 10 minutes of warm up (stretches), eccentric stepper aiming for 20 minutes, walking and light weights, followed by a five minute cool-down period.

Active Comparator: Concentric aerobic exercise group - Concentric aerobic exercise group (usual care): The length of the concentric aerobic exercise based rehabilitation program will be the same as the study group- twice weekly exercise sessions for 8 weeks. Outcome measurements will also be taken after a 3-month follow-up period.
Participants in the concentric aerobic exercise group will participate in the same warm-up and cool down period as the eccentric group. They will also complete walking and light weights. To replace the 20 minutes of eccentric exercise, concentric participants will complete approximately 20 minutes of exercise bike, stair climbing and rowing as able with required rests.

No Intervention: Waiting list control - Waiting list (no exercise): Participants assigned to this group will not receive any intervention during the study period. They will be assessed like other participants at baseline and after eight weeks, but not at three-month follow-up due to ethical concerns around withholding care known to be effective. Given that there is a waiting list for the current exercise program of 4-12 weeks, it is felt that delaying care for a set period of eight weeks is not of ethical concern. Following the completion of assessments, waiting list participants will be able to complete the traditional exercise program as usual but not as participants of the study's experimental groups.


Other interventions: walking and light weights


Other interventions: eccentric aerobic exercise


Other interventions: concentric aerobic exercise


</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>functional improvement measured by change in six-minute walk distance</outcome>
      <timepoint>post 8-week exercise program and 3-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life measured by participant questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>post 8-week exercise program and 3-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  aged &gt; 18 years

          -  a clinical diagnosis of heart failure either systolic or diastolic on transthoracic
             echocardiogram

          -  mild to moderate heart failure

          -  medically stable heart failure

          -  have received approval when assessed by the group physiotherapist to participate in
             the exercise program as is usual practice. Where concerns arise during assessment,
             clearance will be sought from the treating cardiologist.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  hospitalisation for a CHF exacerbation within the previous month

          -  severe heart failure classified as level four on the New York heart association
             classification (short of breath at rest)

          -  unstable medical condition such as uncontrolled angina, diabetes or hypertension

          -  dementia or a psychological disorder that would interfere with participation in group
             exercise

          -  participation in a cardiac or heart failure rehabilitation program in the prior six
             months

          -  contraindications to exercise (ie aneurysm, valvular disease)

          -  the presence of any pre-existing neurological or musculoskeletal condition, for
             example stroke, that on assessment is deemed to interfere with exercise participation.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Factorial</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/08/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>75</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/12/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Northern Hospital - Epping</hospital>
    <postcode>3076 - Epping</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>La Trobe University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Northern Hospital, Australia</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Many studies have shown that exercise training is beneficial for patients with chronic heart
      failure (CHF). Heart Foundation guidelines strongly recommend regular physical activity and
      referral to a specifically designed rehabilitation program for all patients with CHF who are
      medically stable. Such programs usually comprise aerobic exercises such as walking, and light
      weightlifting with care to avoid heavy straining due to stress that this may place on the
      heart.

      Eccentric contractions are those in which the muscle lengthens as it contracts. Exercise
      involving eccentric contractions is known to increase muscle strength and this type of
      exercise also requires less oxygen. This is because it requires less power to resist lowering
      a weight than it does to lift a weight. Initial evidence suggests that this form of exercise
      has favourable outcomes in the frail elderly and those with chronic disease.

      This study aims to determine if eccentric exercise can be applied to patients with heart
      failure to increase their physical function while using less energy so that exercise is more
      tolerable for patients who complain of significant breathlessness and fatigue. This study
      also aims to determine if eccentric exercise is a safe alternative exercise option for
      patients at risk of negative events.

      The investigators propose to run a randomised controlled trial. Eccentric exercise will be
      delivered to a group of heart failure patients referred to the existing heart failure
      rehabilitation program at the Northern Hospital. The program will consist of eight weeks of
      twice weekly exercise of one hour's duration comprising eccentric exercise combined with
      walking and light weight training. This will be compared to a group of patients participating
      in the current exercise program consisting of light weightlifting and aerobic exercises for
      the same length and duration of exercise and also to a third group of patients who will be
      wait listed for 8 weeks. Following the completion of the eight week waiting period, these
      patients will be offered the option of joining the standard exercise program.

      The investigators expect that the eccentric exercise group will have improved walking
      capacity and quality of life compared with the traditional program and the wait-list control
      group. It is also possible that there is no difference between the eccentric and traditional
      program in terms of functional outcomes but that the participants report that eccentric
      exercise is easier.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02223624</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Rachel E Ellis</name>
      <address>Northern Hospital, Australia</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Rachel E Ellis</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+61384058580</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rachel.ellis2@nh.org.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>