<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6777">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/10/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/10/2017</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT03328767</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation Physical Training</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Pilot Randomised Controlled Trial in Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation Physical Training (ECMO-PT)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ECMO-PT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>ANZICRC/ECMO/001</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Critically Ill, Mechanically Ventilated</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation Complication</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Behaviour - Early activity and Mobilisation intervention

Experimental: Early activity and Mobilisation intervention - Patients will be randomised within 48 hrs of commencing ECMO. Patients unable to initially receive active physical training will receive passive physical training for a minimum of 20 minutes and a maximum of one hour per day to maintain joint and muscle activity until active physical training is commenced. The intervention involves a progression of exercises with the objective of rehabilitating the patient at the highest level of exercise possible for the patient for the longest period of time that can be tolerated (up to 60 minutes) at each session, based on our published ICU mobility scale now used internationally in ICU trials. This is performed with or without IMV (including both endotracheal tubes or tracheostomies).

No Intervention: Standard Care - The control group will receive standard care from physiotherapy staff not involved in delivering the intervention. We have previously established that standard care in Australia for a patient receiving prolonged IMV (control group intervention) frequently involves no active exercise out of bed.


Behaviour: Early activity and Mobilisation intervention
The early activity and mobilisation intervention is comprised of exercises based on a reproducible, physiological approach using both strength and functional activities

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility of delivering the intervention in the first 7 days after randomisation and the separation between the groups - Feasibility of delivering the intervention in the first 7 days after randomisation and the separation between the groups using the ICU mobility scale to report the highest level of activity. It is reported as median (IQR) over 7 days.</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to first stand out of bed - Time to first stand out of bed (within the first 28 days)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within the first 28 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events, Safety events (including decannulation of ventilator or ECMO cannula, fall to the floor during mobilization, desaturation SpO2 &lt; 85%) at anytime during the first 7 days - Incidence of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events, Safety events (including decannulation of ventilator or ECMO cannula, fall to the floor during mobilization, desaturation SpO2 &lt; 85%) at anytime during the first 7 days</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the first 7 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Strength at day 7 and 10 - Strength at day 7 and 10</outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 7 &amp; 10</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Function (reported as ICU mobility scale) measured at days 7, 10 and 20 - Function (reported as ICU mobility scale) measured at days 7, 10 and 20</outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 7, 10 &amp; 20</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>ICU and hospital length of stay - ICU and hospital length of stay (time from ICU admission to ICU and hospital discharge respectively censored at day 90)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time from ICU admission to ICU and hospital discharge respectively censored at day 90</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>ICU and in-hospital mortality - ICU and in-hospital mortality (time from ICU admission to ICU and hospital discharge respectively censored at day 90)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time from ICU admission to ICU and hospital discharge respectively censored at day 90</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  adults = 18 years of age

          -  were physically independent prior to the current admission;

          -  receiving ECMO (veno-arterial or veno-venous) for at least 24 hours;

          -  clinician in charge of patient care has no objection to randomisation</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  have been in ICU &gt; 5 days prior to the commencement of ECMO;

          -  have received ECMO for more than 48 hours;

          -  in the opinion of the treating clinician, is not expected to recover in 90 days (e.g.
             intracerebral haemorrhage);

          -  whom death is expected within 24 hours;

          -  are unable to communicate in English</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/11/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>The Prince Charles Hospital - Chermside West</hospital>
    <hospital>Alfred Hospital - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>4032 - Chermside West</postcode>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3065 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australian and New Zealand Intensive Care Research Centre</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Toronto General Hospital</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Monash University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>The Alfred</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>St. Vincent's Medical Center</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital, Sydney, Australia</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>The Prince Charles Hospital</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Critically ill patients who require extracorporeal membrane oxygenation (ECMO) are the
      sickest in the hospital. More patients are surviving but survivors have compromised
      functional recovery for months or years. This trial aims to determine if early, physical
      training commenced within 48 hours of ECMO is feasible and improves muscle strength and
      functional status in patients compared to standard practice in a randomised controlled trial
      of 30 ICU patients.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03328767</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Schweickert WD, Pohlman MC, Pohlman AS, Nigos C, Pawlik AJ, Esbrook CL, Spears L, Miller M, Franczyk M, Deprizio D, Schmidt GA, Bowman A, Barr R, McCallister KE, Hall JB, Kress JP. Early physical and occupational therapy in mechanically ventilated, critically ill patients: a randomised controlled trial. Lancet. 2009 May 30;373(9678):1874-82. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(09)60658-9. Epub 2009 May 14.
Craig P, Dieppe P, Macintyre S, Michie S, Nazareth I, Petticrew M. Developing and evaluating complex interventions: the new Medical Research Council guidance. Int J Nurs Stud. 2013 May;50(5):587-92. doi: 10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2012.09.010. Epub 2012 Nov 15.
Hodgson C, Needham D, Haines K, Bailey M, Ward A, Harrold M, Young P, Zanni J, Buhr H, Higgins A, Presneill J, Berney S. Feasibility and inter-rater reliability of the ICU Mobility Scale. Heart Lung. 2014 Jan-Feb;43(1):19-24. doi: 10.1016/j.hrtlng.2013.11.003. Epub 2013 Nov 19. Erratum in: Heart Lung. 2014 Jul-Aug;43(4):388.
Tipping CJ, Bailey MJ, Bellomo R, Berney S, Buhr H, Denehy L, Harrold M, Holland A, Higgins AM, Iwashyna TJ, Needham D, Presneill J, Saxena M, Skinner EH, Webb S, Young P, Zanni J, Hodgson CL. The ICU Mobility Scale Has Construct and Predictive Validity and Is Responsive. A Multicenter Observational Study. Ann Am Thorac Soc. 2016 Jun;13(6):887-93. doi: 10.1513/AnnalsATS.201510-717OC.
Borg G. Ratings of perceived exertion and heart rates during short-term cycle exercise and their use in a new cycling strength test. Int J Sports Med. 1982 Aug;3(3):153-8.
Berney S, Haines K, Skinner EH, Denehy L. Safety and feasibility of an exercise prescription approach to rehabilitation across the continuum of care for survivors of critical illness. Phys Ther. 2012 Dec;92(12):1524-35. doi: 10.2522/ptj.20110406. Epub 2012 Aug 9.
Hodgson CL, Stiller K, Needham DM, Tipping CJ, Harrold M, Baldwin CE, Bradley S, Berney S, Caruana LR, Elliott D, Green M, Haines K, Higgins AM, Kaukonen KM, Leditschke IA, Nickels MR, Paratz J, Patman S, Skinner EH, Young PJ, Zanni JM, Denehy L, Webb SA. Expert consensus and recommendations on safety criteria for active mobilization of mechanically ventilated critically ill adults. Crit Care. 2014 Dec 4;18(6):658. doi: 10.1186/s13054-014-0658-y. Review.
Puthucheary ZA, Denehy L. Exercise Interventions in Critical Illness Survivors: Understanding Inclusion and Stratification Criteria. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2015 Jun 15;191(12):1464-7. doi: 10.1164/rccm.201410-1907LE.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Carol Hodgson, A/Prof</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+61 448 674 532</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>carol.hodgson@monash.edu</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>