<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4060">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/04/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/04/2013</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01829295</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Methotrexate and Mycophenolate Mofetil for UVEITIS</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>First-line Antimetabolites as Steroid-sparing Treatment (FAST) Uveitis Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>FAST</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>5U10EY021125</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>EY021125-01</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Uveitis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other inflammatory or immune system disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Mycophenolate mofetil
Treatment: drugs - Methotrexate
Treatment: drugs - Prednisone

Experimental: Methotrexate - oral methotrexate

Experimental: Mycophenolate Mofetil - oral mycophenolate mofetil


Treatment: drugs: Mycophenolate mofetil
For the first two weeks, an introductory dose of 500 mg BID orally. After two weeks, the dose will be increased to 1.5 g BID.

Treatment: drugs: Methotrexate
For the first two weeks, an introductory dose of 15 mg/week (7.5mg BID once a week) orally. After two weeks, the dose will be increased to 25 mg/week (12.5mg BID once a week)

Treatment: drugs: Prednisone
All patients enrolled in the study will be initially taking concomitant oral corticosteroids at 1 mg/kg or 60 mg daily, whichever is less. Initial corticosteroid dose will be continued for 2 to 4 weeks at which point prednisone will be gradually tapered. Prednisone will be tapered to and held at 7.5 mg/day for the first 6 months of the study.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Treatment Success - Controlled ocular inflammation (= 0.5+ anterior chamber cells, = 0.5+ vitreous haze, no active retinal/choroidal lesions in both eyes) with 7.5 mg/day of oral prednisone and = 2 drops/day of topical 1% prednisolone acetate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 Months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  All the following criteria must be met at enrollment:

        Historical non-infectious intermediate, anterior and intermediate, posterior or panuveitis
        in at least one eye

        Active inflammation within the last 180 days, defined by the presence of any of the
        following (in at least one eye) according to SUN criteria:

          -  = 2+ anterior chamber cells

          -  = 2+ vitreous haze

          -  active retinal or choroidal lesions

        Active inflammation at enrollment, defined by the presence of any of the following (in at
        least one eye) according to SUN criteria:

          -  =1+ anterior chamber cells and/or

          -  =1+ vitreous haze and/or

          -  active retinal/choroidal lesions

        At least one of the following criteria must be met before or at enrollment:

          -  Active inflammation after 4 weeks of high-dose (1mg/kg prednisone equivalent)
             corticosteroid treatment or 4 weeks following a regional corticosteroid injection

          -  Treatment with oral corticosteroids resulting in a reduction of inflammation, followed
             by an increase in inflammation (of at least 1 grade in anterior chamber cells or
             vitreous haze or a change of non-active to active lesions) when corticosteroid is
             tapered, in the 180 weeks prior to enrollment

          -  Active inflammation after long-acting corticosteroid injection 4 weeks to 180 days
             prior to enrollment

          -  Active inflammation after treatment with &gt;10mg/day oral prednisone for at least the
             past 90 days prior to enrollment

          -  Known chronic condition necessitating corticosteroid-sparing immunosuppressive
             treatment: Behcet's disease with posterior segment involvement, multifocal choroiditis
             with panuveitis, serpiginous choroidopathy, birdshot retinochoroidopathy, diffuse
             retinal vasculitis, Vogt-Koyanagi-Harada with bullous serous retinal detachments
             and/or choroidal detachments, sympathetic ophthalmia. No prior therapy required for
             these patients

        Willingness to start corticosteroid treatment at 1mg/kg or 60mg a day of prednisone,
        whichever is less

        Willingness to limit alcohol consumption

        Willingness to use an acceptable method of contraception during the study period (i.e.
        pharmacologics, devices, barrier methods) or abstinence.

          -</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any of the following

        Any infectious cause of uveitis

        Prior immunosuppressive therapy other than corticosteroids in the past 12 months

        Prior intolerability or safety issues with methotrexate or mycophenolate mofetil

        Prior failure to control ocular or other inflammation using methotrexate or mycophenolate
        mofetil

        Prior biologic therapy at any time

        Media opacity (such as cataract and/or corneal scar) and/or extensive posterior synechiae
        such that examination of the posterior segment is not possible in both eyes

        Chronic hypotony (IOP &lt; 5 mm Hg for &gt; 3 months) in both eyes

        Periocular or intravitreal corticosteroid injection in the past 4 weeks

        Fluocinolone acetonide implant in either eye in &lt; 3 years

        Intraocular surgery in &lt; 30 days, or planning on getting surgery within the next 6 months

        Best spectacle-corrected visual acuity (BSCVA) of hand motions or worse in better eye

        &lt; 16 years of age at enrollment

        Planning to conceive during the study period, pregnant or breast-feeding (blood or urine
        pregnancy test for all females, excluding those who are post-menopausal is mandatory)*

        Any history of cancer (If a patient has a history of non-melanoma skin cancer they can
        still be considered for inclusion in this study, provided it is not currently active).

        Systemic autoimmune disease anticipated to dictate treatment course

        Abnormal Complete blood count (= 2,500 white blood cells and/or = 75,000 platelets and/or
        =9 hemoglobin) within 4 weeks prior to enrollment*

        Abnormal alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and/or aspartate aminotransferase (AST) = 2 times
        the upper limit of normal for the lab and/or creatinine = 1.5 within 4 weeks prior to
        enrollment*

        Evidence of active tuberculosis, HIV infection, syphilis, or hepatitis B or C (patients
        must have a tuberculin skin test, or interferon-gamma release assay, a chest radiograph,
        RPR/VDRL, FTA-ABS, or other treponemal tests, Hepatitis B surface antigen, Hepatitis C
        antibody tests, and HIV test within 90 days prior to enrollment)**

        *Testing required within 4 weeks prior to enrollment; **Testing required within 90 days
        prior to enrollment.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/08/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>216</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/08/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Victorian Eye and Ear Hospital - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3002 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Illinois</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Oregon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>India</country>
      <state>Tamil Nadu</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mexico</country>
      <state>Mexico, D.F.</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
      <state>Riyadh</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of California, San Francisco</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Aravind Eye Hospitals, India</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Oregon Health and Science University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Asociación para Evitar la Ceguera en México</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Royal Victoria Eye and Ear Hospital</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Northwestern University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Government body</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>National Eye Institute (NEI)</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>King Khaled Eye Specialist Hospital</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In the First-line Antimetabolites as Steroid-sparing Treatment (FAST) Uveitis Trial, the
      investigators propose to establish which immunosuppressive therapy, methotrexate or
      mycophenolate mofetil, is more effective as a first-line, corticosteroid-sparing agent for
      the treatment of non-infectious uveitis in a block-randomized, observer-masked, comparative
      effectiveness trial.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01829295</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Galor A, Jabs DA, Leder HA, Kedhar SR, Dunn JP, Peters GB 3rd, Thorne JE. Comparison of antimetabolite drugs as corticosteroid-sparing therapy for noninfectious ocular inflammation. Ophthalmology. 2008 Oct;115(10):1826-32. doi: 10.1016/j.ophtha.2008.04.026. Epub 2008 Jun 25.
Siepmann K, Huber M, Stübiger N, Deuter C, Zierhut M. Mycophenolate mofetil is a highly effective and safe immunosuppressive agent for the treatment of uveitis : a retrospective analysis of 106 patients. Graefes Arch Clin Exp Ophthalmol. 2006 Jul;244(7):788-94. Epub 2005 Sep 15.
Teoh SC, Hogan AC, Dick AD, Lee RW. Mycophenolate mofetil for the treatment of uveitis. Am J Ophthalmol. 2008 Nov;146(5):752-60, 760.e1-3. doi: 10.1016/j.ajo.2008.03.004. Epub 2008 May 2.
Thorne JE, Jabs DA, Qazi FA, Nguyen QD, Kempen JH, Dunn JP. Mycophenolate mofetil therapy for inflammatory eye disease. Ophthalmology. 2005 Aug;112(8):1472-7.
Larkin G, Lightman S. Mycophenolate mofetil. A useful immunosuppressive in inflammatory eye disease. Ophthalmology. 1999 Feb;106(2):370-4.
Baltatzis S, Tufail F, Yu EN, Vredeveld CM, Foster CS. Mycophenolate mofetil as an immunomodulatory agent in the treatment of chronic ocular inflammatory disorders. Ophthalmology. 2003 May;110(5):1061-5.
Choudhary A, Harding SP, Bucknall RC, Pearce IA. Mycophenolate mofetil as an immunosuppressive agent in refractory inflammatory eye disease. J Ocul Pharmacol Ther. 2006 Jun;22(3):168-75.
Bom S, Zamiri P, Lightman S. Use of methotrexate in the management of sight-threatening uveitis. Ocul Immunol Inflamm. 2001 Mar;9(1):35-40.
Dev S, McCallum RM, Jaffe GJ. Methotrexate treatment for sarcoid-associated panuveitis. Ophthalmology. 1999 Jan;106(1):111-8.
Foeldvari I, Wierk A. Methotrexate is an effective treatment for chronic uveitis associated with juvenile idiopathic arthritis. J Rheumatol. 2005 Feb;32(2):362-5.
Gangaputra S, Newcomb CW, Liesegang TL, Kaçmaz RO, Jabs DA, Levy-Clarke GA, Nussenblatt RB, Rosenbaum JT, Suhler EB, Thorne JE, Foster CS, Kempen JH; Systemic Immunosuppressive Therapy for Eye Diseases Cohort Study. Methotrexate for ocular inflammatory diseases. Ophthalmology. 2009 Nov;116(11):2188-98.e1. doi: 10.1016/j.ophtha.2009.04.020. Epub 2009 Sep 12.
Holz FG, Krastel H, Breitbart A, Schwarz-Eywill M, Pezzutto A, Völcker HE. Low-dose methotrexate treatment in noninfectious uveitis resistant to corticosteroids. Ger J Ophthalmol. 1992;1(3-4):142-4.
Shah SS, Lowder CY, Schmitt MA, Wilke WS, Kosmorsky GS, Meisler DM. Low-dose methotrexate therapy for ocular inflammatory disease. Ophthalmology. 1992 Sep;99(9):1419-23.
Taylor SR, Habot-Wilner Z, Pacheco P, Lightman SL. Intraocular methotrexate in the treatment of uveitis and uveitic cystoid macular edema. Ophthalmology. 2009 Apr;116(4):797-801. doi: 10.1016/j.ophtha.2008.10.033.
Daniel E, Thorne JE, Newcomb CW, Pujari SS, Kaçmaz RO, Levy-Clarke GA, Nussenblatt RB, Rosenbaum JT, Suhler EB, Foster CS, Jabs DA, Kempen JH. Mycophenolate mofetil for ocular inflammation. Am J Ophthalmol. 2010 Mar;149(3):423-32.e1-2. doi: 10.1016/j.ajo.2009.09.026. Epub 2009 Dec 30.
Sobrin L, Christen W, Foster CS. Mycophenolate mofetil after methotrexate failure or intolerance in the treatment of scleritis and uveitis. Ophthalmology. 2008 Aug;115(8):1416-21, 1421.e1. doi: 10.1016/j.ophtha.2007.12.011. Epub 2008 Jan 25.
Jabs DA, Nussenblatt RB, Rosenbaum JT; Standardization of Uveitis Nomenclature (SUN) Working Group. Standardization of uveitis nomenclature for reporting clinical data. Results of the First International Workshop. Am J Ophthalmol. 2005 Sep;140(3):509-16. Review.
Jabs DA, Rosenbaum JT, Foster CS, Holland GN, Jaffe GJ, Louie JS, Nussenblatt RB, Stiehm ER, Tessler H, Van Gelder RN, Whitcup SM, Yocum D. Guidelines for the use of immunosuppressive drugs in patients with ocular inflammatory disorders: recommendations of an expert panel. Am J Ophthalmol. 2000 Oct;130(4):492-513. Review.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Nisha Acharya, MD, MS</name>
      <address>University of California, San Francisco</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Nisha Acharya, MD, MS</name>
      <address />
      <phone>4154768183</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nisha.acharya@ucsf.edu</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>