<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5734">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/04/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/04/2015</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02434263</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Clinical Evaluation of the HYDRA Self Expanding Transcatheter Aortic Valve</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Clinical Evaluation of the HYDRA Self Expanding Transcatheter Aortic Valve</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>VI-CL-HYDRA-02</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Aortic Valve Stenosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - Hydra TAVI

Experimental: Hydra TAVI - Percutaneous Replacement of the Diseased Aortic Valve


Treatment: devices: Hydra TAVI
Percutaneous Replacement of the Diseased Aortic Valve

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>All cause mortality - 30-day mortality of procedure is defined as all deaths occurred in subjects attending the Hydra prosthesis implantation within 30 days post procedure. All deaths include in-hospital mortality, cardiac death, valve-related death, and death of unknown cause</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Procedural Success - Composite outcome measures consisting of Effective orifice area, mean aortic valve gradient, degree of prosthetic valve regurgitation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 6, and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Aortic annulus diameter meets the range 18 to 28mm as measured by CT conducted within
             the past 120 days, or echocardiogram (TEE 3D recommended) if medically contraindicated
             to CT.

          2. Patient has severe degenerative aortic stenosis with echocardiography derived mean
             gradient &gt;40mmHg and/or peak velocity greater than 4.0 m/s and/or an initial valve
             area of &lt;1.0 cm2.

          3. Patient has symptomatic aortic stenosis as demonstrated by NYHA Functional
             Classification of II or greater.

          4. Patient is deemed high operable risk and suitable for TAVI.

          5. Patient's predicted operative mortality or serious, irreversible morbidity risk is
             &lt;50% at 30 days.

          6. Patient has structurally normal cardiac anatomy.

          7. Willing and able to comply with all required follow-up evaluation</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>55</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Patient has a history of a cerebral vascular accident (CVA) or transient ischemic
             attack (TIA) within the past 6 months.

          2. Patient has carotid artery disease requiring intervention.

          3. Patient has evidence of a myocardial infarction (MI) within the past 6 months.

          4. Patient has hypertrophic cardiomyopathy.

          5. Patient has a native aortic valve that is congenitally uni-cuspid, bicuspid,
             quadricuspid or non-calcified as seen by echocardiography.

          6. Patient has mitral or tricuspid valvular regurgitation (&gt; grade III) or moderate to
             severe mitral stenosis.

          7. Patient has aortic root angulation &gt;70 degrees (horizontal aorta).

          8. Patient has aortic root diameter of &lt; 26 mm or &gt;36 mm.

          9. Patient has a pre-existing prosthetic valve or prosthetic ring in any position.

         10. Patient refuses blood transfusion or surgical valve replacement.

         11. Patient has resting left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) &lt; 20%.

         12. Patient has documented, untreated symptomatic coronary artery disease (CAD) requiring
             revascularization.

         13. Patient has severe basal septal hypertrophy.

         14. Patient has had a percutaneous interventional or other invasive cardiac or peripheral
             procedure = 14 days of the index procedure (does not apply for diagnostic angiography
             or Angio-CT).

         15. Patient has a history of or has active endocarditis.

         16. Patient has echocardiographic evidence of intracardiac mass, thrombus, or vegetation.

         17. Patient has hemodynamic instability (requiring inotropic support or mechanical heart
             assistance).

         18. Patient is in acute pulmonary edema or requiring intravenous diuretic therapy to
             stabilize heart failure.

         19. Patient with significant pulmonary disease (FEV1 &lt; 30% as predicted).

         20. Patient has significant chronic steroid use as determined and documented by the
             Principle Investigator.

         21. Patient has a known hypersensitivity or contraindication to anticoagulant or
             antiplatelet medication.

         22. Patient has renal insufficiency as evidenced by a serum creatinine &gt; 3.0 mg/dL
             (265.5µmol/L) or end-stage renal disease requiring chronic dialysis.

         23. Patient's iliofemoral arteries have severe calcification, tortuosity (&gt;two 90 degree
             bends), diameter &lt;6mm, or subject has had an aorta-femoral bypass that preclude safe
             placement of a 18 French sheath.

         24. Patient has blood dyscrasia (leukopenia, acute anemia, thrombocytopenia, bleeding
             diathesis, or coagulopathy).

         25. Patient has a current autoimmune disease that, in the opinion of the Principal
             Investigator precludes the subject from study participation.

         26. Patient has significant aortic disease.

         27. Patient has a pre-existing endovascular stent graft in the supra- or infrarenal aorta
             or pre-existing stent grafts in the iliofemoral arteries.

         28. Patient has an active peptic ulcer or has had gastrointestinal (GI) bleeding within
             the past 90 days prior to procedure

         29. Patient has a life expectancy &lt; 12 months.

         30. Patient has other medical, social or psychological conditions that, in the opinion of
             the Principal Investigator, preclude the subject from study participation.

         31. Patient has a known allergy to contrast media, nitinol alloys or bovine tissue.

         32. Patient has a history of any cognitive or mental health status that would interfere
             with study participation.

         33. Currently participating in another trial.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>70</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/12/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Hamilton</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Vascular Innovations Co. Ltd.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>MedPass International</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is the evaluation of the performance, safety and efficacy of Hydra
      Aortic valve in real-world patients. Following initial implantation, all patients will have
      clinical follow up at 30 days, 3, months, 6 months and 12 months</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02434263</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Stephanie Simpson</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+33142128861</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>stephaniesimpson@medpass.org</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>