<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2675">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/02/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/02/2010</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01074944</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Study of Eliglustat Tartrate (Genz-112638) in Patients With Gaucher Disease to Evaluate Once Daily Versus Twice Daily Dosing (EDGE)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 3, Randomized, Multi-Center, Multi-National, Double-Blind Study to Evaluate the Efficacy, Safety and Pharmacokinetics of Once Daily Versus Twice Daily Dosing of Genz-112638 in Patients With Gaucher Disease Type 1 Who Have Demonstrated Clinical Stability on a Twice Daily Dose of Genz-112638</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>2009-015811-42</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>GZGD03109</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Gaucher Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human Genetics and Inherited Disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other human genetics and inherited disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Eliglustat tartrate

Experimental: Twice Daily (BID) Dose Regimen - Patients will receive either 50 mg BID or 100 mg BID

Experimental: Once Daily (QD) Dose Regimen - Patients will receive either 100 mg QD or 200 mg QD


Treatment: drugs: Eliglustat tartrate
Oral Capsule in 50 mg or 100 mg dosages

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PAP: Percentage of Participants Who Remained Stable for 52 Weeks During the PAP - Participants were considered as stable if they met all of the following criteria: 1) no more than 2 bone crisis during PAP (with no more than 1 bone crisis during either the first 6 months or the later 6 months of the period), and were free of other clinically symptomatic bone disease during the entire 52-week PAP; 2) hemoglobin level not decreased &gt;1.5 g/dL from Baseline for PAP; 3) platelet count not decreased &gt;25% from Baseline for PAP; 4) spleen volume (in multiples of normal [MN]) did not increase &gt;25% from Baseline for PAP; 5) liver volume (in MN) did not increase &gt;20% from Baseline for PAP. Baseline for PAP was defined as the last assessment prior to randomization.</outcome>
      <timepoint>PAP Baseline up to the end of PAP (Week 52)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PAP: Mean Hemoglobin (Hb) Level at Baseline, Weeks 26 and 52</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 26, Week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PAP: Mean Platelet Count at Baseline, Weeks 26, 52</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 26, Week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PAP: Mean Spleen Volume at Baseline, Weeks 26, 52</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 26, Week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PAP: Mean Liver Volume at Baseline, Weeks 26, 52</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 26 and Week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PAP: Mean Biomarker (Chitotriosidase) Value at Baseline, Weeks 26 and Week 52 - Chitotriosidase biomarker was assayed from plasma.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 26, Week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PAP: Mean Biomarker (GL-1 on DBS) Value at Baseline, Week 26 and Week 52 - GL-1 on DBS biomarker was assayed from dried blood spot (DBS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 26 and week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PAP: Mean Biomarker Macrophage Inflammatory Protein-1 Beta (MIP1-beta) Value at Baseline, Weeks 26, 52 - MIP1-beta biomarker was assayed from plasma.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 26, Week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PAP: Bone Mineral Density (BMD) at Baseline and Week 52 - BMD measurements of the spine and bilateral femur were acquired by dual-energy x-ray absorptiometry (DXA) scan.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PAP: Total T-Scores for BMD at Baseline and Week 52 - Images of the spine and bilateral femur were obtained by DXA to determine T-score for each bone area and total bone mineral density. The T-score bone density categories were: normal (score &gt;-1), osteopenia (score -2.5 to &lt;=-1), and osteoporosis (score &lt;= -2.5).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PAP: Total Z-scores for BMD at Baseline and Week 52 - Images of the spine and bilateral femur were obtained by DXA to determine Z-score for each bone area and total bone mineral density. The Z-score bone density categories are: normal (score &gt;-2) and below normal (score &lt;=-2).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PAP: Number of Participants With Mobility Status Asessments (MS) at Baseline, Weeks 26, and 52. - Mobility, i.e., ability to walk was assessed as a part of Gaucher disease assessment in participants. In this outcome, number of participants with their different mobility status along with the use of mobility aids (unrestricted mobility, walks with difficulty, walks with orthopaedic aid, requires wheelchair, bedridden) at specified time points were reported.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 26 and Week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PAP: Number of Participants With Bone Crises at Baseline, Weeks 26 and 52 - Bone crisis was assessed as a part of Gaucher disease assessment in participants. Acute, excruciating episodic bone pain is characteristic of Gaucher bone crisis, which typically causes debilitation lasting several days or longer and requires treatment with immobilization, hydration, and opioid analgesics. Participants were categorized as 0= no bone crisis, 1= 1 bone crisis, and 2= 2 bone crises during the assessment period. In this outcome, number of participants with different bone crises levels at specified time points were reported.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 26, and Week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PAP: Number of Participants With Bone Pain Levels During the Past 4 Weeks at Baseline, Weeks 26 and 52 - Bone pain was assessed as a part of Gaucher disease assessment in participants. Participants were categorized as none (no bone pain), very mild bone pain, mild bone pain, moderate bone pain, severe bone pain and extreme bone pain during the past 4 weeks. In this outcome, number of participants with different level of bone pain during the past 4 weeks at specified time points were reported.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 26, and Week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PAP: Total Bone Marrow Burden Score (BMB) at Baseline and Week 52 - BMB Score was measured using magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), range from 0 (no abnormalities) to 8 points (severe disease) for the lumbar spine and from 0 (no abnormalities) to 8 points (severe disease) for the femurs. The total score was calculated as the sum of scores for femur and lumbar spine regions which ranged from 0 (no abnormalities) -16 (severe disease) points. A higher BMB score signified more severe bone marrow involvement.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>LIP: Mean Hemoglobin (Hb) Level at Baseline, Weeks 26, 52 and 78</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 26, Week, 52, and Week 78</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>LIP: Mean Platelet Count at Baseline, Weeks 26, 52 and 78</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 26, Week 52, Week 78</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>LIP: Mean Liver Volume at Baseline, Weeks 26, 52 and 78</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 26, Week 52, Week 78</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>LIP: Mean Spleen Volume at Baseline, Weeks 26, 52 and 78</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 26, Week 52, Week 78</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>LIP: Mean Biomarker (Chitotriosidase) Value at Baseline, Weeks 26, 52, and 78 - Chitotriosidase biomarker was assayed from plasma.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 26, Week 52 and Week 78</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>LIP: Mean Biomarker (GL-1 on DBS) Value at Baseline, Week 26, Week 52, and Week 78 - GL-1 on DBS biomarker was assayed from dried blood spot.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 26, Week 52 and Week 78</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>LIP: Mean Biomarker (MIP1-beta) Value at Baseline, Week 78 - MIP1-beta biomarker was assayed from plasma.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Week 78</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>LIP: Number of Participants With Mobility Status (MS) at Baseline, Weeks 26, 52 and 78 - Mobility, i.e., ability to walk was assessed as a part of Gaucher disease assessment in participants. In this outcome, number of participants with their different mobility status along with the use of mobility aids (unrestricted mobility, walks with difficulty, walks with orthopaedic aid, requires wheelchair, bedridden) at specified time points were reported.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 26, Week 52, Week 78</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>LIP: Number of Participants With Bone Crises Assessment at Baseline, Weeks 26, 52 and 78 - Bone crises was assessed as a part of Gaucher disease assessment in participants. Acute, excruciating episodic bone pain is characteristic of Gaucher bone crises, which typically causes debilitation lasting several days or longer and requires treatment with immobilization, hydration, and opioid analgesics. Participants were categorized as 0= no bone crisis, 1= 1 bone crisis, 2= 2 bone crises, 6= 6 bone crises, and 24= 24 bone crises during the assessment period. In this outcome, number of participants with different bone crises levels at specified time points were reported.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 26, Week 52, Week 78</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>LIP: Number of Participants With Bone Pain Levels During the Past 4 Weeks at Baseline, Weeks 26, 52 and 78 - Bone pain was assessed as a part of Gaucher disease assessment in participants. Participants were categorized as none (no bone pain), very mild bone pain, mild bone pain, moderate bone pain, severe bone pain and extreme bone pain. In this outcome, number of participants with different type of bone pain during the past 4 weeks at specified time points were reported.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 26, Week 52, Week 78</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>LTTP: Percentage of Participants Who Maintained a Stable Bone Criterion ,Hemoglobin Level, Platelet Count, Liver Volume and Spleen Volume at 1 Year and 2 Years - Participant were considered as stable if they met the following criteria: hemoglobin level did not decrease &gt;1.5 g/dL from baseline for PAP, platelet count does not decrease &gt;25% below Baseline for PAP, liver volume does not increase &gt;20% above Baseline for PAP, spleen volume does not increase &gt;25% above Baseline for PAP. Baseline for PAP was defined as last available assessment prior to randomization.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 Year, 2 Years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>LTTP: Number of Participants With Mobility Status (MS) at Baseline, 1 Year and 2 Years - Mobility, i.e., ability to walk was assessed as a part of Gaucher disease assessment in participants. In this outcome, number of participants with their different mobility status along with the use of mobility aids (unrestricted mobility, walks with difficulty, walks with orthopaedic aid, requires wheelchair, bedridden) at specified time points were reported.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1 year, and 2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>LTTP: Number of Participants With Bone Crises Assessment at Baseline, 1 Year and 2 Years - Bone crises was assessed as a part of Gaucher disease assessment in participants. Acute, excruciating episodic bone pain is characteristic of Gaucher bone crises, which typically causes debilitation lasting several days or longer and requires treatment with immobilization, hydration, and opioid analgesics. Participants were categorized as 0= no bone crises, 1= 1 bone crisis during the assessment period. In this outcome, number of participants with different bone crises levels at specified time points were reported.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1 year and 2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>LTTP: Number of Participants With Bone Pain Levels During the Past 4 Weeks at Baseline, 1 Year, and 2 Years - Bone pain was assessed as a part of Gaucher disease assessment in participants. Participants were categorized as none (no bone pain), very mild bone pain, mild bone pain, moderate bone pain, severe bone pain and extreme bone pain. In this outcome, number of participants with different level of bone pain during the past 4 weeks at specified time points were reported.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1 year and 2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>LTTP: Bone Mineral Density (BMD) at Baseline, 1 Year, and 2 Years - BMD measurements of the spine and bilateral femur were acquired by DXA scan.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1 year, and 2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>LTTP: Total T-Scores for BMD at Baseline, 1 Year, and 2 Years - Images of the spine and bilateral femur were obtained by DXA to determine T-score for each bone area and total bone mineral density. The T-score bone density categories were: normal (score &gt;-1), osteopenia (score -2.5 to &lt;=-1), and osteoporosis (score &lt;= -2.5).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1 year, and 2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>LTTP: Total Z-scores for BMD at Baseline, 1 Year, and 2 Years - Images of the spine and bilateral femur were obtained by DXA to determine Z-score for each bone area and total bone mineral density. The Z-score bone density categories are: normal (score &gt;-2) and below normal (score &lt;=-2).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1 year, and 2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>LTTP: Total Bone Marrow Burden Score (BMB) at Baseline, 1 Year, and 2 Years - BMB Score was measured using MRI, range from 0 (no abnormalities) to 8 points (severe disease) for the lumbar spine and from 0 (no abnormalities) to 8 points (severe disease) for the femurs. The total score was calculated as the sum of scores for femur and lumbar spine regions which ranged from 0 (no abnormalities) -16 (severe disease) points. A higher BMB score signified more severe bone marrow involvement.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1 year, and 2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>LTTP: Mean Biomarker (Chitotriosidase) Value at Baseline, 1 Year, and 2 Years - Chitotriosidase biomarker was assayed from plasma.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1 year, and 2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>LTTP: Mean Biomarker (GL-1 on DBS) Value at Baseline, 1 Year, and 2 Years - GL-1 on DBS biomarker was assayed from dried blood spot.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1 year, and 2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>LTTP: Mean Biomarker (MIP1-beta) Value at Baseline, 1 Year, and 2 Years - MIP1-beta biomarker was assayed from plasma.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1 year, and 2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  The participant who was willing and provided signed informed consent prior to any
             study-related procedures.

          -  The participant was =18 years of age.

          -  The participant diagnosed with GD 1 confirmed by a documented deficiency of acid
             ß-glucosidase activity by enzyme assay.

          -  Female participants of childbearing potential had a documented negative pregnancy test
             prior to administration of the first dose of eliglustat tartrate (Genz-112638) in this
             study. In addition, all female participants of childbearing potential used a medically
             accepted form of contraception throughout the study, i.e., either a barrier method or
             hormonal contraceptive with norethindrone and ethinyl estradiol or similar active
             components

          -  The participant met all of the following criteria at the time of screening: hemoglobin
             level =9 g/dL (mean of 2 measurements); platelet count =70,000/mm^3 (mean of 2
             measurements); spleen volume =25 multiples of normal (MN); liver volume =2.0 MN.

          -  The participant consented to provide a blood sample for genotyping for Gaucher disease
             and for CYP2D6 to categorize the participant's predicted rate of metabolism, if these
             genotyping results were not already available for the participant.

          -  The participant was willing to abstain from consumption of grapefruit, grapefruit
             juice, or grapefruit products for 72 hours prior to administration of the first dose
             of Genz-112638 and throughout the duration of the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  The participant was participating in GZGD02607 study, "A Phase 3, Randomized,
             Multi-Center, Multi-National, Open-Label, Active Comparator Study to Evaluate the
             Efficacy and Safety of Genz-112638 in Participants with GD1 who have been Stabilized
             with Cerezyme ® ," or was eligible for inclusion in GZGD02607 (while enrollment was
             ongoing) and had access to a physician participating in GZGD02607, or the participant
             was participating in GZGD02507 study, "A Phase 3, Randomized, Double-Blind,
             Placebo-Controlled, Multi-Center Study Confirming the Efficacy and Safety of
             Genz-112638 in Participants with GD1," or was eligible for inclusion in GZGD02507
             (while enrollment was ongoing) and had access to a physician participating in
             GZGD02507.

          -  The participant received miglustat within 6 months prior to administration of the
             first dose of Genz-112638 in this study.

          -  The participant had a partial or total splenectomy within 3 years prior to
             randomization.

          -  The participant received pharmacological chaperones or miglustat within 6 months prior
             to administration of the first dose of eliglustat tartrate (Genz-112638) in this
             study.

          -  The participant had any evidence of neurologic disorder (e.g., peripheral neuropathy,
             tremor, seizures, Parkinsonism or cognitive impairment) or pulmonary involvement
             (e.g., pulmonary hypertension) as related to Gaucher disease.

          -  The participant was transfusion-dependent.

          -  The participant had a documented deficiency of iron, vitamin B-12, or folate that
             requires treatment not yet initiated or, if initiated, the participant had not been
             stable under treatment for at least 3 months prior to administration of the first dose
             of Genz-112638 in this study.

          -  The participant had documented prior esophageal varices or clinically significant
             liver infarction or current liver enzymes (alanine transaminase [ALT]/aspartate
             aminotransferase [AST]) or total bilirubin &gt;2 times the upper limit of normal (ULN),
             unless the participant had a diagnosis of Gilbert Syndrome.

          -  The participant had any clinically significant disease, other than Gaucher disease,
             including cardiovascular, renal, hepatic, gastrointestinal, pulmonary, neurologic,
             endocrine, metabolic (including hypokalaemia or hypomagnesemia), or psychiatric
             disease, other medical conditions, or serious intercurrent illnesses that, in the
             opinion of the Investigator, precluded participation in the study.

          -  The participant was known to have any of the following: Clinically significant
             coronary artery disease including history of myocardial infarction [MI] or ongoing
             signs or symptoms consistent with cardiac ischemia or heart failure; or clinically
             significant arrhythmias or conduction defect such as 2nd or 3rd degree AV block,
             complete bundle branch block, prolonged QTc interval, or sustained ventricular
             tachycardia (VT).

          -  The participant who tested positive for the human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)
             antibody, Hepatitis C antibody, or Hepatitis B surface antigen.

          -  The participant received an investigational product (other than eliglustat tartrate
             (Genz-112638)) within 30 days prior to administration of the first dose of eliglustat
             tartrate (Genz-112638) in this study.

          -  The participant was scheduled for in-participant hospitalization, including elective
             surgery, during the study.

          -  The participant had a history of cancer, with the exception of basal cell carcinoma,
             within 5 years prior to administration of the first dose of Genz-112638 in this study.

          -  The participant was pregnant or lactating.

          -  The participant had received any medication that may cause QTc interval prolongation
             within 30 days prior to the first dose of Genz-112638. Exception: Diphenhydramine
             (Benadryl) or other medications used as premedication for ERT infusions were allowed
             up to 7 days prior to the first dose of Genz-112638.

          -  The participant had received for the first time (i.e., the participant was not already
             chronically using) any of the following medications within 30 days prior to the first
             dose of Genz-112638:

               -  Strong inhibitors of CYP2D6 or CYP3A4;

               -  Inducers of CYP3A4. Exception: Premedications for ERT infusions were allowed up
                  to 7 days prior to the first dose of Genz-112638.

          -  The participant was a CYP2D6 non-poor metabolizer or an indeterminate metabolizer with
             one allele identified as active who was chronically receiving both a strong
             competitive inhibitor of CYP2D6 and a strong competitive inhibitor of CYP3A4 and for
             whom no reasonable alternative medication exists. or

          -  The participant was a CYP2D6 poor metabolizer or an indeterminate metabolizer with
             neither allele known to be active who was chronically receiving a strong competitive
             inhibitor of CYP3A4 and for whom no reasonable alternative medication exists.

        Exception for both cases: Premedications for ERT infusions were allowed up to 7 days prior
        to the first dose of Genz-112638.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2>The people administering the treatment/s</masking2>
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/06/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>170</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/10/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Clayton, VIC</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Perth Hospital - Perth, WA</hospital>
    <postcode> - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode> - Clayton, VIC</postcode>
    <postcode> - Perth, WA</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Connecticut</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Georgia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Illinois</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Pennsylvania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Utah</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Virginia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Austria</country>
      <state>Vienna</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Belo Horizonte</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Brasília</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Campinas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Cuiaba</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Fortaleza</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Franca</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Rio de Janeiro</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Sao Paulo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Toronto</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Beijing</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Shanghai</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Tianjin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Croatia</country>
      <state>Zagreb</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Bordeaux</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Bron</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Athens</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>India</country>
      <state>Mumbai</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Hiroshima</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Tokyo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Tsu, Mie</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Amsterdam</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <state>Lisboa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <state>Ponta Delgada - São Miguel - Açores</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Romania</country>
      <state>Cluj-Napoca</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Chelyabinsk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Moscow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>St. Petersburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Serbia</country>
      <state>Belgrade</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Lund</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Genzyme, a Sanofi Company</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary objective of this study was to evaluate the efficacy and safety of once daily
      (QD) versus twice daily (BID) dosing of eliglustat tartrate (Genz-112638) in participants
      with Gaucher disease type 1 who had demonstrated clinical stability on BID dosing of
      eliglustat tartrate (Genz-112638). The secondary objective was to evaluate the
      pharmacokinetics (PK) of Genz-99067 when eliglustat tartrate (Genz-112638) was administered
      QD and BID in participants with Gaucher disease type 1 who had demonstrated clinical
      stability on BID dosing of eliglustat tartrate (Genz-112638).</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01074944</trialwebsite>
    <publication>McEachern KA, Fung J, Komarnitsky S, Siegel CS, Chuang WL, Hutto E, Shayman JA, Grabowski GA, Aerts JM, Cheng SH, Copeland DP, Marshall J. A specific and potent inhibitor of glucosylceramide synthase for substrate inhibition therapy of Gaucher disease. Mol Genet Metab. 2007 Jul;91(3):259-67. Epub 2007 May 16.
Lukina E, Watman N, Arreguin EA, Banikazemi M, Dragosky M, Iastrebner M, Rosenbaum H, Phillips M, Pastores GM, Rosenthal DI, Kaper M, Singh T, Puga AC, Bonate PL, Peterschmitt MJ. A phase 2 study of eliglustat tartrate (Genz-112638), an oral substrate reduction therapy for Gaucher disease type 1. Blood. 2010 Aug 12;116(6):893-9. doi: 10.1182/blood-2010-03-273151. Epub 2010 May 3.
Lukina E, Watman N, Arreguin EA, Dragosky M, Iastrebner M, Rosenbaum H, Phillips M, Pastores GM, Kamath RS, Rosenthal DI, Kaper M, Singh T, Puga AC, Peterschmitt MJ. Improvement in hematological, visceral, and skeletal manifestations of Gaucher disease type 1 with oral eliglustat tartrate (Genz-112638) treatment: 2-year results of a phase 2 study. Blood. 2010 Nov 18;116(20):4095-8. doi: 10.1182/blood-2010-06-293902. Epub 2010 Aug 16. Erratum in: Blood. 2011 May 19;117(20):5551.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Medical Monitor</name>
      <address>Genzyme, a Sanofi Company</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>