<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2104">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/09/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/09/2008</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00752791</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy and Safety of Peginesatide Injection for the Maintenance Treatment of Anemia in Peritoneal Dialysis Participants Previously Treated With Epoetin.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 2 Study of the Safety and Efficacy of Hematide Injection for the Maintenance Treatment of Anemia in Peritoneal Dialysis Subjects Previously Treated With Epoetin</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>2008-003458-13</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>AFX01_201</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Anemia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaemia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Peginesatide

Experimental: Peginesatide - 


Treatment: drugs: Peginesatide
Peginesatide 0.04 to 0.16 mg/kg, subcutaneous injection, once every 4 weeks for up to 25 weeks. Initial dose based on patient's previous total weekly Epoetin dose, and thereafter could be adjusted to maintain hemoglobin values in the target range of 10 to 12 g/dL and ±1.5 g/dL from Baseline.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Change in Hemoglobin Between Baseline and the Evaluation Period - The primary efficacy endpoint was the mean change in Hemoglobin between Baseline (the mean of the 4 most recent hemoglobin values prior to Enrollment and the hemoglobin on the day of Enrollment) and the Evaluation Period (mean hemoglobin from Weeks 20 to 25).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Week 20 to Week 25.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants With Hemoglobin Within the Target Range of 10.0 to 12.0 g/dL During the Evaluation Period - Mean hemoglobin was calculated from measurements taken during the Evaluation Period (Week 20 to Week 25). The target hemoglobin range was 10.0 to 12.0 g/dL.
The 95% confidence interval was calculated from the normal approximation with continuity correction.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 20 to Week 25.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants With a Change in Hemoglobin From Baseline to the Evaluation Period Within 1 g/dL - Percentage of participants with a mean change in Hemoglobin between Baseline (the mean of the 4 most recent hemoglobin values prior to enrollment and the hemoglobin on the day of enrollment) and the Evaluation Period (mean hemoglobin from measured at Weeks 20 to 25) of less than or equal ± 1 g/dL. The 95% confidence interval was calculated from the normal approximation with continuity correction.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Week 20 to Week 25.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants With Red Blood Cell Transfusions - The percentage of participants who received one or more red blood cell transfusions, including packed red blood cells and whole blood transfusions, during the Titration Period (Weeks 1 - 19) and Evaluation Period (Weeks 20 -25). 95% Confidence Intervals were calculated from the normal approximation with continuity correction. One patient had the last study visit during the titration period and the transfusion after the titration period. This patient is excluded from the summary of evaluation period.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 25 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Hemoglobin During 4-week Intervals - Hemoglobin was measured every 2 weeks during the Titration Period (Weeks 1-19) and weekly during the Evaluation Period (Weeks 20-25). One patient did not have central lab hemoglobin value during a regularly scheduled visit during weeks 2-5.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 25 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants With Target Hemoglobin of 10.0 to 12.0 g/dL by 4-week Intervals - Percentage of participants with mean hemoglobin levels falling between the target level of 10.0 to 12.0 g/dL during 4-week study intervals. Hemoglobin was measured every 2 weeks during the Titration Period (Weeks 1-19) and weekly during the Evaluation Period (Weeks 20-25). 95% Confidence Intervals were calculated from the normal approximation with continuity correction.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 25 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants With Dose Adjustments During the Study - The peginesatide dose was adjusted to maintain hemoglobin values in the target range of 10 to 12 g/dL and ±1.5 g/dL from Baseline during the Titration Period (Weeks 1-19) and Evaluation Period (Weeks 20-25). A dose was classified as adjusted if it was not within 20% of the previous dose. A dose was classified as increased or decreased if it was &gt;20% higher or &gt;20% lower respectively, than the previous dose.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Week 4 to Week 25</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. The patient was a man or woman and 18 to 90 years of age, inclusive.

          2. The patient had CKD and had been on peritoneal dialysis for =3 months before
             enrollment.

          3. The patient was on stable SC epoetin (alfa or beta) maintenance therapy continuously
             prescribed for a minimum of 8 weeks prior to enrollment.

          4. The patient had 4 consecutive Hb values with a mean =10.0 and =12.0 g/dL during the
             screening period, with the difference between the mean of the first confirmed (2
             consecutive) Hb values and the mean of the last confirmed (2 consecutive) Hb values
             being =1.0 g/dL.

          5. The patient had 1 ferritin level =100 ng/mL within 4 weeks before enrollment.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>90</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. The patient had known bleeding or coagulation disorder.

          2. The patient had known hematologic disease or cause of anemia other than renal disease
             (e.g., pure red cell aplasia, homozygous sickle-cell disease, thalassemia, multiple
             myeloma, hemolytic anemia, and myelodysplastic syndrome).

          3. The patient had received a recent course of intensive iron replacement (i.e., more
             than 500 mg IV in the 28 days before enrollment).

          4. The patient had advanced chronic congestive heart failure defined by New York Heart
             Association Class III or IV.

          5. The patient had a known history of seizure disorder or received antiepileptic
             medication for a seizure disorder within 6 months before enrollment.

          6. The patient had a scheduled kidney transplant. (Note: patients who were currently on a
             transplant waiting list were not excluded unless there was an identified donor).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/10/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>59</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/05/2010</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital> - New Lambtom</hospital>
    <postcode> - New Lambtom</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Georgia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Illinois</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Kansas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Louisiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Mississippi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Virginia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Modena</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Dunedin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>England</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Takeda</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Affymax</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to determine the efficacy and safety of peginesatide injection
      for maintenance treatment of anemia in participants on peritoneal dialysis.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00752791</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Medical Director</name>
      <address>Takeda</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>