<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="131">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/08/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/08/2010</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01180231</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Study of the Effect of Moxonidine and Diet on Sympathetic Functions in Young Adults With Obesity</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Assessment of the Effect of Moxonidine and Diet on Cardiac, Renal and Endothelial Function in Young Subjects With Abdominal Obesity</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Project 168-10</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Overweight</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Moxonidine (Physiotens)
Other interventions - Dietary intervention

Active Comparator: Moxonidine - 

Active Comparator: Diet - 

Active Comparator: Moxonidine and diet - Subjects will be asked to take moxonidine and follow dietary plan designed by a qualified nutritionist for 6 months.

No Intervention: Control - Subjects will not be asked to take any interventions.


Treatment: drugs: Moxonidine (Physiotens)
Subjects will be asked to take moxonidine, dosage to be determined prior to commencement by a medical doctor for 6 months duration.

Other interventions: Dietary intervention
Subjects will be asked to follow dietary plans designed by a qualified nutritionist for 6 months.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine whether moxonidine is able to reverse the early organ damage compared to the effect of weight loss alone, and whether the addition of moxonidine during a weight loss program confers greater beneficial effect.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Males age between 18 to 30 years old

          -  Abdominal obesity according to International Diabetes Federation (IDF) definition</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>30</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Male</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Any medications

          -  history of cardiovascular disease

          -  history of diabetes

          -  history of psychiatric illness</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/09/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>77</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Unknown status</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/09/2014</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>BakerIDI Heart and Diabetes Institute - Prahran</hospital>
    <postcode>3004 - Prahran</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Baker IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The prevalence of obesity is increasing rapidly among adults and has more than doubled in the
      past 10 years. The metabolic syndrome (MS) is often associated with obesity. It is
      characterized by abdominal obesity, high blood pressure, unfavorable blood cholesterol
      profile, elevated blood sugar and impaired insulin action. Persons with the MS have an
      increased risk of developing type 2 diabetes as well as heart and kidney disease.

      The prevalence of obesity and MS is also very high in children and young adults. While there
      are increasing numbers of studies assessing risk factors for cardiovascular and kidney
      disease in middle aged to older obese subjects, few studies have addressed the issue of the
      presence of obesity in young adults and its association with MS on early damage to the organs
      such as the kidneys, the heart and the blood vessels. The investigators' laboratory has a
      particular interest on the sympathetic nervous system, which is an important regulatory
      mechanism of both metabolic and cardiovascular function, as altered sympathetic activity may
      play a role in the complications of obesity.

      Moxonidine is a medication that is approved in Australia by the Therapeutic Goods
      Administration to treat high blood pressure. It works by decreasing the activity of the
      sympathetic nervous system. With the elevation of the sympathetic activity in obesity, the
      investigators believe moxonidine may have a favourable role in rescuing early organ damage
      associated with obesity. This study will assess whether treating obese subjects with
      moxonidine have positive effects on blood vessels, cardiac and kidney function and anxiety
      disorder. The investigators will also examine the influence of the sympathetic nervous system
      activity in these possible altered cardiac, kidney and vessel functions.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01180231</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Elisabeth Lambert, PhD</name>
      <address />
      <phone>03 8532 1345</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>elisabeth.lambert@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>