<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5266">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/12/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/12/2015</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02622321</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Study to Evaluate the Efficacy, Safety, and Pharmacokinetics of Prophylactic Emicizumab Versus no Prophylaxis in Hemophilia A Participants With Inhibitors</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomized, Multicenter, Open-Label, Phase III Clinical Trial to Evaluate the Efficacy, Safety, and Pharmacokinetics of Prophylactic Emicizumab Versus no Prophylaxis in Hemophilia A Patients With Inhibitors</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>HAVEN 1</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>2015-002866-21</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>BH29884</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hemophilia A</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Clotting disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human Genetics and Inherited Disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other human genetics and inherited disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Emicizumab
Treatment: drugs - rFVIIa

Experimental: Arm A (Episodic Treatment): Emicizumab - Participants who received episodic treatment with bypassing agents prior to study entry will be randomized to receive prophylactic emicizumab. Participants will continue to receive episodic bypassing agent therapy to treat breakthrough bleeds, preferably with recombinant activated factor VII (rFVIIa) at the lowest expected dose to achieve hemostasis.

Active Comparator: Arm B (Episodic Treatment): No Emicizumab - Participants who received episodic treatment with bypassing agents prior to study entry will be randomized to not receive prophylaxis. These participants will have the opportunity to switch to emicizumab prophylaxis after 24 weeks on-study. Participants will continue to receive episodic bypassing agent therapy to treat breakthrough bleeds, preferably with rFVIIa at the lowest expected dose to achieve hemostasis.

Experimental: Arm C (Prophylactic Treatment): Emicizumab - Participants on prophylactic bypassing agents prior to study entry will be enrolled to receive prophylactic emicizumab. Participants may receive episodic bypassing agent therapy to treat breakthrough bleeds, preferably with rFVIIa at the lowest expected dose to achieve hemostasis.

Experimental: Arm D (Episodic or Prophylactic Treatment): Emicizumab - Participants on episodic bypassing agents prior to study entry, who participated in Study BH29768 but were unable to enroll in Arms A or B, or participants on prophylactic bypassing agents who were unable to enroll in Arm C, will be enrolled in this arm to receive prophylactic emicizumab. Participants will continue to receive episodic bypassing agent therapy to treat breakthrough bleeds, preferably with rFVIIa at the lowest expected dose to achieve hemostasis.


Treatment: drugs: Emicizumab
Emicizumab will be administered subcutaneously at a dose of 3 milligrams per kilogram per week (mg/kg/week) for 4 weeks followed by 1.5 mg/kg/week up to the end of the study.

Treatment: drugs: rFVIIa
In case of a breakthrough bleed, participants will receive a bypassing agent, preferably rFVIIa, at the lowest expected dose to achieve hemostasis (no more than 90 micrograms per kilogram as an initial dose).

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Arms A and B: Number of Bleeds Over Time</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline up to 24 weeks or discontinuation from the study, whichever occurs first</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Arm A and B: Reduction in Number of All Bleeds (Whether Treated or not Treated by Coagulation Factors) From Baseline to 24 Weeks</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Arm A and B: Reduction in Number of Spontaneous Bleeds From Baseline to 24 Weeks</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Arm A and B: Reduction in Number of Joint Bleeds From Baseline to 24 Weeks</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Arm A and B: Reduction in Number of Target Joint Bleeds From Baseline to 24 Weeks</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Arm A and B: Hemophilia-Specific Quality of Life (Haem-A-QoL) Questionnaire Score in Adult (&gt;/= 18 years of age) Participants</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Arm A and B: Haemo-QoL-Short Form (SF) Questionnaire Score in Adolescent (12 to 17 years of age) Participants</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Arm A and B: European Quality of Life-5 Dimensions-5 Levels (EQ-5D-5L) Utility Score</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Arms A and C: Reduction in Number of All Bleeds (Whether Treated or not Treated by Coagulation Factors) From Pre-study to 24 Weeks</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 52 weeks before study entry (will be assessed retrospectively at baseline), 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Arms A and C: Reduction in Number of Treated Bleeds From Pre-study to 24 Weeks</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 52 weeks before study entry (will be assessed retrospectively at baseline), 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants With Adverse Events</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline up to approxiamtely 26 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants With Anti- Emicizumab Antibodies</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline up to approximately 26 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Trough Plasma Concentration (Ctrough) of emicizumab</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-dose (Hour 0) Every week during Weeks 1-4, every 2 weeks during Weeks 5-8, every 4 weeks during Weeks 9-24, every 8 weeks during Weeks 25-48, every 12 weeks thereafter while on emicizumab until the end of the study (approximately 26 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Body weight &gt;/= 40 kg at the time of screening

          -  Diagnosis of congenital hemophilia A of any severity and documented history of
             high-titer inhibitor ( that is [i.e]., &gt;/= 5 Bethesda Units [BU])

          -  Documentation of treatment with episodic or prophylactic bypassing agents for at least
             the last 24 weeks

          -  &gt;/= 6 bleeds in the last 24 weeks prior to screening (if on an episodic bypassing
             agent regimen) or &gt;/=2 bleeds in the last 24 weeks prior to screening (if on a
             prophylactic bypassing agent regimen)

          -  Adequate hematologic, hepatic and renal function

          -  For women who are not postmenopausal or surgically sterile: agreement to remain
             abstinent or use single or combined highly effective contraceptive methods</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>12</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Participants with inherited or acquired bleeding disorder other than hemophilia A

          -  Participants with ongoing (or plan to receive during the study) immune tolerance
             induction therapy or prophylaxis with Factor VIII (FVIII), with the exception of
             participants who have received a treatment regimen of FVIII prophylaxis with
             concurrent bypassing agent prophylaxis

          -  Previous (in the past 12 months) or current treatment for thromboembolic disease (with
             the exception of previous catheter-associated thrombosis for which antithrombotic
             treatment is not currently ongoing) or current signs of thromboembolic disease

          -  Participants with other conditions (example [e.g]., certain autoimmune diseases) that
             may increase the risk of bleeding or thrombosis

          -  History of clinically significant hypersensitivity associated with monoclonal antibody
             therapies or components of the emicizumab injection

          -  Known human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection with cluster of differentiation 4
             (CD4) count &lt; 200 cells/microliter within 24 weeks prior to screening

          -  Use of systemic immunomodulators (e.g., interferon or rituximab) at enrolment or
             planned use during the study, with the exception of antiretroviral therapy

          -  Participants who are at high risk for thrombotic microangiopathy (TMA; e.g., have a
             previous medical or family history of TMA), in the investigator's judgment

          -  Concurrent disease, treatment, or abnormality in clinical laboratory tests that could
             interfere with the conduct of the study or that would, in the opinion of the
             investigator or Sponsor, preclude the participant's safe participation in and
             completion of the study or interpretation of the study results

          -  Planned surgery (excluding minor procedures such as tooth extraction or incision and
             drainage) during the study

          -  Receipt of emicizumab in a prior investigational study; An investigational drug to
             treat or reduce the risk of hemophilic bleeds within 5 half-lives of last drug
             administration; A non-hemophilia-related investigational drug within last 30 days or 5
             half-lives, whichever is shorter; An investigational drug concurrently

          -  Unwillingness to use highly effective contraception methods for the specified duration
             in the protocol (females only, unless required otherwise by the local health
             authority)

          -  Clinically significant abnormality on screening evaluations or laboratory tests that,
             in the opinion of the investigator, may pose an additional risk in administering study
             drug to the participant

          -  Pregnancy or lactation, or intent to become pregnant during the study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional(has expanded access)</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>19/11/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>113</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/08/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital; Haematology - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>The Alfred Hospital, Melbourne; Thrombosis and Haemostasis Unit - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Colorado</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Georgia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Louisiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Massachusetts</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Michigan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Oregon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Pennsylvania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Washington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Costa Rica</country>
      <state>San Jose</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Bron</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Le Kremlin Bicetre</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Lille</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Paris</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Bonn</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Hamburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Mörfelden-Walldorf</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Lombardia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Toscana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Aichi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Hiroshima</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Hyogo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Kanagawa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Kitakyushu-shi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Nara</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Tokyo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Seoul</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Gdansk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Lublin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Poznan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Warsaw</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Johannesburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Sevilla</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Valencia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Taipei City</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Cardiff</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Oxford</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Hoffmann-La Roche</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Chugai Pharmaceutical</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This multicenter, open-label study will evaluate the safety, efficacy and pharmacokinetics of
      prophylactic emicizumab treatment in participants previously treated with episodic or
      prophylactic bypassing agents. Episodic bypassing agent participants will be randomized in a
      2:1 fashion to receive emicizumab prophylaxis (Arm A) versus no prophylaxis (Arm B) and will
      be stratified across Arms A and B according to the number of bleeds they experienced over the
      last 24 weeks prior to study entry (less than [&lt;] 9 or greater than or equal to [&gt;/=] 9
      bleeds); Arm B participants will have the opportunity to switch to emicizumab prophylaxis
      after 24 weeks on-study. Prophylactic bypassing agent participants will switch to emicizumab
      prophylaxis (Arm C) from the start of the trial; enrollment will be extended for 24 weeks
      after the last participant has enrolled in Arms A or B or until approximately 50 participants
      have enrolled in Arm C, whichever occurs first. Episodic bypassing agent participants who
      previously participated in the non-interventional study BH29768 (NCT02476942) or prophylactic
      bypassing agent participants who were unable to enroll in Arms A, B, or C prior to their
      closure will have the opportunity to enroll in Arm D. Like participants in Arms A and C, Arm
      D participants will receive emicizumab prophylaxis from the start of the trial. All
      participants will continue to receive episodic bypassing agent therapy to treat breakthrough
      bleeds, preferably with rFVIIa at the lowest expected dose to achieve hemostasis.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02622321</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Clinical Trials</name>
      <address>Hoffmann-La Roche</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>