<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3704">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/08/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/08/2012</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01744158</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Exploring Hypertonia in Children With Cerebral Palsy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Exploring Hypertonia in Children With Cerebral Palsy- a Population-based Approach.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>HypE-CP</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>REC2202/8/12</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cerebral Palsy.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - No intervention applicable

Children with cerebral palsy - No intervention applicable


Other interventions: No intervention applicable
Following consent, children will undergo a comprehensive assessment performed by a research team including rehabilitation paediatrician and therapist. Hypertonia and abnormal movements will be assessed by a pediatrician with expertise in treating children with movement disorders. The assessments will be performed at a rehabilitation clinic, or child's home, and will include:
differentiation of hypertonia by application of the Hypertonia Assessment Tool-Discriminate (HAT-D)
measurement of severity of dystonia using the Barry Albright dystonia scale, based on video recording
measurement of severity of spasticity using the modified Ashworth score
description of presence of chorea or athetosis
classification of gross motor abilities using the GMFCS and functional mobility scale (FMS)
classification of fine motor abilities using the manual ability classification system (MACS)
collection of demographic data and associated medical history

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hypertonia Assessment Tool-Discriminate (HAT-D) - The Hypertonia Assessment Tool (HAT) is a seven-item standardised clinical assessment tool used to differentiate the various types of paediatric hypertonia. There are 2 spasticity items, 2 rigidity items and 3 dystonia items and a standardized protocol for administration has been developed. Each item is scored yes or no. A positive score for at least one item of the subgroup confirms the presence of the subtype of hypertonia in the limb examined.</outcome>
      <timepoint>One hour</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Barry-Albright Dystonia scale - The Barry-Albright Dystonia scale is a 5-point criterion-based ordinal scale for measuring dystonia in CP, with sound validity and reliability. 7 It assesses dystonia in 8 body regions: eyes, mouth, neck, trunk, and the 4 extremities. Severity is scored from none to severe, with each body region having specific descriptors for scoring.</outcome>
      <timepoint>One hour</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Modified Ashworth Scale - The Modified Ashworth scale is a 6-point ordinal scale of muscle tone and involves a subjective assessment of muscle resistance as a limb is moved trough its full passive range.</outcome>
      <timepoint>One hour</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  children with a confirmed diagnosis of cerebral palsy

          -  aged between 2 and 18 years</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>2</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  presence of any progressive neurological disorder, including forms of genetic dystonia

          -  children less than two years, or greater than 18 years of age</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/03/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Unknown status</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/01/2014</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Women's and Children's Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>5006 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Women's and Children's Hospital, Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Allergan Australia Pty Ltd</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Abnormal limb and trunk movements are seen in many children with cerebral palsy. Recognizing
      the difference between types of these movements is not well understood. This study aims to
      describe how common are these movements in children recruited from a population-based sample
      of children identified on a cerebral palsy register, and to explore associations with motor
      abilities. It is hoped this will lead to improved understanding and recognition of movement
      disorders in CP, to allow clinicians to choose appropriate treatments. We hypothesise that
      the underlying prevalence of dyskinesia is higher than that previously identified through
      conventional motor descriptions in cerebral palsy populations in Australia, and may approach
      20%.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01744158</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>James E Rice, MD</name>
      <address>Women's and Children's Health Network</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>James E Rice, MD</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+618 8161 7367</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>james.rice@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>