<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2414">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/06/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/06/2009</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00930982</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of Cipro Inhale in Patients With Non-cystic Fibrosis Bronchiectasis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomized, Placebo-controlled, Double-blind, Multi-center Study to Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of Ciprofloxacin Inhale Compared to Placebo in Patients With Non-cystic Fibrosis Bronchiectasis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>2009-009869-34</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>12965</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Bronchiectasis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Ciprofloxacin (Cipro, BAYQ3939)
Treatment: drugs - Placebo

Experimental: Ciprofloxacin Inhale (BAYQ3939) - 32.5 mg ciprofloxacin hydrated corresponding to 50 mg Ciprofloxacin PulmoSphere Inhalation Powder twice daily

Placebo Comparator: Placebo - Inhalation of matching placebo twice a day


Treatment: drugs: Ciprofloxacin (Cipro, BAYQ3939)
Inhalation of 32,5mg Ciprofloxacin inhaled twice a day

Treatment: drugs: Placebo
Inhalation of matching placebo twice a day

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Total Bacterial Load in the Sputum at End of Treatment (Day 29). - Total bacterial load was determined in sputum collected before the inhalation of study drug. Sputum samples were either provided by the participant during the respective study visit, or participants had to bring a sputum sample that had been produced within the 4 hours prior to the visit. Induced sputum samples could be collected if the participant was unable to produce a spontaneously expectorated sputum sample of &gt; 2 mL. Imputation method: last observation carried forward (LOCF). CFU: colony forming units, log10: decadic logarithm</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 29 days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Forced Expiratory Volume in 1 Second (FEV1) - Pulmonary function testing (spirometry) was conducted in accordance with American Thoracic Society standards. FEV1 was defined as the maximal volume of air exhaled in the first second of a forced expiration from a position of full inspiration, expressed in liters at body temperature and ambient pressure saturated with water vapor (BTPS). Imputation method: last observation carried forward (LOCF).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and up to end of study (planned at Day 84)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Forced Vital Capacity (FVC) - Pulmonary function testing (spirometry) was conducted in accordance with American Thoracic Society standards. FVC was defined as the maximal volume of air exhaled with maximally forced effort from a maximal inspiration, i.e. vital capacity performed with a maximally forced expiratory effort expressed in liters at BTPS. Imputation method: last observation carried forward (LOCF).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and up to end of study (planned at Day 84)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Exacerbation With Antibiotic Intervention - Acute exacerbation was defined according to the joint American Thoracic Society/European Respiratory Society criteria. For detailed information with regard to this definition of acute exacerbation, please refer to the detailed description in the protocol section. The time to an acute exacerbation with antibiotic intervention was determined.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to end of study (planned at Day 84)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Effect of Ciprofloxacin Inhale Treatment on Health-related Quality of Life (HRQoL) as Measured by the Saint George's Respiratory Questionnaire (SGRQ), Total Score - Participants completed the Saint George's Respiratory Questionnaire (SGRQ). They were assured that all data would be treated confidentially and that the answers would not have any influence on study drug treatment. Participants completed the questionnaires on their own in a quiet area, without discussing them with study staff or accompanying persons (e.g. friends or relatives) and before being seen by the clinician. The score ranges from 0 to 100 with 100 being the worst possible score.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to end of study (planned at Day 84)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Effect of Ciprofloxacin Inhale Treatment on Health-related Quality of Life (HRQoL) as Measured by Chronic Respiratory Questionnaire - Self Administered Standardized (CRQ-SAS) - Participants completed the Chronic Respiratory Questionnaire - Self Administered Standardized (CRQ-SAS). They were assured that all data would be treated confidentially and that the answers would not have any influence on study drug treatment. Participants completed the questionnaires on their own in a quiet area, without discussing them with study staff or accompanying persons (e.g. friends or relatives) and before being seen by the clinician. The score ranges between 1 and 7, 1 being the worst possible score.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to end of study (planned at Day 84)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in High Sensitive C-reactive Protein (hsCRP) - High sensitive C-reactive protein (hsCRP) was determined from safety blood samples. Missing or invalid values were replaced with the last valid value available.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and up to Day 42</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Absolute Neutrophil Count (ANC) - Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) was determined from safety blood samples. Missing or invalid values were replaced with the last valid value available.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and up to Day 42</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>24-hour Sputum Volume - Participants were asked to start 24-hour sputum collection samples 24 hours before coming for the respective study visit. The volume of the completed sample was determined.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to end of study (planned at Day 84)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>24-hour Sputum Color (Percentage of Participants With Non-clear Sputum) - Participants were asked to start 24-hour sputum collection samples 24 hours before coming for the respective study visit. Sputum color was assessed as either 'clear', or as 'yellow', 'green' or 'rust', or an assessment of 'no sputum' was made.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to end of study (planned at Day 84)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Microbiological Response of Cipro Inhale Per Participant - Microbiological response was defined as reduction in bacterial load or eradication (measured as the percentage of participants with positive culture). Missing values were not imputed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to end of study (planned at Day 84)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Microbiological Response of Cipro Inhale Per Pathogen - Microbiological response was defined as reduction in bacterial load or eradication (measured as the number of participants with positive culture). Missing values were not imputed. Pathogens analyzed: Staphylococcus aureus, Streptococcus pneumoniae, Escherichia coli, Klebsiella pneumoniae, Klebsiella oxytoca, Proteus mirabilis, Serratia marcescens, Pseudomonas aeruginosa, mucoid, Pseudomonas aeruginosa, non mucoid, Stenotrophomonas maltophilia, Achromobacter xylosoxydans, Moraxella catarrhalis, Haemophilus influenzae</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to end of study (planned at Day 84)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Emergence of New Potential Respiratory Pathogens - The emergence of new potential respiratory pathogens was evaluated using microbiological analysis. Evaluated was the cumulative number of participants with first appearance of new potential respiratory antigens at each time point. In some cases, participants attended the end of study visit later than Day 84 (up to Day 88).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to end of study (planned at Day 84)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Emergence of Resistance Among Baseline Pathogens - The emergence of resistance (at least two-fold increase of Minimal inhibitory concentration, MIC, vs. baseline values) probably or possibly related to study medication among baseline pathogens was evaluated using microbiological analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to end of study (planned at Day 84)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Patients with a proven and documented diagnosis of non-cystic fibrosis idiopathic or
             post pneumonic bronchiectasis

          -  Stable pulmonary status and stable regimen of standard treatment at least for the past
             30 days</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Forced Expiratory Volume 1 &lt; 35% or &gt; 80%

          -  Allergic bronchopulmonary aspergillosis

          -  Immunodeficiency disease requiring immunoglobulin replacement

          -  Inflammatory bowel disease</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2>The people administering the treatment/s</masking2>
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/06/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>124</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/09/2010</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,SA,VIC,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital> - Concord</hospital>
    <hospital> - South Brisbane</hospital>
    <hospital> - Woollongabba</hospital>
    <hospital> - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital> - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <hospital> - Prahran</hospital>
    <hospital> - Nedlands</hospital>
    <postcode>2139 - Concord</postcode>
    <postcode>4101 - South Brisbane</postcode>
    <postcode>4102 - Woollongabba</postcode>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>5065 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
    <postcode>3181 - Prahran</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Arkansas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Colorado</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Connecticut</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>District of Columbia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Indiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Utah</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Baden-Württemberg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Brandenburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Hessen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Niedersachsen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Nordrhein-Westfalen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Rheinland-Pfalz</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Schleswig-Holstein</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Thüringen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Berlin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>A Coruña</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Illes Baleares</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Badajoz</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Uppsala</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Avon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Cambridgeshire</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Merseyside</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>North Ireland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Tyne and Wear</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Edinburgh</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Norwich</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Bayer</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Novartis</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to find out if bacterial load in the airways can be reduced
      after inhalation of ciprofloxacin for 28 days.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00930982</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Bayer Study Director</name>
      <address>Bayer</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>