<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4400">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/04/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/04/2014</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02112734</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can Vitamin D Supplementation in Infants Prevent Food Allergy in the First Year of Life? The VITALITY Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Can Vitamin D Supplementation in Infants Prevent Food Allergy in the First Year of Life? The VITALITY Trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>VITALITY</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>HREC # 34168 A</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Food Allergy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Allergies</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Vitamin D
Treatment: drugs - placebo

Active Comparator: vitamin D - 400 IU /daily cholecalciferol/vitamin D

Placebo Comparator: placebo - carrier formulation minus vitamin D


Treatment: drugs: Vitamin D
400 IU/daily for 10 months

Treatment: drugs: placebo
identical placebo daily

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>the prevalence and severity of challenge-proven food allergy in study participants with positive skin prick tests (SPT)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at age 12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>prevalence of food sensitisation (positive skin prick) test</outcome>
      <timepoint>age 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-Healthy, term, breastfeeding infants who will be predominately breastfed for at least
        6-months. This will be determined by answering yes/no to question 'do you intend to
        breastfeed until your infant is at least 6 months of age.'</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Weeks</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>8</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Weeks</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Infants who have already received postnatal vitamin D supplementation

          -  prematurity (&lt;37 weeks)/low birthweight &lt;2500 g

          -  poor health due to a current or past significant disease state or congenital
             abnormality.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2>The people administering the treatment/s</masking2>
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/12/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>3012</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/12/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Murdoch Childrens Research Institute - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3052 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Murdoch Childrens Research Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There is an urgent need to prevent the onset and progression of food allergy in our
      population. Evidence demonstrates that food allergy and atopic eczema represent the earliest
      manifestations of the atopic march with 50% of infants with food allergy predicted to develop
      respiratory allergic diseases later in life. We report that Australia has the highest
      prevalence of IgE-mediated food allergy in the world, with 10% of infants having
      challenge-proven food allergy in Melbourne. There has been a 5-fold increase in hospital
      admissions for life-threatening anaphylaxis. These changes are most pronounced in children
      less than 5 years, suggesting a causal role for early life determinants. We have primary data
      to inform hypotheses for the rise in food allergy, which appears to result from potentially
      modifiable factors related to the modern lifestyle, particularly Vitamin D insufficiency
      (VDI), and have demonstrated an association between VDI and increased risk of
      challenge-proven food allergy in 12-month old infants, which supports numerous ecological
      studies showing an increased risk of food allergy the further a child resides from the
      equator (associated with decreased UV exposure and Vitamin D levels). Despite Australia's
      sunny climate, population rates of VDI have steadily increased in infants and pregnant women
      in parallel to the apparent rise in food allergic disease. This association is biologically
      plausible, as there is evidence Vitamin D is critical to the healthy development of the
      immune system in early life. We propose an intervention study to assess if infant Vitamin D
      supplementation during the first year of life significantly decreases the risk of early-onset
      food allergy. Australia is ideally placed to answer this important question since, unlike the
      USA, Canada and Europe, there are no population recommendations for routine infant
      supplementation with Vitamin D and we are one of the few developed countries that do not
      supplement the food chain supply with Vitamin D.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02112734</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Allen KJ, Koplin JJ, Ponsonby AL, Gurrin LC, Wake M, Vuillermin P, Martin P, Matheson M, Lowe A, Robinson M, Tey D, Osborne NJ, Dang T, Tina Tan HT, Thiele L, Anderson D, Czech H, Sanjeevan J, Zurzolo G, Dwyer T, Tang ML, Hill D, Dharmage SC. Vitamin D insufficiency is associated with challenge-proven food allergy in infants. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2013 Apr;131(4):1109-16, 1116.e1-6. doi: 10.1016/j.jaci.2013.01.017. Epub 2013 Feb 27.
Allen KJ, Panjari M, Koplin JJ, Ponsonby AL, Vuillermin P, Gurrin LC, Greaves R, Carvalho N, Dalziel K, Tang ML, Lee KJ, Wake M, Curtis N, Dharmage SC. VITALITY trial: protocol for a randomised controlled trial to establish the role of postnatal vitamin D supplementation in infant immune health. BMJ Open. 2015 Dec 16;5(12):e009377. doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2015-009377.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Katie Allen, PhD</name>
      <address>On-X Life Technologies, Inc.</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Michael Field</name>
      <address />
      <phone>613 99366027</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michael.field@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>