<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4169">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/10/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/10/2013</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01966445</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Dose Escalation Study to Investigate the Safety, Pharmacokinetics, and Pharmacodynamics of GSK2849330 in Subjects With Advanced Her3-Positive Solid Tumors</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase I, First Time in Human, Open-Label, Dose Escalation Study to Investigate the Safety, Pharmacokinetics, and Pharmacodynamics of Anti-Her3 Monoclonal Antibody GSK2849330 in Subjects With Advanced Her3-Positive Solid Tumors</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>117158</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cancer</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - GSK2849330

Experimental: GSK2849330 Part 1 - 1 hour infusion administered intravenously at intervals of one week or more (escalating doses).

Experimental: GSK2849330 Part 2 - Intravenous infusion administered at the dose and schedule established in Part 1


Other interventions: GSK2849330
Solution containing 100 mg/millilter (mL) GSK2849330 for intravenous infusion

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of subjects with adverse events (AEs) and serious adverse events (SAEs) - SAEs assessed as related to study participation , study treatment or GSK concomitant medication must be recorded from the time a subject consents to participate in the study up to and including any follow-up contact</outcome>
      <timepoint>Part 1 and Part 2: From Day 1 up to 45 days or 5 half lives (whichever is longer) after last dose of study treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dose-limiting toxicities (DLTs) - An event will be considered a DLT if it occurs within the first 4 weeks (28 days) of treatment, and meets one of the protocol defined criteria unless it can be clearly established that the event is unrelated to treatment</outcome>
      <timepoint>Part 1 and Part 2: From Day 1 up to Day 29</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in laboratory values - Laboratory tests will include hematology, clinical chemistry and urinalysis parameters</outcome>
      <timepoint>Part 1 and Part 2: From Screening up to approximately 28 days after the last dose of study treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in electrocardiograms (ECGs) - Single 12-lead ECGs will be obtained at scheduled time points</outcome>
      <timepoint>Part 1 and Part 2: From Screening up to approximately 28 days after the last dose of study treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in vital signs - Vital sign measurements will include systolic and diastolic blood pressure and pulse rate</outcome>
      <timepoint>Part 1 and Part 2: From Screening up to approximately 28 days after the last dose of study treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PK parameter values for GSK2849330</outcome>
      <timepoint>Part 1 and Part 2: Scheduled timepoints from Day 1 until 45 days or 5 half lives (whichever is longer) after last dose of study treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total and phospho-HER3 from tumor tissue - Tumor biopsies will be obtained and analyzed for total and phospho-HER3</outcome>
      <timepoint>Part 1 and Part 2: Screening (pre-treatment) and either Day 15 or Day 22 depending on dosing schedule</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Antibodies to GSK2849330 assessed in serum</outcome>
      <timepoint>Part 1 and Part 2: Scheduled timepoints from Day 1 until 45 days or 5 half lives (whichever is longer) after last dose of study treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall response rate - Response evaluations (either complete response [CR] or partial response [PR]) will be determined according to the definitions established in the Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST 1.1)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Part 2: Screening and Every 8 or 9 weeks from the first dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tumor markers - Tumor markers will be collected as applicable to the subject's primary tumor type</outcome>
      <timepoint>Part 2: Day 1 and Every 8 or 9 weeks from the first dose.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Males and females &gt;=18 years of age (at the time consent is obtained).

          -  Written informed consent provided.

          -  Performance Status score of 0 or 1 according to the Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group
             (ECOG) scale.

          -  Sufficient archival tumor specimen is available for HER3 immunohistochemistry (IHC)
             analysis, or subject is willing to undergo a fresh tumor biopsy for HER3 IHC analysis.

          -  Histologically or cytologically confirmed diagnosis of one of the following solid
             tumor malignancies for which no standard therapeutic alternatives exist: bladder
             cancer, breast cancer, castrate-resistant prostate cancer, cervical cancer, colorectal
             cancer (CRC), gastric cancer, hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC), melanoma, non-small cell
             lung cancer (NSCLC), ovarian cancer, pancreatic cancer, squamous cancers of the head
             and neck region (including parotid and nasopharynx).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Subjects with leptomeningeal or brain metastases or spinal cord compression.

          -  Prior HER3- directed treatment (HER2- or EGFR-directed treatment is acceptable).

          -  Concurrent medical condition that would jeopardize compliance.

          -  Receiving chronic immunosuppressive therapies (includes daily steroid doses in excess
             of 20 milligrams [mg]/day of prednisone).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>26/11/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>29</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>18/09/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Nedlands</hospital>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Colorado</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Utah</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Amsterdam</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Groningen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Nijmegen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Rotterdam</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>GlaxoSmithKline</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Human Epidermal Growth Factor Receptor 3 (HER3) expression is seen across a wide variety of
      solid malignancies and is associated with poor prognosis. Up-regulation of HER3 expression
      and activity is also associated with resistance to multiple pathway inhibitors. GSK2849330, a
      monoclonal antibody targeting HER3, is a new agent for subjects whose tumors express HER3.
      This study is a phase I, first time in human, open-label, dose escalation study. The purpose
      of this study is to investigate the safety, pharmacokinetics (PK), and pharmacodynamics (PD)
      of GSK2849330 in subjects with advanced HER3-positive solid tumors. The study will be
      conducted in two parts. Part 1 (Dose-Escalation Phase) will include dose escalation and PK/PD
      cohorts to evaluate safety, PK, and PD to guide selection of dose regimen(s) for Part 2. In
      Part 2 (Expansion Cohorts), up to 3 cohorts will be enrolled at the dose regimen(s) selected
      based on Part 1 data, to evaluate safety in a larger cohort of subjects at the recommended
      dose regimen and also to evaluate preliminary evidence of clinical benefit.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01966445</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>GSK Clinical Trials</name>
      <address>GlaxoSmithKline</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>