<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3154">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/04/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/04/2011</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01346592</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Safety, Tolerability, and Immunogenicity of the Adjuvanted Trivalent Subunit Influenza Vaccine and the Non-Adjuvanted Trivalent Subunit Influenza Vaccine Compared to the Non-Adjuvanted Trivalent Split Influenza Vaccine in Children 6 to &lt; 72 Months of Age</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase III, Observer-Blind, Randomized, Multi-center Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, and Immunogenicity of Fluad and Agriflu Compared to the Non-adjuvanted Trivalent Influenza Vaccine Fluzone in Children 6 to &lt; 72 Months of Age</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>V70_29</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Influenza Disease</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - Trivalent split influenza vaccine (TIV)
Other interventions - MF59-adjuvanted trivalent influenza vaccine (aTIV)
Other interventions - Licensed comparator trivalent split influenza vaccine (comparator TIV)

Active Comparator: aTIV (6 to &lt;72 months) - Subjects received an investigational MF59-adjuvanted trivalent influenza vaccine (aTIV), subjects aged between 6 to &lt;36 months received two doses of 0.25 mL each, while subjects aged =36 months received two doses of 0.5 mL each, at Days 1 &amp; 29

Active Comparator: Comparator TIV (6 to &lt;72 months) - Subjects received a licensed comparator trivalent split influenza vaccine (comparator TIV), subjects aged between 6 to &lt;36 months received two doses of 0.25 mL each, while subjects aged =36 months received two doses of 0.5 mL each, at Days 1 &amp; 29

Active Comparator: TIV (6 to &lt;72 months) - Subjects received an investigational trivalent split influenza vaccine (TIV), subjects aged between 6 to &lt;36 months received two doses of 0.25 mL each, while subjects aged =36 months received two doses of 0.5 mL each, at Days 1 &amp; 29


Other interventions: Trivalent split influenza vaccine (TIV)


Other interventions: MF59-adjuvanted trivalent influenza vaccine (aTIV)


Other interventions: Licensed comparator trivalent split influenza vaccine (comparator TIV)


</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of Antibody Responses of aTIV With TIV and Comparator TIV in Terms of Geometric Mean Titers (GMTs) Against Homologous Strains - The non-inferiority of Hemagglutination Inhibition (HI) antibody responses of aTIV compared to TIV and comparator TIV assessed in terms of post vaccination GMTs at three weeks after last vaccination against the three homologous vaccine strains.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1, Day 50</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of Antibody Responses of aTIV With TIV and Comparator TIV in Terms of Percentage of Subjects Achieving Seroconversion or =4-fold Increase in HI Titers Against Homologous Strains - The non-inferiority of HI antibody responses of aTIV compared to TIV and comparator TIV assessed in terms of percentage of subjects achieving seroconversion or =4-fold increase in HI titers at three weeks after last vaccination against the three homologous vaccine strains.
Seroconversion defined as prevaccination HI titer &lt;10 and postvaccination HI titer =40 or at least a 4-fold increase in HI titers from prevaccination HI titer =10.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 50</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of Antibody Responses of TIV Versus Comparator TIV in Terms of Geometric Mean Titers (GMTs) Against Homologous Strains (6 to &lt;36 Months) - The non-inferiority of HI antibody responses of TIV to that of comparator TIV, in subjects aged 6 to &lt;36 Months, assessed in terms of post vaccination GMTs at three weeks after last vaccination against the three homologous vaccine strains.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1, Day 50</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of Antibody Responses of TIV Versus Comparator TIV in Terms of Percentage of Subjects Achieving Seroconversion or =4-fold Increase in HI Titer Against Homologous Strains in Subjects 6 to &lt;36 Months of Age - The non-inferiority of HI antibody responses of TIV to that of the licensed comparator TIV assessed in terms of percentage of subjects achieving seroconversion or =4-fold increase in HI titers at three weeks after last vaccination against the three homologous vaccine strains.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 50</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of Antibody Responses of aTIV With TIV and Comparator TIV in Terms of GMTs Against Homologous Strains (6 to &lt;24 Months) - The superiority of HI antibody responses, in subjects 6 to &lt;24 months of age, of aTIV compared to TIV and comparator TIV assessed in terms of post vaccination GMTs at three weeks after last vaccination against the three homologous vaccine strains.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1, Day 50</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of Antibody Responses of aTIV With TIV and Comparator TIV in Terms Percentage of Subjects Achieving Seroconversion or =4-fold Increase in HI Titer Against Homologous Strains (6 to &lt;24 Months) - The superiority of HI antibody responses, in subjects 6 to &lt;24 months of age, of aTIV compared to TIV and comparator TIV assessed in terms of number of subjects achieving seroconversion at three weeks after last vaccination against the three homologous vaccine strains.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 50</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of Antibody Responses of aTIV With TIV and Comparator TIV in Terms of GMTs Against Homologous Strains (6 to &lt;72 Months)-FAS - The superiority of HI antibody responses, in subjects 6 to &lt;72 months of age, of aTIV compared to TIV and comparator TIV assessed in terms of post vaccination GMTs at three weeks after last vaccination against the three homologous vaccine strains.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1, Day 50</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of Antibody Responses of aTIV With TIV and Comparator TIV in Terms of Percentage of Subjects Achieving Seroconversion or =4 Fold Increase in HI Titers Against Homologous Strains (6 to &lt;72 Months)-FAS - The superiority of HI antibody responses, in subjects 6 to &lt;24 months of age, of aTIV compared to TIV and comparator TIV assessed in terms of number of subjects achieving seroconversion =4 fold increase in HI titers at three weeks after last vaccination against the three homologous vaccine strains.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 50</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The HI GMTs Against Homologous Strains, by Vaccine Group - The HI antibody titers against the three homologous strains following vaccination with either aTIV, licensed comparator or TIV, at three weeks and at six months after vaccination are reported as GMTs.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1, Day 29, Day 50, Day 209</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Geometric Mean Ratio (GMR) of Post- Versus Pre-vaccination HI Titers Against Homologous Strains - The GMR of post-vaccination versus pre-vaccination HI titers against homologous strains, three weeks (day 29/day 1; day 50/day 1)and six months (day 209/day 1) after vaccination with either aTIV, licensed comparator or TIV.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 29, Day 50, Day 209</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Subjects With HI Titers =40 Against Homologous Strains, by Vaccine Group - The percentage of subjects demonstrating HI titers =40,against homologous strains, at three weeks and six months after vaccination with aTIV or licensed comparator or TIV.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1, Day 29, Day 50, Day 209</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Subjects Achieving Seroconversion or =4 Fold Increase in HI Titers, Against Homologous Strains - The percentage of subjects achieving seroconversion =4 fold increase in HI titers from baseline, against homologous strains, at three weeks and six months after vaccination with ATIV or licensed comparator or TIV.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 29, Day 50, Day 209</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of Antibody Responses of aTIV With TIV and Comparator TIV in Terms of GMTs Against Homologous Strains, Subjects at Risk/Not at Risk, by Age Subgroup - The non-inferiority of Hemagglutination Inhibition (HI) antibody responses of aTIV compared to TIV and comparator TIV assessed in terms of post vaccination GMTs at three weeks after last vaccination against the three homologous vaccine strains, in subjects with a defined set of underlying medical conditions (at risk) and healthy subjects (not at risk), by age sub group.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 50</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of Antibody Responses of aTIV Versus Comparator TIV and TIV in Terms of Percentage of Subjects Achieving Seroconversion or =4-fold Increase in HI Titer Against Homologous Strains in Subjects at Risk/Not at Risk, by Age Subgroup - The non-inferiority of HI antibody responses of aTIV to that of the licensed comparator TIV and to investigational TIV was assessed in terms of percentage of subjects achieving seroconversion or =4-fold increase in HI titers at three weeks after last vaccination against the three homologous vaccine strains in subjects with a defined set of underlying medical conditions (at risk) and in healthy subjects (not at risk) , by age sub group.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 50</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of Antibody Responses of TIV Versus Comparator TIV in Terms of Percentage of Subjects Achieving Seroconversion or =4-fold Increase in HI Titer Against Homologous Strains in Subjects at Risk/Not at Risk, by Age Sub Group-FAS - The superiority of HI antibody responses of aTIV compared to TIV and comparator TIV assessed in terms of of percentage of subjects achieving seroconversion or =4-fold increase in HI Titer at three weeks after last vaccination against the three homologous vaccine strains in subjects with a defined set of underlying medical conditions (at risk) and healthy subjects (not at risk), by age sub group.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 50</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of Antibody Responses of aTIV With TIV and Comparator TIV in Terms of GMTs Against Homologous Strains, at Risk/Not at Risk, by Age Sub Group-FAS - The superiority of HI antibody responses of aTIV compared to TIV and comparator TIV assessed in terms of post vaccination GMTs at three weeks after last vaccination against the three homologous vaccine strains, in subjects with a defined set of underlying medical conditions (at risk) and in healthy subjects (not at risk), by age sub group.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 50</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The HI GMTs Against Heterologous Strains, by Vaccine Group (6 to &lt;72 Months Age Group) - The HI antibody titers against the heterologous strains following vaccination with either aTIV, licensed comparator or TIV, at three weeks and at six months after vaccination are reported as GMTs.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1, Day 50, Day 209</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Subjects Achieving Seroconversion or =4 Fold Increase in HI Titers, Against Heterologous Strains - The percentage of subjects achieving seroconversion or =4 fold increase in HI titers from baseline, against heterologous strains, at three weeks and six months after last vaccination with aTIV or licensed comparator or TIV.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 50, Day 209</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of Antibody Responses of aTIV With TIV and Comparator TIV in Terms of GMTs Against Homologous Strains, After One Vaccination - To demonstrate the GMTs at three weeks after one dose of aTIV are statistically significantly higher to the corresponding response's of comparator TIV and TIV.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1, Day 29</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects Reporting Solicited Adverse Events After Vaccination - The number of subjects reporting any solicited local and systemic adverse events (AEs), following vaccination with aTIV or licensed comparator or TIV.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 through Day 7 after any vaccination</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Subjects Reporting Unsolicited Adverse Events After Vaccination - The number of subjects reporting any unsolicited adverse events (AEs) between Day 1 to Day 50, serious adverse events (SAEs), AE leading to withdrawal (WD), new onset of chronic disease(NOCD), adverse events of special interest following vaccination with aTIV or licensed comparator or TIV throughout the study (Day 1 to Day 394).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 to Day 394</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.Children 6 months to 72 months of age.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Months</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>72</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Months</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Children

          1. Who had been hospitalized at the time of enrollment

          2. Who had any serious reaction or hypersensitivity to any vaccine component, eggs, or
             chicken protein

          3. Who had known impairment of the immune function

          4. Who had fever interfering with normal daily activities at the time of enrollment

          5. Who had received licensed vaccines within 14 days (for inactivated vaccines) or 28
             days (for live vaccines) prior to enrollment in the study

          6. Concomitant participation in another clinical study

          7. Who had surgery planned during the study period that in the investigator's opinion
             would have interfered with the study visits schedule.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/04/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>6104</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/07/2012</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>206 Vaccine and Immunology Research Trials Unit University Department of Paediatrics 2nd floor Clarence Reiger Bldg Womens and Childrens Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>201 Royal Children Hospital Department of Respiratory Medicine - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>205 Vaccine and Immunisation Research Group Murdoch Childrens Research Institute School Of Population Health - Level 5 207 Bouverie St</hospital>
    <hospital>202 Sydney Children Hospital Department of Immunology and Infectious Diseases - Randwick</hospital>
    <hospital>204 National Centre for Immunisation Research and Surveillance Kids Research Institute The Childrens Hospital at Westmead - Westmead</hospital>
    <postcode>5006 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>4029 - Herston</postcode>
    <postcode> - Level 5 207 Bouverie St</postcode>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
    <postcode>2145 - Westmead</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Argentina</country>
      <state>Buenos Aires</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Argentina</country>
      <state>Cordoba</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Argentina</country>
      <state>Cuidad Automa de Beunos Aires</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Argentina</country>
      <state>Guaymallen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Argentina</country>
      <state>Mendoza</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Chile</country>
      <state>Santiago</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Philippines</country>
      <state>Cavite</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Philippines</country>
      <state>Dbbb Dasmarinas Cavite</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Philippines</country>
      <state>Manila</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Philippines</country>
      <state>Muntinlupa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Philippines</country>
      <state>Quezon City</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Philippines</country>
      <state>Quezon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Benoni</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Johannesburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Pretoria</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Soweto</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Novartis Vaccines</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This Study Aims to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, and Immunogenicity of the Adjuvanted
      Trivalent Subunit Influenza Vaccine and the Non-Adjuvanted Trivalent Subunit Influenza
      Vaccine Compared to the Non-Adjuvanted Trivalent Split Influenza Vaccine in Children 6 to &lt;
      72 Months of Age.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01346592</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Novartis Vaccines</name>
      <address>Novartis Vaccines</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>