<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6602">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/05/2017</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT03173573</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Study to Assess the Safety, Tolerability and PK Profile of FDL176 in Healthy and CF Participants</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Five Part Phase 1 Study to Assess the Safety, Tolerability and Pharmacokinetic (PK) Profile of Single and Repeat Oral Doses of FDL176 in Healthy and Cystic Fibrosis (CF) Participants</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>FDL176-2016-01</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cystic Fibrosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Connective tissue diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other inflammatory or immune system disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human Genetics and Inherited Disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Cystic fibrosis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - FDL176
Treatment: drugs - Placebo

Experimental: Part 1 SAD FDL176 level 1 to 6 - Part 1: Single dose of FDL176 test formulation Level 1 to 6 on healthy males.

Placebo Comparator: Part 1 SAD Placebo - Part 1: Single dose of Placebo for FDL176.

Experimental: Part 2 SAD FDL176 at fasted state - Part 2: single dose of FDL176 test formulation, fasted state.

Experimental: Part 2 SAD FDL176 at fed state - Part 2: single dose of FDL176 test formulation, fed state

Experimental: Part 3 SAD FDL176 test formulation - Part 3: Single dose of FDL176 test formulation on healthy females.

Placebo Comparator: Part 3 SAD placebo - Part 3: Single dose of Placebo for FDL176.

Experimental: Part 4 MAD FDL176 Level 1 to 3 - Part 4: Dose escalation of FDL176 test formulation Level 1 to 3.

Placebo Comparator: Part 4 MAD Placebo - Part 4: Dose escalation of Placebo for FDL176 Level 1 to 3.

Experimental: Part 5 SAD FDL176 test formulation - Part 5: Single dose of FDL176 test formulation.


Treatment: drugs: FDL176
CFTR modulator

Treatment: drugs: Placebo
Placebo for FDL176

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Part 1 and Part 4: Incidence of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events. - Part 1 and Part 4: Safety and tolerability of FDL176 in healthy male participants as determined by the incidence of adverse events (AE)s and serious adverse events(SAE)s.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Part 1: 4 weeks; Part 4: 6 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Part 2, 3 and 5: Pharmacokinetic parameters, Cmax - The pharmacokinetic parameters of FDL176: maximal plasma concentration</outcome>
      <timepoint>Part 2: 5 weeks, Part 3: 4 weeks and Part 5: 4 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Part 2, 3 and 5: Pharmacokinetic parameters, Tmax - The pharmacokinetic parameters of FDL176: maximal concentration</outcome>
      <timepoint>Part 2: 5 weeks, Part 3: 4 weeks and Part 5: 4 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Part 2, 3 and 5: Pharmacokinetic parameters, AUC - The pharmacokinetic parameters of FDL176: area under the plasma concentration curve</outcome>
      <timepoint>Part 2: 5 weeks, Part 3: 4 weeks and Part 5: 4 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Part 2, 3 and 5: Pharmacokinetic parameters, CL/F - The pharmacokinetic parameters of FDL176: clearance</outcome>
      <timepoint>Part 2: 5 weeks, Part 3: 4 weeks and Part 5: 4 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Part 2, 3 and 5: Pharmacokinetic parameters, V/F - The pharmacokinetic parameters of FDL176: apparent volume of distribution</outcome>
      <timepoint>Part 2: 5 weeks, Part 3: 4 weeks and Part 5: 4 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Part 2, 3, and 5: Incidence of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events. - Safety and tolerability of FDL176 in healthy male participants as determined by the incidence of adverse events (AE)s and serious adverse events(SAE)s.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Part 2: 5 weeks, Part 3: 4 weeks and Part 5: 4 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Part 1 and 4: Pharmacokinetic parameters, Cmax - The pharmacokinetic parameters of FDL176: maximal plasma concentration</outcome>
      <timepoint>Part 1: 4 weeks; Part 4: 6 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Part 1 and 4: Pharmacokinetic parameters,Tmax - The pharmacokinetic parameters of FDL176: maximal concentration</outcome>
      <timepoint>Part 1: 4 weeks; Part 4: 6 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Part 1 and 4: Pharmacokinetic parameters,AUC - The pharmacokinetic parameters of FDL176: area under the plasma concentration curve</outcome>
      <timepoint>Part 1: 4 weeks; Part 4: 6 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Part 1 and 4: Pharmacokinetic parameters, CL/F - The pharmacokinetic parameters of FDL176: clearance</outcome>
      <timepoint>Part 1: 4 weeks; Part 4: 6 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Part 1 and 4: Pharmacokinetic parameters, V/F - The pharmacokinetic parameters of FDL176: apparent volume of distribution</outcome>
      <timepoint>Part 1: 4 weeks; Part 4: 6 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion Criteria (Part 1 to Part 4):

          -  If sexually active, must be willing to use two highly effective methods of birth
             control from Day 1 until 3 months after the last dose of investigational medicinal
             product (IMP)

          -  Body mass index (BMI) between 19 and 30 kg/m2 inclusive.

          -  Healthy as determined by the PI or delegate, based upon a medical evaluation including
             medical history, physical examination, laboratory tests and ECG.

        Inclusion Criteria (Part 5):

          -  Males and females aged 18 years and older.

          -  Diagnosis of CF defined as a sweat chloride value =60 mmol/L by quantitative
             pilocarpine iontophoresis or two CF-causing mutations, documented in the participant's
             medical record.

          -  History of pancreatic insufficiency, documented in the participant's medical record.

          -  Stable CF disease as judged by the Investigator (or delegate).

          -  Forced expiratory volume in one second (FEV1) &gt;40% of predicted normal for age, sex
             and height at screening.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion Criteria (Part 1 to 4):

          -  Prior or ongoing medical condition, medical history, physical findings, ECG findings
             or laboratory abnormality that, in the Investigator's (or delegate's) opinion, could
             adversely affect the safety of PK of the participant or would place the participant at
             increased risk.

          -  Surgery within the past three months prior to the first study drug administration
             determined by the PI or delegate to be clinically relevant.

          -  Alkaline phosphatase (ALP), aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and/or alanine
             aminotransferase (ALT) &gt;1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN) at screening. Repeat testing
             at screening is acceptable for out of range values following approval by the Sponsor's
             Medical Monitor.

          -  Serum creatinine or total bilirubin &gt; 1.5 x ULN (isolated bilirubin &gt;1.5 x ULN is
             acceptable if bilirubin is fractionated and direct bilirubin is &lt;35%).

          -  Abnormal renal function at screening, defined as creatinine clearance &lt;60 mL/min using
             the Modification of Diet in Renal Disease (MDRD) equation

          -  History of prolonged QT and/or QTcF interval.

          -  ECG with a single QTcF &gt;450 msec in males, &gt;460 msec in females, at Screening.

          -  Positive urinary drugs of abuse screen at Screening or Day -1, or positive alcohol
             screen at Screening or Day -1

          -  History of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or positive HIV, hepatitis B or
             hepatitis C results at screening.

          -  Use of any prescription drugs within 14 days or 5 half-lives (whichever is longer)
             before the first dose of IMP, unless in the opinion of the Investigator (or delegate)
             and the Sponsor's Medical Monitor the medication will not interfere with the study
             procedures or compromise participant safety. Hormonal contraceptives are allowed.

          -  Use of any non-prescription drugs, including vitamins, herbal and dietary supplements
             within 14 days or 5 half-lives (whichever is longer) before the first dose of IMP,
             unless in the opinion of the Investigator (or delegate) and the Sponsor's Medical
             Monitor the medication will not interfere with the study procedures or compromise
             participant safety.

          -  Pregnant or nursing females. Female participants of childbearing potential must have a
             negative pregnancy test at the screening visit. Determination of participant
             eligibility will be at the discretion of the Investigator (or delegate) following
             consultation with the Sponsor's Medical Monitor.

          -  History of regular alcohol consumption within 6 months of the study defined as an
             average weekly intake of &gt;21 units. One unit is equivalent to 8 g of alcohol: a
             half-pint (~240 mL) of beer, one glass (125 mL) of wine, or one (25 mL) measure of
             spirits.

          -  Current smoking or use of tobacco products or substitutes. Former smokers will be
             eligible, provided they have not smoked for at least 6 months before Day 1.

          -  Participation in another clinical trial involving receipt of an IMP within the past 90
             days or exposure to more than four new chemical entities with 12 months of the first
             dosing day.

        Exclusion Criteria (Part 5):

          -  A pulmonary exacerbation, or changes in therapy for pulmonary disease within 4 weeks
             prior to the Baseline (Day 1) visit.

          -  Abnormal liver function =3 × ULN: AST, ALT, total bilirubin.

          -  Serum creatinine or total bilirubin &gt; 1.5 x ULN (isolated bilirubin &gt;1.5 x ULN is
             acceptable if bilirubin is fractionated and direct bilirubin is &lt;35%).

          -  Abnormal renal function at screening, defined as creatinine clearance &lt;60 mL/min using
             the MDRD equation.

          -  Hemoglobin &lt;10 g/dL.

          -  History of prolonged QT and/or QTcF interval.

          -  ECG with a single QTcF &gt;450 msec in males, &gt;460 msec in females, at Screening.

          -  Use of ivacaftor or lumacaftor within 14 days prior to Day 1.

          -  Any change (initiation, change in type of drug, dose modification, schedule
             modification, interruption, discontinuation, or re-initiation) in a chronic
             treatment/prophylaxis regimen for CF or CF related conditions within 4 weeks prior to
             Day 1.

          -  Pregnant or nursing females. Female participants of childbearing potential must have a
             negative pregnancy test at the screening visit. Determination of participant
             eligibility will be at the discretion of the Investigator (or delegate) following
             consultation with the Sponsor's Medical Monitor.

          -  Participation in another clinical trial involving receipt of an IP within the past 90
             days or exposure to more than four new chemical entities with 12 months of the first
             dosing day.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2>The people administering the treatment/s</masking2>
    <masking3 />
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>27/06/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>112</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>5/03/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QueenlandWA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Wayne Hooper Clinic Clive Berghofer Cancer research Center - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>Linear Clinical Research - Perth</hospital>
    <postcode>4006 - Herston</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Perth</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Flatley Discovery Lab LLC</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a 5-part study of FDL176. Part 1 is a double blind, placebo-controlled, dose
      escalation study in healthy male participants. Part 2 is a single dose, open-label study in
      healthy male participants. Part 3 is a single dose, double blind, placebo-controlled study in
      healthy female participants. Part 4 is a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled,
      dose-escalation study in healthy male and female participants.Part 5 is a single dose,
      open-label study in male and female participants with CF.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03173573</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Claudia Ordonez, MD</name>
      <address>Flatley Discovery Lab</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jingwen Chai</name>
      <address />
      <phone>6172420720</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jingwen.chai@flatleydiscoverylab.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>