<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5168">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/09/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/09/2015</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02555475</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Prime Study - Comparing Hepatitis C Care and Treatment in a Primary Health Care Service With a Tertiary Hospital</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Prime Study - Comparing Hepatitis C Care and Treatment in a Primary Health Care Service With a Tertiary Hospital: a Randomised Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>HREC/15/SVHM/41</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hepatitis C</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - community based hepatitis C care and treatment

No Intervention: Group 1, tertiary hospital based care - Group 1: (n=190) Following their initial screen, these participants will be referred to a tertiary hospital for hepatitis C care, transient elastography and DAA treatment (traditional / standard model of care).

Experimental: Group 2, community based care - Group 2: (n=190) Following their initial screen, these participants will be offered community based hepatitis C care and treatment. Hepatitis C care, transient elastography and DAA treatment will be delivered at the primary healthcare centre only.


Other interventions: community based hepatitis C care and treatment


</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To measure the proportion of people attending at a Primary Health Care Service for their genotype 1 HCV infection who commence antiviral treatment (Viekira Pak and ribavirin) and have a SVR 12.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Sustained virology response (SVR) rates at week 12 post treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To measure the proportion of people attending a PHCS with G1 HCV infection who commence antiviral treatment (Viekira Pak and ribavirin) if they are managed at a PHCS compared to those who are referred to and managed at a tertiary hospital.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Treatment uptake within 8 weeks of randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To measure the proportion of people with G1 HCV who have an SVR12 at a PHCS compared a tertiary hospital.</outcome>
      <timepoint>SVR rate at week 12 post treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To measure the reduction in HCV viraemia (community viral load) among participants considering retention through the cascade of care and SVR12.</outcome>
      <timepoint>up to 24 weeks post treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To measure the cost effectiveness of managing and treating people in a primary health service compared to a tertiary hospital.</outcome>
      <timepoint>up to 24 weeks post treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To define the cascade of care for patients referred to a community hepatitis nurse for assessment of HCV.</outcome>
      <timepoint>up to 12 weeks post treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Aged =18 years;

          -  Attendance at a study PHCS defined as; Attended appointment at PHCS at least once in
             2014 or; Attended at least one consultation with a study community hepatitis nurse
             between 2012-2014

          -  Evidence of chronic G1 HCV infection (HCV antibody positive for &gt; 6 months and HCV RNA
             positive);

          -  Absence of cirrhosis defined as one of the following:

        Liver biopsy within 24 months prior to screening demonstrating absence of cirrhosis (e.g. a
        Metavir score of 3 or less or an Ishak score of 4 or less); or A screening FibroScan result
        of &lt;9.6 kPa; or if a FibroScan is unsuccessful A screening Aspartate Aminotransferase to
        Platelet Ratio Index (APRI) = 2 and no clinical or laboratory evidence of cirrhosis;

          -  HCV treatment naive or pegylated or standard interferon and ribavirin experienced;

          -  Willing and able to provide written informed consent

        Subjects must have the following laboratory parameters at screening:

          -  ALT = 10 times the upper limit of normal (ULN);

          -  AST = 10 times ULN

          -  Haemoglobin = 12g/dL for males; = 11g/dL for female subjects;

          -  Platelet count = laboratory lower limit of normal;

          -  INR = laboratory upper limit of normal, unless stable on an anticoagulant regimen
             affecting INR;

          -  Albumin = laboratory lower limit of normal;

          -  Direct bilirubin = laboratory upper limit of normal;

          -  Creatinine clearance (Clcr) = 60mL/min as calculated by Cockcroft-Gault equation.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Known cirrhosis defined as:

        Liver biopsy within 24 months prior to screening demonstrating cirrhosis (e.g. a Metavir
        score &gt; 3 or an Ishak score &gt; 4); or A FibroScan result of &gt;12.5 kPa; or Prior clinical
        evidence of cirrhosis or portal hypertension (i.e. ascites, varices).

          -  Prior exposure to HCV DAA protease inhibitors

          -  Currently receiving HCV treatment;

          -  Testing positive for HIV;

          -  Testing positive for HBsAg;

          -  HCC;

          -  Pregnancy or breastfeeding at screening or baseline;

          -  Evidence of any condition, therapy, laboratory abnormality or other circumstance
             (current or prior) that may confound the study's results, or interfere with
             participation for the full duration of the study, such that it is not in the best
             interest of the participant;

          -  Use of concomitant medications that are contraindicated with Viekira Pak within 28
             days of the baseline/day 1 visit, that are unable to be ceased for the duration of
             treatment.

        Additional exclusion criteria for participants receiving ribavirin:

          -  increased baseline risk for anaemia (i.e. history of thalassaemia, spherocytosis,
             history of GI bleeding) or;

          -  patients for whom anaemia would be medically problematic or;

          -  documented of presumed coronary artery disease or cerebrovascular disease, if in the
             judgement of the investigator, an acute decrease in haemoglobin by up to 4 g/dL (as
             may be seen with ribavirin) would not be well tolerated.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/03/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/12/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St Vincents Hospital Melbourne - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Burnet Institute - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3065 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3181 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Christchurch</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Macfarlane Burnet Institute for Medical Research and Public Health Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>St Vincent's Hospital Melbourne</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The Prime Study is a randomised trial investigating models of care for hepatitis C in the era
      of direct acting antiviral (DAA) therapy. The study aims to compare outcomes of hepatitis C
      care and DAA treatment provided in a primary health care service with a tertiary hospital.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02555475</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Amanda Wade, Dr</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+61392822111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amanda.wade@burnet.edu.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>