<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3902">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/01/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/01/2012</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01524887</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Phase 3 IGIV, 10% in Alzheimer´s Disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 3 Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-Controlled Study of the Safety and Effectiveness of Immune Globulin Intravenous (Human), 10% Solution (IGIV, 10%) for the Treatment of Mild to Moderate Alzheimer's Disease</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>2011-000914-21</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>161003</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Alzheimer´s Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Alzheimer's disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dementias</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - Immune Globulin Intravenous (Human), 10% Solution
Other interventions - Human albumin 0.25%

Experimental: IGIV, 10% at high dose (0.4 g/kg) - 

Experimental: IGIV, 10% at low dose (0.2 g/kg) - 

Placebo Comparator: Placebo control - 


Other interventions: Immune Globulin Intravenous (Human), 10% Solution
Intravenous infusion every 2 weeks over 18 months

Other interventions: Human albumin 0.25%
Intravenous infusion every 2 weeks over 18 months

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline to Month 18 in Cognitive Subscale of the Alzheimer´s Disease Assessment Scale (ADAS-Cog) - The ADAS-Cog is a validated psychometric instrument that evaluates memory (word recall, word recognition), attention, reasoning (following commands), language (naming, comprehension), orientation, ideational praxis (placing letter in envelope) and constructional praxis (copying geometric designs). This test was administered by experienced raters certified by Alzheimer's Disease Cooperative Study (ADCS) at each site.
Scores on the ADAS-Cog range from 0-70 with higher scores indicating greater impairment; hence increases from baseline reflect potential cognitive deterioration.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to 9 Months (actual time frame)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline to Month 18 in Alzheimer´s Disease Cooperative Study (ADCS)-Activities of Daily Living (ADL) Inventory - The ADCS-ADL scale is a validated tool to assess instrumental and basic activities of daily living based on a 23 item structured interview of the caregiver or qualified study partner.
Scores on the ADCS-ADL range from 0-78 with lower scores indicating greater impairment; hence decreases from baseline reflect potential functional deterioration.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to 9 Months (actual time frame)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>ADCS-Clinical Global Impression of Change (CGIC) at 18 Months - The ADCS-CGIC is a validated categorical measure of change in a participant's global clinical status between baseline and follow-up visits, based on interview of the participant and the caregiver by a skilled and experienced clinician who was blinded to treatment assignment. The ADCS-CGIC score is based on a 7-point Likert scale, ranging from 1 (marked improvement) to 7 (marked worsening).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to 9 Months (actual time frame)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline to Month 18 in Neuropsychiatric Inventory (NPI) - The NPI is a validated instrument used to assess behavioral psychopathology in AD; it evaluates the frequency and severity of 10 neuropsychiatric features including delusions, hallucinations, dysphoria, anxiety, agitation/aggression, euphoria, disinhibition, irritability/lability, apathy, aberrant motor activity, sleep and night-time behavior change, and appetite and eating change. The NPI total score ranged 0-144, with higher scores indicating greater impairment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to 9 Months (actual time frame)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline to Month 18 in Volumetric Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) Parameters: Rate of Whole Brain Atrophy and Ventricular Enlargement</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to 9 Months (actual time frame)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline to Month 18 in Logsdon Quality of Life in Alzheimer´s Disease (QOL-AD) - The QOL AD is a validated, 13-item instrument developed specifically for individuals with dementia. The assessment rates the participant´s quality of life for physical, emotional, interpersonal, and environmental domains. The QOL-AD total score ranged 13-52, with lower scores associated with a lower quality of life.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to 9 Months (actual time frame)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline to Month 18 in Impact of Alzheimer´s Disease on Caregiver Questionnaire (IADCQ) - The IADCQ is a 12-item validated questionnaire that has been developed to measure the emotional, physical, and social impact of care giving on AD caregivers. Higher scores on the IADCQ are associated with a higher impact. IADCQ total score range: 0 (no impact) - 48 (greatest impact). Each item can be scored either 0 (Not at all), 1 (A little), 2 (Somewhat), 3 (A lot), or 4 (Extremely). As this is a 12-item scale, the minimum possible score is 0 and the maximum possible score is 4x12 = 48.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to 9 Months (actual time frame)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants Experiencing Study Product-related Adverse Events (AEs) and/or Serious Adverse Events (SAEs)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout the study period: 18 Months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants Experiencing Any AEs and/or SAEs</outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout the study period: 18 Months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Infusions Temporally Associated With AEs and/or SAEs - A temporal association was defined as an AE and/or SAE occurring during or within 72 hours of completion of an infusion, regardless of causality.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During or within 72 hours of completion of an infusion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Infusions Associated With AEs and/or SAEs Occurring During or Within 7 Days of Completion of an Infusion</outcome>
      <timepoint>During or within 7 days of completion of an infusion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Infusions Causally Associated With AEs and/or SAEs</outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout the study period: 18 Months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Infusions Discontinued, Slowed, or Interrupted Due to an AE</outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout infusions, approximately 2-5 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Males or females of age 50 to 89 years inclusive at the time of screening

          -  Written informed consent obtained from either the subject or the subject's legally
             authorized representative prior to any study-related procedures

          -  Written informed consent obtained from an able and competent caregiver who is willing
             to comply with the requirements of the protocol pertaining to him/her, including
             facilitating the subject's participation in the study

          -  Diagnosis of Probable Alzheimer´s Disease (AD) according to NINCDS-ADRDA* 1984
             criteria (* National Institute of Neurological and Communicative Disorders and Stroke
             - Alzheimer's Disease and Related Disorders Association)

          -  Dementia of mild to moderate severity (Mini-Mental State Examination [MMSE] 16-26
             inclusive at the time of screening)

          -  Neuroimaging (computed tomography [CT] or MRI) performed after symptom onset
             consistent with AD diagnosis

          -  Willingness to comply with the requirements of the protocol and ability to comply with
             testing and infusion regimen, including adequate corrected visual acuity and hearing
             ability

          -  For at least 12 weeks prior to screening, on stable doses of AD medication(s) approved
             by local regulatory authorities. Subjects must not be on two acetylcholinesterase
             inhibitors concurrently.

          -  Venous access for repeated infusion and phlebotomy

          -  If receiving psychoactive medications (eg, antidepressants other than monoamine
             oxidase inhibitors [MAOIs] and most tricyclics, antipsychotics, anxiolytics,
             anticonvulsants, mood stabilizers, etc.), must be on stable doses for at least 6 weeks
             prior to screening

          -  For women of childbearing potential, the subject must have a negative pregnancy test
             at screening and must agree to employ adequate contraceptive measures (eg, birth
             control pills/patches, intrauterine device, or diaphragm or condom [for male partner]
             with spermicidal jelly or foam) throughout the course of the study

          -  For subjects with a coronary artery stent, the subject must receive documented medical
             clearance from an interventional cardiologist stating that the subject is not at
             increased risk for stent occlusion with immunoglobulin treatment

          -  For subjects with an endovascular stent, the subject must receive documented medical
             clearance from a vascular surgeon stating that the subject is not at increased risk
             for thromboembolic events with immunoglobulin treatment

        Main</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>89</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Possible AD by NINCDS-ADRDA criteria or non-Alzheimer dementia (eg, vascular dementia,
             dementia with Lewy bodies, frontotemporal dementia, or dementia arising from other
             diseases or conditions such as Parkinson's disease, vitamin B12 deficiency, thyroid
             abnormalities)

          -  Current residence in a skilled nursing facility

          -  Contraindication to undergoing MRI (eg, pacemaker [with the exception of an
             MRI-compatible pacemaker], severe claustrophobia, ferromagnetic implants such as a
             metal plate)

          -  Clinically significant congestive heart failure (eg, New York Heart Association [NYHA]
             Class III/IV symptoms or untreated Class II)

          -  Current atrial fibrillation of unstable angina (angina at rest) or history of
             myocardial infarction within the 12 months prior to screening

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension defined as systolic blood pressure &gt; 160 mm Hg and/or
             diastolic &gt; 100 mm Hg confirmed upon repeated measures

          -  History of thrombosis and/or thromboembolic disease (central or peripheral) within the
             12 months prior to screening

          -  Known history of procoagulant abnormalities (eg, factor V Leiden, antiphospholipid
             syndrome, protein S/protein C deficiency, AT III deficiency)

          -  History of intracerebral hemorrhage within the 5 years prior to screening

          -  Evidence on MRI of: greater than 4 microhemorrhages (regardless of their anatomical
             location or diagnostic characterization as "possible" or "definite"), a single area of
             superficial siderosis, vasogenic edema, a macrohemorrhage, major stroke, prominent
             white matter disease with a rating score of 3 on the age-related white matter changes
             (ARWMC) scale from the European Task Force on ARWMC, or multiple lacunae (defined as
             more than 2 lacunae that are greater than 0.5 mm in size)

          -  Head trauma with loss of consciousness, contusion, or open head injury within the 12
             months prior to screening

          -  Uncontrolled seizure disorder as defined by two or more breakthrough seizures per year
             despite adequate antiepileptic drug (AED) treatment

          -  Modified Hachinski score &gt; 4 at time of screening

          -  Subjects with active malignancy or history of malignancy within 5 years prior to
             screening with the exception of the following: adequately treated basal cell or
             squamous cell carcinoma of the skin, carcinoma in situ of the cervix, and stable
             prostate cancer not requiring treatment

          -  Active autoimmune or neuro-immunologic disorder

          -  Uncontrolled major depression, psychosis, or other major psychiatric disorder(s)

          -  Poorly controlled diabetes, defined as glycosylated (or glycated) hemoglobin (HbA1c) =
             6.5% at screening

          -  Creatinine clearance &lt; 50% of normal adjusted for age and gender, as calculated
             according to the Cockcroft-Gault formula, at the time of screening

          -  Known history of untreated vitamin B12 deficiency within 6 months prior to screening,
             or clinically significant abnormally low vitamin B12 at the time of screening

          -  Abnormal clinical chemistry panel or hematology panel meeting any one of the following
             criteria:

          -  Serum alanine aminotransferase (ALT) &gt; 2.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Clinically significant anemia that precludes repeated blood sampling or hemoglobin
             (Hgb) &lt; 10.0 g/dL

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &lt; 1000 cells/µL

          -  Known coagulopathy or platelet counts &lt; 100,000 cells/µL

          -  Total serum protein &gt; 9 g/dL

          -  Known history of or positive serology at screening for one or more of the following:
             hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg), hepatitis C virus (HCV) antibody, or human
             immunodeficiency virus (HIV) type 1/2 antibody

          -  Immunoglobulin A (IgA) deficiency (&lt; 8 mg/dL)

          -  Known history of hypersensitivity following infusions of human blood or blood
             components (e.g. human immunoglobulins or human albumin)

          -  Currently receiving or has received: anti-CD20 therapy within 12 months prior to
             screening, or other immunomodulatory therapies (e.g. anti-TNF, anti-IL-1, interferon)
             within 12 weeks prior to screening. The following exceptions are allowed: non-systemic
             corticosteroids (eg, topical, opthalmic or inhaled glucocorticoids) and low-dose
             systemic corticosteroids (prednisone &lt; 10 mg/day or its equivalent)

          -  Currently receiving or has received intravenous or subcutaneous immunoglobulin
             treatment within the 2 years prior to screening, or has received immunoglobulin in
             Baxter Protocol 160701

          -  Currently receiving or has received at any time active immunization aimed at
             modulating AD progression

          -  Currently receiving or has received within 12 months prior to screening any
             investigational device, drug or biologic (eg passive immunotherapies with monoclonal
             or polyclonal antibodies) aimed at modulating AD progression

          -  Subject has been exposed to an investigational product (IP) or investigational device
             within 12 weeks prior to screening or is scheduled to participate in another clinical
             study involving an IP or investigational device during the course of this study

          -  Subject is a family member or employee of the investigator

          -  The subject is nursing or intends to begin nursing during the course of the study

          -  Any disorder or disease, or clinically significant abnormality on laboratory or other
             clinical test(s) (eg, blood tests, urine tests, electrocardiogram, chest x-ray), that
             in medical judgment may impede the subject's participation in the study, pose
             increased risk to the subject, or confound the results of the study

          -  Currently receiving anti-coagulant agent and/or anti-platelet agent other than
             acetylsalicylic acid (a.k.a. aspirin)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/01/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>508</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Terminated</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/07/2013</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital> - Woodville South</hospital>
    <postcode> - Woodville South</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Alabama</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Arizona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Georgia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Illinois</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Kentucky</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Minnesota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Mississippi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Nevada</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Jersey</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Oklahoma</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Rhode Island</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Vermont</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Virginia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Wisconsin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Edegem</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Gent</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Hasselt</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Leuven</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Roeselare</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Quebec</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Akashi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Akita</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Azumino</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Chiba</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Fukui</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Kyoto</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Niigata</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Osaka</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Saga</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Tokushima</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Tokyo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Lublin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Scinawa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Warszawa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Vizcaya</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Valencia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>East Sussex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Bath</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Brentford</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Brighton</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Glasgow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Shire</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to provide evidence of efficacy and safety to support the
      development of IGIV, 10% as a treatment option for patients with mild to moderate Alzheimer´s
      Disease.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01524887</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kathy Tobias, MD</name>
      <address>Baxter Healthcare Corporation</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>