<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3307">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/09/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/09/2011</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01442636</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Drug Eluting Stents In The Critically Ischemic Lower Leg 2</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>a Prospective, Multicenter, Controlled Trial Evaluating the Implant of a Drug Eluting Stent (XIENCE PRIME, Abbott Vascular) in the Critically Ischemic Lower Leg</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>DESTINY 2</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>FMRP-101021</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Peripheral Arterial Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - stent

Experimental: Xience Prime stent - Patients with critical limb ischemia due to below the knee arterial lesion between 30 and 100mm in length, treated with the XIENCE PRIME Everolimus Eluting Coronary Stent System.


Treatment: devices: stent
Implantation of one or more Everolimus-eluting XIENCE PRIME Everolimus Eluting Coronary Stent Systems.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary patency at 12 months - Absence of restenosis (=50% stenosis) or occlusion within the originally treated lesion based on angiography</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Technical success - The ability to cross and dilate the lesion to achieve residual angiographic stenosis no greater than 30%</outcome>
      <timepoint>procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hemodynamic primary patency rate at 1, 6, 12-month follow-up - Patients that present without a hemodynamically significant stenosis at the target area on duplex ultrasound (systolic velocity ratio no greater than 2.4) and without prior TLR are defined as being primary patent at the given follow-up.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1, 6, 12-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Limb-salvage rate at all follow-up visits - Absence of major amputation. Major amputation is defined as amputation at or above the ankle, as opposed to minor amputation, being an amputation at or below metatarsal level, preserving functionality of the foot).</outcome>
      <timepoint>1, 6, 12-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary assisted patency rate at 1, 6, 12-month follow-up - Defined as flow through the treated lesion maintained by repeat percutaneous intervention completed prior to complete vessel closure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1, 6, 12-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary patency rate at 1, 6, 12-month follow-up - Defined as flow through the treated lesion maintained by repeat percutaneous intervention after occlusion of the target lesion.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1, 6, 12-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Target lesion revascularization (TLR) at all follow-up visits - A repeat intervention to maintain or re-establish patency within the region of the treated arterial vessel plus 5 mm proximal and distal to the treated lesion edge.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1, 6, 12-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical success at all follow-up visits - An improvement of Rutherford classification at 1 day and 1, 6, 12-month follow-up of one class or more as compared to the pre-procedure Rutherford classification.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1, 6, 12-month</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serious adverse events until follow-up completions - Any clinical event that is fatal, life-threatening, or judged to be severe by the investigator; resulted in persistent or significant disability; necessitated surgical or percutaneous intervention; or required prolonged hospitalization.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1,6,12 months and interim visits</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Patient presenting with rest pain or minor tissue loss (Rutherford class 4 or 5)

          -  Patient is willing to comply with specified follow-up evaluations at the specified
             times

          -  Patient is &gt;18 years old

          -  Patient understands the nature of the procedure and provides written informed consent,
             prior to enrolment in the study

          -  Patient has a projected life-expectancy of at least 12 months

          -  Patient is eligible for treatment with the XIENCE PRIME stent (Abbott Vascular)

          -  Male, infertile female, or female of child bearing potential practicing an acceptable
             method of birth control with a negative pregnancy test within 7 days prior to study
             procedure

        Angiographic 

          -  De novo lesion or restenotic lesion after PTA in the infrapopliteal arteries, suitable
             for endovascular therapy

          -  Total target lesion length minimally 30mm and maximally 100mm

          -  Target vessel diameter visually estimated to be &gt;2.0mm and &lt;3.5mm

          -  Guidewire and delivery system successfully traversed lesion</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Patient refusing treatment

          -  The reference segment diameter is not suitable for the available stent design

          -  Untreated flow-limiting inflow lesions

          -  Perioperative unsuccessful ipsilateral percutaneous vascular procedure to treat inflow
             disease just prior to enrollment

          -  Any previous surgery in the target vessel (including prior ipsilateral crural bypass)

          -  Aneurysm in the target vessel

          -  Non-atherosclerotic disease resulting in occlusion (e.g. embolism, Buerger's disease,
             vasculitis)

          -  Severe medical comorbidities (untreated CAD/CHF, severe COPD, metastatic malignancy,
             dementia, etc) or other medical condition that would preclude compliance with the
             study protocol or 1-year life expectancy

          -  Major distal amputation (above the transmetatarsal) in the study limb or non-study
             limb

          -  Septicemia or bacteremia

          -  Any previously known coagulation disorder, including hypercoagulability

          -  Contraindication to anticoagulation or antiplatelet therapy

          -  Known allergies to stent or stent components

          -  Known allergy to contrast media that cannot be adequately pre-medicated prior to the
             study procedure

          -  Patient with known hypersensitivity to heparin, including those patients who have had
             a previous incidence of heparin-induced thrombocytopenia (HIT) type II

          -  Currently participating in another clinical research trial

          -  Angiographic evidence of intra-arterial thrombus or atheroembolism from inflow
             treatment

          -  Target lesion access not performed by transfemoral approach.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>60</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/11/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Prince of Wales Private Hospital - Randwick</hospital>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Antwerp</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>East-Flanders</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Bad Krozingen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Leipzig</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Münster</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Flanders Medical Research Program</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The objective of this clinical evaluation is to evaluate the immediate and long term (up to
      12 months) outcome of the XIENCE PRIME Everolimus Eluting Coronary Stent System (Abbott
      Vascular) in a controlled prospective investigation for the treatment of patients with
      critical limb ischemia due to the presence of lesions between 3cm and 10cm in length at the
      level of the below the knee arteries. Specifically the trial aims to illicit angiographic and
      ultrasound patency, clinical improvement, and adverse events associated with the use of this
      stent. The trial design is single armed, prospective, controlled trial run over 12 months of
      follow-up.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01442636</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Marc Bosiers, MD</name>
      <address>A.Z. Sint-Blasius Hospital</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>