<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6321">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/01/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/01/2015</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02343692</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Phase II Multicentre Trial of Endoscopic Ultrasound Guided Radiofrequency Ablation of Cystic Tumours of the Pancreas</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase II Multicentre Trial of Endoscopic Ultrasound Guided Radiofrequency Ablation of Cystic Tumours of the Pancreas (RADIOCYST01)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>RADIOCYST01</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>13/0427</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pancreatic Cyst</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pancreatic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: surgery - EUS guided RFA of cystic tumours of the pancreas

Experimental: Radiofrequency abalation - Intervention: Endoscopic Ultrasound (EUS) guided radiofrequency ablation (RFA) of cystic tumours of the pancreas
Device: An RFA generator (ERBE VIO 300D, Dolby medical products, Scotland)
Procedure: Delivery of sequential doses of electrical energy at 10W for a total of up to 4 minutes 30 seconds (3 x 90 second applications) to ablate the cystic lesion.
Ablation of cystic tumours of the pancreas


Treatment: surgery: EUS guided RFA of cystic tumours of the pancreas
Endoscopic ultrasound guided radiofrequency ablation of pancreatic cysts

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Presence of pancreatic cyst - To evaluate pancreatic cyst ablation at 12 months following EUSguided radiofrequency ablation therapy in patients with pre-diagnosed cystic tumours of the pancreas.</outcome>
      <timepoint>One year</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mortality</outcome>
      <timepoint>One year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Morbidity</outcome>
      <timepoint>One year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression following treatment</outcome>
      <timepoint>One year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of surgical resection</outcome>
      <timepoint>One year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Local complication rate</outcome>
      <timepoint>One year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluation of surrogate markers of response (Imaging (CT, MRI, EUS) and serum markers.)</outcome>
      <timepoint>One year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Preliminary health economics analysis from questionnaires and cost diaries (Self-completed EQ-5D-5L questionnaire and cost diary.) - Self-completed EQ-5D-5L questionnaire and cost diary.</outcome>
      <timepoint>One year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. A diagnosis of a pancreatic cystic tumour based on multidisciplinary review of
             imaging, for which further surveillance with non-invasive imaging is indicated.

          2. Pancreatic cystic tumour between 0.5 and 3cm in size. Cysts greater than 3cm or with
             mural nodules can be included only if patients are unsuitable for surgical resection.

          3. ECOG performance status 0, 1 or 2.

          4. Estimated life expectancy of at least 12 weeks.

          5. Age &gt;18 years.

          6. Capable of giving written informed consent.

          7. Women of child-bearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test (qualitative
             serum hCG) in the week before treatment, AND be using an adequate contraception
             method, which must be continued for at least 1 week after RF.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. A diagnosis of a pancreatic cystic tumour where surgical resection is indicated.

          2. Pancreatic cysts greater than 3cm or less than 0.5cm in size.

          3. Benign pancreatic cysts (e.g. pseudocyst).

          4. Serous cystadenomas.

          5. Pancreatic cysts with malignant transformation.

          6. Cysts involving or in close proximity to vessels or the biliary tree where the zone of
             ablation is likely to compromise these structures.

          7. Cysts arising from the main pancreatic duct.

          8. History of active or prior malignancy that will interfere with the response evaluation
             (exceptions include in-situ carcinoma of the cervix treated by cone-biopsy/resection,
             nonmetastatic basal and/or squamous cell carcinomas of the skin, any early stage
             (stage l) malignancy adequately resected for cure greater than 5 years previously).

          9. Acute pancreatitis within the previous 4 weeks.

         10. Any evidence of severe or uncontrolled systemic diseases or laboratory finding that in
             the view of the investigator makes it undesirable for the patient to participate in
             the trial.

         11. Any psychiatric disorder making reliable informed consent impossible.

         12. Pregnancy or breast-feeding.

         13. ECOG performance status 3 or 4</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/03/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>97</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/08/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>Epworth Richmond - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode> - Melbourne</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Birmingham</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Newcastle-Upon-Tyne</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Nottingham</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University College, London</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Up to 13.5% of patients that undergo a magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan of their abdomen
      without pancreatic symptoms are found to have an incidental pancreatic cyst, with the
      frequency increasing with age. In a post-mortem series, 25% of patients had a pancreatic
      cyst, of which 32% were potentially premalignant and 3% malignant. Premalignant cysts are
      currently either observed or removed surgically according to international guidelines.
      Observation is associated with significant anxiety for patients and a growing cost to the
      National Health Service, while surgery for this usually benign condition is associated with
      not insignificant morbidity and mortality. Premalignant pancreatic cysts may be indolent for
      a number of years before malignant transformation, creating a window of opportunity for
      minimally invasive intervention and cure. New early treatment options for premalignant
      tumours are urgently required. This study will evaluate the safety and efficacy of a novel
      minimally invasive technique for the treatment of pancreatic cystic tumours; endoscopic
      ultrasound guided radiofrequency ablation (EUSRFA).

      If successful it will offer an alternative to long term observation or surgery for patients
      with this condition.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02343692</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Stephen P Pereira, MB BS, FRCP</name>
      <address>Royal Free London</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Bina Shah</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>situ.radiocyst@ucl.ac.uk</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>