<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2666">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/02/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/02/2010</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01068509</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Ovarian Cancer Vaccine for Patients in Remission</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomized, Open-label Phase IIb Trial of Maintenance Therapy With a MUC1 Dendritic Cell Vaccine (Cvac) for Epithelial Ovarian Cancer Patients in First or Second Remission</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>CAN-003</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Epithelial Ovarian Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ovarian and primary peritoneal</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - Cvac

Experimental: Non-randomized Cvac - Participants received 6-8 intradermal injections of Cvac at 4 sites along both upper arms and both thighs. The 6-8 injections contained ~ 60 × 10^6 dendritic cells. Following evaluation after the first dose, participants received additional injections as described for the randomized Cvac group below.

Experimental: Randomized Cvac - Participants received 6-8 intradermal injections of Cvac at 4 sites along both upper arms and both thighs every 4 weeks for 24 weeks (7 doses at Weeks 8, 12, 16, 20, 24, 28, and 32), and then every 8 weeks for 24 weeks (3 doses at Weeks 40, 48, and 56). The 6-8 injections contained ~ 60 × 10^6 dendritic cells.

No Intervention: Observational standard of care - Participants in this group did not receive any treatment during the study.


Other interventions: Cvac
Cvac consists of autologous dendritic cells (DCs) incubated with the antigen, mannosylated fusion protein (M-FP), to target the DCs to the specific mucin 1 antigen.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression-free Survival - Progression-free survival was defined as the time from randomization to the date of documented disease progression or death from any cause, whichever occurred earlier. Disease progression occurred when a patient met either the Gynecologic Cancer Intergroup (GCIG) cancer-antigen (CA)-125 definition or the Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) radiological definition of progressive disease. The GCIG CA-125 definition of disease progression was defined as a CA-125 level = 2 × the upper limit of normal documented on 2 occasions at least 1 week apart. The radiological RECIST criteria of disease progression was defined as the appearance of new lesions or an overall increase = 20% or at least 5 mm in existing tumors.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to 48 weeks after the last visit or dose of Cvac (up to 104 weeks)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Survival - Overall survival was defined as the time from randomization until death from any cause.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to the end of the study (up to 4 years 10 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Mucin 1 Antibody Levels at Weeks 20, 56, and 104 - Mucin 1 antibodies were assessed in serum samples using a quantitative enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA). Detection was achieved with electrochemiluminescence.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to Week 104</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in ICS of IL2, IL4, IL17, TNF, and IFNg in CD4+ and CD8+ Cells at Weeks 20, 56, and 104 - Intracellular cytokine staining (ICS) for IL2, IL4, IL17, tumor necrosis factor (TNF), and interferon gamma (IFNg) was done in both CD4+ and CD8+ cells from serum samples collected at Weeks, 20, 56, and 104. Intracellular cytokine staining data were acquired with 8-color flow cytometry on a BD LSR II flow cytometer and a high-throughput screening microplate reader.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to Week 104</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Female subjects = 18 years old with histologically confirmed Stage III or IV
             epithelial ovarian, primary peritoneal or fallopian tube cancer who have previously
             undergone surgical cytoreduction and received first or second line conventional
             chemotherapy and are currently in complete remission (based on clinical and radiologic
             studies).

          -  Cancer antigen (CA)-125 = upper limit of normal with a prior history of an elevated
             CA-125.

          -  Able and willing to undergo mononuclear cell collection.

          -  Not more than 12 weeks between enrollment and the last dose of chemotherapy that
             resulted in complete remission.

          -  No prior surgery to the peritoneum or pleural space within 28 days of enrollment,
             excluding removal of catheters used for chemotherapy administration.

          -  No prior treatment with an investigational product within 30 days of enrollment.

          -  Baseline electrocardiogram within normal limits or any abnormalities deemed not
             indicative of cardiac disease for which intervention is required.

          -  Serum creatinine = 2 mg/dL.

          -  Serum aspartate aminotransferase or serum alanine aminotransferase = 2.5x the upper
             limit of normal or serum total bilirubin = 1.5x the upper limit of normal.

          -  White blood cell count = 3.0 K/µL; absolute neutrophil count = 1.5K/µL; hemoglobin =
             9.0 g/dL, and platelets = 100,000/mm^3. (These complete blood count results are
             required for enrollment. It should be noted that complete blood count results,
             including monocyte count = 0.2 × 10^9/L, will be needed prior to leukapheresis to
             determine if sufficient dendritic cells can be obtained for Cvac manufacture.)

          -  Life expectancy of at least 12 months.

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group Performance Status of 0-1.

          -  All toxicities from prior therapies, excluding alopecia, must have resolved to Common
             Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events Grade = 1.

          -  Must be non-pregnant and, if of childbearing potential, must use adequate birth
             control (hormonal or barrier method of birth control or abstinence) for the duration
             of the study and for 3 months after study completion.

          -  Able to provide written informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Female</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Coexisting or other malignancies unless in complete remission for not less than 3
             years. Does not include in situ carcinoma of the cervix or basal cell or squamous cell
             carcinoma of the skin for which no restrictions apply, assuming they have been
             adequately treated.

          -  Ovarian germ cell, sarcoma, or mixed Mullerian tumors.

          -  Prior cancer vaccine or cellular therapy.

          -  Active uncontrolled infections or any organ system toxicity = Grade 2 by Common
             Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events criteria.

          -  Inability to provide informed consent or to comply with study-related procedures.

          -  Concurrent systemic treatment with steroids or other immunosuppressive agents.

          -  Diagnosed immunodeficiency and/or autoimmune disorders.

          -  Myocardial infarction in the past 6 months and/or clinically significant heart
             disease.

          -  Infection with human immunodeficient virus (HIV), hepatitis B or C virus.

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding.

          -  Evidence or history of central nervous system metastases.

          -  Full dose anticoagulation therapy administered within 7 days of leukapheresis
             procedure.

          -  Hematopoietic growth factors administered within 14 days of enrollment.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>63</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/04/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD,SA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Greenslopes Private Hospital - Greenslopes</hospital>
    <hospital>Gold Coast Hospital - Southport</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>Peter MacCallum Cancer Cetnre - East Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Austin Health Cancer Centre - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <postcode>4120 - Greenslopes</postcode>
    <postcode>4215 - Southport</postcode>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>3002 - East Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Georgia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Indiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Jersey</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>South Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Washington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Prima BioMed Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to determine the safety and efficacy of an investigational
      therapeutic agent (Cvac) in ovarian cancer patients in first or second remission and to
      determine its ability to prevent cancer from returning.

      Study objectives

      Primary objectives:

        -  To confirm the safety of administering Cvac in this population.

        -  To determine the effects of Cvac on progression-free survival (PFS).

      Secondary objectives:

        -  To determine overall survival (OS) for ovarian cancer patients who receive Cvac after
           achieving remission in the first or second-line setting.

        -  Evaluation of host immunologic response to Cvac administration.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01068509</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Jemal A, Siegel R, Ward E, Hao Y, Xu J, Murray T, Thun MJ. Cancer statistics, 2008. CA Cancer J Clin. 2008 Mar-Apr;58(2):71-96. doi: 10.3322/CA.2007.0010. Epub 2008 Feb 20.
Grossi M, Quinn MA, Thursfield VJ, Francis PA, Rome RM, Planner RS, Giles GG. Ovarian cancer: patterns of care in Victoria during 1993-1995. Med J Aust. 2002 Jul 1;177(1):11-6.
Ozols RF, Rubin SC, Thomas G, et al. Epithelial ovarian cancer. In: Hoskins WJ, Perez CA, Young RC, eds. Principles and Practice of Gynecologic Oncology, 4th ed. Philadelphia: Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins. 2005:919-922.
Markman M, Liu PY, Wilczynski S, Monk B, Copeland LJ, Alvarez RD, Jiang C, Alberts D; Southwest Oncology Group; Gynecologic Oncology Group. Phase III randomized trial of 12 versus 3 months of maintenance paclitaxel in patients with advanced ovarian cancer after complete response to platinum and paclitaxel-based chemotherapy: a Southwest Oncology Group and Gynecologic Oncology Group trial. J Clin Oncol. 2003 Jul 1;21(13):2460-5.
Apostolopoulos V, McKenzie IF. Cellular mucins: targets for immunotherapy. Crit Rev Immunol. 1994;14(3-4):293-309. Review.
Desai J, Mitchell P, Loveland B, et al. A phase I trial of dendritic cells pulsed with MUC1 peptide in patients with solid tumours. Proc ASCO 2002; 21:15b (A1868).
Rustin GJ, Nelstrop AE, Bentzen SM, Bond SJ, McClean P. Selection of active drugs for ovarian cancer based on CA-125 and standard response rates in phase II trials. J Clin Oncol. 2000 Apr;18(8):1733-9.
Apostolopoulos V, McKenzie IF, Pietersz GA. Breast cancer immunotherapy: current status and future prospects. Immunol Cell Biol. 1996 Oct;74(5):457-64. Review.
Apostolopoulos V, Karanikas V, Haurum JS, McKenzie IF. Induction of HLA-A2-restricted CTLs to the mucin 1 human breast cancer antigen. J Immunol. 1997 Dec 1;159(11):5211-8.
Meyer T, Rustin GJ. Role of tumour markers in monitoring epithelial ovarian cancer. Br J Cancer. 2000 May;82(9):1535-8. Review.
Liu PY, Alberts DS, Monk BJ, Brady M, Moon J, Markman M. An early signal of CA-125 progression for ovarian cancer patients receiving maintenance treatment after complete clinical response to primary therapy. J Clin Oncol. 2007 Aug 20;25(24):3615-20.
Clinical Study Report: A Phase II Trial of Cellular Immunotherapy with M-FP Cancer Vaccine in Subjects with Epithelial Ovarian Cancer, 2007 (with permission from Martin Rogers of Prima Biomed).
Immunotherapy for Prostate AdenoCarcinoma Treatment (IMPACT) Phase 3 study summary of sipuleucel-T in castrate-resistant prostate cancer: http://www.bio-medicine.org/medicine-technology-1/
Austin Research Institute. SOP #811609. Leukapheresis for ex vivo Culture or Human Dendritic Cells for Immunotherapy. V004, 9 January 2004.
Austin Research Institute. SOP #8116 Stages 3-4. Procedures for the ex vivo Generation of MF-P Vaccine Pulsed SC, Phase I Clinical Trial. V006, 10 June 2003.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Heidi Gray, MD</name>
      <address>University of Washington</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>