<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3063">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/02/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/02/2011</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01289223</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Trial to Investigate the Efficacy of Bendamustine in Patients With Indolent Non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma (NHL) Refractory to Rituximab.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomised, Open Label, Multi-centre, Phase III Study to Investigate the Efficacy of Bendamustine Compared to Treatment of Physician's Choice in the Treatment of Subjects With Indolent Non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma (NHL) Refractory to Rituximab</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ROBIN</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>2010-022102-41</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>BDM3502</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Indolent B-cell NHL</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lymphoma (non Hodgkin's lymphoma) - High grade lymphoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lymphoma (non Hodgkin's lymphoma) - Low grade lymphoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Bendamustine IV
Other interventions - Treatment of Physicians Choice

Active Comparator: Treatment of Physicians Choice - Defined as any cancer specific therapy or best supportive care. Treatment should be given according to the label and based upon local institutional medical practice and clinical judgement.

Experimental: Bendamustine IV - Up to 8 cycles of Bendamustine (120mg/m2 Days 1 and 2, every 21 days (+ 3 days).


Treatment: drugs: Bendamustine IV


Other interventions: Treatment of Physicians Choice
Defined as any cancer specific therapy or best supportive care. Treatment should be given according to the label and based upon local institutional medical practice and clinical judgement.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression-free survival - Screening of 14 days, prior to ramdomisation. 8 cycles of 21 days, then follow up every 3 months after end of last cycle until disease progression, then every 6 months.</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 cycles of 21 days, then follow up every 3 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Response Rate - Complete remission (CR)/partial remission (PR), Duration of response (DR), Overall survival (OS), Safety and tolerability, Change in health related quality of life (HRQL) measures</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 cycles of 21 days, then follow up every 3 months until progressive disease, then every 6 months for overall survival</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Indolent B-cell lymphoma: grades 1-3a follicular, small lymphocytic,
             lymphoplasmacytic, and marginal zone lymphoma; stages III-IV, or bulky disease stage
             II (i.e. as any single mass &gt; 5 cm in any direction) defined according to WHO
             Classification, 2008

          2. CT imaging in screening phase (based on local evaluation) showing 2 or more clearly
             demarcated lesions with a largest diameter = 1.5 cm, or 1 clearly demarcated lesion
             with a largest diameter = 2.0 cm. CT imaging performed at screening will be considered
             the baseline image

          3. Indolent B-cell NHL that remains stable or unresponsive during or within 6 months of
             treatment with rituximab or a rituximab-containing regimen:

               -  Maintaining stable disease or failure to achieve PR to rituximab-based therapy.
                  (CT imaging will support this finding, and will be performed at least 30 days
                  after the last dose of rituximab-based therapy) or,

               -  Disease progression while on rituximab-based therapy (e.g., includes 4 weekly
                  courses of rituximab given at 6 week intervals) or,

               -  Disease progression in subjects with stable disease or better response to
                  rituximab-based therapy &lt; 6 months of the last dose of rituximab Note: Subjects
                  must have received at least 4 infusions of rituximab (either as monotherapy or in
                  combination with any chemotherapy).

          4. Screening laboratory values:

               -  Platelets = 75,000/µL (7 x 109 cells/L)

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) = 1,000/µL (1.0 x 109 cells/L)

               -  ALT, AST and alkaline phosphatase = 2.5 ULN and total bilirubin = 1.5 xULN
                  (isolated predominantly indirect hyperbilirubinaemia due to Gilbert's syndrome is
                  acceptable for inclusion)

          5. ECOG Performance Status of 0, 1, or 2

          6. Age = 18 years

          7. Life expectancy of at least 3 months

          8. Signed written informed consent prior to performing any study-specific procedures

        Main exclusion criteria:

          1. Grade 3b follicular lymphoma or evidence that the indolent lymphoma has transformed to
             aggressive lymphoma as verified by biopsy confirmation [e.g. constitutional symptoms,
             poor performance status, fast growing tumour or increasing lactate dehydrogenase (LDH)
             level]

          2. Previous allogeneic stem cell transplant

          3. Previous external beam radiation therapy to the pelvis. Previous external beam
             radiation therapy for bony disease to the cranium, mediastinum, and axilla or to more
             than 3 vertebral bodies

          4. More than 10 mg prednisolone daily at the time of randomisation

          5. Prior bendamustine treatment within 1 year of randomisation not resulting in a CR or
             PR for at least 6 months

          6. Known CNS involvement of indolent lymphoma

          7. Other past or current malignancy. Subjects who have been free of malignancy for at
             least 5 years, or have a history of definitively treated non-melanoma skin cancer, or
             successfully treated in situ carcinoma, are eligible

          8. Chronic or current active infectious disease requiring systemic antibiotics,
             antifungal, or antiviral treatment such as, but not limited to, chronic renal
             infection, chronic chest infection with bronchiectasis, tuberculosis and active
             Hepatitis C

          9. Clinically significant cardiac disease including unstable angina, acute myocardial
             infarction within 6 months of screening, congestive heart failure, and arrhythmia
             requiring therapy, with the exception of extrasystoles or minor conduction
             abnormalities. Subjects with well controlled congestive heart failure and atrial
             arrhythmias need not be excluded but should be discussed with the study Medical
             Monitor

         10. Significant concurrent, uncontrolled medical condition including, but not limited to,
             renal, hepatic, haematological, gastrointestinal, endocrine, pulmonary, neurological,
             cerebral or psychiatric disease

         11. History of significant cerebrovascular disease or event with significant symptoms or
             sequelae

         12. Current active liver or biliary disease (with the exception of Gilbert's syndrome or
             asymptomatic gallstones, liver metastases or otherwise stable chronic liver disease
             per investigator assessment)

         13. Jaundice

         14. Known HIV, Hepatitis B or Hepatitis C positive

         15. Creatinine clearance = 10 mL/min (measured or estimated using Cockcroft and Gault
             equation)

         16. Treatment with any known non-marketed drug substance or experimental therapy within
             5-terminal half-lives or 4 weeks prior to screening, whichever is longer or currently
             participating in any other interventional clinical study unless the sole purpose of
             the study is for collection of survival data

         17. Known or suspected inability to comply with study protocol

         18. Lactating women, women with a positive pregnancy test at screening or women (of
             childbearing potential) as well as men with partners of childbearing potential, who
             are not willing to use adequate contraception from study start through last treatment
             dose and for 6 months following cessation of treatment. Female contraception must be
             individually recommended by an expert. Adequate contraception is defined as
             abstinence, oral contraceptive, either combined or progestogen alone, injectable
             progestogen, implants of levonorgestrel, estrogenic vaginal ring, percutaneous
             contraceptive patches, intrauterine device (IUD) or intrauterine system (IUS), male
             partner sterilization (vasectomy with documentation of azoospermia) prior to the
             female subject's entry into the study, and this male is the sole partner for that
             subject, or double barrier method: condom and an occlusive cap (diaphragm or
             cervical/vault caps) with a vaginal spermicidal agent
             (foam/gel/film/cream/suppository).

        20.Major surgery less than 30 days prior to start of treatment. 21.Known hypersensitivity
        to the active substance or any excipients that cannot be controlled by appropriate
        pre-medication</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria />
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/02/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>125</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/10/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Brisbane</hospital>
    <postcode>QLD 4102 - Brisbane</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Slovakia</country>
      <state>Bratislava</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Mundipharma Research Limited</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To compare the efficacy of bendamustine against treatment of physician's choice on
      progression-free survival in subjects with indolent B-cell NHL.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01289223</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Margaret C Wilson</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>info@contact-clinical-trials.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>