<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="1473">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/02/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/02/2007</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00436020</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>rTMS in the Treatment of Bipolar Depression</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Double-Blind Sham Controlled Trial of rTMS in the Treatment of Bipolar Depression</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>paulfitzgerald</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Bipolar Affective Disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human Genetics and Inherited Disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other human genetics and inherited disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: devices - TMS
Treatment: devices - Sham TMS

Active Comparator: 1 - Active

Placebo Comparator: 2 - Sham TMS


Treatment: devices: TMS
Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation

Treatment: devices: Sham TMS
Sham Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>HAMD</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks and 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients will be included if they:

          1. Have a DSM-IV diagnosis of a bipolar disorder (type I or II) and currently meet
             criteria for a major depressive episode (SCID 11).

          2. Be aged 18-70.

          3. Have the persistence of depressive symptoms for at least one month at sufficient
             severity to warrant a diagnosis of major depressive episode

          4. Have a Hamilton Depression Rating Scale Score of &gt; 20 (moderate - severe depression).
             Including only a more severely ill group of subjects limits the placebo response rate
             [32]. Moreover, this will allow us to address the application of rTMS methods in the
             most clinically relevant subgroup of patients (in addition helping to constrain group
             heterogeneity, a major issue in depression research).

          5. Have had no increase or initiation of new antidepressant (or other psychoactive)
             therapy in the 4 weeks prior to screening.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Patients who have an unstable medical condition, neurological disorder or any history
             of a seizure disorder or are currently pregnant or lactating.

          2. In the opinion of the investigator, are a sufficient suicidal risk to require
             immediate electro-convulsive therapy.

          3. Have a current DSM IV diagnosis of substance abuse or dependence disorder, a diagnosis
             of a personality disorder (SCID II) or another axis 1 disorder.

        Please note: several of these criteria (e.g. inclusion criteria 1 &amp; 2, exclusion criteria
        3) have been selected to explicitly constrain the heterogeneity of the sample to increase
        the likely power of the study to detect differences between the groups given the
        potentially subtle difference between the treatment methods.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/04/2007</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Unknown status</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/12/2009</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Alfred Psychiatry Research Centre - Prahran, Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3181 - Prahran, Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Bayside Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Bipolar affective disorder (BPAD) is:

        -  A serious mental illness

        -  Estimated to be present in as high as 6.4% of the population in Western populations

        -  Associated with considerable disability and high morbidity.

        -  Characterized by periods of both lowered and elevated mood (i.e. depression and
           mania/hypomania respectively).

      The depressive aspect of bipolar disorder is often overlooked, possibly due to its less
      dramatic nature, despite its significant impact on the lives of those affected. Bipolar
      depression (BPAD-DP) is associated with a twenty fold increased risk of suicide, and
      typically lasts three to five times as long as a manic or hypomanic episode. Despite this,
      there has been relatively sparse investigation of treatments for BPAD-DP, with guidelines
      based primarily on expert judgment rather than clinical trials. In addition a significant
      proportion of patients with bipolar depression do not respond to the range of commonly used
      medications. One of the only substantially new treatments developed for unipolar depression
      in recent years has been the advent of repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS).
      Repetitive TMS has been evaluated in over 20 trials conducted over the last ten years, but no
      substantive trials have explored its use in bipolar depression. We propose to do this,
      conducting a large scale clinical trial. The trial will include the assessment of both high
      frequency left sided rTMS (as there is clearly the greatest evidence for the effectiveness of
      this in unipolar depression) and low frequency right sided rTMS (as this there is growing
      evidence of the effectiveness of this in unipolar depression and we have an excellent pilot
      study to suggest its potential in BPAD-DP and it has never previously been assessed in a
      clinical trial exclusively targeting this patient group). Our previous research strongly
      supports the effectiveness of rTMS paradigms including low frequency right-sided stimulation
      in unipolar depression and suggests these may have value in BPAD-DP. As BPAD-DP is clearly a
      clinical problem of significant impact and with limited treatment options, there is a
      pressing need for the development and definitive testing of novel treatments such as rTMS.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00436020</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Paul B Fitzgerald, FRANZCP, PhD</name>
      <address>Alfred Psychiatry Research Centre</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Paul B Fitzgerald, MBBS, MPM, FRANCZP,PhD</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+61 03 90766564</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.fitzgerald@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>