<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4351">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/03/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/03/2014</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02088437</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>High Intensity Physiotherapy for Hip Fractures</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>High Intensity Physiotherapy for Hip Fractures in the Acute Hospital Setting</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>HIP4hips</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>32/14</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hip Fractures</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fractures</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - Intensive physiotherapy
Other interventions - Usual Care

Active Comparator: Usual care - usual care physiotherapy - once daily treatment whilst inpatient in acute hospital

Experimental: Intensive physiotherapy - additional once daily physiotherapy and once daily allied health assistant intervention


Other interventions: Intensive physiotherapy
additional once daily physiotherapy and once daily allied health assistant intervention (equals two more treatments) whilst an inpatient in acute hospital

Other interventions: Usual Care
once daily physiotherapy whilst acute hospital inpatient

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>modified IOWA Level of Assistance Scale - Functional score measuring 6 mobility domains</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>length of stay - acute and rehabilitation - the length of acute hospital stay and rehabilitation stay - until discharge home or to a long term facility</outcome>
      <timepoint>participants will be followed for duration of hospital stay - average one month</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>timed up and go</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Glasgow Outcomes Score -Extended</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>discharge destination - discharge destination from the acute hospital - options include: home, fast stream rehabilitation, slow stream rehabilitation, long term facility</outcome>
      <timepoint>participants will be followed until discharge from the acute hospital - average 10 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>physical readiness for discharge - when a patient is deemed physically ready go home - eg can access their house and mobilise within house and outdoors</outcome>
      <timepoint>average one month</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>12-Item Short Form Health Survey (SF-12)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>EuroQOL five dimensions questionnaire (EQ-5D)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Admission to The Alfred with an isolated hip fracture and treated with internal
             fixation, aged 65 or above</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  fracture is in the sub-trochanteric region of the femur,

          -  if it is pathological,

          -  if post operative orders are for non-weight bearing on the operated hip,

          -  if they were unable to mobilise independently (or with gait aid) prior to admission,

          -  or if they were admitted from a nursing home.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2>The people administering the treatment/s</masking2>
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/03/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>92</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/09/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3181 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Alfred</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Every day, more than 40 Australian break their hip, Most are over the age of sixty five. Hip
      fractures are a significant problem for the older people, the hospital system and community
      as a whole because of the increasing numbers of fractures and the cost of hospitalisation and
      ongoing care. After one year, less than half of all people with a hip fracture can walk as
      well as they did before the fracture. Physiotherapy in the acute hospital setting is an
      integral part of patient care, although the intensity of physiotherapy a patient receives is
      variable and the optimal number of treatment sessions per day remains unknown. Studies in
      other patient groups have shown that increased physiotherapy can improve patient outcomes by
      increasing muscle strength and mobility. It can also reduce the negative effects of bed rest
      such as muscle wasting, blood clots in the lungs or leg veins and chest infections such as
      pneumonia. This study aims to investigate the effectiveness of an intensive physiotherapy
      program in hip fracture patients to further understand this and the effect it has on patient
      function.

      In this research the investigators will randomly allocate patients into 2 groups; usual care
      and intensive physiotherapy. The usual care group will have physiotherapy treatment daily
      whereas the intensive physiotherapy group will have an additional daily treatment by a
      physiotherapist as well as a daily treatment by an allied health assistant. The objectives
      are to achieve better functional outcomes in the patient's hospital stay (ie improved
      mobility), reduce the time for patients to be physically ready to go home, increase the
      number of patients able to go directly home or to fast stream rehabilitation (rather than a
      slow stream option).

      If increased intensity of physiotherapy is found to improve patient's mobility outcomes, this
      research will provide the confidence to endorse a change to current clinical practice.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02088437</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Lara A Kimmel, B.Physio</name>
      <address>The Alfred</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>