<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4192">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/06/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/06/2013</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01881230</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluate Risk/Benefit of Nab Paclitaxel in Combination With Gemcitabine and Carboplatin Compared to Gemcitabine and Carboplatin in Triple Negative Metastatic Breast Cancer (or Metastatic Triple Negative Breast Cancer)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 2/3, Multi-Center, Open-Label, Randomized Study of Weekly Nab®-Paclitaxel in Combination With Gemcitabine or Carboplatin, Compared to Gemcitabine/Carboplatin, as First Line Treatment in Subjects With ER, PgR, and HER2 Negative (Triple Negative) Metastatic Breast Cancer</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>tnAcity</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>2013-000113-20</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>ABI-007-MBC-001</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Breast Tumor</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Breast Cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cancer of the Breast</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Estrogen Receptor- Negative Breast Cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>HER2- Negative Breast Cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Progesterone Receptor- Negative Breast Cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Recurrent Breast Cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Stage IV Breast Cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Triple-negative Breast Cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Triple-negative Metastatic Breast Cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Metastatic Breast Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - nab-Paclitaxel 125 mg/m2
Treatment: drugs - Carboplatin AUC 2
Treatment: drugs - gemcitabine 1000 mg

Experimental: nab-Paclitaxel 125mg/m^2 plus gemcitabine 1000mg/m^2 - (Phase 2) Treatment Arm A: nab-Paclitaxel 125mg/m^2 on Days 1 and 8 by intravenousI (IV) administration over 30 minutes, followed by gemcitabine 1000 mg/m2 on Days 1 and 8 by IV administration over 30 minutes in triple negative metastatic breast cancer (TNMBC) subjects

Experimental: nab-Paclitaxel 125mg/m^2 plus carboplatin AUC2 - (Phase 2) Treatment Arm B: nab-Paclitaxel 125 mg/m^2 on Days 1 and 8 by IV administration without hypersensitivity prophylaxis, followed by carboplatin AUC 2 on Days 1 and 8 by IV administration

Active Comparator: Gemcitabine 1000mg/m^2 plus carboplatin AUC2 - (Phase 2) Treatment Arm C: Gemcitabine 1000 mg/m^2 on Days 1 and 8 by IV administration followed by carboplatin AUC2 on Days 1 and 8 by IV administration

Experimental: Selected nab Paclitaxel arm from Phase 2 inTNMBC subjects - Phase 3 Treatment Arm 1 -Selected Phase 2 nab paclitaxel treatment arm of either nab-Paclitaxel 125 mg/m2 on Days 1 and 8 by IV administration without hypersensitivity prophylaxis, followed by gemcitabine 1000 mg/m2 on Days 1 and 8 by IV administration OR nab-Paclitaxel 125 mg/m2 on Days 1 and 8 by IV administration without hypersensitivity prophylaxis, followed by carboplatin AUC 2 on Days 1 and 8 by IV administration

Active Comparator: Gemcitabine 1000mg/m^2 plus carboplatin AUC 2 - (Phase 3) Treatment Arm 2: Gemcitabine 1000 mg/m^2 on Days 1 and 8 by IV administration over 30 minutes, followed by carboplatin AUC2 on Days 1 and 8 by IV administration


Treatment: drugs: nab-Paclitaxel 125 mg/m2


Treatment: drugs: Carboplatin AUC 2


Treatment: drugs: gemcitabine 1000 mg


</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression Free Survival (PFS) for triple negative metastatic breast cancer subjects (Phase 2) - Time from the randomization date to the start of disease progression or subject death from any cause (progression assessed by investigator using Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors 1.1 (RECIST 1.1 guidelines) for triple negative metastatic breast cancer (TNMBC) subjects</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to approximately 18 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Investigator-determined Overall Response Rate (ORR) (Phase 2) - Complete response (CR) or partial response (PR) based on investigator assessment of response using RECIST 1.1 guidelines</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to approximately 18 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of subjects who initiated Cycle 6 receiving doublet combination therapy (Phase 2) - Defined as the Percentage of subjects who initiated Cycle 6 of treatment</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to approximately 18 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Investigator determined Overall Survival (OS) for triple negative metastatic breast cancer (TNMBC) subjects (Phase 2) - Defined as the time between randomization and death</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to approximately 18 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety for triple negative metastatic breast cancer (TNMBC) subjects (Phase 2) - Number ofTreatment Emergent Adverse Events (TEAEs), Serious Adverse Events (SAEs), laboratory abnormalities Percentage and number of subjects who discontinued for adverse event</outcome>
      <timepoint>up to approximately 19 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of subjects experiencing dose modifications (dose interruptions and reductions); - The number of subjects with dose interruptions and reductions experienced by participants that occurred during the treatment period. Dose interruptions and reductions are typically caused by clinically significant laboratory abnormalities and /or treatment emergent adverse events/toxicities.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 19 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of subjects who discontinued from all study treatment adverse events - An adverse event (AE) is any noxious, unintended, or untoward medical occurrence that may appear or worsen in a subject during the course of a study. It may be a new intercurrent illness, a worsening concomitant illness, an injury, or any concomitant impairment of the subject's health, including laboratory test values (as specified by the criteria below), regardless of etiology. Any worsening (ie, any clinically significant adverse change in the frequency or intensity of a preexisting condition) should be considered an AE</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 19 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>A subject will be eligible for inclusion in this study only if all of
        the following criteria are met:

          1. Female subjects, age = 18 years at the time informed consent is signed

          2. Pathologically confirmed adenocarcinoma of the breast

          3. Pathologically confirmed as triple negative, source documented, defined as both of the
             following

               1. Estrogen Receptor (ER) and Progesterone Receptor (PgR) negative: &lt; 1% of tumor
                  cell nuclei are immunoreactive in the presence of evidence that the sample can
                  express ER or PgR (positive intrinsic controls)

               2. Human Epidermal Growth Factor Receptor 2 (HER2) negative as per American Society
                  of Clinical Oncology - College of American Pathologists (ASCO/CAP) guidelines i.
                  Immunohistochemistry (IHC) 0 or 1 Fluorescence In Situ Hybridization (FISH)
                  negative (or equivalent negative test). Subjects with IHC 2 must have a negative
                  by Fluorescence In Situ Hybridization (FISH),, (or equivalent negative test).

          4. Subjects with prior breast cancer history of different phenotypes (ie, ER/PgR/HER2
             positive) must have pathologic confirmation of triple negative disease in at least one
             of the current sites of metastasis

          5. Subjects must have received prior adjuvant or neoadjuvant anthracycline therapy;
             unless (a) anthracycline treatment was not indicated or was not the best treatment
             option for the subject in the opinion of the treating physician; and (b) anthracycline
             treatment remains not indicated or, in the opinion of the treating physician, is not
             the best treatment option for the subject's metastatic disease.

             a. Newly diagnosed subjects presenting with TNMBC are eligible for the study if
             anthracycline treatment is not indicated or is not the best treatment option for the
             subject in the opinion of the treating physician.

          6. Subjects with measurable metastatic disease, defined by Response Evaluation Criteria
             in Solid Tumors 1.1 (RECIST 1.1) guidelines

          7. Life expectancy = 16 weeks from randomization

          8. No prior cytotoxic chemotherapy for metastatic breast cancer. Prior immunotherapy
             and/or monoclonal antibody therapy are acceptable. Prior treatments must have been
             discontinued at least 30 days prior to start of study treatment and all related
             toxicities must have resolved to Grade 1 or less.

          9. Prior neoadjuvant or adjuvant chemotherapy, if given, must have been completed at
             least 6 months before randomization with all related toxicities resolved, and
             documented evidence of disease progression per RECIST 1.1 guidelines is required.

             a. If prior neoadjuvant or adjuvant chemotherapy contained taxane, gemcitabine, or
             platinum agents, the treatment must have completed at least 12 months before
             randomization

         10. Prior radiotherapy must have completed before randomization, with full recovery from
             acute radiation side effects. At least one measurable lesion must be completely
             outside the radiation portal or there must be unequivocal radiologic or clinical exam
             proof of progressive disease within the radiation portal, in accordance with RECIST
             1.1 guidelines

         11. At least 30 days from major surgery before randomization, with full recovery

         12. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0-1

         13. Subject has the following blood counts at screening:

               -  Absolute Neutrophil Count (ANC) = 1500/mm^2 ;

               -  Platelets = 100,000/mm^2 ;

               -  Hemoglobin (Hgb) = 9 g/dL

         14. Subject has the following blood chemistry levels at screening:

               -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) Serum glutamic-oxaloacetic transaminase (SGOT),
                  Alanine Aminotransferase (ALT ) Serum Glutamic Pyruvate Transaminase (SGPT) = 2.5
                  x upper limit of normal range (ULN); if hepatic metastases present = 5.0 x ULN

               -  Total serum bilirubin = ULN; or total bilirubin = 3.0 × ULN with direct bilirubin
                  within normal range in subjects with documented Gilbert's Syndrome

               -  Creatinine clearance &gt; 60 mL/min (by Cockcroft-Gault)

         15. Females of child-bearing potential [defined as a sexually mature women who (1) have
             not undergone hysterectomy (the surgical removal of the uterus) or bilateral
             oophorectomy (the surgical removal of both ovaries) or (2) have not been naturally
             postmenopausal for at least 24 consecutive months (i.e., has had menses at any time
             during the preceding 24 consecutive months)] must:

               -  Demonstrate a negative serum pregnancy test result at screening (performed by
                  central lab) confirmed by local negative urine pregnancy dipstick within 72 hours
                  prior to the first dose of IP); pregnancy test with sensitivity of at least 25
                  mIU/mL; and

               -  Either commit to true abstinence* from heterosexual contact (which must be
                  reviewed on a monthly basis) or agree to use, and be able to comply with, two
                  physician approved effective contraception methods (oral, injectable, or
                  implantable hormonal contraceptive; tubal ligation; intra-uterine device; barrier
                  contraceptive with spermicide; or vasectomized partner) without interruption for
                  28 days or longer as required by local guidelines, prior to starting study drug,
                  during the study therapy (including dose interruptions), and for 28 days after
                  discontinuation of the study or longer as required by local guidelines

         16. Females must abstain from breastfeeding starting at randomization, during study
             participation and for 28 days or longer as required by local guidelines, after IP
             discontinuation

         17. Understand and voluntarily sign an informed consent document prior to any study
             related assessments/procedures are conducted

         18. Able to adhere to the study visit schedule and other protocol requirements</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Female</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>A subject will not be eligible for inclusion in this study if any of the following criteria
        apply:

          1. Male subjects

          2. Concurrent chemotherapy or any other anti tumor therapy for breast cancer. Prior
             immunotherapy &amp; monoclonal antibody therapy are acceptable.

          3. Subjects who received prior cytotoxic chemotherapy after incomplete resection of
             locoregional recurrent disease

          4. History of, or known current evidence of brain metastasis, including leptomeningeal
             involvement.

          5. Subjects with bone as the only site of metastatic disease

          6. Subjects with regional lymph node as the only site of metastatic disease

          7. Serious intercurrent medical or psychiatric illness, including serious active
             infection

          8. History of class II-IV congestive heart failure or myocardial infarction within 6
             months of randomization

          9. History of other primary malignancy in the last 5 years prior to randomization.
             Subjects with prior breast cancer history are eligible, however, the most recently
             obtained biopsy must demonstrate triple negative disease (source documented). Subjects
             with prior history of in situ cancer or basal or localized squamous cell skin cancer
             are eligible.

         10. Subjects with a history of interstitial lung disease, history of slowly progressive
             dyspnea and unproductive cough, sarcoidosis, silicosis, idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis,
             pulmonary hypersensitivity pneumonitis or multiple uncontrolled or unstable allergies
             which, in the opinion of the investigator, may lead to serious complications

         11. Peripheral neuropathy Grade = 2 by National Cancer Institute Common Terminology
             Criteria for Adverse Events (NCI CTCAE) v4.0

         12. Subjects who have received an investigational product within the previous 4 weeks
             prior to randomization

         13. Subject is currently enrolled, or will enroll in a different clinical study in which
             investigational therapeutic procedures are performed or investigational therapies are
             administered while participating in this study

         14. Pregnant or nursing women

         15. Subjects with prior hypersensitivity to nab-paclitaxel, gemcitabine, carboplatin or
             any other platin, or nucleoside analogue agents

         16. Any significant medical condition, laboratory abnormality, or psychiatric illness that
             would prevent the subject from participating in the study

         17. Any condition including the presence of laboratory abnormalities, which places the
             subject at unacceptable risk if she were to participate in the study

         18. Any condition that confounds the ability to interpret data from the study

         19. History of seropositive human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)

         20. Subjects who are receiving immunosuppressive or myelosuppressive medications that
             would, in the opinion of the investigator, increase the risk of serious neutropenic
             complications</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>26/09/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>191</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>28/10/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Canberra Hospital - Garran</hospital>
    <hospital>Frankston Hospital Oncology Research - Frankston</hospital>
    <hospital>Border Medical Oncology - Wodonga</hospital>
    <hospital>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital - Nedlands</hospital>
    <postcode>2605 - Garran</postcode>
    <postcode>3199 - Frankston</postcode>
    <postcode>3690 - Wodonga</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Arizona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Arkansas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Illinois</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Indiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Louisiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Maryland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Michigan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Minnesota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Missouri</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Hampshire</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Jersey</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Oklahoma</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Oregon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Pennsylvania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>South Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Tennessee</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Virginia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Washington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>West Virginia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Wisconsin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Austria</country>
      <state>Innsbruck</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Austria</country>
      <state>Salzburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Austria</country>
      <state>Vienna</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Bahia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Paraná</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Rio de Janeiro</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Rio Grande do Sul</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>São Paulo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Fortaleza</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Ribeirao Preto</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Sao Jose Do Rio Preto</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Sao Paulo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Quebec</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Saskatchewan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Clermont-Ferrand</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Berlin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Bonn</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Frankfurt</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Freiburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Heidelberg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Hildesheim</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Köln</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>München</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Trier</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Ulm</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Athens</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Faliro</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Heraklion</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Rio Patras</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Bologna, Emilia-Romagna</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Ferrara</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Genova</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Grosseto</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Messina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Monza</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Napoli, Campania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Padova</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Reggio Emilia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Roma</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Rozzano (MI)</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Torino, Piemonte</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Treviglio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <state>Evora</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <state>Lisboa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <state>Porto</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Cordoba</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>San Sebastian</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Santiago de Compostela</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Sevilla</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Zaragoza</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Bath</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Manchester</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Middlesex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Sheffield South Yorkshire</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Celgene</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to compare the safety and efficacy of nab-paclitaxel in
      combination with either gemcitabine or carboplatin to the combination of gemcitabine and
      carboplatin as first line treatment in female subjects with triple negative metastatic breast
      cancer (TNMBC) or metastatic triple negative breast cancer.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01881230</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Yardley DA, Brufsky A, Coleman RE, Conte PF, Cortes J, Glück S, Nabholtz JM, O'Shaughnessy J, Beck RM, Ko A, Renschler MF, Barton D, Harbeck N. Phase II/III weekly nab-paclitaxel plus gemcitabine or carboplatin versus gemcitabine/carboplatin as first-line treatment of patients with metastatic triple-negative breast cancer (the tnAcity study): study protocol for a randomized controlled trial. Trials. 2015 Dec 16;16:575. doi: 10.1186/s13063-015-1101-7. Erratum in: Trials. 2016;17:63.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Debora Barton, M.D.</name>
      <address>Celgene Corporation</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>