<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6776">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/09/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/09/2017</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT03327155</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Western Australian Pre-exposure Prophylaxis for HIV Implementation Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Western Australian Pre-exposure Prophylaxis for HIV Implementation Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>PrEPIT-WA</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>HEPP1701</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>HIV Prevention</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Tenofovir disoproxil fumarate (TDF)/emtricitabine (FTC)

Experimental: TDF/FTC (300mg/200mg) once daily - Tenofovir disoproxil fumarate (TDF)/emtricitabine (FTC) (300mg/200mg) on tablet once daily with food.


Treatment: drugs: Tenofovir disoproxil fumarate (TDF)/emtricitabine (FTC)
One tablet, containing 300mg of TDF and 200mg of FTC once daily with food.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of HIV infection per 100 person years among study participants - Statistical analyses of risk of HIV seroconversion among individuals who were prescribed PrEP (as part of the study) will focus on estimating the risk of seroconversion per 100 person years after TDF/FTC prescription and the effect modifying role of non-adherence to the prescribed medication schedule.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 weeks after the last participant completed their last follow-up visit (Month 18 visit)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of HIV diagnoses among gay and bisexual men notified to Western Australian Department of Health - Number of diagnoses will be measured using routinely reported data from the Western Australia registry of HIV diagnoses</outcome>
      <timepoint>number of HIV diagnoses in the 12 month period prior to the date of first recruitment will be compared to the annual number of HIV diagnoses in the 12 month period after the study is fully recruited</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Trends in test positivity of Sexually Transmitted Infections (STIs, gonorrhoea, chlamydia and infectious syphilis) among study participants - To calculate trends in test positivity of STI (gonorrhoea, chlamydia and infectious syphilis) among study participants, and describe changes over time</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 weeks after the last participant completed their last follow-up visit (Month 18 visit)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of enrollment to the study by clinic type - To measure in the four study sites</outcome>
      <timepoint>up to 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. HIV negative at enrolment, with a negative HIV test result conducted at the enrolment
             clinic within seven days of initiating PrEP

          2. At high and ongoing risk for acquiring HIV infection [as defined by Behavioural
             Eligibility criteria in the Australasian Society for HIV, Viral Hepatitis and Sexual
             Health Medicine (ASHM) HIV PrEP Clinical Guidelines]

          3. Aged 18 years or over

          4. Live in WA or visit WA enough to attend clinics for follow-up assessments

          5. Willing and able to provide informed consent

          6. Medicare ineligible individuals may be enrolled if the clinical service is able to
             cover the costs of monitoring of the patient</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. HIV-1 infected or has symptoms consistent with acute viral infection (If HIV positive
             status is not confirmed by testing, delay starting PrEP for at least one month and
             reconfirm negative HIV-1 status)

          2. Having an estimated creatinine clearance (glomerular filtration rate [eGFR]) &lt;60ml/min

          3. Having or developing clinical symptoms suggestive of lactic acidosis or pronounced
             hepatotoxicity (including nausea, vomiting, unusual or unexpected stomach discomfort,
             and weakness)

          4. Concurrently taking a nephrotoxic agent (e.g., high-dose non-steroidal
             anti-inflammatory drugs / NSAIDs)

          5. Allergic to TDF and/or FTC (based on self-report or recorded)

          6. Concurrently taking prescribed products containing FTC or TDF including ATRIPLA速,
             COMPLERA速, EMTRIVA, STRIBILD速, VIREAD, TAF (tenofovir alafenamide), GENVOYA, DESCOVY;
             other drugs containing lamivudine; HEPSERA

          7. Factors or conditions that may compromise a participant's access to health services
             for follow-up (incarceration or planned relocation and potential absence from Western
             Australia)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>2000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/06/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>South Terrace Sexual Health Clinic - Fremantle</hospital>
    <hospital>GP on Beaufort - Mount Lawley</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Perth Hospital Sexual Health Clinic - Perth</hospital>
    <hospital>M Clinic - Perth</hospital>
    <postcode>6160 - Fremantle</postcode>
    <postcode>6050 - Mount Lawley</postcode>
    <postcode>6000 - Perth</postcode>
    <postcode>6005 - Perth</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Kirby Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Government of Western Australia, Department of Health</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Western Australia AIDS Council</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Despite all prevention efforts, many people in Australia continue to be infected with HIV.
      The Seventh National HIV Strategy 2014-2017 in Australia aims to work towards the elimination
      of HIV transmission by the year 2020. This project will evaluate a new additional way to
      lower people's chances of getting HIV. It will provide pre-exposure prophylaxis (PrEP) to
      people who are at high risk for HIV and evaluate what impact this new prevention approach
      will have on HIV in WA at the community level.

      The drug used in PREPIT-WA is called generic TDF/FTC (made by Mylan Laboratories Ltd.). The
      generic TDF/FTC is a single tablet made up of two HIV medications: tenofovir disoproxil
      fumarate and emtricitabine (a combination known as TDF/FTC). TDF and FTC have been widely
      used for many years to treat HIV. When used with other medicines in people who already have
      HIV, TDF/FTC reduces the amount of HIV virus in the blood. TDF/FTC does not cure HIV or AIDS,
      and it is not an HIV vaccine.

      As a treatment for people who already have HIV, TDF/FTC is approved for use in most of the
      world, including Australia. As a medicine for PrEP, to lower chances of HIV in those who are
      not infected, TDF/FTC has been approved in the US, and Truvada速 (which contains TDF/FTC made
      by Gilead Sciences Inc.) was approved for PrEP in Australia in May 2016. At the start of the
      project, the generic TDF/FTC is not approved in Australia for the use as PrEP but it may
      become registered for use and more freely available in Australia in the future.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03327155</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>David Cooper, MD</name>
      <address>The Kirby Institute, UNSW Sydney</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Barbara Yeung, BHSc, MPH</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+612 9385 0879</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>byeung@kirby.unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>