<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6733">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/09/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/09/2017</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT03292237</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Intensive Nutrition in Critically Ill Adults</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Intensive Nutrition in Critically Ill Adults: A Pilot Randomised Controlled Study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>ANZICRC/ER/001 Draft</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Critical Illness</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Critically Ill</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - Supplemental parenteral nutrition

No Intervention: Standard Nutrition Arm - In ICU:
After enrolment, patients allocated to the standard nutrition therapy (control) group will commence or continue nutrition via an enteral tube to a target rate according to unit protocol including the use of promotility agents and the placement of nasojejunal feeding tubes if required.
PN will only be used if the above methods have been attempted, or an absolute contraindication to EN develops.
Unless there is specific indication for a compounded PN solution, the PN used in the standard care group will be the same as used in the intervention arm.
After ICU:
Nutrition management will be as per usual site management at that hospital.
Nutrition intake amounts will be recorded 3 times per week using provided study documents and assessment tools.

Experimental: Intensive Arm - In ICU:
Supplemental PN will be commenced within 2 hours of randomisation. The starting dose of PN will be determined by the amount of energy received in the 24 hours prior to randomisation
The need for the intervention will be based on the adequacy of nutrition provision from both PN and EN and assessed daily until ICU discharge
If there is an actual or anticipated interruption of EN for greater than 2 hours the PN must be run at 20 kcal/kg calculated body weight until EN is recommenced. After the interruption, EN should be recommenced as per local protocol.
After ICU:
An intensive nutrition intervention will be provided on the ward in the intervention group. This will include daily review from dedicated study dietitians and a clearly protocolized hierarchical management plan which reflects best practice clinical management.


Other interventions: Supplemental parenteral nutrition
Supplemental parenteral nutrition (product to be confirmed)

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total energy delivered - Total energy delivered to the participant from nutritional therapy over hospital admission</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 28</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total protein delivered - total protein amount delivered over hospital admission</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total infectious complication rate - Total infectious complication rate (measured as prescription of new antibiotics)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of mechanical ventilation - Duration of mechanical ventilation</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of hospital stay - length of hospital stay for the participant</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In hospital mortality - Number of participant deaths</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional measures - ICU Mobility Scale (Tipping et al)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life - Euroqol 5 D</outcome>
      <timepoint>90 and 180 day follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Days alive and at home - The number of days the participant has spent alive and at home since hospital discharge</outcome>
      <timepoint>90 and 180 day follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resource Utilisation - Use of healthcare resources following hospital discharge (readmissions to hospital, surgery, allied health services)</outcome>
      <timepoint>90 and 180 day follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost effectiveness - Cost of hospital stay between the 2 different arms</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients should be screened for eligibility up until 120 hours of their first ICU
        admission. Those meeting all the inclusion and none of the exclusion criteria will be
        eligible for enrolment.

        Patients in intensive care who meet all of the following will be eligible:

          -  Admitted to intensive care between 72 hours and 120 hours previously

          -  Mechanically ventilated at the time of enrolment

          -  At least 16 years of age

          -  Have central venous access suitable for PN solution administration

          -  Have 1 or more organ system failure (respiratory, cardiovascular or renal) related to
             their acute illness defined as:

               1. PaO2/FiO2 = 300 mmHg

               2. Currently on 1 or more continuous vasopressor infusion which were started at
                  least 4 hours ago at a minimum dose of:

                    1. Dopamine greater than 5 mcg/kg/min

                    2. Noradrenaline = 0.1mcg/kg/min

                    3. Adrenaline = 0.1 mcg/kg/min

                    4. Any dose of total vasopressin

                    5. Milrinone &gt;0.25mcg/kg/min)

               3. Renal dysfunction defined as

                  In patients without known renal disease:

                    1. Serum Creatinine &gt; 171 mmol/l OR

                    2. Currently receiving renal replacement therapy

                  In patients with known renal disease:

                    1. An absolute increase of &gt; 50% in serum Creatinine from baseline OR

                    2. Currently receiving renal replacement therapy

               4. Currently has an intracranial pressure monitor or ventricular drain in situ</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Both EN and PN cannot be delivered at enrolment (i.e. either an enteral tube or a
             central venous catheter cannot be placed or clinicians feel that EN or PN cannot be
             safely administered due to any other reason).

          2. Currently receiving PN

          3. Standard PN solutions cannot be delivered at enrolment (i.e. clinicians believe that a
             patient definitely needs a specific parenteral nutrition formulation (e.g.
             glutamine-supplementation or specific lipid formulation).

          4. Death is imminent or deemed highly likely in the next 96 hours.

          5. There is a current treatment limitation in place or the patient is unlikely to survive
             to 6 months due to underlying illness

          6. More than 80% of energy requirements have been satisfactorily delivered via the
             enteral route in the last 24 hours .

          7. Are known to be pregnant

          8. The treating clinician does not believe the study to be in the best interest of the
             patient</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Supportive Care</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2018</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>240</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/07/2022</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>ANZIC-RC - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australian and New Zealand Intensive Care Research Centre</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Baxter Healthcare Corporation</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Despite the widespread use of nutrition therapy, no large scale randomized controlled trials
      (RCTs) have demonstrated positive outcomes with delivery of nutrition therapy early in
      critical illness, with some showing no effect with delayed nutrition or even harm.

      There are several possible reasons for the lack of observed benefit from RCTs to date;
      interventions have been short in duration (usually 3-10 days after intensive care unit (ICU)
      admission), perhaps applied at the incorrect time in regards to the patients metabolism and
      recovery, do not consider the patients nutrition risk, and have not addressed what happens to
      nutrition intake post ICU in critically ill individuals. This may explain why RCTs to date
      have not observed any positive associations with the delivery of nutrition; our focus to date
      may have been on the wrong stage of illness. A future study is thus urgently needed, which
      addresses the deficiencies in current RCTs by optimizing nutrition delivery for the whole
      hospital stay and collecting meaningful clinical, process and outcome data, which will
      potentially inform a larger trial of a similar nature.

      This initial study aims to determine whether optimization of energy and protein using a
      pre-tested supplemental parenteral nutrition (PN) strategy in the Intensive Care Unit (ICU)
      and an intensive nutrition intervention in the post ICU period will deliver more total energy
      and protein than standard nutrition care during hospital admission in a group of critically
      ill patients with at least one organ system failure.

      It is hypothesized that use of a supplemental PN strategy in ICU and an intensive nutrition
      intervention in the post ICU period will lead to a minimum increase of 15% in daily energy
      delivery for the whole hospital admission compared to standard nutrition care.

      Fifteen percent has been estimated as the minimum acceptable clinical difference between the
      two groups.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03292237</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Emma Ridley</name>
      <address>ANZIC-RC</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Emma Ridley, MPH</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+614399030350</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>emma.ridley@monash.edu</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>