<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3403">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/10/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/10/2011</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01494610</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pharmacokinetic and Pharmacodynamic (PK and PD) Study of Fluticasone Propionate and Salmeterol Combination Product Delivered in a Capsule-based Inhaler and in a Multi-dose Dry Powder Inhaler in Moderate Asthma Patients and Moderate to Severe Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD) Patients.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Comparative Bioavailability Study to Compare the Pharmacokinetic (PK) and Pharmacodynamic (PD) Effects of Fluticasone Propionate and Salmeterol Delivered by Fluticasone Propionate/ Salmeterol Combination in a Capsule-based Inhaler and a Multi-dose Dry Powder Inhaler, in Moderate Asthma Patients and Moderate to Severe Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD) Patients.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>114334</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Asthma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Asthma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - SERETIDE Rotacaps
Treatment: drugs - SERETIDE Diskus

Experimental: SERETIDE Rotacaps - Fluticasone propionate (250 micrograms [ug])/Salmeterol (50 ug) combination delivered in a capsule-based inhaler

Active Comparator: SERETIDE Diskus - Fluticasone propionate (250 ug)/Salmeterol (50 ug) combination delivered in a multi-dose dry powder inhaler

Placebo Comparator: Placebo Rotacaps - Placebo delivered in a capsule-based inhaler

Placebo Comparator: Placebo Diskus - Placebo delivered in a multi-dose dry powder inhaler


Treatment: drugs: SERETIDE Rotacaps
The study consists of four treatment periods of 10 +/- 1 days each in a cross-over fashion. Each patient will be administered SERETIDE delivered via a capsule-based inhaler (Rotacaps) twice for two treatment periods and a placebo delivered via a capsule-based inhaler (Rotacaps) twice for two treatment periods in a randomised, double-blind, double-dummy fashion. Dosing is twice daily in the morning and evening over the duration of each treatment period.

Treatment: drugs: SERETIDE Diskus
The study consists of four treatment periods of 10 +/- 1 days each in a cross-over fashion. Each patient will be administered SERETIDE delivered via a multi-dose dry powder inhaler (Diskus) twice for two treatment periods and a placebo delivered via a multi-dose dry powder inhaler (Diskus) twice for two treatment periods in a randomised, double-blind, double-dummy fashion. Dosing is twice daily in the morning and evening over the duration of each treatment period.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Area Under the Concentration Time Curve Over the Dosing Period (AUC[0-tau]) for FP - Blood samples of participants (par.) with asthma and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) were collected and analyzed for AUC(0-tau), a measure of the amount of drug available at target tissue (in plasma) for a fixed dosing interval (12 hours). Asthma is a disorder that causes the airways of the lungs to swell and narrow, leading to difficulty in breathing. COPD is a chronic lung disease with structural changes in lungs, leading to difficulty in breathing.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At pre-morning dose; 5, 10, 30 minutes post-dose (PD); and 1, 2, 4, 8, 10, and 12 hours PD on Day 10 of each study period (P): Study Day (SD) 10 (reference day is SD 1 or Randomization day), 20, 30, and 40 (+/-1) for P 1, 2, 3, and 4, respectively</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weighted Mean Serum Cortisol (SC) Over 0 to 12 Hours Post Dose - Participants' blood samples were collected and analyzed for SC levels. Weighted mean SC levels are evaluted as a measure of the degree of cortisol suppression, allowing for the determination of whether differences in systemic exposure to the inhaled steroid component of two devices can be significant enough to result in the differences in the body's ability to release cortisol. Weighted means were derived by calculating the AUC over the 0-12 hour period, using the linear trapezoidal rule (statistical technique used for numerical analysis) and then dividing it by the actual time interval.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At pre-morning dose; 30 minutes post-dose (PD); and 1, 2, 4, 8, 10, and 12 hours PD on Day 10 of each study period (P): Study Day (SD) 10 (reference day is SD 1 or Randomization day), 20, 30, and 40 (+/-1) for P 1, 2, 3, and 4, respectively</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Plasma AUC(0-tau) and Plasma AUC From Time Zero (Pre-dose) to Last Time of Quantifiable Concentration (AUC[0-tlast]) for Salmeterol - Blood samples of participants with asthma and COPD were collected and analyzed for AUC(0-tau) and AUC(0-tlast). AUC(0-tau) is a measure of the amount of drug available at target tissue (in plasma) for a fixed dosing interval (12 hours). AUC(0-tlast) is a measure of the plasma drug concentration from pre-dose to the last measurable concentration.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At pre-morning dose; 5, 10, 30 minutes post-dose (PD); and 1, 2, 4, 8, 10, and 12 hours PD on Day 10 of each study period (P): Study Day (SD) 10 (reference day is SD 1 or Randomization day), 20, 30, and 40 (+/-1) for P 1, 2, 3, and 4, respectively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean AUC(0-tlast) for FP - Blood samples of participants with asthma and COPD were collected and analyzed for AUC(0-tlast). AUC(0-tlast) is a measure of the plasma drug concentration from pre-dose to the last measurable concentration.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At pre-morning dose; 5, 10, 30 minutes post-dose (PD); and 1, 2, 4, 8, 10, and 12 hours PD on Day 10 of each study period (P): Study Day (SD) 10 (reference day is SD 1 or Randomization day), 20, 30, and 40 (+/-1) for P 1, 2, 3, and 4, respectively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Maximum Observed Concentration (Cmax) and Minimum Observed Concentration (Cmin) of FP - Blood samples of participants with asthma and COPD were collected and analyzed for Cmax and Cmin of FP in the blood. Cmax and Cmin are used to estimate the time at which the activity of the drug will be at its maximum and minimum, respectively.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At pre-morning dose; 5, 10, 30 minutes post-dose (PD); and 1, 2, 4, 8, 10, and 12 hours PD on Day 10 of each study period (P): Study Day (SD) 10 (reference day is SD 1 or Randomization day), 20, 30, and 40 (+/-1) for P 1, 2, 3, and 4, respectively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Terminal Phase Half-life (t1/2) for FP - Blood samples of participants were collected for evaluating t1/2. The t1/2 is the time required for the plasma/blood concentration of the drug to decrease by 50% after the false equilibrium of distribution has been reached.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At pre-morning dose; 5, 10, 30 minutes post-dose (PD); and 1, 2, 4, 8, 10, and 12 hours PD on Day 10 of each study period (P): Study Day (SD) 10 (reference day is SD 1 or Randomization day), 20, 30, and 40 (+/-1) for P 1, 2, 3, and 4, respectively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time of Occurrence of Cmax (Tmax) for FP - Blood samples of participants were collected for evaluating Tmax. Tmax is a measure of the time required to reach the maximum concentration of the drug.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At pre-morning dose; 5, 10, 30 minutes post-dose (PD); and 1, 2, 4, 8, 10, and 12 hours PD on Day 10 of each study period (P): Study Day (SD) 10 (reference day is SD 1 or Randomization day), 20, 30, and 40 (+/-1) for P 1, 2, 3, and 4, respectively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Maximum Observed Concentration (Cmax) and Minimum Observed Concentration (Cmin) for Salmeterol - Blood samples of participants with asthma and COPD were collected and analyzed for Cmax and Cmin of Salmeterol in the blood. Cmax and Cmin are used to estimate the time at which the activity of the drug will be at its maximum and minimum.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At pre-morning dose; 5, 10, 30 minutes post-dose (PD); and 1, 2, 4, 8, 10, and 12 hours PD on Day 10 of each study period (P): Study Day (SD) 10 (reference day is SD 1 or Randomization day), 20, 30, and 40 (+/-1) for P 1, 2, 3, and 4, respectively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Terminal Phase Half-life (t1/2) for Salmeterol - Blood samples of participants were collected for evaluating t1/2. t1/2 is the time required for the plasma/blood concentration of the drug to decrease by 50% after the false equilibrium of distribution has been reached.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At pre-morning dose; 5, 10, 30 minutes post-dose (PD); and 1, 2, 4, 8, 10, and 12 hours PD on Day 10 of each study period (P): Study Day (SD) 10 (reference day is SD 1 or Randomization day), 20, 30, and 40 (+/-1) for P 1, 2, 3, and 4, respectively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tmax for Salmeterol - Blood samples of participants were collected for evaluating Tmax. Tmax is a measure of the time required to reach the maximum concentration of the drug.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At pre-morning dose; 5, 10, 30 minutes post-dose (PD); and 1, 2, 4, 8, 10, and 12 hours PD on Day 10 of each study period (P): Study Day (SD) 10 (reference day is SD 1 or Randomization day), 20, 30, and 40 (+/-1) for P 1, 2, 3, and 4, respectively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Urine Cortisol Excretion Over 0 to 24 Hours Post Dose for FP - Urine samples of participants were collected to evaluate urine cortisol excretion over 0-24 hours post treatment dose. A 24-hour urine cortisol sample was used to measure the total amount of cortisol excreted in urine in 24 hours. Any differences in systemic exposure as a result of the absorbed steroid component of the two differing inhaled devices should also result in differences in the amount of cortisol excreted in the urine.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0-24 hours post dose on Day 10 of each study period (P): Study Day (SD) 10 (reference day is SD 1 or Randomization day), 20, 30, and 40 (+/-1) for P 1, 2, 3, and 4, respectively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum Cortisol Minimum (Cmin) for FP - Blood samples of participants were collected for the evaluation of minimum serum cortisol. Any differences in systemic exposure as a result of the absorbed steroid component of the two differing inhaled devices should also result in differences in serum cortisol concentrations.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 10 of each study period (Periods 1-4); Study Day 10 (+/-1) (reference day is Study Day 1 or Randomization day), Period 1; Study Day 20 (+/-1), Period 2; Study Day 30 (+/-1), Period 3; Study Day 40 (+/-1), Period 4</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weighted Mean Over 0 to 4 Hours Post Dose of Heart Rate for Salmeterol - The heart rate (number of heartbeats per unit of time, typically expressed as beats per minute [bpm]) of the participants was monitored for evaluating the weighted mean over the course of 0 to 4 hours post dose. The Capsule-MDPI difference for heart rate was calculated for each participant, and the weighted mean value from the time of the morning dose on Day 10 to 4 hours post dose was calculated. The weighted mean was calculated by using all values at the indicated timepoint contributing to the calculation of the mean but with different weightage.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At pre-morning dose; 15, 30, 60, 90 minutes post-dose (PD); and 2, 4, 8, 10, and 12 hours PD on Day 10 of each study period (P): Study Day (SD) 10 (reference day is SD 1 or Randomization day), 20, 30, and 40 (+/-1) for P 1, 2, 3, and 4, respectively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean of Maximum Heart Rate Over 0 to 4 Hours Post Dose for Salmeterol - The maximum observed value of heart rate was measured from the time of the morning dose on Day 10 to 4 hours post dose.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At pre-morning dose; 15, 30, 60, 90 minutes post-dose (PD); and 2, 4, 8, 10, and 12 hours PD on Day 10 of each study period (P): Study Day (SD) 10 (reference day is SD 1 or Randomization day), 20, 30, and 40 (+/-1) for P 1, 2, 3, and 4, respectively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Minimum Diastolic Blood Pressure (DBP), Maximum Systolic Blood Pressure (SBP), and Weighted Mean for DBP and SBP Over 0 to 4 Hours Post Dose - The diastolic and systolic blood pressure of the participants was measured. The maximum and minimum observed values from the time of the morning dose on Day 10 to 4 hours post dose were measured for SBP and DBP. The weighted mean value from the time of the morning dose on Day 10 to 4 hours post dose was calculated. Weighted mean was calculated by using all values of DBP and SBP at the indicated timepoint contributing to the calculation of the mean but with different weightage.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At pre-morning dose; 15, 30, 60, 90 minutes post-dose (PD); and 2, 4, 8, 10, and 12 hours PD on Day 10 of each study period (P): Study Day (SD) 10 (reference day is SD 1 or Randomization day), 20, 30, and 40 (+/-1) for P 1, 2, 3, and 4, respectively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximum and Weighted Mean Over 0 to 4 Hours Post Dose of the QT Interval Corrected According to Bazett's Formula (QTc[B]) and the QT Interval Corrected According to Fridericia's Formula (QTc[F]) - The electrocardiogram (ECG) of the participants was taken, and the maximum and weighted mean of QTc(B) and QTc(F) was measured. Weighted mean was calculated by using all values of QTc(B) and QTc(F) at the indicated timepoint contributing to the calculation of the mean but with different weightage. The ECG helps in the assessment of the condition of the heart. The QT interval gives the measure of the heart rate, and the cQT interval gives the corrected value.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At pre-morning dose; 15, 30, 60, 90 minutes post-dose (PD); and 2, 3 and 4 hours PD on Day 10 of each study period (P): Study Day (SD) 10 (reference day is SD 1 or Randomization day), 20, 30, and 40 (+/-1) for P 1, 2, 3, and 4, respectively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weighted Mean Over 0 to 4 Hours Post Dose of Plasma Potassium and Minimum (Min) Plasma Potassium - Blood samples of participants were collected for the evaluation of weighted mean over 0 to 4 hours post dose and the minimum plasma potassium level. Weighted mean was calculated by using all values of plasma potassium at the indicated timepoint contributing to the calculation of the mean but with different weightage.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At pre-morning dose; 30, 60 minutes post-dose (PD); and 2 and 4 hours PD on Day 10 of each study period (P): Study Day (SD) 10 (reference day is SD 1 or Randomization day), 20, 30, and 40 (+/-1) for P 1, 2, 3, and 4, respectively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weighted Mean Over 0 to 4 Hours Post Dose and Maximum Plasma Glucose - Blood samples of participants were collected for the evaluation of weighted mean over 0 to 4 hours post dose and the maximum plasma glucose level. Weighted mean was calculated by using all values of plasma glucose at the indicated timepoint contributing to the calculation of the mean but with different weightage.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At pre-morning dose; 30, 60 minutes post-dose (PD); and 2 and 4 hours PD on Day 10 of each study period (P): Study Day (SD) 10 (reference day is SD 1 or Randomization day), 20, 30, and 40 (+/-1) for P 1, 2, 3, and 4, respectively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Basophils, Eosinophils, Lymphocytes, Monocytes, Total Neutrophils, Platelet Count, and White Blood Cell (WBC) Count - Blood samples of participants were collected for the evaluation of basophils, eosinophils, lymphocytes, monocytes, total neutrophils, platelet count, and WBC count. Data are reported for the first (1st) and second (2nd) administration (admin) of FP/salmeterol via MDPI or capsule-based inhaler. The timing of the first and second administrations depended on the randomization schedule. If the treatment sequence received was "ABBA," then Days 10 and 40, respectively, correspond to the first and second administrations for treatment A.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 10 of each study period (P): Study Day (SD) 10 (reference day is SD 1 or Randomization day), 20, 30, and 40 (+/-1) for P 1, 2, 3, and 4, respectively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Hemoglobin and Mean Corpuscular Hemoglobin (MCH) Concentration - Blood samples of participants were collected for the evaluation of mean hemoglobin (mean level of hemoglobin in the whole blood sample) and MCH concentration. The MCH concentration is the average concentration of hemoglobin in a red blood cell. Hemoglobin is the red pigment in the blood, and it is reponsible for carrying oxygen. The timing of the first and second administrations depended on the randomization schedule. If the treatment sequence received was "ABBA," then Days 10 and 40, respectively, correspond to the first and second administrations for treatment A.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 10 of each study period (P): Study Day (SD) 10 (reference day is SD 1 or Randomization day), 20, 30, and 40 (+/-1) for P 1, 2, 3, and 4, respectively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Red Blood Cell (RBC) Count and Reticulocytes - Blood samples of participants were collected for the evaluation of RBC and reticulocytes count. Reticulocytes are immature red blood cells. Normally, about 1% to 2% of the red blood cells in the blood are reticulocytes. The timing of the first and second administrations depended on the randomization schedule. If the treatment sequence received was "ABBA," then Days 10 and 40, respectively, correspond to the first and second administrations for treatment A.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 10 of each study period (P): Study Day (SD) 10 (reference day is SD 1 or Randomization day), 20, 30, and 40 (+/-1) for P 1, 2, 3, and 4, respectively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Corpuscule Hemoglobin (MCH) - Blood samples of participants were collected for the evaluation of MCH. MCH is the average mass or amount of hemoglobin per red blood cell in a sample of blood. The timing of the first and second administrations depended on the randomization schedule. If the treatment sequence received was "ABBA," then Days 10 and 40, respectively, correspond to the first and second administrations for treatment A.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 10 of each study period (P): Study Day (SD) 10 (reference day is SD 1 or Randomization day), 20, 30, and 40 (+/-1) for P 1, 2, 3, and 4, respectively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Corpuscle Volume (MCV) - Blood samples of participants were collected for the evaluation of MCV. MCV is a measure of the average red blood cell size that is reported as part of a standard complete blood count. The timing of the first and second administrations depended on the randomization schedule. If the treatment sequence received was "ABBA," then Days 10 and 40, respectively, correspond to the first and second administrations for treatment A.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 10 of each study period (P): Study Day (SD) 10 (reference day is SD 1 or Randomization day), 20, 30, and 40 (+/-1) for P 1, 2, 3, and 4, respectively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Hematocrit - Blood samples of participants were collected for the evaluation of hematocrit. The hematocrit is the percentage of the RBCs in the blood. The timing of the first and second administrations depended on the randomization schedule. If the treatment sequence received was "ABBA," then Days 10 and 40, respectively, correspond to the first and second administrations for treatment A.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 10 of each study period (P): Study Day (SD) 10 (reference day is SD 1 or Randomization day), 20, 30, and 40 (+/-1) for P 1, 2, 3, and 4, respectively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Albumin and Total Protein - The timing of the first and second administrations depended on the randomization schedule. If the treatment sequence received was "ABBA," then Days 10 and 40, respectively, correspond to the first and second administrations for treatment A.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 10 of each study period (P): Study Day (SD) 10 (reference day is SD 1 or Randomization day), 20, 30, and 40 (+/-1) for P 1, 2, 3, and 4, respectively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Alkaline Phosphatase (AP), Alanine Amino Transferase (ALT), Aspartate Amio Transferase (AST), and Gama Glutamyl Transferase (GGT) - Blood samples of participants were collected for the evaluation of AP, ALT, AST, and GGT. All of these parameters are measured to help assess the condition of the liver. The timing of the first and second administrations depended on the randomization schedule. If the treatment sequence received was "ABBA," then Days 10 and 40, respectively, correspond to the first and second administrations for treatment A.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 10 of each study period (P): Study Day (SD) 10 (reference day is SD 1 or Randomization day), 20, 30, and 40 (+/-1) for P 1, 2, 3, and 4, respectively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Direct Bilirubin (DB), Total Bilirubin (TB), Creatinine, and Uric Acid - Blood samples of participants were collected for the evaluation of DP, TB, creatinine, and uric acid. DB and TB are measures that help assess the condition of the liver, and creatinine and uric acid are measures that help assess the condition of the kidneys. The timing of the first and second administrations depended on the randomization schedule. If the treatment sequence received was "ABBA," then Days 10 and 40, respectively, correspond to the first and second administrations for treatment A.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 10 of each study period (P): Study Day (SD) 10 (reference day is SD 1 or Randomization day), 20, 30, and 40 (+/-1) for P 1, 2, 3, and 4, respectively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Calcium, Chloride, Glucose, Potassium, Sodium, Carbon Dioxide (CO2) Content/Bicarbonate (Bicar), and Urea/Blood Urea Nitrogen (BUN) - Blood samples of participants were collected for the evaluation of calcium, chloride, glucose, potassium, sodium, carbon dioxide (CO2) content/bicarbonate, and urea/BUN. All of these parameters are measured to help assess the condition of the kidneys. The timing of the first and second administrations depended on the randomization schedule. If the treatment sequence received was "ABBA," then Days 10 and 40, respectively, correspond to the first and second administrations for treatment A.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 10 of each study period (P): Study Day (SD) 10 (reference day is SD 1 or Randomization day), 20, 30, and 40 (+/-1) for P 1, 2, 3, and 4, respectively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Participants With an Adverse Event (AE) - An AE is defined as any untoward medical occurrence in a patient or clinical investigation participant, temporally associated with the use of a medicinal product, whether or not considered related to the medicinal product.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Randomization (Day 1) up to Follow-up (Days 47-50)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        ALL PATIENTS:

          -  Available for the duration of the study and able to attend the clinic for all study
             visits.

          -  Gender: male or female

        A female subject is eligible to participate if she is of:

          -  Non-childbearing potential defined as pre-menopausal females with a documented tubal
             ligation or hysterectomy; or postmenopausal defined as 12 months of spontaneous
             amenorrhea [in questionable cases a blood sample with simultaneous follicle
             stimulating hormone (FSH) &gt; 40 MlU/ml and estradiol &lt; 40 pg/ml (&lt;140 pmol/L) is
             confirmatory]. Females on hormone replacement therapy (HRT) and whose menopausal
             status is in doubt will be required to use one of the protocol allowed contraception
             methods if they wish to continue their HRT during the study. Otherwise, they must
             discontinue HRT to allow confirmation of post-menopausal status prior to study
             enrollment. For most forms of HRT, at least 2-4 weeks will elapse between the
             cessation of therapy and the blood draw; this interval depends on the type and dosage
             of HRT. Following confirmation of their post-menopausal status, they can resume use of
             HRT during the study without use of a contraceptive method.

          -  Child-bearing potential and agrees to use one of the protocol allowed contraception
             methods for an appropriate period of time (as determined by the product label or
             investigator) prior to the start of dosing to sufficiently minimize the risk of
             pregnancy at that point. Female subjects must agree to use contraception until they
             have attended the site for the follow-up visit.

          -  Capable of giving informed consent, which includes compliance with the study
             requirements and restrictions listed in the consent form.

          -  Body mass index between 18 and 35 kg/m2 inclusive at Screening

          -  Able to use the inhaler devices adequately after training

          -  AST and ALT &lt; 2xULN (upper limit of normal); alkaline phosphatase and bilirubin less
             than or equal to 1.5xULN (isolated bilirubin &gt;1.5xULN is acceptable if bilirubin is
             fractionated and direct bilirubin &lt;35%).

          -  QT interval corrected for heart rate (QTc)* &lt;450 millisecond (msec)** QTc &lt;480 msec
             for patients with bundle branch block

               -  either QTcB (QTc Bazzett's formula) or QTcF (QTc Fridericia's formula), machine
                  or manual overread, males or females. The specific formula that will be used in a
                  study should be predetermined prior to the initiation of the study. The QT
                  correction formula used to determine inclusion and discontinuation should be the
                  same throughout the study.

                    -  based on single or averaged QTc values of triplicate ECGs obtained over a
                       brief recording period

        COPD PATIENTS:

          -  Diagnosis: COPD patients, defined as either Stage III to Stage IV COPD diagnosis
             according to GOLD criteria (Global Strategy for the Diagnosis, Management, and
             Prevention of COPD, updated 2009) [GOLD, 2009]. Individuals must be otherwise healthy
             individuals who are free from significant cardiac, gastrointestinal, hepatic, renal,
             haematological malignancy, endocrine, neurological and psychiatric disease as
             determined by history, physical examination and screening investigations.

          -  Age: 40-80 years inclusive at the time of signing the informed consent.

          -  Post-bronchodilator forced expiratory volume in one second (FEV1) &lt; 50% of predicted
             normal values at Screening. Patients must abstain from short acting beta agonist
             (SABA) use for 6 hours prior to the screening visit.

          -  Post-bronchodilator FEV1/FVC ratio = 0.70 at Screening

          -  An increase of less than 15% from baseline FEV1 or an absolute change of &lt; 200ml, 30
             minutes after inhalation of 400mcg of salbutamol by metered-dose inhaler (MDI) and
             spacer or 2.5mg by nebuliser at Screening.

          -  Ex smokers for at least the past 3 months with a pack history =10 pack years [number
             of pack years = (number of cigarettes per day / 20) x number of years smoked].

          -  COPD therapy:

          -  Patients on fluticasone propionate/salmeterol combination 250/50mcg bid via a
             multi-dose dry powder inhaler prior to the study will be allowed to remain on their
             treatment regimen until randomization provided all other eligibility criteria are met.

          -  Patients on fluticasone propionate/salmeterol combination 250/50mcg bid via a metered
             dose inhaler or the equivalent dose of budesonide/formoterol, 800/24mcg (total daily
             dose) via a turbuhaler will be switched to fluticasone propionate/salmeterol
             combination 250/50mcg bid via the GSK provided multi-dose dry powder inhaler for
             between 14 and 28 days prior to randomization.

          -  Patients on tiotropium in addition to ICS/LABA (long-acting beta agonist) treatment
             (up to a total daily dose of 500mcg fluticasone propionate or other ICS equivalent eg.
             800mcg budesonide) may continue their tiotropium treatment throughout the study.

          -  Patients on tiotropium monotherapy will need to start treatment with fluticasone
             propionate/salmeterol combination 250/50mcg bid via the GSK provided multi-dose dry
             powder inhaler for between 14 and 28 days prior to randomization. They may continue
             their tiotropium treatment throughout the study.

          -  Patients on LABA therapy (eg. salmeterol 50mcg) will need to start treatment with
             fluticasone propionate/salmeterol combination 250/50mcg bid via the GSK provided
             multi-dose dry powder inhaler for between 14 and 28 days prior to randomization.

        ASTHMA PATIENTS:

          -  Diagnosis: Patients with moderate asthma as defined by the Global Initiative for
             Asthma (GINA) guidelines at Screening. A best FEV1 of 60-85% of the predicted normal
             value at the Screening visit. NHANES (National Health and Nutrition Examination
             Survey) III predicted values will be used [Hankinson, 2009]. If a subject is recorded
             as having Hispanic or Latino ethnicity, then the Mexican-American equations will be
             used (irrespective of race). If a subject is recorded as being of African
             American/African Heritage race, then the African American equations will be used. If a
             subject is recorded as being of Asian or of Pacific Islander race, then the Caucasian
             formula will be used with a conversion factor of 0.88. Otherwise, the Caucasian
             equations will be used.

          -  Age: 18 and above at the time of signing the informed consent.

          -  Best clinic screening pre-bronchodilator FEV1 between 60 and 85% of predicted normal
             values (NHANES III values). Patients must abstain from SABA use for 6 hours prior to
             the Screening visit.

          -  Asthma therapy:

          -  Patients on fluticasone propionate/salmeterol combination 250/50mcg treatment via a
             multi-dose dry powder inhaler prior to the study will be allowed to remain on their
             treatment regimen until randomization provided all other eligibility criteria are met.

          -  Patients on treatment with ICS alone (up to a total daily dose of 500mcg fluticasone
             propionate or other ICS equivalent eg. 800mcg budesonide) will be required to switch
             treatment to fluticasone propionate/salmeterol combination 250/50mcg bid via the GSK
             provided multi-dose powder inhaler for between 14 and 28 days prior to randomization
             if deemed appropriate.

          -  Patients on treatment with budesonide/eformoterol combination (up to a total daily
             dose of 800/24mcg via a Turbuhaler) will be required to switch to fluticasone
             propionate/salmeterol combination 250/50mcg bid via the GSK-provided multi-dose powder
             inhaler for between 14 and 28 days prior to randomization.

          -  Patients on treatment with fluticasone propionate/salmeterol combination at a dose up
             to 250/50mcg bid via a metered dose inhaler or multi-dose dry powder inhaler (eg.
             100/50mcg) will be required to switch to fluticasone propionate/salmeterol combination
             250/50mcg bid via the GSK-provided multi-dose powder inhaler for between 14 and 28
             days prior to randomization.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        ALL PATIENTS:

          -  Any clinically relevant medical condition or abnormality identified during the
             screening medical assessment and procedures, physical examination, or laboratory
             assessments (including clinical chemistry and haematology), which in the opinion of
             the GSK Medical Monitor is likely to affect the safety of the subject and/or interfere
             with the study procedures and outcomes.

          -  Current or chronic history of liver disease, or known hepatic or biliary abnormalities
             (with the exception of Gilbert's syndrome or asymptomatic gallstones).

          -  A positive pre-study Hepatitis B surface antigen or positive Hepatitis C antibody or
             positive HIV test result within 3 months of screening.

          -  Patients on treatment with fluticasone propionate either as monotherapy or in
             combination at a total daily dose higher than 500mcg or budesonide monotherapy or in
             combination at a total daily dose higher than 800mcg are excluded from the study

          -  Use of oral/injectable/depot corticosteroid for any indication within 3 months prior
             to the Screening visit.

          -  Use of intra-nasal steroids (INS). To be eligible for the study, patients on INS
             therapy will be required to switch to non-INS therapy at randomization.

          -  Patients with abnormal levels of serum cortisol at Screening

          -  Abuse of alcohol consumption within 12 months of the Screening visit defined by the
             following Australian guidelines:

        Males: An average weekly intake greater than 21 units or an average daily intake greater
        than 3 units. Females: An average weekly intake greater than 14 units or an average daily
        intake greater than 2 units.

        One unit is equivalent to 270 mL of full strength beer, 470 mL of light beer, 30 mL of
        spirits and 100 mL of wine.

          -  A known or suspected history of drug abuse within 12 months of the Screening visit.

          -  The subject has participated in a clinical trial and has received an investigational
             product within the following time period prior to the first dosing day in the current
             study: 30 days, 5 half-lives or twice the duration of the biological effect of the
             investigational product (whichever is longer).

          -  Exposure to more than four new chemical entities within 12 months prior to the first
             dosing day.

          -  Where participation in the study would result in donation of blood or blood products
             in excess of 500mL within a 56-day period.

          -  Known hypersensitivity to salbutamol or any ingredient in the study medication
             preparation and/or history of any other drug or other allergy that, in the opinion of
             the GSK medical monitor and the investigator contraindicates participation of the
             subject

          -  Grapefruit or grapefruit juice containing products are excluded from 2 weeks prior to
             randomisation until collection of the final blood sample at treatment period 4.

          -  Drugs that inhibit the cytochrome P450 isoform, 3A4 (CYP3A4), are excluded from 2
             weeks prior to randomisation until collection of the final blood sample at treatment
             period 4. CYP3A4 inhibitors include cimetidine, clarithromycin, erythromycin,
             ciprofloxacin, ritonavir, ketoconazole, and azole antifungals, a complete list is
             provided in the protocol.

          -  Use of prescription or non-prescription drugs, vitamins, herbal and dietary
             supplements, within seven days or 5 half-lives (whichever is longer) prior to the
             first dose of study medication, which in the opinion of the Principal Investigator,
             may interfere with study outcome. Specifically, calcium and vitamin D supplements and
             bisphosphonates are not allowed throughout the study.

          -  Pregnant females as determined by positive serum or urine ßhCG (ß-human chorionic
             gonadotropin) test at Screening or prior to dosing.

          -  Patients, who, in the opinion of the Investigator, are not able to comply with the
             protocol requirements.

        COPD PATIENTS:

          -  Subjects with a respiratory disorder in addition to COPD (e.g. bronchiectasis,
             fibrosis) or significant co-morbidity that might affect lung function (e.g. poorly
             controlled heart failure, atrial fibrillation or ischaemic heart disease).

          -  Regular oxygen or nebulised bronchodilator therapy

          -  The subject has history of a respiratory infection (including sinusitis) within 4
             weeks prior to the Screening visit

          -  Any previous lung resection surgery (eg., lung volume reduction surgery or lobectomy)

        ASTHMA PATIENTS:

          -  Acute exacerbation of asthma requiring hospitalisation in the 6 weeks prior to the
             Screening visit.

          -  Subjects may not have used inhaled tobacco products within the past 3 months (ie.
             cigarettes, cigars or pipe tobacco) or have historical use of 10 pack years or more;
             [number of pack years = (number of cigarettes per day / 20) x number of years smoked].</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria />
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2>The people administering the treatment/s</masking2>
    <masking3 />
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>25/10/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>60</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>8/06/2011</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>GSK Investigational Site - Randwick</hospital>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Wellington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>GlaxoSmithKline</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a comparative bioavailability study to compare the pharmacokinetics and
      pharmacodynamic effects of Fluticasone propionate and Salmeterol delivered in a capsule-based
      inhaler versus a multi-dose dry powder inhaler in patients with moderate asthma and in
      patients with moderate to severe Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD).

      Co-primary endpoints will be the area under the curve (AUCt) measured for plasma Fluticasone
      propionate (pharmacokinetic) and the pharmacodynamic effects of Fluticasone propionate
      (weighted mean serum cortisol over 0-12h) on the last day of each 10 day study treatment
      period. Secondary endpoints will include the following pharmacokinetic parameters for both
      fluticasone propionate and salmeterol: AUClast, AUC(0-t), Cmax, Cmin, tmax, ?z, and t1/2 as
      well as the pharmacodynamic effects of salmeterol (pulse rate, blood pressure,
      electrocardiogram [ECG], potassium and glucose) and Fluticasone propionate (urine cortisol
      levels). Safety (adverse events and laboratory abnormalities) will also be assessed as a
      secondary endpoint.

      The study is a randomised, double blind, double dummy, four-period cross-over study.
      Approximately 60 asthma or COPD patients will be randomised. Patients meeting eligibility
      criteria will receive Fluticasone propionate/salmeterol 250/50mcg bid, from a capsule-based
      inhaler and from a multi-dose dry powder inhaler for a period of 10 days each in a randomised
      order. All patients will receive treatment from each device twice. To maintain the double
      blind, each patient will receive active treatment and placebo at the same time from two
      separate devices.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01494610</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Former Glaxo Wellcome study RPS10001/SFCF1001: A Phase I, monocentric, randomised, double-blind, double dummy, cross-over study to compare the pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamic effects of Seretide 50µg/250µg bid after repeat dosing, delivered by GSK's multi-dose dry powder inhaler versus RPID in patients with moderate asthma; [GW Document number PM1998/00015/00].
GINA: Global strategy for asthma management and prevention. NHLBI/WHO/GARD, Washingon DC 2006-updated 2009.
GlaxoSmithKline Document Number RM2002/00280/01. CCI18781 Investigator's Brochure, dated 22 Aug 2006
GlaxoSmithKline Document Number RM2007/00413/01. CCI18781+GR33343 Investigator's Brochure, version number 10, dated 26 Mar 2009.
GlaxoSmithKline study SAS10006: A 12-week, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, 3-way crossover study in adult subjects with asthma aged 18-55 years to examine the pharmacodynamics and pharmacokinetics of Fluticasone propionate (FP) administered twice daily via the GSK'S MULTI-DOSE DRY POWDER INHALER® (FP 100mcg) and the FP/Salmeterol (SALM) combination product (FP 100mcg/SALM 50mcg) administered twice daily via the GSK'S MULTI-DOSE DRY POWDER INHALER; [GSK Document number RM2002/00219/00].
Fabbri L, Pauwels RA, Hurd SS; GOLD Scientific Committee. Global Strategy for the Diagnosis, Management, and Prevention of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease: GOLD Executive Summary updated 2003. COPD. 2004 Apr;1(1):105-41; discussion 103-4.
Patterson S, Jones B. 2006. Bioequivalence and statistics in clinical pharmacology. Chapman &amp; Hall/CRC.
Potvin D, DiLiberti CE, Hauck WW, Parr AF, Schuirmann DJ, Smith RA. Sequential design approaches for bioequivalence studies with crossover designs. Pharm Stat. 2008 Oct-Dec;7(4):245-62.
Schuirmann DJ. A comparison of the two one-sided tests procedure and the power approach for assessing the equivalence of average bioavailability. J Pharmacokinet Biopharm. 1987 Dec;15(6):657-80.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>GSK Clinical Trials</name>
      <address>GlaxoSmithKline</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>