<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6488">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/05/2017</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT03159416</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Study of Inclisiran in Participants With Renal Impairment Compared to Participants With Normal Renal Function (ORION-7)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Single-Dose, Open-Label, Parallel-Group Study to Assess the Pharmacokinetics of Inclisiran in Subjects With Renal Impairment Compared to Subjects With Normal Renal Function (ORION-7)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>MDCO-PCS-16-03</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Renal Impairment</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Inclisiran

Experimental: Inclisiran (normal renal function) - Participants will receive a single dose of 300 milligram (mg) inclisiran administered by SC injection on Day 1. Normal renal function is defined as estimated creatinine clearance (CrCl) of =90 milliliter (mL)/minute (min).

Experimental: Inclisiran (mild renal impairment) - Participants will receive a single dose of 300 mg inclisiran administered by SC injection on Day 1. Mild renal impairment is defined as CrCl ranging from 60 to 89 mL/min.

Experimental: Inclisiran (moderate renal impairment) - Participants will receive a single dose of 300 mg inclisiran administered by SC injection on Day 1. Moderate renal impairment is defined as CrCl ranging from 30 to 59 mL/min.

Experimental: Inclisiran (severe renal impairment) - Participants will receive a single dose of 300 mg inclisiran administered by SC injection on Day 1. Severe renal impairment is defined as CrCl ranging from 15 to 29 mL/min.


Treatment: drugs: Inclisiran
Inclisiran is a synthetic, chemically modified small interfering ribonucleic acid (siRNA) targeting proprotein convertase subtilisin kexin type 9 (PCSK9) messenger ribonucleic acid (mRNA) with a covalently attached triantennary N-acetylgalactosamine (GalNAc) ligand.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetics: Maximum Observed Plasma Concentration (Cmax) Of Inclisiran - Measurement of effect of renal impairment on PK of inclisiran by assessment of Cmax. Serial blood samples will be collected for the analysis. PK parameters will be determined from the plasma concentration-time profiles using a noncompartmental approach.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 (pre-dose), 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 12, 24, and 48 hours post-dose and Day 4, Day 7, Day 14, and Day 30 post-dose</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetics: Tmax And t1/2 Of Inclisiran - Measurement of effect of renal impairment on PK of inclisiran by assessment of time to reach maximum plasma concentration (Tmax) and time for inclisiran to reach half of its initial value (t1/2). Serial blood samples will be collected for the analysis. PK parameters will be determined from the plasma concentration-time profiles using a noncompartmental approach.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 (pre-dose), 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 12, 24, and 48 hours post-dose and Day 4, Day 7, Day 14, and Day 30 post dose</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetics: AUC0-24, AUC0-48, And AUC0-inf Of Inclisiran - Measurement of effect of renal impairment on PK of inclisiran by assessment of area under the curve of the plasma concentration (AUC) from time 0 to 24 hours (AUC0-24), from time 0 to 48 hours (AUC0-48), and from time 0 extrapolated to infinity (AUC0-inf). Serial blood samples will be collected for the analysis. PK parameters will be determined from the plasma concentration-time profiles using a noncompartmental approach.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 (pre-dose), 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 12, 24, and 48 hours post-dose and Day 4, Day 7, Day 14, and Day 30 post dose</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetics: Apparent Total Clearance (CL/F) Following SC Administration Of Inclisiran - Measurement of effect of renal impairment on PK of inclisiran by assessment of CL/F. Serial blood samples will be collected for the analysis. PK parameters will be determined from the plasma concentration-time profiles using a noncompartmental approach.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 (pre-dose), 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 12, 24, and 48 hours post-dose and Day 4, Day 7, Day 14, and Day 30 post dose</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetics: Vd/F During The Terminal Elimination Phase Following SC Administration Of Inclisiran - Measurement of effect of renal impairment on PK of inclisiran by assessment of apparent volume of distribution (Vd/F) of inclisiran during the terminal elimination phase. Serial blood samples will be collected for the analysis. PK parameters will be determined from the plasma concentration-time profiles using a noncompartmental approach.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 (pre-dose), 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 12, 24, and 48 hours post-dose and Day 4, Day 7, Day 14, and Day 30 post dose</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetics: Amount Excreted Unchanged In Urine (Ae) Of Inclisiran Over 48 Hours Post-Dose - Measurement of effect of renal impairment on PK of inclisiran by assessment of Ae of inclisiran. Pooled urine samples will be used for the analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 up to 6 hours, 6 up to 12 hours, 12 up to 24 hours, and 24 up to 48 hour post-dose intervals</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetics: Fraction Excreted (Fe) Of Inclisiran - Measurement of effect of renal impairment on PK of inclisiran by assessment of the urinary recovery rate over a specific collection interval (Fe), calculated as 100*Ae/Dose. Pooled urine samples will be used for the analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 up to 6 hours, 6 up to 12 hours, 12 up to 24 hours, and 24 up to 48 hour post-dose intervals</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetics: Renal Clearance (CLr) Of Inclisiran - Measurement of effect of renal impairment on PK of inclisiran by assessment of CLr, calculated as Ae/AUC0-48 plasma. CLr will be calculated if possible (for example, if the percent of unchanged drug excreted in urine exceeds 20%). Pooled urine samples will be used for the analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 up to 6 hours, 6 up to 12 hours, 12 up to 24 hours, and 24 up to 48 hour post-dose intervals</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline In Lipids And Lipoproteins At Day 60 - Pharmacodynamic effects of inclisiran on lipids and lipoproteins (total cholesterol, triglycerides, and high-density lipoprotein cholesterol, calculated and measured by beta-quant low-density lipoprotein cholesterol [LDL-C]) will be measured as a percentage of change from baseline. Lipids and lipoproteins will be measured at baseline, 4, 48, 96 (Day 4), and 168 (Day 7) hours, and Day 30 and Day 60.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Day 60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline In PCSK9 At Day 60 - Pharmacodynamic effects of inclisiran on PCSK9 will be measured as a percentage of change from baseline. PCSK9 protein levels will be measured at baseline, 4, 48, 96 (Day 4), and 168 (Day 7) hours, and Day 30 and Day 60.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Day 60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Male and female participants 18 to 80 years of age

          -  Participants should be qualified for inclusion based upon estimated CrCl ranges for
             normal renal function group and mild, moderate, and severe renal impairment groups</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Participants with acute renal disease and/or history of renal transplant

          -  Urinary incontinence without catheterization

          -  Participants requiring hemodialysis

          -  Participants with LDL-C &lt;60 mg/deciliter (dL) (or less than 1.55 millimoles/liter
             [mmol/L])

          -  Participants with Amyloid Kidney (if known by pathology)

          -  Participants with any significant hepatic, cardiac, or pulmonary disease or
             participants who are clinically nephritic

        The above information is not intended to contain all considerations relevant to a
        participant's potential participation in a clinical trial.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>22/06/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>24</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/09/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Christchurch</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Medicines Company</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is a Phase I, single-dose, open-label trial to evaluate the safety, tolerability,
      pharmacokinetics (PK), and pharmacodynamics of a single dose of inclisiran subcutaneous (SC)
      injection in participants with mild, moderate, and severe renal impairment compared to
      participants with normal renal function.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03159416</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Richard Robson, PhD</name>
      <address>Christchurch Clinical Studies Trust</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>