<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="1248">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/07/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/07/2006</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00359424</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Interventional Management of Stroke (IMS) III Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Interventional Management of Stroke Trial (IMS III): A Phase III Clinical Trial Examining Whether a Combined Intravenous (IV) and Intra-Arterial (IA) Approach to Recanalization is Superior to Standard IV Rt-PA (Activase®) Alone</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>IMSIII</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>U01NS052220</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>U01NS052220</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - IV rt-PA alone
Other interventions - endovascular therapy

Active Comparator: intravenous (IV) rt-PA alone - Group one will receive the standard dose of intravenous (IV) rt-PA alone given over an hour.

Experimental: Endovascular therapy - Group two will receive a lower dose or a standard dose of IV rt-PA and then undergo an angiogram test (cerebral angiography) right after the medicine is given to check for blood clots. If a clot is not seen then no more treatment will be given. If a clot is seen, the neurointerventionalist will then choose (based on the location and extent of the blood clot) a protocol approved endovascular treatment given directly in the brain artery that will be most effective in reopening the blocked artery.


Treatment: drugs: IV rt-PA alone
Intravenous (IV) recombinant tissue plasminogen activator (rt-PA) is the only approved acute stroke therapy; Group one will receive the standard dose of IV rt-PA given over an hour.

Other interventions: endovascular therapy
Group two will receive a lower dose or the standard dose of IV rt-PA and then undergo an angiogram test (cerebral angiography) right after the medicine is given to check for blood clots. If a clot is not seen then no more treatment will be given. If a clot is seen, the neurointerventionalist will then choose a protocol approved endovascular treatment given directly in the brain artery that will be most effective in reopening the blocked artery. Endovascular therapy can be implemented with or without interarterial rt-PA use.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Modified Rankin Scale (mRS) Score Dichotomized to 0-2 Versus Greater Than 2. - The modified Rankin Scale (mRS) runs from 0-6 running from perfect health without symptoms to death. 0 - No symptoms at all. 1 - No significant disability. Able to carry out all usual duties and activities. 2 - Slight disability. Unable to carry out all previous activities but able to look after own affairs without assistance. 3 - Moderate disability. Requires some help, but able to walk unassisted. 4 - Moderately severe disability. Unable to walk unassisted and unable to attend to own bodily needs without assistance. 5 - Severe disability. Bedridden, incontinent, and requires constant nursing care and attention. 6 - Dead. Persons with a Rankin of 0-2 are considered functionally independent.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 90 days post randomization</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Death Due to Any Cause</outcome>
      <timepoint>within 90 days post randomization</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptomatic Intracranial Hemorrhage - Symptomatic Intracranial Hemorrhage- Symptomatic ICH is defined as an intracranial hemorrhage temporally related to a decline in neurological status as well as new or worsening neurologic symptoms in the judgment of the clinical investigator and which may warrant medical intervention. These events are identified via Adverse Event CRF submitted by the site</outcome>
      <timepoint>within the first 30 hours post IV rt-PA</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of Parenchymal Type II (PH2) Hematomas - a dense intracerebral hematoma involving more than 30% of the infarcted area with substantial space-occupying effect or any hemorrhagic area outside the infarcted area, determined via central read of the submitted CT scans.</outcome>
      <timepoint>within 30 hours post IV rt-PA</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Asymptomatic Intracranial Hemorrhage - Asymptomatic intracranial hemorrhage is defined as an intracranial hemorrhage without evidence of decline in neurological status or new or worsening neurologic symptoms in the judgment of the clinical investigator. These events are identified via Adverse Event CRF submitted by the site.</outcome>
      <timepoint>within 30 hours post IV rt-PA</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>National Institutes of Health Stroke Scale Score (NIHSS) &gt;&gt; Dichotomized 0-1 Versus 2 or Greater. - The National Institutes of Health Stroke Scale (NIHSS), a serial measure of neurologic deficit, is a 42-point scale that &gt;&gt; quantifies neurologic deficits in 11 categories, with 0 indicating normal function without neurologic deficit and higher
&gt;&gt; scores indicating greater severity of deficit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 24 hours post randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>National Institutes of Health Stroke Scale Score (NIHSS) Dichotomized 0-1 Versus 2 or Greater. - The National Institutes of Health Stroke Scale (NIHSS), a serial measure of neurologic deficit, is a 42-point scale that quantifies neurologic deficits in 11 categories, with 0 indicating normal function without neurologic deficit and higher scores indicating greater severity of deficit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 90 days post randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Barthel Index (BI) Dichotomized 0-90 Versus 95-100 - The Barthel Index (BI)is an ordinal scale used to measure a subject's performance in activities of daily living (ADL) in ten variables- feeding, transfer (bed to chair), grooming, toilet use, bathing, mobility on a level surface, stair use, dressing, bowels and bladder. It is an assessment of independence in ADL and is scored in increments of 5 points. The lowest possible score on the index is 0 which implies total dependence on others for ADL and the highest total score is 100 which indicate full independent in ADL. A higher score is associated with a greater likelihood of being able to live at home with a degree of independence.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 90 days post randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Trail Making Test Part A Time - The Trail Making Test is a neuropsychological test of visual attention and task switching that is thought to be sensitive to the presence of cerebral dysfunction. It is a timed test consisting of two parts where the subject is asked to draw a "trail" made by connecting numbers in sequential order (part A) and then in part B the combination of numbers and letters. Scoring is calculated separately for Parts A and B but both scores are provided as the minutes and seconds it takes for the subject to complete each part. Normally, the entire test (A and B) can be completed in 5 to 10 minutes.</outcome>
      <timepoint>90 days post randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Trail Making Test Part B Time - The Trail Making Test is a neuropsychological test of visual attention and task switching that is thought to be sensitive to the presence of cerebral dysfunction. It is a timed test consisting of two parts where the subject is asked to draw a "trail" made by connecting numbers in sequential order (part A) and then in part B the combination of numbers and letters. Scoring is calculated separately for Parts A and B but both scores are provided as the minutes and seconds it takes for the subject to complete each part. Normally, the entire test (A and B) can be completed in 5 to 10 minutes.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 90 days post randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Modified Rankin Scale (mRS) Score Dichotomized to 0-2 Versus Greater Than 2 - The modified Rankin Scale (mRS) runs from 0-6 running from perfect health without symptoms to death. 0 - No symptoms at all. 1 - No significant disability. Able to carry out all usual duties and activities. 2 - Slight disability. Unable to carry out all previous activities but able to look after own affairs without assistance. 3 - Moderate disability. Requires some help, but able to walk unassisted. 4 - Moderately severe disability. Unable to walk unassisted and unable to attend to own bodily needs without assistance. 5 - Severe disability. Bedridden, incontinent, and requires constant nursing care and attention. 6 - Dead. Persons with a Rankin of 0-2 are considered functionally independent.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 180 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Modified Rankin Scale (mRS) Score Dichotomized to 0-2 Versus Greater Than 2 - The modified Rankin Scale (mRS) runs from 0-6 running from perfect health without symptoms to death. 0 - No symptoms at all. 1 - No significant disability. Able to carry out all usual duties and activities. 2 - Slight disability. Unable to carry out all previous activities but able to look after own affairs without assistance. 3 - Moderate disability. Requires some help, but able to walk unassisted. 4 - Moderately severe disability. Unable to walk unassisted and unable to attend to own bodily needs without assistance. 5 - Severe disability. Bedridden, incontinent, and requires constant nursing care and attention. 6 - Dead. Persons with a Rankin of 0-2 are considered functionally independent.</outcome>
      <timepoint>270 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Modified Rankin Scale (mRS) Score Dichotomized to 0-2 Versus Greater Than 2 - The modified Rankin Scale (mRS) runs from 0-6 running from perfect health without symptoms to death. 0 - No symptoms at all. 1 - No significant disability. Able to carry out all usual duties and activities. 2 - Slight disability. Unable to carry out all previous activities but able to look after own affairs without assistance. 3 - Moderate disability. Requires some help, but able to walk unassisted. 4 - Moderately severe disability. Unable to walk unassisted and unable to attend to own bodily needs without assistance. 5 - Severe disability. Bedridden, incontinent, and requires constant nursing care and attention. 6 - Dead. Persons with a Rankin of 0-2 are considered functionally independent.</outcome>
      <timepoint>360 days post randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion Criteria

          -  Age: 18 through 82 years (i.e., candidates must have had their 18th birthday, but not
             had their 83rd birthday)

          -  Initiation of intravenous rt-PA within 3 hours of onset of stroke symptoms. Time of
             onset is defined as the last time when the subject was witnessed to be at baseline
             (i.e., subjects who have stroke symptoms upon awakening will be considered to have
             their onset at beginning of sleep)

          -  An NIHSSS &gt;/= 10 at the time that intravenous rt-PA is begun or an NIHSSS &gt;7 and &lt;10
             with an occlusion seen in M1, ICA or basilar artery on CTA at institutions where
             baseline CTA imaging is standard of care for acute stroke patients.

          -  Investigator verification that the subject has received/ is receiving the correct IV
             rt-PA dose for the estimated weight prior to randomization</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>82</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion Criteria

          -  History of stroke in the past 3 months

          -  Previous intra-cranial hemorrhage, neoplasm, subarachnoid hemorrhage, or arteriovenous
             malformation

          -  Clinical presentation suggests a subarachnoid hemorrhage, even if initial CT scan is
             normal

          -  Hypertension at time of treatment; systolic BP &gt; 185 or diastolic &gt; 110 mm Hg) or
             aggressive measures to lower BP to below these limits are needed.

          -  Presumed septic embolus, or suspicion of bacterial endocarditis

          -  Presumed pericarditis, including pericarditis after acute MI

          -  Suspicion of aortic dissection

          -  Recent (within 30 days) surgery or biopsy of parenchymal organ

          -  Recent (within 30 days) trauma, with internal injuries or ulcerative wounds

          -  Recent (within 90 days) severe head trauma or head trauma with loss of consciousness

          -  Any active or recent (within 30 days) hemorrhage

          -  Pts with known hereditary or acquired hemorrhagic diathesis, coagulation factor
             deficiency or oral anticoagulant therapy require coagulation labs results prior to
             enrollment. Any subject with INR &gt; 1.7 or institutionally equivalent prothrombin time
             is excluded. Patients without history or suspicion of coagulopathy do not require INR
             or prothrombin time lab results to be available prior to enrollment.

          -  Females of childbearing potential who are known to be pregnant and/or lactating or who
             have positive pregnancy tests on admission

          -  Baseline lab values: glucose &lt; 50 mg/dl or &gt; 400 mg/dl, platelets &lt;100,000, or Hct &lt;25

          -  Requires hemodialysis or peritoneal dialysis, or has a contraindication to an
             angiogram for whatever reason

          -  Received heparin or a direct thrombin inhibitor (Angiomax, argatroban, Refludan,
             Pradaxa) within 48 hours must have a normal partial thromboplastin time (PTT) to be
             eligible

          -  History of an arterial puncture at a non-compressible site or a lumbar puncture in the
             previous 7 days

          -  History of seizure at onset of stroke

          -  History of a pre-existing neurological or psychiatric disease that would confound the
             neurological or functional evaluations, mRS score at baseline must be &lt; 2. This
             excludes patients who live in a nursing home or who are not fully independent for
             activities of daily living (toileting, dressing, eating, cooking and preparing meals,
             etc.)

          -  Other serious, advanced, or terminal illness

          -  Any other condition that the investigator feels would pose a significant hazard to the
             subject if Activase (Alteplase) therapy is initiated

          -  Current participation in another research drug treatment protocol

          -  Informed consent is not or cannot be obtained.

          -  High density lesion consistent with hemorrhage of any degree on baseline imaging

          -  Significant mass effect with midline shift on baseline imaging

          -  Large (&gt;1/3 of the middle cerebral artery) regions of clear hypodensity on the
             baseline CT scan. (ASPECTS of &lt; 4 can be used as a guideline) Sulcal effacement and/or
             loss of grey-white differentiation are not contraindications to tx

          -  CT evidence of intrapararenchymal tumor

          -  Baseline CTA without evidence of arterial occlusion</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/08/2006</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>656</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Terminated</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/04/2013</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital, Level 10 King George V Building, Missenden Rd - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>St. Vincent's Hospital, Clincial Trial Centre Level 5, 378 Victoria St., Darlinghurst - Sydney</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital, Dept. of Neurology, 4 East, Grattan St, Parkville - Victoria</hospital>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Center, Dept. of Neurology, 246 Clayton Rd, Clayton - Victoria</hospital>
    <postcode>NSW 2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>NSW 2010 - Sydney</postcode>
    <postcode>3050 - Victoria</postcode>
    <postcode>3168 - Victoria</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Alabama</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Arizona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Colorado</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Connecticut</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Illinois</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Iowa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Kentucky</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Maryland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Massachusetts</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Michigan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Mississippi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Missouri</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Oregon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Pennsylvania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>South Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Virginia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Wisconsin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Alberta</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>British Columbia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Quebec</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Cedex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Dresden</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Freiburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Greifswald</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Halle</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Hamburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Nieuwegein</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Badalona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state>Basel</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state>Lausanne</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Joseph Broderick</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Government body</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Medical University of South Carolina</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of Calgary</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to compare two different treatment approaches to recanalization
      started within 3 hours of symptom onsetcombined intravenous (IV) and endovascular therapy
      and standard intravenous (IV) rt-PA alone.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00359424</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Joseph P. Broderick, MD</name>
      <address>Primary Neurologist Investigator, University of Cincinnati Academic Health Center</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>