<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4105">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/04/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/04/2013</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01844986</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Olaparib Maintenance Monotherapy in Patients With BRCA Mutated Ovarian Cancer Following First Line Platinum Based Chemotherapy.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase III, Randomised, Double Blind, Placebo Controlled, Multicentre Study of Olaparib Maintenance Monotherapy in Patients With BRCA Mutated Advanced (FIGO Stage III-IV) Ovarian Cancer Following First Line Platinum Based Chemotherapy.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>SOLO-1</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>D0818C00001</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Newly Diagnosed</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Advanced Ovarian Cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>FIGO Stage III-IV</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>BRCA Mutation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Complete Response</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Partial Response</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>First Line Platinum Chemotherapy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ovarian and primary peritoneal</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Olaparib 300mg tablets

Experimental: Olaparib tablets p.o. 300mg twice daily - Olaparib/placebo tablets p.o 300mg twice daily for up to 3 years or until objective radiological disease progression as per RECIST as assessed by the Investigator. Patients with evidence of stable disease (or those who have progressed), may continue on treatment beyond 2 years, if in the patient's best interest. Dose reduction to 250mg and subsequently 200mg is permitted following confirmation of toxicity

Placebo Comparator: Placebo tablets p.o. twice daily - Olaparib/placebo tablets p.o 300mg twice daily for up to 3 years or until objective radiological disease progression as per RECIST as assessed by the Investigator. Patients with evidence of stable disease (or those who have progressed), may continue on treatment beyond 2 years, if in the patient's best interest. Dose reduction to 250mg and subsequently 200mg is permitted following confirmation of toxicity


Treatment: drugs: Olaparib 300mg tablets
Olaparib/placebo tablets p.o 300mg twice daily for up to 2 years or until objective radiological disease progression as per RECIST as assessed by the Investigator. Patients with evidence of stable disease (or those who have progressed), may continue on treatment beyond 2 years, if in the patient's best interest. Dose reduction to 250mg and subsequently 200mg is permitted following confirmation of toxicity.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression Free Survival (PFS) by review of investigator-reported RECIST data - To determine the efficacy by progression free survival (PFS) using investigator assessment of scans according to modified Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumours (RECIST 1.1) of olaparib maintenance monotherapy compared to placebo in BRCA mutated high risk advanced ovarian cancer patients who are in clinical complete response or partial response following first line platinum based chemotherapy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Radiologic scans performed at baseline then every ~12 weeks up to 3 years (156 weeks) and every ~24 weeks thereafter until objective radiological disease progression. Study data collection expected to last for ~10 years.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Efficacy in patients following First Line Platinum Based Chemotherapy by assessment of overall survival. - To determine the efficacy of olaparib maintenance monotherapy compared to placebo in BRCA mutated high risk advanced ovarian cancer patients who are in clinical complete response or partial response following first line platinum based chemotherapy by assessment of overall survival (OS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Survival assessed every 4 weeks until treatment discontinues or up to 3 years (whichever is earlier), then assessed every 12 weeks. Study data collection expected to last for ~10 years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in Health-Related Quality of Life (HRQoL) as assessed by the individual domains of the trial outcome index (TOI) of the Functional Assessment of Cancer therapy - Ovarian (FACT-O) - To compare the effects of olaparib maintenance monotherapy compared to placebo on Health-related Quality of Life (HRQoL) as assessed by the trial outcome index (TOI) of the Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy - Ovarian (FACT-O) in BRCA mutated high risk advanced ovarian cancer patients who are in clinical complete response or partial response following first line platinum based chemotherapy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Questionnaires completed by patient at baseline, Day 29, every 12 weeks until week 156 and then 24 weeks or until the data cut off for the primary analysis, whichever comes first. Study data collection expected to last for ~10 years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Efficacy in patients with a deleterious or suspected deleterious variant in either of the BRCA genes by assessment of progression free survival. - To assess efficacy of olaparib in patients identified as having a deleterious or suspected deleterious variant in either of the BRCA genes using variants identified with current and potential future BRCA mutation assays (gene sequencing and large rearrangement analysis).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Radiologic scans performed at baseline every ~12 weeks for up to 3 years and every ~24 weeks thereafter, until disease progression. Study data collection expected to last for ~10 years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and tolerability of olaparib by assessment of the number of AEs - To assess the safety and tolerability of olaparib maintenance monotherapy in BRCA mutated high risk advanced ovarian cancer patients who are in clinical complete response or partial response following first line platinum based chemotherapy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>AEs collected from informed consent until post treatment 30-day follow-up period. Study data collection expected to last ~10 years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Efficacy in patients following First Line Platinum Based Chemotherapy by assessment of time to earliest progression by RECIST or Cancer Antigen-125 (CA-125). - To determine the efficacy of olaparib maintenance monotherapy compared to placebo in BRCA mutated high risk advanced ovarian cancer patients who are in clinical complete response or partial response following first line platinum based chemotherapy by assessment of time to earliest progression by RECIST or Cancer Antigen-125 (CA-125) or death.</outcome>
      <timepoint>CA125 assessed every 4 weeks for up to 3 years, then every 12 weeks. Radiologic scans performed every ~12 weeks for up to 3 years, then every ~24 weeks until disease progression. Study data collection expected to last for ~10 years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Efficacy in patients following First Line Platinum Based Chemotherapy by assessment of time from randomisation to second progression. - To determine the efficacy of olaparib maintenance monotherapy compared to placebo in BRCA mutated high risk advanced ovarian cancer patients who are in clinical complete response or partial response following first line platinum based chemotherapy by assessment of time from randomisation up to study completion at the latest.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Radiologic scans performed at baseline then every~12 weeks for up to 3 years, then every~24 weeks until first progression. Then disease is assessed as per local clinical practice until 2nd progression. Study data collection expected to last for~10 years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and tolerability of olaparib by assessment and review of laboratory parameters. - To assess the safety and tolerability of olaparib maintenance monotherapy in BRCA mutated high risk advanced ovarian cancer patients who are in clinical complete response or partial response following first line platinum based chemotherapy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Laboratory parameter assessments collected until study treatment discontinued. Study data collection expected to last ~10 years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Efficacy of olaparib by time to first subsequent therapy or death (TFST). - To determine the efficacy of olaparib maintenance monotherapy compared to placebo in BRCA mutated high risk advanced ovarian cancer patients who are in clinical complete response or partial response following first line platinum based chemotherapy by assessment of time from randomisation to first subsequent therapy or death (TFST).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time elapsed from randomisation to first subsequent therapy or death. Assessed at time of primary PFS analysis and at final OS analysis. Study data collection expected to last ~10 years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Efficacy of olaparib by time to second subsequent therapy or death (TSST). - To determine the efficacy of olaparib maintenance monotherapy compared to placebo in BRCA mutated high risk advanced ovarian cancer patients who are in clinical complete response or partial response following first line platinum based chemotherapy by assessment of time from randomisation to second subsequent therapy or death (TSST).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time elapsed from randomisation to second subsequent therapy or death. Assessed at time of primary PFS analysis and at final OS analysis. Study data collection expected to last ~10 years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Efficacy of olaparib by time from randomisation to study treatment discontinuation or death (TDT). - To determine the efficacy of olaparib maintenance monotherapy compared to placebo in BRCA mutated high risk advanced ovarian cancer patients who are in clinical complete response or partial response following first line platinum based chemotherapy by assessment of time from randomisation to study treatment discontinuation or death (TDT).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time elapsed from randomisation to study treatment discontinuation or death. Assessed at time of primary PFS analysis and at final OS analysis. Study data collection expected to last ~10 years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Female patients with newly diagnosed, histologically confirmed, high risk advanced
             (FIGO stage III - IV) BRCA mutated high grade serous or high grade endometrioid
             ovarian cancer, primary peritoneal cancer and / or fallopian-tube cancer who have
             completed first line platinum based chemotherapy (intravenous or intraperitoneal).

          -  Stage III patients must have had one attempt at optimal debulking surgery (upfront or
             interval debulking). Stage IV patients must have had either a biopsy and/or upfront or
             interval debulking surgery.

          -  Documented mutation in BRCA1 or BRCA2 that is predicted to be deleterious or suspected
             deleterious (known or predicted to be detrimental/lead to loss of function).

          -  Patients who have completed first line platinum (e.g. carboplatin or cisplatin),
             containing therapy (intravenous or intraperitoneal) prior to randomisation:

          -  Patients must have, in the opinion of the investigator, clinical complete response or
             partial response and have no clinical evidence of disease progression on the post
             treatment scan or rising CA-125 level, following completion of this chemotherapy
             course. Patients with stable disease on the post-treatment scan at completion of first
             line platinum-containing therapy are not eligible for the study.

          -  Patients must be randomized within 8 weeks of their last dose of chemotherapy</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>130</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Female</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  BRCA1 and/or BRCA2 mutations that are considered to be non detrimental (e.g. "Variants
             of uncertain clinical significance" or "Variant of unknown significance" or "Variant,
             favor polymorphism" or "benign polymorphism" etc).

          -  Patients with early stage disease (FIGO Stage I, IIA, IIB or IIC)

          -  Stable disease or progressive disease on the post-treatment scan or clinical evidence
             of progression at the end of the patient's first line chemotherapy treatment.

          -  Patients where more than one debulking surgery has been performed before randomisation
             to the study. (Patients who, at the time of diagnosis, are deemed to be unresectable
             and undergo only a biopsy or oophorectomy but then go on to receive chemotherapy and
             interval debulking surgery are eligible).

          -  Patients who have previously been diagnosed and treated for earlier stage ovarian,
             fallopian tube or primary peritoneal cancer.

          -  Patients who have previously received chemotherapy for any abdominal or pelvic tumour,
             including treatment for prior diagnosis at an earlier stage for their ovarian,
             fallopian tube or primary peritoneal cancer. (Patients who have received prior
             adjuvant chemotherapy for localised breast cancer may be eligible, provided that it
             was completed more than three years prior to registration, and that the patient
             remains free of recurrent or metastatic disease).

          -  Patients with synchronous primary endometrial cancer unless both of the following
             criteria are met: 1) stage &lt;2 2) less than 60 years old at the time of diagnosis of
             endometrial cancer with stage IA or IB grade 1 or 2, or stage IA grade 3 endometrioid
             adenocarcinoma OR = 60 years old at the time of diagnosis of endometrial cancer with
             Stage IA grade 1 or 2 endometrioid adenocarcinoma. Patients with serous or clear cell
             adenocarcinoma or carcinosarcoma of the endometrium are not eligible.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional(has expanded access)</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2>The people administering the treatment/s</masking2>
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>26/08/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>450</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>29/03/2023</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>Mercy Hospital for Women - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <hospital>The Royal Womens Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Prince of Wales Hospital - Randwick</hospital>
    <postcode> - Heidelberg</postcode>
    <postcode> - Parkville</postcode>
    <postcode> - Randwick</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Alabama</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Alaska</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Arizona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Colorado</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Connecticut</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Georgia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Hawaii</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Illinois</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Indiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Iowa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Kentucky</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Maine</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Maryland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Massachusetts</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Michigan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Minnesota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Mississippi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Missouri</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Nebraska</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Nevada</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Jersey</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Mexico</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Dakota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Oklahoma</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Pennsylvania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Rhode Island</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>South Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>South Dakota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Virginia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Wisconsin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Barretos</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Goiânia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Itajai</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Porto Alegre</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>São José do Rio Preto</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>São Paulo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Quebec</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Beijing</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Changchun</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Changsha</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Chengdu</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Chongqing</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Guangzhou</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Hangzhou</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Harbin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Huangzhou</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Ji Nan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Shanghai</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Suzhou</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Xian</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Bordeaux</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Caen Cedex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Lyon Cedex 08</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Nantes,</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Paris</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Vandoeuvre Les Nancy</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Villejuif Cedex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Haifa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Kfar Saba</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Petach Tikva</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Tel Hashomer</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Tel-Aviv</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Bari</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Catania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Milano</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Napoli</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Padova</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Roma</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Akashi-shi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Chuo-ku</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Fukuoka</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Hidaka-shi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Matsuyama-shi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Niigata-shi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Sapporo-shi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Sunto-gun</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Goyang-si</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Seoul</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Amsterdam</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Maastricht</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Grzepnica</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Olsztyn</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Warszawa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Izhevsk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Moscow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Omsk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Saint Petersburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>St.Petersburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Tomsk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Córdoba</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Hospitalet deLlobregat(Barcelo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Valencia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Birmingham</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Cambridge</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Coventry</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Edinburgh</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>London</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Sutton</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>AstraZeneca</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Gynecologic Oncology Group (GOG)</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Myriad Genetic Laboratories, Inc.</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Olaparib Monotherapy in Patients with BRCA Mutated Ovarian Cancer following First Line
      Platinum Based Chemotherapy.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01844986</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Prof Paul DiSilvestro, MD</name>
      <address>Women &amp; Infants Hospital, Providence, Rhode Island, USA</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>