<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3840">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/10/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/10/2012</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01709578</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>To Evaluate The Effect Of SAR153191 (REGN88) Added To Other RA Drugs In Patients With RA Who Are Not Responding To Or Intolerant Of Anti-TNF Therapy (SARIL-RA-TARGET)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomized, Double-blind, Parallel, Placebo-controlled Study Assessing the Efficacy and Safety of Sarilumab Added to Non-biologic DMARD Therapy in Patients With Rheumatoid Arthritis Who Are Inadequate Responders to or Intolerant of TNF-a Antagonists</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>U1111-1115-8466</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>EFC10832</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Rheumatoid Arthritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Rheumatoid arthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Sarilumab
Treatment: drugs - placebo
Treatment: drugs - hydroxychloroquine
Treatment: drugs - methotrexate
Treatment: drugs - sulfasalazine
Treatment: drugs - leflunomide

Placebo Comparator: Placebo q2w - Placebo matched to sarilumab once every 2 weeks (q2w) was added to one or a combination of the nonbiologic DMARD (hydroxychloroquine, methotrexate, sulfasalazine and/or Leflunomide), except for simultaneous combination use of leflunomide and methotrexate for 24 weeks.

Experimental: Sarilumab 150 mg q2w - Sarilumab 150 mg q2w was added to one or a combination of the nonbiologic DMARD (hydroxychloroquine, methotrexate, sulfasalazine and/or Leflunomide), except for simultaneous combination use of leflunomide and methotrexate for 24 weeks.

Experimental: Sarilumab 200 mg q2w - Sarilumab 200 mg q2w was added to one or a combination of the nonbiologic DMARD (hydroxychloroquine, methotrexate, sulfasalazine and/or Leflunomide), except for simultaneous combination use of leflunomide and methotrexate for 24 weeks.


Treatment: drugs: Sarilumab
Pharmaceutical form:solution Route of administration: subcutaneous

Treatment: drugs: placebo
Pharmaceutical form:solution Route of administration: subcutaneous

Treatment: drugs: hydroxychloroquine
Dispensed according to the local practice.

Treatment: drugs: methotrexate
Dispensed according to the local practice.

Treatment: drugs: sulfasalazine
Dispensed according to the local practice.

Treatment: drugs: leflunomide
Dispensed according to the local practice.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants Who Achieved at Least 20% Improvement in the American College of Rheumatology (ACR20) Criteria at Week 24 - ACR responses are assessed with a composite rating scale of the American College of Rheumatology that includes 7 variables: tender joint count (TJC); swollen joint count (SJC); levels of an acute phase reactant (C-reactive Protein levels [CRP]); participant's assessment of pain; participant's global assessment of disease activity; physician's global assessment of disease activity; participant's assessment of physical function by (health assessment questionnaire disability index [HAQ-DI]). ACR20 is defined as achieving at least 20% improvement in both TJC and SJC, and at least 20% improvement in at least 3 of the 5 other assessments of the ACR.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 24</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in the Health Assessment Questionnaire-Disability Index (HAQ-DI) at Week 12 - Physical function was assessed by HAQ-DI. It consisted of at least 2 questions per category, participant reported assessment of ability to perform tasks in 8 categories of daily living activities: dress/groom; arise; eat; walk; reach; grip; hygiene; and common activities over past week rated on a 4-point scale where 0 = no difficulty; 1 = some difficulty; 2 = much difficulty; 3 = unable to do. Overall score was computed as the sum of category scores and divided by the number of categories answered, ranging from 0 to 3, where 0 = no disability and 3 = unable to do, high-dependency disability. Least-squares (LS) means and standard errors (SE) at Week 12 were obtained from a mixed-effect model with repeated measures (MMRM) with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline HAQ-DI as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 12</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Disease Activity Score for 28 Joints -C-Reactive Protein (DAS28--CRP) Score at Week 24 - DAS28 is a composite score that includes 4 variables: TJC (based on 28 joints); SJC (based on 28 joints); General health (GH) assessment by the participant assessed from the ACR rheumatoid arthritis (RA) core set questionnaire (participant global assessment) in 100 mm visual analog scale (VAS). Marker of inflammation assessed by the high sensitivity C-reactive protein (hs-CRP) in mg/L. The DAS28 score provides a number indicating the current disease activity of the RA. DAS28 total score ranges from 2-10. A DAS28 score above 5.1 means high disease activity, whereas a DAS28 score below 3.2 indicates low disease activity and a DAS28 score below 2.6 means disease remission. LS means and SE at Week 24 were obtained from a MMRM with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline DAS28-CRP score as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants Achieving ACR50 Criteria at Week 24 - ACR responses are assessed with a composite rating scale that includes 7 variables: TJC; SJC; levels of an acute phase reactant (CRP level); participant's assessment of pain; participant's global assessment of disease activity; physician's global assessment of disease activity; participant's assessment of physical function by HAQ--DI. ACR50 is defined as achieving at least 50% improvement in both TJC and SJC, and at least 50% improvement in at least 3 of the 5 other assessments of the ACR.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants Achieving ACR70 Criteria at Week 24 - ACR responses are assessed with a composite rating scale of the American College of Rheumatology that includes 7 variables: TJC; SJC; levels of an acute phase reactant (CRP level); participant's assessment of pain; participant's global assessment of disease activity; physician's global assessment of disease activity; participant's assessment of physical function by HAQ--DI. ACR70 is defined as achieving at least 70% improvement in both TJC and SJC, and at least 70% improvement in at least 3 of the 5 other assessments of the ACR.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants Achieving Clinical Remission Score (DAS28-CRP) &lt;2.6 at Week 24 - DAS28 is a composite score that includes 4 variables: TJC (based on 28 joints); SJC (based on 28 joints); GH by the participant assessed from the ACR rheumatoid arthritis core set questionnaire (participant global assessment) in 100 mm VAS; marker of inflammation assessed by hs-CRP in mg/L. The DAS28 provides a number indicating the current activity of the RA. DAS28 total score ranges from 2-10. A DAS28 score above 5.1 means high disease activity, whereas a DAS28 score below 3.2 indicates low disease activity and a DAS28 score below 2.6 means disease remission.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Clinical Disease Activity Index (CDAI) at Week 24 - CDAI is a composite index constructed to measure clinical remission in RA that does not include a laboratory test, and is a numerical summation of 4 components: TJC (28 joints), SJC (28 joints), Participant's Global Assessment of Disease Activity VAS (in cm), and Physician's Global Assessment of Disease VAS (in cm). Total scores ranges from 0 to 76 with a negative change in CDAI score indicating an improvement in disease activity and a positive change in score indicating a worsening of disease activity. LS means and SE at Week 24 were obtained from a MMRM with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline CDAI as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in HAQ-DI at Week 24 - Physical function was assessed by HAQ-DI. It consisted of at least 2 questions per category, participant reported assessment of ability to perform tasks in 8 categories of daily living activities: dress/groom; arise; eat; walk; reach; grip; hygiene; and common activities over past week rated on a 4-point scale where 0 = no difficulty; 1 = some difficulty; 2 = much difficulty; 3 = unable to do. Overall score was computed as the sum of category scores and divided by the number of categories answered, ranging from 0 to 3, where 0 = no disability and 3 = unable to do, high-dependency disability. LS means and SE at Week 24 were obtained from a MMRM with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline HAQ-DI as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in 36-Item Short-Form Health Survey (SF-36) Physical Component Summary Scores (PCS) at Week 24 - SF-36 is a generic 36-item questionnaire measuring health-related quality of life (HRQL) covering 2 summary measures: PCS and mental component summary (MCS). The SF-36 consists of 8 subscales. The PCS had 4 subscales: physical function, role limitations due to physical problems, pain, and general health perception. The MCS had 4 subscales: vitality, social function, role limitations due to emotional problems, and mental health. Participants self-report on items in a subscale that have between 2-6 choices per item using Likert-type responses (e.g. none of the time, some of the time, etc.). Summations of item scores of the same subscale give the subscale scores, which are transformed into a range from 0 to 100; 0= worst HRQL, 100=best HRQL. Higher scores indicate better health and well-being. LS mean and SE at Week 24 by MMRM with treatment,region,number of previous anti TNFs,visit,and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline SF-36 (PCS) as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in SF-36 MCS at Week 24 - SF-36 is a generic 36-item questionnaire measuring HRQL covering 2 summary measures: PCS and MCS. The SF-36 consists of 8 subscales. The PCS is represented by 4 subscales: physical function, role limitations due to physical problems, pain, and general health perception. The MCS is represented by 4 subscales: vitality, social function, role limitations due to emotional problems, and mental health. Participants self-report on items in a subscale that have between 2-6 choices per item using Likert-type responses (e.g. none of the time, some of the time, etc.). Summations of item scores of the same subscale give the subscale scores, which are transformed into a range from 0 to 100; 0= worst HRQL, 100=best HRQL. Higher scores indicate better health and well-being. LS mean and SE at Week 24 were obtained from a MMRM with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline SF-36 MCS as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in the Functional Assessment of Chronic Illness Therapy Fatigue (FACIT-fatigue) Score at Week 24 - The FACIT-Fatigue is a 13-item questionnaire assessing fatigue where participants scored each item on a 5-point scale (0-4): 0=not at all, 1=a little bit, 2=somewhat, 3=quite a bit, 4=very much. A total score ranging from 0 to 52. A higher score corresponded to a lower level of fatigue. A positive change from baseline score indicates an improvement. LS mean and SE at Week 24 were obtained from a MMRM with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline FACIT-fatigue as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Morning Stiffness VAS at Week 24 - RA is associated with stiffness of joints, especially in the morning after prolonged stationery state. The degree of stiffness can be an indicator of disease severity. The severity of morning stiffness was assessed on a VAS scale from 0 mm (no problem) to 100 mm (major problem). LS mean and SE at Week 24 were obtained from a MMRM with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline Morning Stiffness as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Work Productivity Survey - Rheumatoid Arthritis (WPS-RA) at Week 24: Work Days Missed Due to RA - The WPS-RA is a validated questionnaire that evaluates productivity limitations within work and within home associated with RA over the previous month. The questionnaire was interviewer-administered and was based on participant self-report. It contains 9 questions addressing employment status (1 item), productivity at work (3 items), and within and outside the home (5 items). Number of work days missed in the last month by the participant was reported. LS mean and SE at Week 24 were obtained from a MMRM with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline WPS-RA as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in WPS-RA at Week 24: Days With Work Productivity Reduced by = 50% Due to RA - The WPS-RA is a validated questionnaire that evaluates productivity limitations within work and within home associated with RA over the previous month. The questionnaire was interviewer-administered and was based on participant self-report. It contains 9 questions addressing employment status (1 item), productivity at work (3 items), and within and outside the home (5 items). Number of work days with reduced productivity by = 50% in the last month by the participant was reported. LS mean and SE at Week 24 were obtained from a MMRM with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline WPS-RA as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in WPS-RA at Week 24: RA Interference With Work Productivity - The WPS-RA is a validated questionnaire that evaluates productivity limitations within work and within home associated with RA over the previous month. The questionnaire was interviewer-administered and was based on participant self-report. It contains 9 questions addressing employment status (1 item), productivity at work (3 items), and within and outside the home (5 items). Interference in the last month with work productivity is measured on a scale that ranges from 0 (no interference) to 10 (complete interference). LS mean and SE at Week 24 were obtained from a MMRM with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline WPS-RA as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in WPS-RA at Week 24: House Work Days Missed Due to RA - The WPS-RA is a validated questionnaire that evaluates productivity limitations within work and within home associated with RA over the previous month. The questionnaire was interviewer-administered and was based on participant self-report. It contains 9 questions addressing employment status (1 item), productivity at work (3 items), and within and outside the home (5 items). Number of days with no household work in the last month by the participant was reported. LS mean and SE at Week 24 were obtained from a MMRM with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline WPS-RA as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in WPS-RA at Week 24: Days With Household Work Productivity Reduced by = 50% Due to RA - The WPS-RA is a validated questionnaire that evaluates productivity limitations within work and within home associated with RA over the previous month. The questionnaire was interviewer-administered and was based on participant self-report. It contains 9 questions addressing employment status (1 item), productivity at work (3 items), and within and outside the home (5 items). Number of days with reduced household work productivity by = 50% in the last month by the participant was reported. LS mean and SE at Week 24 were obtained from a MMRM with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline WPS-RA as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in WPS-RA at Week 24: Days With Family/Social/Leisure Activities Missed Due to RA - The WPS-RA is a validated questionnaire that evaluates productivity limitations within work and within home associated with RA over the previous month. The questionnaire was interviewer-administered and was based on participant self-report. It contains 9 questions addressing employment status (1 item), productivity at work (3 items), and within and outside the home (5 items). Number of days missed of family/social/leisure activities in the last month by the participant was reported. LS mean and SE at Week 24 were obtained from a MMRM with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline WPS-RA as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in WPS-RA at Week 24: Days With Outside Help Hired Due to RA - The WPS-RA is a validated questionnaire that evaluates productivity limitations within work and within home associated with RA over the previous month. The questionnaire was interviewer-administered and was based on participant self-report. It contains 9 questions addressing employment status (1 item), productivity at work (3 items), and within and outside the home (5 items). Number of days with outside help hired in the last month by the participant was reported. LS mean and SE at Week 24 were obtained from a MMRM with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline WPS-RA as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in WPS-RA at Week 24: RA Interference With Household Work Productivity - The WPS-RA is a validated questionnaire that evaluates productivity limitations within work and within home associated with RA over the previous month. The questionnaire was interviewer-administered and was based on participant self-report. It contains 9 questions addressing employment status (1 item), productivity at work (3 items), and within and outside the home (5 items). The RA interference in the last month with household work productivity was measured on a scale that ranges from 0 (no interference) to 10 (complete interference). LS mean and SE at Week 24 were obtained from a MMRM with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline WPS-RA as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Rheumatoid Arthritis Impact of Disease (RAID) Scores at Week 24 - RAID is a composite measure of the impact of RA on participants that takes into account 7 domains: pain, functional disability, fatigue, physical and emotional well being, quality of sleep, and coping. The RAID is calculated based on 7 numerical rating scales (NRS) questions. Range of the final RAID value is 0-10 where 0= not affected, very good and 10 = most affected weighted and calculated with a total score range of 0 (not affected, very good) to 10 (most affected). A higher RAID value indicate worse status and lower indicate not affected. LS mean and SE at Week 24 were obtained from a MMRM with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline RAID as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in European Quality of Life-5 Dimension 3 Level (EQ-5D-3L) VAS Scores at Week 24 - The EQ-5D-3L is a standardized, generic measure of health outcome. It was designed for self-completion by participants. It was specifically included to address concerns regarding the health economic impact of RA. The EQ-5D-3L comprises 5 questions on mobility, self-care, pain, usual activities, and psychological status with 3 possible answers for each item (1=no problem, 2=moderate problems, 3=severe problems) and a vertical VAS that allows the participants to indicate their health state today that can range from 0 (worst imaginable) to 100 (best imaginable). LS mean and SE at Week 24 were obtained from a MMRM with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline EQ-5D-3L Scores as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants Achieving ACR20, ACR50 and ACR70 Criteria at Week 12 - ACR responses are assessed with a composite rating scale of the American College of Rheumatology that includes 7 variables: TJC; SJC; levels of an acute phase reactant (CRP level); participant's assessment of pain; participant's global assessment of disease activity; physician's global assessment of disease activity; participant's assessment of physical function by HAQ--DI. ACR20 is defined as achieving at least 20% improvement in both TJC and SJC, and at least 20% improvement in at least 3 of the 5 other assessments of the ACR. ACR50 is defined as achieving at least 50% improvement in both TJC and SJC, and at least 50% improvement in at least 3 of the 5 other assessments of the ACR. ACR70 is defined as achieving at least 70% improvement in both TJC and SJC, and at least 70% improvement in at least 3 of the 5 other assessments of the ACR.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in DAS28-CRP at Week 12 - DAS28 is a composite score that includes 4 variables: TJC (based on 28 joints); SJC (based on 28 joints); GH by the participant assessed from the ACR rheumatoid arthritis core set questionnaire (participant global assessment) in 100 mm VAS; marker of inflammation assessed by hs-CRP in mg/L. The DAS28 provides a number indicating the current activity of the RA. DAS28 total score ranges from 2-10. A DAS28 score above 5.1 means high disease activity, whereas a DAS28 score below 3.2 indicates low disease activity and a DAS28 score below 2.6 means disease remission. LS mean and SE at Week 12 were obtained from a MMRM with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline DAS score as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of Participants Achieving Clinical Remission Score (DAS28--CRP &lt;2.6) at Week 12 - DAS28 is a composite score that includes 4 variables: TJC (based on 28 joints); SJC (based on 28 joints); GH by the participant assessed from the ACR RA core set questionnaire (participant global assessment) in 100 mm VAS; marker of inflammation assessed by hs-CRP in mg/L. The DAS28 provides a number indicating the current activity of the RA. DAS28 total score ranges from 2-10. A DAS28 score above 5.1 means high disease activity, whereas a DAS28 score below 3.2 indicates low disease activity and a DAS28 score below 2.6 means disease remission.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in SF-36 at Week 12 - SF-36 is a generic 36-item questionnaire measuring HRQL covering 2 summary measures: PCS and MCS. The SF-36 consists of 8 subscales. The PCS is represented by 4 subscales: physical function, role limitations due to physical problems, pain, and general health perception. The MCS is represented by 4 subscales: vitality, social function, role limitations due to emotional problems, and mental health. Participants self-report on items in a subscale that have between 2-6 choices per item using Likert-type responses (e.g. none of the time, some of the time, etc.). Summations of item scores of the same subscale give the subscale scores, which are transformed into a range from 0 to 100; 0= worst HRQL, 100=best HRQL. Higher scores indicate better health and well-being. LS mean and SE at Week 12 were obtained from a MMRM with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline SF-36 as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in WPS-RA at Week 12: Work Days Missed Due to RA - The WPS-RA is a validated questionnaire that evaluates productivity limitations within work and within home associated with RA over the previous month. The questionnaire was interviewer-administered and was based on participant self-report. It contains 9 questions addressing employment status (1 item), productivity at work (3 items), and within and outside the home (5 items). Number of work days missed in the last month by the participant was reported. LS mean and SE at Week 12 were obtained from a MMRM with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline WPS-RA as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in WPS-RA at Week 12: Days With Work Productivity Reduced by = 50% Due to RA - The WPS-RA is a validated questionnaire that evaluates productivity limitations within work and within home associated with RA over the previous month. The questionnaire was interviewer-administered and was based on participant self-report. It contains 9 questions addressing employment status (1 item), productivity at work (3 items), and within and outside the home (5 items). Number of work days with reduced productivity by = 50% in the last month by the participant was reported. LS mean and SE at Week 12 were obtained from a MMRM with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline WPS-RA as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in WPS-RA at Week 12: RA Interference With Work Productivity - The WPS-RA is a validated questionnaire that evaluates productivity limitations within work and within home associated with RA over the previous month. The questionnaire was interviewer-administered and was based on participant self-report. It contains 9 questions addressing employment status (1 item), productivity at work (3 items), and within and outside the home (5 items). Interference in the last month with work productivity was measured on a scale that ranges from 0 (no interference) to 10 (complete interference). LS mean and SE at Week 12 were obtained from a MMRM with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline WPS-RA as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in WPS-RA at Week 12: House Work Days Missed Due to RA - The WPS-RA is a validated questionnaire that evaluates productivity limitations within work and within home associated with RA over the previous month. The questionnaire was interviewer-administered and was based on participant self-report. It contains 9 questions addressing employment status (1 item), productivity at work (3 items), and within and outside the home (5 items). Number of days with no household work in the last month by the participant was reported. LS mean and SE at Week 12 were obtained from a MMRM with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline WPS-RA as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in WPS-RA at Week 12: Days With Household Work Productivity Reduced by = 50% Due to RA - The WPS-RA is a validated questionnaire that evaluates productivity limitations within work and within home associated with RA over the previous month. The questionnaire was interviewer-administered and was based on participant self-report. It contains 9 questions addressing employment status (1 item), productivity at work (3 items), and within and outside the home (5 items). Number of days with reduced household work productivity by = 50% in the last month by the participant was reported. LS mean and SE at Week 12 were obtained from a MMRM with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline WPS-RA as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in WPS-RA at Week 12: Days With Family/Social/Leisure Activities Missed Due to RA - The WPS-RA is a validated questionnaire that evaluates productivity limitations within work and within home associated with RA over the previous month. The questionnaire was interviewer-administered and was based on participant self-report. It contains 9 questions addressing employment status (1 item), productivity at work (3 items), and within and outside the home (5 items). Number of days missed of family/social/leisure activities in the last month by the participant was reported. LS mean and SE at Week 12 were obtained from a MMRM with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline WPS-RA as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in WPS-RA at Week 12: Days With Outside Help Hired Due to RA - The WPS-RA is a validated questionnaire that evaluates productivity limitations within work and within home associated with RA over the previous month. The questionnaire was interviewer-administered and was based on participant self-report. It contains 9 questions addressing employment status (1 item), productivity at work (3 items), and within and outside the home (5 items). Number of days with outside help hired in the last month by the participant was reported. LS mean and SE at Week 12 were obtained from a MMRM with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline WPS-RA as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in WPS-RA at Week 12: RA Interference With Household Work Productivity - The WPS-RA is a validated questionnaire that evaluates productivity limitations within work and within home associated with RA over the previous month. The questionnaire was interviewer-administered and was based on participant self-report. It contains 9 questions addressing employment status (1 item), productivity at work (3 items), and within and outside the home (5 items). The RA interference in the last month with household work productivity was measured on a scale that ranges from 0 (no interference) to 10 (complete interference). LS mean and SE at Week 12 were obtained from a MMRM with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline WPS-RA as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in the FACIT-fatigue at Week 12 - The FACIT-Fatigue is a 13-item questionnaire assessing fatigue where participants scored each item on a 5-point scale (0-4): 0=not at all, 1=a little bit, 2=somewhat, 3=quite a bit, 4=very much. A total score ranging from 0 to 52. A higher score corresponded to a lower level of fatigue. A positive change from baseline score indicates an improvement. LS mean and SE at Week 12 were obtained from a MMRM with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline FACIT-fatigue as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in EQ-5D-3L VAS Scores at Week 12 - The EQ-5D-3L is a standardized, generic measure of health outcome. EQ-5D was designed for self-completion by participants. The EQ-5D was specifically included to address concerns regarding the health economic impact of RA. The EQ-5D-3L comprises 5 questions on mobility, self-care, pain, usual activities, and psychological status with 3 possible answers for each item (1=no problem, 2=moderate problems, 3=severe problems) and a vertical VAS that allows the participants to indicate their health state today that can range from 0 (worst imaginable) to 100 (best imaginable). LS mean and SE at Week 12 were obtained from a MMRM with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline EQ-5D-3L scores as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in RAID Scores at Week 12 - RAID score is a composite measure of the impact of RA on participants that takes into account 7 domains: pain, functional disability, fatigue, physical and emotional well being, quality of sleep, and coping. The RAID is calculated based on 7 NRS questions. Range of the final RAID value is 0-10 where 0= not affected, very good and 10 = most affected weighted and calculated with a total score range of 0 (not affected, very good) to 10 (most affected). A higher RAID value indicates worse status and lower indicates not affected. LS mean and SE at Week 12 were obtained from a MMRM with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline RAID scores as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Individual ACR Components - TJC and SJC at Week 12 and Week 24 - ACR components were: TJC, SJC, physician global VAS, participant global VAS, pain VAS,HAQ-DI &amp; CRP. 68 joints were assessed for tenderness (TJC scoring 0-68) and 66 joints for swelling (SJC scoring 0-66). The 66 SJC evaluated the following joints: temporomandibular, sternoclavicular, acromioclavicular, shoulder, elbow, wrist, metacarpophalangeal, interphalangeal of thumb, distal interphalangeal, proximal interphalangeal, knee, ankle mortise, ankle tarsus, metatarsophalangeal, interphalangeal of great toe, and proximal/distal interphalangeal of the toes. The TJC examined hip joints, in addition to the joints assessed for SJC. Increase in number of tender joints/swollen joints indicated severity. LS mean and SE at Week 12 &amp; 24 by MMRM with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline ACR components as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 12 and Week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Individual ACR Component - Physician Global VAS, Participant Global VAS and Pain VAS at Week 12 and Week 24 - ACR components were: TJC, SJC, physician global VAS, participant global VAS, pain VAS, HAQ-DI &amp; CRP. Physician global VAS &amp; participant global VAS was done by 100 mm non-anchored VAS, from no arthritis (0) activity to maximal arthritis (100) activity. Pain VAS by 100 mm VAS ranging from 0 "no pain" to 100 "worst pain". LS mean and SE at Week 12 &amp; 24 by MMRM with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline ACR components as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 12 and Week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Individual ACR Component - CRP Level at Week 12 and Week 24 - ACR components were: TJC, SJC, physician global VAS, participant global VAS, pain VAS, HAQ-DI &amp; CRP. An elevated CRP level was considered a non-specific "marker" for RA. A reduction level indicates improvement. LS mean and SE at Week 12 &amp; 24 by MMRM with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline ACR components as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 12 and Week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change From Baseline in Individual ACR Component - HAQ-DI at Week 12 and Week 24 - ACR components were: TJC, SJC, physician global VAS, participant global VAS, pain VAS,HAQ-DI &amp; CRP. HAQ-DI consisted of at least 2 questions per category, participant reported assessment of ability to perform tasks in 8 categories of daily living activities: dress/groom; arise; eat; walk; reach; grip; hygiene; and common activities over past week rated on a 4-point scale where 0 = no difficulty; 1 = some difficulty; 2 = much difficulty; 3 = unable to do. Overall score was computed as the sum of category scores and divided by the number of categories answered, ranging from 0 to 3, where 0 = no disability and 3 = unable to do, high-dependency disability. LS mean and SE at Week 12 &amp; 24 by MMRM with treatment, region, number of previous anti-TNFs, visit, and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects and baseline ACR components as a covariate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 12 and Week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria:

        Diagnosis of RA =6 months duration, according to the ACR /European League against
        Rheumatism (EULAR) 2010 RA Classification Criteria

        ACR Class I-III functional status, based on 1991 revised criteria

        Anti-TNF therapy failures, defined by the investigator as participants with an inadequate
        clinical response, after being treated for at least 3 consecutive months, and/or
        intolerance to at least 1 anti-TNF blocker(s), resulting in or requiring their
        discontinuation:

          -  TNF-blockers included, but were not limited to, etanercept, infliximab, adalimumab,
             golimumab and/or certolizumab

        Moderate-to-severely active RA

        Continuous treatment with one or a combination of DMARDs (except for simultaneous
        combination use of leflunomide and methotrexate) for at least 12 weeks prior to baseline
        and on a stable dose(s) for at least 6 weeks prior to screening:

          -  Methotrexate - 6 to 25 mg/week orally or parenterally

          -  Leflunomide - 10 to 20 mg orally daily

          -  Sulfasalazine - 1000 to 3000 mg orally daily

          -  Hydroxychloroquine - 200 to 400 mg orally daily</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria:

        Participants &lt;18 years of age or legal adult age

        Past history of, or current, autoimmune or inflammatory systemic or localized joint
        disease(s) other than RA

        History of juvenile idiopathic arthritis or arthritis onset prior to age 16

        Severe active systemic RA, including but not limited to vasculitis, pulmonary fibrosis,
        and/or Felty's syndrome.

        Treatment with anti-TNF agents, as follows:

          -  Within 28 days prior to the baseline visit - etanercept

          -  Within 42 days prior to the baseline visit - infliximab, adalimumab, golimumab,
             certolizumab pegol

        Treatment with previous RA-directed biologic agents with other than TNF antagonist
        mechanisms:

        Within 28 days prior to the randomization (baseline) visit - anakinra Within 42 days prior
        to the randomization (baseline) visit - abatacept

        Within 6 months prior to the randomization (baseline) visit - any cell depleting agents
        including but not limited to rituximab without a normal lymphocyte and cluster of
        differentiation (CD) 19+ lymphocyte count

        Treatment with any DMARD other than those allowed per protocol and limited to the maximum
        specified dosage within 12 weeks prior to baseline

        Treatment with prednisone &gt;10 mg or equivalent per day, or change in dosage within 4 weeks
        prior to baseline visit

        Any parenteral or intra-articular glucocorticoid injection within 4 weeks prior to baseline

        Prior treatment with anti-interleukin (IL) -6 or IL-6 receptor antagonist therapies,
        including tocilizumab or sarilumab, participation in a prior study of sarilumab,
        irrespective of treatment arm

        Prior treatment with a Janus kinase inhibitor (such as tofacitinib)

        New treatment or dose-adjustment to ongoing medication for dyslipidemia within 6 weeks
        prior to randomization, ie, stable dose for at least 6 weeks prior to randomization

        Participation in any clinical research study evaluating another investigational drug or
        therapy within 5 half-lives or 60 days of first investigational medicinal product (IMP)
        administration, whichever was longer

        History of alcohol or drug abuse within 5 years prior to the screening visit

        Participants with a history of malignancy other than adequately-treated carcinoma in-situ
        of the cervix, nonmetastatic squamous cell or basal cell carcinoma of the skin, within 5
        years prior to the randomization (baseline) visit. Nonmalignant lymphoproliferative
        disorders were also excluded

        Participants with active tuberculosis or latent tuberculosis infection

        The above information was not intended to contain all considerations relevant to a
        participant's potential participation in a clinical trial</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>The people receiving the treatment/s</masking1>
    <masking2>The people administering the treatment/s</masking2>
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/10/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>546</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/03/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>Investigational Site Number 036014 - Victoria Park</hospital>
    <postcode>6100 - Victoria Park</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Alabama</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Arizona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Colorado</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Delaware</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Idaho</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Kansas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Kentucky</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Louisiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Maryland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Michigan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Mississippi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Nebraska</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Oklahoma</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Pennsylvania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>South Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Tennessee</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Washington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>West Virginia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Argentina</country>
      <state>Buenos Aires</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Argentina</country>
      <state>Caba</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Argentina</country>
      <state>Capital Federal</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Argentina</country>
      <state>Cordoba</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Argentina</country>
      <state>La Plata</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Argentina</country>
      <state>Ramos Mejia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Argentina</country>
      <state>Rosario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Argentina</country>
      <state>San Miguel De Tucuman</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Argentina</country>
      <state>Zarate</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Austria</country>
      <state>Stockerau</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Austria</country>
      <state>Wien</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Curitiba</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Goiania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Juiz De Fora</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Rio De Janeiro</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Toronto</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Trois-Rivires</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Victoria</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Chile</country>
      <state>Temuco</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Colombia</country>
      <state>Bogota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Colombia</country>
      <state>Bogot</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Colombia</country>
      <state>Bucaramanga</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Colombia</country>
      <state>Chia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Colombia</country>
      <state>Medellin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Hostivice</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Ostrava</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Praha 2</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Uherske Hradiste</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czechia</country>
      <state>Zlin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ecuador</country>
      <state>Cuenca</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ecuador</country>
      <state>Guayaquil</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ecuador</country>
      <state>Quito</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Bad Nauheim</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Berlin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Deggingen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Erlangen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Halle/Saale</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Hamburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Leipzig</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Mnchen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Osnabrck</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Tbingen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Zerbst</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Heraklion</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Thessaloniki</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Guatemala</country>
      <state>Guatemala City</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Budapest</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Debrecen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Veszprm</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Haifa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Petach Tikva</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Tel Hashomer</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Catania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Firenze</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Genova</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Milano</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Udine</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Daejeon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Seoul</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Lithuania</country>
      <state>Kaunas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Lithuania</country>
      <state>Klaipeda</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Lithuania</country>
      <state>Vilnius</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mexico</country>
      <state>Chihuahua</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mexico</country>
      <state>Guadalajara</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mexico</country>
      <state>Mexicali</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mexico</country>
      <state>Monterrey</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mexico</country>
      <state>Mxico</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mexico</country>
      <state>Queretaro</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Hamilton</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Nelson</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Otahuhu</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Timaru</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Wellington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Peru</country>
      <state>Lima</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Bialystok</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Bydgoszcz</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Elblag</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Poznan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Szczecin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Warszawa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Wroclaw</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <state>Lisboa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <state>Ponte De Lima</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Romania</country>
      <state>Bucuresti</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Romania</country>
      <state>Iasi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Moscow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Novosibirsk</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Saint-Petersburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Samara</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Slovakia</country>
      <state>Kosice</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barakaldo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Cadiz</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>La Corua</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Mlaga</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Sabadell</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Santiago De Compostela</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Sevilla</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Kaohsiung</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Taipei</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Taoyuan County</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>Edirne</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>Gaziantep</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>Samsun</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ukraine</country>
      <state>Kharkiv</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ukraine</country>
      <state>Kyiv</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ukraine</country>
      <state>Vinnytsia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ukraine</country>
      <state>Zaporizhzhya</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Sanofi</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Regeneron Pharmaceuticals</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Primary Objective:

      To demonstrate that sarilumab added to disease modifying anti-rheumatic drugs (DMARDs) were
      effective for:

        -  reduction of signs and symptoms at Week 24 and

        -  improvement of physical function at Week 12

      in participants with active rheumatoid arthritis (RA) who were inadequate responders or
      intolerant to tumor necrosis factor alpha (TNF-a) antagonists.

      Secondary Objectives:

      The secondary objectives were to investigate the effects of SAR153191 (REGN88) when added to
      DMARD therapy, in participants with active RA who were inadequate responders or intolerant to
      TNF-a antagonists, for:

        -  Reduction of signs and symptoms at Week 12;

        -  Improvement in physical function at Week 24;

        -  Improvement in disease activity score as measured by other American College of
           Rheumatology (ACR) derived components at Weeks 12 and 24;

        -  Improvement in quality of life as measured by participant reported outcomes (PROs) at
           intermediate visits and Week 24.

      To assess the exposure of sarilumab added to DMARD therapy in this population.

      To assess the safety of sarilumab in this population.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01709578</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Clinical Sciences &amp; Operations</name>
      <address>Sanofi</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>