<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="4149">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/06/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/06/2013</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01915303</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Study of the Efficacy and Safety of Pasireotide s.c. +/- Cabergoline in Patients With Cushing's Disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase II Trial to Assess the Efficacy and Safety of Pasireotide s.c. Alone or in Combination With Cabergoline in Patients With Cushing's Disease</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>CSOM230B2411</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cushing's Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other endocrine disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Pasireotide with or without cabergoline

Experimental: pasireotide +/- cabergoline - pasireotide alone or with cabergoline


Treatment: drugs: Pasireotide with or without cabergoline
The trial consists of Pasireotide-untreated patients will start pasireotide 0.6mg twice a day for 8 weeks. If biochemical control is not achieved by the end of the 8 weeks, and the 0.6mg dose is well-tolerated, the dose will be increased to 0.9mg twice a day for another 8 weeks. If biochemical control is not achieved, cabergoline will be added and patients will begin combination treatment with cabergoline at the starting dose of 0.5mg once a day for 8 weeks. If biochemical control is still not achieved at the end of the third 8 week period, the dose of cabergoline wlil be increased to 1.0mg once a day. Patients can also immediately start the combination treatment by adding cabergoline 0.5mg once a day at study entry to their current maximal tolerated dose of pasireotide. Patients will continue with the combination treatment for 8 weeks. If biochemical control is not achieved by the end of the 8 week period, the dose of cabergoline will be increased to 1mg once a day.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients who attain mUFC =1.0 ULN at week 35 with pasireotide alone or in combination with cabergoline - Proportion of patients who attain mUFC = 1.0 x ULN at week 35 with pasireotide alone or in combination with cabergoline</outcome>
      <timepoint>at week 35</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage change in mUFC from baseline to study end at each scheduled visit when UFC is measured - Percentage change in mUFC from baseline to study end at each scheduled visit when UFC is measured</outcome>
      <timepoint>at weeks 4, 8, 13, 17, 22, 26, 31, 35</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients attain mUFC = 1.0 x ULN as assessed at each scheduled visit when UFC is measured - Proportion of patients that attain mUFC = 1.0 x ULN as assessed at each scheduled visit when UFC is measured</outcome>
      <timepoint>at weeks 4, 8, 13, 17, 22, 26, 31</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients who attain mUFC = 1.0 x ULN or have at least 50% reduction from baseline in mUFC as assessed at each scheduled visit when UFC is measured - Proportion of patients who attain mUFC = 1.0 x ULN or have at least 50% reduction from baseline in mUFC as assessed at each scheduled visit when UFC is measured</outcome>
      <timepoint>at weeks 4, 8, 13, 17, 22, 26, 31, 35</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of controlled or partially controlled response - Duration of controlled or partially controlled response is defined as the period starting from the date of patient's first normalization (mUFC = 1.0 x ULN) or at least 50% reduction from baseline up to the date when the patient's mUFC &gt; 1.0 x ULN and the reduction from baseline falls to less than 50% from the first time</outcome>
      <timepoint>from the date patient's first normalization (mUFC = 1.0xULN) or at least 50% reduction from baseline up to the date when the patient's mUFC &gt; 1.0 x ULN</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in plasma ACTH and serum cortisol over time - Change from baseline in plasma ACTH and serum cortisol over time</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 4, 8, 13, 17, 22, 26, 31 and 35</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Toxicity will be assessed using NCI-CTCAE v.4 and for laboratory assessments - Shift tables using CTC grades to compare baseline to the worst post-baseline value</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline visits, and at weeks 4, 8, 13, 17, 22, 26, 31, 35 and study completion visit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria:

          1. Written informed consent obtaine prior to screening procedures

          2. Adult patients with confirmed diagnosis of ACTH-dependent Cushing's disease as
             evidenced by all of the following:

               1. The mean of three 24-hour urine samples collected within 2 weeks &gt; 1xULN with 2
                  out of 3 samples &gt;ULN

               2. Morning plasma ACTH within the normal or above normal range

               3. Either MRI confirmation of pituitary adenoma &gt; 6 mm, or inferior petrosal sinus
                  gradient &gt;3 after CRH stimulation for those patients with a tumor less than or
                  equal to 6 mm*. For patients who have had prior pituitary surgery, histopathology
                  confirming an ACTH staining adenoma *If IPSS had previously been performed
                  without CRH (e.g. with DDAVP), then a central to peripheral pre-stimulation
                  gradient &gt; 2 is required. If IPSS had not previously been performed, IPSS with
                  CRH stimulation is required.

          3. Patients with de novo Cushing's disease can be included only if they are not
             considered candidates for pituitary surgery (e.g. poor surgical candidates, surgically
             unapproachable tumors, patients who refuse to have surgical treatment)

          4. Male or female patients aged 18 years or greater

          5. Karnofsky performance status = 60 (i.e. requires occasional assistance, but is able to
             care for most of their personal needs)

          6. Patients on medical treatment for Cushing's disease the following washout periods must
             be completed before screening assessments are performed

               -  Inhibitors of steroidogenesis (ketoconazole, metyrapone): 1 week

               -  Pituitary directed agents: Dopamine agonists (bromocriptine, cabergoline) and
                  PPAR? agonists (rosiglitazone or pioglitazone): 4 weeks

               -  Octreotide LAR, Lanreotide SR and Lanreotide autogel: 14 weeks

               -  Octreotide (immediate release formulation): 1 week

               -  Progesterone receptor antagonist (mifepristone): 4 weeks

          7. Patients can be considered to enter the trial if they meet any one of the following
             criteria: 1) They are naive to pasireotide 2) They have received pasireotide in the
             past and have been discontinued because of lack of efficacy (2 weeks for washout prior
             to screening for patients treated with pasireotide subcutaneously and 12 weeks of
             washout prior to screening for patients treated with pasireotide LAR) 3) Patients who
             are on maximal tolerated dose but have not achieved biochemical control

          8. Women of child-bearing potential, defined as all women physiologically capable of
             becoming pregnant, if they are using highly effective methods of contraception during
             dosing and for 30 days after stopping study medication.

          9. Male participants in the trial must agree to use a condom during intercourse, and not
             to father a child during the study and for the period of 30 days following stopping of
             the study treatment.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria:

          1. Patients with compression of the optic chiasm causing any visual field defect that
             requires surgical intervention

          2. Diabetic patients with poor glycemic control as evidenced by HbA1c &gt;8%

          3. Patients with risk factors for torsade de pointes, i.e. patients with a baseline QTcF
             &gt;450 ms in males, and &gt; 460 ms in females. hypokalemia, hypomagnesaemia, uncontrolled
             hypothyroidism, family history of long QT syndrome, or concomitant medications known
             to prolong QT interval.

          4. Patients with clinically significant valvular disease.

          5. Patients with Cushing's syndrome due to ectopic ACTH secretion

          6. Patients with hypercortisolism secondary to adrenal tumors or nodular (primary)
             bilateral adrenal hyperplasia

          7. Patients who have congestive heart failure (NYHA Class III or IV), unstable angina,
             sustained ventricular tachycardia, clinically significant bradycardia, advanced heart
             block, history of acute MI less than one year prior to study entry or clinically
             significant impairment in cardiovascular function

          8. Patients with liver disease such as cirrhosis, chronic active hepatitis, or chronic
             persistent hepatitis, or patients with ALT/AST &gt; 2 X ULN, serum bilirubin &gt;2.0 X ULN

          9. Patients with serum creatinine &gt;2.0 X ULN

         10. Patients with WBC &lt;3 X 10e9/L; Hb 90% &lt; LLN; PLT &lt;100 X 10e9/L

         11. Patients with presence of Hepatitis B surface antigen (HbsAg)

         12. Patients with presence of Hepatitis C antibody test (anti-HCV)

         13. Patients with severe hepatic impairment (Child Pugh C) and hypersensitivity to
             pasireotide or cabergoline

         14. Patients with lung, pericardial, and retroperitoneal fibrosis; gastro-duodenal ulcer
             or digestive haemorrhage, galactose intolerance, Parkinson's disease, uncontrolled
             hypertension and Raynauds syndrome.

         15. Pregnant or nursing (lactating) women where pregnancy is defined as the state of a
             female after conception and until the termination of gestation, confirmed by a
             positive hCG laboratory test (&gt; 5 mIU/ml)

         16. Patients with end-stage renal failure and/or hemodialysis

         17. Patients with presence of active or suspected acute or chronic uncontrolled infection

         18. Patients with a history of non-complance to medical regimens or who are considered
             potentially unreliable or whill be unable to complete the entire study

         19. Patients with presence of Hepatitis B surface antigen (HbsAg)

         20. Patients with presence of Hepatitis C antibody test (anti-HCV)

         21. Patients with severe hepatic impairment (Child Pugh C) and hpersensitivity to
             pasireotide or cabergoline

         22. Patients with lung, pericardial, and retroperitoneal fibrosis; gastroduodenal ulcer or
             digestive haemorrhage, galactose intolerance, Parkinson's disease, uncontrolled
             hypertension and Raynaud's syndrome

         23. Pregnant or nursing (lactating) women where pregnancy is defined as the state of a
             female after conception and until the terminiation of gestation, confirmed by a
             positive hCG laboratory test (&gt; 5mIU/mL)

         24. Patients with end-stage renal failure and/or hemodialysis</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>6/03/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>70</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/12/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Novartis Investigative Site - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <postcode>4102 - Woolloongabba</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Alabama</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Oregon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Argentina</country>
      <state>Buenos Aires</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Gent</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Leuven</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>PR</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>RJ</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>RS</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>SC</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>SP</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Bulgaria</country>
      <state>Sofia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Colombia</country>
      <state>Cundinamarca</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Vandoeuvre Cedex</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Erlangen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Würzburg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Athens</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Thessaloniki</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Budapest</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>India</country>
      <state>Tamil Nadu</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>India</country>
      <state>Chandigarh</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>India</country>
      <state>New Delhi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>MI</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Napoli</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <state>Wilayah Persekutuan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mexico</country>
      <state>Distrito Federal</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mexico</country>
      <state>Durango</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Rotterdam</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Andalucia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Comunidad Valenciana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>Balcova / Izmir</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>Fatih / Istanbul</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>Pendik / Istanbul</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is to assess whether pasireotide alone and combined with cabergoline will give
      reliefs on patients with recurrent, persistent and newly diagnosed Cushing's disease. The
      study will also assess study drug safety, the changes in Quality of Life and on clinical
      signs and symptoms of Cushing's disease.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01915303</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>