<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2678">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/02/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/02/2010</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01075789</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Using Lignocaine Spray and Gel to Reduce the Pain Associated With Nasogastric Tube Insertion in Children</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Combined Use of Intranasal Lignocaine Spray and Oral Lignocaine Gel to Reduce the Pain and Trauma Associated With Nasogastric Tube Insertion in Hospitalised Children.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>NGTIPPS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NGTIPPS</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Intubation; Difficult</healthcondition>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Lignocaine
Treatment: drugs - Placebo

Placebo Comparator: Placebo - This arm will include children aged 6 years of age and older seen at the Royal Children's Hospital who are having an NGT inserted for a clinical indication and who have never experienced an NGT insertion before. These children will be randomised to be in this placebo arm or the treatment arm in a 1:1 ratio. The placebo for swallowing is a viscous, coloured, sucrose-flavoured gel designed to match the appearance of the treatment lignocaine gel to be swallowed by the treatment arm, and normal saline will be delivered to the nasal turbinates and nasopharynx in a similar way to atomised xylocaine in the treatment arm.

Active Comparator: Lignocaine - This arm will include children aged 6 years of age and older seen at the Royal Children's Hospital who are having an NGT inserted for a clinical indication and who have never experienced an NGT insertion before. These children will be randomised to be in this treatment placebo arm or the treatment arm in a 1:1 ratio. The children in the treatment arm will receive xylocaine viscous 2% to swallow, and atomised 10% xylocaine to the nasal turbinates and nasopharynx.

Active Comparator: Pre/post intervention evaluation group - This is a contemporaneous arm of children aged 6 years of age and older requiring nasogastric intubation for a clinical reason, who have previously had a nasogastric tube inserted. These children will be ask to rate by recall their previous NGT intubation on a VAS pain scale, and then will perform a post-procedure VAS pain assessment.


Treatment: drugs: Lignocaine
Lignocaine 10% solution administered intra nasally plus lignocaine 2% solution administered orally.

Treatment: drugs: Placebo
Viscous, coloured, sucrose flavoured gel solution to match xylocaine viscous in appearance, normal saline administered intranasally to the nasal turbinates and nasopharynx.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction in mean visual analogue scores (VAS) in study arm</outcome>
      <timepoint>10 minutes following nasogastric tube intubation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Signed informed consent from parent of guardian

          2. Signed assent from subject

          3. Subject must have insertion of a nasogastric tube ordered as part of his/her current
             treatment

          4. Must be 6 years of age or older

          5. Must be able to complete visual analogue scale (VAS)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Congenital abnormalities of the naso/oropharyngeal area

          2. Any surgical alterations in the naso/oropharyngeal area

          3. Mucositis

          4. Known history of hypersensitivity to xylocaine or other local anaesthetics

          5. Known history of hypersensitivity to other components of the xylocaine solutions such
             as methyl or propyl hydroxybenzoate, ethanol, polyethylene glycol 400, banana flavour
             PHL-131980, menthol, saccharin

          6. Allergy to food colouring

          7. Presence of tracheotomy / tracheostomy

          8. Presence of tumour in the nasopharyngeal/oropharyngeal area

          9. Impaired gag reflex

         10. Impaired swallow

         11. Any cardiac condition

         12. Diabetes

         13. Hypertension

         14. Current use of antidepressant medication

         15. Current use of cimetidine or propranolol

         16. Significantly impaired liver function

         17. Significantly impaired renal function

         18. Current use of anti-arrhythmic medication</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/05/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>13</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Terminated</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/03/2011</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Queensland Children's Medical Research Institute - Brisbane</hospital>
    <postcode>4029 - Brisbane</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Queensland Children's Medical Research Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Nasogastric tube insertion is one of the most common invasive procedures performed in
      children's hospitals, and has long been recognised as one of the most traumatic and painful.
      As a once off procedure, a nasogastric tube insertion is extremely distressing but the
      repeated procedures that many children endure as a necessary part of treatment for a chronic
      disease can be so traumatic that psychological damage may occur. There have been a limited
      number of studies carried out which have looked at methods to reduce the pain and trauma
      associated with this procedure, but most of these have been carried out in the adult
      population.

      The investigators propose to carry out a research project in a paediatric setting to
      definitively investigate the use of local anaesthetic spray, in combination with local
      anaesthetic gel, to numb the nasal passages and the back of the throat, with the aim of
      reducing or removing the unpleasant sensation of the nasogastric tube placement. If the study
      shows a benefit from the use of local anaesthetics, it would be an inexpensive and easily
      incorporated intervention that could be inserted into the routine procedure for nasogastric
      tube insertion.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01075789</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Nicholas T O Neill, BN</name>
      <address>Royal Children's Hospital, Queensland Paediatric Infectious Diseases Laboratory</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>