<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3896">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/04/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/04/2013</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01838200</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Phase I Study of Intralesional Bacillus Calmette-Guerin (BCG) and Followed by Ipilimumab Therapy in Patients With Advanced Metastatic Melanoma</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase I Study of Intralesional Bacillus Calmette-Guerin (BCG) and Followed by Ipilimumab Therapy in Patients With Advanced Metastatic Melanoma</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>LUD2012-003</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Metastatic Melanoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Malignant melanoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - Bacillus Calmette-Guérin (BCG) vaccine
Treatment: drugs - Ipilimumab

Experimental: Cohort 1 - Cohort 1 will include patients with an induration &lt;10 mm in diameter after the pre-study PPD reactivity test. These patients will be enrolled into 3 groups sequentially, each given a single dose IL dose of BCG vaccine into a single selected melanoma lesion on Study Day 1. Each group will include 3 patients to be given a BCG at 16 - 0.64 x 106 cfu BCG (200 µl volume), 0.8 - 3.2 x 106 cfu BCG (200 µl volume), and 4.0 - 16.0 x 106 cfu BCG (200 µl volume)for groups 1, 2, and 3 respectively
All patients in these 3 groups will receive 300 mg daily doses of Isoniazid, commencing 28 days following the BCG injection and continuing for 4 weeks, and Ipilimumab administered intravenously starting 5 weeks after BCG, on Day 36. Four doses of 3 mg/kg ipilimumab are to be given every 3 weeks.

Experimental: Cohort 2 - Cohort 2 will include maximum 9 patients with a pre-study PPD reactivity to tuberculin that is =10 mm. Patients will receive 0.16 - 0.64 x 106 cfu BCG (200 µl volume) followed by administration of 300 mg daily doses of Isoniazid, commencing 28 days after the BCG and continuing for 4 weeks. Ipilimumab is administered intravenously starting 5 weeks after BCG, on Day 36. Four doses of (3 mg/kg) ipilimumab are to be given every 3 weeks.


Other interventions: Bacillus Calmette-Guérin (BCG) vaccine
Bacillus Calmette-Guérin (BCG) is a living attenuated strain of Mycobacterium bovis that stimulates cell-mediated immunity by producing a localized and self-limiting infection. BCG is used worldwide for vaccination against tuberculosis. BCG is an immunostimulating agent that has been also shown to have anti-tumour activity in several clinical studies. The exact mechanism of action is not well known, but study data suggest that active non-specific immune responses are induced. It is probable that BCG invokes a local inflammatory response involving a variety of immune cells, such as macrophages, natural killer cells and T cells

Treatment: drugs: Ipilimumab
Ipilimumab is a human CTLA-4-blocking antibody, designed to suppress the CTLA-4 inhibition of T cells. Ipilimumab is marketed by Bristol-Myers-Squibb under the name Yervoy® and was first approved by the FDA and TGA in 2011 for the treatment of unresectable or metastatic melanoma

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety - Adverse events as defined by CTCAE Version 4.0</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical Efficacy as measured by tumor response - Tumor response as accessed by RECIST v1.1 and immune-related response criteria (irRC)</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Immunogenicity: Humoral Immunity - Induced antibodies from peripheral blood will analyzed by ELISA for NY-ESO-1 and Melan-A, and by proteomics chips for other tumor antigens.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1, 36, 78, 113, 141, 204</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Immunogenicity: Cellular Immunity - Antigens for cellular immunity will be selected on the basis of serological responses identified through ELISA and proteomic chips.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1, 36, 43, 57, 78, 113, 141, 204</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Immunogenicity; In situ Immunity - Optional Tumor samples will be collect for exploratory analyses</outcome>
      <timepoint>Screening, Day 36, 43, 204</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Histologically confirmed stage III (unresectable) or stage IV melanoma

          -  Minimum one metastatic lesion, cutaneous or subcutaneous, but ideally three or more
             lesions, to accommodate IL injection (1 lesion), accessibility for biopsy (1 lesion),
             and evaluability for response by RECIST v.1.1 (1 lesion) and modified RECIST (irRC).

          -  Performance status of ECOG 0-1

          -  Within the last 2 weeks prior to study day 1, vital laboratory parameters should be
             within normal range, except for the following laboratory parameters, which should be
             within the ranges specified:

        Haemoglobin: = 100 g/L, Platelets: = 100 x 10^9/L, INR: = 2.0, Creatinine: = 120 µmol/L,
        Bilirubin: = 30 µmol/L, eGFR: &gt; 0.75 x LLN, ALT/AST: = 2.0 x ULN, Albumin: &gt; 28 g/L,
        Neutrophils: &gt; 1.5 x 10^9/L, Lymphocytes: &gt; 0.9 x 10^9/L,</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Active cerebral metastases unless stable after radiation for at least one month and
             not requiring corticosteroid treatment for 30 days prior to enrolment

          -  Other known malignancy within 3 years prior to entry into the study, except for
             treated non-melanoma skin cancer and cervical carcinoma in situ.

          -  History of tuberculosis

          -  History of hypersensitivity to BCG

          -  Any contraindication to the use of isoniazid

          -  Generalized skin disease

          -  Autoimmune disease: Patients with a history of inflammatory bowel disease, including
             ulcerative colitis and Crohn's Disease, are excluded from this study, as are patients
             with a history of symptomatic disease (eg, rheumatoid arthritis, systemic progressive
             sclerosis [scleroderma], systemic lupus erythematosus, autoimmune vasculitis [eg,
             Wegener's Granulomatosis]); motor neuropathy considered of autoimmune origin (e.g.
             Guillain-Barre Syndrome and Myasthenia Gravis). Exceptions: vitiligo, type I diabetes,
             pernicious anaemia (treated).

          -  Any underlying medical or psychiatric condition, which in the opinion of the
             investigator will make the administration of ipilimumab hazardous or obscure the
             interpretation of AEs, such as a condition associated with frequent diarrhea.

          -  Prior immunotherapy or systemic adjuvant therapy for melanoma following most recent
             relapse and/or resection of melanoma

          -  Prior treatment with a CTLA4 inhibitor

          -  Concomitant therapy with any of the following: IL-2, interferon, or other non-study
             immunotherapy regimens; cytotoxic chemotherapy; immunosuppressive agents; other
             investigation therapies; or chronic use of systemic corticosteroids

          -  Known HIV positivity, Hepatitis B or Hepatitis C

          -  Chemotherapy or radiation therapy within the preceding 4 weeks (6 weeks for
             nitrosourea drugs).

          -  Lack of availability for immunological and clinical follow-up assessments.

          -  Participation in any other clinical trial involving another investigational agent
             within 4 weeks prior to first dosing.

          -  Mental impairment that may compromise the ability to give informed consent and to
             comply with the requirements of the study.

          -  Women who are pregnant (positive pregnancy test at baseline), or breastfeeding

          -  Men and women unwilling or unable to use an acceptable method of contraception to
             avoid pregnancy for their entire study period and for at least 8 weeks after cessation
             of study drug.

          -  Prisoners or subjects who are compulsorily detained (involuntarily incarcerated) for
             treatment of either a psychiatric or physical (e.g., infectious) illness.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/04/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>6</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Terminated</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/04/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Austin Health, LICR Melbourne Austin Branch - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <postcode>2084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Ludwig Institute for Cancer Research</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Bristol-Myers Squibb</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is an open-label, dose-escalation, non-randomized, phase I study in patients with
      histologically confirmed Stage III or IV melanoma and at least three metastatic cutaneous or
      subcutaneous lesions suitable for: intralesional (IL) injection (1 lesion), accessible for
      biopsy (1 lesion), and response evaluation by RECIST (v1.1) and modified RECIST (irRC) (1
      lesion). The primary objective is to determine whether IL administration of BCG followed by
      intravenous (IV) infusion of ipilimumab is safe. Ipilimumab (YERVOY®) is the monoclonal
      anti-CTLA-4 antibody approved by the FDA and TGA as anticancer therapy for melanoma.
      Secondary objectives of the study are: a) clinical efficacy, to document whether this
      combination therapy induces tumour responses; and b) immunogenicity, to identify if the
      combination induces immune responses against the tumours. All patients will be included in
      the analysis of efficacy and immunogenicity.

      Cohort 1 (9 patients with &lt;10mm induration after tuberculin Purified Protein Derivative [PPD]
      test): Group 1 (3 patients) will receive one IL injection of 200 µl BCG containing 0.16 -
      0.64 x 106 cfu followed by four IV infusions of 3 mg/kg ipilimumab every 3 weeks, starting on
      day 36. Group 2 (3 patients) and 3 (n=3) will receive 200 µl BCG containing 0.8 - 3.2 x 106
      cfu and 4.0 -16.0 x 106 cfu, respectively, followed by the same ipilimumab regimen. Safety
      will be evaluated in this cohort.

      Cohort 2 (up to 9 patients with =10mm induration after PPD test): Enrolment will start after
      the final patient in Cohort 1, Group 1 has reached study week 7. Then enrolment can proceed
      in parallel for Cohort 2 and Cohort 1 Groups 2 and 3. Patients will receive 0.16 -0.64 x 106
      cfu BCG followed by four IV infusions of 3 mg/kg ipilimumab every 3 weeks, starting on day
      36. Evaluation of safety in this cohort will be observational.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01838200</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jonathan Cebon, MBBS, FRACP, PhD</name>
      <address>Austin Health</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>