<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3187">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/05/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/05/2011</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01368367</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Exercise Training Post Burn Injury</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Safety and Efficacy of Exercise Training Post Burn Injury: a Randomized Controlled Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>ETPB1</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Burns</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Burns</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Other interventions - Intensive exercise

Active Comparator: Intensive exercise group - 

Placebo Comparator: Stretch exercise only - 


Other interventions: Intensive exercise
Both groups, stretching exercise monitored once per week Intensive exercise group An aerobic and resisted exercise program for a minimum of three times per week for a total of approximately 60 minutes per session for six weeks. Aerobic exercise will be conducted on a treadmill, exercise bike or arm ergometer at an intensity of 80 % of VO2peak during initial assessment. For resistance exercise, the three repetition maximum (3RM) (maximum weight able to be lifted a maximum of 3 times) will be established and then resisted exercise will be commenced at 60% of the 3RM in the first week. Resisted exercise will then be progressed weekly by 5-10% by increasing the number of repetitions or the weights lifted. All resisted exercises will be done using variable resistance machines or free weights.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Burns Specific Health Scale - Abbreviated (BSHS-A) - The BSHS-A is an injury specific self reported questionnaire consisting of 80 questions encompassing four primary domains namely physical, psychological, social and general, with reports of good internal consistency, test/ retest reliability and strong convergent validity data.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change from baseline to six weeks, change from 6 weeks to 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The modified shuttle walk test (MSWT) - The modified shuttle walk test (MSWT) is an established test of functional exercise capacity. It is an objective measure with 15 incremental levels of both walking and running. Total distance acheived will be recorded.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change from baseline to six weeks, change from 6 weeks to 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>VO2peak (ie the volume of oxygen consumed by the cells at the most intensive level during the exercise test) - VO2peak (ie the volume of oxygen consumed by the cells at the most intensive level during the modified shuttle walk test) will be recorded by a portable metabolic monitor (Metalyzer 3B analyser (Cortex:biophysik, GMbH, Germany) Cortex MetaMax 3B).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change from baseline to six weeks, change from 6 weeks to 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resting heart rate (beats/minute) - Resting heart rate was recorded by a polar heart rate monitor (PE3000, Polar Electro, Kemple, Finland) in beats/minute.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change from baseline to six weeks, change from 6 weeks to 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Muscle strength - Muscle Strength - a baseline measure of the quadriceps and latisimuss dorsi muscles will be taken by the one repetition maximum or 1RM. This is the maximum amount of weight one can lift in a single repetition for a given exercise and has been utilized as an outcome measure in subjects post burns.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change from baseline to six weeks, change from 6 weeks to 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Grip strength - Grip strength will be measured using a Jamar dynamometer as per the protocol for the American Hand Therapists Society with an average of three measurements taken. This dynamometer is a hydraulic appliance which can measure grip strength in five alternate grip position settings. This has been shown to have good reliability and validity and is considered the gold standard of hand grip measurement.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change from baseline to six weeks, change from 6 weeks to 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>QuickDash - The Quick disabilities of the arm, shoulder and hand (QuickDASH)is a self rated questionnaire on upper limb function with good repeatability, validity and responsiveness in burns patients. Sixty percent of the questions relate to overall upper limb disability with the remainder of the optional questions relating to work, sports and musical activities. Lower scores on this scale indicate less disability of the upper limb.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change from baseline to six weeks, change from 6 weeks to 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Lower Extremity Functional Scale (LEFS) - The Lower Extremity Functional Scale (LEFS) measures disability related to the lower extremities with regard to work, activities of daily living and recreation and has been shown to have sensitivity to change in burns patients and excellent test-retest reliability and construct validity in general patients. Higher scores indicate less disability with a possible total of 80.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change from baseline to six weeks, change from 6 weeks to 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Burns greater than 20% total body surface area

          -  18 years of age and over

          -  English speaking

          -  Post final grafting procedure</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Accompanying anoxic brain injury

          -  Cardiac disease or injury (American College of Sports medicine ACSM criteria)

          -  Quadriplegia

          -  Severe behaviour or cognitive disorders

          -  Compassionate care only</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>The people assessing the outcomes</masking3>
    <masking4>The people analysing the results/data</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/12/2007</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>36</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Unknown status</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/12/2012</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital - Brisbane</hospital>
    <postcode>4029 - Brisbane</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to determine whether a high intensity aerobic and resisted
      exercise program will improve physical, functional and psychological outcomes in patients
      post burn injury.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01368367</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>